Hello.
So I suppose we are back with the streaming.
We had a little bit of issues that are not under our control
with whatever internet provider is between Twitch TV
and the location of the streaming server.
But hopefully, you are able to see.
It might not look exactly like it
used to look at the beginning of the session,
but we are back.
It is coming on the stream and now we basically see the Canoes room view
with the images on the side.
Yes, so sorry for this issue but sometimes it's still better than what happened a couple of years
ago during code refinement streaming where the whole internet was down or a huge subset of the
whole internet. So people of course realized that it wasn't us. It was literally 50% of the internet
that was down. Today we only have some part of Helsinki internet. I think what's interesting is
that both these incidents happened at the same presentation that I'm about to give here. So
it's correlated with this talk. All right, so we have two data points that this presentation
coincides with some network outage. Let's see if the third time will happen again.
But anyway, let's get to the business. We have now here with us [name], who is the master
of everything. Well, master is maybe a big word, but at least one of the biggest drivers of the
Code Refinery network and workshop and so on. [name], do you want to say something about
yourself? What do you do in your daily? Yeah, so it's so nice to be here. I work in Norway.
In Tromsø, I work on code refinery training, training in software development, software tools,
in computing. In Norway, I work at the national infrastructure. So there is a national compute,
We have National Compute Courses and I provide support
and help and training so that researchers
get more out of their CPU cycles.
And it's nice to be here with this Finland,
with this training, which is driven by Aalto,
because I really like to collaborate with my Aalto colleagues.
we work together on many different training events.
And also I really like talking about this topic.
And I think it's very, it doesn't matter
whether this is now Norway or Finland or a different country.
I think some of the,
some of the points that we will discuss
are really transferable and they,
so it will be fun to talk about how we do help TESC
and support in here in Tromso, but also at Aalto
and how can we improve it?
How can we improve the experience for everybody?
And this small change here is that I will be presenting
this together with [name] because [name] has been
heroically restoring the stream in the meantime
and had to switch computer.
And I will now switch to, so for everybody,
the best way to follow the next 20 minutes
because we are a little bit behind schedule
is you can find the slides, the slide deck here.
Is it linked from the schedule?
It is also linked here in the notes.
And the best way to interact is to watch us presenting
and please ask us lots of questions, give comments.
And [name] will help me raising some questions
that I might overlook.
So I will now open up this presentation
And when I do that, I already have it here in this browser.
We'll just resize a little bit,
and I will make sure that I can see your questions
here on the bottom.
So let's talk about how to ask for help
with computers and supercomputers.
And it's really about,
the goal is to improve your experience
when solving issues.
And some of the topics that I will talk about
is what kind of help is available,
when to ask for help,
and then how you can formulate your support requests
so that you get quick and useful answers.
And if we have time,
we can talk about reproducible examples
and the value of growing your calculation
and simplifying problems,
how that can help you find answers quicker.
And the slide deck is, there's credit.
It has, I've learned a lot from other people
and some of the persons are here
and thanks so much for this input.
And I would like to start with this question.
There are these many places where you can ask for help
and I can ask [name], if you look for help,
I mean, if you look for a solution,
how do you, like, where do you ask?
How do you ask?
Yeah, it depends, of course, on the type of issue.
But maybe I really like that there's people.
So we have this Zulip, which is a system
for chatting together.
We have one at Aalto, we have one with the Code Refinery.
So we have dedicated channels when anyone can ask for help.
And when the question is too difficult,
the human is the best, in my opinion.
What about you?
Yes, I really like that.
that and I want to highlight here so it can be colleagues also hopefully you have somebody
in the corridor who who knows an answer. There are also these at alto it's called the garage.
It's a daily help desk session where you can come and ask questions. We have something
similar here in terms of weekly office hours. Then we have monthly q&a sessions in Norway.
So hopefully, your, like your compute center provides these sessions.
So it's really nice to, I think, come and talk to a person.
Then there are, I think, very popular these days is to also ask the AI through a chat
interface.
There is documentation issue tracker.
Resource software engineers who can help you with when it's more about the code rather
but then about the computation
and then mailing this forum stock exchange.
I tried to order them a little bit how they are.
So the ones on the bottom are at least for me
maybe a little bit scarier to ask
because then it's, I asked the question
to the whole internet.
Some people prefer to ask questions more to colleagues.
So many places to ask.
Oh, thanks for highlighting at CSE,
weekly user support sessions.
So I think these are great initiatives.
Because as I will show later,
sometimes an email is not enough
because in an email, we have to read between the lines.
Sometimes the actual question is not asked
and it can help to really discuss in person.
When to ask for help, don't hesitate, don't wait too long.
Really many people really like helping.
But I can also say that as a support staff, I do appreciate when I see that the person
who is writing the email, maybe spent two minutes on the problem before asking.
And not because it's about like my two minutes of work, but it often makes it open often
sharpens the question, it makes it that they think a little bit about about the problem
and give me a little bit more context.
Oh yeah, also on Lumi every Wednesday of the month, wonderful.
So please keep these comments coming and the questions I really like that.
Next slide.
It's sometimes I give myself a time limit that I tell me that, okay, I will, I will
try to fix this.
I will give myself one hour.
And then if it doesn't work, I will go to the garage, open off office hour or user support
session and ask for help there.
And it can be also nice to say like, what, what do you want from the help?
Would you like advice?
Or would you like them to do something for you like to install software or to, to do
profiling or do some programming?
Who is on the other side?
So when I send an email, it's good to know that on the other side, there is a human being.
Also when I reply to email, and as a reminder to myself, so when I'm staff and helping others,
I want to remind myself, it's not easy to ask for help.
The person who's asking me didn't spend the last 25 years with Unix and Linux.
Maybe the person on the other side has spent weeks on this problem and waited for my answer.
So really, it's important to be respectful.
It's good to know for those who ask questions via email, that the support that is helping
and answering these might maybe change every week.
So in Norway, we are rotating.
So every few weeks, there might be different people answering.
I answer these questions, I don't know everything. I might sometimes I feel like I'm spending
less time on the supercomputing supercomputer than the person asking. So very often, I don't
know the answer. But I can we can together try to try to find the answer and solve it.
And especially if this is if this is a system with with many users. So on on our systems,
we have something around 2000 users.
How about Alto?
How many users are there?
Yeah, many, at least the cluster is 1,500 more.
So yeah, same levels.
And probably Lumi comparable, CSE comparable,
maybe even more.
And which means that I might not know the person
who's writing the email.
I might not have the context.
It's good to create this context
when asking through like email chat.
And I remember my first question,
my first ever technical email request
that I wrote to somebody.
So I wrote a long email to a professor,
very respectful, paragraphs and paragraphs.
And what I really wanted is I wanted to get access
to the source code that they used in a publication.
But, and after a while I got this very short email back
And the answer was, hi, I guess what you meant asking
in between all those paragraphs was,
can I please get the code X?
And here it is.
So I got what I wanted,
but I felt a little bit embarrassed
because it was just not clear what I wanted.
I didn't make it clear.
One thing that can help is that in these email requests,
oh, email subject is the first thing that I see
when trying to help, so to make it descriptive.
So if the CML subject is problem, it is not very useful
because then everybody needs to open it up
and see what is inside.
If there is a descriptive subject,
it's easier for us to route the email to the right person.
Sometimes I don't know the answer,
but my colleagues know the answer,
and then I can try, it makes it easier for me
to find the right colleague.
About providing context.
So what are the things that can help us to having this context, like having a username,
if you are one of the 1500 users or 2000 users, I can probably figure it out, but it will
take time.
If you talk about storage and location, then it is good to have an explicit path.
It's better than saying it is in my home folder or it is in a relative folder because then
it means something else for you than for me and I need to find out.
It takes some time.
And if if there are multiple clusters machines, tell us which machine it is, which software
which research field if if relevant.
if you modify your software environment
in a file like .bashrc,
then tell us about it because your .bashrc
where you can have your own customization
is different than mine.
So I might have a different environment.
Good.
It would be nice to have more questions
here in the document.
And speaking about questions,
One thing that is really good to know is
if something doesn't work, tell us, has it ever worked?
So is it the first time that you try this
or has it worked last Tuesday
and today it doesn't work anymore?
That's really useful.
What are you trying to accomplish?
And here, what is your ultimate goal
and not the current technical obstacle?
And I might return to that point.
And what did you do so far?
So try to be specific.
Copy paste all the commands, so that I can reproduce it.
And then what do you need?
Do you need a complete solution?
Do you need advice?
Do you need?
It's just that we allocate the right time.
It helps me when I see that, like the support email tells me what you have tried, again,
has it stopped working?
Or has it ever worked?
Does it always fail this way, or only sometimes?
And if you have tried to simplify the problem, then tell us how and that that helps a lot.
And please check documentation at web,
but sometimes the web is wrong.
So don't hesitate to ask,
because sometimes the web gives help
on how to solve something on a laptop,
and that doesn't work on a cluster.
And I think what the comment that comes down,
comes here at the bottom is a very good comment,
is that sometimes when you ask a question,
you get the feeling that support people are bothered and that's really sad if it's like
that. So I think the support hub should always be welcoming and understanding. And it is
really sad if through the short electronic communication, it feels like people are distracted
have bothered. I think it is really our one of our main roles is to help research and
help you to to solve computational problems. So unfortunately, that's sometimes true. And
I think we we here work hard on on improving this. I mentioned that it's good to know what
is your what is your goal, not what is the current technical obstacle. And when we meet
in person in during garage and during office hours, it's easier to figure this out. When
when we just send an email, it's sometimes hard because so one famous thing is this so
called XY problem where imagine a user wants to solve something wants to do something and
then searches the internet. And somewhere finds out that in order to do this, you need
to do this obstacle. The technical obstacle is why. And then, then the user tries this
and hits a problem. And then asks for help with this technical obstacle. And then we
spend some time or much interaction, a couple of emails back and forth. And after this couple
of interaction, we figure out that this technical obstacle that we solved was not even the suitable
solution. And what the user really wanted to do is x, but it was never written, we didn't
know, we never knew. And if we knew we would have suggested maybe a completely different
solution to do this. So it's really good to to say it, what do you really want to do?
And I think I will show two examples in a moment.
Maybe good to know what happens with your email when you send it.
So on our side in Norway, and I think it's similar in in other places, when you send
us an email, it opens up something called a ticket and issue it gets a number.
And there we have a place to track it and keep track of it to have a conversation in
it to keep a context. And it's good to know that these tickets issues can change hands.
That's why we need to really document this context. And good, better formulated requests
avoid this lengthy back and forth. And once a problem is resolved, and the ticket or issue
gets closed. And I want to show you two, two example requests that they are a little bit
redacted but they are real. And we can discuss here with an echo what we like about them.
So here's a real request. Hi, I'm a user of some some name on the cluster saga. So that's
a that's a cluster here that we have in Norway. And since this morning, I cannot log in anymore.
I have tried to log in into some other clusters, and this works. And I use SSH keys to log
login, and the error that I get since this morning is the following.
And thank you in advance for help advice how to solve this.
So what do we like about this request?
What is really nice about this?
Yeah, I mean, at least I clearly see the problem, the issue, I can already see that the user
has tried to do some type of, you know, debugging or whatever you want to call it troubleshooting.
Yeah.
really good context here. Just from this email I can see that I can see what the
user tried. Cannot login anymore but can login on to other clusters
which means that it's probably there is a problem probably since this morning on
the cluster. Just from this email I can see that it's probably not
something on their side. It's something on our side. And there is even an error
message which means that from this I get a really good idea of what it might be
be. And I might be able to solve it in sort of one shot solution. And the next email is
says it's solved. And I can see the time. So I can see that we have maybe maximum five
minutes left. So to the moderators here, don't worry, I can see that. I want to show one
another example, which is also real. And the email that we got was, hi, I'm not sure I
I wrote to the right support line,
but what I'm looking for is a virtual machine
where we can install a PHP web server
with a MySQL database behind it.
And what we have in mind is to set up a service
where we can share the data from our recent study
and the data can be fully public.
It's about 2000 records, so not so much data.
And we would like to create a web front end
where people can search through and plot our data.
and looking forward to hear more, whether this is possible.
What do you like about this one?
Well, I mean, I would say that it looks like
they know what they're doing and what they want to do
because most likely they might be already familiar
with web development and MySQL.
What do you think about this one?
Yeah, so what I like is that they ask
very specific what they want.
But what I also like is that they give a context
of what they what. So really the goal. So here's the technical things. But here is what
they would like to have, they would like to have a web service. I also like that they
tell me that it's public data. So immediately, I know I don't have to worry about, it's not
something for a sensitive, sensitive data, it's public. Also, I get a good idea of the
the size of it.
So this will probably not be terabytes and petabytes.
And what was good here is that if the question
was just this, we would have done it.
We would have created a virtual machine
and installed exactly what they wanted.
But thanks to this paragraph, we, in this particular case,
we realized that there was a better way of doing it.
And we did something different for them.
And they are very happy about it.
So we didn't do this because for their example,
we found something that was a better fit.
But since we had this big picture,
we could suggest this other suggestion.
And so we did it, everybody's happy.
And I liked that it was not just the immediate next step,
but it was where do they want to be at the end.
Good, we have very few minutes left.
Would be nice to have more questions here, please keep them coming.
I think the last few slides are some recommendations on how you can create examples that you can
share with support to make it easier.
And one recommendation that I like to give is that when you are on a new machine, or
you have never been on a cluster before, or something is failing.
It's it's nice if you can start with a small example.
So don't start with a gigantic example with the trends on lots of compute nodes and requires
40 hours to run.
If the same problem can be reproduced with a small example, then it's really useful for
you and it's really useful for the support.
And when I'm on a new system that I don't know well, I like to start with something
that runs in five minutes, maybe on one core.
And then once it works, then I go to more time, more cores, bigger system.
And then then I make my calculation longer.
That really helps me identifying lots of problems early.
And I don't have to wait 40 hours to to figure this out.
And then whenever I suggest it, a good comment could be but but wait a bit.
Making a small system is not realistic.
My my realistic system is big and takes long.
And then my advice is that it doesn't have to be realistic.
It can be a synthetic example.
So very simplified, you remove lots of, you make the,
I don't know, smaller resolution, smaller data set,
but it can help us to debug lots of technical issues.
And then once they are sorted out,
then we can go back to the realistic system.
So this is a technique that I really like to use
and it can make it much, much easier to solve problems.
And I think only two, two minutes left.
So I really highly recommend to create
a small reproducible example
for a typical calculation that you run.
Because then when this doesn't work anymore,
you can quickly verify, is this a problem on your side
or is it a problem on the cluster side?
And if it's a problem on the cluster side,
you can send them this small example
and they can run it as well
and use it to diagnose the problem.
If this is an interactive job,
where you type commands and run the job sort of live,
then please provide all commands from login to problem.
Also, this helps us to diagnose and to reproduce
and retrace your steps, step-by-step,
precisely as you did.
And the smaller examples, they make it, often they simplify the problem.
They can help identify the reason they reduce the number of freedoms.
It's easier to debug.
And also it doesn't queue, it doesn't wait in the queue forever if it's smaller.
We as staff, we also have to wait in the queue, like we don't have a prioritized queuing.
So if this is a very long example, it's also long for us.
And I think my time is up.
I think I want to go to the summary slide.
You are not alone.
Approach, support, and resources for engineers near you.
Pop into a garage session or a Q&A help session
or an office hour and say hi.
It's also a great place to not just ask questions
but give suggestions on how we can improve the systems.
You are probably not alone experiencing a problem.
And the questions are never too stupid, too simple.
They are very often good questions.
Many people really enjoy helping.
And the people who organize this discourse,
they really, really enjoy helping and are good at this.
It's also okay from time to time to tell us
if something is working well.
It doesn't happen very often that, you know,
at 2 a.m. in the morning, you get an email
that somebody's thinking,
well, the system is actually working, and thanks.
But good to hear that as well.
And here, the comment.
Yeah, so it can be, you can start with your own team,
start with a colleague,
and then you can escalate, go to other places.
So it can be a progression.
What did we miss? Anything I missed to say?
No, I think this was super useful, especially considering that I know that let's say half of the participants who are registered for this session are people who just started with their summer internship.
So asking for help and getting the most out of it is really important when you're just starting.
Wonderful.
Thank you so much [name], this was very useful and regarding the streaming, so the connection
from the streaming server to the rest of the internet is fine again.
So I hear from the back room that we should be able to switch to the better streaming
server.
Good.
So then thanks everybody for listening.
Thanks a lot.
I give back to the studio, and I will look forward to more.
Thank you so much.
So let's see if the streaming goes to the new.
Yeah, hello.
Yeah.
OK.
wait I need to say that for everyone there will be a short break and it will
hopefully be back what is left here