CodeRefinery.org
you
Hello, can everyone hear us?
Can someone give a reaction, if you can?
Hello, hello.
So if you can, we are here.
What I've shared here is our notes.
If you've registered, you should have it as a link.
We can scroll down to this icebreaker and begin talking a little bit while I try to
stop my cat from destroying something on my desk.
How come the cat is very active?
It's just 11.50.
I guess it just, well, I don't know, like sometimes it comes earlier in the day.
So for anyone new here, my cat often visits during courses, especially later in the day
as it approaches 4 o'clock when it's its feeding time.
So that's the motivation for staying through the whole time.
So if you leave early, you lose cat observation possibilities.
Anyway, yeah.
So hi everyone.
gotten any indication of audio yet?
I checked the stream and it it seemed to
work at least. Okay, good. But if others want to respond to the
notes that's of course a good idea. Yeah, so the next question is
is our audio balanced?
Should we do the standard test?
Yep.
Okay.
Me, [name], [name].
One.
Two.
Three.
Four.
Five.
Six.
Okay.
Let us know who might be quieter.
How can people let us know?
Well, at least the channel people could.
Yeah.
So you can write it in the notes here.
me open that up. Oh yeah, actually, someone is writing. I'm the loudest. Okay. Yeah,
I'll turn myself a bit up or just shout a bit louder. Okay.
So anyway, some people have already figured out how Notes and Stuff works. So basically,
we have this document everyone can write. And as we're talking at any time, you can write questions
answer comments. One of the co-instructors might see it, but we also have a whole bunch
of people in the background who will be reading and answering during the course. So, you can
ask as many questions as you want, and usually we get most of them answered.
And as a practice, we have icebreakers here. So, please open it up if you're registered.
If not registering, we'll get you the link automatically emailed to you.
And then scroll down to these sections.
So what's your position?
Use this O symbol to vote.
So as you see, people are adding different votes here.
It's like a dynamically generated bar graph that's a poll.
So yeah, add in your votes there.
Then you can also add in where you are now,
so as in what city or country you're in.
Or you can try to be more clever if you want to.
What's the biggest computer you've used so far?
Yeah, I mean it could be your own computer or some workstation.
And then what do you work on?
Yeah, so like what kind of scientific work or other work, basically, while you're here?
here. So we want to know a little bit about you. And maybe we can start by telling about
us some. So I'm [name]. I'm a, well HR considers me a staff scientist at Aalto
University. I work in the computing, the high-performance computing team at Aalto. And we also do a
lot of teaching, and then a lot of research software engineer support. So basically going
and helping you with your very code. And I'm really glad to be here. So this is one of our
best and most important courses of the year, and we're glad that we have several hundred
registrations here. [name], do you want to tell a little bit about you?
Yes, so my name is [name]. I'm a Research Software Engineer in Aalto Scientific Computing.
Previously worked on the HPC side of the team as well.
Yeah, I've been teaching this course for many years now in conjunction with other people and yeah, I think it's very good.
we try to make this course as palatable for people that are new to HPC so that they don't get scared
and people can can do their research in the best way possible. So I'm very happy to be here and
see what we can achieve together during the few days. Yeah okay and [name]. And then it's me
which most likely you've seen my name in your mailbox. So I've been coordinating this
adventure as well as many other that we have had and we will have in the in the future. So in
general we are organizing these type of open courses. I don't know if this is the first time
that you attend a course on Twitch TV. For us it's always exciting even though we've been doing this
for what, two years now? Two years. Or is it three years? Yeah, maybe three years.
Or is it 2021 January? Yeah, anyway. And we hope even actually that this way of
teaching is inspiring in a way that maybe next time you want to join us for some broadcasting
together to talk about your research or how you solve some problems that could be helpful
for others too. So I would want to quickly mention that we mentioned Twitch. One
quality of life thing for the Twitch stream. I would highly recommend that everybody goes
in the Twitch stream and then checks the gear icon on the bottom right and sets it instead of auto
into the best possible resolution.
Because Twitch tries to modify the bandwidth
or which compression it uses in the stream.
So if you want to see the crisp clear text that we are streaming
then setting it to the best possible resolution is a good idea.
Is this new? So I thought at one point
point Twitch didn't do transcoding for free streams.
I think it does for all streams.
Yeah, it does like less time with performance.
Yeah, exactly.
So from the gear icon on the settings,
you can check the quality.
And if you set it to be the source quality,
you will get the best view of the material.
Yeah.
OK.
So my next question, what's the coolest thing about today
that people should look forward to?
Let's go backwards.
[name].
Well, I'm going to briefly talk about Code Refinery, which
is a six-day workshop, but I will
try to compress it in 20 minutes just
give them motivation for people to take it next time we run it. So at least that's the most exciting
thing that I will talk about today. But what about you [name]?
Well I would say the most interesting part for me is like new demos that we have planned for this
year. So new demos on how to run new software for softwares in the cluster and hopefully they will
demonstrate what sort of capabilities the computing cluster can have. But also I would
say that I always enjoy listening to our guest talk and the guest people who come and discuss
about how they how they do their SPC work and how they ended up in the computer like
in the field of doing computations with well scientific computations.
Yeah. Because that's something new every year for me.
Yeah. And same for me. I mean, it's easy to get courses and read about technical things,
but the way we've added this interview with how people actually find their careers in these fields,
I think, is a story that is really often not told. But with that being said,
it's almost time to get started. Should I switch to my screen for the intro?
Yep. Okay, so we've got 10 minutes. Here we go. This is the
main page. You should have this in your info. If we scroll down to the schedule,
we have this Keycomp kickstart intro.
So, really quick.
Who are we? So, well, we just basically introduced that. We are a team at
Alta University, but this course is not just about our cluster. It's about many
clusters, and we have many partners here who are helping us, although we wish we had more.
So if you're watching, please be a partner next year.
What's in this course?
So day one is sort of general big picture things.
So about data, reproducibility, computing, and also a little bit of connecting
to prepare for day two.
But it's quite generic and stuff that almost anyone could be or should be watching
that's doing anything about computing.
Day two and three get more specialized.
This is the part where we're actually talking about how to use the cluster.
And, well, not everyone needs to do that yet, but more people do.
But some people do.
So who's attending?
So we have multiple universities, as I said.
Our demos are based on our own universities cluster,
so some of the examples may need adapting to other sites.
we will carefully explain what these differences might be and give you time
to figure it out for yourself. But the big picture, we're trying to make this
useful for everyone. You can ask questions about other universities. They
might have people watching the notes or they might have their own breakout rooms
or things like that. You have to talk to your own local people. Practicalities.
How it works. So unlike most courses we can reach hundreds of people. Right now
we have 100 people watching right now. So we are a live stream broadcast. Anyone can watch,
and we have these different pauses, sort of like commercial breaks, for you to work on exercises
or for normal breaks. There is a Zoom for some people, and if you're there, you can work on
exercises when you're there. There's many different parts. So there's talking and demos,
which is on the live stream. There's type along where we're typing and you should also be typing
at the same time. There's exercises where we tell you what to do and then you have time to do it
yourself. And we have breaks at least 10 minutes every hour, usually towards the top of the hour.
For chat and communication. So we've already gone over the notes here. So the idea is you
you register, you get this link, you can switch to edit mode, and you ask questions in bullet
points, and you make answers. Or other people make answers. We have a whole bunch of people
who are here to do this. So just ask whatever you want, whatever.
So the biggest problem that you might experience is that there's too many questions, and you
can't follow them all. In that case, just don't. I mean, ask your question, come back
later, come read it later, search for what you need, but there's definitely going to
be too many questions asked for you to follow them all.
So don't let that trip you up.
I guess people have figured out the view and edit modes.
So the notes are public, so don't include any names there or other identifying information,
please.
We will remove that right away.
also try to remove it before archival, but better to just do it right now. So can everyone go to
the notes now and try to answer the icebreaker if you haven't done it already? So that is
this here that I was sharing before.
Okay, so where do you focus? So yeah, there's so much there. So the first priority should be the
screen share and what we're talking. If you have time, then your own type along.
Then if you're bored or have a bunch of extra mental capacity, you can start browsing the
notes and seeing what else is there, what other questions. And then the lesson webpage,
if that's relevant to what we're talking about. So we have this really unique vertical screen share.
the idea is to make it big and it takes half your screen and the other half is for you.
After you've experienced this, you'll wonder why other courses don't
do this because it just makes so much sense. As [name] had said, you can go to Twitch and
make sure it's on source resolution and not auto to keep it as high as possible.
So we want to be accessible to many learning styles, and not everyone has to take the same
path.
So some people may prefer to watch passively and do the exercises and self-study later.
Some people might be active in all the exercises.
You might leave this on in the background while you do other things.
You might miss a part and want to review videos later in the evening.
answer the Twitch chat question. Yes, this is being recorded. Twitch will have it right away,
and we'll have process videos on YouTube by this evening.
Yeah, so please be nice to all the community and be respectful to each other.
So, teaching is a pretty difficult thing to do, and there's many things going on.
This is a live course, so yeah, things will go wrong. It's okay. Please follow along with us
anyway. Everyone's at different skill levels. That's okay. Please help each other. Everyone
is somehow both a teacher and a learner. We learn from you, and you learn from us.
If you're in any small groups or whatever, take the time to check in and ask,
how's it going? Does anyone need help? Things like that. We try to do that often with feedback.
And once something isn't right, then speak up very quickly.
Especially if you can't see something you need to see,
or you can't hear something, like our audio is bad.
Just tell us, hey, we're not following, please do something.
And we'll fix that right away.
Okay, what can and most certainly will go wrong.
So as I said, you can get overloaded with information.
This is definitely going to happen.
And as we said, take a step back and be more passive.
and realize you can come back to it later. The notes, this should say notes and not HackMD,
it's too fast to follow, so then don't follow it. It's published for future reference, so
just hide it and remove it as a distraction. If the notes lag and you can't edit, that sometimes
happens, so we try to keep it short but then switch to view mode and wait a little bit for it to
calm down some. There's an archive that's posted and a link should be at the top
and use that for the stuff that has been removed. If we don't have time to cover
everything, well that's just a fact. We won't. There's far more that we can cover
than we have time to. So we aim to give a big summary and to start you on your
learning path but all the materials there for you to review and come back to
later. We deviate from the schedule. We'll try to stay on track but it's
gonna happen sometimes. We'll adapt to what people are interested in. If there's
major accessibility problems like the audio quality is bad, the screen isn't
visible, you need a break but we're not doing it, our explanation is completely
unintelligible, write the problem right away and say hey I don't understand this
we have this problem. Our instructors will see this and we will do something.
Let's see. If the stream suddenly dies, that means my computer has crashed. In that case,
wait a few minutes and it will come back. If you're missing something important for the course,
well, sorry, that's okay. Wait and come back the next day and work on it. If you can't attend
every day, that's okay. If a cat visits us, well, that's the opposite of a problem, and I'll make
sure to turn on my video so everyone can see it. Expect it later in the day, some. If you want to
know more, ask around. So as final notes, the course is recorded, everything will be put on
YouTube. You cannot possibly be in the video because of the way we're doing it as livestream,
that's the whole point here. But don't add names to notes or anything like that. Anything you
write in the notes will be published with a CC license, so everyone that follows you will be able
to follow up on it. Do we assign credits for this course right now? No, we don't. Okay, yeah.
And please join us for future courses or things like that. You can join our chat,
join Code Refinery, and take part next time. Okay, that's my part. Is there anything in the notes
for the intro now no nothing special but please people feel free to add whatever
questions you might have okay so that's the intro so who's next for the screen
yeah I could I'm ready sharing if you wanna okay I'll send it to you and [name]
and head off now. Bye.
Bye.
So now it's 11 past 12.
So we are almost perfect with the timings.
As you see in the schedule here,
there's going to be me and [name] now
talking about from data storage to your science.
It's, you know, very generic talk,
but it's good in my opinion to set the basics.
We've been doing it.
We've been doing this type of basic things over the years and it's good to start with
some definition of what people mean with computing and of course, it's always good to cite some
XKCD cartoon and this is very, very representative of the average picture of a researcher in academia
but also in industry. Honestly, the picture is the same. So the one guy is asking, this is your
machine learning system. Yep. You put the data into this big pile of linear algebra and then
collect the answers on the other side. And what if the answers are wrong? You just steer the,
you know, steer the pile until they spit, until they start looking right. So in general,
scientific computing is about getting some data in doing some magic with the data and getting
something out but of course in between it's not just a black box there's so many things to take
into account which resources do you need and i'm really talking about physical you know hardware
hardware resources or maybe what you need to be careful with the code with the environment
so that you can, for example, reproduce what you do.
So here we have a common scientific computing flow chart,
which is basically what the cartoon was saying earlier.
You get some data.
You get some models that might come from other sources.
You have hypotheses from the literature or whatever you learn from the literature.
And then everything gets gathered into this process block.
And so given the data, the models and whatever else you need to gather together, you generate
the outputs, which could be these derivatives, so-called derivatives file, they can be figures,
they can be tables. And then you write your papers, your posters and so on.
So what actually happens in practice, and I know this is super basic, maybe most of you have done
this in high school, but it's always good to set the dictionary for everyone. So there's this type
of user layer, which is where we are right now. And as a user, you might work with some applications.
You might use R, Matlab, Python, and so on. The applications are on top of a so-called
operating system. It can be Linux, it can be Windows, it can be Mac, whatever. And on top
of the operating system we have the actual hardware, the CPU central processing units where
the actual math happens, the memory random access memory which is where you want to store your
variables or your code for the time that the CPUs can access it, this SSD which is basically the
a little bit slower and bigger storage for storing the data or the code or whatever else
you need to store.
In some hardwares, we also have the GPUs,
which are like CPUs, but many of them
compressed together so that things can be
done much faster in parallel.
And we will talk about this in the day two and three.
But then, of course, you have connectivity,
because sometimes you need to download data
from external sources to your laptop,
or maybe you're not even on your laptop,
like we will show tomorrow.
and the day after, because your laptop doesn't have GPUs,
your laptop doesn't have enough RAM.
So you are in some remote system connected via the internet
where you can run your things.
So here we wrote together kind of a glossary of these terms
in case some of these are not familiar.
But now maybe if I can ask a question to [name],
like what I'm kind of started to describe what's a laptop
what's the normal workflow that people might be familiar with, but how do I know how to know when
I need to scale up to a bigger system? Maybe another question that I can add is that often
people they move their workflow from the laptop to some HPC system and they realize that it's
actually slower there. Why is it so? If we think about the previous diagram of the scientific
process that you showed, it didn't show anything about how do you plan on doing this? Or which
hardware are you planning to use for any of these things? Where do you do the processing for the raw
data and the models and what do you do with the derivatives? It doesn't have any connection or
necessary like definition of where do where should you run these where should you do these
calculations and for many of us it's of course we are using the nearest machine that we have let's
say our computer like our laptop that is provided by the department so we are using the most obvious
resource that we have to do many of these calculations and usually that machine is for you
that machine is dedicated for you, that is yours. And when we are then speaking about
high-performance computing, we are talking about the process where we're pooling resources so that
we can share the resources. Like we have usually funding from a bigger provider that gives us
possibility of getting bigger machines and the bigger machines are then shared by multiple people.
So some of that process, let's say we have an experiment that we want to do, but one part of
that process of doing the analysis is so slow with our laptop that we would want to do it
faster and for that we need to use some shared resource. But the shared resource, because of
the nature that it's shared, we need to usually ask the correct things from it, or we need to
reserve our correct portion of it. So if we don't reserve the correct portion of this resource,
we might reserve less resource than what our laptop has, or we might reserve resources that
that don't solve the correct problem
that we are currently doing.
So for example, we might reserve a GPU
and think that, well, GPUs usually make stuff faster, right?
Like that's the narrative.
So let's just reserve a GPU
and let's just hope that it runs faster,
but that doesn't necessarily work like that.
If the program you're using doesn't use GPUs,
it doesn't necessarily work.
So when we are switching from our laptop to the shared resources,
we usually switch to a different location.
So in a different location might have different things
that make the computing faster.
So we need to basically take advantage
of the specialized hardware.
So for example, our laptops might have maybe eight,
maybe 16 CPUs, and the nodes,
the computational servers in an HPC cluster,
they might have up to 256 processors,
but those processors might be slower
than the laptop processors on average,
but because there's so many of them,
if your program can utilize many processors,
program can still be faster. There's different kinds of resources in the HPC cluster that are
specialized for certain kinds of things. When we are asking, okay, I want to run my code
better or faster, we need to know what our program does and then ask for those resources that
the computational cluster can provide that makes it faster. And here are a few of the
really great questions that you can ask yourself. So, for example, do you need more CPUs? If you
can parallelize your processing. We'll talk about this on day three. You might benefit from adding
CPUs. Sometimes you don't. You might want one big computer or multiple small computers.
That might also benefit you. If your code uses GPUs, like for example, deep learning stuff
nowadays, your only option might be to run it on a computing cluster because the model might
be so big that you cannot run it on a normal laptop or computer. Your laptop might not even
have a GPU. Sometimes you have a lot of data that you need to process, so you need to get the data.
You need to make certain that the data is in the correct place so that the speed is good.
So when you're switching from your laptop to using these shared resources,
do keep in mind that you're basically switching places.
You're switching to a completely different environment.
And in that environment, there are different kinds of considerations.
It's optimized for different kinds of use cases.
And if you don't know necessarily what use case you want to do
or you don't know what your program is doing
it's usually a good idea to ask help from more experienced users
or the system administrators and so forth
so that they can figure out which program your program benefits most from
Yeah, one aspect that you see here at the bottom that sometimes maybe you don't even
need like your laptop would be totally fine with the resources that you have, but it's
the data that you're working with that cannot be taken away, that cannot be taken out from
your share folder in the university.
And so then these remote resources, these large computational resources can also be
useful that the computations and the data stay in the remote, but of course you can still
use your laptop with fake data or just for development.
But basically, yeah, this session
is kind of just to set the basics for everyone here.
There's some, how do I do scientific computing?
It's most likely you already know where to start,
whether you're a Python, R, or whatever programming languages.
There are good practices for each language and tools
available.
And you can understand already that what works on your laptop
doesn't necessarily, it's not necessarily going to work
on the remote cluster.
But what we will see in the rest of the day
and also in the next days is basically strategies to move,
for example, the same so-called Python environment
from your laptop to a remote location,
or to make sure that you have the software
that you need to run in the remote location.
Here, there's a picture of what [name] was saying earlier
that once you leave your laptop,
if you think that this is the internet,
you can basically request remote servers,
remote so-called nodes.
So there are other pieces of hardware,
there are other machines that can allow you
to do your computations, not on your laptop anymore,
but on the remote location.
This picture is generic enough in a sense
that this is not specific to Alto.
There are some of these open services,
There's a list here in the bottom, like MyBinder or Google
Colab, where you can run this type of computations
via a so-called notebook interface with a web browser.
What we will explore more tomorrow
is this type of HPC clusters that universities usually
give access to, and also the national providers,
like CSC in Finland.
And often what you will notice, and what we will remind also
today, is that sometimes to work with this system,
you need to, it's not as easy as, you know,
opening a web browser
and using the so-called notebook interface.
You might need to be familiar with the command line interface
and access, for example, the login node,
and then later request, you know,
one of the hundreds of CPUs or GPUs and so on.
But don't worry about this.
We will cover this during the connection session
in later today.
We are perfectly on time with our schedule now because it's 12.25 and I could keep screen sharing
and give a motivational talk with [name]. [name], are you here?
I'll jump out.
Thank you, [name]. You will hear [name] a lot in the next.
[name], do you want to say something briefly about yourself?
Yeah. Hi, everyone. I work as an application specialist at CSC, IT Center for Science.
You will hear about that also, I think, last day of this workshop more. I work there in
user support, outreach, and training. And I'm also community manager of the Code Refinery
Project, which we will be talking about now a little bit. And I also do still my PhD on
very low part-time at Aalto University about satellite remote sensing stuff.
Excellent. So what we wanted to cover in the next 25 minutes, and then we can have a break
for 10 minutes to stretch our legs, is to mention the importance of reproducibility
and open science. I don't know how many of you are familiar with the concept of reproducibility,
but most likely I know that many of the people watching are starting their summer internship
or starting their doctoral research career, you want, you know, to be reproducible. You want to
start from the first day to make sure that what you've been doing today, what you've been working
on today, you can replicate it in one month. So the materials that are linked now from this,
from the schedule of the day, are from the so-called Code Refinery workshop. And as [name]
has mentioned, Code Refinery is a larger workshop that covers various aspects of the so-called
computational reproducibility.
So in this short 25 minutes, the workshop
is actually lasting for six days, three hours every day,
three hours and a half.
Here in this short slot, we just want
to inspire you, give you a bit of a motivation of why
reproducibility is important, and then
how does it fit into the picture of the Code Refinery
Workshop.
For those who will be interested in the next Code Refinery
workshop it is now planned in the first half of September so if you register for this course and
you mark that you want to stay up to date you will receive further emails when the registrations are
open. But in general when it comes to reproducibility the situation is like this so
this is a professor with some research assistant or actually this is a doctoral doctor researcher
and the professors say don't worry you don't have to start from you have to start your code
from scratch which is you know it's great you got some code from the previous postdoc or whoever
you can reuse the software that the previous person on the project wrote several years ago
are there instructions for how to use it i doubt it is the code commented not likely where are
the files who knows this is going to be painful isn't it it's just a scratch so i don't know
about you, [name], but I've seen this situation. I don't know, I still see it on a, maybe not daily
basis, but weekly basis, which is, I mean, yeah, it's also understandable. People join the research
project, whether they are for an internship, whether they are for those years of the doctoral
research, and then they move on, they change university. And then if there's not a culture
of preserving, archiving and making things reproducible and documented, this process will
keep on staying. So we don't need now to go through the whole page but in general what you can think
when you read a scientific article that the article is actually just the tip of the whole
process of getting the data, collecting the data, analyzing the data, producing the statistical
article results, summaries, tables, outputs, whatever. And so the article, sometimes with
the article itself, it's impossible to replicate what other people are doing. So you need the
documentation on the process, on the software, you need maybe actually access to the actual
code or to the actual data. And sometimes even if you have the same code and the same
data, you still get different numbers. And this is because maybe the environment, the
libraries, the operating system, and other things
have changed in the meantime.
So all these parameters, all the elements you see here
would actually be needed for achieving the reproducibility.
So in these materials that you see linked there,
you can browse them like this.
We cover various aspects of the so-called, you know,
pyramid that you just show,
but it's nice to put it all in the context
of the Code Refinery workshop.
So, [name], maybe it would be better than me to give an overview of this picture.
One, two, three, four, five, six steps.
Do you want to briefly?
Yes, I can do that. And here, maybe also just in addition to what [name] already mentioned.
So we have these workshops twice a year, but we also have these lesson materials that [name] is showing right now.
And there is a link to this in the collaborative notes as well.
So you can also go through the materials yourself,
see what interests you, and maybe learn
something new related to this.
So we have really liked this little figure here
by Heidi Seibold, who made it about the six helpful steps
for reproducible research.
So it all starts already from the very beginning
when you start your research journey.
And you start having files.
you start creating folders.
And there, it already is very useful to take a step back
and think about your naming and how you order things.
And there is multiple guides out there
who can give you a structure that you can follow
that's always very useful to do.
And that's something that this reproducible research lesson
that we're showing here is also about.
so we talk a little bit about different naming conventions
that you can follow,
different structures that you can follow, and so on.
So in our workshop, that's day four, like it's noted here,
but it's the first day of where it goes actually deep
into the different tools and techniques
that you can use for your research.
Yeah, then this is also already step two,
use good names for them, also for functions.
you write your own code, you can save a lot of documentation and commenting things if you just
have good names for your things. And that is also mentioned in our documentation lesson,
how to document your research software, and in the modular code development lessons that we have.
Then, I mentioned already documentation is a very important step because you might be working
on different projects, so if you have been doing something and you had a really good reason for
setting something up in a certain way, you might not remember that when you get back to it like
two days later, a week later, a year later. And then also when others take a look at your codes
or your software as a whole, it helps you to kind of keep your time free because not everyone has
to come and run to you and ask you about like, oh how do I actually use this or why is it done
that way. That's stupid. So you can do that by documenting your codes from the beginning.
And there's different levels of doing that. And that's what we also talk about in this
documentation lesson. And then the first week of the Code Refinery Workshop is all about version
control. Why you would want to use it, what it is, what it actually is, how to use it for yourself,
how to use it when you are collaborating with others and to understand a bit on what's behind
different commands that you might have already used, like commands like git clone, for example,
git push, git commit, these things. Hopefully you have heard about this before, but if not,
then the first week of the Code Refinery Workshop introduces this on a very, how do you say,
shallow learning curve, so you start with what you might already know and then you go deeper and deeper step by step into that you can in the end work together with others using version control.
Then, step five here, stabilizing the computing environment and the software, that basically
many of our lessons have in some way.
We talk about Jupyter notebooks for doing that.
That's a nice way of collaborating with others, but also to prototyping for yourself.
In the reproducible research lesson, we talk about this with, what is it called, now I
the word, but containers we talk about. We talk about workflows there, like how you can run
multiple steps of your analysis pipeline, for example, automatically without having to worry
too much about is it run in the right order? Is it run on all my files and so on? And then also
about like, I still don't remember the word, but these computing environments that you can create
with virtual environment, with Conda for example, you might have heard about these things before
and what's behind that, why do you want to use them and how can you use them to make your research
more reproducible. And then also a little bit about publishing your research outputs. So you will
have maybe in the end of your research project you will have code, you will have data, you will have
other documents. And those are, I don't want to say useless, but less useful for others when they
are just lying on your own computer. And there is a few things that you have to think about then,
like what kind of license do I want to add to my code? Do I want others to easily reuse it,
or do I maybe not want others to reuse it? And does my university have guidelines on this?
and these are the things that we are talking in this social coding and open software lesson.
I believe that in my opinion these six steps are extremely useful because truly if I start a new
project I'm really starting with the folders, with the files and as [name] has already mentioned
all of these six steps that you see here from the you know day zero setting up the folder and
gathering the code that you already have already some documentation some readme so-called file
already all these materials are available I can give you a demo or help you kind of browsing
these materials so the materials that are linked from the web page from today is this reproducible
research and so there for example there is the section that is about organizing your project
and here now I will not go through the teaching part but you see this is a kind of a standard
folder structure that you can create for a new project there are you can create this manually
or you can even there are how can I say automated way to create this type of folder structures we
discussed this here they are linked here but the goal actually what is important when it comes to
reproducibility is that often you're not working alone.
You maybe are working with other people,
with other colleagues,
so most likely you want to have a share place,
a share project name with share convention.
So it's very important that you actually talk
with your peers.
If you don't yet already have a standardized way
of storing the data, storing the process data,
the results, the code, and so on,
it's now a good moment to start the discussion.
And for example, use these pages for getting inspirations
and already starting from the very beginning
with reproducibility in mind.
Another aspect that [name] touched
was about the so-called computational steps.
So of course, version control for those who are using Git.
By the way, we have added in our shared notes document
a little question to know if you're already familiar
with Git version control or not.
But in general, we need to also record the computational steps
because it's very rare that you just
have one single script that will just load the data,
do some math, and save the outputs.
Most likely, there's many steps to do.
And again, this type of steps, there's
no other way to document them except having
humans writing what the actual steps are there.
So in this other part of the reproducibility lesson,
you can see some ways of how to record steps.
There's the so-called scripts,
where you could basically write the plot
of all the code that you need to run.
But in general, even have a simple so-called readme file.
So a txt file that is living there close to the code
that will just tell to the future user
in one year or in five years,
first you need to run the function
or the Python script name like this.
And second, you will need to run another one and so on.
Here in this lesson, there are also some advanced things.
This is the beauty of the code refinery materials
that they are written as accessible as possible.
So there's no prerequisite,
but also the more experienced user can learn something new.
So for example, there are workflow tools
and SnakeMake is one of them.
If you know what's Make,
SnakeMake is kind of uses the same principle,
but instead of building code like you would do with Make,
building software, you would actually use it
for basically writing a so-called acyclic pipeline
to basically go from the input data
to the actual derivatives file that you need.
In the same lesson that we're browsing here quickly,
then we go to the level of dependencies.
And this is, again, another XKCD to inspire people.
But this is truly what it is in all
modern digital infrastructure.
This is not just about research.
This is about all the services that you use,
that sometimes, if not always,
they are based on components like this little block there.
There is a project by some random person in Nebraska
that has been thanklessly maintained since 2003.
There are many, many example of this type of process.
There's the Curl, for example,
which is one of the most used protocol
tool to transfer data between systems, and it used to be for many years just a random person
somewhere, I think in Sweden, that was maintaining it. Now it's better maintained.
But in general, this is the thing, that even though you are good at documenting your code
and your data, and so that hopefully in five years or even yourself in one year after peer review
to be able to rerun things, you then realize that in the meantime the Python library that you were
using has changed, that Python 3.something had a problem and now you need to upgrade to the new
Python and nothing works anymore. So sometimes you really need to preserve not just the code
and the documentation and the data, but also all the dependencies, all the libraries that are
attached. Again here, this is just a quick intro, 10 minutes, they were working together, but if
And if you're starting a new project, it's very much important to invest in fixing the
versions of the tools that you want to use and basically agreeing on what type of libraries
you will use and defining these type of dependencies and so on.
So in this lesson, for those who are familiar with the so-called CONDA, it's one way of
taking care of Python environments where you can define all the type of dependencies that
your code has.
So if you are starting today a new project, it's good to have a discussion again with
your colleagues and agree, for example, on what type of libraries do you want to use
and what type of dependencies your project should have.
So this is at the level of the dependencies of the software.
Sometimes, in some cases, you really
need to go to the highest level that you
need to have also that the environment
that the whole operating system is reproducible.
We recently moved from an old operating system
to a new operating system with our Triton cluster.
And sometimes, most of the software
were working in the new operating system,
but there were some specific cases
that were dependent on the old operating system.
So one way to get over this type of dependency
that is related to the actual system is to adopt containers.
So with containers, they're basically,
it's like not only having the libraries that you need
and the code that you need, but it's really
having the full image of the operating system
where everything runs on top.
If you remember at the beginning,
I was talking about the operating system
and all these other layers up to the user.
So with the container, it's really this joke
that it works on my machine.
Well, then we'll ship your machine.
And this is our Docker, which is one of these container
technologies.
Again here, we don't have the time
to cover to the containers.
But you know that if you have this type of problem,
or if you ever had this type of need
that you would like to move the full pipeline from one system,
from one cluster to another, then
it's good to invest in learning containers.
Here, these are simple learning materials
that you can read by yourself and test things by yourself.
But in general, we also have more advanced courses
for those cases.
And this kind of covers everything from this reproducibility lesson
and this reproducibility summary. We still have five minutes.
I don't know if [name] is still here with me.
But in general, the Code Refinery workshop doesn't only cover,
even though the reproducibility is at the code of the Code Refinery workshop.
Code Refinery is like a large also informal network.
Let me type the address, a large informal network of basically people who are passionate
on data science, software, open science, good practices, they join together and they discuss
together.
I don't know if [name], if we still have five minutes, do you want to mention the type
of engagement that people could have with the Code Refinery, especially we are looking
for ambassadors?
Do you want to tell something? I can also open some of these other links if you want me to.
So yes, maybe the first entry point into CodeRefiner is to visit one of our workshops.
So our next workshop is coming up, like [name] already mentioned there, and it's written there September 10th to 12th and 17th to 19th.
It's always half a day, and we'll talk about all the topics that I mentioned in this reproducible research steps.
And then, if you get excited about this, or if you maybe are already excited about these topics that we have been talking about here now,
So then we're already always looking for contributors to the lesson material, for example, or also
just people in different places that will advertise the workshop to their network.
Because that's one of the hardest things that we have to do is to actually get this message
that these workshops exist to the people that have use of it.
We very often get the feedback, oh, I wish I would have known this in the beginning of
my PhD or something like this.
You can help with that. If this is something that interests you, the best way is to sign up for our
newsletter, then you will get a message when actually the registration opens for our workshop,
and then you can send that forward to your network. If you like doing that kind of stuff,
like spreading the word about Code Refinery, maybe you go to conferences and you have talks about,
I don't know, your own topic. If you just want to add one little slide about Code Refinery,
just making your network aware that it exists, then becoming an ambassador is a nice way of
supporting us and we also want to support you doing that. So if you go in the top about join
and for individuals.
So there are all the different ways that you can engage with the community are mentioned here and
and if you scroll a little bit down there is this Code Refinery Ambassador.
So if you want to become one then let us know and that can work either via
our contact email address which you can also find on that page
or by joining our Zulip chat or you can also
let us know via the collaborative document of this course for example.
We will read that and then we will reach out to you and we will have
meetups of the ambassadors and try to support you in any way we can. We also have stickers
that you can distribute that always gets people interested in things. And yeah, we're very happy to
connect with you. But yeah, also just joining as a learner. Joining in Aalto, for example,
we will have an in-person room where you can follow the workshop all together with [name]
and you will have [name] there answering all your questions that you might have regarding the material.
So it's a really nice and community experience to join the workshop in Otoniemi.
For those who are, well hopefully some of you who are listening actually were in some of the recent workshops, for example the March workshop,
but we are all very open with our lessons and also documentation from the workshops,
So let's say that you don't want to wait for September the 10th
and you already want to start learning,
you can click on the March workshop.
And there you see the schedule.
And for each part of the schedule,
let's say day one, Introduction to Version Control,
there are links to the lesson material.
There are links to the videos, to the recordings.
So truly, if one wanted, you could actually have,
you could actually do the full workshop by yourself
with just using the videos, the recordings,
the archive materials, the archive questions,
and all the lesson materials that are there.
But of course, yeah, it's more fun to do it together,
to do it with a colleague.
Here at Alto, we're trying to promote
this type of hybrid room so that people can come here
and have some cookies, fruits,
and at the same time, watch the stream.
The stream still happens on Twitch TV,
so being in person is not necessary,
especially because Code Refinery is a Nordic network,
So we have people streaming from Norway, from Denmark,
from Sweden and so on.
But then the social part is also important,
especially during the exercise is what that can be
some interesting questions or things like that.
But anyway, hopefully this was motivational enough.
Thank you so much [name] for joining us
for this overview, very quick overview
of the whole Code Refinery.
Thanks for having me.
Yes, and we are perfectly on time, it's 12.50.
So let's quickly check if there's anything in the notes
that should be mentioned.
But eventually, we can get to the notes later.
Maybe let's have the break now until 1 o'clock sharp.
And please stretch your legs, have a glass of water,
and see you.
The stream will start again at 1 PM Finnish time
and at the hour in other time zones.
Thank you.
you
Hello, welcome back. Hopefully you had a good little break. So next up we have something
which we call the humans of scientific computing. So it's interviews where we basically talk
about ourselves. And our special guest this time here is [name], who was in the
previous talk, actually. Hi. So, [name], can you tell us a little bit about
yourself again and maybe go more into what's your background and how did you start your career?
Okay, yes. So, I did my bachelor in Germany in Geoecology or Natural Sciences and then went on to
to start my Master's in Geoinformatics from where I went on an exchange year to Finland
to Aalto University during my Master's in Geoinformatics and that led me to being in
contact with the Finnish Geospatial Research Institute where I asked for a possibility
to do my master thesis here because I really liked Finland and I really wanted to stay here.
This was almost nine years ago now, I'm still in Finland, so it all worked out. I got to do
my master thesis, they actually paid me for it and even offered me a job after that at the
Research Institute where I was working with satellite remote sensing mainly and at some point
they said okay we would actually like everyone to have a PhD because that just makes life at
the Research Institute much easier. Don't you want to start one? And I hadn't thought about this
before so much but I was like hey it's the same as my normal work so why not like package it and
do a PhD. As you maybe mentioned before I'm still working on that even though this is now also
already almost seven years ago. That's mainly due to it being very short only full-time,
but mainly being part-time. So I did other work during the same time. For a short while,
I did it full-time because I got a grant from Aalto University to focus on it, but there was
a few projects that didn't go as planned. Maybe you know about these things. And yeah, nowadays,
like two years ago I got an email that CSE was looking for a geoinformatics specialist and I was
reading like through the job ad and was like yes yes yes yes oh this sounds interesting but I was
a little bit like afraid also of it because CSE like the big scientific computing center and
my background is not in like really computing or something. I learned most of it actually during
the PhD times like I learned about how to use Linux, I learned programming in Python and so on
during that time and I learned also how to use or well yeah how to use supercomputer partly
through this course, but also through CSC courses. I knew how to apply this for my research. I knew
how to run something in parallel on the supercomputer, but I had never looked behind that.
So I was a little bit like, is this really something for me? But then I talked to a lot
of people in especially the code refinery community and they very much encouraged me to do that
still and yeah here I am nowadays. I work two years now as a geoinformatics specialist
helping geoinformatics researchers with bringing their computations
to the supercomputer and doing training and so on and nowadays a bit more general so it's not
any more geoinformatics specific, but also for other fields and to outreach, trying to reach
people in the early stages, for example, of their PhD to know that there is these CSC services and
stuff like Code Refinery available. So what does it mean trying to help people to bring their work
to the CSC supercomputers? Let's exclude the Code Refinery work and other teaching things.
What's a day in your life look like?
Well, so in that regard, it's basically like this morning we had a workshop with,
in this case, humanists. So we asked them, do you know about CSC resources,
do you know about supercomputers, that they exist for your work? And they said no.
So we had to say like, okay, this is not just for supercomputation, but it's also like if you have
something, a small thing that you need to run multiple times, like trying to explain it in a way
that they can relate to it based on their current work. And that is mainly what a lot of this is,
trying to lower the barrier towards supercomputing, HPC, all those big words that if you're not
coming from computational backgrounds are maybe not that familiar.
Yeah.
So do you actually help them to like, do you take their code or analysis and actually help
them get it started running?
Things like that.
Yes.
So if we know about that people struggle with making their own code run, for example, on
our supercomputers, then we get to help them.
And we get to tell a little bit about the maybe different way of thinking that you need
to start when you switch from your own laptop to the supercomputer.
it's very often that we don't know about it. Very many people find that their problem is too small
or they are they have not read enough documentation or have some other reason for not asking for help
and then of course we cannot help and sometimes we then get to know about it very late in the process
And then of course we also still try to help, but the best experience for us and also for the researchers that we support is like when we get involved right in the beginning.
For CSC services, for example, when we are already part of choosing the right service because we have so many of them.
And as a researcher, it's not necessarily clear what is the right service for me.
service for me. So that is also, for example, a very general question that one can ask from
us where we can say like, okay, this is perfect for this service or perfect for another service.
Yeah. Okay. What have you learned in your past research, like from your research career
to what you do now? What did you learn when studying research that helps you now?
I think the main thing that helps me in my job right now that I have learned from the
time as a researcher is how, I don't know how to put it, but how a researcher thinks.
It's not just telling, okay, we have these awesome services, here are 20 courses you
can do to learn about these services.
But it's more like also thinking about where the researchers are and what are their goals.
For most researchers, that is to get the paper out.
So, that is the main focus.
All this stuff like version control, reproducible research is like a minor thing at the side
which might even be bugging them rather than helping.
Yeah.
And I think...
It's like this researcher mindset.
Yeah, exactly.
Like being able to help on a level that is actually helpful for a researcher.
Not only like, okay, here is all the things you need to know, but also trying to convey
that there is something as good enough.
There is like small steps you can take to make your and other's life better.
You don't have to do everything.
And that we can actually help with that.
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay, so you said you were a little bit worried about the transition when you started.
I mean, were you, like, how worried were you and, like, what were the kinds of things you
worried about?
Let's put it that way.
And then how did it turn out in the end?
Was it actually anything worth worrying about?
No, it was not.
That was the first thing.
I was very worried about not being able to answer all the questions people might have,
because one big part of this job that I applied for was user support and was training.
I was not doing a lot of this at the time, mainly with Code Refinery, actually, and there
it was always a second person there.
When I didn't know something, then the second person could jump in.
about this being alone there and being alone with a user, with a researcher who asks me questions
and I might not know the answer that was a very scary thing because for me the support I have
gotten from CSC was very personal and very good and like of course like that was my picture of
how it's supposed to be and I'm still thriving for that but since then I've also learned that
like, it's okay to not know everything. We cannot know everything. There's so much to know,
like, not only about our services, but about scientific computing in general.
And very often, I still know maybe one little thing more than the researcher who is asking
the question. So even just telling, hey, I know that we have a documentation page about this,
or, hey, you could look into this tool, this might do what you want to do. That already helps
sometimes so much that the researcher is happily going away. And it feels like having accomplished
something, even though I actually didn't know the actual answer to the problem. And that was maybe
the main worry, like not being good enough with the computational side of things. Like someone who
has like programmed their whole life or studied computer science or anything like that.
So what do you say? It's like you bring your researcher mindset to the current things.
When you were a researcher, you solved problems no one knew the answer to and you do the same
now.
Yes, yes, I think so. And I have to remind myself once in a while about that, like how
it was these, let's say five years ago, when I was the researcher struggling with something and
also feeling all my questions not big enough, like what would I have needed at the time to
kind of brave off, ask my questions from the specialists and also what kind of
of support would I have needed?
Like that in many occasions,
because everyone is short on time,
it is the easy answer to find a link to documentation
and just say, hey, read this.
This is an easy solution to many of troubles
that people have.
But as a researcher,
I have gotten that answer also at some point.
And maybe I've even read the page at the time,
but I was not able to put what is written there
into the context of my work.
So nowadays I try to remember that.
And when someone asks a question,
I like try to first ask, okay,
what is this actually about before answering?
With also some links in a side sentence,
like saying, okay,
you could also take a look here at this tutorial,
but also try to explain how this relates
to the actual question that was asked.
Okay, that's good.
So we've got a question from the note.
So I'm at the beginning of my career as a master's student
and I'm considering academia.
What is the thing that one should know when starting?
I guess you're not the academic career path,
but this is similar to a common question I've asked people.
What do you know now that you wish someone
had told you years ago?
so. That this path exists, like that there is a way to not be an academic, not be a researcher,
doing your own research, trying to write papers and doing that stuff, but that there is also
stuff like you do at Aalto, the research software engineer, stuff like we do at CSC with the user
support and so on. People that are very much connected to the research but don't have to
write their own papers but rather support everyone who needs the support doing their
research and that can be more efficient, faster or just even like getting started with it.
So I wish I had known that earlier. I got to know that actually through Code Refinery because when
When I visited the Code Refinery Workshop, I got really excited about this, and asked
to get involved in the project and do stuff there, and went then from helper to instructor
to an organizer and community manager.
But only through joining that network, I got to know that there is so much more beyond
the traditional academics and research software engineering and so on.
Yeah. The next question there asks about what kind of positions are in private companies,
which I guess neither of us are really qualified to answer. Maybe next year I could try to
find someone that works at a private company and invite them.
Yeah. And I know that there is also a research position in private companies, for example.
But yeah, that as a short answer.
But I mean, I guess the point of this whole interview is that there are positions which
are related to research and quite interesting in their own right, which are not the academic
track, which many people are qualified for and don't know about.
Yeah, and it's so interesting to also, as a researcher, you are in your own little world
with your focus point, especially as PhD,
you have your little slice of the world
that you're working on.
But as what we do, we get in contact
with many different people from many different domains,
backgrounds, levels in their, or stages in their career.
And it's very interesting to be part of kind of all of that,
even when it's just a little bit through one question
that we get in our user support sessions or something.
Would you say that you have a wider variety or more interesting problems now or when you
were in the academic track doing your own stuff?
Yes, definitely.
Also partly because, well, when I was a full academic, it was just when I started with
programming and scientific computing things in general, so I worked on one big project
for very, very long because I just had to learn at the time also.
So I got very sick of that project, but it's still also with me.
But now it's more varied.
So there's many different questions that people come with.
Some are easy to solve, like within a few minutes.
Some need more hours.
Some maybe need more days.
Yeah. And very much varied. Yeah.
So we're coming a little bit close to the end here. There's still almost 10 minutes, but please, so now's the time people start writing all your random questions in the notes, the ones that are most relevant to [name], I will raise up, but other people can also answer there.
There is a question I would like to answer actually. Do people in industry use these things you mentioned earlier, like conda containers and HPC?
Conda and containers, yes, definitely, if they know about it, that's not necessarily
a given.
And for us, it's probably harder to reach people in companies.
HPC, maybe nowadays a bit more than earlier, because, for example, the Lumi supercomputer
is available for companies as well.
And if you go to the Lumi website, you can find out that there is a few companies using
Lumi.
So for those, we also offer kind of a specific training and get, oh, we wish, I don't know
how it really is in industry.
Maybe someone who's working in industry can talk.
Okay.
Yeah.
So what do you say that this course that's here now is also useful for industry track
people?
Yes.
I would say so, because you might be the one bringing that stuff to the company.
They might not know about it for whatever reason, and you might be the one that then has a solution
to a problem by, for example, knowing how to, well, organize your project to start with,
or if you visit a code refinery course, like knowing how to use Git that can make
many processes more efficient, and then the company will be very happy about that.
Yeah, yeah. So would you say that these kind of courses give you an advantage when looking for
other jobs? I mean, I guess, well, that's probably obvious. Let's say you finish a PhD and you have
a bunch of articles to your name, or you have a bunch of articles and you say,
I've trained to use supercomputers in Git. That's pretty obvious.
Yeah, that probably depends on what you're then looking for.
So what I have learned from getting the job at CSC is that just having used a supercomputer is
a very good starting point for even working in supercomputing support, for example.
because you actually know, you might not know every detail, but you can learn that also on the
job. I learned so much every day on the job. But you know where the researchers are coming from,
so you have been in the situation that you have asked some of these questions yourself. So
I think with that knowledge you can be a very good person to be between the IT admins
and the researchers to translate between them, like if the IT admin says like oh this is not
something we do here, then you can start explaining why this is not something we do here for example.
Yeah, cool. So what's your experience with the PhD overall? Would you say it was worth it?
So I'm still working on it, so yes I think it's still worth it.
Mainly because I have now also seen in my current job, it's a permanent position, so I would not necessarily need it for that.
But we are still working so close with academia that we also want to support research projects from the beginning and support them really a bit more in depth.
depth and for that we need to be part of the research project funding application and for
that it's better to have a PhD to your name because you actually have some academic
merits that help with this with the project application while without that we have only
like a few people who can be this PIs of the research project within the company so too many
research projects that want to maybe put us on the application, we have to say no,
because we don't have the people to actually cover that. And I have learned everything that brought
me right here, right now, during the time of my PhD. Basically, none of it I learned during my
actual studies, master's or bachelor.
Yeah. Okay. When do you say like the PhD is basically experience that counts for something?
Yes. And I think like, of course, you don't need to do a PhD. You can also work as a researcher after your master's.
The PhD maybe allows that you can do or also gives a bit easier the possibility to do courses.
Like for example I could get I think over 10 credits for my PhD from visiting CSE courses
for example and that also of course motivated me to do the courses because I could fill my credits
with that. If I would not have done the PhD I would have maybe done like maybe one course
a year or something just to learn something new, stay up to date and stuff.
But in that sense it was really useful. Yeah, so we're almost out of time. So
what do you hope to continue learning and what comes next?
Well, I hope to continue learning more about how things work, how many of our services work,
How to reach, like currently my focus is a lot on outreach so I hope to learn more about
how to best reach out to people that would have use for our services and that would have
use for our support because there is so much of it available, so many people that are very
happy to help with things and I'm always so sad to hear stories like that someone has
been struggling with something that we could have helped with if we had only known
after two years of struggling or something like this. Yeah. Okay.
Yeah, I guess we're basically out of time. There's a comment that you're really cool
and a good role model. So yes, I would agree with that.
Thank you.
You know, many of our visitors here are like that. So yeah, I mean, we have to keep finding
more for next year.
I'm glad to hear this was useful. Thank you for having me.
Yeah, I mean, like really, [name] and all of us, we're basically normal people that
want to keep work going, help, basically, yeah.
You're normal nerds.
Yeah.
But yeah, OK.
So I guess thank you, [name], and see you
around at the next Code Refinery workshop in September.
Yeah, and if you have any more questions,
I'll still be here and answer them in the document.
Keep them coming.
OK, great.
Thanks.
Bye.
OK, who is next?
I think we're about to have some demos, if I remember correctly.
Yeah.
Okay.
Whose screen should I go to?
I can take the screenshot.
Okay.
And.
So yeah.
Yeah.
I will head out for a bit.
So see you later then.
Yes.
Okay.
So yeah, throughout the day we've had very interesting discussions about what computing is.
And we thought that it might be nice to have some demos showing what can be done in a computational cluster.
And these are straight out of the press, so let's see how much of a demo effect we will get.
So, to help me today, we have [name]. Do you want to introduce yourself?
Yeah, I'm a research software engineer at Aalto in [name]'s group.
been there now for three years, and still having fun.
Yeah, so it's good to hear that you're having fun.
[name], your sound might be coming from a room microphone.
Yeah, sorry.
Yeah, so what do we have for you today?
Okay, so I prepared two demos.
So these are like two demos that might interest
in like different people in our audience.
So the first demo, I will demonstrate
like how you could run this molecular dynamic simulator
called LAMPS, which might be physicists out there
might be interested in, which uses like
Mesas passing interface on MPI for parallelization.
talk about that soonish. So, I have here a terminal. It's running on our login node. So,
these demos are very much like demos that... Yeah. Are you going to talk about the big picture of
what we're doing and what people should try to follow and not try to follow right now?
Yes. So, these are very much demos that are for our site. So, they might not work for your site.
And these demos are to show what sort of things you're capable of doing in the computing cluster.
So, you shouldn't necessarily worry about writing these up or taking notes or anything like that.
what we want you to focus on is the big picture of like, okay, you have a scientific problem,
you want to solve it in the computing cluster, so what sort of workflow you might encounter.
In this case, let's say we want to run some simulation with this LAMP's molecular dynamics
code. First off, I would probably want to get the example. I have prepared this git clone command.
What this does is that it clones the LAMPS repository, which contains the examples that
we want to run. On the bottom, you can see history of the commands that I'm running.
So there's like a terminal there showing what commands I'm running.
So you might encounter this kind of like a command line interface.
This is only one way of accessing the computational cluster.
But we'll be working with the command line interface quite soon.
But you can just now limit yourself to the knowledge that I'm in the computational cluster.
I'm taking out the demos.
And here I have now the lamps folder and I will go to examples and I will try this simple
like intendation example.
So in this example, we have like a 2D plane of atoms where we modify or we make an intendation
into this atom lattice by forcing a spherical indenter
into that lattice.
And first of all,
You're smashing something into it.
Yeah, we're smashing atoms, so it sounds better.
So I will first modify the input file a bit.
I'll actually use Mano for them.
I will make here, I will modify one line that
make certain that we get a dump or this kind of like output
from the demo that we can then visualize later on.
So we store the atom positions every 250 time steps.
So I will modify this file.
And what we do typically in a computed cluster,
we'll talk about this in much more detail tomorrow.
But what we usually do is that we write these instructions
for the computer, what it should run on the resources,
the computational resources.
So what I would do here is I'm going
to quickly write this script.
Maybe, [name], if you want to explain shortly what I'm doing.
Essentially, when you want to submit a photo to a cluster, you need to tell it what kind of
resources you want. And that's what Simu is currently indicating. So in this case,
it's using the Slurm scheduler. And the Slurm scheduler essentially reads a bash script
and interprets these comments that are here in the beginning. Using a bash script, everything
that's starting with a hashtag is a comment and when the scheduler sees or when the submission
system sees this s-batch it knows that this is a command for the scheduler and here it's
this should be running on one node it should have should get 16 cpus the memory per cpu
should be 2 gigabytes so a total of 32 gigabytes well or 16 now yeah yeah and it should be running
for a specific time. After that time the process would essentially be killed. So in this case it's
10 minutes that this will be running at most. And below those comments, good explanation,
thank you, beyond those comments we will have instructions that we expect the code to run.
So commands that we want the code to run. So in this case we'll do this module loading. We'll
talk about this later as well, but we will basically load some pre-installed software
that is installed by the cluster people and we will preload that and then we will run it,
this lump command, with the input that we have. Let's hope that this works.
And to quickly say, the reason why all of this software is not just available is that
you want to keep the nodes where these tools are running as clean as possible.
So if you would install lots and lots of software on all of the nodes, there would be a significant
amount of resources already taken up just by that, because not necessarily every node
has a hard drive. And if you don't have a hard drive, you need to store all of these things in
memory. And that's why these tools are installed elsewhere. So I had a mistake in the script. So
I fixed that. I had a wrong setting because I mistyped it. After fixing that, I submitted this
script to the queue. In these HPC clusters, we have a queue. We'll talk more about it later.
That will run it whenever it finds a correct place for the job to run. Currently,
you can see that actually there's an interactive session that I have open on another
So not a place open, but that job actually probably finished.
So let's see.
I just want to give one more comment here.
I'm not sure if the Slurm command as such
is available on clusters, because I
think that is a script that was created in Alto.
So if you want to do that, or if you want to check queues,
I think we are coming to that later as well.
Yes.
There was one more mistake.
I didn't specify which MPI implementation I want to use.
But now it's run.
We can see the output.
So we see what Lumps provides is this kind of like an output,
but it also provides this dump file that, well,
is a video basically of what happened during the run.
There's a question in, yeah.
If we could introduce a bit of the background of this script.
So why do we need this script?
Why can't we just run it, like, well,
essentially on that command line as it is?
Yes, that's an excellent question.
So the question comes back to what
we were talking earlier today about computing resources,
because we are sharing resources.
We are not running this on, we could run this
on our own laptop, but in this case,
want to run it, like, this is of course like a bit of a toy example, but if we
would be running like an actual simulation, we would be, it would require
a lot more resources and we, because we're sharing the resources, there needs
to be a way of sharing these resources.
And we'll talk about this tomorrow a lot more, how the sharing happens
and how the queue system works.
But basically there's like a queue system that organizes how the different jobs
run. And I want to add to that. So normally, or in almost all clusters I've seen up until
now, if you connect to the cluster, you are actually on the login node. So if you would
run the login, the login node is kind of the access point for everyone to that cluster.
So if you start running code on this directly on that node, you would run it on one machine
that is shared by everyone.
And very often, these machines have restrictions
how much resources someone can actually use on them.
And very often, they also have kind of automated script
that kill or stops stop code that
is taking too much resources.
So running things on the logger node is not a good idea,
or it shouldn't be done.
So that's why we need to write this script,
because the script has the information on how
for the scheduler that [name] mentioned
on how to put it to the actual cluster.
And the cluster is not the same here.
Maybe.
Yeah, I would quickly mention that you can think about it
more if you look at the script again,
like we asked for eight CPUs
currently, let's say my laptop, I'm watching the stream currently. I'm having a Zoom open. I have
some browsers open and anything. If I would run these on my own laptop, my laptop would basically
overheat. It's currently running at about 70 degrees anyway, so it would basically be game
over for that if I would try to run this simulation at the same time while I'm running other stuff.
So that's why I want to run it in the cluster.
So let's think in a more traditional high performance
computing situation, where if you are a physicist and you
would want to run this code, but you want to run it in a
production size, it might be thousands of times bigger.
So then you might need tens of nodes, hundreds of CPUs to
actually run a big simulation.
So in those cases, yeah, laptop isn't any more an option to do.
But we'll talk about the parallelization later on.
But this is like, OK, if we return back to the example,
OK, this is all fine and nice that I managed to run it.
But OK, if I want to now see what the result was,
like these command line interfaces, it might be good for programming what I want the computer to
do, what I want the queue to do, and what I want to run. But if I want to visualize it, this might
not be the best option. So for that, at least here in Aalto, in other sites there might be
different ones. We have this open on demand, so CSC at least has this kind of a service,
where you can launch like a temporary virtual desktop. You might have other, like in Alto
there's also the VDI service, but this runs in a cluster that basically provides you a desktop
in a browser. So you can visualize the results that you have. So let's try that out. So
over here, I will launch one desktop with one CPU and eight gigabytes of memory. It should take
take up like a few seconds to launch.
While we're waiting for that,
I want to briefly mention that essentially
the layout of the cluster is such that
the resources are somewhat shared.
The login node, for example, has essentially,
it shares the file system with the compute node.
So anything that you create on the login node,
the compute nodes can see, that's how essentially the data
transfer, it's not really data transfer, it's stored at the
same place. It's just a network file system.
Yes. And over here, you can notice that I'm now like the
terminal that I'm starting here is starting on some PE21. So
it's a computing node. So it's one of the like computers that
we have in the system. And over there, I can start Ovito, which
this kind of like open visualization tool that is often used to simulate various simulations.
So like this molecular dynamic simulations. So over here I will browse to the folder
folder that the simulation was done in, so it was the indent simulation.
And I will visualize the dump file over here.
So you can notice that here we have the visualization.
So it's basically like this kind of like a lattice, 2D lattice of some atoms that don't
move and some atoms that do move and when we play the simulation we can see that we can see the
indentation starting to happen when the push comes to solve and the lattice will move
from the spherical indenter. So this would happen like, I don't know, like you push something into
a metal and that would happen. So this kind of a visualization, so this is just to demonstrate
like a workflow that you might have in a computing cluster. So you do something in the command line
or from some other interface where you submit your job into the queue and it runs on some machine
and once it has run you maybe use open on demand or some other way to visualize the results or
to check the results and what is the result that you want to have.
So this is the kind of like a workflow that you might have in the cluster.
So yeah, so in the simulation, there's a question in the chat.
So they say you cannot see the indenter.
It's basically like some material
with infinite density that pushes to the infinite force
pushes like so that nothing cannot go over here.
So it's some indenter that basically pushes the material
on that side.
OK, but this is like an example of,
like let's say this kind of like a traditional physics
simulation that you might do in a cluster.
We'll talk about how do you do it in more
detail in the coming days.
Another example, I hope we are not running out of time
or going too much over time.
But another example I want to give is for the deep learning people or for the
language processing people. In many cases, you might have a situation that
you want to utilize, let's say, the large language models that are
are like nowadays available everywhere basically.
So you would want to do some,
you want to run some queries to a large language model.
So in this example, what I will use is like
this already written example that we have done,
this large language model example.
And what the example does is that it uses this Lama2 large language model to batch
process multiple queries to a large language model.
So when people are doing query, like many people are using ChatGPT and programs
like that for that, but they are closed models.
So you cannot really know what happens behind the scenes.
And you will just have to send a request to OpenAI and they will give you a response of what was the prompt that you queried.
But if you're doing research into large language models or if you want to use open source alternatives for that, you might need to run it yourself.
But those models are very heavy on the GPU requirements.
like they are big models usually.
So you'd need a system that has those kinds
of resources to do it.
And in our cluster, we have GPUs that are capable
of running some of these large language models.
So in this example, let's go to the batch inference folder.
And what we have here, we have this kind
submission script that is a bit more complicated. But what we have here is that we request
quite a bit of memory, we request a certain number of CPUs, we request a GPU,
and then we use like here in Aalto we have already downloaded certain deep learning models
or pre-existing models. You could download them yourself from, let's say, HuggingFace or somewhere.
But we have already some downloaded models existing. And over here we will use an environment
that I have already pre-created to run this kind of like an inference script.
And this inference script is like a Python script that loads the models and it will
it will take some prompts that we have
and it will run it through the model.
So let's just run this.
So this is the kind of like, yeah.
You have this Python unbuffered in there.
Yes.
Why?
Well, that is so that if we want to look
at the output over here,
it will show it to us immediately.
That's normally not required,
but that is just so that we can quickly see the output.
If we would run this in a production environment,
that wouldn't be necessary because we would be more
interested in getting a lot of questions done.
But over here, for the sake of the demo,
we want to get output as soon as possible,
so that we can see what's happening there.
So now it's running on a GPU node.
Our model is being loaded and the model is being initialized
and it takes a minute to do that.
I would also say that this Python buffer too
is pretty important if you need to debug.
Yes.
Because if you have some statements,
some print statements in and don't have that,
or tail the print statements to directly write out,
you can easily end up with code that you think is running,
or think is not running anymore, but actually ran.
Yeah. So the model run,
it produced the output,
but the output is pretty hard to read from this.
so it also produced the output into like a response file so in order to visualize a bit
better I'm loading this JSON formatter called jq and running this command to open it up in
the editor so we can see what sort of responses it gave. So for example what is the history of
of the Eiffel Tower and then it describes in lots of detail
the history of the Eiffel Tower.
And these kinds of like batch processing is very important
when in our case, we had,
I'm not certain how many prompts we have here,
maybe a hundred, maybe a few hundred,
but like if we want to test out these AI models
with thousands and thousands of different prompts,
It could get pretty expensive if you want to use, let's say, OpenAI's models.
Or maybe you want to test out how different models behave, what sort of output they produce.
Or maybe you want to try different things.
For these, it might be a lot cheaper and a lot easier to do this kind of batch processing in the compute cluster compared to, let's say, using an already existing JATCPT.
But those are also good ways of doing a research, of course.
This is only one way of doing research.
But if you need to process a huge bunch of these queries, yes, this is one way of doing that.
So but these kind of stuff you will be able or hopefully you will be able to do
after this course or you will know how you should get started on working these kinds of examples.
But we like there are many questions already in the in the chat about like many of the concepts
we introduced here. And don't worry, like we'll go through the concepts in like better detail
or in more detail like during the next upcoming two days. We won't like go through them in this
one half an hour session and expect that you would need to like learn everything from this.
This was just a demo. This is just the preview to know what kind of things you might learn.
And really to show the point that what we're learning
the next few days, we're not doing something ourselves,
but we're telling a computer how to do it.
And thus we can tell the computer to do it 10 times
or a hundred times for us automatically.
Okay.
With that being said, it's a break time.
So after the break, we begin,
we do a practice connecting to the cluster.
Let's see you then.
Bye.
you
And welcome back.
So now we are essentially at the next stage and we actually want to connect to our clusters.
The documents or documentation that we have is mainly for Alto but conceptually it's the
same for any other cluster.
are plenty of different ways how you can connect to the clusters and we will talk about two of them.
Essentially we will talk about an SSH connection and we will show a bit of the
on-demand that [name] has already showed in the last session.
So if I scroll down a bit in the materials there's a long list here but some will exist on your
cluster and some will not. All of them exist on Aalto, but they show the two main things, I guess.
We will, for demonstration purposes, assume that you have direct internet access to your cluster.
That means if you are on Aalto, you need to be on the virtual private network because the
Sorry, because the Triton cluster is not directly accessible from the internet except the open
on demand approach.
So if you want to follow and want to type along, you will need to be on the VPN.
the question came up before what's the difference between the login node and the compute nodes.
I think this image shows it quite well. So the login node is the element that's connected to
the net. In this case to the ALTA network on Lumi or other CSC machines it's directly connected to
the internet and this machine is essentially your entry point to the cluster this is the machine
where you submit jobs where you get where you put things uh onto onto the cluster or tell the
cluster okay i want this to be computed um in general why if you want to connect to the cluster
the first thing you have to do is you have to get an account i assume that all of the all of
of you have done that for your respective clusters.
And we will first go through the SSH connection,
and [name] will demonstrate that.
OK, so just to be sure, I'll just say again.
So I'm connected to the, I mean, the Alta network through the VPN.
[name]'s, there's notes that [name]'s voice is much louder.
Okay, well, the only easy way I can access that is from here, so just a moment.
Okay, does that change the volume?
[name], can you say something? Does it change it?
I hope it changed our list.
Okay, well.
I guess we can, we should move on. Yeah, okay, sounds good.
Okay, so I have a terminal open here and yeah, I am on the Alta network.
work. That's important. So what do I do? I will use a standard method. I have some setup
here that would make it  I could type a significantly shorter command, but I will
try to stick to whatever, something that works on whatever system you're on.
So the command is ssh.
Actually before I do that, why don't I show where I am right now.
So I can type the command hostname.
That is the name of my laptop.
That's another laptop.
have usually a name that's something like this, starting with an L and with a number.
I can also show my username, and that is, well, that is my username. It's, again, an
ALDA username, so actually you will see the same one on Triton. Maybe it would have been
more interesting to see it change, but, well, if you're going from an ALDA machine, you
always have the same username.
Okay. So I am on this machine and now I will type the command.
So username, add,
and then the name of the machine.
So that's triton.alto.fi.
The important bit here is it's
the username that you have on the system that you want to connect.
Yes.
And you seemingly already have set up SSH keys.
Yes, that is true.
If you, I'm on the VP,
right, it didn't ask for a password, correct, yes.
So should we demonstrate again
what it looks like if you haven't set it up?
There's not a big change.
The main difference is that you will be asked
for your password on the machine.
And there are actually systems like Lumi
where you have to have a sage keys being set up.
Otherwise you can't.
So I think the biggest difference,
I think that people will see,
well, there is that it will ask for a password.
It will, if it's the first time connecting
to a new server, so a new machine,
it will also ask you, it will print this key
That's essentially a random string of characters and it will ask you if that is the correct
one.
So if you're connecting to something for the first time, it's pretty much safe to just
type in yes.
You can check it somewhere.
You can check that it's correct.
Yeah.
I will put that into the document, at least for Triton.
So, I will go to the shared document.
For essentially any HPC service,
there will be a page where the SH key fingerprints
are being listed.
And you can check whether what's being shown to you
will be, or is the same as what's listed on there.
And if it is, then you are connecting to the correct.
Yeah, so this, having this key on the system
essentially proves that it is the right machine.
Nobody's trying to fake Triton.
You are actually in the actual correct Triton machine.
The main thing though is,
because when you're connecting for the first time,
it will just send it to you
and your machine has nothing to compare it to.
So it will ask you to accept it.
From then on, if it ever changes,
your machine will either just refuse to connect,
or it will at least ask you to check what's going on.
And it refuses the connection and tells you,
yeah, you can remove the old key there.
But that's the point where checking
whether the keys have actually changed makes sense.
Yes.
So if the key changes, it's either something really drastic
has happened, like we have a new version of Triton
something. It's a completely new machine or someone is actually doing an attack and trying
to get you to lock into the wrong system. So if it complains about this, it is a good thing to check
but usually it doesn't. But essentially this is how you connect via SSH. Yes. There's really
not much more to it. Actually, now in the prompt you do have the name of the machine. It's login4.
You do have my username. We can type hostname and see. It's login4.try.alta.fi and
who am I again? It's the same as before unfortunately, but well that is my username on Alta.
Okay, well, are we going to do anything more here?
I guess not much.
We will, of course, be using the machine much more in the next two days.
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay, then for the on-demand, which...
So this is in the browser.
Yeah, this is a way that is quite convenient as well, depending on what you want to do.
So essentially, you go to the page that [name] had shown earlier, which is on-demand.
Yes, so there is a, well, first of all,
there's instructions for connecting with SSH.
And then there is a link to ondemand.triton.aldo.fi.
It's relatively easy to remember or bookmark.
Let's go there.
I didn't actually want to close the materials, so I'll open it back up.
Okay, so this is what the Triton Open On Demand looks like.
I'm already signed in.
I'm already logged in.
It will ask you to log in with your Aldo credentials.
which you have seen many times already.
It's using a standard multi-factor authentication for that.
So, in here you have multiple different things that you can do.
One thing, or the most convenient thing to use is the Triton Shell access,
which is essentially another...
Shell, this will do exactly the same thing as SSH, except in the browser.
browser.
Except in the browser.
So you don't even need to type in any passwords
because it already has your credentials.
So that's kind of convenient if you just
want to throw in a few commands and you haven't set up
the command line in more detail.
And this works from outside Aalto.
But you do need to log in in the browser
with the two-factor authentication.
Yep.
The second thing is something that [name] has already shown.
Essentially, the Triton desktop.
This is for any graphical applications.
It could also be if you have some software that
has a simple graphical installer,
you could essentially just request the session
and run it there and see if it installs
or if it's missing things.
If it installs and it's a graphical tool,
you might encounter some issues running things later on
if you're not running it via Triton desktop,
because the desktop does load a couple of libraries that
are only available on some of the nodes.
Because as mentioned earlier, we want
to keep the nodes themselves as nimble as possible
so that they are not wasting resources
and there are only a limited amount of things now.
So I have access now, so I can click through here.
There are, well, one or two things
that we might want to show.
So if you work with Chrome, Chrome
has the option to share the clipboard with the browser,
which is quite convenient.
If you have a browser that doesn't support that,
you have this thing on the side where you also
have a clipboard.
I'm going to copy the address from here,
so that it should now be on the clipboard.
And indeed, because I am on Chrome,
it is here on the clipboard.
But if it's not, you can paste it in,
and then you have it in a clipboard of this remote system,
this Triton session.
Might be a convenient thing if you, as I said, want to install some software and have a license
key or something like that, you can essentially copy-paste that via this method.
Otherwise, if you're used to the Linux desktop environments, this is very familiar.
And in general, it's of course very similar to any desktop environment.
I can also open a terminal from here or run any other software.
Of course, running a terminal from here is not necessarily the easiest way of accessing
a terminal in Triton.
Now I'm actually on a compute node, which is an interesting difference to the previous
one.
Yeah.
So, this is not the login node.
We can do more stuff here.
You are essentially only restricted by the amount of resources that you have requested
when you were requesting this session.
And there's one third thing that I think is worth mentioning on this on-demand, and that's
a relatively easy way to transfer files.
So we go out of the desktop.
I don't know if logging out is very important.
Can I go and delete it?
You can go and delete it from here as well.
Yeah.
If on demand, you go to this files thing.
Yes.
[name] has access to a couple of projects, obviously.
Normally, you only have your home directory,
your work directory, and potentially additional projects
that you are a member of.
And that is a relatively convenient method to at least upload smaller files and smaller things.
If we are getting into the gigabyte range, I would personally recommend to use the command
line and things like rsync or similar. But for smaller files, using this file browsing
utility for uploading and downloading is absolutely fine.
So, that's kind of the two approaches that you can, or the approaches that you can use.
On the command line, you have everything that you have on a command line.
On OOD, you are somewhat restricted with the connection to your machine by what things
can be transferred.
And, for example, on the Triton desktop, there's no copy-paste of files.
Right.
You cannot very easily move a file between the whatever laptop you're working on and Triton
from there. But you can go through the files menu here and just upload it there and it will
show up on the Triton desktop in the folder that you placed it in.
So there are also several applications that are pre-installed here.
So, Jupyter, RStudio, Paraview, you know if you want to use them.
And Speech-to-Text, for example, is for translating, well, spoken word into text.
So that might be very useful for you.
That's purely auto.
So yeah, so different clusters will have different ways of accessing, but many of them do have
some sort of way, this online system, something very similar to Open On Demand.
Let's see, other questions.
So the point of the rest of this session is to get connected.
And if you have questions, problems, feel free to ask.
There is also the help Zoom session.
If you are signed up, you should have received a link.
There's one question that's already mainly answered, but what if you forget to close
the desktop?
What I would like to add to the answer that's in the HackMD is,
you are essentially built for your time,
but not in the sense that you're paying money for it.
You're paying in priority, i.e.,
how fast you get resources if the resources are in high demand.
If you leave something running while it could be closed,
you might have to wait longer for resources in the future.
So there is this in jobs,
you have this active jobs.
I don't have any active jobs,
but that's one way to find what you have running.
Actually, how do I get to the view where I had all of my old jobs as well?
Well I mean there was a big red button to delete the job. I mean that will only delete it from the
list but if you see a running job there, there will be a button. I think it's a big red button
to close that job. So if you close a tab and your desktop is still running, you can always go and
close the job from there. I think you can always do it. You can also find it in here if it's still
running. And you can close it. Anything else?
Okay, it's the big picture. Okay, so our goal is, so there's lots of stuff that
can happen here, and you saw a lot of demos. For tomorrow, what do people need
know how to do. Well, the main thing is to connect to the cluster in some way. So, find a way to get
a terminal running on Triton or on your local cluster. So, either SSH into it or find a way
accessing it through a browser either on-demand or similar and open a terminal from there.
So the main thing probably would be though to use SSH to access it and there's instructions
here for different operating systems that may be slightly different, a few options for
Windows, but Windows nowadays has just SSH built in to the command line interface, so it's actually
pretty much the same as on Linux and on macOS. So yeah, at least as far as I know, the main thing is
to get access to the cluster, get a terminal running on the cluster, and it's nice if
you can check out what other features your cluster has and try them out. So if you're on Triton,
try OpenOnDemand, see what you like there and how you like to use it. Yeah. Okay. Yeah. And
you don't need this after this break, but you need it by tomorrow. So there's plenty of time to
keep figuring stuff out and to ask for support tomorrow morning and all that.
And so do keep asking stuff in the notes, and we will take a break now until the next hour, so 3 o'clock finish time or 35 minutes away from now.
You might come back a bit early, but if you can log in, go take a break and come back. Don't sit here waiting for us.
Okay.
If that's all, I'll talk to you later.
Bye.
you