CodeRefinery.org
you
Just say one two three.
test we started. Sorry, I didn't give the countdown. Hi. So, we're here. I guess the
first order of business is adding some icebreakers here.
Yeah, let's do that.
We'll add the audio test.
Me then [name].
One.
Two.
Three.
Four.
Okay. Five.
Six.
I was listening to the audio and it was pretty confusing to hear.
Which number should I say?
Yeah.
Okay.
There's some icebreakers.
Yeah.
So, what can we...
So, one question I would have for our audience is that, have you used an HPC system before?
Like a computational cluster?
Yeah.
And let's say we have questions of never, occasionally, and then.
one and something completely fun.
I always remember this question,
what was your favorite fruit that got some of
the best response from anything.
What's your favorite ice cream flavor?
In honor of the weather the last few days.
That's a good question.
I would say maybe like an old-timey strawberry
with some jam inside of it or something like that.
That's pretty good.
Yeah.
What's yours?
Oh, that's a good question.
There's this, um, maito flavor from Suomen Jäätelötehdäs, that's pretty good.
Yeah.
So for the, how long have you used computers?
One of my interesting questions there, like, how did you get started and what did it mean
to you?
Like when I was growing up there were computers in our home and I mean I guess my parents had
one of course this was in the 90s or something like that so it wasn't really a powerful commonly
used thing but I didn't really like have a feeling that this is a thing that I could learn about and
know about until maybe my last year of high school, something like that, and then I got
one that I could mess with just for myself.
And then I could start, you know, breaking things.
And then when you break stuff, you really understand it.
So I wonder, how did this progression go for other people?
Like for you, [name], what was your starting point of?
Yeah, I would say that the starting point was when my father bought a secondhand computer from his work
that his coworker had preloaded with some shareware games or something like that, like DOS games.
It was a Windows 95 computer, but yeah, I would say that trying to even get those to work
was an effort in and of itself, like old shareware games. So yeah, that was basically like
you immediately start to do problem solving because you want to play the games and the
games don't work. So yeah, yeah, okay. So basically games seems to be the way that people start
with computers. Do we need some HPC games that people can play and get familiar with things and
so on? Like I would say that why people start, like I tried my, I learned my parents like 486
as well with MS-DOS, but what can I do with that? I can use a matrix printer and write some text,
but if I'm like six years old or something, what does a six-year-old need a matrix printer for?
The games are much more suitable, I would say, because if you only have a productivity computer,
it's not that fun. Eventually, of course, the productivity can get fun as well.
So, yeah.
Hopefully.
Yeah.
Hmm.
Does anyone want to hear what happened yesterday with the stream going down?
And some more stories behind that.
Go right ahead.
Uh, yeah, so in my home a few weeks ago, I got these messages saying electricity meters
will be replaced in your building sometime in the next few weeks, but you'll get a text
message a day or two before that happens, so you have some warning.
So I worried, ah, okay, this is going to be bad, because it's right during the kickstart
course time. But I haven't gotten a message about it yet, so, you know, I've just ignored it.
But, of course, whenever they're replacing the meter of the common
telco equipment in the building, I guess I wouldn't get notified. So my hypothesis is that
yesterday they did that. So I lost my connection for 15 minutes or so. Incidentally, like they
said yesterday, it was right at the same time before the same talk that was interrupted by
the Fastly CDN breaking several years ago. So then I... So at first I was hoping it would
come back soon. It happened towards the beginning of this long break. But then
When it was getting closer and closer to time, I switched my laptop tether to my mobile device,
which incidentally my mobile operator had some problems with their network, their mobile
network earlier in the day.
And luckily they weren't right at the same time because then I would have had zero connection
to the outside world at all.
That would be pretty funny.
And all of the fancy production tricks that you might see during the streams, [name]
is basically the person behind all of these.
So we would have been in a creek without a paddle if [name]'s internet didn't come
back.
Yeah.
And then you saw me dynamically adjusting stuff trying to recover.
So that was kind of fun.
But it did show me that it actually wasn't that hard.
My laptop could handle it with the outside screen, and if I just had a little bit more
preparation then it would have been much easier.
The hardest part is that I couldn't copy stuff by SSH from my desktop to my laptop
because there was no network and I didn't really know what to do about that problem.
Anyway, so it's almost time. Let's review what we've got here for our
answers. So most people haven't used clusters that much.
Please do go and open up the notes and answer these, so this is really important for us to see the interaction and know how many people are around.
Yeah, and also usually we have so many people watching this, or hopefully we have a lot
of people watching this.
But when we have a lot of people watching, if you encounter something during the talks
that was rushed too fast or something like that, that's something that was unclear for
you.
notes is the best way to make us notice that, and then we can elaborate on the answers that
we're giving.
So because today, [name] will talk a bit more about what we're going to be going through
today, but there's going to be this kind of like, we're building on a foundation type
of a thing where we build upon the previous things.
If something gets lost in translation or something, then it's basically like the foundation
is cracked. It's good to fix immediately so that we know how to build upon the information that we
have given. Use the notes a lot. Let us know about any questions that you have. Ask a lot
of questions that there's other people answering as well, because it really, really helps us and
it helps you. Yeah. Okay, so let's get started. I will switch to my screen here, I hope. Yes.
So as usual, we have our schedule. It should say everything we're doing.
If we go down to day two, we begin with about clusters and your work.
I will also quickly mention that public service announcement, remember to put the stream to
maximum resolution if it's not already there, so that any text will appear as crisp as possible.
But we will mostly talk and look at pretty pictures, but there's text sometimes as well.
Okay, so yesterday we talked a lot about basic concepts of scientific computing, like where
you can store your data, who we are, how to ask for help, things like that.
Now we get to the real stuff.
The general plan is that today we go into basics.
So what is a cluster, what are resources, how to request them, and so on.
We get to some of the interesting parallel and GPU stuff tomorrow.
But because a cluster is easy to use if you're familiar with the command line Linux, things
like that, and hard if not, we're going nice and slow today in order to make sure that
everyone can keep up and we have this good solid background.
So yeah, what's a cluster?
Yeah, so if we think about the cluster, it's basically like a bunch of computers in a trench
coat.
But it's also a bit more than that.
So a cluster is basically a big system that has many features in it.
So what we usually have in the cluster is that we first off have a lot of computers
there that are meant for computing. So in this diagram that you can see we have the CPU nodes
like that is the main thing of the cluster really. We have a lot of hardware there that can be used
for computing. There's also specialized hardware like the GPU nodes that have GPU cards
that are used for GPU computing. And then usually a cluster has a file system as well
So it's own file system, which is connected to these nodes in some fast lane, so that you can
have big data flowing into the CPU nodes and the GPU nodes. And then, yeah.
So how big is our cluster, just as a reference? So the one at Aalto University.
So our is like a medium size, maybe. Medium, small. Medium in Finland, small in international scale.
But we have a lot smaller clusters. Some other universities might have a smaller cluster.
And for example, the CSC supercomputers, they are a lot bigger. But in our case, it's,
Well, I don't know, actually remember the numbers, like a few hundred nodes?
Yeah, I think it's like the order of 300-ish.
Yeah, and maybe a few hundred GPUs.
Yeah, a few hundred GPUs, 10,000 processors roughly, last I remembered.
Yeah.
But you can already hear from what I'm describing here that the cluster,
what is important about the cluster is not necessarily how much there is on the backend
or something, it's how you're going to be using it. And you're going to be using it through this
login systems, like login node or the on-demand. And then we will talk about how you get access to
the resources later on. But for me, at least personally, it's more of like, I know that
there's just resources there, I just need to be able to use them. But it doesn't really matter
where they come from. They are there on the background and there is a way of
getting those resources. And we'll talk about that soon. But basically, there is just a bunch
of computers and those computers are connected to each other with a fast network and there's a
a storage space for your data and then you can use those computers using certain things
that we'll be talking about.
So about our own cluster at Aalto University.
It was completely upgraded and reinstalled, well, a month ago.
And everything has changed.
So many of the things you might read might be out of date.
trying to update them or add warnings there, but just be aware that things are different now.
And we'll talk more about this later. The final thing on this page is asking for help.
So it is really hard to go and do everything alone, especially when you're starting.
So do read about getting help and come to your local support early if you need it.
don't struggle forever. And with that I think we can go on from this page.
Yes. Okay. So next up in the schedule is Slurm, the queuing system.
So Slurm is the drink from Futurama, and it's also the simple Linux utility for resource
management. I don't even know. I think nowadays it's just a word. I don't think it's an acronym
anymore, but that's probably the original one. That was the original one. Yeah. So, we already
talked about what's a cluster. Is there anything else to add here? Yeah. So, we mentioned the
that there is a cluster and there's lots of resources.
And I also already hinted that there's
a way of getting access to those resources, and that is Slurm.
So we have this nice analog for this, what the Slurm is.
And it's this kind of like, the analog
is this HPC diner or HPC restaurant.
Do you want to, [name], explain the analog?
Oh, yeah, that's a good metaphor.
So let's say you're going to a restaurant. Do you go to a restaurant to sit at the stove and
cooking yourself? Or do you go at the restaurant for someone else to cook for you? Well, for
someone else to cook for you. That's the first thing. But when you arrive there, so that way
you can do other things while someone is cooking for you. But when you arrive there, do you
immediately go and pick any table and sit down? Or is there usually a sign when it's
busy that says, please wait to be seated? And what does this person do? You have to
tell them how many people you are. Usually you don't tell them how long you'll be eating,
but this would be a relevant piece of information if there's another reservation there. And
And this host that's there looks at everyone that's in the queue and then tries to assign
them to tables so that the most possible number of people can eat at once.
So for example, they won't have two people sit at a table for four people if there's
space for just two.
They won't go, like they'll try to save some big tables for big parties that might come
in later, especially if they have a reservation.
And this is basically what Slurm is doing.
So there's a bunch of people waiting and want to run more jobs than there's time.
So the host has the queue, they order the queue in priority somehow, and they try to
give something to all the resources in a way that will use them as optimally as possible.
Do you think of this metaphor?
Yes, I think that is very well put.
So in our case, the Slurm, what it considers
when you look at what sort of tables are you booking
and that sort of stuff, it also takes
into account stuff like your priority
or how much you have visited there before.
Basically, let's say the restaurant is very popular and they try to make certain that as many people
have an opportunity to eat at the restaurant. They try to organize it so that it's fair for
everybody. If somebody goes there every day and takes a table, they try to book other people as
well so that as many as possible have the opportunity to go there. So the queue manager
takes into account various things about what sort of things you require, so what sort of
things you need. And then it can manage this large, large restaurant from a simple lobby.
Yeah. So I guess you have to tell the host what you want if you come in and you say,
I'd like a table and they ask you, okay, how many people are you? And you're like, I don't know.
Then they'll look at you and wonder what's wrong with this person.
Yeah. But the restaurant manager is also very understanding that if you want to book a table
for four when there's only two people eating, they will book it, but you're limited to basically then
only tables of four. They will try to accommodate every kind of a guest, but at the same time,
by, well, the question what you don't need, you might be limited to some place. If we go back
into, from this analog, partly back to the actual reality of what is happening, if you, [name],
want to show the picture of the cluster. Yeah, if you show the picture of the cluster. So what
happens in the cluster is that you go into the login node with an SSH or you take the on-demand
connection to login node or VS Code connection. You are there and that is basically the lobby
of the restaurant. When you are there, you're in the lobby and now you have the sign in front of
you that, okay, wait for seating. And who is the host? That is the SLURM, like the queue manager.
And when you ask the queue manager that, hey, I would want to have these sort of resources for
this sort of time, aka I would want to have this table with these kind of seatings for this amount
of time, then the queue manager will process your request and it will, once the table is free,
it will seat you there. So in the case of a cluster, it will find you a computer that has
those resources and it will put you into that computer and then it will run your code in that
computer. So basically, we go back to the real world, what is happening, that is what's happening
in the background. Yeah. So I guess on the cluster, we're not asking for seats for people,
But what are we asking for? And that's why we come to here, the resources Slurm manages.
Yeah, so the most important or the simplest resources that Slurm considers are the amount
of processors you want. Like yesterday, there was talk in notes that do I really need to know
about these processors and do I need to really know about how the CPUs are. In a sense, you need.
There's, I will, we will show like some shorthands of how you can like estimate these things
soon, but you need to know a bit about your program, like you need to know a bit about the
like the requirements of your program, that how many processors it needs, how much memory it needs
and how much time it needs. So that Slurm can fill you a slot in one of the computers
so that your code can then run there. Of course, basically, you can think of Slurm as trying to
solve like a Tetris puzzle constantly, and you're just giving it different kinds of blocks all the
time. If you don't like the table analogy, another analogy with that. And Slurm tries to get the full
Tetris of filling the computers fully and it will consider these kinds of like slots or blocks
when it's calculating the jobs. Yeah, actually you have a good picture of this slot concept.
Should we show that? If you have it right away then sure why not. So this how big is my program
page. Yeah. So this is written last year-ish. Yeah. And yeah, so there's these good pictures.
So a typical laptop computer, what's it like? Yeah, a typical laptop, like what you might
have, these might be a bit old, maybe they're bigger now, like since last year, but it's
It's about four CPUs and 16 gigabytes of RAM, and a workstation might be eight CPUs and
maybe 32 gigabytes of RAM, and a typical computational server or compute node, compute node is another
way that we just say it's a server, it's about maybe 32 CPUs.
Nowadays, it can be up to 128 or 256 CPUs and up to terabytes of RAM or something.
But that's about the ballpark, but that's an estimate.
So you can say that one server is about four desktop computers or eight laptops.
So when you're trying to decide what the resources are
that your program needs, it's usually a good idea
to use this as sort of a natural measuring stick.
That's like, OK, let's just say that.
So if you have no idea what to request at all,
but you know it works on your laptop,
you could start with roughly this amount
and then adjust up or down.
Yes.
And the simplest option is that if you run the program on your computer,
if it runs on your computer, you can just check your task manager.
Like there's instructions below how you could do it, but basically this is the kind of like
natural number or like natural unit that you can use to measure your codes.
That's a good starting point.
So first ask what your laptop provides and then see how it works.
That's usually a good starting point.
So what are the resources we'll be requesting in our jobs?
What resources does it allocate?
So yeah, like we mentioned, there's the CPUs, then the memory, and then the time.
We'll be talking about these throughout, like, we'll first start in the first examples that
we are going to be running quite shortly, and that you can run as well.
We'll be mainly focusing on time and memory, because those are something that always need
to be basically set.
And then the processor count, when we get to the parallel stuff tomorrow, we'll talk
a lot more about the processor count.
For now, let's just focus on one CPU jobs, but we can do more on that.
There's also, of course, special hardware like GPUs.
You might need a machine with a specific hardware, so you might need a GPU.
There's also a possibility that if you want to use a certain kind of a CPU,
like our cluster, it has multiple generations of CPUs.
whenever we buy more machines, we usually don't throw the old ones away. We try to be ecological
in a sense like that. So, we use them until they are no longer usable or useful anymore.
So, you might want to limit yourself to a certain architecture or something.
And in those cases, you can do the limiting. But those are more advanced stuff and we don't
necessarily need to focus on that.
So maybe, this wasn't exactly asked in the notes, but
I questioned, so CPUs and cores and processors, do these all mean the
same thing?
Well, basically yes, like CPU can have multiple,
or CPUs usually have multiple cores, so the
actual like physical CPU chip. It usually has multiple cores, but they can be also said to be
like CPUs in many cases. So they appear as like separate GPUs in the operating system.
So they are usually referred to as cores. So practically speaking, it's the same thing.
Yeah, it's like from the user perspective, it's the same thing. And that is, yeah.
And then second, there's a good question. The new Mac processors, M1 and so on,
seem to have a lot of VRAM, and also a different architecture, and I think more
cores than usual. How does this play into this, if it usually works on my laptop?
Yeah, so what [name] said, the Mac architecture is different, so it's an ARM-based processor.
most of the computing clusters. Well, there are some ARM-based computing clusters in, I think
Amazon has some and that sort of stuff, but ours are like the x86, you might have heard that
architecture. So they are using that architecture. So they have a different kind of CPU style.
still. So they work in a bit different way. And like the VRAM stuff, like Mac has this
unified memory architecture that is like a bit different than this kind of like x86.
So it's a bit more complicated. But usually that means that's just like, yeah, you cannot
run the exact same program because you need two different CPU architecture, but usually
can get it working in both systems without any hassle. And I guess understanding the resources
your program needs actually is a big part of running on the cluster somehow. Like on your
own computer you just do it and it either works or it doesn't. But on the cluster
you have to really think about this. I will also mention that when we are going through
the examples here. And when you're starting on your work, it's a good idea to request more
than less. And we will show you various tools that Slurm provides that you can then monitor
what the code actually used. And based on that output, you can try to determine whether your
code ran correctly. But as a first step, I would request more than less and then see if I actually
managed to use all of that. So if you don't know how many people are coming to your birthday party
or something, it's better to book a table that is big enough for the biggest group that you expect
instead of maybe just book a small table and then have a problem. Important to realize we're not
running things just once usually, so it's better to request more and then look and see what it uses
And then for all the future ones, you can adjust and we'll actually talk about monitoring later today
So we don't need to go into details, but but there's this is enough theory. Let's go to actual like let's do something
So should we move on to the next lesson?
Yes to interactive jobs
So, okay. So do you want to throw the screen to my screen?
Sure. Are you ready for it? Yeah, okay
There is your screen.
Yes. So before we start looking at the lessons,
let's check this copy of code to the cluster section.
We will do one thing here.
So the upcoming examples,
we'll use these HPC examples repository that we have created.
So, if you want to follow along with the examples, you should clone this repository as well.
So, we'll talk about when there's time to, like, when do you want to write yourself and
when do we, when there's type along and when there's not.
But if you want to do the same commands that we do, just be mindful that you need to get
this repository.
I will do this in my terminal that I have enabled here and now I have the repository.
So I'm now in the folder of the repository.
I just made a quick poll to see how many people have gone through the cluster shell tutorial
here.
Yeah.
So, but that's quite simple.
a few commands to do if you want to follow that. But let's go to start with the interactive jobs.
And [name], what do we mean with interactive jobs?
Yeah, so on the cluster, there's two main types of jobs you can run. So let's say you go to a
restaurant. You can go, you can tell the host, I would like to have this kind of table. And you can
sit there waiting in the queue, or you can go walk around, do something else, and come
back when your table's ready.
So this isn't actually perfect because the better metaphor would be coming back once
your food is already eaten, which doesn't make sense in that metaphor, but it's the
general idea here.
So with interactive jobs, we say we'd like these resources, and you wait until they're
there and then you can do something yourself.
So it requires your time and mental effort.
What we'll do next is called batch jobs, where we say we'd like to do this, and then it's
submitted and then you come back when it's all done.
So we start with interactive jobs because it's easy to understand, it's easy to see
what happens, and then we can get familiar with making these different resource requests
and so on.
Oh, OK.
Yeah.
Was that a good explanation?
OK.
So we'll actually do it.
Yeah, let's do it.
So let's look at the following command here.
I will make this a bit smaller.
So OK, so where are we now?
So you can try to follow along and type with us also.
Also, we will give you time.
We're going to go through some things,
you'll have a nice long exercise break where you can try yourself. So, if you can't follow
as we're typing now, don't worry. There's time later. And about the setup here, on that
window here, I will be typing some commands and [name] will explain them. And on the bottom here,
you can see the history of the commands. Yeah. And so, we assume that you already can connect
to the cluster by SSH or on-demand or something and get a terminal. This is what we demonstrated
yesterday and should have been the homework for today. If you can't already get a terminal that
looks like this and type commands, then you're a bit behind and then that's okay.
You can watch what we're doing and try to catch up later during the break.
So, [name] is there. He has cloned the HPC examples repository using the git version
control system. Which is, by the way, a good way of transferring code to the cluster in
general. And then has changed into the directory. And then is running Python3 slurm/pi.py
1000. So what does this program do? So this program does like this kind of like a
like this is like a common example in like if you do Monte Carlo simulations like this
example where we estimate pi by throwing dart at a dartboard and because dartboard is a circle
and if we take random numbers from zero to one, like either square, we can basically estimate
the pi by the ratio of how many darts hit the dartboard. So this is like a small example code
that just does something. And we use it for many examples. So where did this code now run, [name]?
Well, we haven't... I don't see anything that looks like it's requesting resources, so this must have just run on the login node, I guess.
Like, we didn't give any instructions to the host saying what we wanted.
So let's... should we do the interactive request then?
Yeah, so let's request from Slurm some resources. So srun is the program to use for it.
it. The memory option says we need 100 megabytes of memory, which by the way is very small.
We need 10 minutes of time, which is way too much. And then we give all the normal options
we would give on the command line. So the program to run, which is Python, the program,
which is Py, and 10,000 iterations. So what do I see here? It says srun,
Slurm job submit automatically setting partitions is this in the background telling it
where it's running somehow yeah so on the on our cluster it might be different in your cluster
but on our cluster like the different kinds of hardware that we have is separating the
entity set different partitions because like if somebody wants to run on a specific hardware
they might want to run only on a specific partition.
But if the user doesn't specify what hardware they want to use,
there's this automatic script that
basically use a sensible default.
In your cluster, if you're in a different cluster,
you might need to specify this dash-dash partition flag like this.
In some sites, you might also
need to specify an account that you want to use.
So there might be different projects or something
that you want to specify that, OK, use
this account for the billing of job, basically.
We'll talk about the billing in a second.
But in our cluster, these are set basically automatically,
so you don't necessarily need to do them.
But let's say you run it on a CSC machine,
you might need to set this.
Yeah.
But what happened afterwards?
So then we see srun job id, thus queued and waiting for resources, job allocated resources,
calculating pi, so that's the standard output. So yeah, basically it's telling us it
got the resources and then it ran, and I guess it ran on some other computer somewhere.
Yes. While it was running, we could have tried to see what was happening in the queue, like
how it was doing in the queue. You can either use this squeue command or this slurm q to do it.
Because it's so fast to go through the queue, it's very hard to capture this for this specific
program, but if you have a program in the queue, you can use this to check the queue status. We'll
talk about this more in the monitoring part, but yes, you can do this. Okay. Maybe we can go on
and let people explore this more themselves. Yeah. To verify, this is a good example that
that if we just run a command like hostname,
which tells us which host we are in,
we can show that if we run just hostname,
we see that we are actually in the login for.
Because in the output,
we didn't necessarily see that we
were in a different place where we were running.
But if we run srun hostname,
now it just uses some default values for time and memory.
But usually we don't want to use the defaults because they are not set by us, but in this
case, let's just run it.
It's running, waiting for resources, and it has been allocated some compute node.
So we know that, okay, this command actually run in some different system.
There's a request in the notes.
Can we show an srun with huge resource request and show it waiting in the queue?
Yes.
So, what is big?
Can we say 200 gigabytes of memory?
Yeah.
And then...
Yeah, well, it still runs quite quickly because, like, yeah, there's like...
It's kind of arranged for that.
But let's say we ask for 200 terabytes of memory.
Now it says that there's no such node.
We don't have a computer that has 200 gigabytes of memory.
So, yeah.
Could we request 200 gigabytes of memory, 50 processors, and, say, one day of time?
Is that huge?
Well, let's not do the processors.
Let's just say, like, four days of time.
So, this is the day syntax.
And it still ran immediately.
There seems to be like a node...
Okay, let's put the CPU.
Okay, now it's...
Okay, it's still...
So, this is...
Okay, but there's a free resource for you to take.
So, part of the reason why it's running so fast is that
[name] hasn't run much lately.
And the less you run, the higher your priority is.
So basically, [name] hops to the front of the queue and gets anything immediately.
And this is also one of the situations that can happen if you are dealing with interactive jobs.
If we think about the restaurant metaphor, if we go to an empty restaurant,
we can basically choose which table we want to eat anyway, right?
We can pick the biggest table, it doesn't really matter if the restaurant is empty.
If there is enough free space, then the queue manager can basically fill our strange requests.
But if the place is full, it might be that we suddenly need to wait a lot.
So let's show the interactive shell and the sinteractive command quickly.
So what we did here is we ran a command line program on a node.
But we can also request it to run just a normal shell,
and then we see things.
So here we're making the standard resource request.
This time we've told it the interactive partition.
And we get this.
So now we see it.
This is because of the recording thing.
Don't worry about that.
Like recording the history.
Yeah.
But we see here, if you read this last line,
it looks different.
It says [name] username and then PE22.
And PE22 is the name of one of these compute nodes
that's available.
So now [name] has waited once and can run things multiple times,
like this hostname command and other things.
Yeah.
Yeah, OK.
If I exit them, yeah.
I don't know why that history doesn't work.
I have an idea, but let's worry about it later.
Okay. Yeah. Okay.
So, yeah.
So, yeah, this is, like, if you want to run multiple commands,
like, you can use this if you want to temporarily get, like,
let's say you want to do, like, a big installation or something,
and the login node doesn't have the resources to do that.
like there was a question there in the notes about like if you're doing like a
big build on your laptop like it might require lots of resources like that might happen also
in the cluster you so you might want to get like temporarily lots of resources but do note that
these because these are interactive resources when you're not using them they're basically
still reserved for you, so you're reserving resources. So if you're not using them,
it's a good idea to usually give them away so that other people can use them instead.
And this other command, sinteractive, is it even still installed? Did we
install it on the new cluster? Yeah, it's installed.
Okay. So this is pretty similar to the srun one, but it sets some other defaults
and can allow graphical programs to run. But now we would recommend doing graphical things with
open on demand, so wouldn't really recommend this, I guess.
Yeah, but if you have a need to do it, then yeah. Yes. Okay. So the error is
probably because of the recording script that I'm using. Yeah. Okay.
So should we go on and we need to talk about checking the jobs so we can see the history.
I'll quickly mention that if you want to see what jobs we had previously run, you can use
the slurm history command.
I will make the terminal a bit smaller so that I can see it.
And it will show me the history of all of the jobs
that I have previously run, for example, the interactive jobs
and that sort of stuff.
We'll talk about this more about when
we talk about monitoring jobs, but it
is possible to see the history.
So but let's scroll down.
Yeah, should we?
We've got these exercises here.
So we'll give you some time to explore this yourself
and ask questions.
There are how many different things you can try?
I count five of them.
And you can also try the other things
we've demonstrated above here.
Give it a try.
See how it adapts to your own clusters.
Read some more things.
Yeah.
I will switch to the notes here.
And I see that there's many different questions here, and they've been being answered. So do
keep asking. Is there anything we want to talk about now? I think most people can probably...
The Jupyter Terminal does work, yes.
MATLAB.
Maybe we'll talk about MATLAB a bit later if someone can answer some default.
Yeah, okay, I'd say let's go on to the exercises.
How long should people have?
Should we have maybe 5 to one?
Yeah, maybe 5 to one and then we can do a brief wrap up and then have a break.
Yeah.
Okay.
Sounds good.
See you then.
Yep.
Yep, do keep asking questions and respond with your progress to our poll there.
See you later.
Bye.
you
Yeah, we could then demo.
Also, I will mention that this goes into the next subject that we are going to be talking
about, there's also a question of, can you attach to already existing job? And it goes to,
what we're next going to be talking about is these non-interactive jobs.
So in many cases, the interactive is fine if you are actually watching. My personal
approach is that if I'm not watching the actual screen, I'm not using interactive jobs.
Like, if I'm not actually using, like, humanly watching it, I'm not using interactive talks
because why?
I'm not interacting with it.
I realized I forgot to turn on my audio when coming back on stream.
But anyway, we're back.
What did I say that was the podcast?
If you wanted us to do a demo of one of the exercises, put a vote to the exercises.
Please vote down here.
What else did I say?
If you, do you need to close jobs when they're completed?
And that is yes.
If you don't close one of the ones that gives you a shell, then the resources will stay
reserved for you.
So there was at least one vote for exercise one.
So we can do a quick demo of that.
So let's do the most simple one over here.
I'm heading to [name]'s screen.
Yes.
In this exercise, we run this memory use script that uses memory and then we
want to see what happens when we increase the memory requirements and with various memory requirements.
So let's try first just running with just srun and no any requirements specified,
any specific requirements. So let's just try running this and see what happens.
So you can see here, yeah maybe I typed it too fast. So I wrote srun and just what I want to run.
So just add the SRUN. That's usually this one handy trick that you can use. Just add the SRUN
if you don't know what happens. And it was trying to use 50 megabytes of memory and it
allocated up to that point. It worked. So let's add an actual memory requirement here.
So I press the up arrow to get the previous command and now I will request 500 megabytes.
And because it's less than the 50, it still worked quite well.
But now let's do the C part where we try to increase the memory limit.
So let's try, we have the 500 over here.
So let's try like 500 over here.
Okay.
Ah.
Yeah.
It's memory killed because it's actually probably using a bit more than the 500.
So let's increase the memory limit a bit and let's see how much it actually used even though
it tried to use 500.
Let's see if 600 works.
Okay.
600 works.
So let's add the sleep parameter there
to check what was the actual memory usage.
We can use Slurm history to check the memory usage.
But we need to, like Slurm captures it only once
every 60 seconds or 30 seconds or something.
So, we need to let it run a bit longer.
Yeah.
Right.
And you notice here that,
let's say I would be running like a long job.
This would be really annoying to watch at the screen
to keep it open, like the terminal open constantly
or the connection open.
So, in the next session, we'll talk about
how you can avoid this kind of like situation
where you have to keep it open while it's running somewhere
in the background.
So if this would last for, let's say, multiple hours,
it would be really annoying to watch at this screen
and let it wait.
OK, there, it's done.
Yeah, I will make it a bit smaller.
Hopefully, you can still see the font.
So you notice here there is some overhead in the code, so it actually used 518 megabytes.
We'll talk about the memory usage and that sort of stuff a bit more later.
I guess this is basically how it goes when you don't know how much memory it uses.
you try a few things and you see what's happened, what happens, and then yeah. Okay, should we go
to a break now? Yeah, I will quickly say that about the interactive stuff, the most important
thing to remember is basically this diagram at the top of the documentation here, that when you're
using srun or sinteractive, you're no longer in the login node, you're suddenly over here.
So you're in the compute node. And that's the most important thing to remember that,
okay, if I ask the queue system to place me somewhere, you end up into a different place.
And that's basically the most important thing to remember.
Yeah. Okay.
Okay. Let's...
Great.
Should we take a 10 minute break until...
10-minute break until 13 past. Okay, great. See you later. Bye.
you
Hello.
So we are back, and I've remembered to set the audio correct.
So were there any more questions while we were waiting?
I will quickly mention there were a few questions about various, like for example, the sinteractive
and the Slurm commands.
So these are like helper scripts that we have created.
They are available in GitHub if you are interested.
You can ask your admins to set them up or you can set them up yourself if you want to.
there's alternatives that they're basically just wrappers for the slurm commands so there's
alternatives provided in the notes if you don't have those at your site yeah okay so off to the
section on serial jobs and I sent it to [name]'s screen yes
Okay, so yeah, a serial or batch job. What does it mean? So I guess I gave the metaphor
that you don't have to sit there and wait for it. So how does that go?
Yeah, so like if you think about like what you are doing with your computer, like usually of
course, there's a lot of coding that you do interactively. You code your code and then you
do some modifications. Maybe you use a notebook interface or something like that, and then you
constantly run each individual cell in the notebook. You might do most of your job like that.
But when it comes to the parts that are actually heavy or computationally, that might take four
hours to run that you might need the HPC resources, like the cluster resources for,
you don't usually want to be there watching at it, right? It's a waste of your time
to basically watch at that. Yeah. And then you can only do one thing at a time.
Yes. Yeah. Yeah. You want to usually offload that to something else. So basically,
So basically, you want to, like what [name] said about the table reservation, you want
to, well, okay, you basically order like takeout.
Like you order that the meal be prepared and once it's prepared, let me know so that I
can fetch it and just like eat the result.
So it's prepared for you on the background, so you don't have to like worry about, you
don't have to wait for it.
Yeah.
And we do this via the batch script.
So can you go over what's the general idea here?
So we tell the cluster what we want.
And we do that by, I guess, this batch script
that we're showing here.
So can you go over what these lines mean?
Yeah, so in the batch script, like we have an example batch script over here that you can look
at and over there we have various strange looking lines but these lines basically tell the queue
manager, the slurm, what it should do for you on the background. So the first line over here,
this line is this so-called shebang line which tells which interpreter, which tool we should
use to interpret the script or which program we should use to run the script. Usually,
commonly it's the shell, so the bash shell or some other terminal so that it would be basically
like, okay, execute these commands. Previously, when we just ran the Python 3, for example,
and then we ran the PI example, then we just called commands from the command line.
So, basically, this would mean that, okay, just use the command line to run these commands.
The next two lines are directives to the queue system.
So when we want the queue to manage this script, we want it to get us the resources what we
want.
And how do we tell it?
We usually give these comments in the script, these Sbatch directives.
And this is like a format that is very like, you need to write it in this format.
So it's not S bash or S batch with a space.
So it's written like this.
Exactly like that.
Yeah.
Because like the Slurm, when it takes this script, it will look for these comments and
if it sees these comments, then it will interpret what comes after the comment as an argument
for the queue manager, basically. Like, okay, I want this time, I want this memory for this job.
And afterwards, you can have whatever your code is after that. Like, whatever commands you want
the code to run, like the queue manager to run. And what happens is that when we call this
SBATCH and then the script that we have written, we call it, we basically say we are in the login
node, we have our terminal or whatever, we have it on the login node. And when we call that command,
the queue manager takes that file and then it will like read the comments that, okay, I will,
I know that this script needs these resources, and it will find you the correct place on
the compute node, in the CPU node, where it can execute that, that has those resources,
and then it will just plow through it.
It will just run the commands.
And it will, like, done it non-interactively.
So once you give the queue manager the script, you don't have to, you can just go to something
else and the queue manager will run it for you somewhere in the background.
There was a good comment in one of the previous notes questions.
If you log out, is all your stuff saved?
So I guess the synchronization here is everything starts as a file and everything comes out
as a file.
So your program, if it writes something,
if it prints something to the screen, where does that go?
Yeah, so if you would run in an interactive session,
for example, the Python code that we previously run,
it just printed it out there.
So it's basically ephemeral.
So it just disappears once you close the terminal,
because it's just output.
But if we run it non-interactively,
then Slurm will gather whatever output your code will write, like whatever text output it will
print, and it will collect that into a file. Of course, in many cases, you would want your code to
let's say read input files in the code and then write maybe some output file.
So basically, what happened during the computation is stored in those files.
But if you want to record the printed output of your code,
it will be recorded by Slurm.
Should we run a simple example on this?
Yeah, sure.
Let's go.
So if we scroll down a bit under your first jobscript,
I guess we can do the full demo.
So the starting point is at the shell, like we've had before.
And we need to make a new file.
So I guess [name] will use the nano editor to open a file and make it, but you can use any editor
you're comfortable with, whether it's VS Code with the remote SSH or through Jupyter or some other
command line thing. So [name]'s opened the file and will paste all the contents in there.
I'll make it a bit bigger so that it doesn't look so...
Okay, so we paste it here and I guess we know what these things mean, time, memory, output
is where it writes the output.
Yeah, and control X to save and yes to save it into a file name if you are using nano.
And then we do sbatch.
So sbatch and run-pi.
And if we push enter, so we see job submit automatically setting partitions, submitted
sbatch job.
So we have a job ID.
If we do slurm history, what do we see?
Or slurm queue, I guess.
Well, it already ran.
Yeah.
We should add some sleep there or something.
Let's do that, actually.
Just for the demo, let's add a bit of a sleep here.
So you can use this command sleep to add, let's say, 10 seconds so that we can capture the output.
So I will submit it again.
but this time I will run slurm q.
You can see it's now running there. Make it a bit smaller so the whole output fits.
Yeah.
And now in the script itself, if we look at the script again over here, we have this sbatch
output.
Right.
Yeah.
Like Slurm has various flags.
There's like a huge reference.
There's one in our page, but there's also the Slurm's own reference.
lots of different parameters you can give it. And this output is basically, if we want to
name the output in a certain way, we can do that.
Yeah, okay. And can we see the output? If we do ls, do we see things here?
Yeah, let's do them.
So we see day2.out, pi.out. Yes, so that's the example. And if we use...
Do we do cat or less?
I guess we can show cat first.
Yeah.
So cat is, first of, the thing that
comes and visits me sometimes.
But also, it's the Unix program that
is short for concatenate.
So it basically writes out what's in the file.
And we see.
There's an error.
Oh, slurm.
Yeah, I'm in the wrong folder.
That's the reason.
Yeah.
So let's move the run-pi to HPC examples.
Now let's try it again.
OK.
So I guess this is a common real life thing.
You make a job, you submit it, and then you
see, oh, there's something wrong.
And you adjust it and submit again.
It happens.
I mean, it's solely iterative.
This is often why we start with interactive jobs,
just to see quickly, does it even run at all?
and then write the commands in there.
Slurm q is a shorthand for slurm queue,
but you can use either one if you use the slurm command.
OK, now we probably have the pi.out.
Yeah, OK.
So we have pi.out, and yeah.
And if you look at the script, that's
exactly what it should do.
Echo hello user, hello [username], right there.
So this line, which might look, if you are not familiar with bash shell scripting might look a
bit complicated, but basically this, we often use this bash or this terminal languages because you
can do a lot of like housekeeping work with the terminal. Like you can move folders around,
you can rename files, you can do whatever stuff in the, like, and you can programmatically
do those. Instead of drag and dropping files in your file browser, you can do it in a systematic,
programmatic way. That's why we often use the terminal and why it's a powerful tool
when you're writing these things. Over here, we always get these parameters called,
or these variables called user and host name
that tell what is our username
and where are we executing this script.
And then we here call a program date
to get the current date.
So that's the output over here.
And you notice that it's not in the script,
it's like these variables,
but they are only filled when the script is run.
So they are filled when we are running it
in the compute node.
So we actually did run it in the compute node.
Yes.
Should we go to , actually, we have a bit of time.
There's a really good question in the notes.
If you take the script and you submit it
with bash the shell instead of sbatch,
it will look like it runs, but it's not taking these resource requests and it's not running
on the other thing. Yeah. We can demonstrate this. So, this is something you shouldn't do. Like,
it's unfortunate that the sbatch and bash sound so similar. Like, it's an unfortunate thing.
But if we, like, Lee, you remember I mentioned about how this is going to be filled when it's
going to be running. Now, if we run it with bash, what we expect to happen, bash is the terminal
or the terminal emulator or the interpreter for the code language that we have written here.
We expect that it heals these according to where we are currently running.
Because we are running it on the login node currently, our current host name
So, if we now run it, you notice that we are on the login node and we have this strange
thing happening where we have job queued and waiting for resources and then job has been
allocated to cases. So what happened is that basically we wrote these commands out. So if
we would have written these commands into the terminal itself, we would get the same output.
So if we run it with bash. So don't run it with bash, that's a different thing.
If we use it with sbatch, we give it to the Slurm manager that runs it only when there's
the correct space and time to run it in the correct computer to run it.
That way, we can make certain that it runs in the correct place.
You might also be wondering, why do we have srun over here?
do we have srun in the script? Why is it there? And the reason for that is that in some cases,
especially if you're using these MPI jobs that are parallel jobs, you might want to call srun
so that the Slurm manager can allocate these jobs correctly with the MPI jobs. But also,
So if you are using this srun, you will get extra information to the history.
So if I look at the Slurm history, when I...
Let's first run it once more so that we can get like that.
We can just...
Yeah.
We run it properly with the sbatch, and if we look at the Slurm history afterwards, let's
Let's see if I did it already finish.
Yes.
We can notice here that the, I'll
have to make it a bit smaller, I guess.
You can also have it run off the edge of your screen.
Yeah.
Yeah, there.
OK, yeah.
We notice here that the last job that we run,
we see these batch, extern, and zero.
So what this batch means is that all the commands that
didn't have srun on top of them, what did they run?
So basically, all of this stuff, how much resources it used,
and then how much resources did the srun call do?
We can get more up-to-date resource users information
for each individual part of our code.
You can do also kinds of fancy stuff for that.
But the srun is optional in the sbatch script.
But if you want to get more like this kind of
gradual resource information, you can use that.
So if you have a script and you're running,
say, three different steps with
different memory and CPU requirements,
you can understand them separately.
And we'll learn more about this in the next lesson about monitoring jobs.
But I think, yeah, what we probably want to do is do more exercises so you can learn how
to write these scripts yourself.
Because this is like the meat and potatoes of the whole thing.
When we go into Parallel Jobs and everything, the power of the cluster comes from the ability
of it doing work for you while you're just doing something else. And for that, you need
to be able to tell it that they are like, do this for me. And how do you do it? You
write these scripts that you execute so that you don't have to like watch what's happening
there. So learning this is a very important skill and very useful. So I highly recommend
and find the exercises.
Yeah.
OK, so should I propose we give a nice long time?
Should we let it go on until after the break
and return at, say, 10 minutes after the hour?
Yeah.
I will also like one thing we forgot to mention actually is that how do you cancel these jobs?
Like once you have submitted a job you can also cancel them. So let's say that I open the pi
the run pi script and I put here sleep
a long time, and it's not going to finish.
And I submit this script here.
I can check the queue, and you notice this job, each job gets its own job ID, so that
the Slurm can manage them.
And once this is running, you can always cancel.
If you notice that the job is not going to finish correctly, or you made a mistake or
something, you can always use scancel and the job ID to cancel the job.
So that way, when you run the scancel, the job will be gone.
It will just kill the job.
So basically, if you look at the quick reference, you can find all the common control and monitoring
things you need.
But yeah, read the page.
There's a little bit more in there.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, yeah, I'd propose exercises until the hour and then break until 10 minutes past
the hour all combined.
what we're doing right now is sort of the most important lesson, I'd say. It combines the shell,
the batch job, the resource requirements. And from here, it should get much smoother.
Yeah. Basically, like I said, what we want to now learn is how can we utilize the resources in the
computing cluster. Like there are lots of resources there and this is the way, like these are the,
this is the language that the queue manager understands. So we want to learn that language
so that we can translate our, whatever we want to run to a language that the queue manager
understands. So that the queue manager can do it for us. Yeah. Okay, great. So see you in
what, like 30 minutes? Okay, I guess that's all. Keep asking the questions and we'll
keep reading and answering. Okay, bye.
you
Hello.
We are back.
So yeah, how was the exercise?
I forgot to add the poll asking how it went.
There are some good questions here,
including a lot which we're asking
about using more resources.
For example, more processors at the same time
or running several things at once.
Yeah, we'll talk about parallel processing tomorrow, so different methods of parallel
processing.
But for now, the focus is on making certain that your workflow is in a way that you can
easily then leave something for the queue system to manage.
Like basically, you can write this kind of stuff
that the queue system does non-interactively,
so you don't have to worry about it.
But we're going to do some demos of Serial 3 and 5.
I'll switch to [name]'s screen here.
Yeah. So, these are pretty helpful examples of showing a couple of interesting...
Like this kind of Gedanken experiment, as Einstein would put it. Thinking experiments would make you
think about, okay, what's really happening in the background? So, in this example,
example, we try to demonstrate basically what happens if you start modifying something that
is already submitted.
Let's look at the run-pi that we have over here.
As per the exercise, let's add sleep 120 there, but I removed this older one at the end, and
we put sleep 120 here, so it will sleep for two minutes.
Maybe we can put it into one minute so that we don't have to wait that long.
And then, after we have submitted it, let's open the script and let's add something to
the Slurm script, so to this run-pi script.
So I'll prepare myself and I will take this into clipboard already.
I'll save the script and I'll submit it.
So let's see.
it and I'll edit it and I'll add here the line modified and I'll save this okay and now we can
use the Slurm queue to check what's happening it's it's now running in the queue so now it's
sleeping for a bit okay so what do we expect to happen [name]? So I guess it depends on if
if Slurm is remembering, if Slurm already read the file and then runs it, or if it just
remembers where the file is. No, actually, no, it's not queuing, it's running. I mean,
I guess if it's running, there's no way our modifications could have any effect because
Python has already opened it.
But also, even if it wouldn't be running, it wouldn't have an effect.
Because like Slurm, when you give it the script, what the Slurm sees is that it sees the script,
it will copy that script into its memory.
You can even later on, if you want, you can view the script for what it keeps in memory.
So basically, once you press Sbatch and the script, Slurm will remember the script and
after that, you can no longer modify that.
You have fired it away.
You have written the letter and you have sent it to the post and it's basically, it's there
going already.
You cannot modify it anymore.
So when we look at the output, the pi.out, we cut and edit, we see that there's no co-modified
line there.
because Slurm already took the script. But if we, yeah, go right ahead.
What would happen if instead of modifying the script itself,
we modified some of the other libraries or files it imported or ran?
Yes, let's do that exactly. So I'll quickly...
So I'll remove this modified line over here.
here. Save the file. Now, let's submit the run.py. Now, it's basically the exercise four.
Let's modify the actual Python script. Let's do that. I'll take this already into the clipboard.
I'll sbatch the run-pi, and now I will quickly edit the slurm/pi.py, and I'll add this over
here.
Okay.
Yeah.
And we can notice that it's now doing the sleep thing over there.
So what do we expect over here now?
Like the Slurm is running.
It has taken the sh script that we have given it, but it will run through it line by line.
And because it's now stuck in the sleep line, it hasn't yet reached the Python line.
But we have now modified the Python line, but the Python isn't something that we gave
to Slurm.
It's something that Slurm will, when it executes the commands, it will find from the disk.
So it will find the file that we have modified.
So usually it's not recommended to modify either the Slurm script or the script that
you are submitting, because you're now changing the state of the system.
You're changing either the script or the code, and now it will give a different error.
So you can see that if I now print it out, it gives me an exception.
Yeah.
Okay.
Not what we expected because of something else, but still.
Yeah.
Okay.
So I guess the point of these exercises is basically, once you submit a job, it's been
recorded and what you do may or may not have an effect on it, but it's better to leave
it alone.
Not modify them at all.
You have to be very careful to understand what you submitted and what you're modifying and how
it will affect things. So, basically, what usually is recommended that you would have,
like, let's say for your experiment, you would have an Sbatch script. And for the corresponding
to the Sbatch script, you would have your code or your parameters or something. We'll talk about
Array jobs tomorrow, if you have a lot of parameters, you can use these fancy things to
do lots of code calls at one time. But yeah, that is usually...
You want to have a script that is... Basically, it shows how you can replicate the results of your
or code. If you want to do a simulation or a run, some compilation or some code run,
you can replicate it by using the Sbatch script and you don't want to mess them up while they're
running.
Okay. So, yeah.
Number five.
Yeah. So, let's look at the third example. So, let's create a Slurm script that runs
this following program that produces some output. So, this ties up neatly to the next section that
we have. So, let's call it monitor_output.sh, and I will quickly write the usual lines.
Yeah. The usual magic words, I guess.
Yeah, once you have written enough of these, these are pretty self. You become familiar with those.
Yes, so what we do here is that every 30 seconds we print date and then we,
sorry for 30 times we print date and then we sleep for 10 seconds. Okay so
this is basically pretending that you're running something and it's periodically
outputting the status. Yes. Okay. So let's submit it and now let's it's probably
morning. Someone warns that you set the sh files to output file. Oh, did I? That's a good catch.
Yeah, that's a good catch. Okay, well then, I'm in trouble. Okay. I'm in danger,
like as Aral would say. So, let's cancel this one and let's do another recap.
So these can happen, this can happen.
Like I said, once you're familiar with these,
you can write them really fast, but you can also
write problems really fast.
Yeah.
OK.
OK, let's try it again.
The repetition makes everything better.
Yeah.
So now monitor_output.out
OK.
Yes.
And then let's go here.
And let's try it again.
Yeah.
Here.
OK.
And it's going.
Yeah.
And let's.
So now, yeah.
Now we can catenate the output.
So monitor output, cut out.
Not the SH.
OK.
Ah, so there's some stuff running.
Yeah.
And yeah, so it's appearing.
Yeah, so this is typical when you're running something.
What we talked earlier, interactivity
and non-interactivity.
In many cases, there's a situation
where do you really need to get the output constantly?
Do you really need to watch it?
Do I really need to watch this every second
of the output. Most likely not. I'm just interested that it runs, it produces reasonable results and
then I can leave it running. If I have a longer simulation or something, I can just leave it
running and I don't have to look at it constantly. But of course, you want to view the output.
So you can either do here, catenate the output. One other option is to use this tail -f and there's
other tools as well, but this tail is like follow the end of the file basically, it says here,
and it keeps it open. So every time a new line appears it automatically. Okay, yeah.
Okay, so if someone submits like a long training job or something, they can check the status this
way. Yeah. I will also mention that for some cases, for example with Python, like in many
cases, the output is buffered. Once you read a certain amount of output, it will flush the buffer
into the file. If your code produces very small amounts of output at the start of the run,
it might seem that nothing is happening because it hasn't yet filled the buffer.
There are various things that you can say to make certain that the buffers are flushed every
now and then, but like there are these certain situations where the output doesn't appear
necessarily immediately. Yeah, I mean I'm actually kind of surprised it does appear so quickly here
and doesn't get buffered. But anyway, should we go on to the next one?
And this is about monitoring, like what we already started to do.
Oh, sorry. I'm just adding the link to the notes. There's a good question here. It's
still about the... Remember there's a warning on some cluster, never use tail-f or something
like that.
Yeah, it might differ on the cluster. It's about whether the file system is like how
it's syncing, like how the syncing is done, like if there is this kind of like a global
lock or not. And it might differ in some clusters. There are then other tools to view the output.
But if your cluster says that don't use those, don't use those, just because I said to use
because, like, buyer beware or something like that.
I mean, you should trust your local admin over me.
So at Aalto, we've invested significant resources
in having a strong and performant file system.
So whenever there is lots of stuff, like, yeah.
So basically, it can handle things like tail-f.
Yeah, but it's probably a technical reason that other sites wouldn't have the file system capable
of doing it. It's probably a technical system regarding the mount and whatever,
but let's not go that far. Yeah. Okay. So monitoring. Sorry for this short distraction.
So we've already did a little bit about monitoring, but what are the main
things we might want to watch and what does it mean?
Yeah, so for the monitoring, we already talked about how can you watch the queue,
how can you monitor, and that's like monitoring basically in a workflow type of monitoring.
You monitor that is your work running and that sort of stuff. You're monitoring your workflow
and is it going through correctly. And that's, of course, the important part that
But did you manage to get your code running and is it running on there?
But then there's the question of, okay, is it running like I expected?
And is it using the resources like I expected?
And for the first part, is it running as I expect it to run?
The best way of monitoring is in your code to have monitoring output.
Basically, in your code, when there is a specific step that it's doing, it's a good idea that
your code prints those outputs.
It's a good idea that your code tells that, hey, I'm doing this part.
Maybe some timing information as well, like, okay, I'm here, time is this, I'm running
this.
Maybe at the start of your code, you might want to have output that, okay, I'm running
at this machine, I'm running here, that the code itself will tell you what it thinks it's doing.
That way, it will make it a lot easier. If you run into a problem, your code crashes or it does
something that you don't expect it to do, it's much easier to pinpoint at what part of the code
the problem occurred, especially if you're running it non-interactively. If you're running it
interactively, and let's say in Jupyter, you're running it cell by cell, it's very easy to see,
okay, the cell crashed, like it didn't run, or it crashes when I try to run this cell
in the Jupyter. But if you're not running it interactively, you want more output.
And usually you want to have the program, got to use some debugging output for yourself.
And that is something that is left for basically, we cannot do much for it. It's up to the programmers
or the people who run the code to do that. So that's the first thing to remember. It's good
to add, especially at key points of your code, what is your code doing? And the second thing
about, okay, did it actually use the resources? That's a different question. And that
that the queue system can answer, like did it actually use what it was needed.
And there are a few tools that you can use.
So first one that we already have touched on is the slurm history.
So if I look at the slurm history command, I'll make this a bit bigger.
So the font will go smaller, and it will overwrite.
So Slurm history, or with s-act, you
can get the similar kind of information.
So from this output, we can also limit to, let's say, 15 min.
I think you can, yes.
Yeah, okay, so we can tell it for jobs in the last 15 minutes, this is what's run and
all the stuff.
Yeah, so this is pretty standard, I guess.
Yeah, so from this output you can see stuff like, okay, what was the starting time of
the job, how much memory you requested, what was the actual memory usage of the job, how
much CPU time it used.
So the CPU time is basically the time it took, like how much CPU calculation seconds it used
basically, like how much actual CPU calculation it used.
And the wall time is like the real clock time.
So the CPU time, like let's say you ask for four CPUs, you would expect the CPU time to
be four times the real time.
It might sound a bit confusing here, but basically because you're using four CPUs for the same
time you're using.
So you can think about it like man hours, like we sometimes calculate stuff in man hours.
So, how many man, like if you're working for, yeah, four hours.
Yeah.
So, if something takes 10 man hours, it takes one man 10 hours or two men, five hours.
Like, because it's like a, so the CPU time is basically how many like CPU hours you used.
And you can use this as the starting point.
tool provided by Slurm is this seff. I'll make this a bit bigger now. So, if you run seff and a comma,
like one of your job IDs, you can get this sort of an output, which tells, okay, how much CPU was
utilized and what was the efficiency. So, in the case of these example codes, it's pretty bad
because they don't basically do anything and the measurements might be incorrect because they're
short. But basically, it will tell how much CPU was used and the same with the memory. So,
what is the memory utilization? So, what we talked earlier about how to decide which resources to
use, well, a good starting point might be to request as much resource as your own computer has
and then after you have run it once, then check what was actually utilized and then lower the
resources. It's good to have a bit of overhead, especially in the memory department, but not too
much. So like maybe a few gigabytes overhead or something like that. There's a really good
question. How reliable is the seff in history utilized resource estimate?
That's a great question, because the memory utilization is only measured every...
It depends on the cluster.
Yeah, every 20 seconds or something. But also, it depends how the measurement is recorded. So,
So all measurement is recorded using these so-called control groups, which is a technical
thing, but basically it should record it quite accurately, at least the maximum number, but
the averages...
Did we switch to control groups now?
Yeah.
Okay.
At least the maximum requirement, maximum memory requirement should be pretty accurate,
But the others, because they're calculated from averages, they might be all like, yeah,
it's their averages.
So they might not be ... You might have a code that, let's say it requests a huge amount
of memory when it loads a dataset or something, and then it does nothing with that afterwards.
So you might have a situation where you have a big spike in your memory usage, and these
averages don't necessarily capture that.
that you need to do a bit more like profiling of the code to capture that sort of behavior.
Yeah. Yeah. And monitoring is really a big deal, like getting good accurate measurements of the
resources your jobs use is really necessary to get any good performance out. And there's far
more things that we can do that we can talk about now. But anyway, I propose we go to an exercise
time. So yeah, we can take the break by 10.50 or a bit after.
Yeah. So in the exercises we have for you, we have a few
exercises, like first, like some verbosity exercises, and then
testing out, like checking the how that's how do the seff and
and their SLURM history, what do they look like when you actually run something?
So of course, these are pretty much a toy problem, but you can try them out and see
what the seff looks like.
Because for an actual program, they will look pretty much the same, the utilization and
those sort of numbers.
yeah okay uh i've written this in the notes now um so yeah give it a try i wrote down we can come
back at 50. So, good luck and see you soon. Bye.
you
Welcome back.
So, um, yeah.
I don't know how many people were trying to exercises because there wasn't much comment there but there's definitely some questions about this.
Um, did we already talked about how reliable the estimates were right.
Yes, yes.
Should we do some examples?
Yeah, let's do some.
How to execute the command run-pi.sh file.
Where did that come from?
from I think the ssh file, I don't know, like this.
Maybe it means sh.
Yeah, maybe it means sh.
We would need a bit more WebAssembly probably,
or WebAssembly example.
Okay. Well, let's do some examples. So, what should we look at? Monitoring WAND?
Yeah. So, these examples might seem a bit like, okay, they might be simple or self-evident
whatever. But I would say that they are only simple and self-evident because the program
is simple and self-evident. If you think about if we would be running some really complex program,
it would be very much harder to decipher what's happening there. For the simple program,
it's of course easy to see, but for a more complex program, this is by no means self-evident.
I think it's important to keep in mind that even though these might look simple,
you can plug whatever there and it would be immediately much more complex if the script
would be much more complex. So, in the serial example, if we, for example, look at the run
-pi.sh. So, let's, we can add here, there was already this hello user, but let's add here
some echo that says starting analysis now.
Very simple. Let's put maybe the date there as well.
Okay, yeah.
And question mark in parentheses means it runs the date command.
So you can also write it like this if you want to utilize the automatic highlighting
a bit better.
Or automatic.
So it shows that this is a command.
So let's submit this.
So let's say we would have a problem in the, oh, I may still have the error there, yeah.
And let's look at the output, yeah.
So we would have here the timestamp.
This might be really helpful if your program has tens of steps, multiple steps, having something
like that might be really good. Let's try this set-x as well. This is very good for debugging.
If we open the run-pi and we put here set-x, what that does is that it
It tells the bash interpreter to print all of the commands that we are going to be running.
So if you have, especially if you have like any sort of like if sentence or something
like that, like conditional logic, it might be good to have this because then you can
see what the script is actually like executing.
it will produce this kind of an output where we will see first the command that is being run
and then the output. You can see that before it could run the echo, the script needed to run the
date. It has these double pluses over here. It first needed to get the date before it could
to create this echo.
So that's why we have this double plus over here.
So you can use that to produce extra monitoring.
Let's maybe check the seff example.
Should we do straight up?
Like we can all, like tomorrow we'll talk about
how to do multiprocessing.
Maybe we can do this example as this kind of like a teaser on how do we utilize
or can utilize multiple processors. Let's add cpus per task to Python.
How many zeros are there?
Well, I don't want to count.
Let's just copy-paste.
OK.
So error.
Oh, Python 3?
There's no, yeah, Python 3.
A bit of a mistake.
OK.
That should be fixed.
Yeah.
So now it's using two processors to do the calculation.
So we'll talk about parallelism tomorrow.
So then we'll have a lot more stuff on that.
But for now, let's just marvel at the ease
of use of multiple processors in this example.
OK, yeah.
So let's see how long it takes.
I would expect that the default would be set, but it's, yeah.
OK, so it's done.
And if we do storm history, now we
should see something interesting.
Yeah.
I'll make this a bit.
So the CPU time and wall time is what we want, right?
Yes.
I'll put here the 15 min as well.
OK, that's still too long.
Let's hit 5 min.
Yeah.
One minute?
Well, let's, yeah.
Yeah, now it's good.
OK, there we go.
Oh, okay. Here we see the code. So this is the job that we submitted. And we see that the CPU
time, total CPU time was one minute and 14 seconds. And the wall time was 38 seconds.
So now you can like, there was a question in the notes that like some site doesn't have
seff installed. You can get it from GitHub. It's available there. And I think it's part of some
Slurm installations as well. But what the seff basically does is that calculates
this number multiplied by the number of CPUs. So that would be 38 seconds times two. So
So what's it like, 78 seconds, sorry, 76 seconds.
So and what we utilized was one minute, 14 seconds.
So that's like 74 seconds.
So 74 seconds over 76 seconds, we would expect the CPU efficiency to be, well, close to what's
it like close to a hundred percent.
So let's use seff to do this calculation so that we don't have to do it manually.
So yeah, it's 97% utilization.
But that's basically the kind of calculation it does.
So it takes the wall time, the total time that the job took.
It checks how much resources were actually requested, how many CPUs were requested.
will calculate the total amount of time used and then it checks how much CPU time was actually
utilized. We can see here that the memory utilization is pretty horrendous. This is not
nice. It's way overkill. At one gigabyte, it doesn't really matter. It's still quite small,
the memory requirement. But the CPU efficiency was pretty good. But these kind of like, okay,
you have an assumption how your program behaves. How do you see it in the numbers? This is a quite
complex task, actually. And something that you only get familiar the more you do the thing.
but basically it's easier to check usually if numbers are like, if the percentages
are closer to 100% then it's easier to check like that. Yeah. Okay, so it's time for a break.
So we'll be out for 10 minutes and then we'll come back and we'll have some, well basically,
lightning talks on several other things which we summarize but you need to read yourself.
And then there's a very long Q&A session and you can really ask us anything.
So prepare all your questions, bring your friends, whatever, and try to challenge us.
Yeah, and during the Q&A session, remember, already you can pepper whatever questions you have,
what sort of questions you have, you can already have them in your mind.
So, yeah, but let's have a break.
Yeah. Okay. 10 minutes.
See you later.
Bye.
you
Hello, we are back.
Hello.
Yeah.
So, during the break, we were thinking that, like, hopefully everything appears simple
for you.
Like, we were thinking that, like, is this simple or is it not?
Is this complicated?
Or is it not?
We don't know.
So at the end, remember to put the feedback on so that we know
that was everything clear.
And do remember to put stuff in the notes
as well so that we know what's happening.
So [name], what do we have for us
at this last lightning round of talks?
So there's, as you see from the schedule, there's four things you want to cover.
Application, software modules, data storage, remote access to data.
Each of these is itself not a very long page, but a bit involved.
But behind the scenes, there is so much going on there.
So our goal is to give you the summary of why it's important,
but you can read it and ask questions on your own time.
And that's better than what we've done before when we spent hours on all of these and everyone just
gets bored. Yeah, we'll try to like basically provide you with the cliff notes of what is
yeah what you should be like basically public service announcement or this kind of like
At this point, probably everybody's a bit already like there's so much happening already in the
course. So we try to keep it as simple as possible. So let's talk about applications.
What are applications, [name]? I mean, I guess whenever anyone wants to run something on the
cluster, you want to run some software. And it might be something that you've created completely
by yourself, but often it's something that is automatically installed. And for this,
what does it mean? So yeah, you log in and you want some software, like you want Python,
which appears to be here, or you might want R, or you might want MATLAB, or any number of more
specialized things. So if you go to the random page of some random application and ask,
how do I install it? That will probably not work on the cluster itself
because you don't have admin access there. But there are other things you can do.
So, first of all, I would say, like [name] said, the system is shared, so you cannot
get the admin access there.
But of course, in many cases, the cluster administrators try to install something that
will benefit the whole community.
So there already exists usually software
that has been installed.
We'll talk about how these pre-installed software,
we use this module system to load these,
how these can be loaded.
But yeah, this is one option.
Yeah.
Can you ever install things by yourself?
Yeah, I would say like most of the time, yes.
But for many programs, especially on Linux that the computers, like these cluster computers
usually run, you either need to compile it or you need to get it pre-compiled somewhere
else.
Like somebody already has done the dirty work for you.
If you take it from somewhere else, there are various things you can use. We use Conda nowadays
a lot to provide various kinds of softwares. You can use these Apptainer or Singularity containers
to install libraries. If your code doesn't require to compile its own libraries, it's
like interpreted code, like Matlab code or R code or Python code. In many cases, you can use
which is like the already existing software modules that we provide.
Yeah.
So when someone comes and needs to use something,
I guess this page will give the general summary.
But first you look and see, is it already there?
And then you would decide,
do you ask us or do you try to install yourself?
and it depends on how good you are at adapting installation instructions.
There's also this thing called containers.
Yeah, I already mentioned it in passing.
So there are these containers, this Apptainer or Singularity containers
that can make you so that you can run.
So if you're familiar with Docker containers, they're a bit similar but a bit different.
If you're interested, we were having this workflows course for high-performance computing
and I gave a tutorial on these there.
The recording should be in the Code Refinery YouTube page and the course page is linked
in that course as well.
We can link it into the chat as well.
those can be used to install basically if your program only runs on Ubuntu let's say
you can install it in a container and run that container in the cluster yeah
okay um should we go on so the next up is modules and
so module is one of the things that allows you to
load software. So you'll often see in order to use Python or R or whatever run the command
module load something. So for example we could like let's say we have some MATLAB users already
commented there in the in the notes. So if you want to use MATLAB we have MATLAB
installations usually. Most of the computing clusters, we all use this lmod module system.
In these, there's this command called module spider that you can use to check what versions are
installed. For example, MATLAB. You can write the search with the usual terms, for example,
module spider R or something. And there's like a R version there. And let's say if we want to use
that, we would load that module. So let's say we load that R module. And now we can use command
like which to check which R we have. And we notice that it comes from somewhere, a magical place
way it suddenly found an R for us. There's a big list of these usually by the module purge
cleans up the modules. All of the commands are documented in the page if you want to read it.
There's usually a whole bunch of this software that is available on the computing clusters.
modules. So if you're looking for something, you might find it already here. So one place
to look at it would be over here.
Yeah. And there is quite, well, you need to know a little bit about module for almost
anything you do. So I'd encourage you to read this page.
Yeah, but the modules basically do, like in one sentence, they change various parts in
the Linux terminal so that it finds, like when you look for a program, it will find
the program in different places.
And we use this, instead of installing everything at the same time, we use this so that we can
have multiple different software that might not be compatible with each other.
So let's say multiple versions of R or multiple versions of Python or something like that.
Okay, should we go on to data storage?
Now, data storage is a very big thing and complex.
I mean, the cluster without data, what's the point?
And for the cluster, it's not near as simple as add some hard drives there.
Because the cluster has, the storage has to be big. So ours is 5 petabytes.
It has to be accessible to hundreds of compute nodes and possibly thousands of jobs at the same time.
All of which are reading and writing.
Yeah, so you can basically think of it as like a big pile of disks that has some magic
that makes it so that it appears as one file system.
So it's one big file system and everybody has their own files on that system.
And they are usually these, like you can look at the documentation for the places where
should put stuff. But in Aalto, for example, you basically always want to work on the scratch
file system, which is the work directory, like the big file system that we have. We also have this
bit of a legacy home folder that is much smaller and it's not meant for high-performance computing,
so the other part is meant to store your actual data.
The important things would be to note that usually these file systems have a quota.
By default, the home folder has a 10 gigabyte quota and the scratch file system has a 200
gigabyte quota, like a personal quota. But then we also provide bigger quotas, especially for
projects. So if you belong to a resource project, we can create a shared folder for your project
and they can run to terabytes and more, the quotas. So how much files can you store?
And if you run out of file storage, then ask us and we can increase it.
To me, the most important lesson here is that there's different types of storage for different
purposes. So our big Scratch storage is, well, it's called Scratch for a reason. It's not backed
up, but it's big. Aalto has other places, for example, this hidden out Aalto network drives
here, which are not as higher. Actually, yeah, let's come here. This is good. So for example,
Aalto has network drives that are not as big, but they're very backed up. They're backed up,
They have snapshots.
They have all kinds of, um, yeah.
Sorry.
I, um, yeah, it's sort of great out there.
Yeah.
Um, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Uh, so, so whenever you have a bunch of data, you might need to,
um, put it in different places.
For example, if you're collecting some original data, you would first put it
on the project Aalto storage where it's backed up and then make a copy to Triton where it's not
backed up but available to everywhere. And same for other things. There's like some of the compute
nodes have really fast local disks which are good for some things and so on. Yeah like usually like
you want to think about like what is your overall workflow but usually you have something that is
important like the starting point of your thing. You want that to be backed up in a project folder
in the Aalto network trial and then you want to create a copy of that usually into the work
directory or into the cluster so that you can work on that in the fast file system.
Then your code might be in a version control system. You might want to put your code into the
Git version control so that you can modify it there and you can keep a better check of that.
And then you might need to navigate some of these different file systems, but it's not as
complicated as it might look initially. Because once you figure out your own workflow,
it's usually quite easy to then manage afterwards. Yeah, there's a good comment. Can we...
Okay, there was just an explosion or boom outside. Okay, more like something falling.
Okay, so someone asked to mention separate quotas for number of files and size. So this is a good
point. So on your own computer, you usually think the size is what matters, because your hard disk
is a certain number of terabytes. But on a cluster, the number of files is also quite important.
And you can have a separate quota for both of these.
Yes. So if I run quota command, for example, in our cluster, you notice that I have, well,
quite a bit of files. So you can see here that there's these quotas over here.
Yeah, let's read this. Yeah, let's make it a bit. Yeah, so under group quotas we see space,
quota limit, files, quota limit. Yes, so the space is the actual space that I'm using. So currently
because I need to do lots of tests and developments. I need to have a bit bigger
quota than normally. My quota is three terabytes and I have two terabytes of data. Then my file
quota is three million files, and I'm almost hitting that. I'm pretty certain that 50% of
that is different kinds of Conda environment installations. Many of the installations might
create huge amounts of files. This can get problematic in many clusters. Many clusters
might have different documentations on how you should mitigate problems by having too
many files and that sort of stuff. Our file system, luckily, it's designed to pretty much
handle it quite well, but the quota can still get quite full at some point. In those cases,
I personally just need to do a cleanup at some point. You should be mindful or know about that
there's a difference there. There's a number of files and then there's the actual size of
those files and both are tracked by the voter. Okay. Should we go to the remote access?
Can you scroll down and show the available data storage options?
Oh, yeah.
So hopefully your cluster has a table that looks something like this
and will show the different places that are available and all the different properties.
And it's worth looking at this and seeing what fits.
But we don't need to go into details now.
Yeah.
We also have another page for all the provided
and it's like double the size because there's so many places
is you can put your data. If you're unsure where should you put your data, just come and ask us.
That's the easiest way. Yes, I agree. And we enjoy answering these questions because it saves
others a lot of time and is quite useful. So remote access. So you somehow need to copy data
from wherever you're working to the cluster, unless you edit and write everything directly
on there. But most people need to do this. And let's be honest, the copying of data,
if you don't use the command line, it can be a little bit tricky and complex. But luckily,
we have lots of different ways to do that now. So it's getting better. There's two main different
options here. One is remote mounts of data. So mounting means, let's see, where does it come from?
like you take a hard drive and okay here we go so basically and you mount the disk into somewhere
and then it becomes available on that computer and in this case because we are mounting it through
the network but it means that the file is actually in the file system in triton or in your cluster
but you basically have the shadow of it in your computer and whenever you request,
okay, can I have that file, it will have to transfer it through the network and then if
you do a modification, it will have to transfer the file back there. For example, what we talked
earlier about VS Code yesterday, VS Code basically, it's running on Triton. If you edit the file on
your VS Code editor, it will have to send the modifications back to Triton because it's
editing the actual file in the cluster.
So that's basically how it works.
Yeah.
And this is really convenient because as files are being made in some directory, you immediately
see it on your own computer.
But for opening big files and so on.
Yeah.
Yeah, you need to transfer the whole file in order to get access to it.
So, the second picture is transferring data.
And this is what it looks like.
So there's one copy somewhere and you make another copy somewhere else.
And there's a lot of different tools that help you with this.
The benefit of this is that once you then start processing the file at your own computer,
the results of your simulation or something. You now have it locally, so it's much faster to work
on that usually. But the problem might be that now you have two copies and how do you make certain
that they are actually in sync, especially if you do modifications or that kind of stuff.
There are tools that make transferring these files or syncing these even large files very useful,
like Git Annex and DataLAD and various other tools that you can use to do this.
But you need to figure out a workflow that suits your specific use case usually.
But yeah, if you ever encounter the situation where you're like,
okay, I have a file underscore date underscore back or something like that in your folder that
everybody has at some point, then you know that, okay, you could probably come and talk to us and
we'll figure out a better tool for you to do the copying. Yeah. Okay. And for general purposes,
I see many people using the mounting these days for lightweight use and then copying for
bigger data. So with that being said, I propose that we go to the Q&A and maybe
we can start by describing our typical workflows when we were doing research
type of things. Does that sound good? Yeah. Okay, so I will switch to the notes here.
So yeah, I'll put this in auto-scroll mode.
Yeah, okay, so, um,
[name], when you were doing research, how did you typically
typically deal with data transfers and where was your data stored and stuff like that?
Yeah, well, when I was finishing my master's, I had this kind of like horrible setup.
So that I think everybody who's doing something eventually ends up if they have a deadline.
So, what I had is that I transferred some files from Triton to a virtual machine that
I had on my Windows machine, and then I copied them from there to my Windows side where I
was writing my latte, like actual the paper, the thesis.
Basically, it was like I copied the files from the cluster to a virtual machine where I did
plotting that I copied into my Windows machine. It was a mess and I wouldn't dare anybody to
replicate it. Workflows are this kind of a thing where you quite quickly end up with a workflow
that is bad, but it's your workflow and now you have gotten used to it and now it's too much hassle
to change it anymore. But the next time you start a new project, you know that you don't want to
replicate it anymore. So, I think this is quite a common occurrence for everybody. So, when you
start working on something, you think that, okay, I will just wing it. I will just improvise,
whatever. And then later on, you realize, okay, maybe I should have planned this previously.
But nowadays, I would say that I do vast majority of my work either straight on Triton or I use
Git to sync all of the code so that I don't ever have to copy any code anywhere, hopefully.
There's a question, is the cluster the VM?
In this case, the virtual machine was running on my Windows desktop, so it was a virtual
machine that I run on my Windows desktop, because I needed some plotting things and
stuff like that.
I don't know why I hadn't.
I could have probably installed the tools to the cluster
as well.
Yeah.
Let's see.
So what was my workflow?
So for many of my projects, I was quite comfortable
with SSH and using an editor on Triton.
So I would SSH to the cluster and then have all of my,
I'd be developing my code right there.
And then I would track my code with a version control system, and usually not commit it often
enough, although I would always try to. The code gets synced to, um, well, my own computer or
to github or something and then I usually wouldn't make good backups of
the okay if I had raw data I would store it on one of the Aalto file servers and
then make a copy on my own computer but if it was generated data usually the
only copy would be on Triton because it could be regenerated if absolutely
needed, although this wasn't the best setup, really.
But that was pretty typical for many of my things.
There's a good question, I think, related to this,
because I think things have changed quite a bit.
The code transfer is very easy using Git,
but there was a question about how
you see using VS, Visual Studio connected via SSH to modify the code folders and modify
the .sh files and then run from the OOD shell with Sbatch.
I think that's something that a lot of people are now just doing more and more.
So basically, what I do commonly is that I have terminals, like I use this tool called
tmuxinator to create like this templated terminals basically for myself, for anybody who's interested.
And I've gotten so accustomed to vim, so I'm basically at this kind of like a situation
where it's hard to change learned habits.
So I've got my workflow, but I think for many people it's very useful that you can edit
your code in the same place where your rest of your stuff is.
I think with VS Code it has some problems
related to all of the file searching that we talked about yesterday,
but it's a very powerful tool and very powerful interface.
You can also use the VS Code terminal to also submit the jobs.
So you don't necessarily have to go to
OOD to submit the jobs if the VS Code works fine for you.
And I agree, this VS Code plus open on demand for submitting stuff, that is a very usable
workflow. And that's good. We need much more usability in clusters these days.
There's a question, like, is it possible to work on Triton directly to files in the disks
without moving files to scratch, which is not backed up?
So the disks, I assume the disks are, you mean, like, maybe the disks on your own computer
or?
I mean, to me, this sort of implies people don't want it on Scratch because it's not
backed up.
But we should say Scratch isn't backed up, but it is reliable.
It's a huge rack of probably several hundred disks now that are all grade-sixed.
Yeah.
So there's a good, like, this is, I think this is a great question because it's like,
like, how would, well, I can briefly talk about the technology.
So in the system, there's the six of these disk arrays.
And each of these disk arrays is in this right setup
so that if one of the disks fail,
you can lose one complete array out of these six,
like complete all of the disks.
You could lose all of these.
And it's still duplicated.
And all of the connections are duplicated.
So there's multiple like nodes answering the connections.
So it's a very reliable system, but it's not backed up.
So the backup doesn't like, you don't have a backup that protects you from human error.
You have a basically very reliable system that protects from like system failure kind
of a thing.
Like it's a very reliable system that protects from hardware failures and that sort of stuff.
if you delete the file, it's gone. So it's not backed up in the sense it's very reliable,
but it's as reliable as you are. Personally, I don't trust myself that much with not messing up
stuff. So that's why taking backups is important. But at the same time, that's why I often think
that the most important thing to backup is your thoughts, which is basically your code that you
right? If that is under version control, I can lose a lot of stuff. And that makes it much easier
to decide what is important and what is not. Because usually the problem is that if you don't
know what is important and what is not important, everything is important. If you don't know what
you can throw away, you cannot throw anything away basically. And then suddenly you need to
back up like everything. But if you know that, okay, this initial data set is very important
because I actually need to record measurements from subjects or something like that. If I
actually need to do some measurements, then you know that that is important. You can back up
that. And let's say the processing code for that is backup, like inversion control. You know that
you can reproduce the results with the processing code. Because in science, you're at a problem if
you cannot reproduce anyway, right? So, if you have your code backup and your initial data backup,
you're already quite good to go. So, you shouldn't worry about the scratch that much.
Of course, don't go removing all of your files because then you need to do the preprocessing
again or that kind of stuff. But usually it's like you shouldn't worry about it. I should say
it's much more secure than the disk in the hard drive. Let's give an example. So on a typical
computer, if one hard disk breaks, then you lose all your data. On some computers like mine,
it requires two hard disks to break to lose my data because it's mirrored across two disks.
On Triton, it requires two disks to break because it's mirrored in a way that is designed this way.
Yeah, so it is and my computer is sitting here in my apartment where there could be a fire or
anything. But Triton's data is in a nice climate controlled and fire protected machine room.
So, yeah. But if this means can it be stored on Aalto network disks,
which are backed up and snapshotted and all that stuff, basically
no, because it doesn't have performance to be exported to the whole cluster.
There's a there's a good question about so what's the difference between cluster workstations
or virtual machines they're already like a good answer there so so basically I would
just basically read it out loud so the workstation or one computer is like you have an actual
computer and you have an operating system on that a virtual machine is that you have
an actual hardware like computer but on top of that computer you basically fake another
computer. So, and that's like a virtual machine. It's virtual because it's not actually like,
it's like created on top of the, like you're in the matrix now, like basically.
And then the cluster is this kind of like, you take multiple computers and you stitch them
together using these tools that make it possible to like operate across multiple computers.
Okay, let's see.
The benefits of on-demand for terminals.
I think this is pretty accurate, so it's the ease of use.
I think for most purposes, if you can, the SSH is probably better overall, or is it even
better though?
Well, I think it depends, like I personally like, it's this kind of like.
You don't have to use a web browser.
So if you can use it and directly connect it to your own desktop, that's good.
Yeah.
Like the terminal is basically like, I would say it's like, it said that in, for example,
blues music, it's not the notes you play. It's the notes you don't play. So the terminal is the
minimal things, basically. I personally like it because if I didn't say terminal to do something,
it didn't do anything, basically. If I click a button in a browser or something,
meaning, it usually has some like maybe predefined meaning coded into that button.
But if I use a terminal, I can decide like everything.
And it's a different kind of like a paradigm of usage.
Like the one is like programmatic usage and the other is like interactive usage.
Like you click something and it's like more visual and in many cases it's easier.
But if the button does a lot of things for you, it's very good, of course.
So it's just like complementary approaches, I would say.
You can decide which one works for you best.
Yeah, okay.
Is it precise to say Lumi is a cluster?
Yes, definitely.
Just a question, can we deploy a robotic simulator in Visio ISAX in a container and run it in
cloud mode?
Yes.
I mean, like that answer says, that's a pretty typical thing that happens.
And I think, did we deploy that for other people?
Yeah, I've installed it at least once for somebody.
Yeah.
So if you're thinking about that.
Yeah, go right ahead.
I was going to say, if you have this kind of question, it's good to make the issue and say, can I do this? And we can say, well, first you search and see, is it already there? Then you can make an issue and ask us to install it. And we'll decide if it's, yeah.
Yeah, like the IsaacSim is a good example of a program that definitely benefits from
using the container approach because it's basically like it's a robotic simulation program
that also incorporates like computer vision and that sort of stuff.
So you need to like create like a virtual environment where the virtual robot can then
drive around and that sort of stuff.
So it needs visualization tools that are usually like anything
involving visualization or that sort of stuff
usually requires libraries and things that
are quite complex to install.
So for that approach, these kind of container approaches
are very good.
Yeah, what else is there?
More questions, like what's the limit between some connected workstations and the cluster?
Like this question here.
Yeah, like usually the cluster is like a shorthand for the high performance computing cluster
or something like that, like what people use, where the high performance computing, that's
also like this kind of like, okay, what does this even mean?
kind of like a word salad. But the cluster, the idea behind the cluster is that it's usually
like multi-user system. Like it's a multi-user system where there's usually some queue manager
that manages the thing. So you can create a cluster at a workstation. So there's a thing
called, well, I'm blanking out. What's that? It's the Condor. It's the Condor that can
create a cluster out of workstations basically. But usually the cluster also implies these kinds
of features that you can do. So you have a queue system, you have multi-user setup, you have a
shared file system usually. It's basically like you know the story about the elephant and blind
men trying out the elephant and one thinks it's a broom and one thinks it's a tree and that sort
of stuff. It's the same kind of thing that cluster is a combination of all of these different
features. It's compute nodes, it's the shared file system, it's the queue system,
system, it's the software stack. It's all the cluster. It means that it's one system
designed to utilize all of these features in order to make it possible to run certain
kinds of programs which require these features. Especially in Lumi's case, what is a supercomputer
and a cluster like supercomputer usually means that it's big first off and there's usually
like a certain kind of architecture throughout the computer so you can run like these massive
jobs on it like very big jobs and that requires all of the infrastructure what the cluster has
but basically Lumi and our cluster is basically similar kind of a system the scale is just
different and what's in there, like what software is there and that sort of stuff is different.
But both use, for example, same kind of file system, both use same kind of queuing system
and both use LMod. So basically, we'll hear tomorrow more about how do you get from laptops
to Lumi basically, like how can you scale up. And if you know how to run stuff in your local cluster,
it's quite easy to jump or easier to jump to these supercomputers as well.
Yeah. And would you say that, well, there is no real strict definition? I mean, there's all
different types of things and different people may call them clusters or not and so on.
Like, I just think that there's so much technical stuff that is like, like, and everybody's like,
I don't know. There's so much technical jargon going in the field, but nobody can decide on
what's what. You can call them whatever you want as long as they do what you want.
I would think more in the line of, okay, what can I do with that? Instead of, okay,
what should I call it? Can I run my code on Lumi? Can I run my code on my local computer?
Can I run it? It doesn't really matter what the system is called as long as it produces
just the results that I want.
Yeah.
OK, so if you notice there's feedback here,
please fill out the poll.
I see there's a lot more people watching than are answering.
We really need these answers to improve things.
Yeah, do give us as much feedback as you can,
because we are just wondering here,
are we doing stuff correctly, or should we
modify it for the next year, and what should we do?
So don't leave us hanging.
Yeah.
So for tomorrow, in case anyone's leaving already, so we'll go over we'll go through the more advanced
uses, which is mainly many different ways of running things in parallel. And this is really
the real power, like what you've done so far. Well, you could do this on most of this on your
own computer and survive. But tomorrow, yeah, we'll see how we can run tens or hundreds of
things at once with only really small changes from what we're doing now. Make sure you understand
the batch job and monitoring parts of the day because that's what we're using.
So yeah like today we have been like what the name of the job was serial jobs interactive and
serial so they are like very one way but tomorrow we'll talk about like okay what if we add a
for loop basically here or like what if we do a lot of stuff at the same time and yeah hopefully
we can get that through in the best possible way yeah
okay if there's no more questions up here should we start wrapping up
So there is some feedback that it was a bit fast and there wasn't much time for
exercises. We know, unfortunately, but luckily you can continue exploring on
your own afterwards. There's no way we could cover it all in a few days or in a
few hours. So our hope it was to give you the inspiration and big picture and then
And you can go and follow up.
So is there any other preparation or things
people should do for tomorrow?
Not really.
I don't know.
I guess that's it.
Yeah.
OK.
Like, it's pretty much like tomorrow
is pretty much the same, but on a bigger scale.
But just like whatever we have talked about today,
about Slurm and parameters and whatever,
just keep in mind that, OK, you'll
be needing those tomorrow.
Yeah.
OK.
For this comment here about a demo of these,
I can give some, I'll put some links in here.
But yeah, okay, so see you tomorrow at the usual time.
Yeah, okay, thanks a lot. Thanks a lot. Bye. Bye.
you