CodeRefinery.org
you
Hello.
Can anyone hear us?
Yeah, I think they can hear us, at least.
I can hear us on the stream.
You hear us?
Okay, good.
That's a good start.
Let's get all these controls going.
Yeah, we have icebreakers, like, unless you like icy weather in the chat.
What is your favorite weather?
Yeah.
OK, so yeah, so [name], what's your favorite weather?
I would say that it's like, it's a weather that changes
every two weeks or something.
Like, I don't usually like it to be
the same too long at a time.
But I do like Finnish winters.
It's great.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, a cold, dry winter is good.
Yeah, dry, yeah.
Yeah.
And you know, like once it gets to 20, it can get too hot sometimes, but maybe
15 to 20 and sunny, occasional rain every few days to keep the fire warnings away.
It's often said that, especially in the cold weather, it's a question of what are you wearing.
But I think for different kinds of weather, it's the question of what are you planning on doing.
Summer weather is very nice if you're planning on going to the beach or something like that.
But it's not very nice if you're inside and have to work.
If you say you happen to be inside with a bunch of computers running a streaming setup in a insulated building.
Yeah. Not necessarily the best weather for that sort of an activity. I don't know who would do that.
Yeah. Yeah.
Okay. The next question is which technologies have you used?
And there are some things there like Python, multi-processing, R parallel and so on.
These are all basically ways to use multiple processors at once, and maybe other people can add more of them there.
If you don't know the terminology, it's okay, you'll learn later, but if you do know it and you've used it, then mark it down.
And this is really important, because this is basically going to be... well, this is what we'll go through here.
Yeah, and don't worry about the word salad again like this, there's going to be a lot
of these terms and we'll try to explain them when we go, like when we encounter them.
But yeah, there's going to be some of these words that especially like we already encountered
yesterday the bash batch kind of a thing where you basically have to have a keen ear to differentiate
the different technologies, like which is a Bash shell and which is a Bash script,
especially depending on pronunciation, they can sound pretty much the same. We have some
similar kind of stuff happening today with MPI and MP. Don't get worried about it. If
something is unclear, just ask in the notes and we'll try to clarify the thoughts.
Okay, and the last question, which task,
not computing related,
has involved the most number of synchronized people
working on the same things?
So it could be, for example,
like what's the typical thing?
These Olympic opening ceremonies or something
where the countries try to get the most number of dancers
just to put on a show,
or it could be a sporting event,
or what else involves a lot of synchronized people?
There have been these shows, I think in Italy at least,
where people are playing, like hundreds of people
are playing like instruments together,
like guitars or drums and rocking together,
like a thousand people playing electric guitar
at the same time.
I think this summer there's going to be like a bass
playing this kind of like show in Helsinki center that will involve like hundreds of
bassists playing together with the same song so. Yeah there's an interesting comment there
street fighting with the police I hope that was well I hope that's a joke and not actual protest
in some country where that happens.
Or maybe it's like a football activity or something like that.
Ah, yeah. Is football hooliganism considered synchronized though?
That's a good question, yeah.
But anyway, yeah, protests are probably the most synchronized things I would imagine.
I mean, I guess there's different kinds of synchronized, for example, a protest is people
are working towards the same thing, but there's usually not a central leadership managing
every little operation. Maybe getting people in one place, but it's separate. While some
things like these Olympic Opening Ceremony would be... what's it called? Olympic Opening
Ceremony. This is very strongly synchronized probably with a single leader that is guiding
everyone like an orchestra so there's clearly one leader and everyone sees
this person and is following their cues. Oh army is a good one yeah some big
military exercises involve huge numbers of people and all kinds of complex
logistics. Okay now the hard part try to make a metaphor of these tasks to the
different parallel programming styles.
I didn't think that far ahead.
Like, I think, yeah, like, all of these are, like, some of them
are more in sync than others.
For example, like dancing, I would say is probably the most
in sync out of these.
And some of them are like just individuals doing stuff, but at
same time. So some of these, like we're going to be talking
about different methods of parallelization in the cluster
environment. And some of these are more synchronous, and some
of them aren't. And in many cases, probably throughout your
your work where you will encounter situations where
you're basically like middle manager for computer programs.
So instead of like, like, you need to manage all of these
different workers that try to do stuff for you. So basically you have your own small
virtual office of workers and you try to like keep them in check and then there's always one
of these programs that doesn't work correctly or something. You need to waste a lot of time
trying to get it working. So we'll talk about many of these things throughout the day.
I wish I could think of this metaphor to what we're going to talk about, but it's okay.
Technoparty, yeah, there you've got some music playing which everyone's going for, or like
dancing to it at the same time.
Yeah.
Well, should we begin?
Yeah, sure.
So are you going to play it to my screen or?
Sure.
Do you give a start of, do you start off with the day's intro?
It's going to your screen now.
You can do it.
OK.
Maybe I'll, I'm coming to my screen then.
Hey, it worked.
OK.
So yeah, we are beginning day three.
And as you see from the schedule,
it's all about Parallel.
We start with a big picture here.
And then we go to the different forms of Parallelism.
We have a brief intermission where
The CSC comes and gives a talk about their services.
And then we talk about GPUs.
And as usual, there's an Ask Us Anything session where we expect lots of good questions.
So the hardest part about today isn't so much the commands we learn, which are similar,
knowing what to use and how they fit with the programs.
So one thing I've often seen there's some program it says it runs parallel
but it's not clear about how it runs parallel and thus isn't clear how to
run a parallel on our cluster. And that's the most important thing
we can say and what we'll focus on. And of course as every day
there's a lot of different...
well we give a summary but you need to read yourself.
So with that said, I guess we go to what does parallel mean? And I push it to [name]'s screen.
There we go. So, hello. [name], parallel computing, what does it mean?
Yeah, so like [name] said just previously, in many cases you might see a paper or something
where somebody says that, okay, we executed, or especially in a talk where people don't
have time to explain how they did a thing, they will say that, okay, we did a thing with
a massive parallel simulation and we got these results.
And then you're left wondering like, okay, how is it done actually behind it?
And in many cases, there are these different ways that you can do different things, but
they are not differentiated enough so that you can actually say simply that, okay, they
use these kinds of ways.
And there are multiple ways that you can do parallel computing.
And parallel computing in a nutshell is basically just like you run multiple processes at the
same time in some way that you can then get the results done faster. There are multiple ways of
doing this, like parallel calculations. You can either do them completely independently,
somewhat together, or you can do them completely in sync. We are going to be talking about these
different methods of parallelization throughout the session.
Right now, does anyone need to know what the methods are? Are we expecting any initial knowledge?
Not really. Not really. I would just say as a historical footnote,
If you were alive back in early 2000s or something around that time, there weren't really that
many parallel processors in any of the computers.
Most of the computing that was done, they were parallel clusters, of course, and vast
majority of those were using one of the parallelism methods that we are going to be talking about,
this MPI parallelism.
But around the year 2000, you might have heard about Moore's law that tells about the number
of transistors in a processor is going to double every two years.
Well, as the processors went smaller and smaller, suddenly at some point there was a situation
where there's not that much space anymore for the transistors.
What many processor manufacturers started to do is to add multiple processors into their computers,
like into the CPUs. So your phone might nowadays have like maybe eight processors,
and your laptop might have like eight or something like that as well.
So this change happened, but the programs didn't necessarily change. So this is kind of like
Like, lots of modern programs already are parallel, but lots of older ones might not
yet be.
And we'll see how these different methods happen.
So basically, you're saying that processors haven't gotten much more faster than 20 years
ago, but there's more of them.
So we have to be able to use more.
Yeah.
They have gotten faster, but at the same time, they haven't gotten as fast as, let's say,
from 60s to 80s or something like that.
But there are more of them, a lot more of them nowadays.
So if we look at the picture in the screen, we can see that basically in the compute cluster,
we of course have lots of processors.
So the Triton cluster has about 10,000 processors.
So yesterday we were talking what is a core, what is a CPU, well in the case of the computing
cluster, there are cores of individual CPUs, but it doesn't really matter.
You can just think of it like something that can do computations.
We have 10,000 things that can do computations.
And if you want to utilize them, we have to try to utilize them in parallel usually to
get the most out of the system.
So should we go through the different methods quickly?
OK, let's see.
Can you explain them to me?
Pretend I'm a new undergrad student
and don't know much about computers.
So in various linking parallel, what does that mean?
Yeah.
Yeah, let's look at the pretty picture about this.
So, in this picture, is each red box a single thing that's running?
Yes. So, if we think about the cluster that is compromised of different computers and
different CPUs, you can think of each of these blocks as, let's say, one core that can take one
job each. In the case of an array job, we have this kind of parallelism called an array job.
And what that means is that it's basically like a situation where if you want to do something
So if you want to do a thing, like let's say I want to cook spaghetti and then I want to cook a different kind of a pasta at the same time, I can do them separately in two different burners, like I don't necessarily have to, you know, I don't have to do the same thing over and over again.
I don't necessarily have to put them into the same pot or something like that.
So I have, so it's like I want to make five pots of pasta.
I can get five people and do it separately and that works perfectly.
Yes.
So if you have a thing that you can like split up in some way, let's say you have a simulation
and you have different parameters for that, you can embarrassingly parallel that or run
in an embarrassingly parallel way. There was another term that somebody used that was
easily parallelizable or something like that. That basically means that you can split it
in some natural way, the computation. You run a different experiment in a different calculation.
You can split it among different data sets, different models, something like that. Something
that is very easy to split up and what in the embarrassingly parallel way that utilizes these
array jobs you can like spread them out throughout the cluster or in different places and you don't
necessarily have to worry where they end up they just get done and the question is more about okay
how can you manage these jobs so that they can get to the queue how can you put all of your
different parameters into the queue. So in the picture here in below, you can see that,
let's say we have one of these array jobs that we would submit, some of them might get into
one computer and one could get into a different computer and they would be completely independent
of each other. And there was a great question in the notes that do they all have their own
copies of variables. And yes, they would all be independent. So, basically, there would be
something to differentiate them, like some sort of different task that they are supposed to do,
but they would all run completely independent of each other.
Yeah. Okay. I think I understand this. So, what's the next version?
Yeah. So the next version is this so-called shared memory parallelism.
So this is basically what your laptop is doing, like if you're running something.
So, for example, my Zoom that I'm talking to [name] and to you.
Right.
Utilizing most likely multiple processors on my computer to encode the video and do all kinds of stuff.
And what in the shared memory parallelism, what we do is that we have a process that runs on a computer.
And that computer, that process can like spawn multiple other processes and they can work together in the same computer.
And why is it called shared memory parallelism?
parallelism is that, well, they are physically in the same machine, like they are working
like the processes are in the same machine, so they can interact with each other through
the shared memory, the shared random access memory they have.
So in the image, in the top, you can see that in the shared memory parallelism, we want
all of the processes in the same physical machine so that they have access to that shared memory.
So that's like when someone in the note says do parallel runs all have their same copy of
the variables. So here they do all have the same copy because they access the same memory space.
Yes, of course they can have their own local variables. Each process can have their own
local variables. But the performance comes in the idea that, okay, they can share information
with each other and they can do a calculation together. So if you look at the picture at the
bottom, you might have a program, like a main program, and that main program might start
multiple processes that each work in a different CPU, and they communicate through the shared
memory. This is commonly used, for example, with Python multiprocessing. In R, if you're using
parallel. In MATLAB, if you're using parallel pool, those all utilize this sort of a parallelism
and various other technologies. One technology is this technology called OpenMP,
So open multiprocessing. And it's used in many kinds of libraries underneath many languages.
So for example, if you're using Python, there's this NumPy library that utilizes these OpenMP
parallelism to do these calculations automatically with multiple CPUs.
So I'm trying to think of the metaphor here. So now I have five people cooking pasta,
but they're in the same kitchen. And if we want to share the salt or something, I can put it down
on the counter and someone else can just pick it up and use it. So we all have the same workspace
or something like that. Yeah, that's a great analogy. Okay, so what's the next one?
Yeah, so the next one is this, what I already mentioned, this historically
used parallelism that is used especially in like the supercomputer kind of a thing,
supercomputer systems. And this is called message passing interface parallelism or MPI parallelism.
So if you have heard about MPI, this is the thing. So in the message passing interface
or MPI parallelism, you have a program that consists of multiple programs.
So basically, you start, let's say, a thousand copies of the same program on different computers.
And each of those programs knows that, okay, I'm a part of some greater whole.
I'm a part of this great MPI program, and I need to work together with my…
It's basically like an anthill, like everybody's working together for the common good.
In my pasta analogy, so now we can't directly share things, we have to communicate.
So is it like we have multiple cooks in different apartments, and if I make something that someone
else needs, someone has to get up there, go to the other place, knock on the door, say
say, okay, I made this for you, and they answer and receive it, and then we go back or something.
Yeah.
That would be a good analogy.
So what the MPI programs do is that when you start them up, they create this communication
layer so that they can like, they can share information through each other.
And they all like, usually what you would have is that, let's say one process would
have its own, let's say, simulation range or certain area of the simulation that they
would handle.
And what they would communicate to the other processes are the edge regions of that simulation
area.
So that they would do minimal amount of communication with each other, but they would do stuff collectively
to simulate, let's say, a weather model or something like that.
Okay yeah so like you divide it up into different domains like physical domains and each edge
condition can do things. Yeah. So what is MPI most often used for? It seems a bit harder to use or
program. Yes so it is much more complicated because the program usually needs to be designed
around the communication also like the algorithms that are used. It's quite often used in like
physics simulations. So, for example, like CP2K, GPAW, LAMMPS, OpenFOAM, many weather models,
like all weather models usually do that sort of stuff. And you usually need to build the program
around the communication layer. So, basically, you need to design your program to be an MPI program.
So compared to like the multi-processing thing or the shared memory parallelism
where the programs are usually like you can just like quite trivially usually
use them in different kinds of contexts, the MPI programs are usually like you need to
from ground up design the program to be an MPI program. But it's very powerful when you
design a program like that because then you can utilize these supercomputers.
Yeah. Okay. Are there any more methods?
Well, the last one...
Oh, yeah, GPUs. I see.
Yeah, you might have heard is GPU
parallelism. And it's a different kind of like a parallelism, basically, because
like in a GPU, you have like internal parallelism in the GPU card itself. So this graphics processing
unit. They are basically like big vector calculators that can do a lot of calculations
in parallel. Let's say they can multiply a matrix really fast, but they are in the GPU.
Usually, when you have a GPU program, it's parallel in a sense that you have a CPU part
And then usually that CPU part tells the GPU program, okay, here's some, let's say, matrix
you need to multiply, and here's another matrix that you need to multiply with.
And then they are transferred into the GPUs, this VRAM, so this video RAM.
The GPUs have their own fast memory that they can access.
And then these individual calculating units, they're often called like CUDA cores or compute
units or something like that.
They do the calculation in parallel.
So they work basically like this kind of like a fast calculator for these kinds of programs
that can do a lot of stuff in parallel.
But they don't, and of course, there's cases where you also have programs where the calculations
are done using, let's say, some communication so that you can have multiple GPUs working
together.
But usually, the GPU parallelism is internal to the program structure.
And that also means that your program needs to be designed to use GPUs or, well, it can't
use the GPUs.
So, what's a good metaphor here with my pasta analogy?
Is it like, you have one of these, well, if you want to, let's say you want to make the
pasta sauce and you have like an onion slicer or something like that, you just can slice
the whole onion with one go, but you cannot really cook pasta with that really, like you
You can, it does that one thing in parallel.
Instead of chopping with the knife,
you can just chop a full onion at one time.
Actually, I could show my slide with the GPU metaphor
for the pasta thing.
OK.
I'll switch to my screen here.
There.
So this is part of some other thing.
But in the cooking metaphor, so what we see here
is from some restaurant in Switzerland where they're cooking a bunch of chickens on a fire.
And here it's designed where you could cook probably 20 chickens at once. And sorry for
vegetarians, I am too, but this is, well, the metaphor I found. So with this, with very little
effort and quite good efficiency, we can cook so much food at once. But how much pasta can we cook
None.
Not that many.
Yeah.
So the GPU is intrinsically suitable for some types of problems, but not all types.
So if it matches the GPU model, you can do a whole lot.
But if it doesn't, well, it just doesn't run there.
With the GPUs, because why the GPUs are powerful, why they are like that, they originate, of
course, for historical reasons, designed for computer graphics.
And if you do 3D computer graphics, you need to do a lot of rotations and that sort of
stuff in order to calculate vector graphics in the computer programs.
And that's why the computers or the chips of the GPUs were designed to do lots of these
matrix calculations.
And then afterwards, people realized that, hey, what if we use these really good matrix
calculation units to do all kinds of other computations?
And then when, let's say, the deep learning boom started, people realized, okay, we can
run these models in GPUs very efficiently.
And just today I saw news that NVIDIA has surpassed Apple in the stock price.
So they are basically like the GPU trend is ongoing and it's going really fast because
these can be utilized as long as you can formulate your program in this kind of like a matrix
kind of a way, you can usually utilize GPUs to do these fast calculations.
and that's why you said it has to be completely designed around the GPU basically from the start.
So before we move forward to the actual first examples and first exercise,
I want to talk a bit about what is serial and what is parallel in your code. So not every
Every program parallelizes with the GPU parallelization or the shared memory parallelization, because
every program by design or by maths, basically, needs to have a serial part or it has some
part that is serial part.
And then you have some parallel part.
And if you parallelize the parallel part, you can get different amounts of speed up
based on well how much of the program execution was done in parallel. So for example in the first
picture you can see that there's only a small parallel part and if you parallelize that with
two CPUs so you basically divide it by half and then you run it with two CPUs you only save a
small amount of time but if you have like a larger parallel part and you parallelize it you get a
bigger time saver. So it depends on your program. And this is why the embarrassingly parallel is
often the best case. Parallelism in many cases. Because not every problem is easy to parallelize
in these more advanced ways. And it's not a problem. Not everything goes faster by adding
more power to it. So, for example, like Ferrari doesn't go faster in Finnish roads because
there's speed limits. Like, you can use an older car as well.
What about this metaphor? So, with the pasta thing again. So, if I have two people making
pasta in my house, it's probably still okay. Actually, this metaphor isn't perfect. But
Let's say I have 50 people making pasta in my home, or in one home, and it has one sink.
Eventually, everyone's going to need to use the sink, and there'll be a queue there.
That's actually not correct.
Yeah, but if you, like, let's say, like, if you break the pasta in half, like, if you
break the pasta in half and cook it in two pots, does it cook any faster?
Like, do you get it done any faster?
Most likely not, because the pasta has a set cooking time that will always, like pasta
in a sense is always, it will only cook for certain minutes.
You cannot make it faster by spreading, putting it into multiple pots, usually at least.
So that's good to keep in mind when doing parallel computations.
So should we start doing them?
There's one more question, though.
So it's a question, running same simulation,
different random sets, inside each simulation,
I use a GPU for large matrix multiplications.
Each simulation is in a different CPU,
but how to handle the GPU part?
So this is somehow related to the combining
different forms of parallelism.
Yes.
it's not exactly what's there, but yeah. Yeah, so one thing that you can remember is that you can
combine these different methods of parallelization. You can combine, like you can run, if you have
multiple different simulations, you can run this kind of an array job, this embarrassingly parallel
simulation with each job so that each job has a GPU, if your code uses GPUs.
In that case, if you have a simulation and then you need to use a GPU to do some part
of that simulation, there are methods for that, but it requires a bit more finesse so
that the different CPUs can communicate with the GPU.
In many cases, you might have a situation where you have one processor that discusses
with the GPU, and the other processors are doing the simulation.
So you have basically a shared memory part of the simulations, and then you have one
part that does the matrix multiplication with the GPU.
So you have basically these two linked by one CPU, but this is a special case.
But do remember that it's possible to combine all of these methods together.
And if you scroll down the page more, it finally says the research software engineers can help
with parallel computing.
And this is something I'd really recommend.
I mean, these things are confusing.
Even when I'm doing things, I'll often ask [name] just to make sure that I'm running it
correctly or to save me some time.
So if you get to the point where you wonder how it works,
and you're at Aalto University, we're here.
And our job is to save you time figuring out this stuff.
So come by and ask.
I will also mention that it's always a good idea
before creating your own, let's say,
computing framework or something.
It's always good to check if somebody else has done it
before you, because many of these parallel things
are complicated to write, so you don't usually
want to write your own.
There's usually, for example, for R,
there's the parallel package.
And for Python, there's multiple,
like joblib, and there's parallel.
My many parallel processing libraries
that already do this kind of stuff
so that you don't necessarily have
to worry about how it's done underneath it.
So keep that in mind.
whenever using, it's a good idea to use code because like writing the actual like communication
and that sort of stuff is super complicated. So most people that are listening to this
won't be writing their own parallel code but they'll be using existing libraries or frameworks
and yeah I would recommend at least that. You can always write your own but
But yeah, so should we move forward to the array jobs
and actually get to do something?
So I'll flip back to my screen.
Yes.
OK, so here we are, to array jobs.
So I guess we go like before.
So let's look at the abstract here.
So what's an array job?
So array makes me think a bunch of things in parallel.
And from before, I know it's somehow related to embarrassing parallel.
So how would you explain it?
Yeah.
So an array is basically like what the name says.
It's like a list of numbers, basically.
And in this case, let's say we want
to do a simulation with multiple different data sets.
We have data set one.
We have data set two, data set three, and so forth.
We want to do the same simulation with we
have something that we want to iterate over, basically.
And all of these simulations would
be independent of each other.
So we have independent simulations that we can do, but we just want to do them all.
And what we could do is we could write our Sbatch script for each simulation at a time.
So we would have like n Sbatch scripts to run like serial jobs.
But what we can do in Slurm, there's this feature called array, where you can give this
slurm comment that we previously already see called array and give it a list of numbers or
different kinds of numbers and then it will launch basically one job that consists of
multiple of these independent jobs. So basically it launches copies of the same job
but with the key difference that each job gets one number different. So each job gets its own
Slurm_Array_Task_Id. So, each one gets its own environment variable, which is the number
of that job's number in that array. So, that job's number in that list of jobs.
Yeah. So, this variable right here, this runs 10 times with input underscore one,
input underscore 2 and so on up to 10. Okay. So when the job is running, if we look at the
minimal example script over here, when the job is running, that number, the slurm array task ID,
will go from numbers 1 to 10 because we have specified there in the comment that we want
them to run an array from 1 to 10. That number will change. That number then we can, for example,
In that code, we can run input one, input two, input three, and they all run independently
at the same time. The Slurm will try to allocate all of those into the queue, and they will run
independent of each other in different computers, different nodes, and whatever.
All of the other requirements that we have specified, if we require a certain amount of
of memory, certain amount of time, whatever, they are copied as well.
The rest of the script is basically copied between all of the jobs, but the array index
is just different.
Yeah.
So I run sbatch once, but 10 things come out the other end.
Yes.
Yes, basically.
So we can do this.
What you can do then, or what is the question usually, is that, okay, you have a number,
like the array is a number, and how can you convert that number into something else, let's
say a parameter or something.
We'll go through a few examples of this.
Yeah.
Maybe we could-
Should we do the example?
Yeah.
Let's do an example.
Okay.
And run that.
There's some good questions in the notes.
we can answer those first. Simulation is relatively fast. So yeah, if the array jobs take
a few minutes or less, then it's better not to have thousands of them. Try to group them together.
And there's some hints about this later in the page. It's exactly like an overall for loop
kind of thing. The number assigned to the array randomly done. I'm not sure exactly what that
means. So the Slurm_Array_Task_IDs come exactly from this here.
And you can skip values. You can choose different number ranges. You can do it like
you can do like every fifth number or something like that. There's different
syntaxes you can use to which numbers you want to use. But you will get like each of these jobs
will get one of those numbers that you have specified in the dash dash array comment.
The array jobs result in multiple sessions. Yes, so they can run at the same time,
but they might run at different times, and they're all completely independent
and have no knowledge of each other.
Yes.
Okay.
Let's go on.
So, if I scroll down.
Yeah.
Let's look at that example.
Where's the first example we get?
My first array job.
Yeah.
This seems like the place to start, right?
Yes.
Okay.
Yeah.
If we look at the script.
So, if we look at the script over here, we have, like, we have the usual suspects.
So, we have the first line.
We have the shebang, shebang, how it's pronounced.
And then we have a few of these comments, so if [name], you want to open our editor and copy the script there.
I've just realized I haven't cloned the HPC Examples repository or gotten set up.
Yeah.
Okay.
Well, in the meantime, I can, while [name] is copying the repository, I can, oh, yeah,
yeah.
Actually, for this, you don't need that, yeah.
The next ones, maybe, yes.
OK.
What?
Yes.
So, in the script, we have the time and the memory requirements at the start.
So these are the usual suspects that we always want to give anyways.
And after that, we have the output.
And this time in the output comment, we have a directive for the Sbatch.
We have a few different characters there.
We have this %A and %a, and what these do is that because we now launch multiple jobs
at the same time, we don't want them all to write in the same output file because it would
get really cluttered and it would be really hard to see what each of these would do.
What we can do is that we can divert each output into a separate file where the person's
capital A is like a shorthand for the job ID as a whole, like the whole array will get
one job ID.
So that will be the job ID for the array job, for the whole SLURM submission basically.
So basically, they all have the same capital A.
Yes.
The lowercase a is the number from it?
Yeah, that's the Slurm array task ID.
So each we will get, like if we submit in this example,
we submit from 0 to 15, so we get 16 outputs
when we calculate them together.
So we get 16 output files in this case.
And then, in the example, we run this echo.
And here, I'm just printing it out.
Yes.
OK, does this look correct?
Yeah, let's try and run it.
OK, I Control-X and Y, and Enter to save.
If I list, I see array example.
So I run with sbatch?
Yes.
So we do one submission.
And now if you run slurmq, we can see, hopefully.
It already ran.
The thing you saw pending was something I have.
Yeah, we need to put maybe a sleep there.
But OK, it already ran.
And now we already see the output.
So we see there that we have generated the overall job ID was 476680, and then we have
from 0 to 50 in these output files.
If [name] now looks at the output 0, you can see that the task ID is 0.
And if you pick, let's say, 1 is 1 and so forth.
You can notice that each process, when they were running, or each array task, when they
were running, they all got a different number for the slow array task ID.
There was a question also in the chat, but can you map this number into two parameters?
Yes, you can.
You can basically, whatever countable set you have, you can map into that, like whatever,
like two dimensions, three dimensions.
The question is just like, how complicated does the thing start to be?
And usually, we will look at a few examples on what you can do with this or what sort
of things you can do with this.
But in many cases, if it starts to get really complicated, the mapping, it's easier to just
the number to your program and then write it in your program. Okay, what should it do
with numbers? So, quite often, let's say it loads a line from a configuration file and
then loads the parameters from there or something like that.
Yeah. Okay. So, is that basically what there is? Do we, I think...
Maybe we could run the same example, but with a sleep in there and just demo, just to verify
that it actually runs on separate jobs.
I'm pushing the up arrow key to go up in history to find my nano command.
Yeah.
I push enter.
So what we get when we run this, we get 15 different individual jobs that all run the
same except the task ID is different.
And if we, based on that Slurm task ID, we do something different, or use a different
data set or different parameters or something, we will get 15 different results.
Yeah.
Okay. Should I do it?
Yes. Let's do it.
Press Enter.
Okay. I push Enter and then I run Slurm q immediately.
Yeah.
So here it looks like.
Yeah. They all got running immediately.
They're all running very quickly.
You can notice on the left,
you can see that they have this underscore there,
where you have the different array indices separated. So you have the same thing running
with different indices. And on the right, you can see where the node list is. Some are running in
PE40, some are running in PE41, and some are running in PE43, I think, or something.
So the computers where they are running might be completely different because they are independent.
But using this array thing makes it possible for you to run a lot of simulations at the
same time and it also is very nice for the queue manager because the queue manager doesn't
now have to consider each job independently.
It can consider the array job as a whole and it's much better for the queue manager to
do this for you to do this this way you don't get you don't accidentally like cause like a denial
of service and this could be the denial of service by submitting like thousands of jobs
so many of our users might run arrays that have like hundreds or maybe even maybe thousands of
jobs in the array so if they want to do like really big lots of simulations like different
random numbers or different parameters or something like that.
So there's a question, does it run the same program ten times?
Yes, and it has, but your program has to be able to use this variable to do different things each time.
If that's what you want. And below, I think we have a bunch of examples of this.
So we won't really go through the examples, but maybe we can show the spirit of them.
Yeah.
Maybe we can show the first two as this kind of like, yeah.
So here we see it's the array job.
There's 30 things in the array.
And I see there's some application that says input.
And here every program will take a different piece of input data.
if you have your input data all numbered, then that's relatively easy.
Yeah, and if you scroll a bit down, there's two examples of how can you map those numbers
into some parameters. One example is that you can use this case structure in Bash.
If the Slurm array task ID is something, set the seed in this case to be some other value.
And there is also below, there's another example where you can use, if you don't want to write,
you can write it a bit more concise.
you can use this bash array. This is a different array than the slurm array we are talking
about. Basically, bash has this list or all this kind of array structure. So, you can
list the numbers there and then pick from this array that specific number based on the
index of the, like, there.
And I guess the whole thing could be done in Python, basically, where you give a single
number to your Python or R MATLAB program, whatever, and internally it maps to whatever
parameters it's supposed to use.
Yes.
Okay.
Yeah.
You can also, like, read a line from a file, like, below this example also, like, if you
want to write your different parameters in a file and then read it from there.
But maybe we should go into exercises and let people try them out themselves.
Yeah, I agree.
There's a little bit more here you can read yourself.
So for exercises, what should we recommend people to work on?
I would probably say that the exercise 1 would be probably best.
So you can choose whichever of these previous examples
that we provide in the page and try
to give this pi.py different seed numbers.
So you can try out one of these exercises.
I would say that run one of these, at least,
and try it out.
Also, there was a good question, what
a difference between job and a program. Job, in this case, often refers to Slurm job. Basically,
like an allocation that Slurm needs to fulfill for you. When you submit with sbatch some script,
then Slurm thinks of it as a job that it needs to do. I need to do this thing.
thing. I need to execute this thing. If you give it an array job, it knows that, okay,
I need to execute this like 100 times, but with different array index each time. That's
a slurm job. Inside the script in that job, it can have multiple programs that you run
and then one after the other.
Yeah.
OK.
And how long should we give?
I guess this has to be combined with the break
because it will be break time.
So assuming people start 10 minutes from now
after the break, should we give 20 minutes maybe?
Would you say this is the most important one,
so we should give the most time here?
I think it would be good to have enough time to really test
these examples, because this is something that can give you a lot of power with minimal changes
to your code. And that's why this is very good to learn, because you can then utilize it in
multiple different ways. So yeah, I would say 20 minutes at least. Yeah. Okay. Sounds good.
So I wrote down until 20.
20 pounds.
So that's.
And do ask the questions.
It's very good to have the questions in the notes.
Yeah.
This is the most important interactive lesson
we're doing today.
So OK, see you in half an hour.
Yeah.
Thanks.
Bye.
you
Hello, we're back.
And there have been really many very good questions here, and I think most have been
answered.
There's a good question about how does the program understand Slurm_Array_Task_ID.
is called an environment variable and it's not specific to Slurm. Environment variable is a thing
which all Unix and probably Windows programs have a concept of and many languages can read
them and get the values. We're showing how to do it with Bash but there's other ways too.
Yeah, we will quickly mention when in the next session that we start soon, how you can like
calculate or get the CPU number, how many CPUs you have allocated in the script,
like in your code, how you can get that number and you can use the same kind of structure for the
array ID as well. Yeah.
There's a good thing here about confusing terminology.
And yes, it's confusing. My recommendation is to
run it several times and see what happens.
And also, I would say that
try to look beyond the terminology and look at the
functionality. All of these have so
many conflicting terms that it's very hard to keep it in check, even in speech. We might
use confusing terminologies all the time that are not correct because there's so many different
terms. But what I think the most important thing is to keep in mind that, okay, you have
this workflow that you might write your serial job. You might do an interactive, first interactive
job on your program, then you write it into a serial script. And then when you have run it
through the serial script, like we did yesterday, after that, you want to do it with, let's say,
multiple parameters or something. So, then you add the array constructor. And then in your code,
you write some way that, okay, it understands that there's different things that it needs to do.
Yeah, like there's multiple ways of doing that.
And usually it's a good idea to recommend a way is that first you launch like one array
job.
Like I mean, like one array index.
So let's say array equals, that's just array equals zero.
So you basically launch, it would be basically the serial job, right?
Okay.
Yeah.
Like because you're launching only one of them and you see that, okay, did it work correctly?
And then maybe you launch the array, and that's just array equals one, and you launch the
next one.
Okay.
Yeah.
And you see that, okay, did it do the different thing that you expected?
And then you launch array from zero to thousand or something.
Because like, so you basically like copy paste the same code without doing the copy paste.
And that's this kind of workflow, once you get hang of that, that is the most important
thing.
call it is not the most important issue, I would say.
Okay, yeah. So what's coming up next?
Do we do some examples of the array jobs? Or should we go on?
I think we should move on because we have a lot of
ground to cover. But, yeah, so maybe we should...
My screen. So it's a shared memory parallelism.
Yeah. Okay. Yeah. And for the next two, do we give a
very high-level overview, but
we don't do as many examples? Yeah, yeah. Like, we will run
through some examples, but yeah, so we won't necessarily, because these are very dependent
on your program, so we don't necessarily like, it's very hard to do like a good example because
it depends on what program you're using, but we can demonstrate how the queue thinks about
these things. So the array job, like if we think about the array job that we just had,
But we are running basically the same serial job, but we're just running with more of those.
We are running more of those simultaneously and separately of each other.
But all of those will, like, let's say if we run one of those and that takes like an
hour to run, the other ones will also most likely take an hour to run as well if they're
quite similar jobs.
But in many cases, you would want it to run faster.
You want it to actually finish faster.
And in that case, you might want to try to use multiple processors to make it run faster.
And the first question here is that, can your program actually do it?
Does your program support multiple processors so that it can internally run faster?
If we look at the picture below, again, we see that in the shared memory jobs,
we get for the one single job, and I mean, again, let's focus, let's put the array idea that we had
and put that in the back of our mind, but let's think about the serial job. We start one,
we submit one job first to the queue and in the shared memory job, we would want to give this one
job more resources. We wanted to give that to have access to multiple CPUs.
So in the array job, we had individual jobs that are completely independent and all of those were
running with one CPU. But in this case, we want to give like, okay, let's have one of these scripts
and let this script should be able to use multiple CPUs.
And it's very easy to ask for these resources.
So you can just give this dash dash CPUs per task
and then a number in this Sbatch comment.
Yes, and you can then reserve multiple CPUs for a job.
The question is that does your program actually use those, or can it use those?
In many cases, the program might recognize that there's multiple processes there, and
in some cases it doesn't.
What is usually important in your program, if you see something like nTasks or nProcs
or nCPUs, or CPUs, or processors, something like this,
like a flag that tells that, OK, this can be run in parallel.
What you usually want to do is you
want this number that the process,
like what the program takes in, to be
equal to the number of processors
you have requested from the queue.
And this doesn't happen automatically all the time.
Yes, it doesn't because the program doesn't know where it's being run. The program doesn't
understand that it's in a computer cluster. It's being run in this allocation of, let's say,
four CPUs. The program doesn't necessarily know that, okay, I've been given four CPUs,
And it might see that there's like 40 CPUs or 100 CPUs in the machine.
And it might think that, hey, I can go full ham and I can take all of these CPUs.
But in reality, it's only been given four.
So you might get completely overloaded by having the program at start like 100 processes on those four CPUs.
So, what you usually want to do is you want to check your program, where your program
takes the value of how much parallelism I should use, how much parallelism I should do, and
then make certain that that number matches the request that's in there.
I think I remember some mention of this at the bottom of the page.
Should we look there now, or maybe come back to it after we've seen it?
We can maybe come back to it, but maybe we should just, like, this is too theoretical,
So run something and see if it's faster.
OK.
So I'll scroll down some.
Where's an example?
Here's an example.
Running an example shared memory program.
Yeah.
So the program here is the same Py Script
that we have used as an example.
And it has this flag called dash dash nprocs.
So how many procs?
like it uses Python multiprocessing to start
do the calculation in parallel and any if you give it the number then
it will use multiple processors yeah okay so
let's try running this example over here
so cpus per task equals two so i tell it two processors
Yes. And then, yeah, and the usual suspects like the memory and time and then we call it
and then the number of processes. And do note that now [name] is putting the numbers to be
like the same on like the number of CPUs per task and the number of processors.
Because it's the same over here.
So let's try running it.
Okay.
Oh, here it says using two processes.
I guess that's the program printing that out.
Yeah.
It knows that it now needs to use multiple processes.
So maybe let's try it out.
Can you put time at the start of the call?
Okay.
In Linux, there's this program called time that you can put, if you put it before the Srun.
Should I do it before Python?
Yeah, before that.
Yeah, that's good.
So what the time does is that it will give some like timing information,
like how long did the program execution take.
Let's try it out and see how long it took.
0.91 seconds, user.
or?
Maybe we should add a 0 there into the number of.
OK.
So now we're running 10 times more.
Yeah.
Processes.
So it says 8.7 seconds user time and 4.4 seconds elapsed.
So it did go about twice as fast.
Yes.
We also note that time also produces this 198% CPU.
OK, yeah.
So we can also use the seff that we previously yesterday
talked about to see the utilization.
So if you use the seff and the job ID,
we can quickly check that the utilization, what was it?
So nine seconds.
Here it says only 112.
Yeah.
It might be that maybe it didn't have time to,
because it's so short, maybe it didn't have time
to measure it correctly.
Yeah, probably.
Probably, if that is the case.
Yeah.
So it wasn't that bad, right?
Yeah, I mean, that's not easy.
What happens if I don't give the nprocs here?
Let's try it out.
So if you run it like that without the nprocs.
I remove nprocs.
So it most likely will take about 16 seconds.
So I would assume if the previous one was eight.
So it took, it used 8.4 seconds of CPU
and took 8.5.
So basically, it only ran on one CPU.
And everything, we wasted one CPU.
What happens if I use four CPUs, or I request four CPUs?
Or I go like this.
So I'm telling the program to use more CPUs.
put something bigger there, put something like 32 or something
so that we see an actual thing there.
So now we are overbooking, basically, the CPUs.
We have only requested two CPUs, but we
are running 32 processors there.
So you notice that it didn't run any faster or any slower here.
Yeah. So you notice that it runs at the same speed basically as if it would have two CPUs.
But the difference is, like this is a toy program. If the program would do something
like really complicated, it would slow down the program because it's oversubscribing.
It definitely can slow down.
Yeah. There's a good question in the notes that,
But what is the difference and benefit of allocating multiple CPUs for a single program
against allocating multiple arrays or like I assume like multiple jobs in an array?
And that's an excellent question because like it raises the question that which is better?
Like is it better to run one program twice as fast, but run it like multiple?
Like is it better to run one program twice as fast for double the parameters or is it
better to run two individual programs with different parameters?
So basically, is it better to divide the program among parameters or just run it as fast as
possible but then go through multiple parameters?
And usually the case is that it's usually easier to do the embarrassingly parallel route.
If you want to do maximum throughput or you want to do maximum amount of jobs, maximum
amount of parameters and whatever, it's usually better to use small jobs than big jobs.
So does it depend on the scaling?
So in here, this program is actually under the hood,
basically embarrassingly parallel.
It divides it up.
Each one runs separately.
But some jobs get slower the more processors you add to it.
So in that case, it's better to not use too many
and use arrays instead.
And I guess you can combine both of them at the same time.
Yeah.
The thing that you get with running with multiple processors is that if your program takes a
long time to run, let's say it takes 10 hours to run, you want the results today, not in
10 hours.
When you submit a job, you want them to be done so that you can look at them earlier.
And in that case, if your program can be parallelized, it's possible to maybe get them faster.
results and you can view them faster. And also if the program is big enough that it just
would take way too much time to run. It's good to parallelize it then. It's like the whole point
of the cluster to get stuff done faster, I guess. Yeah. Okay, yeah. So, should we continue
you scrolling down, or is there anything else here?
Tell me when to stop.
Common special cases.
Let's look at the example of the submission script,
how we would write it as a submission script.
Okay, yeah.
So, previously [name] ran the example
with the, from the, like an interactive job,
but we can also run this in, of course,
in a submission script, and that's
a better way of running it to write it into a CLI script.
Yeah.
So in this case, if you copy the script,
or modify the existing, yeah.
Modify.
The previous script wasn't a Pi example, though, so I will.
Yeah, maybe you want to do a completely new one.
OK.
I'll copy most of this over.
Yeah.
So.
So sbatch, so two per task.
Yeah.
And now, because we are running this in the script,
we can utilize the environment variable that Slurm sets.
So we can utilize this environment variable
called slurm CPUs per task, so that like slurm will fit when the code is being run,
that environment variable will contain, similar to what the array ID was, it will contain the
number of CPUs reserved for this program, so it will automatically fit that. This is very helpful
if you're running something and first you run it with, and you want to test out, for example,
scaling of the program, how well it behaves. If you run it with one CPU, if you run it with two
CPUs, four, eight, 16, so forth, it's usually a good idea to use this environment variable because
then you can easily test out different CPU numbers and you don't have to go into your
program code or something to change the number to match the request number. Yeah, okay, so let's
Submit it.
Submit, yes.
Do you think it will work?
The command.
Let's see.
If you look at the Slurm queue, it's probably run already.
It's running.
I added an extra zero there, so it would run a bit slower.
Yeah.
OK, yeah, it finished.
OK.
If we look at the output, I'll cat it.
Using two processes, yeah.
OK, should we seff?
Yeah, and also in the chat or in the notes,
there was a good question of, like,
I used the term processors and processors and like all of this million of words, like
the CPU, there's core, there's process, there's processor.
Sometimes there's thread or some and like all of these have their own like specific
different meaning, but they're basically like, like used in places like a synonyms in many
cases.
There are technical differences to all of these words, and the CPU and all of this.
You shouldn't necessarily worry about it.
The most important thing to note is that in the program, there's something that it can
do.
It can execute two programs at the same time within the same program, basically.
do that, it should have a place to run it, basically. If you go back to the pasta analogy,
instead of just cooking pasta in one pot, we are now cooking pasta in two pots or we're doing
two pots in two burners or stovetops. We just add more stuff there.
Yeah.
So yeah, like whatever term is used, like if the program developers, they will also
use all kinds of terms interchangeably all the time.
So don't worry about it too much.
And that's why I was saying that you should look for these various terms because you will
never know what is the term used by the developer.
They might talk about the process, they might talk about number of CPUs, number of processors,
of tasks, like number of jobs, like the terms might be different, but the important thing
is to know that, okay, these refer to, okay, how many processors or CPUs you want to use
and to match that with the number of CPUs that you request from the queue.
And for the queue, the important thing is the CPUs per task.
I run seff on this thing we just did? Sure. And it looks pretty much like before, so not perfect
efficiency, but it's so short that's expected. Yeah, and do note that here the CPU efficiency
refers to the size of the request, like the reservation. So the CPU efficiency is like
like, with respect to the amount of processors requested.
So 100% would mean that you're using all of the requested CPUs.
Yeah.
And I think you've said this before,
but the most important thing to me
is that this nprocs gets automatically detected
from Slurm.
So I only have to keep it up to date in one place,
which seems like it would save me a lot of time and effort and doing stuff wrong.
Yeah. Below, if we scroll a bit below, there's like this using Slurm CPUs per task efficiently.
And you can use this basically also for the array task ID. So here's a few examples on how you can
use this parameter.
So for example, in Python, like in the middle there,
you can use the OS module to get that environment variable.
So in this case, if the variable is set,
the value of that is converted into an integer.
If it's not set, the default value is now one.
Is one, yeah, OK.
So you can use this when in your program to like you can write this there so that it automatically
detects how many CPUs you're using and then you can use the end CPUs in your like to give it to
a library or something. Yeah and same to MATLAB. Okay yeah so basically programs so if programs
were well designed they would all use something like this to automatically detect number of
processors available.
Okay.
And this is, there is one
extra, like
I will add one extra
technical thing, like there is no standard
on how many CPUs you're going to be using.
The closest thing to a standard
that is used by many programs
is this so-called OMP
num threads. It's mentioned
above
there in the multi-threaded
versus multiprocess and double-booking section, but you can read the whole thing if you want.
Here's the technical stuff if you're interested, but the important thing is that many programs,
for example, like NumPy libraries in Python, they utilize internal parallelism already,
and it's done using this technology called OpenMP, open multiprocessing.
And that basically takes this variable, this OMP non-threads that describes how many processors
it should use.
And this is used in many programs.
Many programs use this as this kind of shorthand for how many processors you should use for
the parallelism.
So this is quite common for programs that don't even use OpenMP to do the parallelism.
So this is the only standard that is basically defined, otherwise it's like a wild west that
everybody uses their different environment variables for how many processors to use.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, we have three minutes before we need to go to a break.
What should we do?
I propose we can see if there's any further questions,
go to the break.
We can quickly discuss the MPI parallelism along with GPUs.
So does that sound good?
Yeah.
OK.
Yeah, so let's see.
What else is there?
I think [name] already answered the processes
versus processors.
So if you want to go deep into the computer architecture,
you can learn all kinds of things
about how Unix systems handle processes and threads
and things like that.
But for the most part, if you know
the options that are present in this page,
you can figure out how to run something,
and then you don't need to know more.
You're probably here because you want to do
science stuff and not learn about computer architecture.
I will quickly mention that a common thing that
happens to many researchers is that,
let's say you run a code in your laptop,
And your laptop, like I mentioned previously, they nowadays have multiple processors there.
And in many cases, if you run this code that can do multiprocessing internally,
it can do something with parallel, without you noticing, basically. You don't even notice.
The Zoom that I'm using now, it's doing something multiprocessing on the background.
I don't even know about it, but it's doing it to make certain that the video stream is correct.
and audio is processed correctly. It's doing multi-processing in the background.
And in my laptop, it just assumes that, okay, I can use whatever resources are available there.
And when people and resources go to the cluster where you need to actually request the resources,
the programs usually just think that, okay, they will look at the hardware that is there.
they see a server with 128 CPUs. And maybe when in the job request,
you might forget to add the CPUs per task flag. So then when you run the code in the cluster,
it's suddenly much slower. It suddenly takes four times as much time or eight times as much time.
And then you might wonder, like, okay, what's going wrong?
Like, am I doing something wrong?
Because it's so much slower in the computing cluster.
Maybe the computing cluster is a pile of crap and I don't want to use that.
But the reality is that the program doesn't necessarily know about what number of processors
it should use.
And also, the program doesn't have access to all of those processors, because those
are being reserved by other jobs in the queue. So when you're running a program in the cluster,
it's usually a good idea to just run it with multiple CPUs per task and see how it goes.
And you can also look at your own task manager in your own laptop and see how many processes,
do you see the processes being used while I run my code? And just decipher, does it use some
Multiprocessing.
Yeah.
OK, so we need to go to the break
so we don't get too far behind.
So break until one minute past the hour.
And then we have to talk on CSC resources.
So see you soon.
Bye.
you
Hello, welcome back.
So now with us, we have a visitor from CSC, [name].
I hope I got that correct.
Yeah, pretty, pretty good.
But [name] works at CSC, the IT Center for Science.
So CSC is the national high-performance computing center in Finland, but not just that.
It's actually a whole lot more than just the services you see here.
And even what you see here isn't just high-performance computing.
But anyway, CSC is paid by the Ministry of Culture and Education, I believe, to provide
services for free to academic researchers and others within Finland. So CSC, like all the
things we've been talking about today, CSC has similar but larger, a bigger scale. It might be
a little bit more work to use because you have to apply for the resources and migrate to there.
but if you need power or cross-university collaboration,
this is the place to go.
And was that a good intro?
Should you?
That was an excellent intro.
Okay, yeah.
So I will stay here.
I'll be looking for questions in the notes
and raise them at an appropriate time.
So go ahead.
Okay, thanks [name] for introduction.
So, I will tell, I mean, you already heard in brief what CSC is, I might tell a little bit more
and then I give a bit more details at what kind of computing services CSC provides and for what
kind of use cases you might want to use our computing services. Science for a long time,
even I mean if you're using computers hasn't been only about computing so data
is also a big aspect aspect and we have also some services more more related to
data I'll discuss them briefly and finally some something else like
training we provide and of course if you want or need to use CSC services what
you actually need to do for that. As said, we are owned by the Ministry of Education,
which owns about 80% of the shares and the rest 20% is actually owned by the Finnish
universities. We are a non-profit company and we provide a lot of different services
for the science and higher education.
I didn't actually check now
what's the latest number of staff we have,
but I think it's starting to be close to 700
or something like that.
And out from the 700, maybe 120 or 130
work actually with the scientific computing
and supercomputing.
And even though we are sort of discussing here
that CSC Computing Services and what you need to do in order to get to be used.
I actually can assure you that all of you already at this point,
you are CSC users. If you have ever used any network
within the university, the backbone that's provided by
FUNET, pretty much always when you log into your any university web
services, so you're using account authentication. If you're using Wi-Fi, you're most likely using
Eduroam. So these are sort of these other services and I think many of the
standard administration systems, probably if you look for your course results and things like that,
there is very probably some CSC mode also there. And coming back to the computing services,
And things I'm talking here, as I already said, what's probably of big interest for many of you is that you don't actually need to pay most of this any money.
So that's already paid by the Ministry of Education.
Okay, in what kind of situation you might need CSC services?
I think you can also, first question is that when you actually need to use a HPC cluster and even now
that's probably something you discussed already earlier today but just to remind you
supercomputer is not any machine which automatically makes everything faster.
So actually the supercomputer to be useful, you need to have some
parallelism in your scientific task.
Actually, if I take, I could say, pretty much any simulation or so
that runs on a single core and can fit to the memory of my laptop,
I'm pretty sure that my laptop would actually run faster
than any of the CSC supercomputers.
So you need to have something that runs parallelly.
Sometimes it also might just be that
you just need to run something for quite a long time
and because of that using your own workstation or laptop is not useful.
Second thing might be that actually the problem you are trying to solve
needs lots of memory and that's something that the supercomputers can probably have much more memory.
Same goes for storage space. You need to deal with the terabytes of data.
That's most likely something you don't want to deal with your local port space.
One more reason to use CSC or some other HPC cluster is that the application you want to use,
it might be a commercial application that the principle user pays something for that, but the
CSC has actually bought the license for that, and in terms of the license, academic users can use
that free of charge. Or even though it might be an open source application, it might be something
which is a tedious install, have a lot of dependencies, and having data set ready to use
in a supercomputing system might be might be benefit. Regarding the data,
if you need to share data for other researchers, your colleagues, some of the services that CSC
provide might turn out to be useful and especially if you actually want to publish the data that's
that's something that I'm pretty sure it's very difficult for you to do in them according
all the principles on your own. Yeah we basically don't have our own long-term repositories and
say that's CSC's job. Yeah and I mean to get some DOEs for your data and I mean
something where other people can actually also cite your data if you if you share it.
So yeah this is why you might need CSC. You have something parallel, you need lots of memory
or storage-based application or data. You've already learned quite a bit about the university
clusters, so this question is of course that how do our computers actually differ from those?
And the answer is, from a user point of view, actually very little. The main difference really is in scale.
how many GPU cores, how many GPUs you can use, how much storage space you have, etc.
As an example, in Mahti, or actually also in Lumi CPU Partition, you can, if you need,
you could be running something like 25,000 cores your simulation, or if you need to use
hundreds of GPUs that's in principle available in Lumi. The way you access
CSC supercomputers is pretty much the same as you would access for example Triton, I
mean you can use SSH from your terminal to get the command-line based
access and this is actually I realize a valid point I did not update I think
the web GUI, it's not really as such so new. So in some terms new service, but I mean that's
something we have had already for three years. And I think in Triton, how long you have actually had
that? A little bit, but it's only become a big thing in the last year. We've only really been
starting pushing it for basically the new Triton in the last month. So yeah. But once again,
then something that's also available there.
And I think especially for these web interfaces,
I mean, if you used in one system,
it's more or less same way to use that.
When using from command line,
we also have a module system to selecting compilers
and so on.
And in the batch queue system,
I think most of the supercomputing sites,
only CSC actually use Slurm.
So differences in usage are mainly
what are the partition names and et cetera.
So.
Yeah.
One big difference of course is that
when you want to use CSC computing services,
you actually need to apply project for that
and you need to apply for some billing units
which you could think as CSC money or something like that.
And when you do competitions,
so actually nowadays also for data,
you have a lot of data on the disk
that also consume these billing units.
And it's one way we try to ensure
that the users actually think what they are doing.
It's often too easy.
I mean, I've been there, I've done that,
do some stupid things with the computer and waste resources, so that tries to assure that
users use the resources wise. Yeah, that's probably the biggest difference between
CSC and us. So for us, you just apply for the account, but you don't apply for or account for
individual resources separately, but there's no guaranteed amount available to you. At CSC,
you apply for the resources but there's much more available and
you're much more likely to get what you apply for within a quick time.
I'll come in the end of the presentation what is actually
what is needed for applying this and by the way in the way you you need
to apply for resources comes also that you typically also need
to report something especially I mean when you pre-apply some resources you
you need to somehow report that, what you use them for,
what kind of publication you make, and so.
Yeah.
Okay.
Then a bit about what are the computing,
or what kind of computing resources or services we have.
At the moment, we have two national supercomputers
which are available for basically to the users
users coming from Finnish universities and higher education institutions.
So we have Puhti and we have Mahti.
They both are actually in a sort of end part of their life.
So we are currently
or we have started already the sort of process of buying the next national
supercomputer, probably by the end of next year,
2025 Puhti and Mahtti will retire and we'll have a new system. What that's going to be,
I do not know and something we'll see with the negotiation with the vendors.
Puhti and Mahtti, they have a little bit different user profiles, so Puhti's,
you can somehow think that it's a bit more general purpose for smaller parallel jobs,
having Intel CPUs and some NVIDIA bit older generation GPUs,
MAHDI, SmartWave, Kietow Arts, medium and large scale
parallel simulations. For example, for most of the partitions,
the minimum number of CPU cores you are using,
using that single node, which it's in that system
with the AMD CPUs, it's always 128.
Mahti has also a little bit smaller GPU partition
than Puhti with the newer GPUs.
And what might be useful for some of you
for interactive workloads, development, and so on,
is that some of these GPUs can also actually be
slice the smaller ones so you do not, as the resources is a bit more limited, there are I
think only 24 of these nodes but for purposes where you do not need the full computational
power of single GPU you can get only a subset of that and do some useful stuff with that.
Then, as a sort of flagship, there is also LUMi. LUMi is actually not really a CSC supercomputer,
so it's actually truly a pan-European supercomputer, funding coming from the European Union and 11
countries belonging to Lumi Consortium, but it's hosted in the CSC data center.
User support is not directly given by CSC, so it's distributed to these Lumi Consortium countries,
but if you want to use that for Finnish users, you can access it via CSC
in applied resources a similar way as to Puhti and Matti.
Lumi at the moment is the most powerful supercomputer in Europe and the fifth most
powerful in the world, having over 10 000 AMD GPUs. So it's really a massive compute resource.
There is also a CPU part of that, which still is a quad-signal count, it's around 200,000
CPU cores also there.
Now with all this multitude of different supercomputers CSC has, you might ask, okay, which one of
these I should actually use?
And as I said, it really depends a bit on what kind of satellite task they have, a bit different profiles.
As I said, Puhti is maybe more for small or medium scale parallel tasks.
It has the most extensive software selection available,
while Mahti, as I said, is more for the larger parallel calculations.
duration of your of your simulation in
market the maximum time you get random
queue
and that's also a bit shorter than in
than in Puhti.
And Lumi I would say that
Lumi is really if you have an
application that can really benefit from
AMD GPUs
that's that's when you really should
consider Lumi.
Some projects you might might want to
run also the CPUs but
they do not provide that much advantage over Mahti. Software availability in Lumi is actually
a bit more limited, and talking about the module systems, the Cray module system that is in Lumi,
it's in some ways a bit more, in some cases, a bit more complicated to use than
the ones that we have in Puhti and Mahti, which are, I would say, more similar to Triton.
About the web interface, I'd say this is something that nowadays you can use all the three supercomputers,
either Puhti, Matti or Lumi, and here you can see the sort of selection of applications
within this web interface that you can use, for example,
in Puhti.
I think, personally, I use the Jupyter Notebooks a lot.
That's quite nice.
You can use it in MATLAB or RStudio.
That also might be quite convenient.
And if you need to use some graphical applications using
the NVIDIA web desktop might be also a good option.
In addition to the kind of traditional HPC services,
CSC provides also some cloud-like resources.
They might become useful if you have the operating system,
the system libraries and so on, that are available in supercomputers,
not always the latest possible. I mean the main objective for the for the
system is that it needs to be stable and sometimes you might need a bit more
flexibility. You really would like to run your own operating system or
things like that and for this kind of usage you might want to consider some of
the cloud services. Basically we have three types of cloud services. We have a
a CPoL as a general computing cloud, then I don't know, are
the Antisodius users doing genomics or things like that
where the data is actually sensitive?
Some are. We talked about that a bit on day one, and I think we
mentioned the CSC services, so here.
So for this kind of thing, there is the ePoL, and then there is
also this Pirate Container Cloud that can be useful for some things.
I heard that some of you earlier were
somehow interested but also about the programming.
I won't go in much details how to actually do the parallel programming use.
This is just the very brief overview what kind of
approaches one typically uses using supercomputers and I mean what
you can use in if you're using a CSC. So of course the basic C, C++, C, Fortran, Python,
Archulia. For parallel programming you can use MPI for distributed memory parallelism,
more openMP for shared memory. There are some high-performance libraries and GPUs.
If you're doing machine learning you might be using PyTorch or something like that which is
be readily available in the system or if you want to do the GPU graph on yourself
you might be using OpenMP offloading, OpenACC, CUDA, the HIP. CSC provides also some
performance analysis and debugging tools for parallel applications. So maybe you mention
this later but do you have training for all of these different types of things? Yes, I mentioned
bit of I'll come to try a little bit at the end of the talk.
The technical details I think I will now
skip but I'm in the end of slides so if you're interested you can
you can have some of the actual numbers checked there. You should find pretty
much the same information also from the CSC web pages or user
documentation. I'll include that also in the
presentation. Okay, let us come then to the other
aspect I mentioned that you might be dealing directly with
data or when you're doing the computations
and you're creating data that you would like to do also a little bit
more than just have it in the
in the file system in the supercomputer.
One data service we have is the ALLAS object storage
and you can upload the data from the supercomputer or actually from
anywhere so that's something the data which is in the
supercomputer file system or HPC file system
you can only access from the HPC system but the data you put in this object
storage you can in principle access from anywhere from the internet and you can also have the data
shared to other users. Lumi has actually its own optic storage also which is
it's a physically separate from that so if you you can use Allas either from Lumi or from
Mahti and Puhti. Lumi has this Lumi own object storage, which
similar you can actually use from from different places.
Okay.
CSC provides also some, I don't know if the data findable
accessible, interoperable, reusable is a concept common to
you. But basically it means that you can you can publish your
data set and together with the data set there is also
some metadata and there is also some tools for
searching these data sets so CSC has some services
for example EDA is one such a service that we provide.
Okay, training was already mentioned by [name].
So we have a quite a large amount of training every year in various aspects.
So supercomputing, just how to use our systems, might be related just to Puhti or Mahti,
might be related how to use Lumi,
might be some programming course of parallel programming
or might be just how to use certain static applications like
like Chromux.
There is also possible to get some help if you
have a data set that you would like to visualize.
Something more than just making your xy graphs.
CSC can provide help and for example you can develop your own
scientific application and would need some help in getting more
performance from that. That's something where CSC can also
help. Yeah so if someone say wants to learn
MPI program or OpenMP programming or GPU programming you have these
kind of courses? Or links to them from Lumi or something?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, definitely. Yeah. Here are just examples of
some of the courses we are currently offering. So I think
if you're just want to learn a bit more about the
supercomputers in sort of general level, we have this
online course, Elements of Supercomputing, should be quite accessible and might be
and has been developed in principle for mostly people who don't necessarily have any previous
background of HPC, so it's quite general level. We have also this ongoing online course about
how to use CSC computing environment. We're going to have in the June-July time frame,
we have now for, I think this is now 13th time, we have in the summer school about high-performance
computing. That's a deadline for that has already passed, but that's sort of 10 days
is where you really go through all the basic aspects of how to
do parallel programming with the MPI, how to use OpenMP, how to
do GPU programming. So I think that's something if you if you
think that you will be doing a parallel program, something you
might want to look for in next year, I think that for next year
registration probably opens somewhere in January, February. Some of the courses we
already have in calendar of these hardware formats are in September.
Okay. Yeah, did you have some comment [name]? No, no, please continue. Okay, so all these
wonderful services we provide, so how you how you get to use them. First of all, similar to for
example Triton, you need to have an account and for CSC if you already have Haka available, I mean
you have been using Haka in your university, you can just go to my.csc.fi and with a few mouse
clicks you will get the csc user account. Username will probably be different.
Fast forward ssh keys so that you will be using the DNS cluster but you do not need any
really extra steps other than the account navigates. As discussed, in order to really
get some computational resources and use them there needs to be a project for that and you
one needs to apply billing units for the project and for that not not quite anybody can apply for
the project but on the other hand it doesn't have to be the big processor so basically
experienced researcher postdoc or something like that. I mean if you're doing some research work
there is typically some more experienced researcher that can apply for the project
and he or she can apply for billing unit and with the project the project manager can in principle
add any CSC user to the project. Maybe not so relevant for this audience but just to let you
know that if you're teaching a course and you want to use some CSC resources for that so that is also
possible to apply for a project for that. For courses you typically do not need to apply
billing units. So there is always a fixed amount of resources given there. The duration
is also typically fixed to six months, so it's a bit shorter too. And once a month
you need to then have the CSC account in order to actually use these resources within the
course.
Yeah. And I can say sometimes people come and ask us, oh, what do these questions mean
when applying for resources, but when in doubt, just send an email to the CSC service desk
or even in, if you're that brave, call and ask for details.
And I've always gotten good answers that way and, you know, some solution.
So yeah, it is some work, but don't be afraid.
Yeah.
Okay.
And I mean, when you have these questions, so yeah, we have the service desk.
If you go to our main webpages, you can actually find the phone numbers there, all the user
guides and so on.
You can go to indux.csc.fi, free data and so on, and all the trainings we have coming
there.
You can see there.
So us, the Aalto Scientific Computing team here, we also do, we support CSC things,
if you bring questions to us. So maybe you wouldn't want to for things, but for example,
for using Lumi, our recommendation is to come to us and let us try to figure out how GPU stuff
works there and then you do it yourself. We have people come and asking about CSC virtual machines
or other small debugging things on CSC resources. Okay, yeah. Yeah, that's pretty much what I have
to present and I mean if there are any still more questions or something like that I'm
happy to answer. Let's see, I'll flip to the notes here. So there was a question
where does the abbreviation CSC come from and from Finnish Wikipedia I see it
does come from Center for Scientific Computing decades ago. Decades ago and at
some point I think that was sort of abandoned. There was a time when
Then actually the official name was Center for Scientific Computing, and then at some
point, I don't know, somewhere, someone made the decision that, okay, now it's just CIC,
IT Center for Science, is what the original comes from.
Yeah.
Which is more appropriate these days, anyway.
There's a question, my code is not using GPUs, so Lumi's only beneficial for GPU work.
Lumi, as said, it has also this CPU partition,
which, I mean, it's basically the same type of CPUs
than in Mahti, one generation newer.
I guess whether you should be using Lumi or Mahti
or Puhti in that case is really how...
Is it really just how big and where you're used to
and what has enough spare resources right now?
Something like that, and sometimes it might be just a matter of that depending on time of year or whatever there is more free resources in one supercomputer than in another.
Yeah.
I would say that for Finnish users having only CPU code marked is probably big.
I mean, for Volumio also, you can apply access via this my.csc.dev file.
But for some things, I would say that it's probably easier to work with.
Yeah. Okay. Someone put in the notes here a pointer to the CSC weekly user support session.
Ah, that's actually, yeah.
This is really good. It's like our daily garage at Aalto.
So you can go there and ask questions and join some experts and figure out stuff live.
Yeah definitely something I should add also to the slide something we
we already had for quite some time but yeah that's that's true something I mean there was this that
okay you you can send email and but I mean this is this is a member Wednesday you can just online
join and hopefully be like a low barrier place to ask questions. Yeah and so is CSC a non-profit
organization, or is it a company? Yes, yes. We are a private company, but a special company,
non-profit company. We're actually not allowed to make any real profit than a
sale loan by the Ministry of Education, so. Okay, yeah, yeah. We are here to make the world a better
place, not to make money. Yeah, and yes, our taxes go to supporting CSC, just like they go to
supporting research because CSC is part of research.
Yes, exactly. Anyway, yeah, thank you very much for coming. I
guess UC can stay around in the
notes and answer any further questions that appear there.
I'll just put it in the chat with UC. So yeah, thanks a lot and
see you next year or maybe before next year.
Yeah, we'll see.
Yeah, OK.
Thanks a lot.
Bye.
OK.
So.
Yeah, that was a great talk.
Yeah, very good.
Thank you.
Mostly kept in time, I think.
That's, that's always the difficulty.
So next up is MPI Parallelism, as I just added here.
Uh, did I spell that right?
Okay.
So, um, I guess we're back to the thing, so I'll switch back to my screen here.
So there we go.
So MPI.
So we have, what, 50 minus 10, 40 minutes
to do MPI in GPU plus 10 minutes for break
before we get to the Q&A.
How should we divide this up?
Well, I'd say that let's go quickly through the MPI and then spend more of the time in the GPU
part, because I think a lot of people are interested in that. But I think Jules' talk was
a great introduction to what we are going to be talking about now, because these next technologies,
well, GPUs are used everywhere, but MPI is definitely the workhorse in many of the
the supercomputers, and this kind of like codes are used in this, especially what [name] was saying
about Mahti, which is this kind of like machine designed especially for running these very big
parallel programs, and those programs utilize MPI to do the parallelization.
Yeah, so what's the most important things to know? Let's say you have a program and you
know it uses MPI, because the docs say so. What options do we need for SLURP?
So the first thing with the MPI program, if you need to compile it yourself,
you need to usually use some MPI libraries that are provided by the system administrators.
Because MPI, when we talked about the different packetization strategies,
it's message passing. So a lot of stuff is transferred throughout the network.
So usually these libraries, these MPI libraries are compiled or created in a way that they can
understand the hardware very well. So they can understand the high speed in network that is
between the computers. So that's why all of these like high-performance clusters that have these
kind of like, or want to run these like big jobs, they have this usually this high-speed network
and they have their own MPI installation that knows about this high-speed network.
So when you're doing the MPI communication, the program is literally knowing about the
low-level hardware and sending messages as fast as possible.
in many cases like it tries to bypass the processor itself so in for example when there's
communication happening it tries to like go straight from the memory of the computer to
to the network card and from there through the network straight into the memory of another
computer basically injecting into the memory of another computer without ever going through the
processor to speed up these communications and that for that reason there needs to be it's called
called like remote data management access.
I think like it's the short term, RDMA like anyway,
but basically these kinds of things.
So you first need to find out,
if you need to compile something,
you need to find out the MPI libraries
that are provided by the system and then use those.
Like you need to find those in a module somewhere
and you need to remember to load these
when you're running the MPI program as well.
If you are using pre-existing MPI program
that is installed by the system administrators,
for example, when I used the LAMPS demo on the first day,
I used the LAMPS installation that we had installed.
And in that case, you don't have to compile anything,
you can just use that.
It's same with CSC,
like if you want to use something like GROMACS
or CP2K or something.
In CSC machines, they already have existing installations
and it's usually a good idea to use those
because those have been tested and designed
to use the high-speed interconnects.
But from the queue side, what do you need?
So from the queue side, you need to tell the queue
how many the so-called MPI tasks you need to specify.
So again, like there's going to be more terminology.
it's unfortunate, but because there's differences in the meaning, there's going to be new terms.
So in MPI world, there's going to be these, how many nodes do you want?
Usually you want, if all of your tasks fit into one node, so task is usually one CPU,
but it can have multiple CPUs in the task.
So previously when we asked for multiple CPUs, we had the CPUs per task, and nobody asked
what the task is, but basically that's the MPI task.
So when we are running this shared memory parallelism, we're asking for CPUs per task,
but we're asking for only one task because we're not using MPI.
But in the case of MPI, you want to ask for multiple of these MPI tasks.
And each of these is typically one CPU, but can be more.
And typically, you want to ask for either one node, or you want to divide the program
in a way that it's distributed among the computers in some even fashion.
So in the abstract, there's nodes and n tasks per node.
For example, you would want to have one computer with 20 CPUs and another computer with 20 CPUs,
because this means that then it's more balanced, the job requirement.
Usually, at least in Triton, you want to use srun to run the program because that
tells the program to use this MPI framework that is built into the system, so that the MPI asks
the Slurm, where should I place all of my tasks? And it does this communication layer underneath it
to do it. But in practice, yeah. For most users, this can all be considered magic,
and you know you need these options and that it works.
Yeah, like usually I would recommend just checking like the documentation here
and just using those like values and try to like allocate
like what how many programs you want and try to allocate it in the way that it's mentioned there.
So if we look at the example here, do we want to go through it or?
I think it's probably not needed. I mean, I'd rather go to the GPUs.
Yeah, so the MPI example here is basically just there's like an MPI implementation of the same
Pi code, but it uses multiple processors to do it. And basically what you do is you load
an MPI installation. In our case, in our cluster, it's OpenMPI that we mainly use.
use, and then you compile the code. So, this is C code. So, it's low-level code, and then
you run it. But yeah, if your program uses MPI, you'll know it because they mentioned
it. So, you'll know about it because it mentions MPI. So, if it doesn't have the letters MP
and I somewhere mentioned, it's not using MPI, really. So, try to search the documentation
that sort of stuff if you want to do this MPI programs. And come and ask us if you have problems
with this. Because all of the network layer and that sort of stuff, this is high-performance
computing that basically marries the program with the hardware in a different fashion than
the previous programs we were running. Here we have a much more closely knit connection,
So that's why there's lots of complications and that's why it's mainly used for these
very complex programs that want to run very big simulations.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay.
If you have any questions, then do ask.
For those people who don't want to use MPI, I wouldn't touch the nodes and end tasks.
I would just know that these are not meant for me.
I don't care for those.
Because I just want to use multiple processors.
I don't care for these tasks, things.
Yeah.
Okay.
There's no questions about this, which is roughly what I'd expect, to be honest.
I mean, it's a thing that you'll learn when you need it.
And if you're using it, probably there's someone around you that figured this out already.
If you know that you want to code with MPI, I highly recommend going to the CSC MPI courses.
They are very nice courses. I have taken a few of those myself just to get more information.
They are very good courses on that.
Okay. Should we go to the break now a little bit early
and come back and have a bit more time for GPU stuff?
Yeah. Sounds good.
until 58. Okay, great. So keep asking questions, if any, and see you in 10 minutes.
Yep.
Bye.
you
Hello, we are back for the last little bit.
So GPUs.
So I can say I'm a person that hasn't used GPUs very much.
So my main questions from the next sections would be, if I have code that already uses
GPU, what options in Slurm do I need?
How do I monitor their performance?
And what do I need in my own software or Python environments or whatever in order to use these?
So do you think we can go over that?
Yeah, I think that's a great task list for this session.
Do you want to throw into my screen and maybe I can...
Sure. Here we go. Okay, there you go.
Yeah, so TPUs, this is like a topic with lots of interest and lots of things to cover,
But hopefully, we can get through the most important things in this session.
So what are TPUs? We already talked about it. They're basically the chicken skewers of the
massive parallel processors that do one thing very good. And the one thing that they do good
is the matrix multiplication and that sort of stuff.
So they do that very well.
And that's why they're used in all kinds of codes
from physics to deep learning and that sort of stuff.
And everybody wants to use them because they make stuff
go room, basically.
So when we want the GPUs, how Slurm thinks about them,
how Slurm knows about them, it knows about them
in these so-called generic resources.
So you need to specifically request for these resources.
There's two ways you can do to request these resources.
The old way is the dash-dash-gress GPU one,
but the newer way is this dash-dash-GPUs equal one.
The newer way, if it's supported, I would personally use that because it also allows
you to, like, if you need to do multi-GPU stuff and that sort of stuff later on, there's
other flags that you can use to make it so that you can, like, allocate certain number
of CPUs per GPU and that sort of stuff.
You can make certain that your job gets the correct kind of an allocation.
So the newer method has more, like, leeway on that.
both work so you can use whichever one you want to use. Some clusters have the
GPUs in a separate partition so you might need to
ask for a separate partition.
So basically just like processors and memory Slurm tracks it
and look up your own clusters info for how to request it
and then you got it. Okay that's pretty easy.
Yeah, and when Slurm allocates the job,
it basically makes certain that, OK, you get access to it
and nobody else gets access to it.
So then you will get access to the GPU.
In our cluster, there's also this debug partition
that you can use to debug short jobs, which is very nice.
If you want to do a small debug, run, see that your code runs,
and then just stop it, and then put the actual run going.
Because the GPUs are very popular,
or sometimes there's a lot of people in the queue.
And yeah, let's jump right in and let's start dealing with the actual problems of the GPU
computing or the actual things where you need to, what you need to think about.
So the first thing you need to think about is that the GPUs, like you cannot simply
like talk with the GPU, like you do it,
like you cannot write a normal program with them.
You need to discuss with the GPU
because it's just like a specialized hardware.
Okay.
You need to use this thing called CUDA toolkit
to discuss with that.
So like, because there's so many different like hardware,
there's different kinds of GPUs
and nobody wants to write to a specific like CPU
or GPU architecture.
Like you don't want to write the machine code
only for like certain GPU architecture, what the people at NVIDIA have created and which is
probably the best product, like even more important I would say maybe than the actual hardware
is this kind of like development kit called CUDA, like CUDA development kit that basically
and handle whatever GPU you have underneath it. The CUDA development kit is this kind of
thing that makes it possible for your code to discuss with the GPU. If you have a program
that is like low-level program, you need to compile your code for the GPU.
Okay. So here's an example of a, like, so, so is this like, there's the driver on the
node itself, but depending on what GPU you're using, there may be different driver versions.
So the toolkit translates your program to what's needed for this particular model of
GPU with these particular driver versions.
Yeah. Well, maybe I'll show this picture already.
Okay.
So there's a picture of how the thing actually works.
So what there is in the machine,
you have the GPU connected to the motherboard of the machine.
In the operating system,
there's this CUDA driver.
This CUDA driver can then discuss with the GPU,
but you don't want to code your code for this CUDA driver
because the driver might be updated, right?
Like [name] said, it might be updated,
it might be different.
The GPU underneath is different.
Like if you go into a different computer,
it might be a different GPU.
So you don't want to lock yourself
only to the specific hardware configuration that you have,
a hardware and operating system configuration you want.
So what the programs usually do,
like for example, PyTorch or something,
They don't actually talk with the driver that much.
They don't deal with that.
They actually are written with respect
to the CUDA libraries, so libraries
like Kublas and QFT that implement
certain mathematical operations that run on GPUs,
and then the runtime library that
can be called to, let's say, give information,
is there a GPU available.
So this topmost part is usually specific for your program.
So you have a program, and that program
needs to be compiled against a certain version of CUDA toolkit
usually.
And the driver can handle multiple different toolkits
and then handle the discussion between the program and the GP
basically.
and the CUDA toolkit and the GPM.
So if we look at the example, if we quickly go show it.
So in this example, we are dealing with quite low level
like CUDA code.
So for this, we need to compile it actually.
So for the compilation, I need to load certain modules.
So a compiler and a CUDA toolkit.
So this CUDA toolkit,
I'm now in the login node of the cluster, so this doesn't have a GPU available, but
I have a CUDA toolkit, so I can compile my code with respect to this CUDA toolkit, so
it's linking to that.
And because there's no GPU available, I need to tell my compilation that I need it to work
with different kinds of GPU architectures, so I need to give this kind of a monstrosity
of a command that, okay, build my code so that it runs on these different kinds of GPU
architectures.
So, this is the kind of stuff that usually happens, like, that somebody else has done
for you.
Usually, you don't have to, like, write these kinds of commands.
Yeah, that's a pretty crazy long line.
Yeah.
like you can, there's a link to article about this.
Well, what are these architectures?
That is great article that I always use as a reference,
like to check which GPUs these architectures,
like, well, what do they mean?
So now that we have the program,
like we have this compiled pi.gpu,
we can run it with the GPU.
So basically what I'm asking is one GPU
and then we can run it.
Okay, yeah.
And it's in the queue and it's done
and it's done basically instantaneously.
And because GPUs are so fast,
so this number is pretty similar
that we run with the CPUs.
So let's add like few zeros here.
Okay, yeah.
And let's run it with the GPU and it's basically done.
That's still instant, basically.
Yeah, it's basically like instant.
So this is like a lot faster than the Python code
that we previously run.
Like in order to get like actual some run time,
well, we need to add more zeros.
Yeah.
But this is a lot of work, right?
Like the compilation and that sort of like writing the code
as this kind of like C code and then writing the code,
like dealing with the CUDA.
And most of the programs that use GPUs don't do this.
they are built against a certain version of Huda Toolkit.
And then we just like...
Like they come from whoever else provides them.
They're built against a certain version.
Okay. Yeah.
Yes.
So let's say we have this now, this program.
The second question you asked at the start of this session
was how to do monitoring.
And in our cluster, there's this monitoring script
but because we did release an installation,
it currently doesn't work, but we will fix it.
But there's another way that you can do a monitoring,
which is like going to the compute node
while the job is running.
And this works with other jobs as well.
In different clusters,
you might have a different way of working on it.
I'll add a few zeros here so that it actually runs
a bit longer.
So, you notice that my job is now running, like I have an interactive job running.
I'll open a new terminal and I can use the Slurm queue to check which node it is running
in.
And while the job is running, I'm allowed to go there.
And what happens is that I'm basically going to the same reservation, so I'm using the
same resources.
So, if I start new programs, they are basically taking resources away from the program that
I'm currently running in the queue.
And in here, I can use this tool called NVIDIA SMI, which is provided by the driver, NVIDIA
driver.
And it will tell me the usage or the utilization.
So if I make this a bit bigger.
can see this sort of an output. What we see here is that the GPU name, we have a certain GPU name,
we have a GPU number, we have the power usage and that sort of stuff, we have a memory usage,
and then we have this GPU utilization. This basically means that is the GPU actually doing
something. And below here, we see the processes that are actually using the GPU. So this can be
used as this kind of like a measurement thing that you can go there and check is it actually
doing something. Yeah. So I see it says 100% usage here. Is that typical? Like do most people's GPU
drops hit 100%? No, no. For physics code and that sort of code, it can get to the 100% or close to
the 100%. But in many cases, the situation is that you don't necessarily reach the 100%.
And the reason for this is that quite often the GPUs need something to work on. So if you're
you're dealing with, let's say, a deep learning code,
if we look at this picture above here, this one.
The program memory RAM.
OK, yeah.
Yeah.
So in many cases, you have a situation
where your program, let's say a deep learning code,
it will need to parse a data set or process a data set that
then used for the deep learning process. And for this to happen, the CPU part of the program
usually needs to load data in and process that data and then send it to the GPU for the calculation.
And if the GPU doesn't have enough data, it will just idle and wait for the CPU to
process the data. So what can happen is that the GPU utilization gets low because the CPU part
hasn't done its job fast enough. So it's like, I think something you've said before, the GPU is so
fast it can, what's the thing, resource starvation. So the CPUs can't pump data into it fast enough to
Yeah.
Okay.
And that means that in many cases, like when using GPU code, the actual thing you're coding
is the left part of this program.
You're trying to get, let's say, a data loading system to work so that you get enough data
for the GPU.
And this also means that when you're going from, let's say, your workstation to working
on a cluster, you might encounter a situation where your code is slower again on the GPU.
And you might wonder what's happening. I thought these GPUs are really powerful,
why is it slower? And the reason isn't that the GPU is bad or slower. The reason is that the data
isn't close to the GPU. So often you need to copy, let's say, the data sets to the local
local drive in these machines.
So all of our GPU machines have a local SSD drive there,
so that you can use that as this kind of like a buffer
for your data, so that you can fill out the GPU fast enough.
Because otherwise the GPU will be starving and it won't
get enough data. And often you want to
also utilize this multi-CPU, like the shared memory
a parallelism thing where you have multiple data loaders feeding one GPU enough stuff.
And this is like a whole can of worms. But basically, nowadays, often GPU programming
isn't actually programming on the GPU. You have some existing library that uses GPU or framework,
like by torch and then you have you try to like make certain that the gpu has enough stuff to do
yeah so in the pasta metaphor but if we're in this restaurant we have the chicken cooker
and the chicken cooker can cook 20 chickens at once but we don't have enough chickens in our
restaurant so every time like oh we don't have enough and you send someone to the store to go
buy some and come back and put them on. But by the time they get back, they need even more. So,
okay, go to the store again and come back. And data transfer...
That's an excellent...
Yeah, that's excellent.
And compared to the speed of a processor, data transfer is slow, really slow.
I linked some slides up above that expanded on the kitchen metaphor,
and it was really surprising to me how slow the processing or the data transfer really is.
There's this adage in high-performance computing that computing is fast, but pipes are slow.
So basically, everything that needs to transfer data, that's the part where the stuff usually
gets slow. In the case of a GPU, the problem usually is that the slow part isn't the GPU
The slow part isn't the GPU memory or not even the transfer from the CPU memory to the
GPU part.
The slow part is outside of this picture, some hard drive or something that you need
to transfer stuff to the CPU memory.
And that's usually the bottleneck in this case situation.
There's also a great question in the chat of, do you need to separately reserve a memory
for the GPU?
The answer is no. You will get the whole GPU memory. Let's say I run here
GPUs 1, NVIDIA, SMI. I will just run the monitoring program.
.
So you notice that this run on a V100 with 16 gigabytes of memory.
So all of this VRAM in the GPU, it's for mine to use.
And so all of this memory here is mine for use, even though I didn't request CPU memory
that much.
So unlike the normal processor in one of our computers,
which can be shared by many things,
the GPU is always one GPU, one person, no sharing.
Yeah.
OK.
And also I will mention that quite often you still
need to reserve quite a bit of memory
because, for example, in order to load a large language
model or something, you need to first load it from the disk,
load it into the memory, and then give it to the GPU memory.
So you need to reserve enough memory so that the stuff can fit into the CPU's RAM before
it's transferred into the GPU's RAM.
And these memory considerations are quite important when it comes to these big models
or if you want to do large data processing, you need more and more memory.
And many of these large language models, for example, they might require so much memory
that they don't fit into one GPU. So, you have to use multiple GPUs to run those.
Yeah. Okay. I actually feel like I understand more than when I started, especially about the,
or mainly about the toolkit and the library things.
There's also one excellent question that, can you get an interactive session on a GPU? And the
Answer is in principle, yes, but I would highly recommend not doing that.
The first thing is that for the reason that the GPUs are very important for many calculations,
and they're very expensive, there's internal billing in Slurm that basically your priority
in the queue is determined by the resources you use. And because the GPUs are so important,
and the billing for the GPUs is higher.
So basically, if you use one hour of GPU interactively, you're basically using like 80 hours of CPU
time basically.
So there's this kind of like a billing factor there.
So it will lower your priority a lot.
And secondly, again, like if you're using it interactively, nobody else can use it.
So what I personally usually like to do is I write my stuff, then I run it with S run
or something like that and see how it performs.
And let's say I want to do like a deep learning training or something.
It's enough for me to know that the training starts to know that my code is correct.
And then I can like submit to a longer job.
Usually, if I want to just test it out, I can test out half an epoch or one epoch or
something like that and test out interactively this very short time and then actually submit
it for a longer time and not reserve it constantly because then my priority will suffer
and other people cannot use the GPUs. Okay.
Yeah.
So, was that all the most important things that I had said?
So, let's say there's some existing program, like a Python program, that uses GPUs, I want
to use PyTorch, so what do I need to do to make that work?
Yes, so this is the bane of many people's existence, that what actually happens, and
person in the chat was already discussing like they have a specific case where they want to use
TensorFlow and PyTorch. Both of these are these kind of like deep learning frameworks and some
extra packages on top of it and it's a lot of work to get that installed and getting that working
and that is a complicated thing to do and we have some pre-installed environments but they
they don't, of course, contain your custom packages.
And because it's so complicated,
usually we recommend that people
install their own environments.
In some sites, the recommended way
is to install these environments in containers.
For example, in CSC, the recommended way,
because all of these environments
can create millions of files,
and it can cause some problems.
But the recommended way, usually, is to use these, like...
So we, for example, recommend using Conda a lot, which is this kind of like framework
that can provide already installed, already compiled binaries for you easily.
And yeah, there's a question here.
So every time you want to use GPUs, you first need to load module load GCC CUDA.
But with Python are things you don't need to.
Yes.
Yes, so if you want to use GPUs and you want to compile yourself, you need to load the
development kit.
So basically these parts, this is provided by the module load CUDA.
It provides this part and then you can create your program with respect to these.
If you have an already existing program, let's say PyTorch or framework like PyTorch or TensorFlow,
what you want to do is that you want to install the program and you want that program to decide,
okay, I want the CUDA toolkit that I've been compiled against. Instead of going from bottom up,
you go from top to bottom. You first decide that, okay, I want PyTorch and what CUDA toolkit does
my PyTorch need. And then you let a packaging manager like Gonda decide which CUDA toolkit
fits with the PyTorch. So, you don't start with some, like, you don't basically force
the program to use a certain CUDA toolkit. You let the program decide what CUDA toolkit it needs.
So this is like the dependencies should be declared properly and then it works.
Okay.
Yeah.
So there's some instructions in our pages, in our like Conda page.
We have a separate page for how to use Conda in our cluster and how you can get the corresponding
CUDA toolkit.
If you are using these environments, you should not load the CUDA, because then you have doubled
the toolkits and now the programs don't know what they should be using and everything gets
like super complicated.
You should always have only one CUDA toolkit, either from the module system or provided
by the Conda installation.
There's also a question about MATLAB, and MATLAB is different because it does just-in-time
compilation, so it will use the modules, module CUDA.
What MATLAB does is that when you create your MATLAB GPU arrays, for example, it will just-in-time
compile these. When it needs them, it will compile a code that uses them when it's running,
so it will need the module system once. But this is a bit of a mess. There's so many different
ways of getting these toolkits and basically it means that whenever you want to install
PyTorch, you need to get like a few gigabytes of toolkits usually.
And this is currently the situation, but the reason behind this is that it's so much faster
to work with, let's say, a framework like PyTorch or TensorFlow or something and write
your code in this higher level language, like Python, instead of going to the C route and
writing everything against the CUDA toolkit.
Okay. Are we done with GPU? Should we go to the Ask Us Anything and then we can also answer
more GPU questions? Or is there anything else from this page?
Yeah, I think we are good, I would say.
A huge number of the questions in our daily grad session
are about getting GPU stuff to work.
So if you can't get it, it's okay.
Just come and ask, it's normal.
And if you're interested about this,
we have a course on Python for Scientific Computing
where I've given at least talk about how to use Conda.
So the talks are in Code Refinery, I think,
Code Refinery YouTube.
And the materials are in our webpage.
You can get a link there
or in the Code Refinery page as well.
And they're like, we try to go through the process
of how do you like get the corresponding
like toolkits and stuff and that sort of stuff.
Yeah.
Okay. I'm going to switch to the notes then.
And hit auto-scroll.
Whoever has the dependency thing at the bottom of the screen, can you move it?
Because then auto-scroll doesn't work.
Yeah, there's a question there.
Can a metaphor be made for the pasta example?
for example, Conda, TensorFlow, PyTorch, et cetera.
Oh, and we can somewhat add a new section for Q&A
and maybe the feedback stuff.
My hands are a bit full.
And as you know, cat is the most important thing.
Post example, TensorFlow, PyTorch, CUDA.
That's like, I would say that, yeah.
I mean, TensorFlow is a library that helps you to use the, um,
chicken cooker because it's a lot harder than a chicken cooker to use.
And almost no one goes and tries to use the chicken cooker directly.
Yeah.
I would say that, like, maybe, maybe there, it would be something like,
Like, if you think about, you want to cook the chickens in the GPU, right?
And you don't want, you want somebody to probably, like, prepare them beforehand, like butcher
them and that sort of stuff.
So basically, like, the CUDA toolkit is the person in the store that makes certain that
the chickens are, like, prepared so that you can just buy the, like, the chicken in a way
that you can just like safely cook it and it's not like, it doesn't have a skin and everything on it
and that sort of stuff. So basically like it's an intermediate layer that makes it so that
like you can do the hard stuff on that underneath it. Yeah.
But yeah, go ahead and please tell us, like, all the questions about anything from today.
Yeah.
And also, yeah, like, we might have guests joining us, like, other RCs and other people
from us.
Yeah.
Any of the staff that are around.
You should know where to get the studio info out, you don't need to do that.
Yeah, but for the
Basically, like with the GPUs, it has moved, like the thing has moved rapidly throughout
the years.
Hi [name].
Hey.
So, it used to be that GPUs were like, the only way of coding GPUs used to be that you
write the CUDA code.
So, basically you write C or C++ code and then you compile that and use that CUDA toolkit
to like to use that and then of course people didn't find this like very nice in the long term
like they wanted to do something else on that so they created like many frameworks that that make
it possible to do this kind of like stuff so that you don't have to write the C code the low-level
code so then once you get that into that part you still need to compile against this like
low-level code. So what they do is they compile against this low-level code, but then you run
into problems. Okay, you need the dependencies for this low-level code. They need to be solved.
So, okay, how do you manage that? And then it's like, okay, you need to have these packaging
managers to manage the whole environment. And what I usually think about is that,
okay, what is the version of, let's say, PyTorch I want to install? And then let the guards of the
packaging managers decide what versions of CUDA toolkit I get. The person who decided this thing
was some guy in GitHub who made the pull request or made the build for a specific version of PyTorch.
Some guy in an open source community, most of these are nowadays installed from conda forge,
which is this open source community. Some guy who's interested about this, or maybe is hired to
do this, decided that, okay, I will build my PyTorch with these versions, and then they decided
for me which version of the CUDA toolkit needed to be used, and I will trust them to get the correct
version. I try to give an answer to that rule of thumb whether to use
GPUs or just the other CPUs. Personally, if whatever, well, if there are tools around that
support GPUs, go for them. Why not? You can see how long it takes and at some point
essentially make the decision is it worth waiting for the cpu for the gpu resources or is it worth
waiting for a long time to get the to get your results commonly the gpus are quite a substantial
bit faster but i personally would not start writing gpu specific code if if i'm not really
pressed for time. So, if I need to really start writing GPU-specific code,
yeah, I would need to have a good incentive as in my calculations take weeks and then,
okay, well, maybe it's better to think about whether GPUs could speed this up.
Yeah, and often the first question I would ask myself is that, okay, the scientific problem
that I have in hand, what toolkits and what things are there that solve this scientific
problem?
So, for example, I already mentioned, let's say, Python does NumPy, the numerical library.
uses these libraries called BLAST libraries and FFT libraries that are already existing solutions
for solving linear algebra problems, and they are underneath the whole thing very heavily.
If somebody has already created a library, reusing that library is a very good idea.
Basically, if I would want to do, let's say, machine learning, traditional machine learning,
I wouldn't create my own machine learning framework. I would use something like Scikit Learn
that is already existing and I would just extend on that or maybe PyTorch or something like that
if I want to do. If that's my goal. If I need to start from scratch then the question
like it's like creating a completely new code that doesn't have an existing like mathematical
solver for that. I still would try to look for existing mathematical solvers because
I don't trust that my matrix multiplication code is better than what the last people.
They have done it for 20 years or 30 years or even more. They have optimized it for different
kinds of systems and edge cases and for mathematical rigor. I don't trust myself to do that sort
So, I would trust to use as much as possible from people that have already done existing
libraries.
And if those support GPUs, then it's more for me, but I completely agree.
I think there are a few occasions where the worst product in basic libraries has gotten
more popular than the better one.
The only reasons, well, there are two reasons why that happens from time to time.
is that the worse speed wise one is way easier to use. So usability is a big factor also in coding.
If I have an obscure, extremely fast solver for something, then people might not use it because
it's just too difficult and people can't really be bothered to handle that and the speed up is not
or the speedup is not big enough, or where this unfortunately also has happened, but that's not
so often on open source things, where one site got better publicity. So it kind of got into the
market earlier and essentially covered the market with their product. And also with the GPU stuff,
I would mention that throughout the years, there's been a lot of this kind of situation,
because the field is still like now it's there's already like established solutions for many things
but the field is still moving so rapidly that like instructions on let's say how do you replicate
my results how do you replicate this environment like they can be like very hard to follow even
half year like after the publication. I submitted for one paper that was published like
like last spring, there was published paper
and one of our users wanted to replicate it
and the instructions were already like broken
even though it was like published like a half year earlier.
So, because the field is moving so fast,
so there's this kind of like additional,
additional, how could I say it,
like need for maintenance when it comes to these
it comes to these more cutting-edge technologies. Some of these MPI codes that have been running
since the 90s, you can see in the webpages, they don't have a pressing need to update necessarily
the installation instructions because the technology is so well orchestrated and already
existing but for many of these GPU codes you need to do a lot more like these kinds of usability
maintenance in order to make it replicable by other researchers as well. But it's
of course it's great technology for many cases but you really need to
you need to know if it's worth the effort and the hassle.
Come on, please ask us more questions. We're here. Unless everyone just wants to leave
early. But please give feedback. I see there's about 50 people watching now, and there's
not 50 answers here. Also maybe people could answer in the feedback why would
you not attend this course? So in the past few years the number of attendees
has been going down so of course that could be because all the materials
online and people don't need to attend which is actually a success but we would
just like your feedback, is this, let's see, this is like,
this would be good for us to know, is the material good
enough? We don't need to be here teaching anymore. Do you value
us taking the time to go through it? Do you value the videos
we're making? Are the videos good enough to replace them?
Yeah. And also like what form of like training do you prefer?
do you prefer reading the manuals? Do you prefer like watching videos? Do you prefer these kind of
like live courses where we were like, do you have like averaged talk through of the manuals,
basically? There's a question about, yeah, what kind of, what to do or when to come to Garage
and how much time to spend before.
Personally, I would say
if you have kind of
used the search function on our docs
and didn't immediately find a solution
for your problem, drop by.
That's, I think, or
if you have spent like 10-15 minutes
googling and you didn't find anything useful
Yeah, drop by. That's perfectly fine.
Yeah, the garages, like there was a question, are they similar to these Zoom sessions?
Yeah, it's basically like we are talking with each other about like what we are doing, like
having internal discussions and when the customer drops in, we stop that and then we
ask what the customer wants. And then we try to like,
usually we go into a breakout room and then somebody tries to help you with the problem.
It's very informal and we try to keep it that way.
I think the point with the garage sessions and attending there or coming there and asking
is we might, if it's something that we think, okay, this is already on the documents and
we have the impression we have talked about it for, I don't know how many times, we might
point you to a video or to the resources that are available, but that's perfectly fine.
Yeah, like if you can't find it. Coming in is perfectly fine.
Yeah, like if you can't find it and you come and say hey iSearch is there a
page on this and then we tell you that okay I'll
come back later. Like sometimes people come and go
several times in a day or in the hour as they try to
work themselves some.
Yeah and the overall like the goal of the thing is
to help you do stuff right.
And whatever makes it easier for you to do stuff is, like, if we can help you, that's our top
profile. So that helps keep us employed if we have people to help. So like, yeah.
So in the long term, where do you think scientific computing is going? Will HPC
clusters still be around in 10 years or is there some other solution coming up?
Or is that it really went with a with a simple question to answer yeah like i i think personally
like like there's always going to be like the more the technologies move forward like let's say
for example what has happened with the chat gpt and that sort of stuff there's always going to be
Like the more, the easier stuff gets,
like let's say by PyTorch, like also,
like when we create an interface
that makes it easier to access, let's say GPUs,
or in the case of ChatGPT,
you make it easier to use large language models.
You create more demand for that thing, right?
Like there's more people suddenly starting to use that.
And if you have more people using,
like demanding this thing,
it creates more demand on this lower end side
or the hardware and setting this up.
How does this actually work?
How do we manage this demand?
How can we do this kind of thing?
And underneath all of it,
there's going to be either like a cloud service
or high performance computing service.
But I think anyways,
there's going to be something at the bottom
that is going to require low level stuff.
And knowing about the whole, like the whole onion, like what's at the surface and what's
at the deep end is still going to be important because it makes you, makes it easier to navigate
the whole thing.
What is the eventual queue system?
Is it, is the queue system like Slurm or in the cloud infrastructure, is it Kubernetes
or something?
That doesn't really matter.
As long as you know, like that, okay, there's going to be some sort of a queue and some
sort of an account and I need to run my code in some sort of, let's say, virtual machine
or node or something.
As long as you know how the sausage is made, it makes your life easier.
I think that won't go away ever.
Maybe there will be more of these bigger systems, but I think there's still going to be these
systems.
I would like to also add to the question, is it an appropriate question?
I think the only questions where I would think a bit like, shouldn't you answer that question
is if it's really the research question you have in mind.
We can help you with expertise that we have, and we might actually have someone who has
worked in the field because most of us are originally researchers, but we are not the
people to solve your research question. We can try to help you find the right tools to
solve it, but in the end, you are the expert of your field, so you might need to explain
to us what you're actually doing and what you're actually trying to achieve so that
we can give a suggestion on, okay, this might be a good approach to do that.
But that's kind of, I think, for me, at least the limit of where questions start to not
make a lot of sense anymore for me.
Because if someone comes in with a question about a very, very specific niche concept
of their research field, yeah, it might take quite a bit of time to me to just get what
they are talking about.
Yeah.
There's also a good question about, I completely agree on [name]' answer on the previous one.
There's a good question of what's the difference between Mamba and Konda.
basically Mamba, like we nowadays recommend Mamba instead of Conda for most things. So Conda is this
packaging manager that was originally developed by this Anaconda Incorporated. It used to be
Continuum Analytics, the firm. They basically created this kind of like, okay, let's make
installing these data science environments, like virtual environments easier. Because like
the many Python packages, they depend on these libraries, like, for example, CUDA toolkits and
that sort of stuff. And installing them via peep can sometimes be quite complicated. So,
they created this kind of like packaging manager that can do this. And it, like, got popular.
And then people created this CondaForge, this kind of like distribution channel that people
can distribute basically like a Linux operating system to wherever Linux system you run. So,
you can get very reproducible, well, somewhat reproducible environments in all kinds of
different kinds of computation systems. And for that, they use some packaging manager called
Conda. And this Conda was originally written in Python, and it contains this kind of like
SAT solver that tries to solve these environments, like, okay, I want these packages,
I want these versions. And that was pretty slow. So what people did is that they did what I
mentioned previously. They used already existing low-level SAT solvers that had been created.
And on top of that, they rewrote basically Conda functionality in C++ for Mamba. It might be Go
nowadays. I'm not certain. I think it's C still. But anyway, some low-level code that
rewrote basically the Conda packaging manager. And it's much more faster than Conda when
it solves the environments because it uses these low-level SAT solvers to solve how do
these packages want to. These packets need these packets, these packets need these packets.
solves the environment for you.
Yeah.
It comes down a little bit to the different programming
languages are there for different purposes.
And the additional, if you try to stay
within one of the languages, you might
get stuck with potentially the disadvantages of it.
And Python has done a really good job
in essentially incorporating other languages and making use of other languages being really fast
while python being really convenient so you have things yeah you have things like what [name]
mentioned earlier with numpy that's calling essentially c and other highly efficient
libraries if you would implement the same thing purely in python it would be pretty slow but since
you can just call other functionality, it's fast.
That's kind of the problem of conda here.
Yeah. Somebody creates a new fast thing,
like a low-level thing that is fast, and then somebody creates an interface
for that using some higher level, I mean, like easier to understand language and easier
to write language like Python.
And then people are like, okay, that looks nice.
I would want to use that.
How do I install that?
And then you first have installation instructions that are very cryptic, very technical.
And then somebody's like, okay, I would want this to be easier.
And then they create a packaging manager or something that installs it.
And now you have a packaging manager that does something really complicated, like you
start to have this kind of cascade.
And then there are, of course, alternatives, like, for example, Julia is quite popular
nowadays that does try to be fast and easy to use at the same time.
And there's different things.
But there's this kind of like, usually there's fancy new stuff that is hard to install.
And it's because it's hard to install, nobody can use it.
And when it becomes easier to install, more people start to use it.
And then it starts to get bigger and bigger and somebody figures out, okay, let's create
a new thing.
This old thing is too bloated or it has, it's too like, it's not nice anymore.
And then they create a new fast thing.
And then that's how the circle of software life or scientific software life basically
progresses.
Yeah.
And Python is always there on the background.
Like I like that thing, I will take that thing basically, like I will incorporate that into
my ecosystem.
And they're very good at doing that.
Yeah.
I'm a good Kraken.
Okay.
Yeah.
I take that and that.
give some comments on the overall future of your careers. So there is usually comments that our
courses are both too basic and too advanced. So here we see more people said too advanced, but
it's really hard to give a course that's both simple enough for everyone and advanced enough
for everyone. Because what we're doing here is built on so many layers. I think I've said this
before, but there's like this Linux command line that underlies everything, and then there's like
data storage which sort of fits in there, then there's the connecting to Triton, then there's
the Slurm, and then finally there's your program that you're actually trying to run on there.
And when you know all of these little things down below, using the cluster is not that hard.
But most people starting your career at a discourse, that's not the case.
So you might know little bits here and there, but most people don't know all of them.
And many don't know any very well, and that's okay.
So the point of this course has been to give a big overview that has something for everyone,
but most people do need to go follow up some.
But this also means don't get frustrated here.
There is a lot of new things to learn.
And maybe you want to learn it, maybe you don't.
You have a choice on where you'll go next.
Yeah, I would add to that that, yes,
like a lot of this complexity is like technical complexities that are like for historical reasons
so there's like or like there is a reason for that and that was done like 20 years ago and
something like that like there's lots of like because it's an incremental process when these
things happen so there's like lots huge amounts of like this kind of like okay why Mamba or
something. And then I will give a 10-minute explanation why it's that way. But you don't
necessarily need to know all of that. You can just go straight to the... What we try in this course
also, we try to cut to the chase and get to the actual meat of the subject. Like, okay,
it's not so complicated if you don't care about all of that baggage that comes in these technical
things. It's a good idea to usually look at or try to go through the things and try to cut through
the technicalities and get to the actual, okay, what is the thing that I need to focus here?
Of course, it's complicated when there's so much stuff coming. This course probably is
overwhelming for many people and that's unfortunate because it would be better if the
subjects wouldn't be that overwhelming. We try to still give a condensed
version of the information but there's so much information but don't get
overwhelmed. Try to check what is important to you and your case and
Just use that information for your benefit.
Okay, let's see.
There's the question about using on-demand on Jupyter
and whether things are closing automatically.
At least for Jupyter, if you click on, I think it's shutdown, so file shutdown,
the job will be finished, so the job will stop.
If you just close the tab, the job is still run,
and you can essentially manually delete it
in the interactive sessions tab.
And delete there just means that it calls sCancel,
so it cancels the job.
So it looks bad, like, oh, do I want to delete stuff?
like what will happen, but actually it's a Slack cancels the job, so it's a bit more like, yeah.
And yes, if you click on delete while you still have the Jupyter tab open,
the Jupyter tab will essentially disconnect as well.
yeah
for advanced courses that's probably other people oh there was follow-ups
that I had started writing here what would you recommend people to do next
then we can end we have a page Python environment with conda on SciComp Aalto
I think the path is... I think this is the right path for it. But yeah, this tells
you a lot about installing your own software in Python. We have two other big
workshops that are also livestreamed. There's Code Refinery, which is more sort
version control software testing, like software development, tools for researchers, and a Python
for scientific computing. Of course, that's also live stream. Through Code Refinery, you can find
other workshops, which are by our partners. And while CSC has the big training calendars with
all kinds of advanced things. But for particular pages of SciComp Aalto fee, people should know
for Aalto usage. Is there anything else that we really have to do?
What I would just suggest for people is that repetition just makes better. Don't worry
about it too much about using the cluster. And there's never really a good time to learn new
skills, right? There's always stuff to do. You have a next deadline or next thing to write.
So at some point, every one of us has to bite the bullet and just start using a new thing.
We just have to start. If we want to use a new thing, we don't have to use new things. I still
use the Veeam, for example, when VS Code exists. We get drawn into our own habits, but if you really
want to use a new thing, the best way to use it is just to try using it as much as possible.
In the cluster, you shouldn't be able to do anything that hurts anybody else, except maybe
reserve resources that somebody else might use, but it's not a big thing. So just try using it,
and if you run into problems, then contact us. Yeah.
Okay, should we say goodbye? And hopefully you can use this later and you know how to
find this if there's more. Any final words?
I guess not. Okay, thanks a lot, [name]. Yeah, thanks for attending. Yes, thank you.
Bye. Bye.
you