Hello, hello.
And welcome to another edition
of the Code Refinery Workshop.
So who do we have with us today?
[name].
Good morning.
Me, yes.
I'm [name].
I'm an RSE at Aalto University.
And one of your teachers today.
Excellent.
And [name]?
My name is [name].
I'm a researcher and group
leader at the University of Eastern Finland.
Great and I'm [name],
I'm a staff scientist at Aalto University
and at least when it comes
to Code Refinery I'm one of the coordinators
or organizer or whatever is
the role of that person who
has been emailing you many times.
So in these first 10 minutes
we are just kind of warming up.
and the best thing to warm
up is of course to visit the
link that I just sent as
a reminder these are the notes
that we will use for the
whole workshop now I don't know
if the our faces are hiding
this part of the screen that I'm now
highlighting but basically here in
the top right there's a pencil and
when i click the pencil
this document turns into like
a coding editor text editor and
if you scroll down there's
already some questions for you
where are you connecting from
and how is the weather there and
how are you attending this
workshop it's important that you
test it not just because we want to see
how many people do we need
to crash the server but also
that this will be the main interface
for you to basically interact
with the instructor ask all
sorts of questions and blockers
that you might have
also those of you who are
right now in a physical
room watching the streaming with
others you can also use this
document to ask for questions
although you might have some
local helpers that are there for
you but yes in general
Maybe if I can briefly ask to maybe [name].
So how did you end up in this position
and today or at least this
week the content of the
workshop will be focused on
version control and Git version control?
Is it a tool that you often use?
Have you been using for a long time?
Well, my path, how I ended
up in this position is a
bit convoluted, I guess.
So I did my first degree
was sort of computer science with
a minor in neuroimaging.
And then I did a PhD in neuroimaging.
Did work as a researcher
in neuroimaging, but research
isn't really for me.
So I'm, I've always liked
more helping other people with
their problems, their code.
So that's when they, when the
sort of RSE got a bit
more of an official attention.
And actually, there were positions that
focus only on this type of work
and not be a researcher and
have to publish papers and do
the same kind of work that
I actually wanted to do.
and that was that seemed like a godsend
so um yeah that's how i got here
so um version control well in uh
when i'm i was doing my
first degree my um well it
was a german diploma equivalent
to masters and we used subversion
in the some of the cs courses but
Well, that was just for the
course, and it was a given that you used it.
We didn't really see much
of the actual benefits.
But then doing my PhD in neuroimaging,
and there wasn't any kind
of version control in that.
And at the latest, by the
third year of my PhD, I
was really, really regretting
not having version controls and
having instead this whole...
pile of final version final
amended final march 2014 something like
that um yeah i and then
um actually i still went a long while without
looking back into version control and,
um, only when I started at Aalto
as a researcher and Aalto
has, has, um, their own sort of Git, um, thing.
Um, so I don't know what,
what I would call that.
Um.
then I actually started looking
into how Git works.
And yes, from then on, I've
been trying to promote other
people, especially researchers not
having the same problems that I
had with my PhD code and
not losing their stuff and not
being able to retract what version was
Yeah, I think you really summarized it.
You summarized it well, because
it's really like something that
you learn by doing and during the years.
What about you, [name]?
How did you end up where you're doing?
Have you been using version
control for all your life?
Or more recently?
Well, I would say when I
was mostly writing code for
myself, I haven't really consistently used it.
But when I started playing
more with different ideas, then I
kind of I knew that it existed.
And then I just realized that, OK,
I'm writing something because I
think it's going to work and it doesn't.
So then you go back through the files
and you have to manually try
to undo the damage you've just done
because you just wanted to
try something and that kind of
prompted me to use version control
at least for my bigger projects
and I think that
Actually, I joined Code
Refinery exactly one year ago
with my group and ever since
we are just much more consistent
about using it in my group
because we are doing just
more collaborative work now and
now I really see very much
the benefits for us also and I also
like to use version control, for example,
not just for code, but
for simulation parameters, for instance.
So when I run calculations
that I keep track of my
inputs, also in a version controlled fashion,
it makes it just much more
easy to remain reproducible and
to actually know what you have
run a few weeks back.
And yeah, I think...
yeah this is excellent and
you know you will understand better
what is version control and its power
and i also agree on the
fact that it's absolutely not only
for code if you look at
all our web pages of the
code refinery workshop they're
all built through version control
which makes it also easy
to collaborate fix typos actually if
you find a typo
in a couple of days
after this workshop you're actually
able to submit the fix and then
one of us will review it and approve it
and publish it but we still
have a couple of minutes
before actually starting and so
the two links you received in
your email are the twitch.tv
link that you're hearing us from
and then this notes document
I can see that already 126
of you are editing the
document, which is amazing and
the server is still holding.
And what else?
Are you excited, [name] and [name]?
Yes.
I mean, this year has
been an amazing number of registrations.
We are more than
650 registered participants.
Of course, some of them are
in a physical room, some of
them might rewatch the streaming later.
I made the plot of the
kind of the distribution around the world
and we are covering all continents
and it's quite amazing although
of course most of us are
affiliated with the Nordics
with organization the Nordics so
the presence of the Nordics is
a little bit more how can I
say biased but we are very
happy that also people who are
not from the Nordics are joining this workshop
Hello and sorry to bat
in from the broadcasting room too.
Not just saying hi but
the stream was frozen for the
first couple of minutes when
you were showing those documents.
Don't be scared I'd say.
So when you were saying
things like click here and click
here it wasn't visible.
Thank you [name] because actually
now in Finland it's in every clock
and in Central Europe then
and you can calculate the
differences in your time zone and
so I can officially say welcome
to the Code Refinery workshop
March 2026 edition
I'm [name] from Aalto University
and I'm coordinating the workshop
with many other people behind the scenes.
You can read the long list
of names in the workshop homepage.
The workshop homepage which
you have received also via email
is kind of our reference
and guide whenever you're lost,
this is the place that you should visit.
And the most important part
is the schedule.
So we had a couple of helping session
for those of you who need
that extra help for installing the
tools or for setting up their GitHub SSH keys.
and now today is day one
which will be all about git
version control why it's important
with [name] and [name] who will
be our instructors for the day
before we dive into the actual
you know git details and
running git commands and editing
files and backing them up
I want to spend a couple
of minutes as a welcome
and practical information.
So Code Refinery is a
project, Nordic project and
teaching scientific computing tools.
But Code Refinery is not
just this workshop or it's
not only about teaching.
It's a really gigantic
community of research software
engineers and enthusiasts.
Now some might ask, what
is a research software engineer?
In a way, if you had to write some code
and edit some code, then
you can almost call yourself
a research software engineer.
Maybe research software engineer
do this more often than what you normally do.
but in practice are
those researchers, whether they
are researchers now or maybe
they were researchers that are
helping others figuring out
anything related to software for research.
Code Refinery is funded by the NAIC,
Nordic Infrastructure Collaboration,
and there's many, many partners
from mostly the Nordics.
You can read the list of partners there.
so in one image what is it all about
when it comes to this
workshop well the idea is
reproducible research and reproducibility
is not just something that we
wish to do just because it's
you know nice and clean
reproducibility is rooted in the
principles of research integrity
So reliability, honesty and
transparency of whatever you do
should also mean that someone
else could reproduce the findings
they have found, could verify
the process and so on.
This is a fundamental principle
of science because we don't
want to trust irreproducible findings
or we don't want to build
on top of other work that
doesn't have reliable foundations.
So in general, if we think
of these six helpful steps as visualized here,
the first basic thing is very
close to data management, kind
of getting your files and folders in order.
Then we want to use, you know, good names,
meaningful names from files,
folders, functions, code, and so on.
Documentation is very important.
We will spend some
dedicated lesson on how to
create nice documentation useful
so writing readme using
things like markdown to write
this type of pages that you
see here version control which
is actually what will be the
first week and it's kind of building up
it's kind of like a diary
that you can remember what did
I do yesterday what did
my colleague do yesterday where
are we going what did we do one year ago
so you are allowed to travel
back in time with your code
so that you know you don't
need to worry about trying to remember
what you did and why was
it working six months ago and
then we will focus on
liquid refinery washer we'll also focus on the
kind of what is beyond the code itself
or the program that is run
it's like the computer the environment
that is around the computer
and all the other software
that might be depending and then
the final step is publishing
and it's getting more and more
important to not just publish
the papers and which might
have a method section that explain
what it was that
Journals are now also asking
for a data availability statement
or code availability statement
so that, as I mentioned
earlier, your results are
verifiable, reproducible in a
transparent way.
Now, how this workshop works.
Basically the format is a
live stream on Twitch TV.
We opted for this live streaming
so that we are not depending on any Zoom
or Teams or whatever fancy
tool your organization might want you to use.
The good thing of Twitch TV is
that it's reachable all over the world
and it doesn't really have
limitations on how many people
can watch the stream together.
There's also an advantage that
here in the broadcasting studio
there will never be you
know participants faces or
nicknames or usernames and so on.
For the attendance we don't
track the attendance you can choose
whether you want to watch it
live or you want to watch the recording later.
I guess the good thing of
watching it live is that you
can interact with the
instructors and immediately get
your problem fixed.
All the materials are linked
from the homepage that I
showed earlier and they will
always be available.
They're actually Git version control.
So if something changed, you
can also travel back in time
and look at the materials how they were today.
The recordings are available
immediately through Twitch TV.
Basically, as soon as the
streaming stops, the recording is there.
Then we kind of trim them a little bit,
subtitle or at least verify
the automated subtitles and then
upload them to our YouTube channel.
We will try to have a
10 minutes break at every hour.
Of course, sometimes things might
be a little bit more flexible.
Now, when it comes to how
to ask questions and how to
interact with the instructors.
In the two links that you
received in the reminder, one
link is about this notes
document, which I'm now switching
to the notes document.
and so this is like a web page
but the good thing of this web page is
that everyone can edit it
so it's similar to like
maybe you're familiar with google docs
or this whatever microsoft
word editable where many people
can edit at the same time
it's just that now what i see
here is the view mode so
i'm actually not able to edit anything
There's some information and useful links.
For example, there's this ASCII
picture on how we recommend
to arrange your screen, especially
if you have only one screen
like in a laptop, so that
you could have your browser window vertical.
Now you understand why we
have this vertical ratio.
Then you could have the terminal window
or VS Code, and then the
browser with this image.
But then in the bottom here,
this is the part where everyone can write.
So how to do that?
I scroll up to the very top.
I'm not sure if my face
is hiding the pencil that is
in the top right corner.
But anyway, there's a pencil there.
I click the pencil and
now the document turns into an
editor, a text editor.
And I could answer, for
example, the first icebreaker.
and say for example that I'm in Espoo,
Otaniemi and I didn't check the weather
but I think it's quite warm
plus five oops I wrote minus
I'm biased because it's been minus
for so many months that
it's plus it's springtime
And so you got the idea.
And maybe there's already
some questions here at the bottom.
Yeah, for example, if we miss any session.
So you see, you can
ask your question, whatever is
the question, and immediately an
helper is there to answer.
We have many, many helpers
behind this document.
And in the past, this
document has been very, very successful.
So please write all the
questions or issues you might be having.
The other good thing is
that this document is then
backed up and becomes part of the workshop.
So it's like this live notes
and Q&A that we will form day after day.
A good thing to remind
is basically to always write at the bottom.
This is because our helpers,
it is easier to find it if
it's written at the bottom that
we don't have to identify where
in the middle of the document
is a new edit appears.
But then to also be kind
to our server who is now
at 195 persons concurrently editing.
which I also remind you,
Google Docs allows at maximum 100 people.
So we have already doubled.
But anyway, in the very top,
there's an eye icon that you can click
so that it goes back to
view mode and our server will be happy.
The CPUs will relax a bit
and you can still read what
other people are asking.
And maybe there's also the
question that you would have asked.
Right, so if we finish
this introduction, I already
mentioned this practical setup.
Maybe another practical thing is
that Twitch TV, of course,
they try to optimize the quality, meaning
that they will try to use
the least amount of bits to
deliver the image to you.
So you will need to set
the quality of the screen to source.
This is because then if you
want to read what is being
typed in a terminal window, for example,
you see it much better
without any blurring.
If you don't switch the
Twitch to source, it will look
a little bit blurred.
But otherwise, I mean, maybe
we don't need to mention
anything else from this introduction.
I spent already 10 minutes.
In general, we have a code of conduct.
It's good to respect each other.
If you feel that you
don't understand something or
there's something wrong, you can
write it in the notes document
or you can send an email
at support at coderefinery.org.
And...
That's it.
I hope this was a
clear and motivational introduction
that reproducibility is at the
core of whatever we do in research.
I've been talking way too much.
So it's good that actually
I kept it shorter so we have
more time for Git version
control and questions and so on.
So before I pass the stage to [name]
and [name], is there anything
in the notes that should be mentioned or
yeah someone's asking how to
change the twitch to source
i don't have twitch tv open
here but i think there's like
a like an engine how do you
call those like a like a little wheel
that looks like an engine piece
that you click that and
that's different kind of quality of
the of the streaming so hopefully
you are able to find it
All right, so should we
change the screen share to I think it's Ines?
Yeah.
And I can disappear for now
and enjoy the workshop.
Thanks, [name], for this
great introduction.
And I think [name] has
already teased this quite nicely.
What today is all about is
getting you a bit familiarized
with version control with Git.
So we're in this very first part
and let's actually head over
to the motivation and find out
what this is actually all about.
And essentially Git or
version control itself for that matter,
which [name] has also already
teased about, is all about
keeping track of changes.
So for example, let me try to
zoom in a bit into this example here.
This is a view of a
version controlled file that you
can also browse online.
But in essence, what you see
here is a timeline.
So when we version control
files, we know exactly when things changed,
who changed them, and we
have something that is called
a commit message, which you're
going to learn a little
bit more about throughout the
course of today, that can tell
us a little bit about why
did we change certain things.
And today you don't really
need anything to follow along,
but basically just your GitHub account.
And we are going to
show you everything just in the
web browser to get you started.
But you can actually see
exactly the same thing also in
the terminal or your editor.
So if you're more familiar
with the command line,
or you have your preferred
editor, you're also welcome to explore
that already today via those
channels, but we are going to
come back to those tomorrow primarily.
So you don't really need any setup
for today, but if you want
to follow along tomorrow, then
please also check out the Git
setup for your editor or the command line.
But in essence, you can also
see in this view that you
have the same information.
So you have a timestamp, you see
who has edited something, and
you see kind of what they have done.
And this is what we want
to do with Git, basically.
We want to track changes to our files.
Now, why do we want to do that?
Maybe [name]...
Are you familiar with that problem
that maybe you have done something
and your code used to work
some time ago and suddenly it stops working?
So what do you do?
Well...
what you do is you try to retract, right?
Like you try to get back
to where was it, when was it last working?
And then try to see
what are the differences between now and then.
And then, yeah, you can do
that much more easily with Git.
I think though that this
kind of exercise will be something
that we will be showing on day three.
Maybe already day two.
I'm not quite sure.
But there is going to be
an exercise about the bisecting.
How to find the point.
So we will actually practice this.
We will show that even today.
So you will get an idea.
But maybe some of these
questions you see here or
statements in some cases are
something that if you reflect,
maybe you have come across that.
And it's a very common thing that,
for example, you run some
code, then you change something
and you come back after a
while and something does not work anymore.
You might also, I mean, especially
for me in research, quite often
when I try to run code
that has been published by
someone, it's often not so accurate.
straightforward to know what
exactly did the offers run.
So they might have
continued development and then
you're not really getting exactly
the same results.
And any of these questions
like what are the latest version?
What are you using?
What has changed between then and now?
These are questions you can
quite easily answer with version control.
And that's exactly why we
try to convince you that version
control is a useful skill to pick up.
Actually, when I was doing my PhD,
I had the case where
I had written something and then a few months,
three months or something
later, a colleague was trying to
rerun it and got very different results.
And that feeling of, do I
maybe have to retract my results?
Because we're not even able
to reproduce within the same group.
I wouldn't wish that on anyone.
And the week that it took me to find
that old version and make sure, yeah,
our results still hold, there
was just a change in the code.
And with Git, that would have
been a one hour thing and not a week.
So yeah, that kind of thing.
That's why I'm sort of
passionate about people using
version control, whether it's Git
or something else.
I think that is really
important motivator and that kind
of links also to features we
get from version control.
And the first feature we
want to just introduce by
name is rollback, which is kind of
self-explanatory in a way, but
this is precisely the point.
If you keep track of changes over time
and you know exactly what has changed
and when, there's always a way
for you to go back to a previous version.
And like [name] just kind
of mentioned, she could have
just compared the two versions
and then she would have seen,
okay, there's a change in the code.
And also rollback also gives
you the possibility, of course, to go back
if you changed something and
it does for some reason not work out.
You can also go back to
a previous version and start
over quite straightforwardly.
So having this timeline gives
you a time capsule that just
enables you to start over or
compare things in a
fairly straightforward fashion.
And one other really useful
thing that has a lot to do with collaboration
that we are going to dive
more deeply into on day three
has to do with branching and
merging and we are going
to actually practice this already today.
So the idea of branching
and merging is that you start off a shared base
and then you develop
different ideas simultaneously but you do
that on different branches so
for example here we decided
to add sunglasses and on
another branch we decided to give
that guy a graduation hat and then
if we want to we can
merge those branches together
into basically one shared thing again
And the reason why this
can be really useful now, imagine
that you edit different things
in different files at different
points in time and you want
to bring them together.
If you would have to do
this manually, it would involve
a lot of figuring out
where to introduce changes and
where to copy your code.
into one shared document.
So it will be a lot of manual hassle.
And this is where version
control really excels and helps you
because with this branching
and merging concept, you have a
way to do this fairly automatically
and to bring those changes
together into one simple
joint thing again.
And I also just want to mention that,
of course, this is a
great way to experiment with code, because,
for example, if we decide,
hey, we don't actually like
the sunglasses after all, somehow
he looks weird with the sunglasses on.
So
You can just experiment with an idea
and if you decide it
doesn't really work out for
you, then you forget about it.
So you can, of course,
merge them together, but you don't have to.
Which means if you
experiment with something, it's a
great way to kind of keep
your code clean without having
to basically manually remove things again.
And we can kind of explore
this for this exact lesson.
Let's try to zoom in a bit in here.
So this is the lesson
you are actually viewing right now.
And this is a network
graph that basically shows you exactly that.
The black line is kind of
our main branch that we are
living on and the material we
are viewing right now.
And you see that people
have at different points in time branched off
and done changes that eventually
got merged back into the
lesson you're looking at right now.
And we are going to use
that view later on ourselves today.
And yeah, we've already told
a lot about reproducibility.
The whole workshop is
all about reproducibility.
And we had this story,
okay, if somebody basically asks
you to reproduce something you did a
while ago, or maybe your
colleague gets different results
and you're in this state of
panic and you really need to
find out, okay, what have I done a year ago?
Version control has a great
way of following along with that
and we want to just
briefly introduce you to that blame view.
Let me try to also zoom
into that a little bit so
you can see that better and
you don't really have to read this.
But what you basically see in
this view on the right hand
side is just every line in a piece of code.
And you can see exactly,
okay, this has been last edited 11 years ago.
And then this, for example,
was entered four years ago by somebody else.
So this blame view kind
of dissects files literally line by line,
and you see exactly when
somebody changed it and who changed it.
And that really helps you,
especially also when you're
working with others to make
things really reproducible and
to track potential changes in the
code down to the exact when and how.
And to come back to
the lesson, another thing that
version control gives us that
can be quite useful is when
we actually talk about code.
So have you ever been
in this situation that somebody
sends you code via email and
tells you to take a look
at something like one function
in line whatever in file number
10 of this version of the
code, something like that.
I don't know, but sometimes
this can be really frustrating
and annoying and takes you a
long time to really dissect the code.
And what we can get with
version control is also a way
to help us actually discuss
code by adding those permalinks.
So if you follow this again
to the online version, let me
try again to zoom in a little bit.
So what you can see here
is really just that
I can highlight these exact lines.
So for example, if I want
to point people to a specific
function, this is a way to do
so when you use version
controlled repositories online.
So another useful feature when
you want to talk about code.
But really, let's also talk
a little bit about something
that we have already teased.
So what do we even like to snapshot?
And I think code is the obvious thing.
Scripts is another quite obvious thing.
And I've already said that I
also like to track actually
my simulation parameter files, for example.
So kind of data and input data.
Are there any other
things worth mentioning?
I think, yeah.
Documents, so plain text or this lesson,
for example, is written in
something called Markdown that you
are also using in the collaborated notes.
That you can track quite
nicely for those of you who
know how to work with LaTeX.
LaTeX manuscripts are also
something that you can track.
I think the question quite
often comes up with something
like, for example, Word documents.
It's not so great to
track that usually, but you can do it.
It's just that...
Without any additions, Git cannot
really do that.
Things like the blame view
we have shown that you
know exactly what changed line by line.
yeah also um when you're doing um later
for example um and you're
using something like overleaf um
there are already collaboration
features in overleaf um so
you're basically um i think it's
it's good to decide where do
you want to collaborate you can
use git to collaborate
But if you use the
Overleaf collaboration, also if you
use the word collaboration
things like comments, there's two
places where you do things
and that's usually not a good idea.
So it is usable.
But agree with people what they
want to use before starting something.
Completely agree.
Yeah.
And here we have this nice example
that I think kind of relates to
what you also said initially that you,
before you got back into version control,
that you had this final
project, final, final version tool
and so on, or final March something.
So...
What do you feel like, what
would you tell someone when they
would show you this project
structure these days?
Well, what are really, from your viewpoint,
the problems when you try
to emulate version control like this?
Well, the problem is that you lose track.
You can do version control
yourself by actually adding a
timestamp to every file, but you
need to start it from the beginning.
And a lot of the times,
you won't know that you...
or you won't realize that
you want this under version control.
And your own mental version
control in the beginning.
So this is you start realizing, oh,
I should have version control
this at some point, and then
you start putting your own
sort of naming scheme on it.
And then it gets
a mess very quickly because
we humans aren't all that good
at keeping a scheme for
everything where we don't actually need it.
So yeah, this A, it's a lot of file space.
It's a lot of space on your disk
because you are copying the
same file over and over and over again.
Actually, one point on that, I think
that is also worth mentioning
that really Git tracks the changes.
So you do not have a
copy, but you just have a
track record of the exact
changes you made, which makes
this more space efficient.
And you will not be in three months time,
you are likely not to be
quite sure which version
of the ones that were
before version control, which file goes where.
And I also think because
of these commit messages we've
shown, you can indicate to you
what changes you made.
So when you have this
in the version control, it
tells, for example, okay, fixed bug.
And
for me it's much easier to
then find a specific version where
I know kind of what I'm looking for
than having a timestamp because
without an additional document that
tells me like a readme file
that tells me okay the version
from August 21 was before I fixed that bug
it's very hard to kind of
keep track of what you have actually done.
I mean, it gives it a
timestamp, but you cannot really
search with it.
You cannot really interact with
it in the same way.
And also, since we have
already teased about branching and merging,
It's very difficult to bring
two copies where you did
different changes back together into
one joint thing.
So it requires a lot of manual work,
which you also wouldn't get
from emulating version control like that.
Yes.
There's actually quite an
interesting question about merging
in the nodes.
It's also answered there, but
let's quickly review it.
If you have a merge and
someone else wants to merge
something into the same main
branch, but you've changed the same line,
That's a conflict.
Actually, we are going to take
a look at exactly that.
Me introducing a conflict on
purpose later on to show you
how we can handle that.
But yes, this is something
that can obviously happen.
And there are cases where
you cannot automatically bring
things back together.
So you will be prompted
to resolve the conflict by hand.
So there can be those cases and
that is maybe also a bit
linked to the challenges and
difficulties of version control.
There are things where the
automatism is going to fail
because you have two
different conflicting versions of
the same line and then there
is just no automated way of dealing with that.
Well, that's a great question.
And we will actually demo
that towards the end of the course today.
So you see this also in
practice, how you can resolve it.
And I think clearly we
don't, we're not really here to pretend
that version control is just
all great and simple and
everything always goes well.
And this is actually a
perfect example of things that can
go wrong and that probably will
go wrong at some point.
And it's also one more thing
that you have to learn, but
well, based on our introduction, I think
you have already sensed that
we think it's very much worth
it and it's going to save you
time in the long run.
And it can be also really difficult
and tedious if your collaborators
are not really interested in version control.
So, for example, if they
prefer to send versions,
five different versions of
manuscripts around via email each
and every day, you get a
new one and then you probably
edit the wrong one.
So, yeah, this can happen
and you cannot convince everyone.
to use version control but at
least you can be consistent about it
and control on your side
what you are sending and when
and we also want to admit
that advanced things can
sometimes be challenging but then
again the basics that we are
trying to cover here today
will already help you quite a
long way and you can of course always
ask others for help when
you actually need it or
learn more complex things as they occur.
And I'd say we try our best to make
that introduction to version
control reasonably straightforward and
easy for you.
So you can just get started
and you don't have to be
perfect with it to already be able
to do a lot of very useful things.
So it's just about getting
you over this first hurdle to explore
what you can do with version
control and to just start using it.
And hopefully this course will
help you to get you started.
And I think [name] has...
mentioned another tool for
version control aside from Git.
So why are we teaching Git
as a version control tool?
It's basically just convenience.
It's quite easy to set
up and it's available on
all major operating systems.
And there is a very high chance
that even if you choose
a different system that you are
going to in some way
interact with git repositories.
So collections of files that
are version controlled with git and platforms.
such as GitHub that we
will be showcasing today, but also GitLab
and Bitbucket basically build on
top of Git and add this
kind of online collaboration feature to it.
But there are other tools.
So if you prefer a
different one, details might differ a bit,
of course, but the general gist of it,
the general features are
essentially available in others just
in the same way.
And yeah, without further ado,
I think now it's time to
actually get our hands dirty a
bit and explore something in practice.
So if you hit next in
here, you are going to
this configuring Git command line and editor.
So as said, you are not
going to need this today.
We are just showing you how
to do things online directly on GitHub.
So all you need is your GitHub account.
But if you want to follow
along in the command line or editor tomorrow,
when we cycle back to that,
then you might want to check
out this part to make sure that you are all set.
And if you have any
problems, then of course.
let us know in the collaborative notes.
And what we are next going
for is modifying an existing project.
So in here, you can see this
and we go to the copy
and browse an existing project.
Next.
And I will be
this back so you can see.
So as mentioned, we offer
different ways of following along
and doing the exercises.
And again, today, we will
just demonstrate how to do
things directly with the GitHub web pages.
But if you're already very
familiar with the command line,
if you're very happy with
using editors like Visual Studio
Code, RStudio, for example,
You are welcome to already try that.
But we will demo this more tomorrow.
And now let's say I
found this very interesting piece
of code online and I would like to use it
for my research, but it turns
out that I cannot directly apply it.
I need to make some changes to a function.
Now, how could I do that?
The problem is I do not
know the offers of that code.
So I cannot ask them to change it for me.
And I cannot edit their online repository.
And just to define this
clearly, a repository is basically
just a collection of files that
live inside a directory that
you version control with Git.
And then if you create a copy on GitHub,
you upload this to GitHub,
then it becomes a GitHub repository.
So it's still a collection of files,
but now it lives essentially
on GitHub and you can control the access.
And because you can control the access,
you might just not be able
to go there and modify random
code you find directly.
And what we need to do
in order to enable us
to actually change anything in
the code is create a so-called fork.
So we create our own
copy under our username.
And this is the first
thing we're actually going to
practice today and going to do.
And in order to do that, so please...
For you, use the first link
that just goes to the recipe
book to practice and do the exercise.
And I'm going to use the
one that is recorded, so please
don't use this one, because if you do,
then your contributions might
potentially become visible here.
on the stream and your
names might be visible so if
you don't mind okay but
please please please try to go
with the first one for privacy reasons
that is just easier we are
not going to show that one but
i'm now going to go to
the recorded recipe book at this
point and i am going to try
and zoom into this a little bit
in a moment so here
we basically see our repository,
our online repository for the first time.
And one thing to note in here is
that what you can see, what
it shows by default, this
is basically the README file.
So if we click onto this,
we will see the same text, which is
why it is a good idea to
have a README file if you
put your repository online.
So just create this as a
landing page to tell people what
the project is about and things like that.
But now we want to
actually start editing this repository.
So how do we do that?
And I hope you can actually see this.
Let me zoom in a bit.
So up here, there is this
that is called fork, this button.
And now if I click on
this button, it's going to prompt
me to create a new fork.
So basically at this point,
I'm creating a copy.
under my own username which means
now I am in control and I
can change whatever I like to
change about it and by default
when you create a fork it's
going to inherit the repository
name from the repository you're
forking from which for this
purpose I'm going to just keep
but you can rename it so
actually just for the purpose
of showing let's say we can
We can rename it into anything we want.
And we would also usually
inherit a description if there is
any from the parent repository,
but you can also add this in here.
And in this case, I
will remove this because I want
to copy all the branches and
not just the main branch.
And now let's create a fork
and see what happens.
So now it basically looks the same.
So you again see I have the same README.
We have the same folder structure.
Actually, let's take a look
into the folders.
So for example, in soups,
we have some mushroom soup in here.
Let's take a look at that.
So it's just a recipe for a mushroom soup.
in here with all the
ingredients and instructions.
And this is exactly the same
that we had in the repository we just for it.
But now the point is, hang
on, if it's if it looks the same.
And if you didn't change the
name of the repository, how would
you tell it's yours?
That is exactly what I was
going to show next in here.
So important now is that
you always keep track of where
you are and you can see up
here that this has now my username.
which means I am the owner of
that repository at this point
and I will just show this as well.
So what you can also see now
in here in the address, this
also says my username or
hopefully your username if you created a fork.
So this is one of the important points,
and you can also see in
here that this was forked from
this CIR workshop exercise
recipe book recorded.
And it's important, so this is
kind of the upstream repository,
is what we call it.
That is what you kind of
created the copy from.
And when you create it
under your own username, always
make sure you know whether
you are currently working on your copy,
so you have the right to edit something,
or whether you're currently
actually looking at the
upstream repository where you might
not have the right to change things.
So you can see this here, you
can see it in the URL, and also basically
It would not display that
fork from something if it was
not your own copy.
But okay, now that I have
shown this to you, how to
fork things, I think we are actually ready
for doing something on our
own at this point and going
into the first exercise.
And rather than me just boring you
and showing you things, I
think it's time for you to
explore a couple of things yourself.
And I think we're actually quite good now.
time wise so shall we say
we do still the exercise and
the break together let's do that yes
so exercise will be 20-25
minutes I think 20-25 minutes
for the exercise plus a 10
minute break that would mean meeting back at uh
20 past the hour if
I'm not entirely mistaken.
Yes.
And if you get stuck at any point
or you have any problems or
you just want to let us
know that you are getting
bored and everything is done
and you're just waiting for
us to continue, then just
please use the collaborative notes
to indicate what's happening.
And yeah, I hope you enjoy
doing your first own steps
about exploring all the fancy
things that we have already
told you version control can give you.
And then we see you back 20 past the hour.
All right.
Well, bye for now.
Bye for now.
And welcome back.
And I've seen in the notes
that some of you have been
really busy with the exercise
and some problems came up.
So don't worry too much about it.
We will walk through all
the solutions to the exercise in just a moment.
But before that, there have
been a couple of things coming
up in the notes that we
thought are also worth just
pointing out for everyone and
one question related to sensitive data.
So what we want to stress
is that you can use version
control on your own machine.
You don't have to do anything online,
but Git keeps track of
the changes also locally on your own machine.
So if you're working with sensitive data,
of course, makes perfect sense
that you cannot put this on GitHub.
But that does not mean that
you cannot use version control.
So it can be.
One word of warning here.
If you accidentally put
something on GitHub, it is
really difficult to remove it
again because GitHub tries
to track everything.
And it's very, very...
strongly opinioned about it.
It wants to keep the data
for your safety so you
don't accidentally delete something.
But sometimes that means that
it is really difficult to
actually delete something that
you accidentally put there.
So there is a file called .gitignore.
And if you have sensitive
data like passwords or something
in the same repository, in the
same folder that you have
also a Git repository,
then you you put those
files that are sensitive into
that dot git ignore pretty
sure there's going to be
something about this in this
course probably coming up tomorrow also
when we go through the local changes
but basically git ignore is
really just a file that tells
okay do not touch these files
do not index them do not
keep track of changes that
are happening there so they are just
treated as non-existent for all
purposes of Git.
And I think another interesting
point that came up was about
large data and data sizes.
So indeed, you do have a limit.
So you cannot put really,
really large data necessarily onto GitHub.
You can track everything else,
but also when you have
really large data set sizes,
the same thing applies.
that you might in essence want
to put that into the gitignore
and skip your data.
Was there anything else we
wanted to mention?
I think these were the two.
Those are the important bits, I think, yes.
Okay, then I think let's...
Yeah, let's start with the exercise.
So you should be right now
seeing what the exercise was.
And let's just go through it one by one.
So grow is to commit history.
So we'll do this in the recorded one.
I've got it open in a different tab.
So the commit history is,
well, this time button here is
what GitHub uses as an icon for history.
Never really liked that choice,
but it's what it is.
And this is
where we see the commits to
the main, to the whole web pro.
The question was, are
they understandable, readable?
Are they enough?
What do you think, [name]?
Well, I think some of them
are better than others.
I think generally the rule is
that you should try to
give a short description of
what you have actually done.
So simplify does not really
tell me that much.
I would like to know simplify what.
So simplify a recipe, simplify
something in the readme.
that would be helpful here and
since the question came up in
the notes I also want to
mention that you usually try
to be somewhere between let's say
50 to 70 characters I think
is kind of the accepted
limit for commit messages but you
can have a longer description
that will only show when we go into the details
So if you really need to
explain why you did a certain
change, then keep the commit
message short to indicate just what
it was all about.
But then you could write
a longer description nonetheless.
Yeah, I'm kind of lazy typing.
So for me, it's always a trade-off.
Longer commit message, yes, will
be more easy to read, but
it takes my time now.
So when I'm doing things locally, I mean,
for myself mostly, my commit
messages are very short.
And usually they are like, date
at the end of the day,
not working, or something like that.
But yes, in general, especially
if you're collaborating with people,
it's a very good idea to
make things that are also understandable
Probably also to yourself, you
yourself in half a year, because
you do other things and then
you have a hard time understanding.
Let's continue with the next.
Compare the commit history with
the network graph.
So we have this commit history,
which has a lot of commits
by a person named bust.
In the end, and then a few before,
and then let's, let's compare
this to the network graph.
So this was, I think something
that a few people found how
to find, um, these are actually tabs.
It's not really that easy to find, to,
to see when you're not hovering over them,
but you can, you can change
this and you go to insights
and then you've got the network here.
And then you see, this is
the, this I think is the most recent ones.
And then the earlier ones.
So.
This is a lot going on in here.
A lot going on, but it
doesn't really show the commits.
Why is that?
I mean, the commits by this
bust user, for example.
There's no user bust here.
I think the commits of
bust have already been merged into main.
So if you go to the very
top and that black line, you
will probably find them.
So all the dots actually
correspond now to the commits.
And if you go onto the
dots, you can basically see
the commit message here in the highlight.
And essentially what you otherwise
see in the network graph
are basically users that had
at one point branches.
And then eventually when this
gets merged back into main,
then it becomes part of this
black line and you can see
all the commits in there.
So these are all branches
that have not been merged into main yet.
Yes, exactly.
because main is there.
Right.
Then the next exercise was,
can you find out when a
recipe was last modified?
So let's go.
How do we do that?
Well, let's pick a, we're going
to look at the guacamole recipe
in the next exercise.
So let's, let's look at that already.
Um,
I think there you can already see.
I think you can already see
that it's two years ago, which is, well,
not very precise in years, but then
if it's been modified two
years ago, likely nothing has happened much.
How many changes did this recipe receive?
So let's see.
And then this is the
recipe and then there's a
history button here again, and
this actually now doesn't show
that the whole repository is
history, but just the
guacamole recipes history.
And then, I mean, it
was originally committed in 2024
and then it released one,
two, three, four changes.
Hmm.
Right.
Which recipes include the ingredients?
Salt.
That has also caused some
problems, I think.
One of the challenges is
that it takes GitHub a sweet while to index,
so to actually really go
through everything that you have
put in a fresh fork.
The search might not work right away.
I think many of you have
been facing that issue.
Let's see if you have more luck.
Right, so I'm searching through
the whole repository.
This is what this says.
And then what I'm searching for is sort.
And yeah, well, this is
a repository that has been used quite a bit.
So it has been indexed.
And yeah, so there's...
lasagna, pumpkin pie, mushroom
soup, guacamole, and salads.
Right, next one.
Now we come back to the debated blame view.
What does this even mean?
You don't want to blame
anyone, really, do you?
Yeah, I think the wording
is really rather unfortunate.
And this has been discussed
in the notes too.
So you don't have to worry
that you do anything nasty.
It's really just a
slightly unfortunate name for
basically keeping track of what
has happened in a file line by line.
Maybe we can take a look
at the guacamole again.
Yes.
It takes a while to load for some reason.
Oh, okay.
You see that little blue bar?
Yes.
I clicked the sides folder.
Okay.
No idea why it's so, so high though.
But yes, blame.
For some reason, I think in
Git, there's a lot of things
that could have been named a bit better.
Blame is one of them.
Yes.
And then yeah, things now
it's it's called that.
It's kind of hard to, to
then rename things as well.
So
But mainly just keep in mind
that I guess it's when
you collaborate with others, really,
the point is that you see
exactly who modified which line
at what point in time.
So while it has this negative connotation,
it's nothing but a line
by line breakdown of who
exactly changed each and every line
at a single point in time.
And hopefully it will eventually load.
Hopefully, yes.
This is weird.
I'll try just refreshing the page.
No?
Okay.
No, here we go.
Show me the work commodity, please.
Then we have this tab.
Lame.
And this basically shows in
what user, in what commit changed each line.
What was the question here actually?
Who modified each line last and when.
So this is really basically exactly that.
And it's when you have
really bigger projects where
you collaborate with multiple people
and somebody, for example, edit
a function that broke part of your code.
And this is just useful to know
who might have kind of
triggered changes to something you
might be using downstream.
So you also see who of
your colleagues to, well, no,
I'm using the band word to blame.
I wouldn't say to blame, but
who to talk to, to resolve it.
I mean, you need to know who did what.
And can I actually now
start using those recipes for myself?
Let's see.
I mean, we will get to
this in the social coding lesson
in a lot of detail.
But basically, anything that
someone else creates is they
have the copyright.
So they can say what you
can do and cannot do.
And if they don't say
anything, the assumption is that
you cannot do anything with it.
So hands off.
So what we want to look
for is something that's called a license file.
And now I actually clicked on the commit.
And I wanted to see the
license, not the commit.
and then this is the license
it's put under the whole repository
which is cc0 a lot of fun legal text
but i think yeah there's
a bunch of licenses and as i
said we have an entire lesson
about how to choose a license
what licenses there are, how
they interact with each other.
But for now, there are a
set of licenses that you will
come across again and again and again.
The set of CC licenses,
Creative Commons licenses, is
set of licenses that are
very, very common, actually.
And there's some nice features here
that tell you actually quite
concisely what you can use with it.
What they can do with
it and what limitations there
are to the license.
The common licenses, I guess, do have
that on GitHub that you
get this nice concise overview
what you're allowed to do and
what not, which can be quite helpful.
I think the one important
take home from this is mainly that
what many people get wrong,
if something doesn't have a
license, you might not be able
to use it at all.
So it's a good idea to think also,
what do you want others to
be able to do with code you put on GitHub?
But yes, more on that
in a dedicated lesson.
And now how can we, what
are issues and pull requests anyway?
Yes, issues and pull requests.
So this is the parent repository.
So there's issues here.
Issues are basically, well, a way
to say on GitHub,
a way to say there's something
here that I want changed.
It can be attached to a
pull request or to some code.
You can put links.
But it can also just be
a wish, like a feature request.
For example, last autumn,
someone was looking for Nordic recipes.
And then someone else who's
working on the repository sees this
and then can react, can
discuss, is this something that we want to add?
Is there someone who can do it?
And then potentially
work on it.
So there's this kind of thing.
And then pull requests.
We're going to get into a bit more.
You can see pull requests
for the Paranoia repository here.
And this is basically changes
in the code that someone
else wants to contribute to the repository.
If you think back of that
network graph we have shown earlier.
So while something is on
your own separate branch, it is not necessarily
coming back into the main, if
we think of that graduation
hat and sunglasses thing, if you
want to merge it back in,
this is basically how you do it,
how you get the branch back into the main line.
But we are going to
actually do this ourselves in just a bit.
So if you want to, if
for some reason this was a bit too fast
and you want to read a
solution to the exercises or
reread something, there's a solution
to the exercises in the lesson notes.
And then next, let's click next here.
So the next thing is how to record changes.
If you do want to add changes to
to the repository.
So we've already discussed having
a fork to make changes.
But now, how do we actually do this?
And then there's a bit
of terminology here, maybe.
We have already used the term branch,
but I don't think, well,
have we properly discussed what a branch is?
Basically, a branch is one set of
features, one set of changes
that you want to add to
the repository, you want to
make to the repository.
And it is always based on
the state of the repository when
you start these changes.
And, um, then it can, can
make the, it can, you make
the changes on that branch.
And then, um, the important bit is
that you can merge a branch
back to a different branch.
There always is one branch
that's usually called the main
branch or sometimes the master branch.
And that's the, well, the, the, the.
ground truth, let's call it like that.
Any other branches you can you
can use but you don't you
actually, how often do you use?
If you if you're just working for yourself?
How often do you make separate branches?
I've actually gotten into the habit
that for every feature I'm
adding, I'm working on a separate branch
and I'm merging that back
into main because I have
usually multiple research projects ongoing.
And it's just for me when
I'm jumping from one to
another that some things are in progress.
a not very optimal state and
it might just otherwise break kind
of the main functionality of the script
so while a feature is
in development I actually try to keep
that really on a separate branch
even for myself because I
found it easier for me not
to sort of break working code
somewhere in the middle
So I can still use the
script prior to the changes
and my colleagues can still use
the script, but I'm messing around
sort of on a different branch.
I have adopted this quite
consistently, I'd say.
And I think one reason why I
like to do it is
especially when I'm experimenting with
an idea, of course, I could
always just go back.
But it's much easier to
delete an entire branch when
things don't work out than
basically always reverting back in history
and then starting over from
some earlier version of your main branch.
So I just find it more convenient.
It's also psychologically a bit easier.
It's like a piece of scrap
paper that you do some changes on.
And then if you like
them, you can basically copy
all those changes back into your main document.
But if you don't like them,
well, you throw them up and throw them away.
That's a really good way of viewing it.
Yeah.
Whereas if you make changes
in your main document, even if you know
that you have a copy
before, it's somehow less easy to
let go of it, I think.
There's also one thing
maybe worth mentioning at this point
that when you collaborate with others,
even if you have the rights
to change a repository, you
can basically prevent users
from committing directly to main.
So depending on whom you're working with,
they might actually actively
prevent you from directly changing
anything in Maine.
And then the only way to
do this is to create a
branch and operating on that branch.
So if you ever want to
contribute to bigger projects, it's
also a good idea to play with branches
and get the hang of it for that reason,
because you might not even
be able to change something directly in Maine.
And I think most of the
time, the reason is that if
you change something on Main and
you end up in a state
where you're breaking things, other
people who are working on Main
as well or who are using Main
are going to be not happy.
So yes, that's a bunch.
And then there's...
I think we discussed what
a commit is, right?
But quickly, a commit is
basically any, any, um,
snapshot of a change that you
want to add to the tracking.
Basically, maybe just worth
mentioning, Git will keep track
of all the changes you're doing,
but you can only go back to
a point in time that
you have actively committed, and
that you have attached a message
to to say, okay, bug fix,
for instance, then you can go
back to that version.
While it keeps track of all changes,
but you cannot hop easily
to anything that you haven't committed.
So this is sort of when you decide, okay,
I want to snapshot now, then
you can go back to it.
And then there's the concept
of a tag, which we will use a bit later.
I think basically a tag is
like a name you give to a specific commit.
If you say you have a version
that you have used in the paper, you can,
with the tag, you can label
this commit as, this was version
used in paper XY.
Yeah, and I think the important thing
when you do this, but you will see this
for yourself in a bit, is
that it actually stores really
a version, a copy of your
code at that exact time.
And that's why it's really useful
if people do that and if people take,
okay, this is what you use
to create a poster or this is
what you use to submit that particular paper,
then it's also good for you
because you can go back to
the exact state of the code.
Very easily.
So you don't have to remember, okay,
it was like May two years ago
that I prepared that, but
you can just click and search by the tag.
And yeah, add that sticky
note to remind you in essence
that this is the exact version.
But I think we are going
to explore that now in hands on.
So I think the first bit
is to explore a bit the branching
and so how you create a branch and everything.
maybe would it be a good idea
for us to actually show people
how they can create a branch
so they have an idea to get started
and then anyway it's almost
time for the lunch break so
we can show that before lunch yes so um
on the main GitHub interface,
if you're on the repository,
the first page, basically, you
can have, you're told which
branches is showing up here, right?
Where it says main.
So the
The base branch for this
repository is called main.
Can I actually now go and
create a branch directly on this recipe book?
No, you can't.
Likely.
So actually, I already forked this one.
So let's go to my forked version.
This is kind of important for
you to now make sure that
you are doing this exercise on
your own fork and not
on the upstream repository.
So our repository, because you
will not have the right to
actually operate on it.
So now, as [name] pointed out, we're not,
no longer on this CR
workshop exercises recipe repository.
So this is not, we're, if we
go to my own fork of it
now, [name], that's my account.
I'm owning this part.
And then I have here.
a main branch, one where I
try to add a recipe and
all branches from the main repository.
And if I go to and those
are the sort of the quick selection,
but if I go to view all branches,
It takes a while.
Okay.
Hopefully you can see it now.
So this is the list of all the branches.
And then there's at the top,
there is a button, new branch.
And then let's call it add.
Let's see.
Then I would have to,
there's options to where I want
to source the branch from.
I want my own domain in there.
And then I can create a new branch.
Now, I have two questions for you.
Number one.
Does it matter what I name my branch?
Like, for example, if I
don't really know what I'm going
to do with the branch, is it
bad if I just call it, I don't know, IP branch?
Well...
Maybe I can kind of answer my own question.
So number one, you can
always rename a branch if you so choose,
if you just want to leave
an indicator of what you're
actually doing in the branch.
And number two, it's much
more important what you do in
terms of commits and how you
basically then try to put the
branch back into main if you
so choose and the descriptions
you write there, they will be visible.
And it will show your branch name,
but it's not so critical if
you have used an unfortunate
name for your branch that doesn't
tell you what you do on the branch.
So for other people, it doesn't matter.
It might just help you to
remember what the branch was
supposed to be about.
And then the other thing,
you know, said that you branch off main.
So can we actually, what does that mean?
Like, could we branch off something else?
Well, yes, of course, you
could basically, if you wanted
that, you could branch
a test, you could actually branch off,
for example, my spice nuts
recipe branch and create a
branch of the branch.
At some point, it gets confusing.
Yeah, so I wouldn't do that very often.
I agree, don't really create
an entire forest with that.
But just to mention that
if you made changes on a
branch and then you suddenly realise, hey,
there's something else I would
like to try based on this
branch that has not been
committed to Maine because you're
not really done with an idea, it is possible.
I would also agree that I
try to keep it like pretty much
one branch at a time.
But just to say, you can
also kind of inherit changes
from a different branch, even
if they haven't been merged back into main.
Okay, cool.
So maybe one thing, when you go back here,
just to mention, let me
show the overview one more
time of the repository.
Yeah.
Just the overview of your repository.
So just to mention that when
you now go to that menu that
says main, you can also
directly create branches.
So if you would into that
box, enter a name of a
branch that doesn't exist, it
will also prompt you to create a branch.
So that's the other alternative
that you can basically do.
And then you click here.
No, we are on GitHub.
You don't really have to
usually do anything.
You will immediately land on
the branch you have just created.
That may be different depending
on the environment you're using
in some editors, but just always
good to check that you're
actually on the branch you want
to work on before you do changes.
But hey, I think we have
at least given people an idea
how to create branches.
So maybe we are quite ready
to try that out in practice.
However, it's almost time for lunch.
I think, shall we say,
that we're actually entering the
lunch break and then have
people try creating their own commits
and branches after lunch or
before lunch, depending on your preference.
That sounds like a sensible plan.
So we would be meeting
back again, what, about Tuesday?
20 past the hour one hour lunch break
and 20 minutes exercise makes
quarter past I think at least
according to my talk okay and alright
since it's exercise and break
together you can pick whichever
order you feel best um
Yeah, we try to keep an eye on the notes.
So if you get stuck or
have any issues, we'll try to
be there and help out.
But again, we're also going
to show the exercise then after the break.
Yes.
All right.
Well then, bye for now and
see you in just over an hour.
See you.
Right, hello from us in the recording room.
This is just a quick reminder
that we are at the moment
on an exercise session.
You're supposed to be doing
the exercise practice creating
commits and branches.
And we will actually start
the teaching again in 15 minutes.
The first thing we will do is,
as we did before the
other exercises, to walk through
the exercise and see what
our solutions would have been.
But yes, if you have been
listening to the stream for
the whole day already, don't
let me interrupt you.
But if you've just joined us now, welcome.
And you are very welcome to
try your hands at the exercise.
There's a link to the exercise
in the notes document.
Just scroll up a little from the bottom.
There's a box that you can find.
And if you haven't got the link to,
or if you don't know where
to find the link to the
notes document, that should be in
an email you have been sent.
Either this morning or lately, anyway.
Okay.
So bye for the next 15
minutes and see you in 15 minutes.
Bye.
And welcome back after the lunch break
and hopefully you have
practiced creating commits and branches
a bit and we will walk
through the exercise in just a moment but
Before we go there, there
has been one rather interesting
question in the notes that I'd
like to pick up on first.
So somebody has asked, how can
you save a change without it
being a new commit?
Because I talked about that earlier
and now I think our
learners have learned that I
don't usually actually do any
changes on GitHub because in
fact it's not really possible there.
But I thought it might
be worth mentioning that
and actually addressing.
So when, [name], what do you think?
When would you actually use
GitHub for doing changes?
Would you use it at all for anything?
Well, very, very rarely.
Sometimes I just browse a repository
and if it's just a typo or something
that I just spotted, I don't
really want to go through the
hassle of opening my local copy and everything.
I'm just there.
Then maybe I use modification
of the file on GitHub directly.
But it's so much more
convenient to have all the tools
that I need for my coding,
like my linter and everything.
That is highlighting certain
syntax conventions for those of
you who do not know what linting is.
So basically all languages
come with certain conventions and
that's just helping us to keep
track that we actually obey the conventions.
Yes.
Yeah, no.
I don't actually, I look
at the repositories, I look at the code,
I might decide this needs a fix
and this needs a fix
and obviously there's the issues
and the pull requests that I need a look at.
But for actually modifying a file, very,
very, very, very rarely outside
of this course,
Yeah, I completely agree.
And it's the same thing for me.
So we think that it's useful
if you know how to see
certain things, how to explore
a repository that you might find online.
But I think for larger
changes, you might really want
to more diverge to the local copy,
which we are, of course, going
to cover in depth tomorrow
with hands-on exercises.
And there, that difference applies.
Save changes to a file, but
they are not actually committed at this point.
And then something that is
called staging comes into the mix.
So you decide when save
changes are actually joined into a commit.
You will see all that tomorrow.
But just to say on
GitHub, that's not really possible.
But this is really coming
from working with local copies that you will...
you will get to see and
hear a lot more about tomorrow.
But now, nonetheless, let's get
our hands back to actually
working with commits and branches.
So how do we do that?
As promised, let's walk
through this exercise that we gave you.
So we've already discussed how you see
that you're on your own fork
and how to create a branch.
So I'm just going to go
here to my own repository.
I've got...
a few branches now, but let's
go to the branch where I
actually added a recipe.
And since this is on GitHub,
it is now, it's already committed.
On my IDE, it would most
likely just be saved and I
would now be, have to remember,
oh, I haven't committed this yet.
And would have to commit it manually.
But yes, so in the slides,
I added a recipe for some nuts with spices.
Then we want to actually modify this.
So let's edit this.
So it's
It's called spicy nuts, so
maybe we could add a little
bit of chili or something, right?
Chili sounds good.
Perhaps.
Maybe a teaspoon of chili powder.
What do you feel about curry?
Hmm.
This is actually something that
I wouldn't add to that mix
because the paprika and the
curry wouldn't match.
But maybe you could add
variants or something.
Let's add it like that.
Then we commit the changes.
And now, because we're living
in the day and age of
everything gets suggested for you.
No, I didn't actually add
the cooking method.
I think this also shows
one important thing about
auto generating commit messages with copilot.
It can be a very nice time saver,
but it's a good idea to check
that this is what you
have actually done, or it
might also get misleading.
And now you also see what
[name] is typing right now is
exactly what I mentioned earlier.
So you have a short commit message,
but if you want, you can
add this extended description.
So if it's something that
you really feel you should explain
how you arrived at a certain bug fix
or explain what motivated you
to do a certain change, then you can do so.
And that is also visible in the views
when you go to the details
or you hover over commits, then
you can see those explanations.
I hate typing.
And then I want to commit to this branch.
Maybe also one... Oh, okay.
Cancel.
Okay, now we can do this again.
Then maybe one thing just
to mention what it suggests here conveniently.
So if you ever change something
and you forgot to create
a branch on something where
the main branch might be
protected, then you can also use
that to create a new branch
for it at that point before you commit.
Hmm.
Okay, so it did actually
commit your changes.
Interesting, yes.
Okay.
I think we have just experienced life
that sometimes version control
can do unexpected things.
I don't see why it wouldn't
be able to just fast forward though.
It probably really somehow was
just slow internet and the
change wasn't properly registered by
the time that we tried again.
I just went to the wrong place.
Let's see.
But yeah, so hopefully you
have all managed to add
recipes and change recipes and
you haven't run into similar glitches.
And if you did, you had the patience to.
So now can we maybe... Yes.
So we have this changed now.
Let's see whether it's actually...
And it has to be.
Yes, okay, there it is.
Yes.
And now at the moment, yeah,
it has the chili powder and
it has suggested to use curry.
Curry, yes.
Yes.
Okay.
Now we wanted to switch to
the main branch and modify a different recipe.
Yeah, now you see that.
The page does it.
right now because it tries to
go to the same recipe but
the spiced nuts don't actually exist
on the main branch yet so um
what shall we do maybe we
use the guacamole that we already
saw and who on earth puts cilantro in guacamole
My kids would murder them.
Yes, that seems a bit odd.
So maybe we want to say
that either we remove it or we
say that only if you like it.
Optional.
Very good.
Okay.
Oh, that is actually a good one.
And we don't really need
an extended description for this.
Let's commit this directly.
Excellent.
So now we can see if
we can actually find our own commits.
You mean compare them?
Well, we can first see if
it shows them in the network graph.
This seems to be something
where some people had issues
that the network graph wouldn't
really update for them.
And I'm afraid the only thing
we can say is that you
might sometimes need a bit of patience there.
So that can really happen
that the graph just doesn't seem
to update and you will not
see your own commits.
And then if you come back
after a while, you can...
but in this case it looks
like it was uh friendly and
we can actually see it yes yes
so how do i compare them apart
from no there are a couple
of different options uh
One is, for example, that
you really just after recipe book
or like your clone, you add the slash compare.
And that brings you to the
view where you select what you want to compare.
So maybe let's try and share that first.
Nope.
still has the commit it
has to come directly after record it
and then you okay so we
want my repository and the main um my
Yes, it's okay.
Your comparison point is now your own main.
So there's no difference between
your main and your main.
Just updates first.
Okay.
And then...
But now here we can really
see the two commits we made.
So we edit.
Actually, [name], edit that
before showing you that recipe
for the spiced nuts.
And then we modified it together.
And you can see the
file which changed below and
also the two commits.
And then maybe one other thing
what I think you were after initially.
So this cryptic
hash so this cryptic mix of numbers
and characters you see there
next to the box with the two squares
that is a unique identifier of
that exact commit and you
can basically also use the compare
in the same fashion
with specific commits so you
could copy that commit and
then it's it's basically just
writing slash compare then
your comparison reference three dots
and then what you want to compare it to
I'm actually not, not sure is there a,
like a, a nice gooey way to,
to get to the same thing.
There probably is.
And that's just showing the, so
this is the first commit in
the, we were seeing where it created the recipe.
And as you can see, it's
hasn't got any curry or chili.
which we had before.
Let me see if hitting the
back button gives it.
Yeah, now we have it back.
Yes, now we have that.
That's both of the commits together.
I'm a bit confused why it's
not showing the differences in the
in the file that we just
committed to the main branch.
Just remember that we, that
I committed... Yes, true, you actually edited.
But wait, no, we are
comparing your spiced nuts branch
against main, not the other way around.
Ah, so it's only showing additions?
I think it might.
So what happens if you swap those?
If you would change the base
now to the spiced nuts and
try to... And now against main.
Yes.
Yes, okay.
So basically it does matter
which is your base for the
comparison and which is the one you compare to.
But yeah.
I think people have had
some issues finding that comparison
and I really don't know if
there is any straightforward way
to find that via Vigui.
So I think what I'm aware
of is really just adding the
slash compare to the URL and
then this gets you to the
page where you can select things.
So that's what we are seeing right here.
Well, you can compare if you
go to the pull request.
Let's try not to get into that just yet,
because we're going to cover
that with the next exercise.
Okay, so maybe we can check
out renaming a branch.
So what if, as hinted at
earlier, I used a really stupid
generic name for the branch, but
now I would like to indicate.
But actually, instead of adding recipe,
this is the one where
I'm adding spiced nuts.
So make it a bit more descriptive.
How do I do that?
Actually, not quite sure how
to do that.
I never do this kind of thing.
You should be able to, I
think we might just not be
able to see it because it's
right on the right hand side,
like off your screen share next
to the delete that we still
see should be three dots.
Yeah.
Right here.
And if we click on those,
then it should offer rename branch in there.
I think then yeah well then too
so then the last thing that
has also been asked creating text
so can you maybe show us
what texts are all about this
may be also something that feels
a little bit scary when you
do it the first time and you haven't seen this
So the moment we don't have any.
So maybe can we just try to add one?
Yes.
So it's March 2026.
Just hit enter.
I did.
Let's see.
So apparently we first have
to create a release and this is
the thing why I said it may feel scary at first.
That a release doesn't really
do anything bad or anything
strange or weird or dangerous.
It's basically just saying
that, okay, right now we want
to, for some reason...
create a kind of copy that
we can always come back to.
And one thing that you will
see in a moment is that
when you create a release,
it will actually create a copy
of your code at this exact version
and zip it up for you.
And you always have to create
a release in order to tag
things in that fashion.
And you say here publish, but
if you had a repository that
only you can see, so it's
private, that does not mean
that you actually publish it.
It will just at this point
then do just that.
It will...
basically archive the source code
so you could always download
the exact code version at that point
and now if you go back to
the main page I think then
we could actually see that tag there
and we could essentially always
come back to that version and
you also now see that in
the releases on the right hand side.
So the point is publish
really just means that, okay, now
it builds the release, it packages up the code,
but it still does not mean
that on a private repository,
you're now suddenly publishing this
for the world to see.
Yeah.
Right.
So these are tags and yeah, that is that.
I think that should pretty much.
cover everything.
And yeah, I think the exercises Yes.
I'm creating time.
Right.
So
We have gone over and
practiced creating a branch.
We have done at least some
changes on the branch.
We have committed changes to
the branch through the GitHub page itself.
We have discussed that when
you're working on your local
copy, there might is a
difference between saving and committing.
and you need to
consciously commit something.
Always forget that.
We have looked a bit at the network graphs.
We have also discussed
and mentioned earlier on at
least the gitignore as a file.
And then this one thing that is
entirely irrelevant at the moment.
But once you're on the command line,
if you're ever unsure, where am
I in my Git repository?
Git status is your friend.
When I'm on the command line,
I use Git status about every
quarter of an hour, I would say.
Because it tells you, is
there anything to commit?
Are there any updated files
that haven't been staged or committed yet?
And on what branch are you?
And that kind of thing.
But I think we will see
more of that tomorrow.
Tomorrow.
Yeah.
Right.
Let's continue to the next lesson.
Okay.
Next here.
And the next thing will be
to merge the changes back into.
The main branch or back
into the repository came from potentially.
So.
like committing is taking
a snapshot, merging is taking
the changes from that snapshot
and integrating it with the main line of code.
we think back of the intro
to to branching we had
earlier now you're actually
bringing the sunglasses into the
main branch and you bring
the graduation hat into the main branch
and then it had the hat
and the sunglasses and this is
kind of what we are now trying to do
And so how exactly can we do that?
So you have now created
your mixed nuts recipe.
So let's say you would want
to have this show up in
your main, how would you do that?
Well, so on GitHub, the way
to get things merged are full requests.
So if you have a branch,
And this is not mine.
This, this is mine.
Um, say you have a branch
like the mixed nuts, then you
go to pull requests and then
it might or might not.
And there's a new pull request
and what the pull request does is
We select, we do not want to
go back to the original fork repository.
We want to have the main
and we want to merge the
new recipe into the main.
Then you get the
This is now important for you
when we let you go to the exercise
and try it yourself, make sure
that you are actually selecting
your own main as the base
and not the upstream one
because otherwise you will not be
able to merge the pull request.
And then
Also, this is a bit, usually
I am thinking I want to merge
from my branch to the main, but
the way it is thought of in
GitHub is you're on the main
and you want to pull things
into it, which is why it's
called a pull request.
But that's why where you
put things is first and then
where it comes from is second.
Yes, I find that a bit unintuitive,
but it's just one of the
things that you need to know,
and then you can try to remember it.
Yes, so then we can create a pull request.
So if I create a pull
request now, does that actually just
Put the changes in there or... No,
the pull request is actually
not going to do anything but show
up in the tab you have up
there that says pull requests.
So if you just hit the
button, you will get a
notification that there is a
pull request, hopefully.
Let's see.
At some point.
It's slow today.
Ah, there's a one now.
And the reason why it's
a two-step process is actually
kind of exactly what we mentioned earlier.
So you may not necessarily be
able to do anything with
that request yourself because you
might not be the owner of
a code repository where you
submit the pull request.
And kind of a pull request just means like,
okay, I would like to
merge the sunglasses into the main branch.
And then it depends, basically,
if you're collaborating with someone else,
if this is actually
your repository, whether you can
now approve the pull request
and actually do the merge.
So it's always this two step process.
We first create the pull request.
Now we can have a look at it, actually.
And now, for example, if [name]
and I were collaborating on
this, she could ask me to take a look at
that pull request and make
sure that I approve the spy
stats recipe before we hit
the merge button here.
So when you work with code,
you will cover this a lot
more on day three, the collaborative Git.
But this is essentially the
point where people can work together.
So at the moment I
haven't actually, because it's so short,
I haven't really given the description,
but in a, in a normal,
um, normal pull request where
you're working with other people, you would,
in addition to the commits,
you would give a short
description of what's this about?
Why would you want to, why
would we want to add this to the main code base?
Yeah, exactly.
And then people can add comments.
Um,
Right.
I think that's the bit of the background.
I think that gives you
everything you need to know
in order to actually try this yourself.
So now we've got 20 minutes
for you to try your hands
at actually merging whatever your changes were.
Should we actually say that we
are going to have also a
10-minute break again and then
20 minutes of exercise?
So that would make it...
20 past the hour.
Yeah, 20 past the hour.
Let's come back 20 past the hour.
Again, break and exercise.
If you're faster than the
20 minutes with the exercise, you
can be happy that you've got
a slightly longer break.
But if you find that you
are running out of time...
There's a solution there and
don't skip on the break.
And let us know that
you were struggling because we
are really happy about any kind of feedback.
Also let us know if you
find this really, really easy.
We're also trying to answer
any questions and problems in
the notes document, and we
will walk through the solution
to this exercise just like before.
Okay, I think that we see
you back 20 past the hour.
Okay, bye for now.
Bye.
And welcome back from the
break and the exercise.
So hopefully there haven't been
too many problems with merging
branches and doing pull requests.
And I think [name] has
already nicely demonstrated the gist of it,
but let's just nonetheless go
through the exercise together briefly.
So I'm going to switch to this tab.
And this is now my own
repository that I prepared for you earlier.
So you remember [name] has
created that nice spiced nuts recipe.
I have done something different.
So just to show right now,
we're on my main branch.
And I have created another
branch called pepper soup.
And if we go in here on
my branch, we now have a new
recipe in here that I have added.
So just that you're in line with me.
This is basically what I have done earlier.
So right now you can see
that this same Zoop does not
exist on my main branch yet.
So the first thing I'm again
going to do is that I go
on this new branch with the new Zoop
and in here I can choose
to start a pull request
by hitting the contribute button.
And then we say open pull request.
And now we have said
this before several times, but
just always remember to check.
So right now I do not
want to contribute that upstream
to the repository just yet,
but I actually want to contribute
that to my own main branch.
And well, it says we are able to merge.
So let's say we add pepper soup recipe.
And I'm just adding some
description and we can also review.
So just like you earlier,
I have created the recipe
and introduced some changes.
And we can see that this
is the recipe we are trying to commit.
And I will just go and
create the pull request.
as we've seen earlier.
So right now, let's see
if we're actually lucky.
So right now I have the pull request open.
And if we go here into
the network graph for a second,
let's see if anything actually
has updated two hours ago.
So probably we won't actually
be able to see my changes in here.
You do see that, okay.
Here is the pepper soup branch I created.
And it is still not in my main branch.
That is somewhere on the
far left-hand side up here.
Now let's see if we can actually
get them together by merging
the pull request.
So in, since it's my
own repository, I mean, I know of course
what it is that is coming with
that pull request, but we
can see basically the commits
it's coming from me.
It has a description that we created.
And we have no conflicts.
So let's go and just
merge the pull request.
And we can basically simply confirm that.
And now it says here, the
pull request has been successfully
merged and closed.
And now I could decide
to delete the branch.
If you ever forget doing
this, don't worry about it.
You can always go back,
just moving here into the code
tab and in this view where you
can view all your branches.
No, okay.
I cannot really show this
to you easily, but if we go to the
right hand side then you
have these three dots and next
to it is the option to delete a branch
and in here we can see
that this has been merged and
this is just the number of the pull request
and we also see that that is
the one I just created and
when you have the pull
request and the successful merge
then you can safely delete a
branch so it's always a good
idea to check in here.
all right now moving back over
and checking the network graph
again now let's see if we
are having a good day and if
we can actually see that i suppose
not yes so i don't think
No.
Okay.
So normally after some time,
it should now actually move
that green branch into the black
line and show up here.
But unfortunately, today GitHub seems
to be extra slow.
So I cannot really show that
to you in here.
However, if we just go back to the code.
So now I'm back on my main branch
and you might remember earlier
we did only have one soup and
now we have a pepper soup
and we can also already see
this in here that okay this
is the last commit I've actually
done on the other branch.
Now I have actually, just to show you,
prepared another branch with
a different recipe.
So in this case I have
added a mango salad recipe in
here, again just to show.
Here we have my mango salad.
And if I'm going back from
that branch onto my main branch,
then you will see that we
do not have that salad in here just yet.
And what I'm going to do
now with this branch, the mango salad, is
that now I would like to
actually try and contribute that upstream.
So now I'm again going to
open a pull request.
That is actually fine.
But in this case, I'm not
going to change that.
So be aware that when you
now create the pull request,
this goes to whoever owns
the base repository, your upstream repository.
That might be someone you don't
even know, and you will not
be able to do the merging of that
And also, if they decide
to actually merge it, then at that point,
your contribution will be
under whatever license they have
put for the code.
So this is what actually kind
of gives them the right
to share potentially and show
your recipe to others.
Also generally it's a good
idea to keep that checked so
if you have maintainers so
you contribute to somebody else's code base
and they might have to
make some changes for some conventions
that they are using or
something you've forgotten it's nice
if you allow them to edit.
But if you don't, then
they can write comments, for
example, they can review your pull request
and also let you know if
there is something that needs changing.
But other than that,
it's basically precisely the same process.
So again, it will just do that.
It will also tell that we
don't really have any conflicts in here.
And basically...
It is now open.
And if you look up
here, it has automatically now
bounced me to the upstream repository.
But now, although my pull
request shows in here,
I cannot merge it myself
because I don't have the
right on this repository.
So this is now basically awaiting approval.
So somebody who owns this
repository would now have to go there
and check that this is
all right and whether they want
to merge it or not.
But the general idea is exactly the same.
Okay, now this has actually
come up earlier, so we have
now gone through this exercise
together once more.
Are there any open questions
in the notes at the moment
that we should address before
we talk about things that can go wrong?
No, I don't think there's
anything that is open.
Okay.
Then I think I will directly
come back to my own repository in here.
Hopefully, eventually I can come back.
Yes.
Okay.
So already in the beginning,
we got this very, very good question.
So what if two people
accidentally change or without
knowing change something in the same place?
And you have now seen several times,
we always had this ability
to merge automatically.
And this is usually what you
hope to be able to do.
So if changes are in different places,
then we don't really have a
problem and we can automatically merge.
But now let's say I want
to create a new branch.
Now I'm back on my own
repository just to show you and
what I'm going to do on this
new branch that I just created.
Just let's check that I'm
actually on the right branch.
Yes.
So I'm going to the soup
recipe that I have created earlier.
And let's just say I'm making this soup
for a couple of guests who
are big garlic enthusiasts.
So I decide I'm going to
change up the recipe and
rather than having three to
four cloves of garlic, I want
to use, I don't know, maybe I
want to use six to eight
because they really like garlic.
Okay, so let's commit the
changes and we add more garlic.
Okay, so far so good.
Now we see that we have
a higher amount of garlic in here.
Now let's come back.
in here.
Just move that around a bit
so you can see what I'm doing.
And now I go back to the main branch.
I don't know, two weeks
have passed, maybe two months have passed.
And I have sort of forgotten
about all of this.
And I come back to it.
And I am again making the
same soup for a couple of guests today.
And it turns out that
they unfortunately really hate garlic.
So
I am moving to this recipe
and I'm looking at this recipe
and it says like three to four garlic cloves.
And maybe they hate garlic so
much that I cannot quite do that.
But let's just change that.
And I don't know.
Let's go for them at least.
Yeah, I think.
Let's say one garlic clove.
Okay.
Now again, I commit the
changes, so just amount of garlic.
And I commit that directly
to the main branch in this case.
So now you can see that
in here, in the main branch,
we have now one clove of garlic.
Nice.
What we have is other branch
that we now uncover.
So we totally forgot about it,
but let's actually just try
and merge it into our main.
So, well, it was to add garlic.
Okay, fine.
Let's just try to create
a pull request with that addition of garlic.
What?
Oh, okay.
Yes, that is the wrong pull request
that I just opened because
I actually forgot to check.
And of course, now I
have committed this, made this
pull request to upstream.
That was not what we wanted.
So this is why we keep
telling you and I keep
forgetting to check, which...
which one you're actually on so
yes i do not want to of course contribute
that to upstream but actually
i wanted to in fact contribute that yes
to my own main.
And now you see what I
was actually trying to show.
So now it tells me
that it can't automatically merge.
Now what does that mean?
Not that much at this point, but
Basically in here, I now just see,
okay, this is the change
I'm trying to make, but for
some reason I cannot.
So what happens if we
create the pull request nonetheless
is that we have a conflict
that we must manually resolve.
And if we go to this resolve conflict.
So what you can see here,
let me try to zoom in a bit more.
Come on.
Okay.
Now you see that we
have this incoming current change
that I'm trying to make that
adds even more garlic to the soup.
And then we have a change
that we made on main that
actually reduces the amount of garlic.
And basically, if you have that situation,
you can, in principle, say
you accept the current change,
you accept the incoming change.
Or you can do something else entirely.
And what I think I'm going to do,
so in this case, I want
to just remove those markings.
They just help you to find
out where things have changed.
Let's just say that we
will use anything between one
to eight garlic cloves.
Adjust amount to taste.
And be done with it.
And then when we are done editing that,
so I said, you could have
just clicked the button to accept
one of those options, but you
have to now go and review it
and you can decide to find
a common ground like I just
did, or you can decide which
one you're going to accept.
And once you have done that,
now let's try to go up here.
here on the right hand
side appears something that says,
Mark is resolved.
So now I have removed
the conflicting lines, I can do that.
And then I can commit the merge.
Never actually try to click
that button if the lines were still in it.
Is it complain about you if you do that?
I have actually also never tried.
I think I usually end up
just removing the lines and writing
what I want to do.
But I think if you
have bigger code changes, that
might also be problematic.
Interesting.
Well, I have to admit people
on the on the notes have have ever tried that.
It's a good question.
Again, I'm not usually doing
this on GitHub for most purposes.
So I really can't tell how it handles that.
But anyway, now I'm saying
merge pull request and confirm
merge just like before.
And now
you can see that it
was successfully merged and closed.
Happy compromise.
So now if we go back to our soup
and the pepper soup, and I
can zoom in a bit here,
magically we now have any
number of garlic cloves you
want adjusted to taste, like
you've just seen me do it.
And why are we showing this to you?
Usually you want to be sure
that you do ideally not work
on the same things in your code.
But it can happen.
And there can be those
cases where the automatic merge
is simply not going to
work for these particular reasons.
It doesn't really know which
change to accept.
So...
This is just something you
have to be prepared.
Occasionally you will hit this
kind of stumbling stone and you
might have to just resolve things manually.
Or it will happen to you.
Actually, I do have to say
it has not really happened
much because I really like to
use issues and clarify with
my colleagues where I collaborate with code.
But then again, of course,
this is code that is very
much under my control.
And I think the risk is bigger
when you contribute to much
larger projects where not everybody
might be equally involved.
clear about what they are working on
and I don't know it can
happen I think I've had it maybe once
or twice in the past year or so
but it really depends how
much you collaborate with others I think
how well you communicate with
others what you are working on
what they are working on and so on
But yeah, I think, are
there any questions or comments on
that in the note that we
should be talking about?
Otherwise, I think we can kind
of wrap up and summarize what
we have learned today.
Sorry, I was just looking
at the notes whether there
were any questions that we
should be addressing.
Okay, I hope people are
complaining about things being blurry.
So sorry about that.
I hope you at least gathered
roughly what I was doing.
But I think really the main point is
that if you run into those merge conflicts,
that you have this editor
where you can resolve the conflict online
and something quite similar,
usually in code editors and
on the command line.
But yeah, I think...
hopefully have gotten some idea
how we can merge two branches together
and yeah maybe to recap when
is it useful so I think
like we discussed several times today
it can be useful to
combine different development lines
in your own work so when
you experiment with different ideas
at the same time you can kind of independently
mess things up in different
places of the code and then bring it back
when you feel okay it's ready
but it has also a lot
to do with collaboration and
you will talk about this a lot
more I think on day three
when it's all about collaborative Git
and how to work with others
and this will also address a bit more
how to deal with merge conflicts
and how to avoid such merge conflicts
where people basically work on
exactly the same places in files.
And yeah, I hope you have seen that,
or we have at least mentioned
that branches once merged, the
whole commit history has become
part of your main.
Unfortunately, I couldn't really show
that in the network graph
because it's not updating fast enough today.
But basically, like it says
here, we kind of delete the sticky note
that keeps it separate, but
all the commit history will still
be there in main.
Okay, so I think basically
today we've shown a lot of
the basic things like the
ideas behind things and we've
used the browser for it because that's the
The thing that needs the
least amount of setup from some, from anyone.
Tomorrow, we will look into
the same sort of topics
still doing the understanding Git,
but we will do it.
You can either do it in
the command line entirely, or you can do it
with an IDE or
integrated development environment.
There are a few recommendations
what your setup should look
like on the webpage.
You should have gotten a
link to the installation instructions
as well as far as I know through email.
And there's also a bit of
info about tomorrow and feedback
for today in the notes document.
So it'd be great if you
could give us feedback there.
Maybe I can go here, please.
Yeah, I can mention briefly
for the feedback that this is the way
that we can collect feedback
from you through the notes document.
So if you scroll now to
the very bottom of the notes,
there are this type of polls
that I can already see people
are, you know, for some people,
this was the right speed.
For some people, this was too slow.
It's good that for nobody was too fast.
So that's the best.
And so in general, if you can give,
you know, mention what's good
thing about today and something
that we could improve.
In general, I would say that
we take this feedback very seriously
and at the every run of
this workshop, we actually update
the learning materials or the
ways that we broadcast and any other things.
What about you [name] and [name]?
Do you have any feedback
for our experience today?
Yeah, I think one thing
that somebody has already written
there in the notes since
that those network graphs really
do not behave like they used
to and they are just incredibly slow.
I think we might want to
have some more screenshots of
what it's actually supposed to
look like for the future.
It was a bit of a surprise
to me that this just doesn't
really seem to update.
So is it that artificial
intelligence is sucking all the
resources at Microsoft?
We don't know.
Let's hope not.
But anyway, Sus already mentioned this,
that today was kind of the
basics of Git and tomorrow we
move to your local computer.
I mentioned in this feedback that
if you have issues with
the installation, we will have
an extra installation session
tomorrow morning before the workshop.
So in the email that I
will send in a couple of hours,
you can get more details on
how to join that session if
you need that for the installation.
We still have 15 minutes.
So if there's anything to review
or to check in the, if
you have any questions, if
anyone has any question, we are,
we still have plenty of time or
a bit less than 15 minutes, 10 minutes.
There's a question about whether
the notes will be published.
yeah so the notes are actually
going to be part of the
main workshop web pages at the end
of the day we just revise and make sure
that there are no user names
or things like that that we
don't want to publish and so
yes then notes then will stay
as a kind of permanent
documentation diary of this event.
And we will do this for every day.
Maybe something that I didn't
mention in the intro that some
of you might need the credits for your studies.
For example, if you're
doing doctoral studies,
And there is a page in
the workshop web pages that explains
how to get the certificate and
to get the credits.
The amount of homework is very small
and it's in practice by
doing the exercises that you're
doing here during week one,
you are already doing almost all the homework.
So if you are interested
in that, just check the
certificate page under the workshop web page.
All right.
What about [name]?
How was it today?
Did you have any comment
for future instructors who will rerun day one?
I think for me personally,
since I've been working with
things here and there, I tend to
not pay a lot of attention to the
the online way of doing things.
I'm kind of old school.
I like things on my local computer where,
because I'm from a time
when the network connection was
turn the, press the button and
then go and make a coffee.
And when you've got your
coffee, the connection might be there.
So I like things local and
all this kind of newfangled internet things.
I'm sometimes I'm struggling,
but on the other hand, I'm
also a very pointy clicky thing, picky person.
So I like it when things are, I have,
there's a button that's labeled
it and I don't have to do.
I have to remember the command.
I think also, and this is
the idea of this workshop, that in some sense,
it does not assume that
the viewers know anything about it.
And so by showing all
these different ways of interacting with Git,
because under the hood, there's
always some Git commands that are
run by some servers.
It really makes it easier
for anyone to, for example, now
go and edit a file.
Maybe there's a typo in our web pages.
People can find out where is
that Git file and already submit an edit.
But in general, and I think
you will see this more tomorrow,
the work will start to be
maybe even more local in the sense
that even without using GitHub,
one can absolutely completely
work locally with the Git
version control and keep track
of all the changes.
Anything else to pick from the notes?
Thanks so much for the
comments, by the way, because
these are really going to
improve future runs of the workshop.
I like the idea of
adding sidequests for fast learners.
But then it feels somewhat
like pressuring people who aren't
that fast learners, but who
want to be better, to also do the sidequests.
Yeah, there's always a trade
off, isn't there?
We actually had them actually
be moved in the bottom of
the of the same teaching material
that we used to have more
things, but we move them out
to not confuse people.
So eventually, maybe we could
add back this type of
optional exercises for those who,
you know, manage to do the exercise.
Maybe not necessarily move them
back to the lesson flow to the actual document,
but make a note for
the inspector to mention that
if you're fast, you can scroll
down to the bottom and find
some extra side quests.
Yeah, that's a good point.
And I think what I find encouraging is
that at least seems that
many of our learners feel
like they, they actually got
something out of today.
So this, this is always, I
think the best feedback to see
that you feel like you
have learned something that you
can actually use.
And for sure, I want to
give a feedback to
our notes.coderefinery.org server.
I'm impressed that it's the first time
that we had, there were peaks
of 250 people editing at the
same time and the server didn't crash.
So thanks to the HedgeTalk
open source project that we
are hosting here at Alto.
All right, well, I mean,
if there's no other things to comment
or any other questions, and again,
for the learners, if you have questions,
please write them at the
bottom because it's difficult to
find from the top if something
is being added recently.
But in general, we will continue tomorrow.
I will send information for
those of you who need
help with the installation tomorrow morning.
And then there will be a task
for you for day three, at
least for those of you who
to do the, how can I
say, collaborative Git exercises when
you are pushing and pulling
to somebody else's repository.
So for those of you doing it at home,
we will create a repository and
you will be added as a collaborator.
So for that type of exercise,
we need to prepare, but
the instructions will be sent via email.
So don't worry if it's not
clear what you need to do right now.
All right.
Thank you so much, [name] and [name].
And thank you also to [name]
and [name] who have been
there managing the streaming computer.
I think this was a good day one
and we will continue tomorrow
with day two and Git version control.
Thanks to all our learners,
of course, for joining us today.
Yes.
Thanks.
Bye-bye.
Thanks and bye for today.
Thank you.