All right.
Hello and welcome to day two
of the Code Refinery workshop.
I hope you can all hear us.
I am not at all sure
that they can because I'm not
seeing anything on the Twitch stream.
We can't see you.
We got a message, but can you hear us?
I guess not.
Oh yeah, we can hear.
Okay, that's good.
Now we can see something.
Nice.
So now, are we there?
We see you, we hear, okay, great.
Then another, once more, very
much welcome to day two of
the Code Refinery workshop.
We are here with [name]
and [name], our teachers for
today in the studio and have
a little chat before we start
the workshop at the full hour.
So [name] and [name], are
you excited for today?
How is it going?
Iceland and Germany.
Hello from Iceland.
It's actually nice today.
So it was cold in the
morning, but now blue sky.
And it's sunny.
So it's actually a perfect weather.
For you to sit inside.
For me to watch how people
enjoy their life outside.
Let's hope we can also
enjoy ourselves here today during the workshop.
No, no, no.
I look forward to the lesson today.
Oh, that's great.
For everyone already joining, you
can find the link to our
notes document from the latest
emails where we have prepared,
again, a little icebreaker.
Today, we're asking you what
was the last animal you saw.
Also, for those that only
join us today, welcome.
This is our collaborative
notes document for this workshop.
And we will show you in
a moment also how to edit this
and add your own observations.
And then we also ask you,
which path did you use
yesterday to interact with Git?
But maybe instructors.
So what's your experience with Git?
How do you use it in your daily life?
Hema, maybe start it.
Yeah, so mostly, like, I prefer
to use the terminal, like, probably
kind of old school.
But now I was also trying
to learn the VS Code, basically.
It's like, because I think for teaching,
it's like, most of the
students are liking mostly using VS Code.
So I'm also kind of in
a transition from terminal to VS
Code and VS Code back to terminal.
So
That's indeed what we have
learned from previous feedback.
And please do let us know
also in the collaborative notes,
if that's still true.
Is VS Code really something
that you're using a lot or
would you prefer some other, other ways?
How about Boise?
How do you use Git?
I also mainly use Git in terminal
or sometimes recently I use
terminal in VS code because
there are some features that I
like about VS code, but terminal
is much more powerful.
So I hope we will be
able to demonstrate these features
today a little bit.
Yep.
Okay.
So what's happening today?
Do you want to share a little bit of
what we are going to, or
what you will be showing today?
so let's go to the day to uh schedule
so today mostly we will
be starting uh actually currently we
are in the intro session okay
if you scroll a bit you can
see the day to schedule so
today we will be mostly talking
about uh we will redo the
stuff which you are doing yesterday
in the day one using the
browser but today we will try
to do on your local computer
So you try to clone
the Git repository, some
existing Git repository, like the
recipe book, which you are playing yesterday.
You try to clone it and modify
and do some changes and try
to see what is happening.
And Bloze will be talking
mostly about inspecting the history, like
what are the changes done, and
a couple of other things.
This is the session before the lunch.
And after the lunch, we
will mostly talk about
try to like take a local
folder from your laptop and how
you plan to share it like
for suppose if you want to
share it with your colleagues and
how to do that.
So these are the kind
of rough schedule today.
Okay, thank you.
So we'll move really from
the web interface that we
used yesterday into your local computer.
What do people need to
follow along with the exercises?
there was some setup in
the installation instructions?
Yes.
Let's take a look.
I will click on this local work.
If you scroll a bit on the top,
what you can see here is
you can browse on the left sidebar.
If you click on the
configuration command line and
editor, I suppose you try to
do it either now or
during the exercise sessions.
So it's good to set a few things.
If you're already in
the installation instructions on
Monday, you can skip this part.
But if you're joining today,
I suggest you follow these instructions.
Okay, so a little bit of setup to do,
but there will be a little
bit of time also during the
exercise sessions to do this latest.
Okay.
And we also have today
our virtual help room.
So if you during the exercise notice
that something is not correctly
set up, you can find the link
to that in the latest email.
So you can join there,
ask your questions to maybe
a quick screen share with one of our helpers.
and get some support that way.
Now we are nearing the full hour.
So maybe let's go back to
the top of the notes in
the screen share and start from
there in a moment.
Okay.
Yes, thank you.
And you can leave it for now in the
view mode, we can show in
a moment how to edit it.
All right.
So I hope everyone had a good morning,
good breakfast, got all
the installation and preparations done
for today and is excited
to learn something new with us today.
So it's the top of the hour.
So let's get started.
Very welcome to this Code
Refinery workshop day two.
Welcome back if you have
been with us yesterday.
Welcome new ones as well.
If you couldn't attend
yesterday, please know that you
can rewatch everything you see
here on Twitch for seven days.
So no worries if you miss
part of the session today.
My name is [name].
I work at CSC in Finland
and I will be hosting today's session.
And I'm here with [name] from Iceland
and [name] from Germany, who
will be our instructors for today.
They will introduce themselves in
a moment as well.
Just a few notes here.
So if you have been with
us yesterday, you already
know our collaborative notes document.
You got the link via the last email.
We are showing this here
via the screen share.
And this is the way where
we can ask questions, add comments,
and we have a whole team
behind the scenes answering
your questions there.
So how we use that is
when you click the link, you
will see something like you
see here, nicely rendered.
page and now to edit this
document you can find this little
pen symbol in the top which
might be there where it's shown now
or somewhere to the right depending on
how wide your window is that
brings you to edit mode and
then you can scroll down a
little bit to our icebreaker and
share with us what was the
last animal you saw maybe
this morning maybe it's already some
time ago, for me, it was
a squirrel right outside of
my window, eating the leftovers
of the bird food.
And then we have another poll underneath.
Just curiosity from our side,
how you followed the day one, if you did.
So if you use the GitHub
web interface, VS code, R
studio, the command line,
or something else.
And below that is where
we are already starting to
collect the questions, keep them coming.
Throughout the workshop, we'll try
to add some headers with all
the links to the materials in
between and when we have exercises.
So this is the perfect way to communicate.
And there's also the link to
our code of conduct in the
very top of this document.
As summarized, please be nice
to one another.
We have many, many people
almost 700 registrations for
these workshops here, and many
of them also active in the document.
And with that, I think I
will give it over to [name]
and [name] for the
Git introduction continuation.
Have a good workshop.
Thank you.
Thank you, [name].
And hello.
Welcome to the day too.
So today we will be doing this
Basically, it's like yesterday in
the day one, you actually
tried to do everything on
your favorite browser.
Today, we will try to do
all the stuff using your local computer.
Let's go to today's schedule
and look into this local work basically.
I will try to open this in
a new window and close my previous windows.
Yeah.
So this is the cloning a
Git repository and working it locally.
So basically it's like yesterday
we tried to look into this recipe book,
which was prepared for you, and
you try to browse this recipe
book using your browser.
So today, it's like we will
try to download the recipe book
and try to do some changes,
like doing some edits in the file
and creating the branches and
modifying the main repository
and basically playing around.
So along with me, I have [name].
Hi.
Yeah, hi.
So [name], what, okay.
So what are we going now to
do this in this session?
I think, like you explained very well,
I mean, today we will try
to do similar things as yesterday.
So we will repeat some of
them, but we will do everything locally.
So on your own machine,
not on GitHub anymore.
And of course, to do that,
we will do some cloning
and exploring our repository on
a local machine.
Nice.
So here is just an illustration
of what we were doing yesterday.
So basically, it's like here on
the top on this picture, you
have the code refinery workshop
exercise, and you looked into
this recipe book or
The recipe book specifically
for recording and for this
purpose, we were using a specific repository.
For the users and the
learners, you have this recipe book.
When you clone it, basically it's like it.
What is happening?
I think before jumping into the clone,
maybe let's try to talk a
bit about what is a Git repository.
[name], what is Git repository?
Well, in a way, it's a
collection of all your files
of a project throughout its whole history.
So the main purpose of Git
is to preserve the history of
your project, how it evolved over time.
And every time when you make
a snapshot of your project and
want to preserve your project
at a particular time point,
then this snapshot is included in the Git
So that's how I would say.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think that perfectly
explains what the Git is.
So it has all the files
in the directories of the project,
and you are actually trying to
keep the track of it.
Basically, it's like you're
tracking all the files, the
changes in the history, and everything.
Maybe before we continue, I
was just wondering, shall we zoom
in a little bit so that we
can get rid of the bar on the left side?
Oh, perfect.
Maybe that's better for our viewers.
yeah thanks a lot yeah
that's perfect okay i think
now everyone can see in in a better mood
so yeah let's continue then
about the git repository okay
so it's like basically it has
all this history of changes
like for suppose you can see
like all the commits were made
in the main branch and then
when you clone it basically your download
you're downloading all the files,
all the directories, including the
history and the timestamps of these files.
So basically, what's in this
picture, so the dot is, is a comment.
And a line represents a branch, I suppose.
Yes.
And what is this?
And then there is like a side branch,
like a development branch or
something like this.
And then when you clone,
you are basically taking a copy
of that whole thing to your local machine.
Is that what you're... Yes,
that's what it is.
Like yesterday, they played with
creating a new recipe.
So it's a kind of a new branch, which is...
you created a new branch,
added your new recipe, and you
try to merge into the main branch.
That is the arrow on the top.
Now what we will do today
is we will also try to do
the same thing, but on our computers.
To do that, we try to
first clone the main recipe book,
and then we try to add
a new recipe which creates a
new branch by adding a new
branch and try to merge.
on our computer.
So every time when you try to do a commit,
it will create a hash ID
or a unique identifier, which
you can always refer to the
snapshot or the commit.
And the commit also has
multiple branches and tags.
So whenever you clone
the repository, basically you're
downloading the whole branches
and tags associated with the
main repository, or mostly we call
it as a remote repository.
So the remote repositories,
basically, we can for now, imagine
that the remote repository is
the thing on the GitHub.
And the local repository is the
one on my computer.
Yes, that's it.
and so then you also have like a
when you try to download it
you can also see a dot dot git in your
when you clone it so it's
a hidden files which has
all this metadata information and
all the history of so this
is how the git tracks the
changes and everything okay so
mostly you don't see it okay
because it is hidden for a
purpose but in case if you
are curious you can try to take
a look into it okay
So that is all about the git.
And let's go to the cloning part.
Okay.
So when you clone, what happens?
Like you said, we basically
take the copy of the entire
history of the project and have
it in our local computer so
that we can modify it or
inspect what happened and so forth.
Okay, so today we will not
be covering the push part so
that we will try to do it tomorrow, actually.
So maybe we will do some parts of it now.
Yeah, I think.
Yeah, yes, yes.
After the lunch, not in
the morning session.
Yes, that's right.
okay so now let's jump
into the exercise basically and uh
before the exercise uh I
would suggest in case if you are joining
for the uh today for the
first time uh try to configure your git
so that you can follow
the exercise later okay so yeah
are there any things uh browser which
Yes, so I guess we
should introduce the exercise a little bit
and maybe explain that people
can work on two
different repositories repositories
because one of them is
recorded and it's gonna be
visible on our screen.
So if people don't want to be visible,
I mean, their GitHub names,
then better if they use the other repository.
Yes, you can show that.
Today we will be doing,
as Blauze mentioned, we will do
both using the VS Code and the command line.
In the meanwhile, I will just
scroll a bit up.
If you click on these three
bars, you can actually try to
look into the copy and browse
of this existing project.
Here are the links.
But our helpers will also try
to write it in the notes.
Which one?
I will be mostly using
this recipe book recorded, but
I would suggest you only use this recipe book.
Now let me go back to the exercise.
This is the
So in the exercise, mostly
it's like you try to clone
a repository, like the one which
I just showed you, okay?
And then you can actually
like clone from different ways,
like let's suppose yesterday in
case if you forked the repository,
You can actually clone that
fork repository and then try to
create a new branch or else you
can also try to just clone the un-forked one.
You create a new branch and
do some changes in the new
branch and then switch back to the main branch.
Remember this part, you always need to
switch back to the main branch
for this exercise and do some one
or two commits and merge
the new branch into the main branch.
We will actually follow this exercise
and in let's say 20 minutes
or so, we will come back
and go through this exercise.
When would you like to come back?
Let's say 20 minutes.
So that would be 35 past.
Okay.
So let's come back at 35
past and yeah, bye for now.
go hello welcome back uh
from the exercise session so
we will now continue like
discussing about this exercise so
yeah we are actually like uh
taking a look into the notes
so here is the collaborative notes
and uh our helpers are actually like a
trying to address your questions.
There are some interesting
questions like, for example,
regarding the SSH.
In case if you haven't
configured, then we have a
separate breakout rooms where [name]
and we have a couple of
people there and they can help
you in terms of resolving some of these issues.
Yeah.
So you don't have to worry
about this now, right?
Yeah, the SSH will be
needed after the launch break.
So yes, if you have
any trouble with setting up
the connection, then you can now
focus on the for us when
we walk through the exercise and
then set up the SSH later.
Yeah.
So then let's go to the jump into the
this exercise so let's okay so
let me open my uh terminal
vs code i can basically so are
you now in your uh terminal or
So now I just opened the terminal.
Basically, you can just use the spacebar.
Or if you're on a Windows,
you can just open the VS Code.
So I just tried the VS Code.
And I will drag it a bit
so that you can see.
And I will also.
So this is like what it
looks like in case if you are
using the VS Code for the first time.
So it's like you have a
front screen and there are some
icons onto the left bar.
Today we will be exploring
some of these icons.
So the top one is the
explorer and that is the first one.
And we will also use
the source control, which is
the third icon from the left bar.
Okay, so what is the first exercise?
Cloning the repository.
Okay.
So there are two ways
of cloning the repositories.
Okay.
So for this exercise, I will
be using the recorded one.
Okay.
Recipe book recorded.
And in case if you
are starting, we recommend you
to use the recipe book.
Okay.
So the links are in
the notebook, collaborator notebook.
Let's clone this repository.
In the front window, it's
the fourth icon which shows
you clone Git repository.
Either you can clone from here
or else you can also clone
from using this source control
icon onto your left, depending
upon which you are using.
Let me click on this
clone Git repository and it will
open on the top bar.
You just need to paste the
URL which I just copied.
In my case, it is a
recipe book recorded for you.
Just remove the recorded part.
When you press Enter, it will
ask where to save the files.
Let me wait to clone the repository.
I choose the destination and it
will open a pop-up window and
you just say open.
so what just happened is
like basically it's like we try
to clone the whole repository okay
and uh you can see like
you can explore uh using
the explorer button okay and you
can see all the files cloned okay
So basically, and which URL did you copy?
So you went to the GitHub
page and then you... Let me show the...
this is the local work and
if you scroll down a bit
you can actually look into here okay
so this is the url just
uh you just need either you
can use the code refinery workshop
in case if you cloned forked it
or else you can uh have it
this one this recipe okay okay
Okay.
So once Okay, let me then roll back.
Basically, you just use a standard HTTP.
Yes.
Yeah.
Okay.
And so so now inside, you
are inside this repository in VS code.
How do you know that?
so here you can look
into this basically it's like
which branch you are if you
go to the bottom okay i hope
you can see it yeah bottom left
in the blue blue bar okay the second icon
if you click on this it
will show in which branch you
are okay so there and currently
we are in the main branch okay
And now, so this is how it looks like.
Let me basically close this, the left bar.
Okay.
So yeah, what is the first exercise then?
So we cloned the repository and
now we need to like do some changes.
And before that, we just
need to create some branch.
Okay.
So we will now create a new branch.
To create a new branch, we
go to the source control.
Okay.
And when you go to the source control,
you can look into the
repositories here on the top.
And in these repositories, you
see these three dots.
If you click on these three
dots, then it will list some
options where you can find the branch.
So let's create, and you
can create a branch from there.
So let me create a branch.
Let me call it as a new recipe.
And when you press type the
name of the new branch and
press enter, then you created a new branch.
Okay.
And so you can see the
change here on the bottom again,
like on the bottom icon.
Now it has changed from main to new recipe.
Okay.
So basically it's like today
in this session, we will all
do all the changes locally on your computer.
Okay.
And we just created a new
branch and the new branch
name is highlighted here.
Okay.
And if you want to basically
on the left side, you have
this graph showing the history of the comments.
And on top, you see the
branch that you are currently on.
Yes.
In case if your favorite
editor is terminal, you can
also use the terminal.
To use the terminal, you can
click on these three icons on the top,
like three bars in the menu
bar, and then you can go view,
and there is a terminal here.
You can either choose the
VS Code browser itself, or
if your favorite editor is
the terminal, you can also
play with the terminal.
one one thing that i just realized
so so when you just created
this branch did something happened
on github uh no nothing has happened
because we haven't did uh so
we just cloned and we are
working out locally okay so
nothing has changed like you know from
where you cloned but whatever
you're gonna do now it's
like completely local it's like
separated from the github
Yeah, so on the GitHub we
call it as a remote.
OK, but now we are
working completely locally.
OK, so this is the.
So let's now create some new file.
How do I add a new file?
So basically we go from
this source control to the Explorer bar.
Where all the files were listed.
OK, so now let me create a new recipe.
OK, safer.
Suppose let me create a recipe
in the soups and select the soups
and to add a new file
you can actually press this icon
on the top with the plus
sign and name the recipe.
So let's say soup.
Here come it.
Empty.
So super soup.
Okay.
And let's try to copy.
Here you can add your recipe soup.
I just prepared a recipe
quick soup for you.
So this is just a readymade soup.
You can just buy an instant
mix and add some hot water into it and eat it.
Okay.
That's nice.
So boil water, add soup.
Okay.
Let it sit.
Great.
Yeah.
Actually, I was just wondering,
so what is what has just happened?
Like, you created a new file.
And in the left on the left hand side,
you have this green, like
your like, the file name
is highlighted in green.
And there is like this
you Yes, letter, what does it mean?
So basically, it's like we
have just created a file, but
we are not recording the history of this file.
Basically, it's this is called untracked.
Basically, Git is not tracking
this file as of now.
But we will see shortly how
to track this file changes.
Yes.
So how do you do that now to track?
So to track this file, again,
go to the source control.
And now when you go to
the source control, you will see a plus icon.
And when you click on this plus icon,
basically, it means that you
are staging changes.
this is equal to adding git if
you are on a command line it
is equal to git add basically it's like okay
so so how would you like
how would you explain it in
in simple terms so so what
you have what you have just done is staging
Yes.
So which is like, I don't know
if that's a good comparison, but
or analogy, like if you would
want to take a picture of
your family or like any group picture, right?
You gather people.
And so that's when you call
people, you are like creating a file.
And when you are telling them, hey,
stand here so that you fit
to the camera, that's basically staging.
Yeah.
And what you're gonna now
do is like pressing the button
to take a snapshot, which is a comment.
Yes.
That's a perfect analogy.
Like this.
Nice.
So now we added this changes.
Now we need to do a commit.
Okay.
So basically, it's like you
can write a commit message here.
Okay.
Or else you can actually press a commit.
And let's see, like, basically, it's like a
What happens when I do this?
Okay.
Let me see.
You have to save the file first.
Yes.
Thanks.
Okay.
You need to stage it again.
Yes, I just staged it again.
And let's write the commit message at soup.
Okay.
And do the commit.
So now what happened is we
just created a new QuickSoup
recipe and then did the commit.
And you can see that this
new recipe was added.
and now for the next exercise
we go to the main uh branch
and to go to the main branch
you again can go to this uh
bottom icon so but why why would you do that
Because that's the exercise.
I mean, I know, but I
assume the next step you want to
do is to merge these two branches.
Yes.
Yeah.
Basically, the idea is to show
how to merge these two branches.
Okay.
And so what are you merging?
So I'm merging and what's the target?
The source will be the new recipe
and the target will be
the local repository we have here,
which is the origin slash main.
So basically, yeah, we are
only doing the changes locally.
Okay, so that is the origin.
Okay, so you want to go to the main branch?
Yes.
And you want to merge the
new recipe branch to the main branch?
That's what you want to do?
Yes.
But before doing that, I would
like to add change the some
recipes in the main also.
Okay.
And I think that is the exercise number 3.
OK, so to do that, let's
go to the Explorer again.
OK, now we can see that.
So let's try to go to the.
Again soups OK, let me open
a mushroom soup OK and let me
just try to add a space bar.
Okay.
Just a small dashed line.
And now what you can see,
I think it's a minimal change
I was doing right now.
Okay.
It's absolutely the bare minimum
you can do.
And let me save the file.
Okay.
By control S.
Now, you can see on the source control
that it is telling that the
file has been modified, and you
can see with this small m
letter, and now you need to track these changes.
Basically, it's like now you
stage the changes, and now the
next step is you write a commit message.
If you click on this commit button,
so the vs code
automatically generates basically the
most of the commit message okay
add the space to mushrooms okay
And mushrooms.
Okay.
But this is not a real file, right?
This or like real, in a way,
this is like a temporary file
that is stored in a hidden git.
Yes, yes.
Yeah.
But the file that is
in your working directory.
No.
Yeah, no.
But the good part of the
VS code at least now I'm liking
is like it is showing what
are the files you change
for suppose, currently, I just
only changed this one file.
But in case if you're
changing multiple files, I
suppose it generates all the
files listing below.
And you can write multi
line commit message here on the top.
Okay, so something that's nice
to keep track of what
you are actually committing.
Yes.
Now, let's save the file.
Okay, yeah, if you close
this window, then the commit will be Yep.
Then the commit will be recorded.
Yes.
So what next?
Now the next part is
merging the branches, right?
Yeah, so you will now
create that one comment on each branch.
Oh, you want to combine them?
Yes.
So I just created one commit
on the new recipe and one commit on the main.
Now I would like to merge the branches.
How do I do that?
Again, you just need to be
in the main branch and you
go to the source control.
Again, if you click on
these three icons here, then here
you can see the branch and like
the way we did for the create
branch, now we are merging the branches.
If you click on this merge
branch, now you need to tell
which branch you want to merge to which.
I want to merge the new
recipe branch to the main one.
I click on this new recipe
and you can see that the
new recipe in this timeline, that
the new recipe is merged into the main one.
But this main is like
all the changes you're doing
is like you're doing all the changes locally.
So nothing is, like, if you
go to the Git repository and see, like,
what is happening there,
nothing is happening there, okay?
All the changes are on
your computer only, okay?
So basically this yellow thing
in the graph view, this is
this branch that you created.
Yeah.
And you merge this back to the main.
Yes.
And you can also quickly check
by open on GitHub.
Okay.
And see what has been going on there.
So that's this exercise.
Now, what is next?
What we do next?
Okay, so maybe we can before
we go to the break, maybe we
can recap what we have been doing here.
Okay.
So let me open the window then.
OK, so we just followed
this exercise actually and actually
you can also do the same
thing using the command line.
Here you can look into the command line.
What are the commands?
OK, and you mostly use the switch.
This is the most recent edition.
Earlier it used to be checkout game.
Okay, so maybe sorry to
interrupt, maybe just from a
like, really bird's eye view
perspective, what has what have we been doing?
So we picked a repository
that is on GitHub, right?
Which is the recipe book.
Yes, we then clone it to our local machine.
and when you are doing
everything on vs code you
are doing everything locally yeah
and and you first created a
new branch in that local repository
added a new comment yes then
you switch to a main branch
other than you comment and then
you match these two branches yeah
and all of this was done
locally so nothing actually has
changed on the github repository
Yes, nothing has been changed.
So all the changes were local.
So there is nothing reflecting
on the remote branches.
So basically, you could work
only locally if you don't want
to share your work or if
you don't want to collaborate, right?
It's completely like you can
do everything on your laptop.
yes especially if you're working
on a features or like if you
want to try a few things
it's okay but it's always good to
keep kind of a later like
in the afternoon you try to see like
how to push the changes and
other things so there and also
we will try to see what
to avoid good practices like
It's always good to do small commits
and maybe take a backup
onto the remote repository.
But if you're working alone,
I think what works for you
is the best, basically.
Okay, good.
So maybe let's have a break now.
Yes.
So let it sink for a
while like like your soup.
And then we will continue in
10 minutes, I believe.
Okay, so we will be back in 10 minutes.
And which is like, okay, five past.
Yeah.
So five past.
Okay.
And then we will continue.
Bye.
and welcome back so we are
alive again just after the break and i saw
that there are many questions
in the notes so please
keep posting those questions we
will try to answer them on the fly
as much as possible but also
at the end of the day there
will be a little bit more time
for us where we can like
go through those questions
and potentially answer those that
are maybe interesting for
a general audience or still
need to be clarified.
And so we will now continue.
We go to the next section,
which is about inspecting history.
So previously what we did,
we cloned the repository.
It's sitting on our laptop.
And we can now inspect a
little bit how a particular project has evolved.
So I guess this is
something familiar for you, Herman, right?
Yeah.
Maybe you joined an existing
project, you want to figure
out what's going on, and so forth.
Yes.
Sometimes it's curious to see
how the project evolved.
Because most of the time we use NumPy,
SciPy, these kind of famous
libraries, or else the community libraries.
And you are curious.
It's like what has changed, how it evolved.
Maybe at some point you will
try to develop your own software stack.
yeah or contribute right yes yes yeah
so actually that's a good example
because this is the content
of this next section and for
this section we can actually
look at the existing package um
so this is called network x
it's a python package have you
worked with this uh are you familiar maybe
No, no, actually, I just come
to know from through this exercise
that it's a nice package
like last year during this
code refinery workshop.
Pretty cool.
yeah i think i used it
maybe a couple of years ago
when i was still into brain imaging
and it was pop graph theory
was popular at some point
in neural imaging anyway so let's say um
so you landed on this
repository and let's say you want
to inspect a file or see
how it evolved over time
which which repo maybe you
can just comment to this one.
Yeah.
Where did you get it?
If you are here.
So studying an existing project,
this is the section where we are in.
Yes.
And then inspecting history.
Okay.
And
If you scroll down a little bit,
so we will basically try to
show a few commands, how you
can inspect the history of the project.
So this is the link, right?
Like the one and the
link is basically here.
Okay.
So GitHub com network X network X.
So if you click on it,
you arrive at this GitHub repository.
Okay.
And let's say we go to one particular file.
So maybe an easiest one read me file.
I think this is the
most frequently changed file, I suppose.
Maybe I don't know.
But maybe people can write
in the comments somewhere.
What do they expect that
has changed most of the time in readme?
I don't know, installation instruction or
I don't know what else it
can be project description, I
guess, or examples.
So this is the view that
you are probably familiar from
yesterday, you can click here
to see actually the source code.
And let's say we want to
see how this evolved over time.
And for this, there is
actually a useful tool.
And
And for this purpose, we just
go to the URL address.
Do you see this?
Is it visible on the stream?
And if you change github.com to github.
Maybe you can zoom a bit.
Yeah, that's a problem.
I cannot zoom the actual URL.
What I can do is I will
post this URL in a moment.
So I will just go to this web page.
But I think the URL is
also in the lesson, right?
Exactly.
So can I do a new file?
So what are you doing now?
I just want to show.
So this is the URL of the
you are on github yeah and then
what you can do is you
can swap this part so replace
github com with github dot git
history dot xyz so you just
replace this in your url and
when you do so then you
will arrive at this website okay
So this is like a extension, so to speak.
And on top, you see the comments
and you can now navigate with the key,
uh, yeah, left, right arrow
keys, um, to explore how this file has changed.
Okay.
Maybe you can also increase
like the top bar so that it
is highly so that we can view better.
Maybe this work.
Yeah, yes.
So what are we seeing now?
So we are basically seeing, so
what we are seeing is the readme file.
But we can look at
its entire history, right?
So shall I go over this again?
Or is that clear?
Yeah, I think it's better to go once again.
So you copied the link.
You just added this
github.githistory.xyz on the top
and we landed on this page.
Exactly.
You start with a GitHub
repository that you want to inspect.
Then you pick a file
that you are interested in.
Let's say you're with me.
You click on it and you
see now the source code of this file.
And if you want to inspect
its history the way I just
showed, you just change the URL.
So you change the URL
from github.com to github.githistory.xyz.
You press enter.
and now you see the same file,
but the advantage is that
you can now browse through its history.
So if you go with left, right arrows,
you can see how this file
has changed over time.
So how do I know when
the file was created in the first place?
We can go all the way back.
So when is it created?
I'm just curious now.
January 2020.
Okay.
Yeah.
And so this is the starting point.
So that's basically the that's
the first comment of of that file.
And you can now inspect what's going on.
Did you find any interesting thing?
Like, let's see, I mean,
what's mostly been changing here is the icons.
Here they added a tutorial.
What else?
This is an interesting change
because this is like an
example for finding the shortest
path between two nodes.
And if I go back and
forth, it basically looks as
if nothing has changed.
Yes.
Do you have an idea why is it so?
I actually tried to look
last night what happened, but I'm not sure.
I think they tried to change
the file name from .txt to
something, but I'm not sure, actually.
Yeah, so probably there are
just white spaces.
Yeah, yeah.
Oh, okay.
The one I'm doing in the...
Yeah.
So this is basically how
you can quickly like visually go
through a file and get a
sense of how it's changed over time.
But most of the time, let's
say we have a repository, we
start with a repository and
we have like particular questions
we want to address, like who wrote this line
or where else can I find
this function in the code base
and so forth and so forth.
So maybe this is something
that I can demonstrate now.
And while I'm demonstrating this,
I will also maybe show a
few, address a few questions
from the previous exercise.
Okay, cool.
So this is my VS code.
So I think you can, yes.
I think, quick remark, I think
you can only use the git
history, that one only for
the public repos, right?
Exactly.
So, but in the public repository.
Yeah.
Good point.
And so I will now
clone this network repository.
So I will do the same
way like you, clone repository here.
And we'll just paste the
URL starting with HTTPS.
So this is one is the
easiest press enter, choose the
directory and now it's cloning.
It asks me to open.
Yes.
I want to open it.
And basically here is the
content of the repository.
I can also go to the
source code here, like you showed
before and see the graph.
And many of the questions
or inspection toolbox tools I want
to show are in command line.
So I will mostly work in the command line.
So to open terminal, I can
simply drag from down here.
And now you see my terminal.
Yes, it's guy believe it may
look a little bit different if
you are on Windows.
I am not sure but most
of the comments should work.
And to make sure I am
actually in a GitHub repository, I
can type a less minus a
had to show the entire
content of the directory in which I am in.
And I see that there is
this get that get folder.
And actually, I should have
done a little trick.
Will this work?
What do you want to check if I can
Yes.
So if you are lost at any point,
what I'm typing, all the
comments are shown down here, down here.
So if I type L S a,
you see that this comment appeared here.
And maybe I can also show this graph.
So to like inspect the graph
of the project that was
in the previous exercise that
people were stuck.
So one way to do it is
to use Git log one line,
which basically means that we
will inspect only the first line of a comment.
Minus minus graph.
And oops, I actually should
have added one more.
So minus graph, and then I think decorate.
Yeah.
And if I press this, it
shows, well, it doesn't show the graph.
So let's see what's going on.
Does it matter?
Maybe add on?
Yes, I just added all
somehow doesn't show nicely.
The branches.
Maybe because there are too
many comments on this main branch.
so if i actually go here
and see the visual yeah it
looks like this is basically main
the one in the blue right
exactly okay but let's say um
you join this project and
you want to i don't know
you want to find like uh you
want to improve a function
or something like this okay so
you need to find the file
where this function is actually present right
so one way to do that is
if you just want to inspect
the current state of your
repository you can simply choose
the magnifying glass then you
have the search button okay and
then just type whatever term
you are looking for but this
is a little bit limited because
it's just about the current
state of the directory
So a little bit more
flexibility gives you a command line.
And for this, we can use git grep.
And then we just need to
type the string we are looking for.
So what can we look for?
I think maybe fixes, fix me
like, or this status.
Okay.
Right now we are in the Salads, right?
Or we are on the network.
We are on the network.
So let's say fix, fix me or some graph.
Yeah, we can maybe, I think
the, like the common thing to
do it with this network is
to look for shortest path.
So let's say I want to
see how this function is built.
So I can maybe just type shortest path.
And now it gives me the
list of all files that
include the shortest path, which
is really a lot.
And it's actually a bit
difficult to inspect, right?
It's everywhere.
Yeah.
So what we can do is type
a flag to just get a list of files.
And this is maybe a
little bit more helpful.
So now we have a list of files.
So we see that this
shortest path pattern is present
in docs, in examples and algorithms.
So let's say you want
to develop this function a little bit.
So where would we go to look for it?
Maybe we can actually specify
our search term a little bit more.
So if I would type, so
this is Python, right?
And let's say I want to
look only inside Python scripts.
So I would do minus minus
and then the path to directory
where I want to look for or type of file.
So Python files, they end up with pi.
So here we have now the list of all files.
that are Python files.
And let's say you want to
actually find how this function is written.
So for this purpose, we can
maybe expand a little bit our search term.
So it's a Python script.
So usually when you write
a function, you would write
something like def and then the
name of the function.
And let's see if that helps
us to find a little bit
where this function was written.
OK, so now we have only two files.
And what we can do is
basically we can inspect one of them, right?
Yes.
So we can do it in different ways.
We can go to the Explorer.
So it is networks, algorithms,
and then shortest paths.
And it says generic.
So it looks like this
is actually that file.
And if we scroll a little
bit, this is where this function starts.
So it describes what it does.
It computes shortest paths in the graph.
And we can scroll down to
see what's going on.
Okay, so basically we just
found out where this def
shortest path is defined.
Exactly.
But this looks a little bit like a wrapper.
So probably the source
function is somewhere else.
Because here it looks like
it basically refers you to
other methods of the class.
But I think at least we
nailed down to only two files, right?
Yeah, exactly.
But let's say we want to
know, okay, so there is a
method called Bellman Fort.
And we want to know who
wrote this line of code.
Yeah, Blousey, could you just
repeat why you are using def in Git?
I'm not using def in Git.
It was just a string that I'm looking for.
So
So most of the Python
functions that started starts with the def.
That is what this was just
for me to, to, to find this pattern.
Right.
Yeah.
This was just for me to
find this function, but you
can type anything you want here.
Okay.
Yeah.
Within the courts, basically.
So that tries to find
everything in the courts.
Okay, exactly.
And we inspected this file.
And we want to know a
little bit like, okay, so who
wrote these parts of the file.
So last yesterday, we saw it on GitHub.
Do you remember how to do that on GitHub?
There is?
Yeah, there is an icon in
the GitHub, like a where you
can search for a small
on the front page.
Yeah.
But how to inspect who wrote
which part of the file?
It's like I think you go
to the code and blame you can use Yeah, exactly.
So we can do the same.
I just believe that there is
like an alias to instead of
blame to use annotate annotate.
Okay.
And now you just need to put the
have a path to the file
you want to inspect, right?
Let's copy these files.
We can do this one.
And this is a little bit
difficult to read, I believe.
Okay.
I will just increase my screen.
But what you see here is
line number of the file, who
wrote it, and in which comment.
OK.
So if I move a little bit to this side.
So the first one is the
hash ID, and then the next one is the author.
Exactly.
And the date.
OK.
The date and the number of
the line, which is here.
So let's say I don't
know, there's something interesting
you you found in the in
the script that you want to inspect.
I don't know what can it be.
Maybe the same thing which
we are looking now, like I
said, if when the shortest
path was introduced, say, Okay, so
I just need to find... Can
I use any search with a slash or something?
Yeah.
You just don't see it now, I guess.
So I will just quickly... Yeah.
So we are here.
How did you go there?
This is because I am in a command line.
So you can actually... You can
also do that simply by...
opening the file in the explorer okay
and maybe that's actually
in this particular case faster and
we are in line 43 so
this is where this function has
started line 43 which is here so
if we do git annotate
So I will do that again.
Can I use something like
a backslash or something in the Git annotate?
Yes, basically do backslash and
type what you're looking for
inside this viewer.
Because this is using maybe
if some people attended the session on on bash,
then you have this command
less where you can actually
inspect how the file looks like.
But let's say we want to
see what's going on in this
file number 43, which is here.
And this was written and
committed with this commit hash.
So I will just copy it for now.
Okay.
So, okay.
Yeah.
Introduce this in 2020.
Okay.
Yeah.
And now you want to, let's
say you want to know, so
what happened in that comment?
Right.
Um, and for this, you
can use another function, which
is called get show.
And then the hash of the comet.
And now this will show
you basically what has happened
in that comment.
Okay.
Which looks weird.
Because
So what is this red and green?
So the red thing is the
thing that was deleted.
And the right color denotes what was added.
And do you see any changes here?
It's hard to see.
OK, I see.
I see.
So basically, what has changed
is this line.
Someone just added a white
space here between the equal size.
So that's maybe not that useful to know.
So there is actually a trick to avoid this.
So basically, you are seeing
the difference between the previous
commit and this commit, right?
Exactly.
That's what's happening here.
So I'm looking at this comment.
I can Yeah, I'm looking at this comment.
And you can see that
the difference is between the
comments that I typed, which is here.
Right?
Yeah.
And one comment above.
Okay.
So I think there is a question like
when viewing long messages, how
do someone goes back to the
main line where they can run the commands?
I didn't understand.
Can you say that again?
So I'm taking the question from the notes,
collaborator notes, where people
are writing the questions.
So the question was, when
viewing very long messages, how do
I go back to the main line
where I can run commands?
And someone is stuck there.
You press Q. You press Q. Yes.
So if you press this command, what happens?
Yeah.
So if you type git
show and whatever command hash
you are interested in, and
when you press enter, what
happens behind the scenes is
that there is another program
that opens this commit in your terminal.
Yeah.
And now you navigate inside this program.
So to exit, you press Q.
Okay.
Q for exit.
Nice.
Yeah.
Okay.
And maybe so what what happened here is
so we looked for a particular
file that we are interested in, right?
Maybe I can go to our listen page.
Yes.
Let me just find it quickly.
So what we did here, we
looked at this history of
a particular file using git history browser.
Then we can use git grep
for searching for particular terms.
then we also use git show
which allows us to inspect any
git objects we want so
actually this doesn't have to be
a comet hash it can also be a tag
or yeah nice or a branch right
so it doesn't have to be
a comment hash so every tag has
a hash right is it like that or like a
What you can do is, let's
say you want to see what tags
are available in a repository.
So you just type git tag.
And this gives you a list of tags.
So let's take one as an example.
And if I now do git show
and the name of the tag, I
can also inspect what happened in that comment.
OK.
Right?
Yes.
um so we also looked at
git annotate to find who did
what in a particular file and
maybe a last thing what we can
do is to like go back in
time so basically what would be
the best way to show it maybe there is a
You already cloned the repository, right?
Yes.
Yeah.
Maybe you can switch or
check out a particular branch.
Oh, yeah.
I can switch to another branch
or I can, let's say, I
don't know, let's look at
these comments and which one looks interesting.
There is a bug fix or a new feature.
Someone added a new feature.
Right?
Yeah.
So yeah.
So there are two ways how we
can do it to let's say we
will we would like to go back
in time to this particular
moment to this particular comment.
So there are two ways to do it.
If you just want to
quickly actually, maybe let's
let's first discuss the way
that is recommended.
So
You what would you do in
the cleanest way is basically
basically to create like a
new branch that starts from that comment.
So that would be get switch
and minus C for create.
And then the name of the branch
which can be what I
don't know, some exercise or some best branch.
exercise and now the point from
which this branch should go out okay
so let's say this is this
networks and the comet hash is
this one so okay you can copy the commit
And I now I switched to a different branch.
So you see that this was the main branch.
And now I created a new branch here.
Is there any command to know where you are?
Like, yes, I can always do git log.
Actually, I can.
Yeah, I can always type
git status, which tells me where I am.
So I am on a branch exercise.
And you can also do this
git log, one line, graph,
all decorate, I believe.
Yeah.
But in case if you
already created an alias, like...
Oh, I haven't created the alias yet.
Okay, okay.
I can do that, although we
are running a bit of time now.
Yeah, yeah, that's right.
Okay, so so maybe just to
finish this point so where we are
now is we are here.
So this is the tree of our repository.
And we switch to this comment.
And that means that our working directory,
so the files that we
look in our repository, they are
now exactly at the same state
as they were in that comment
to which we switched.
Okay.
So you can roll back to
the, like the code, which was
edited like five years back.
Exactly.
You can work on it.
Okay.
Yeah.
And we can actually see.
Okay, this is just a list.
But I just wanted to check.
So this we are basically
looking at the state of our repository.
That was on February 18 2026.
Okay.
So
You can look around, explore, browse.
And if you want, you
can create new comments and
develop from that point.
But you can also just go
back right to the original status.
So how would we do that?
Do you have an idea?
Sorry, could you repeat once?
So let's say we want to
go back to the situation as we started.
So as the repository looks on GitHub.
Okay.
You can go to origin main, like main.
Yeah.
So I can switch to
the original branch, which is git switch main.
Yeah.
And now I am on the branch main.
And if I do git log,
This is basically a file
that was created on March 14th, 2026.
So this is the one you clone today.
Exactly.
Okay.
So maybe, maybe this is already enough
for the toolbox to make
you dangerous a little bit.
And what we recommend now is
that you can practice these
comments in the next exercise
so explore basic archaeology.
And you can also.
And so you can work on
the same repository on the network repository.
But you can also work
on any other actually, maybe best
if you work on this network repository.
And you can also go
through the solutions if that makes
you go a little bit faster.
Okay.
So shall we combine this
with the lunch break?
Or Yeah, I think it's a good idea.
Because I think it takes 20 minutes.
And then by the time
we reach the lunchtime,
Okay, so let's say, let's focus
for 20 minutes on this
exercise to practice these different commands.
And from after 20 hours, we
will take one hour break for lunch.
And we will resume basically in
one hour 20 minutes.
Yes.
So that will be 14 in Finland.
13 in Germany and 12 in Iceland.
That's correct.
We will reach them back in
1 hour 20 minutes.
See you.
Bye.
Bye-bye.
And hello, welcome back.
We are live after the lunch break.
I hope you had a good time.
[name], you are still with me.
That's great.
Yes.
Yeah.
So let's just have a quick recap.
I hope before the break, you
had a chance to look at
the exercise and practice yourself
these git history commands.
So what did we work with?
So we work with git grep.
So this one here, which helps
us to find a search term in our repository.
A useful flag is minus I.
So this takes care of the case sensitivity.
So it doesn't matter if I
write it like this or like
that, it will ignore the case.
Another useful flag is minus L
so that it shows only the file names.
And also, if you would
like to search through a specific file,
instead of the entire repository,
you can do minus minus and file path.
Does it sound good?
Yeah, sounds good.
Okay, and another thing we did
or we used is get annotate.
So this is the command that
helps us to identify who and
when wrote a particular line of a file.
And once we are interested
in a specific comment, we can
use get show where the comment
has to inspect that particular comment.
So these are the commands
that are useful to figure out
what's going on in the repository.
If we also want to go
back in a particular time point,
we can do git switch.
Actually, we can...
basically do something like this.
So we can get switched to a new branch
and to a particular comment that
we want to inspect.
Right?
Yes.
And if we want to go back,
we can do git switch main.
Git branch helps us to list
all the local branches.
And git branch all also
includes remote branches.
So references to the remote branches.
And if we want, we can
also use, and this you have to help me, Herman.
I think it's git branch minus D to delete.
A branch, and then... The branch name.
Branch name.
All right.
So let us continue to the next section.
So if we if you look at
the overview of our workshop,
and specifically at day two, we
are now after the lunch break.
And we will do just one
topic from the previous section
here, which is called
git basic git bisect which
should be somewhere at the bottom exactly
so git bisect so what is
this have you ever used this uh hammond
I mean, only for this
exercise, I started using it, but
I found it it's really nice tool.
And yeah, I also didn't know about it.
Yeah, so didn't know about it before.
And I regret because recently
I had that issue.
So what is the issue
basically, that this is useful for?
So basically it's like you
started working on your code
and everything was fine, but all
of a sudden everything is falling apart.
Like something is broken and
you don't know like which part is broken.
Exactly.
Or basically what happened to me
as I started working on
someone else's project and I want to,
I don't know, do some
modification or something, or it
was supposed to work well.
But suddenly, it turns out
that it doesn't work.
And we need to find a bug, or a comment,
a specific comment that created
that back that bug, and to fix it.
So get bisect is helping us
to deal with the situation.
So basically, what we can do is
we can do a short demo
using this repository here.
get bisect exercise.
And what's going on here, and
I will switch to this code.
So I can close this.
And I already cloned out repo.
So I am inside this
get bisect exercise directory.
And
What I want to do is I
want to run a Python script,
which is called Python get pi.
And it gives me a wrong number.
So it should be 3.14.
And we know that this worked before.
So how can we solve that problem?
So maybe if I quickly
demonstrate our situation.
So let's say this is a comment.
And this is a comment.
And so forth.
And we have many, many comments.
Right?
Like hundreds of comments.
And this is comment.
Let's say this is comment one.
So this is the first comment
and this is the comment that we are now.
Uh, I should do it like this.
So as I had, which was
a pointer telling us where we
are and this, we know that
here, our script doesn't work.
Right.
Yeah.
And we know that it worked
somewhere in the past.
So how can we solve this problem?
Do you have a first idea?
Maybe we actually cherry-pick
somewhere in between and see
whether it is fine there.
Exactly.
So one thing you can do
is basically go comet by comet
in history and keep checking
whether it works or not.
But there is a faster way to do it.
And that's where git bisect comes in.
So to do that, we do git bisect start.
And now, to make sure
that we actually started this
program in the background, we
can type git status.
And it tells us we are on branch main.
We are up to date with our remote.
And we are currently
bisecting starting from branch main.
And what we do is we
need to label this comment whether
it's good or bad.
We know it didn't work.
So this is a bad comment.
So we type get bisect bad.
Now it's now it wants to
know where is a good comment.
So it's very likely that a
good comment is the first one.
I mean, it must have worked here.
So we can switch to that
comment and check whether our script worked.
So how do we do that?
Do you have a clue?
Come on?
How to switch to the very first comment.
Okay, it's like, I think you can use head.
I think it is the one code.
That would be the current one.
So and we want to go to the very first one.
So if I do git log, okay, one line.
And this now gives me the
list of all the comments.
So all the comments in that history.
And I can do a trick such
that I will print this to
a function called tail, or actually, yes, tail.
And this is just a bash thing.
So this is not actually
anything related to Git, but this
just helps me to find the
first comment in that very long list.
So now what I know is the
Git cache of the first commit
and I can switch to it, right?
So I can do, so there are
two ways to do it.
And I think people were asking about it.
So one is to use git
switch and the other one is to use git checkout.
And git switch is basically
like a newer version that
mainly deals with branches.
We can use this one or we
can also do git checkout.
I am a bit old school, so
I can use git checkout and
the hash of our comment.
Now we get this scary message.
which says that we are in a detached head.
Maybe for now, we can ignore it.
And if there are questions, why
it is the case, we can address
them in the very last part
of our session today when it's
a little bit of free format,
and we can answer different questions.
So for now, we just ignore it.
And we just want to check where we are.
So I can
by git status.
Again, we are in a detached head.
Here we are still bisecting.
And we can now test if
our script worked our in the first comment.
Yes, it worked.
So we can mark this as it bisect.
Good.
And what we did now is
we mark this comment, the first one is good.
We mark the latest one as bad.
And what we can do now,
instead of going one by one,
like you said, we can go somewhere in between.
So
And that's actually what get
bisect did for us.
So it switched automatically to
get number 252, which is
somewhere in between because we
have about 500 comments.
So let's say in my
demonstration, this is somewhere here.
Okay.
So this is comment number 252.
This is the hash of that comment.
And we can now test
whether our script works here.
It doesn't.
I mean, it runs, but it
produces a wrong number, right?
Yeah.
So we mark this as bad.
And what happens now is
we have the following situation, right?
So we know this was good.
This is bad.
And this is bad.
So we basically what can we
do now, we can ignore everything that is here.
Because if it's between two
bad comments, those comments my
must also be bad.
So can I mark this somehow?
I think you do the same
thing as git commit bad.
You need to find out the code, right?
Right.
You need to find out code
for this bad and the commit.
Yes, so I already did that.
So we are here.
I run Python script.
It gave me wrong number.
And now I have to mark that this is bad.
And now our head.
So our head keeps moving from
here to code number 126,
which must be somewhere.
Oh, that's actually that doesn't
seem right now.
No, it's right.
I think we are going from one to 252.
But and now we are only one point.
Okay.
our starting point is okay, that's correct.
You're right.
So we are going from
here to somewhere here.
Yeah.
I mean, my my representation
is not perfect.
So yeah, we can run our code again.
And this is good.
So this guy is good.
And we again mark it as
good with get by stack.
And now where shall we go?
Where if this is good, this
is good, then all of these guys must be good.
So we must go somewhere here.
And we again go in the middle, so to speak.
And this will be now
roughly here, let's pretend.
So you keep on applying the basic exactly.
Exactly.
I will get bisect I
keep marking the comments whether
they are good at math and
get bisect basically keeps moving
my head so that I travel
across the history of my comments.
So I am now here around the script.
It's bad.
Get bisect bad.
And now we move again.
So we ignore these guys.
Now I have to increase here a little bit.
And we are still 31 revisions to go.
But I think this will be less.
so we are now 157 so
somewhere here let's see if it's
good or bad this is bad
Now we go again somewhere
here we switch running the command again bad.
So we are narrowing down
we are narrowing down
133 so it's somewhere here now
i made too many comments they
don't match the number but i
hope it's fine you can keep track
of it oh this one is good okay so i mark it
And now we are getting closer.
But I think, yeah, for the
sake of time, you can repeat this one.
Like, yeah, we are.
Yeah.
I mean, otherwise, I would
need without get bisect, I would
need to go through all 500 comments, right?
Yeah, this is faster.
I will just speed up.
So this is get bisect that
and only one revision is left.
And this is the comments.
where it worked.
So one comment above that must
be the one that actually introduced the bug.
So if this one worked.
So the one that actually
introduced the bug is 100 136.
And that's how it operates.
Okay.
So I think it's pretty useful thing.
Yeah, I think, but I think
that there is some assumptions that, okay,
there is some good starting point
where you start with and it
was broken and you are trying to find out.
Yeah, exactly.
The bad point.
I mean, if you keep
developing your code base, then
you usually would notice
this immediately, right?
Unless there is something related
to the dependencies of the
scripts that you don't keep
track after every comment.
But I think that's enough
maybe for this demonstration.
Yes.
I think there are a few
questions from the notes.
Like basically it's like
they're asking, how does Git commit?
Sorry, I didn't hear you.
Okay.
How automatic find commit.
So as the basic uses
a popular computer science or
goes all the history at point
and tries to find out.
coming.
So yeah, so I actually
didn't hear everything what you
said, because something was interrupting.
I don't know if this is me.
Okay.
Something is cutting out.
Okay, that's not, that's not good then.
Because we are going to switch now.
Like now it sounds better.
Okay.
Okay, maybe just some loose cable.
Yeah, thanks, [name].
So yeah, then.
So shall we take some?
Shall we switch to the notes?
And then I can connect like,
or we can switch the screens for the next.
We can continue to the
next section, basically.
Okay, let's do that.
Oh, yes.
Yeah, basically I was taking
the question from here, from
the collaborative notes, and
people were asking how Git
finds out this commit number next.
So then let's go to the next slide.
basically git uses the
binary search algorithm to find
out it that's a short answer yes so
so as the name suggests
you know bisect bisect algorithm
so now let's take we will we
are going to the next one
which is a sharing work and let
me click on this sharing work
so what are we going to do
today i mean in this session
is basically it's like a
you have your own project
on your local computer you
are doing like basically it's like
you try to initiate turn your
project into a repo and then
you want to share your work to your friends
or colleagues or someone like a homemade
if you're developing a game
you want to share it with
your friend yeah friends who
are interested who want to try
it so okay so what do we do so these are like uh
So first I will, okay, this
is the small illustration showing, okay,
you have a bunch of files
which you create and we'll
walk through this exercise now,
okay, by creating a small project
with a few files and create
a local repository and then later
like try to host it remotely
using GitHub or GitLab.
For this, we use GitHub.
This is basically like the
other way around we did in the morning.
Yes.
In the morning, it was
from GitHub to local, and now
you work locally and you want
to upload those changes to the Cloud.
Yes.
Or Cloud remote server or a
place where the remote repository is hosted.
Okay.
So let me walk through this exercise.
Basically, it's like we will
follow both the command line and the VS code.
Let me... Shall we give the
people a chance to do that themselves?
What do you say?
I think...
Maybe, okay, then let's give
what they are planning to do
in the next exercise.
So basically, in this exercise,
you need to create a
directory called my project, and
then add some couple of files in that project.
And basically, it's like you
turn this project into a Git repo.
using git init command.
Okay.
And later, like you try to
share this repo on the GitHub.
Okay.
So basically, here you you
need to have access to you
need to have an account on
GitHub, you need to have an access
to be able to connect to it with SSH.
So this is required for this exercise.
Yes.
So until this point two,
you can do everything locally.
But when you go to the
point three, it basically is like
when you want to connect
to the remote, then you
basically need this setup.
So that's why we mentioned in case
if you haven't configured your Git,
you can go to the collaborative nodes
and just follow from after the
break how to configure your SSH or HTTPS.
connection okay so yeah then
you can actually follow either a
vs code path or the command line path
when we come back after
the exercise we will go through
both of them okay and see how
we do it okay so then uh
how much time should we give
like uh say 20 minutes
Yeah, it says 25, but I'm
sure maybe it's less than that.
Yeah, I think let's try 20 minutes
and you can write your
status in the collaborative notes
and then we will see like
if more people need more time,
then we will like come back.
Okay.
come back and again go okay
so we will meet 45 past yeah
so let's come back at 45 past
so let's uh so this is the
exercise and uh can actually yeah
We will add more information
here on the collaborative notes.
Yes.
Bye then.
Hello, welcome back from the break.
Like, yeah, I hope you tried the exercise.
Now I will walk you
through to this exercise.
Okay, so the first task
is like basically trying to
create a directory with the my
project and add two files.
Let us do using, first I
will show using the VS code
and then later it's like a,
Okay, later I will show
through the command line.
So, yeah.
So currently, you can see
from this explorer that there are
no files in this directory.
I will just create a
directory called my project and
change it to that directory by the CD command.
And I will just create
a file called license.
And I'm so lazy, so basically
I will try to copy the
license from the recipe book here.
You can just go here, copy
the license, say a couple of lines here.
And paste it into the file.
This is done, so we have license.
Now I will also create some Python file.
which is a welcome to
the Code Refinery workshop.
So what happened so far?
Like these are the two files
I just created locally, okay,
basically in my computer.
So nothing has happened.
So now I would like to
keep track of these changes.
So how do I do that?
So you're basically haven't used Git yet.
No.
So you can see like if you initialize.
Oh, okay.
Yeah.
If you see if you can
ups, I think I accidentally closed.
I just want to move this one a bit.
Okay.
Yeah.
So let's
Now, if we just type git
status, and you can see that
the git is not initialized.
So what we do is we just type git init.
And while typing this, you can watch
what is happening here on the
VS Code, like on this left side.
So the moment I try git
init, you can see that there
is a U started popping it up,
where it tells you that these
files are not tracked.
You can always use git status
to see what is happening.
So this is like a kind of a thing.
It was telling the same thing.
You is like untracked files,
and now you need to track these files.
So how do I... Basically
what happened is that this
hidden folder .git was created.
Let me again see what are the files here.
Okay, yeah.
So there is this .git folder.
Yeah, apparently like yeah.
Yes, the moment you try getting it.
So this dot git folder is created
and it keeps on tracking if
any changes are committed.
OK, so now.
yeah at any time if you don't know
where you are you can just
always type the git status and see
so now i need to add there
is also kind of some useful comments
if in case if we forget
it tries okay do the git add
so there are two ways of
adding the files or staging the
files uh either you can say
type all the file names like this
Git add license and the
MyScript, or else you can just type git add.
It's up to you.
Now you can see the moment I type git add,
so here it's like all the
files are added with the letter
A. Now we have added and
you can also see through the
VS Code if you click on
the source control that the
commit message pops up.
In the command line, if you
want to do the same thing as
we did in the first half,
you can either write the commit message here
or you can just write the
commit message in the command line
with the git commit.
Say initial commit.
Then
Okay, so far, what we did
is like, we tried to like,
add all the files here.
Okay.
And in case.
Yeah.
Could you do Git log?
Okay, let's say Git log.
Okay, so it confirms that.
You created the comment.
Yes, that's nice.
Okay.
So now what we will do is like, uh,
now we try to push these
changes, uh, to, uh, to your
remote GitLab or GitHub.
Okay.
So in order to do that, what
you can do is like, you
can actually use the command line
to do the same thing or else
like, uh, we will follow, uh,
we will click on this, uh, source control.
Then here it pops up publish branch.
When you click on this publish branch,
it asks on the top
where to publish, whether to
publish in this private repository
or the public repository.
So blows a which one do you recommend?
Like, I mean, but I am a bit confused.
So So where are you pushing this?
Did you already create like,
like a project on GitHub?
Or this is even before that?
No, actually, I'm starting from scratch.
So basically, yeah, I'm
okay so sometimes actually yeah it
is a bit surprising for me also like
when i click on this source icon
either you see this kind of
in the source control it asks
you wait to publish and then
you can choose but currently
it was automatically picking it up by
like a repository okay okay so
if you would go to if you
would go to your github account
you would see this my project
yes let's take a look ah
so you prepared that before yeah
but uh it's only my project
no actually nothing is there
But there is a folder
called My Project One, which
I renamed actually from My
Project to My Project One.
But this already says you did
that 11 hours ago.
yes i mean last night i
was trying uh practicing for this session
so yeah apparently okay let's
go back roll back and see okay so
if you are doing for the first time
what you will see is like
this kind of a screen okay
and you just push publish to github
And then it will recommend
basically some of the projects
if you configure the SSH or the HTTPS,
which we recommended during the
lunch break or in the start
of the session, day two.
So basically, it suggests you to
either choose a public repository
or a private repository.
So which one should I
choose, public or private?
well it's up to you i
assume we go with public okay
let's take a public route okay
so now it is publishing to github okay
so there are some
comments here successfully published
open on github and then it
also asks would you like visual
studio code to periodically run git fetch
For the time, I would say
ask me later, okay?
We will skip this part, okay?
But I think it is a kind
of VS Code would like to update more frequent.
Okay.
So, okay.
Now, okay.
Let's go to your GitHub and
see if it's there.
Yeah.
So how do I go to my GitHub?
Now I lose my icon, like
a kind of a comment.
Yeah.
I think maybe, okay.
Actually you can go here.
Okay.
You can go to the initial commit
and then here you can see like
if you highlight this part in
the main, it will also show you open on GitHub.
Let me open on GitHub.
Wow.
Voila.
Okay.
So here are my files.
Okay, so this is because
you configured something with VS code before.
Yes, from command line, this
would not work.
Okay, basically.
Okay, let's do a bit.
Yes.
Let's try also to do the
same thing with the command line.
Okay.
so in the command line i
will just walk you through the
same thing okay what we are doing
so let me open again a vs code mine
so i will just uh create
my my project command line and
i will just quickly copy the files
license and my script okay so
i will just go to my my
project command line i will just okay
so where so right now
nothing is happening so i will do git init okay
So now the stages are tracking.
I'm sorry.
Git is created a .git folder.
Now I will add all the files.
Git add.
Okay.
And simply write my commit message.
So I did initial commit.
Okay.
now let's take a look whether
i did the commit or not okay so now
when you're doing when you're
doing the command line okay
so what is recommended is
like basically it's like uh so
you need to go to your github
okay let's go to the github okay
and uh if you zoom a bit okay it seems that
Maybe you can create a new one.
Yeah, I would like to create the new one.
But okay, so you can see
this plus icon on the top.
Okay, next to your profile picture.
Okay, close to that.
Then you create a new
repository by clicking this new repository.
Okay.
Then you can give see my project.
say, for suppose, but now,
since I already just did my project,
so now it is not allowing me to do okay,
as maybe you can use the
name that you create, like,
command line, what was it?
Okay, that's a nice one, actually.
My project underscore command line.
Yeah.
okay but just in case
if you're starting from the fork
okay then you are only allowed
to do from one for the project okay
so okay let me skip that
part so yes i created this one
do i need to do anything else
Git automatic for the for
the time being, you can only
choose public or private.
So I'm only choosing the public.
Okay.
And ignore this dot ignore
command for the now.
And also the ad readme file.
Okay.
Yeah.
So basically, you are not
creating any files for GitHub.
Yes.
Okay.
Now let me create a repository.
so once you click the button
then you have two options okay
one thing is like either choosing https
or ssh okay so we recommend ssh in case
if you are working on the project
for a long run but uh https
is a kind of a short uh
for learning purpose it is okay
okay so let me copy these lines okay
by clicking on this copy icon.
And I will now go to the
VS Code and paste these icons.
So what is happening by this?
Okay.
That is a kind of, uh, it
is asking for my password.
Okay.
And I typed in my password.
Oh, all the changes were pushed.
Okay.
Oh, Losey.
What are these comments?
Yeah.
Wait, wait.
Can you refresh now?
Uh, this one?
Yeah, I think.
Yes.
I am in the GitHub, right?
Okay.
Let me see.
Yeah.
Okay.
So it worked.
Yeah, it worked.
Okay.
And if you go back to your commands.
Yeah.
So let me, since the commands are here.
Okay.
Yeah.
So what happens here is first
you to get remote at, which
means at a remote to get like
a local get, which would have a name origin.
You set up branch main as default.
And then you push your main
branch to the remote.
That's basically what happened.
Okay, cool.
Okay, so maybe we can wrap up this session.
Yes, sorry, not the session section.
Yes, so yes, this is what
we created a new repo and
we copied these lines and publish it.
OK, and you can always
basically check it log and get status.
OK, so these are the
most frequent commands which were used.
OK, so that is.
and just a few quick remarks
just in case like you started
with the https and did the
remote at origin which just
blows the explained and later you
try to think okay ssh is
much better then you come across
some of the troubleshooting issues
and our helpers are actually
trying to help in case if we
get stuck in the collaborative nodes.
We are not going to cover
Git push today, but we will
be doing that tomorrow.
That is the remote repository part,
like how to do
the collaborative distributed version control.
So this topic will be
covered tomorrow by the instructors.
And so, Loze, what we have?
Yeah, it looks good.
I mean, maybe we can
talk about this publishing issue
after the break or in the
last part when we discuss advice.
So let us take a break,
like a short break, and meet 10 past.
Yeah.
So after coming from the
break, we will focus on
the practical advice and what to avoid.
Okay.
So how much?
10 minutes break?
Yeah.
Let's meet 10 past.
Okay.
Bye.
Perfect.
welcome back we are live after the break
so we are basically approaching
the end of today's session and
now we will have a little
bit of loose format where we
can discuss um good advice
and other issues around using it
So coming back to the last lesson
where Haman was presenting how
to push local repo to the
remote, there is just this one
part at the end, a question,
is putting software on GitHub
or GitLab publishing?
What would you say, Haman?
Yeah, actually, people used to
think that that is enough.
Publishing the code is a good
thing on the GitHub.
But there are these principles called FAIR.
Basically, it's like a
findable, accessible, interoperable,
and reproducible.
so for these things like there
is a kind of a remark in
terms of okay it's like a now i
try to work on a code okay
and i published a paper on that
code okay on the github okay
what happens after that okay
So basically, there is a
recent survey, people saying that
it's not enough.
Maybe it's like after I
publish the code, maybe I can take it down.
It's like no one is keeping track of it.
So that survey basically is
telling you that I think about
40% of the codes on the
Git are not available after the publication.
so it is uh now strongly recommended
that you actually add this
uh persistent identifier like
basically it's like you publish
the code to genodo or something okay
or similar services so that is
my like kind of uh my experience or like
when i try to like uh look into a paper
and see like okay they give
a github link but the github
link is not working any longer
they take it down basically it's like
So this is a kind of
a risk for reproducibility.
But I don't know, what is your experience?
No, no, I totally agree with you.
I think the important thing
is to maybe distinguish making
things public from making things published.
um in a way that if
you create your github repository
and you choose like you had
these two options public or private
so public means that in
theory this should be discoverable
by others but for publishing what
what we need like you said
is this persistent identifier
Or a digital object identifier
so that this is an identifier
that will remain for let's
say feasible future such that
anybody with that link can go to the
repository or code or whatever
you would like to share and it's findable.
And here we link Zenodo as one option,
but it can maybe also
be like infrastructure provided
by your university.
Yeah.
And, of course, GitHub is just one way
how you can collaborate with
others and make your code public.
But there are also other
services like GitLab, Bitbucket or Codeberg.
They slightly differ.
But I think the main functionality overlap.
Is it at your university
that they provide you with a GitLab account?
Actually, I was actually assigned
to create something similar account.
I mean, I'm not aware of GitLab.
So basically, it's like mostly
I go through basically open
GitHub and then Zenodo.
I think that is a kind of a line.
Yeah, okay.
I do have access to Ulic clusters.
So like collaboration with the
Ulic, they do provide this GitLab.
yeah so in germany there
are universities or usually i would maybe
even say that provide you
a gitlab account and they
store they basically use their
own servers to store your code
which is nice because github is
of course a commercial platform
yeah so the university provides
access to it right yeah
yeah they basically create the instance
Okay, so let us continue
with practical advice.
So what shall we discuss here?
Working on a command line.
So what is your experience
with working on a command line?
How do you usually go about with that?
Yeah, I mean,
Okay, there are some good
practices and bad practices.
Sometimes we do forget checking
your Git status.
But suppose if I was
working and then without checking
the Git status, I try to...
A push.
Okay.
I mean, it's like there
is a remote repository and I
haven't used the git fetch or like
a kind of a thing.
So my local repository is
not maybe not updated.
Okay.
In such cases, I might have come
across the issues of, okay, it's like,
yeah, I need to do
some troubleshooting, basically.
Yeah, so basically using git
status all the time, just to
make sure where you are,
what's going on, right?
So yeah, we would write down.
So if you if you type
git status, you basically get
information about untracked files.
And what was modified,
um what is staged which
files are like modified files stage files
and also the branch so
this is basically very useful
to always keep track of the
situation i mean as the name
says right the status and
And what about comment messages?
What is your experience?
What would you advise or
what would you suggest to avoid?
I mean, it actually depends.
From today's workshop, we saw like,
if you're using a VS code,
VS code is automatically generating
a comment message.
Okay.
But otherwise, I prefer to
use command line.
So it's better to add
some commit message than no commit.
And a commit message with
more information is much better
than a little commit message.
So it should describe
the minimal information in
the commit messages, basically.
Yeah, I think if we can,
this is a good example of a comment.
So we have one short,
one line short message, then the
body of the message that
provides some context and then some references.
So we would like a good
comment could be something
like, sometimes people start with
like a type, type of a comment, then
Or like, for example, for example, yeah,
like this, or that for refactor dogs,
but you know, this also
depends on the convention of your team,
or how you whether you
developed your own routine, maybe
like a feat, like for a new feature, or
performance.
I think that's important,
performance, if you improve the
performance of your code.
So you can give these little indicators
and then short message of your comment,
which here you would, like
you said, it's good not only
to mention what has changed, but why.
Then here you can use body
to provide some context for
what's what have you done and why and so forth.
And at the end, sometimes
you have like this optional
references, especially when you
work on GitHub, you can, for
example, refer to a issue like
a number of an issue that someone posted.
So we could write something
like closes issue 123.
So that could be like a
structure of a good comment.
And yeah,
Nice.
But I think it takes some practice, right?
To get used to it.
But I must say that it's
better to still do it rather
than waiting for a perfect message.
Yeah.
Like there are some bad commit messages.
So this is the good part.
What is the bad part?
Yeah.
Save work.
What I do, which I really
want to avoid, but I type
temp, which is temporary.
So this is really not a good advice, right?
No, I think it is nice actually because,
okay, if for suppose you want to do commit,
but you want to create a feature
which is not completely built,
maybe then you can say that,
okay, this is a temporary commit
I'm making for that particular feature.
I think it's a temp seems
a good type message.
I mean, it depends whether you work alone.
Like, there are many things
like I work alone, let's say I write a paper.
And it's clear that I'm not
gonna push it immediately.
Right.
So I have some time to
let's say, change the comment message,
because there's no risk of
any like conflict with other people.
But if you work on a
project where there are
collaborators involved and you do
stuff in parallel, then maybe that's
not a bad practice.
But in any case, we recommend
to make more comments than less comments.
Yes.
If you click on that bad
example, I think it has a slightly above this.
What the commit.
Bad example, http://whatthecommit, the
one in the blue.
Okay, just above the good references.
Just above the good references.
What the comment?
Yeah, fourth icon from the bottom.
Yeah, what the comment?
So yesterday I was looking
at this, okay, what the bad comments look like.
So every time you refresh this page,
I think it is showing what
the bad comment could be like.
Okay, I have a bit of
anxiety to refresh it.
I'm not sure if whatever comes
on this page will be good to be streamed.
Okay, yeah, let's go back.
But you got the point, I hope.
Yeah.
Okay, so we have status,
commit messages, and what about branches?
Any comment?
yeah i think uh yeah branches
are a nice idea it's like especially
when you want to try
something like basically it's like
uh okay i want to
introduce some functionality or
something okay i want to try
this idea i do highly
recommend of using branches for
those tasks okay
especially also if you have a
big say open source repository and
you want to contribute okay so in
that case anyway you're you can
only do a branch out and play with
that code and add features
what is your experience likewise
i think it's better like i'm
trying to develop this a bit where
I'm branching out from main
and whatever happens, I just
create this development branch or whatever,
because I know it's then
much easier to keep track of
how the code base is developing.
In the best case or in the worst case,
I can always forget about this branch
or merge it back to the
main and that keeps everything more tidy.
And do you also have
some conventions where you create new branches?
Because when you look at the
GitHub, I feel like there are
these couple of conventions like
like you could indicate the
type of changes you make.
So for example, you can
name your branch like feature, and then slash.
Yeah, what kind of feature you
want to add, for example, like, so
When I work on my projects
and let's say I analyze data
and I work with Bayesian analysis.
So for me, it works a
little bit different when I
create a branch because I can
do something like model, you know, like
when I want to experiment a
little bit with like a
Bayesian model I'm trying to build.
So I would start with a
branch called model and then I don't know,
I'm just making this up now.
But let's say this is a
model that uses a softmax function.
Or let's say you can have
a branch called prior.
And then you know that this
is the branch that uses
weekly informative priors.
Or I don't know.
You do simulations.
So that would be sim.
And I don't know.
You have prior.
Yeah, I think it also depends upon like
for suppose if you're working
on a huge like repository or
like a local one because I
would suggest having the branch
name very specific like it has
to convey to others like in case
If you want to like, say
some, say patient analysis for social science.
Okay.
So then there is a big repository.
And so if someone is also
looking into the same idea, okay,
then they can actually look into yours.
Basically it's like, and then, ah, okay.
Someone is working out.
Okay.
Let's take a look.
Maybe I can also contribute
to something about it, or maybe
we can do some collaboration.
So in that way.
Yeah.
Yeah, this is very specific, right?
I mean, more generic would
be something like, I don't know, docs.
And then you write some
sort of documentation, like, read me.
Yeah, yeah, read me documentation,
or you would write.
Yeah, fix.
Or back.
Yeah.
I don't know.
You fix the compilation error.
Yes.
Yeah.
So that's about branching.
Okay, what next?
It's all about staging and committing.
So this is something we
briefly touched upon.
Yes.
So like we say, commit
early and often rather create
too many comments than too few.
You can always combine comments later.
Oh, yeah, that's an interesting like,
to some extent, which also
depends on the context, right?
How much you want to reshape
the history of the project?
Yeah.
That's true.
How large should the comet
be better too small than too large?
Yeah, I guess it depends on
like your own habits and
your own preferences or routines.
Maybe that's actually a good point.
If someone else from the
team could join us, join us
to share some experiences.
Okay.
Let's see who we have here.
We have [name] with us.
Hi.
Would you like to join the discussion?
And we also have [name],
who is handling the stream behind the scenes.
So don't worry, [name], if
you need to continue that.
Oh, [name], we also have.
Hello.
Welcome.
So, yeah.
I have one comment also
about there are really many
good questions coming in to
the notes where actually the
answer is, hey, come back next week.
So I hope that's not too demotivating
that we're not like answering
them in detail right now.
But we have a lesson
coming up on documentation, where
it goes about what goes in a readme, what...
are like in code comments and so on.
And we also have a lesson on social coding,
which goes into exactly this
topic of fear and reproducible
and sharing your code and what
you can do about it.
So please come back next week, Tuesday,
we start again, but also now
stay still a bit for this discussion.
I'll leave you to that.
yeah i mean that this is
addressed to our audience maybe
you can write down advanced users
or beginners and give us your
idea or input how you use git
so that we maybe get some input on
What are the scenarios that
you're dealing with?
And maybe [name], who joined us
and [name], maybe you can
also share with us some
thoughts about stuff that we
were just discussing.
If you have any practical advice.
My most important practical advice is
what y'all probably said earlier,
which is better to commit than not commit.
There have been so many times
when I've worked on something
and said, well, it's not quite done yet.
I don't need to commit.
And then suddenly the whole code is broken.
And I've done too much to just revert
and have to go and try
to figure out what the thing is.
There's nothing that feels worse than that.
Sorry, one short comment
from the sidelines.
Please also introduce yourself,
[name] and [name].
People have not met you yet.
Right, yeah.
Should I go first?
I guess if I was talking.
I'm [name].
I have been a part of
Code Refinery for, I guess, almost 10 years now.
Have done lots of teaching in the past.
And now I'm mainly mentoring
and helping other people with
the production behind the scenes.
And Deanna.
I work in Finland at Aalto University.
Hi, everyone.
So I'm [name].
I have also been with
Code Refinery for quite some years,
not as long as [name].
Really happy to be part of this project.
You will see me tomorrow as
well during the Git collab lesson.
So I hope that you will
join us tomorrow and we'll
We'll teach you more on
how you collaborate with others.
But I also have some
comments on branching and so on
and how to commit, when to commit and so on.
So I think, especially as
a beginner, just commit when
you feel that's right.
Do it often, do mistakes.
play with these Git commands in a Git repo.
Don't be afraid to make mistakes.
I think that's the way we learn.
And then as you get
more comfortable with the commands,
how a commit message should look, I mean,
what information you should put
in these commit messages, then
you can structure them better.
And then when you do
collaborate with others, then it
is more important to follow
some contributing guidelines.
you mean like you you refer
to like this you go to
a github page github repo and
sometimes there is like
a contribute contributions or how to
how to contribute like yeah exactly
so uh so i guess we'll
uh talk more about that more but
i mean if you just work on
your repo i mean you you get
to decide i mean how you want to
how you want the commits to look
and then you can always
squash all your different commits
and prettify the history so
that's that's not a problem but
be be bold when when you are committing
and yeah yeah nothing is
written in stone although once
you public once you make
it public it's difficult to erase that
Yeah, so I mean, what you could do,
I mean, so let's say that
you get to a stage of your
repo that you are happy with,
but then you don't want to
show all this history.
You can actually make a
new repository that just...
just as all these commits squashed
and then that's it history gone
and you start from something
which you are happy with of
course this will not allow
you to change commits from earlier
but I mean you still
have your original repo so I
mean this is something that I would recommend
So this is something like, I'm not sure
if I remember the command
correctly, but it's something like
git clone and then orphan.
Is this what you don't know?
Okay, what I meant is, is rather rebasing.
Okay, three base on your local repo.
And then I mean, then you can you can
push to a new repository.
Or another possibility is to
mark your repository as a template.
So then when you use that as a template,
then you're just going to
get all the commits squashed into one.
So that is also...
But the possibility, this is a little bit.
If I was wanting to get rid of history
and say, Okay, like all my
stuff in the past was just temporary work.
Now I want to start over,
I would make a copy of
the directory as an archive.
In the work new working copy,
I delete the dot get directory, and then
It's gone.
All the history is gone there.
And then you run git init
again to make a new git repository.
And you commit from the current state.
And then that is that.
You've just remade it.
I mean, it's disconnected from
the other thing.
But if you're getting rid
of history, then that's what you want.
That's another alternative.
I like that.
Yeah.
But, you know, in the end, like
for almost every project I
start, it starts as a personal thing.
So there's no one else working on it.
So no one's going to look at it.
If people need to look at
the history, it's only
for historical archaeology.
I mean, when someone's going
and studying like civilizations from ancient
millennia ago, they're like,
oh, these people didn't organize
the stuff on their tables
well enough because who cares?
So when it's a personal
thing, I'll just make whatever commits.
Usually when I'm working and
the project has just begun,
I'm almost rewriting the code over
and over again or making
such big changes that they're
not small commits.
So then I just, it's like,
how do I call it?
Sometimes I call it wiki
rules versus code rules.
So if you're editing Wikipedia
or something, you don't think,
oh, here's my small atomic changes, whatever.
You just do whatever and
you commit it directly and say, if I need to,
I'll work it out later
because it's not, the history
is not that interesting to me right now.
So same for very new projects.
So
If I've just started, I
don't know what's going on.
No one knows what's going on.
Just make abundant changes, commit
all the time.
I can go back if I need to in an emergency,
but at some point it will become stable
and then I'll say, okay, now
I'm going to try to make
smaller changes at once and
actually keep the history looking
good because maybe it's useful to someone.
So that's about what to do
or what you recommend to do.
And how about what to avoid?
Not commit.
If you've done lots of changes,
and then and then you are
about to go on vacation or wherever, please,
it's always good to save
your changes, and then you
can always revert them.
And then if you are
unsure about changes, then work in a branch.
But yeah, okay, so basically not to
so that the single comment
does not include too many
modifications at once.
And [name], you wanted to say something?
Well, I mean, I guess, again,
it's like a difference.
Are you doing like,
organized development where you
want each commit to be one thing
so it can be understood separately?
Or are you in the?
Well, no one cares about this right now.
So I'm committing everything together.
For every rule, you need
to equally know when the rule
like why the rules there and why not to do it.
So
When you're new, I'd say
don't worry too much.
Do good work and sort it out later.
There is the second one
here about committing generated files.
This means, for example, let's
say you have some code and
you compile the code to make the runnable files,
or you're writing a paper
using LaTeX and then you compile
the paper into a PDF.
do you commit that PDF into the repository?
Well, then every time the code changes,
like you change the paper, you
get a new PDF file and that will be updated.
But the PDF file is
just redundant with what's in the
rest of the repository.
So normally for these
automatically generated files, you
will get ignore them.
So that way they're not committed.
And if you need to go back in time,
you go backwards and then
you rebuild it from the past link.
And that's probably the
most important thing that I do
follow all the time.
Like even when it's a
new project, there's no need for
me to save the built things that come out of it.
Yeah, I would agree.
But I would also add a
little Asterix like a little
little comment that
If it's super easy to rebuild, rebuild
that or recompile that file,
I think it's perfectly fine.
If there's something that takes more time,
then maybe you want to
preserve it, unless Git is not
a good tool to do that.
And with respect to PDFs,
I mean, with respect to a
paper, I sometimes would still
like, I agree with what you
said, that it doesn't make sense
to compile it every commit.
but maybe when you have like
a paper in a good stage that
you want to share with someone
or you want to see how it
looks then maybe you can commit
and like create a tag and say
that i don't know prototype yeah yeah
or something like this yeah
i'd i'd agree you know you can
make a copy i'd give it
a different name than the
place that's automatically built but then
If it's useful enough that
you want people to see the
PDF when they clone the
repository without having to
build it themselves, then why not?
I mean, that also applies
to committing huge files, right?
So this is something that we
want to avoid in general
because then the repository is... So
I have a general question.
Like, first, suppose if you
are like a master's or a
PhD student writing on your thesis, it's like,
and that is a scenario
one, and scenario two is like
you're working on a paper, like
a small paper, okay?
where the generated PDF
files are different.
In the thesis, it might be
bigger, and in the article, it
might be a smaller size.
So, I mean, if I
understand correctly, basically, you
try to avoid, basically, it's
like committing the PDF.
If I may add, I think
what you want there is to
have actually the repository saved
in several places.
On your local computer, on
GitHub, on your friend's laptop.
But yeah, because everyone is
maybe your supervisor might be
reviewing the article and then
you changed a bit later like or something.
yeah.
So there is one, I
think yesterday, it's about the sensitive data.
I think we also have
some gitignore earlier.
So yeah, I think maybe, yeah,
how is your experience in terms of this?
Is there actually a good example
of that if I click on this?
I think it only points out
to what we avoid.
how to create a dot git
ignore and there are some templates.
I think if I may comment
on that, I think what is important
when it comes to sensitive
data is maybe not so much
what you're ignoring or not, but,
but yeah, well, actually it
is a bit related, but what, what
ends up on, on which platform?
So if, if you have something
which will end up on GitHub, that is by, by
default not suitable enough
for sensitive data.
Okay, I mean, of course,
there are many different classifications.
So you do want to ignore
everything that is sensitive.
And I mean, you can
still use version control with Git,
but then the remotes you
are using, they need to be on a secure server.
So again, I mean, it depends
on the type of data.
And then, of course, with Git ignore,
you may ignore the files
which are sensitive.
But I would, in that case,
maybe I would actually separate
what is version controlled
and pushed to GitHub in particular
than what is... So, I mean,
I would only push to GitHub
what is not sensitive and
have maybe another repo for
the sensitive part, the data in particular.
Right, yeah.
Yeah, that would be just for the code.
Or, yeah, anything that is
okay to be shared.
And the data or the files
you're working on would be
in a separate directory.
Yeah, separate.
Yeah.
And that can also be version control.
But then it's important that it's
that the remote lives in a
place that is secure enough.
Yeah.
And here on the screen, I
just throw like an example of a git ignore,
someone would like to see I
mean, this is if you work
with R, sometimes you have these
like, files you are not
really interested in because they
are just about your setup or
comments that you use.
So there's no point to keep track of it.
So this you can also ignore
or cache files, stuff like that.
Okay.
um it's quarter two uh i
wonder is there something else
you would like to add or
we should bring amanda and do
a wrap-up yeah any good questions
from the notes that we could
look at i mean this can be
after the wrap-up so there are
a lot of questions yes so if
you have time you can do
you can surely go through and check
if you would like to
bring something up, but maybe let's
do now the wrap up.
And then if you would like
to, you can still stay on
and discuss something if you've
found something interesting, but
for sure, really, really good questions there.
Thank you so much everyone
for bringing them up and also
for helping each other out.
And yeah, like I said,
some of the questions I hope can be, um,
answered also during next week's session.
And if we on the stream
could now show the notes document, please.
Are we still on?
Ah, yes.
Okay.
I could just hear some beeping,
so I'm not sure if you can hear us on stream.
But what I wanted to mention here,
so thank you so much
everyone for participating today.
We hope you learned something.
Please let us know.
There is in the bottom of
the notes now the feedback section.
Same as yesterday, please let us know
if it was too fast, too
slow, too advanced, too basic.
If you would recommend this
to your friends, and if you will use
what you learned today, and
you can also give us a
bit more detailed feedback,
that's always really helpful to
continue the development on
this course format, but also
on the lessons themselves.
One good thing and one thing
to improve, or if you have any general
feedback, then you can also
leave that there.
We do not have like
a separate feedback form afterwards.
So this is really important for us.
So please take a moment to fill that in.
There was one question already
in the general feedback about
Jupyter Notebook and the connection to Git.
And I answered there that
this is actually a lesson that
we used to have as part of this workshop.
So we used to have a
complete lesson on using Jupyter
and there was also a section
on version control with Jupyter.
So if you're interested in
that, those materials are still available.
The link is in the notes.
And we also have recordings about that,
that you can watch where
the instructors walk through the
exercises and so on, but it's
not part of the workshop anymore.
We replaced that section with
a session on AI coding tools, because
that was something that
through this feedback, we got
to know that many are interested in.
But yeah, if you're interested in Jupyter,
please find that material
and the recordings and take a look.
And then for today, thank you
so much to [name] and [name] for today.
We covered everything that we
had in the schedule, working
locally now, moving away from
the GitHub web interface.
We did the inspecting history,
the sharing the work, practical
advice, and now also a little
bit on what to avoid.
And today,
Tomorrow, we will have [name]
and [name] guide you
through collaboration using Git.
And we have both of them
here on the stream.
Would you like to tell
something about what awaits tomorrow?
So yeah, tomorrow we'll be doing
a lot of work on GitHub.
So we'll learn how to
collaborate with others on
different repositories.
Post repositories we have access
to and posters we don't have access to.
So it will be a lot of...
What do I want to say?
Cloning and forking of different repos.
But one important thing I
do want to mention is that
if you are working on your own,
for these exercises, then you
have gotten some instructions via
email from [name].
So you'll need to ask for
access to a certain team.
So it's like a GitHub team
that will use for the exercise.
So again, if you work on your own,
check your email or go to
the workshop page under
communication preparations for day
three, and then you will
have all the information
instructions on what to do if
you work on your own if you
work with a team you don't
need to do anything so
we'll fix everything tomorrow when
would you like to add anything
um well i think you basically
say everything so i just want
to say that i'm looking forward
to seeing you all tomorrow
all right thank you for joining
and giving the brief introduction yes
so please find in your
email the instructions um and
continue to ask questions till today
and give us feedback and then
we will see you tomorrow same
time same place for the next
the day three of this code
refinery workshop and now i would
Maybe ask, we still have a few moments
if you would like to still
stay on and have any of the questions discussed.
Did anyone find anything
interesting you would like to
say something about?
I just would like to say
that I hope you learned something from today.
I can't really quickly
find anything important from the
notes because there are tons of bullet points.
So it's hard to orient myself,
but I hope you managed to
solve all the issues that you
had along the way.
And yeah, I hope you will
learn even more tomorrow.
I don't know.
How about you, Herman?
Yeah, first of all, I would
like to thank all the listeners.
Basically, it's nice you following
and also the instructors
and [name], [name], [name], everyone
who is in the studio
helping us streaming live.
regarding I mean I found
basically it's interesting to see
what people are writing one
good thing about today it's
like people it's like learning your mistakes
or like trying to adopt these
things it is always something
which tells about the teaching
actually so thanks a lot yeah thank you
All right.
Thank you all.
And I think we then, we
leave the notes open for you.
We will archive them later today
so you can find them on the event web page.
And with that, yeah, thank
you for joining and see you tomorrow.
Bye-bye.
Thank you.
See you.
Bye-bye.
Bye.