quite a while so how do we start with um yeah motivation or yeah today we'll talk about
git maybe before going into motivation i want to give people a little bit of overview of what to
expect so we'll maybe dial back here so here you can always find where we are and the link that
that I will open right now is this one, and it's up here.
I want to give you an overview of what to expect today,
what to expect tomorrow, when to expect breaks,
we will do breaks, when to expect exercises.
So I know the font is a little bit small,
I will zoom in to make that more visible.
So plan for today is that we want to talk
about version control in Git.
We will clarify what is the difference
between git and github, it's not a problem at all if you are new to these tools.
And we saw from the notes that many people are new to it.
So what I understand, we have a way for both new and more advanced people to get something
from this week.
Exactly.
So we will try to keep everybody really interested.
there will be, so if you are new to Git, GitHub,
no problem at all, you can start from zero.
If you are already familiar with Git and GitHub,
there will be also interesting new things to learn
both today and tomorrow, so please, everybody stay with us.
Those who are very experienced, they can, for instance,
help us answering questions in the notes.
So that's one, or help your neighbor
if you work in a team, help your teammate,
so many different ways to participate.
We have on kind of, we will do this in an interesting way.
We will actually not start from an empty project.
We used to do that in the past.
We will start today on GitHub.
So we will start with something that already exists.
We will start with an existing repository on the web
because we felt it will be it will be more instructive for everybody to see how does
how does how does it really look in practice today we after short motivation we will then
everybody will copy this repository and the first exercise which will start in circa 15
minutes. 10-15 minutes will be that we will copy this example repository and browse it
and answer a few questions about it. We will then take a break. After the break, we will
learn how to make changes to this repository. And then we will take a longer break. And
then we will practice some more. So we will also learn about what are these things called
branches? How can we merge developments? And then tomorrow, we will, there are a couple
of episodes that we will do tomorrow. So tomorrow, we will learn how to clone, inspect history,
and how to turn your own project into a Git repository that you can share and publish
on GitHub.
Yeah, so the big picture is today, it's like we're contributing to an existing project
someone has already set up, and tomorrow we start to see how to do this from scratch with
your own stuff.
Yes.
Okay.
Good.
And on this page, you will find that there is a lot more stuff, and we will not show
everything that is here on the page.
We chose to show you the most important episodes, but then if you are curious about browsing
some of the other episodes, you can do that. And I mentioned that, so today we will have
three exercise session that will be 20 minutes long. One will be in the first hour, the second
will be in the second hour, and then the third one will be after the longer break. If you
are participating as a team, you can then work together and help each other within the
team. If you are participating on your own, you can also go through the exercises and
all of these will will have solutions. And I also wanted to mention now before we go
in how to participate. So the best way to participate is have the notes open to ask
questions or to read questions of other people.
Then on the other half of your screen, you can have this stream.
You can watch [name] and me instructing.
And then we will do some practicing which will be in the browser or using Visual Studio Code
or using terminal.
So we offer participants to choose then different ways
to participate, to learn Git,
but more about that in a moment.
And if that becomes too much, too many windows,
you can then, you can also unwatch the notes
and just focus on the stream.
And if also, if you need to go to a meeting
or somewhere else, you can later also re-watch a recording.
We will later today publish recordings from these sessions.
Let's talk about motivation. So why do we, I will go into this motivation section here.
Why do we spend two, three days on Git and version control? Because it's maybe the most
important kind of concept in reproducible research coding. Isn't it so?
I guess it's the... well, certainly it's the thing that's transformed my work from a bunch
of random things to something that can seem like work.
But also, when I work with people, the transition to starting to use version control marks the
start of a professionalism that's like, okay, I'm actually making a thing and other people
People actually can use it, they can understand it, they can solve problems better.
So it really is like the first step to, well, stuff.
And what it is, so we've been mentioning version control, it's controlling versions, keeping
track of versions.
And then we mentioned this thing called Git, which is a tool that implements this.
It's not the only tool, but it's the tool that we demonstrate here.
So to be clear, git is the name of a tool?
Yes.
Okay.
And that's the one we teach.
It is the most popular one.
We think it's good for everybody to have seen it.
And keeping track of versions, here I have two examples from a project, which if you
like, you can browse it online.
It's an older project of mine.
And as I was developing, I was like saving versions as I go.
I like to think of Git and version control
like keeping a logbook, like a lab notebook.
So as I go, I was saving versions.
And on this page, we show two different views of it.
The one on top is I took a screenshot from a browser.
So this is the view on GitHub.
GitHub is a place, it's like a web platform
to browse and contribute to Git repositories.
So on top, it's a screenshot from a web.
On the bottom, it's a screenshot
from when I was on the terminal window.
And it's two different views to the same thing.
And what you see here are changes.
So as I was developing, I was saving changes.
And Git and version control
is not only about keeping changes.
It's also about keeping metadata about the changes.
So what you see here is actually
the metadata of the changes.
Who did it?
The author?
When did it happen?
And why was I making these changes?
So I kept these short summaries of changes.
And this is what we will be doing.
And so what we see here,
later we will call them commits.
These are git commits.
A commit is like a snapshot.
A change and a metadata.
And it's really cool that we get questions here.
So please keep these questions coming or [name] will help me that we don't miss any questions
that we should discuss in voice.
And on my different screen, I'm also watching watching your questions.
This first question, are we going to talk about that soon?
Or the Git versus GitHub?
Because this always comes up as one of the first questions.
Yeah, let's clarify it now.
So Git is this program that keeps track of versions, and GitHub is a web portal platform
where we can share, visualize, browse, contribute to Git repositories.
And it's not the only one, another very popular one is called GitLab.
Many universities may have their own GitLabs running.
For example, Aalto University has a GitLab because it has an open source version, GitLab
does, so people can host it themselves.
And we really, today, we want everybody to start using it.
And the reason is because it provides an answer to this, to a couple of questions that maybe
Maybe you have heard or asked.
So the some of them I definitely recognize from my work.
So for instance, it broke.
So you develop something, and suddenly it doesn't work anymore.
Hopefully you have a working version somewhere.
Who here has heard this question?
Can you please send me the latest version?
And where is even the latest version?
And when you collaborate with others on,
it can be code or it can be a manuscript,
we want to avoid confusion of which version
are people using or which version have the authors used
in the paper that I'm trying to reproduce here.
There will be a moment when you find a bug in your code
and then you want to know since when was it there?
Was it there before the publication?
Was it there or did it appear after the publication?
And we need a way to answer these questions.
And what if your laptop is suddenly gone?
Or the hard drive failed?
Is the thesis now gone?
So these questions are maybe familiar,
and version control provides an answer.
Because one thing we can do is we can, if I mess up,
I can go back to a version that used to work.
Yeah, like, even just for me, before I was using Git all the time, there was this constant
problem.
I would make some changes, and then I'd say, oh, I just broke my scientific code, now I'm
getting some different results.
And I would spend hours or days trying to figure out what I changed.
And it's just the worst feeling ever, like, why would I spend that much time?
And the funny thing, this is even when I was using Git, but I wasn't recording often enough.
So there were too many changes and I lost it.
So even just things like this will save you, well, I think it will save you far more time
than you'd spend in it, even without all the other things.
And even if you use it really badly and only with what you learn today and tomorrow, is
than the case, yeah.
Good, and before, there are two more things
that I want to show before we go to our example repository,
because it's not just about keeping versions
and being able to go back.
There are two really important possibilities,
and one is that we can do branching,
and we try to visualize it here with these cute gophers
that you can branch out and for instance if you collaborate with multiple people one person
can work on the graduation hat and another person can work on adding sunglasses to the
gopher and we don't have to wait for each other yeah i don't have to wait until you
send me the version via email we can work at the same time and later we can merge our
developments into the main branch.
So it can also be just me on my own if I'd want to try different things and I'm not very
sure whether this is a good idea I can create branches and later merge them really easily.
So this solves the problem of let's say you're working on a manuscript and you send it out
to your collaborators and they all send back their revised copies and now you have to sit
there and read all of them and combine them, which is a big waste of time. So I guess here,
branching is easy for anything. Merging is hard and what Git does well, if it's in a compatible
format, is that? So what the Git does well is that it's really good at figuring out that
even if multiple people edit the same file, if we edit it in different places,
Because it can figure this out and combine these changes most of the time automatically.
And we will later show also what happens if two people modify the same portion of the
file and how to deal with it.
We will come back to that too later today.
Yeah, one more thing I would like to show and then we will go to our example repository
and that is that it's so important for reproducibility.
And one feature that you will also then you can try out in the exercise is this annotation
feature.
And I will show you a real example here, I will open it up.
And this is this is some Python code written by other people.
We don't need to focus now on the on what it what it really does.
The the interesting feature I wanted to show you is this, this thing that on GitHub, it's
called blame.
It's not a good name.
I wish it was called annotate, but I will.
Oh, here we have it.
We have it on.
So I can switch between code and blame.
But this annotation feature that I wanted to show
is that since we kept track of versions
for each line of the code.
So on the right side, there is some Python codes
for each line of this Python codes.
On the left side, I can see which commit.
So which change modified this line last?
And that is incredibly powerful,
because let's say that you find out
that maybe you have a question about this line,
or you figure out that in this line of the code,
there is a problem suddenly,
and I really need to know when was this problem introduced?
I can find out four years ago.
And I can, here I could browse the precise commit,
precise change and this is so important for producibility because then my next question
is is this before I published it after I published it do I need to inform my collaborators and
we need a mechanism to be able to do this and with git we can
should we go into our example repository sure yeah I'll put paste it in here yeah
So I'll zoom out here just that you know where to find it.
So I will now navigate from the motivation to this modify an existing project, copy
and browse an existing project.
I will go in here.
And we will here explain, we will explain what you need to do very briefly and we will
then send you to a 20 minute exercise block.
And after the exercise block, we will take a break.
And this example repository that we have is a collection of cooking recipes.
So you don't it will not be about Python, it will not be about R or MATLAB or C, it
will be about cooking recipes, we think cooking recipes are relatable.
And we offer you to participate you in different many different ways.
You can participate directly on GitHub, just in the web browser.
If you prefer to work in your editor, we recommend Visual Studio Code, because it interfaces
very nicely with GitHub.
But for those of you who want to participate in the command line, later below, you can
find different tracks, and then you can select between your favorite track.
It can be the GitHub track, or the VS Code track, or the command line track, or even
i think there is some we have also some options about our studio
and the first thing we will do in the exercise is to create a copy and on
on github and on gitlab that is called a fork so we will fork the repository
and create your own copy because then you can modify the copy
copy and when creating this copy and we should also show that I don't maybe I should do it
or you [name] yeah I can do the typing yep so your first step in the exercise block will
be to create this fork and then you can choose do you want to fork this one or do you want
to fork this here both are the same so we have two different ones once we want to record
recipe book recorded because this is the one that we will show you on stream.
If you want to make sure that none of the work you do shows up anywhere, then create
a copy of this one.
The thing that we will see here in the recorded one, we will see, we will see all the copies
we owe, which copies exist, we will not browse them, don't worry, but we will see them.
I don't know if you want to take screen from me and then create the fork, or should I show
it here on?
I can do it.
So I'm answering questions and putting the stuff there.
Okay, so I will switch to my screen and you can walk me through it.
Yeah.
Is that good?
Okay.
Yes.
And this will be part of the exercise.
But we just wanted to really show how that works.
So now it's just demo.
Now it's just demo, I'm just waiting until I see...
Here I am on GitHub, and I guess you can't track me, what I'm doing very quickly, or
can you?
Not very quickly, but go back to the material and click on the recipe book recorded one.
So we go to browsing, this is the material, and we will open recipe book recorded.
Yes.
Okay.
Recipe book recorded.
I open it in a new tab.
Yeah.
Here I am.
Okay.
Good.
And there are commits and so on, but it's part of the exercise, so people will explore
it.
But what we want to now show everybody is how to create this copy.
And this is the fork button on top right.
OK, so I click it, OK, I make a fork, it will be owned by me and the same name.
I guess we can leave all of the stuff the same.
Yes.
And I click create fork.
OK, so to clarify, this is now making a copy of this repository, but it's under my user.
Yeah.
Because here you can make changes.
Okay.
So I make, yeah, I make the changes here and I guess we'll eventually learn how to send
changes back or whatever.
Okay.
Exactly.
Yeah.
What do I do now?
And now you can go back to the lesson material and scroll down to the exercise box.
Exercise.
Yes.
Here we are.
And should I do some of these?
No, we will give people time to do these that we have hints, and we have also walkthroughs.
I just wanted to give you the big picture.
So the big picture, what your goal will be in 20 minutes is to create this fork.
And you will need to have a github account and you need to be logged in on github.
Yeah.
And then we asked you a couple of questions.
So there is for instance, try to find the commits the commit history.
Try to compare the commit history with the network graph and whether you are able to
find the branches.
Okay.
And I think when you forked, you only copied the main branch.
So in your fork, maybe there's only one, but then people can deselect it and they can get
all the branches.
Okay.
And then try to browse the recipes or try to find out when recipe was, for instance,
last modified.
We also have a question for you there on there is a guacamole recipe, and we want to find
out how many changes it received, which recipes contain the ingredient salt and who modified
the guacamole recipe last.
And so right now it's not about making any changes right now it's just browsing because
we will we will make changes we will make new commits in a later exercise approximately
one hour from now now it's just browsing.
So we're role playing that we're a new person starting a project and we're trying to figure
out what the status is, and who's last did stuff, and how I'm going to get started.
Okay.
And if you get stuck, there are hints, and below we have solution and walkthrough, and
what we will then later do with [name] once we return from exercise, and once we return
from break, based on the questions that people have, we might show you some of these steps
here also on stream.
So best way to participate now is to, you will now meet with your team or you work on
your own, go through these exercise steps one to eight.
And if you have questions, you can ask them in the notes, because we will be watching
them, we will be answering them.
And some of them, we will lift them up here to for discussion.
And I would like to start now the exercise, we will be back from the exercise 10 minutes
past the hour.
And then the only thing that we will do then is to announce a break.
Okay.
Sounds good.
So see you in 20 minutes.
See you in 20 minutes.
Good luck.
Thank you.
Bye.
All right, welcome back everybody.
In our studio here we have even, we have a little red light going on that we are live.
So hopefully this worked out.
Thanks a lot for all the questions that came in.
If you got stuck somewhere, don't worry about it, because we will now take a 10 minute break.
But after the break, [name] and me will go through some of the steps here on stream,
so you will also see them.
And then, after the break, we will not only browse a repository, we will now start to
make actually changes, we will start to make commits.
But let's take a 10 minute break and see you in 10 minutes for more Git.
Yeah, thanks.
See you later.
Bye.
All righty, we'll come back from the break.
We will do now more Git.
So far we have only browsed commits created by other people, but soon we will learn how
to really create our own commits.
Something we, I should have spent a little bit more time on, we didn't really comment
so much on this choice to work in GitHub or on VS Code or on the command line.
My recommendation for today is if you are new to Git or GitHub, go for GitHub work in
the browser.
All of today can be done in the browser.
Most of tomorrow can be done in a browser.
It's only tomorrow where we will teach how to move from the web repository to a local
repository.
So tomorrow we will have to choose between an editor and command line.
So tomorrow we will recommend to try VS Code.
But today we recommend to work in the GitHub track.
We offer these two other tracks for the participants who prefer to do these exercises in VS Code
or in command line.
So these are all different ways of doing the same thing, looking at the same data?
Yes.
That's the case.
Okay.
And we recommend GitHub because we believe that it's maybe, maybe this is the easiest
way to kind of understand what, to have a mental representation of what's happening.
And then later it will make, maybe make you more confident to try the same things on the
command line.
And now before we start creating commits, we, we wanted to show you some of these steps
here and comment on them.
So we will spend five minutes on that.
And I will open up my fork.
Let me zoom in.
This is my fork of the recipe book.
How do I know that it's my fork?
it's it's under my username and I can even see where did I fork from
and now there were a couple of things we should we should do one thing was browse the commit
history and there is this clock symbol top right here so if I click here
At the time of when I created the fork, there are 32 commits,
there are 32 changes and we could browse them,
we could compare them.
The other thing that we were supposed to do
is to go on insights and network.
And now it's neat to do a little bit of thinking.
But what we will see here is a visual representation of, we will see little dots, which are the
commits.
So these little dots, each of these is a change.
But we also see that there have been branching, there have been some, some changes have happened
on branches, which have been later merged into the main branch.
And here are even some new branches appearing good
Back to the recipe book.
How do I know when a recipe was last modified?
Well, we could click on one of those, for instance.
Let's go into the sites and guacamole last last modified six months ago.
Which recipes include the ingredient salt?
Now, how many changes?
How many changes did the guacamole recipe have?
What happens if I click on the file?
And maybe I need to zoom out.
How can I see the history?
Is it this one?
Maybe the top right one?
Yeah.
So this one has been changed 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 times.
Which recipes include the ingredient salt?
It's this search magnifying thing here.
I can search for salt, for instance, and now it will search through the entire recipe book.
Except that I should have done that during the break, because it needs a few minutes
to create this search tree so i will skip that but you can i will go to the next which was
in the guacamole recipe we were supposed to figure out
who modified each line last and when and this is this blame feature
The git annotation for each line of my recipe I know who modified it, when precisely, and
I can even have a look at each of these commits.
Question seven, can we, can you use these recipes yourself?
And the hint there is to look at license file and by using means, well, can I change that?
So there is a license and it's creative commons zero.
We will talk more about licenses next week.
Now I clicked on the license thingy here.
Anyway, more about licenses and what that means next week, but that's already a good
instinct to before taking somebody else's code to see is there even a license there
and what does it allow me to do? And then question eight in the upstream repository,
what is upstream upstream is it's a this is how we call the original repository the one
that I forked from if I go back into there. So now there are issues and pull requests
And we will give more meaning to them in a bit.
But now we can already say that issues, it's a good place to keep track of problems, but
also suggestions, ideas.
So it's not, it doesn't only have to be a problem that we know about, it can hear I
earlier today, I shared an idea for, for recipe, and it can be a way to collect feedback before
I do the coding.
And pull requests, these are change proposals.
And we will now create some of those in the next exercise.
So this is now a mechanism to suggest changes, which can be within the same repository or
it can be from a fork towards the upstream repository.
And here earlier today, I made a suggestion for a vegetable soup.
And somebody else made a suggestion to improve the vegetarian lasagna.
Excellent.
But now we should go back to the material and take the next step and that is now we want
to create some commits.
We want to actually modify this repository and since we can, since it's now under your
user name.
So I will navigate to committing changes and let's make sure that you can see that too on
the notes.
Yes, I just can, thanks a lot.
What we want to do here, we want to record new changes and we call them commits.
And we will do that on two separate branches.
And branches are these different development lines.
And we remember this image of these gophers.
So we will try to do something similar here.
And here is another sketch of what this exercise is about.
This exercise will happen on your fork.
And the first thing that you will do is you will create a new branch.
And in git, branches are like sticky notes, you can think of it, it's like a sticky note
that's that is referencing a commit.
Yeah, okay.
Wait, sticky note metaphor.
What does that mean exactly?
So there's some history of commits and the branch, the sticky note refers to what exactly?
Like where?
So when we create a branch, it's like, it's like creating a different name for a commit.
So the first step will be to create this new branch, which will not yet create a new commit.
So this is the situation a.
How should we call the branch, we shouldn't call it your branch, or how do you call your
branches when you create one?
I mean, usually I call it something based on what I'm going to do there.
it might be like improve code or it might be a feature name if I'm adding a
feature usually something about what I'm planning to work on yeah so make it
descriptive so instead of your branch you will call it for instance I guess
the name of the recipe you're making exactly yeah so without spaces a lot of
speed and it will be a new salad or something yeah so step one will be
creating a new branch and again for most people we recommend to do that
directly on github but we also then show tracks on how to do it on the command
line how to do it in in vs code once you have the branch we ask you to create a
commit on the new branch and then create another one so two commits on the new
branch so this would be like you make a new recipe and then you fix something up
about the recipe. Like, you realize, ah, I needed to add this extra thing. Okay, yeah.
New recipe, modifying the ingredient, something like that. So we have a new branch, we have
two commits, and then your goal will be to switch back to main, the main branch, and
create a new commit there. And again, you can modify something, you can modify an existing
recipe. So after this exercise, we will have all created three commits. Yeah, two on a
new branch, one on the main main branch. And then Oh, and then you can browse you can see
whether if you remember if I go back to if I go back to just need to zoom out here on
insights, if you remember insights and network, you can browse the graph of your commits.
And you can then compare, does this look like what you just created?
Yeah.
So, okay.
So that's all the history.
So if we're role playing a young researcher here, I've started a new project, I've understood
it.
I want to contribute to it by adding my own recipe.
So I make a new branch and I start adding there, something there.
So that way it doesn't get, it doesn't mess up what other people may have.
And then at the same time, someone on the main branch does something different.
Correct.
Okay.
And yeah, everything that we will do here is it only exists on your fork.
So you don't have to be worried about you cannot you cannot break anything if so there
are a few more like extra steps.
At the end is to try to compare branches.
And again, below we show solution and a walkthrough.
We also ask you, you can try to rename a branch that you created, because maybe you change
your mind about the name.
try that. And then there is one more step and that is try to create a tag. So what is
a tag? And on GitHub, it's called a release. A tag is very similar to a branch. But it's
It's like a little sticky note that you
want to put on a commit so that you, hm?
Yeah.
Can we say branches and tags all point
to places in the history, but tags don't change?
So the tag is like, this is the version
that I submitted for this paper or something.
And that's just a fact that will never change.
It's like a milestone.
So a typical tag could be a version number,
like this is my version 2.0.
Or it could be this is the submitted paper.
This is the PhD version.
This is the published code.
So that will be, again, we will give you 20 minutes.
step one to eight or one to nine you work on your fork again you can choose your favorite
track again please ask us questions on the notes and before sending you to the exercise
i'm also now just catching up on the notes to see if we missed some really important
question that we should clarify i think we're doing pretty good um
good and then we will be back in 20 minutes so we will give you 20 minutes for this exercise
And in the last five minutes before the longer break, again, we will highlight some maybe
tricky steps and discuss them here.
Yeah.
Okay.
Great.
So we'll keep answering the questions and see you 20 minutes.
Here you can find the exercise.
See you in 20 minutes.
Let's create some commits.
Okay, bye.
Welcome back, everybody.
We have five-ish minutes left before we take a longer break.
And in this five minutes, we wanted to show you some of these steps and discuss and summarize.
And before doing this, I wanted to show you in the notes below the exercise, we have this
poll.
You can use it also in future exercises to let us know how things are going, whether you
are done, whether it's confusing, whether you are not trying.
This gives us an idea of how so that we can adjust better.
So please let us know in future exercises.
Yeah.
And now I will go to my fork and [name], you tell me what I should do and what I should
show.
Yeah.
So this is my.
So we're doing some stuff that's quite similar to the exercises.
So first is making a new branch.
So you've got a new idea for a recipe, I hear, and would like to contribute it.
So yeah.
Yeah.
What is that idea?
I'll show you how I create a branch here, which is.
Here is this main branch symbol and this is, there are some other branches, but I can create
a new one.
Okay.
I like to give branches somehow like my name because then I know who created them.
And in this case, I want to improve pasta.
Okay.
Great, this new branch, good.
So now you can, or can you verify the new branch?
And on here, I'm on it.
So this is, if I would zoom out, it would have the full name.
Okay.
There was a really good question in the notes about this, how do you verify what branch
you're on?
And quite often a thing that can happen is people are using many branches and start doing
stuff on the wrong branch.
And you can sort of recover from that or just ignore it and go on.
But it's good to pay attention to.
Okay, so we're on the right branch.
And now we make one commit for something.
So I will go and I will try to improve this, this recipe here, which which is lacking instructions.
I will add an instruction.
Yeah.
Uh huh.
I will do it here directly on in the web, edit this file button.
And well, maybe we should start by saute the onion and mushrooms.
And later, we need more instructions.
But that's a good starting point.
Yeah.
Okay.
But what to do now commit changes.
So this this will now create this new commit.
And here I verify on which branch I am.
So this is another chance to for me to check that I really wanted to commit to this new
branch.
Good.
I want to change this commit message because this is not very useful to Yes, I modified
the file.
It's much better to describe here in one line.
What did I do?
Why did I change it?
So I starting to improve the instructions for this recipe.
And here, if I wanted, I could add more context, if I'm more explanation, I could refer to
an issue.
But I think here, we are happy.
Well, do we want to commit?
Yes, let's commit.
What should I do next?
Can we verify the commit in the network?
So how did I find it? It was top insights sites. Yeah, and network loading, loading,
loading. I think a couple of other people also reported that things take a little bit
of time. Yeah. But this is a chance to catch up with questions. Here we go. Oh, yeah, there's
a lot of people working now. So all these different commits here. Very cool. And here
is mine. Oh, can you zoom in some? Does it scale properly? Does that basically say the
name you just made? Yeah, I wonder what this is now. Yeah, so it's this green, green little
dot is my new commit. Okay. And if I tilt my head, I can read that this is this vegetable
soup soup branch. Is that what I wanted? No, that's not what I wanted. We that's wrong.
I created, this is the new one.
There we go.
OK.
improved-pasta
Yes.
And the other essential thing is I
think the main branch didn't change.
And these little labels that are sticking next to the commits,
this is what I was referring to as sticky notes.
So these are the branch names.
The other observation is that I created
a new commit and a new branch in my fork which didn't so everybody else can see that it exists
but it doesn't it doesn't appear in in the forks of the other people this we will do
after the longer break on we will learn how how do we really know sent changes both how
do we merge them into the main branch and how do we even make change suggestions across
repositories. This will be later. Yeah. I think we wanted to show one more kind of fun
thing. And that is to whoops, to compare branches. For this, I will just zoom out a little bit.
So if you take a repository, and at the end, you add a compare
Okay, and we can choose two repositories and two branches there.
So basically, we can see what's the difference between the main branch and your new improved
pasta branch, for example.
Yeah, this one.
Okay.
So the difference between main branch and the improved pasta branch is, well, these
two lines were added and this line got removed.
So the red is what got removed, green is what got added.
Yeah.
Okay.
Good.
There was more in the exercise and there is more on the page.
Yeah.
there's a lot of good questions coming in which um let's see is there anything we need
to answer for everyone some still need answers there in the timeline what's the
horizontal axis is it minutes or arbitrary or whatever in the
on the network uh
yes in the network so here the timeline is it's chronologically ordered yeah once
it's loads okay so there are a couple of more questions on the so here this is
chronologically so time time axis very good questions on the bottom we will
answer them. Yeah. But I recommend that we take now this 60 minute break. This is this
has been designed because, well, most participants are in Central Europe. And this is aligns
well with the lunch break. But thanks for everybody else in different time zones to
follow for following. And so we will be back in 60 minutes. And then we will then our goal
will be to learn how to combine these changes from different branches merging
changes and contributing to a project yeah that's the goal for the remaining
one and a half hours which we will do after the one hour break there's one
questions about showing the compare function again but do we have time to do
Yeah, because I think the part that went quickly, I will just navigate back to my repository.
So one was, you take any repository name and at the end, edit or compare, enter.
But the other thing that was a little bit quickly is that you can choose not only which
branch, but also which repository.
So here, the first thing I did is I wanted to compare within my own repository.
So I selected my repository here.
And now it's changed a bit because now it just asked me which branch to which branch.
And now I can select which branch I want to compare.
Yeah.
Good.
Okay.
We will be back in 56 minutes, or should we do say 60 minutes 56 minutes just to make it
easier for those who want to join and we're not here in the morning and then
we will do some some merges yeah and you can keep asking questions we don't
promise to answer during the break but might if we have time so yes great
hopefully see you soon yeah excellent work everybody see you in a bit have a
good break thank you bye
Hi everybody. Hope you had the possibility to take a break and I will also just take
here a few minutes for a few moments for everybody to settle. We have one and a half hour left
to do a bit more with Git and version control. In this remaining one and a half hours, we
will also take there will be another break. Roughly 55 minutes from now. And we will hear
we will continue where we left off before the break. And the place where we left off
is that we copied a repository full of recipes.
I'm switching to your screen.
Is that good?
Oh, yeah.
Yes, please do.
OK.
There you go.
So here is where we left off just before the break.
We copied an existing repository full of recipes.
We created a branch.
and on the new branch, we created one or two commits.
It's, if you didn't manage to get that far,
it's not a problem because in the remaining exercise,
you will have time to catch up there.
But what we now want to do in the remaining time
is to learn how to merge these branches back into main.
So in more explicitly, this, your branch,
in my case, it was some pasta improvement. Now I'm happy with it. And I would like to
now find a way to propose to, to merge this development back into the main branch. Yeah.
And for this, I will now just zoom out so that everybody knows where I will navigate
next. And we will, let's paste it also in the notes. Okay. I will now navigate to the
next episode which is merging changes and contributing to the project.
Okay, it is in the notes.
And thanks also for all the questions.
Some still need an answer but we will get there.
So the goal now for us is that we want to learn about this thing called pull request.
The name is historical, but whenever I hear pull request, I think change proposal.
So we will be saying pull request, pull request, pull request, pull request, and then everybody
will think change proposal, change proposal, change proposal, change proposal.
It's a mechanism to propose changes.
It's a mechanism to merge branches together.
And we will do that within our own repositories.
And maybe accidentally, maybe we will accidentally send a change proposal across repositories
to the upstream.
And that's okay, too.
Because that will be interesting, too.
So in our, like, okay, like to clarify pull request a little bit in my mind, you said
it's like change proposal in this role-playing thing, like I'm a new person that's joined
a research group and I'm doing something, when would the pull request and change proposals
be useful?
Like, when would I use one and when would I not use one, for example?
yeah to answer a question maybe I will use this image here which illustrates a
bit what we tried to do so here I tried to propose a change I want to have to
change on the main branch I want to have this improved pasta recipe on the main
branch but I didn't do it directly on the main branch I first did it on my on
on my improved pasta branch.
And now I suggest somebody to actually review this change.
So the role, the situation here might be
that we are maybe two people or more,
maybe it's us two who collaborate on a research project.
We are both working within this repository.
And one situation could be that maybe I would like you
to review this change before it goes in
and give me your comments.
So it's like a big code that many people are working on and I'm doing something but I'm
not confident it will work or it's correct and don't want to take any risks.
Okay.
Yeah.
It could be that.
It could be about avoiding risk and getting feedback.
It could also be that I just want to inform you about this change.
So it could be that, well, we are, it doesn't have to be a big thing.
It can be a small project and it's maybe just us two.
But I would like you to know about it.
So now I can send the pull request, the change proposal, and I can involve you in it.
Yeah.
So simply a way to have everyone know what's going on without surprises, even if you already
know what you're doing, basically.
Yeah.
Okay.
So I like to, for me, that's actually this, like, collaborative learning and knowledge
transfer is even more important than, like, the quality part of it, the quality assurance.
Yeah.
The it can also be useful if you are just on your own because then maybe I wasn't sure
myself whether this will work out but I will be happy with the recipe and here I am happy
with the recipe and I just want to integrate it back into main and I will use this mechanism
called pull request.
Yeah.
Oh, we again we offer to do that in the browser or in VS code or in a command line.
who will follow in the command line,
they will notice that this is a lot easier
because for them, it's just a command.
It will be one command, enter, and it's merged.
But we still recommend most participants to follow,
to do this on GitHub.
On GitHub, it will be a few clicks.
But the nice thing is that it will already prepare us
for how collaboration works
because when we collaborate on GitHub or GitLab,
It's the same mechanism.
It is always through these change proposals.
It's always through these pull requests.
So this mechanism that we will practice today,
although we are maybe alone, and although it's just
my own repository, it will prepare us
for when we collaborate.
And we will collaborate.
We will learn a lot about collaboration this Thursday.
Yeah.
And I think there was a previous question before lunch
That said, how do I know what branch I'm on?
And this is where this starts to become really important.
If you think you're working on your branch,
like in this picture here,
but you're actually on the main branch,
stuff starts to get really weird and confusing.
And you have to look at the network view
to sort things out.
So yeah, it's good to, when you're doing this,
stop, think, am I on the right branch?
And then do it.
And in approximately five minutes, we will then start another exercise.
But before that, we want to prepare you for what to expect.
There are also some possible traps, and we will show you what to expect and what to avoid.
But really, our goal will be what this illustration shows.
Our goal will be to do two steps.
step is open up a pull request open up a change proposal and in the second step
we will accept it okay so so we're change we make the proposal and we
accepted ourselves possible yes okay okay and it could happen that at the end
of the exercise if somebody wants more and if somebody wants to have some bonus
exercise they can try to send a pull request across repositories not to their main branch
but to our main branch to the upstream yeah and then we will we will see the changes also
in the in the original repository and this already gives us a starting point it will
set us up for collaboration and if it happens accidentally that's also okay so i think some
people will accidentally send the pull request to the upstream repository and that's fine
do yeah it also happen that you modify the same file and the same portion of the file
in two different ways on your branch and on main it might happen so some of you might
see a conflict in this exercise and if you do don't panic because we will be the last
half an hour of today we will discuss conflicts why why they happen why they are good a good
thing and how to solve them but that will be a demonstration so in the last half an
hour [name] and me will we will create a conflict on github and we will show you how
you can solve it okay let me just i will just make sure that i didn't forget anything
essential before we send you to the exercise we wanted to show you what to
what to be careful about when when opening up a request so that will be
part of the exercise but I wanted to demonstrate it I will know so now
please just watch yeah okay and you will have a chance to do the same thing then
as part of the exercise okay yeah I know we start here in my
repository. Your copy of the repository. Exactly, it's my copy. Before the break I
created this branch with one commit in my case. If you don't have it yet,
you can create it in the exercise, I still have it. And one way to open up
this pull request is to click here so the branch is already made and we yeah it
remembers we've made a branch recently so yeah since I'm logged in github now
anticipates that well probably I want to create a pull request yeah so then I can
click here but the the tricky part here is that now we have to be very careful
where is this change proposal coming from and where is it going to
so there is this base repository and head repository and there is the base branch and
this branch here and what this means is that this change proposal is supposed to go from
my branch towards main it's like the direction that arrow is pointing so
And I think if I zoomed out, it would be more intuitive, but harder for you to read now
and stream.
But the thing to double check here is, where do you want to send it to?
Do you want to send it upstream towards the original repository?
No, in this case, no.
It's okay if it happens accidentally.
But in this case, what you what you will want to do is to change this towards your repository.
Okay.
And once I do that, it's now it looks easier.
And now, yes, from my improved pasta, yes, towards the main branch.
Okay.
So main will collect the changes in improved pasta.
To say it again.
Okay.
Yep.
And the other thing you can double check before.
Before writing the title before writing a description and before creating this change
proposal, I normally double check, I scroll down here. And I can see I can actually see
the change. So this should look somehow familiar to you. If this looks like a completely different
change than you thought, then I go back and double check whether this is really correct.
Okay.
Back to the exercise.
So two things.
Open a pull request.
And then merge it.
And after the merge, again, you can browse the network of branches.
And you should also, you should be able to see your improved recipe or your new recipe
should now be on your main branch.
And after the exercise, [name] and me will will then go through some of the key steps
here and discuss discuss maybe some possibilities that we didn't want to point out at this point
yet.
Yeah.
Okay, let's just make sure that we have that in the notes.
And we do.
So now scrolling to the end of the document, at the end of the document you can find where
the exercise is.
If you don't have any commits yet, if you don't have a branch yet, you can still create
it.
Yeah.
And please also let us know here how it's going, whether it's you already or whether
you are confused or whether you wish there was more time.
And our plan is to be back 35 minutes past the hour.
Okay, and if people can't do this, is that okay?
Does anything else depend on it right now?
So if if people get stuck, I would say, write us some questions, look at some questions,
not a problem at all.
meet again here on stream. Because we will go through all the key steps. All the rest
of today will be demonstration and everything tomorrow doesn't depend on it. Tomorrow one
can restart even if today something failed. Yeah, okay. Great. See you all in 20 minutes.
Good luck. And please keep the questions coming. Bye.
Welcome back, back from exercise and thanks so much for giving us here live feedback on
how it's going.
So based on this, it seems that it went pretty well.
And the goal of this exercise was open a pull request and merge.
And if you did it purely within VS code or purely on the command line, then a pull request
wasn't necessary.
You could merge these changes locally without going through GitHub.
Should I show how to do this and then we can maybe discuss some of the key steps in there?
Sounds good.
Okay.
So what do you show first?
Yeah, I will navigate back to my my copy. In during the exercise, I created one more
commit. So I'm still on my like pasta improvement branch. But now there are two commits.
And I would like to get them back domain. So I'm here. If I
reload, yes, five minutes ago, there was another change. Okay. And let me open up the request.
And before the exercise we show that it's now important to double-check where is it
going from and where is it going to and I want I want the pull request to to stay within
my repository.
And I double-check that it's from the branch that I thought I want to send from and towards
the main that looks pretty good it also tells me that it's able to merge so there won't
be any conflicts we will come we will create a conflict a little bit later
yeah okay what else should I do here you need to describe it anyhow yeah this is
maybe not a great description improve pasta it's not very specific yeah so I
like to give make this a little bit clearer that I added two concrete steps
to the instructions or boscaiola that could be a bit more context here I also
like to double-check which commits are part of this change proposal these two
And what is the change this one down here this looks all pretty good
before opening it up we wanted to tell you that there is you can actually choose there
is something called draft request that can be useful to know it can be a really neat
little feature is that sometimes I want to inform my collaborator in this case [name]
it I have I'm working on a change but it's actually not it's not finished yet I don't
want it to be merged but I would like you to look at it I would like you to know it
know about it and maybe give me feedback so this can be useful for let me click on it
I will create a draft request because then if I open the draft request it's here on top
left it's marked as draft it's not meant to be merged it's not even possible to
merge so I we cannot accidentally click here and merge but I can already collect
feedback and once I'm ready with should I make a comment on there yeah yes
please please comment on it
Okay, I've found it, I'm opening it and you should see something appear there.
Because then this way we can actually have a conversation here.
Oh, look, there it appears.
Yeah.
So here we could talk about it, clarify things.
We will also tomorrow and on Thursday, I'll show you how you can then how I can make them
improvements to my change proposal.
I will leave that out for now.
But once this is really ready for review and meaning ready to be merged, I can market ready.
Then it's not draft anymore, it's open.
And now if we are more people in the project, I would actually like somebody else to merge
it not not just me if I'm on my own I'm also the one with the one person
reviewing and here before clicking so now the the change proposal is open but
it's not merged yet before clicking here I again wanted to show you because
somebody asked about it that also here we have several options I can do the
defaulting there is also something called squash squashing what it would do
is it would it would combine these two commits that I had into one so after
it's merged it would show up as one single commit and then there is also
something called rebase which is which is an alternative to a merge so instead
of creating a merge commit, it would, it would move the new commits behind the main branch.
We will not go into much too much detail here.
Yeah. So they're like all different ways of managing the network. But I guess people should
stick with merge commit to be simple until there's.
Fully agree and later I think people can experiment so later on your own in this example repository
you can also test out the other options right now we just wanted you to know that these exist
and then I will now merge confirm and as soon as I click here now the two commits are part
of the main branch.
What is this here?
Delete branch.
What will it do?
Does it delete the commits or does it delete the branch pointer?
Yeah.
So it, it doesn't, it does not delete the commits and I can, I can demonstrate it.
I will show you what it does.
Maybe let's duplicate this tab.
I will now navigate to insights and network and I will try to find the merge commit that
I just created.
And now it needs to do a little bit of thinking because now it's we were many people doing
many changes which is wonderful.
But the one that I the one that I just created is this one.
And I merged from this, this branch here, which is maybe hard for you to read, but it's
a sort of on slash improve pasta.
And it points to the commit just before the merge commit.
And now if I go back here, and if I delete the branch, delete it, it will not delete
any commits.
But if I reload this, we will see what happens.
many questions coming in this is perfect the commits are still there this one is
still there and the other one is still there but the only thing that
disappeared is this sticky note yes to this one so hopefully now we understand
little bit better what what branches are in git and what we can do now if we
think that this would be interesting we could also look into the upstream
repository which is the original repository that we that I forked from
and see if someone has maybe made a pull request there for us to look and yes
Yes, there are. Great.
So what
Some of them accidental, some of them willing, but this is awesome, isn't it?
Yeah, what do each of these mean?
So it's
Okay, you need to you need to speak.
Okay, I will take over here. So what the
What the it's the same thing that we did before. But instead of doing the pull requests within
the repository here, then there are 10 pull requests
which are from your fork towards this original repository.
And now you have a mechanism at your hands
to suggest changes to any open source repository
on GitHub or GitLab.
And I can maybe look at some of those.
This is one that I created earlier today.
One interesting happening,
one thing that is interesting here
is that it has this keyword here
and we will return to it tomorrow and on Thursday.
So in a change proposal, I can even refer to issues.
This is the issue number three.
What was in the issue number three?
In an issue number three, I was sharing an idea.
And I open an issue so that I can collect feedback before even starting the work.
So that's one thing I can do with pull requests, I can then refer to discussions that happened
before and cross reference things.
And I will maybe merge this one.
I looked at it before, it's a nice recipe for a kebab.
Maybe the one thing I would improve that would make my work easier would be a pull request
of a better title.
We also have this thing here, approve and run.
I have a feeling we'll learn about that next week.
But this is just a preview.
So we have here sneakily in this repository
and maybe you can all find it, there is a test.
We have an automated test that verify something.
And here all the checks are passing,
which means that this pull request mechanism
even allows me to run automations like testing
And make sure that the functionality of this recipe book is preserved.
Yeah, this is a wonderful kebab recipe that I will now merge, and then it's part of the recipe book. Thanks so much.
Let's merge, and I will also say thank you.
Okay, cool. So now here's someone that's completely unrelated to us, has made a proposal, nothing
has been changed until we reviewed it and accepted it, and now it's part of our stuff.
And I guess this is basically how all the open source kind of software works. So it's
there, people can contribute, but the managers, owners, whatever, review and accept it.
Just looking at questions. So the next thing we want to do, but I'm now wondering whether
we will do it before the break after the break is that I want to actually create a conflict
some of you might have seen conflicts I will create it and we will also resolve it and
we will discuss what this yeah what it is and what is good about it maybe to keep it
all together we could go over some questions from the notes and then make the conflict
and resolve after the break.
Sounds good.
Yeah.
Okay, let's see.
Which question should we lift up here?
There's two, number 55 and 56, about safely deleting a branch.
So does deleting the branch lose any information?
No, it's it's after merging a pull request. It's I would say it's always safe to delete
it. It's not a problem. If you forget to delete it, it will be just there. It's it doesn't
take much space. Yeah. So sometimes I forget to delete them. And then if I go back into
this repository what is this how can I find all the branches it because I'm
zoomed out here so then sometimes I go into this branches overview which is
next to the name of the branch and it is overview it's you can then I can see
which branches are active, so for instance this branch is 28 commits behind.
You will also see which branches are merged.
This one is open merge request and if I would merge it, it would show a different symbol
and then I can also tidy up here.
So the only bad thing can happen if you forget is that you have lots of branches here, but
it doesn't take any like space and it's always safe to delete it because it doesn't remove
commits, it only removed this label
that we don't need anymore.
Yeah.
There's also several questions about if you
have several different changes and you
want to make separate pull requests out of them.
And I think this is sort of tied up or implicit
if the changes are on the same branch.
That's an excellent question.
And first off, if they are on the same branch, am I correct that you, it's either you merge
the whole branch or none of the branch, like the branch is the fundamental unit of work?
Okay.
So pull requests are from branch to branch.
So all the commits from the source branch will get integrated into the target branch.
And for us, it means that to organize our work, we will try to not put unrelated things
onto the same branch.
So what I like to do is that if I try to do something new, I create a new branch.
And sometimes I get confused and sometimes things get messy.
Also if you are completely new to git and github, I wouldn't overthink it too much.
I think it's better to create lots of commits.
And at the beginning, maybe okay, there will be some unrelated changes in a pull request
and maybe there will be some unrelated changes on a branch.
But later when you get more comfortable, we recommend create new branch for every new thing.
don't put unrelated things into the same branch,
don't put unrelated things into the same commit.
And this will also make the pull request review easier
for the other person,
because then they only have to focus on one thing
and not these like two completely unrelated things.
It might also be that if I review a pull request,
maybe I understand,
I have a good understanding about the one thing,
but I have no knowledge about the other thing,
and then I cannot review it.
And instead, if it was two pull requests,
we could give the one to me
the other one to the other person who knows about this other thing yeah okay do
we still have time for a few more questions yes we have three more minutes
okay I had a good one here uh where was it
Maybe the last one, R60.
Yeah, that's good, yeah, go for it.
So the question is, multiple people, they work on the same file, and they make commits,
and they merge into the same branch.
We can imagine things will get messy, what is the best practice to solve the issue?
So if the multiple people are editing the same file in different places, it's not a
problem, Git will figure it out.
So for instance, if we have a recipe and somebody is working on the ingredients and somebody
else is changing the instructions, it's not a problem, Git will know that these are different
changes and it will merge them automatically.
The conflicts that we will see is when we modify the same portion of the file in two
different ways, and we will do that after the break.
But the best practice to solve the issue is if you notice in your project that lots of
people are working on the same file, I think it's good if they at least know about it.
So hopefully all the three different people who work on the same file at least know that
other two people are doing something.
So sometimes in addition to just creating branches and commits, I notify my colleagues
on the chat and tell them, hey, everybody, in the next two weeks, I will be in this file
and you are there too, just that you know.
Or I open up a draft pull request.
And it's not finished, but at least my colleagues see that, aha, someone is doing something
in that file.
So then maybe they will, we better coordinate a little bit.
it's like you keep updating that file or that pull request constantly over time so people track
yeah yeah and i think we'll talk more about this later like yeah more tomorrow so tomorrow we talk
about how does code review really work and sorry on thursday and really practice this like what
are what are best practices to to collaborate within your own group or what are best practices
to suggest changes to somebody else's project and avoid any surprises.
Yeah. Okay. If there's time, there's a good one. I merged a branch. No.
Which one is it?
49. So I thought this was about updating pull requests, but so it goes, I merged a branch,
but then after the merge, I made some changes to the branch and I did a commit and push to the
branch. So, okay, so the branch was merged and then you keep working on it. Should I...
Maybe let's talk about the general picture here. So, if you make a branch and you make
a pull request out of the branch and you update that branch, then the pull request
gets updated instantly. Is that correct? Yes. Okay. Until it's merged. Until it's merged.
Once it's merged, I consider the branch. It's done for me. I can delete it or not,
but I don't touch it again. For anything new, create a new branch. Yeah. But if you do keep
updating the branch after it's merged, it becomes, well, then this is not automatically merged,
but you can make a new pull request.
Correct.
Yeah. Okay.
Should we go for a break?
Yeah, let's do that.
And then after that, create some conflicts.
And do some conflict resolution, but in a very nice way.
Sounds good. Okay.
We'll be back six minutes after the hour.
Yeah. Let's see.
See you then.
Bye.
you
Yeah, welcome back our remaining 25 minutes.
And we will talk about conflict resolution.
Yeah.
So what's a conflict?
So we have some text about it and explained in a sentence or two, but we really want to
also demonstrate it is it's the same portion of the same file is modified on two different
branches in two different ways and later we try to recombine these branches and this can
either happen that I do two different modifications myself and later try to merge them or it could
be more typical is two different people modify the same portion of the file in two different
ways and as soon as they try to merge changes for instance as part of a pull request they
notice that there is a conflict. And you have maybe already seen it and this will be only
a demonstration.
So this is the common case where the same things get modified twice, and in order to
combine them you have to actually decide, like a human has to be there and decide which
one to take.
And we paste the link here, so right now, for everybody, you can like lean back, watch,
and ask questions on the notes here.
And then later, if you want to test it out yourself, you can, but now this will be just
demonstration.
Yeah.
And I presume Git has good tools to manage this.
So you can solve this locally, you can solve it in GitLab, you can solve it in GitHub.
What we will show here is, I will create the conflict on GitHub, we will also solve it
on GitHub. Okay, I'll do that back in my repository in my recipe book.
Yeah, and I will make now two changes one on main and the other change on this branch.
I think I need to create a new branch for it. So let me first create a branch. I will create
a branch and I want to I will call it less cilantro because I'm not so much a
fan so I will take a guacamole recipe and remove a little bit of cilantro from
the recipe okay so new branch and I am on this less cilantro branch I will now
navigate to the guacamole recipe and make a change there yeah guacamole edit
pen and I would like less 0.5 tablespoons.
Makes sense.
Okay.
And then the typical commit message.
This is not a good message.
I'll have much better is reduce amount of by half and even better is why I did it because
with git you can see who changed and what they changed but sometimes it's hard to see why I did
it because well because I don't like it I don't like that ingredient so much yeah okay and then
And then I guess when someone's looking at it later and resolving, they can understand
why.
Like, was there something wrong, or is this a preference thing?
Yeah.
Okay.
Good.
We have that commit.
Yeah.
No pull request yet.
I will now navigate back to main.
And on the main branch, I will modify the same file.
Now I'm same file.
You notice that on the main branch, it still says one tablespoon.
And on the main branch, this could be now somebody else really likes this ingredient.
Here we go from one to two.
So I created two commits.
We are not not merged yet and I could browse them on the on the graph but let me know
Now we anticipate that there will be a conflict I will create a pull request
And again I want it within my own repository here
From less cilantro to main and already here Okay
we cannot automatically merge.
But we don't worry.
Let me open it anyway.
It will not be a draft one.
I will open it.
Let's see what happens.
It has conflicts.
OK, this looks different.
And I think in the notes, we saw some people with questions
where they saw a message like this.
But I guess this is actually good here.
If two people do the same thing different ways,
the worst possible case is that you pick one of them randomly
and you don't realize it happened.
This is presumably going to let us understand what happened
and solve it.
How do we do that?
So again, I also really emphasize what you that it's a good thing.
This is a really good thing.
It will prevent us from accidentally remove each other's work.
It even it didn't matter whether which change was their first.
So earlier today, we talked a little bit, there were some questions about chronology
of commits.
It doesn't matter whether the one commit was at nine o'clock and the other one at 11 o'clock.
That doesn't matter to the conflict.
It happened on two different branches, it asks me now to intervene, and that's good,
because it cannot decide for me.
And now there are many ways to resolve it, but we will now do the graphical way here
directly on the web, resolve conflicts.
Which is often what I'll do for relatively simple, easy to understand things like this.
So this sure looks pretty clear.
If people try it locally, it will look similar.
So it adds these markers here, which
mark that this change happened on this branch,
and this modification happened on the main branch.
And now it asks me to, well, please decide.
Yes.
OK.
And what are we going to pick?
I don't know.
Yeah, what, or could the recipe say cilantro to taste between half and two tablespoons?
It could, so I don't actually have to pick one of the two, I can also pick a compromise.
I could say zero to two to taste.
But what I have to do is I have to remove these extra markers.
So this stuff is just for me, but I should remove it before I mark it as resolved.
It even doesn't let me.
It tells me now that remove all conflict markers to resolve this file, and what it means is
remove this, and remove all this extra stuff.
Okay.
And now I can mark it as resolved.
And the file looks like it should look now.
So we can tell when it's done.
There's no weird stuff there.
Okay.
And now the resolution will be an additional commit.
I see.
Yeah. So again, it's the idea of making a commit.
Somehow. Okay. Yeah. And now
it's happy. There is no conflict now, because this commit
contained the resolution.
And now we can merge.
Okay.
Yeah, good. I mean, that wasn't that hard. I mean, it showed
us what the problem was. We could look at it. So when would a
conflict resolution be very difficult?
I guess if... So here two people
are doing the same things, but it's one line. But let's say
two people both rewrite the whole recipe from scratch, then you'll basically see two copies
of the recipe there, and have to...
Here it was easy because it was not too many changes, and not in too many places. So sometimes
conflicts can be all over the place. It can also be more complicated if this is a change
to where I simply don't know the answer. I mean git is asking me should I take the one or the other
but what if I just simply don't know. Sometimes I need to ask my colleague who maybe knows more
about that code. But then we can have a conversation on the pull request thread
and figure out which version is the one that we should keep.
But it's good that we get asked so no work is deleted by accident.
Okay, now we have less than 15 minutes left, we can, we still have time for questions.
And did you merge the pull request already?
I didn't yet.
Okay.
Should I?
Yeah.
Oh.
Should you?
I guess.
Why not?
Yeah.
It's, it's on my, my copy.
Save to delete, yes it is. Delete branch.
Okay.
So at this stage, our ambition was that we understand what a conflict is.
How to resolve a conflict, you can try it out on your own. It will anyway appear sooner or later.
It might also appear on Thursday when we collaborate, and then we will return to it.
Yeah. And on Thursday, did we talk about how to reduce conflicts?
yes or make them less likely that's the yeah which is really nothing special to
get but it's ways people work together yeah on things very useful lesson and so
now with on one screen I see your questions coming in and we still have
time for them I also wanted to zoom out here a little bit and again tell you
what was the big picture?
So today, the big picture was seeing a Git repository
and seeing commits.
We started in the web, we created a copy,
we created commits, we created branches,
and we were able to merge them.
Tomorrow, we will move from the web,
we will learn how to copy a repository
from the web to a laptop,
but also we will learn how to go the other way.
if you have a project, if you have some code script files,
how to turn it into a Git repository
and share it on the web.
And we will learn a bit more really useful tools
on how to inspect the history of a project
because very often we don't start from zero
but we join an existing project
and how to navigate in that.
And we will then close tomorrow by discussing
like where to start and how to find a good balance of not trying to make things too perfect
first day will be all about collaboration yeah
i will open up questions here we should also paste somewhere of feedback form because at
the end of every day we want to ask you about yeah one thing that you liked and one thing
that we should improve.
And if we can improve it already until tomorrow,
we will try to.
Let me browse here through the questions.
Let's see, I'm looking for the feedback.
Yeah, question 62.
That's a good question,
and we will return to it on Thursday,
but already as a little preview,
is that my fork is now
It has a couple of commits that nobody else has, but also it's lacking a couple of commits.
And you can then, on Thursday, we will then learn how you can then synchronize, update
your fork so that I get also the nice kebab recipe and other recipes that might have been
submitted to the upstream repository.
So more about that on Thursday, but it's a great question.
Question 63, how about using branches no matter how small the changes are and no matter the
size of the team, one person or several?
Really great question.
So if I'm on my own and I know that I want to have that change, I often just commit directly
on main.
I typically start using branches when I'm not so sure about whether this will work out
or I want to keep it separate because it's changing lots of things and I want to not
keep it in the main main code yet or if I'm more than one person.
If we are more than one person then I typically start using branches and start using code
review.
Yeah.
Yeah, can I retract the merge request? Yes, you can close it. So if you close it, then
that means retracting. Often it's nice to write down why you closed it. So sometimes
I see people just closing it and I'm not sure why was it closed. So you can add a sentence
that Oh, yeah, I found out that this is maybe not the best way of doing it. I need to think
about it more. I close it, I might reopen it later. And you can so you can also later
reopen a pull request which has been closed.
Yeah.
And here a little bit further down on the screen is the
feedback form.
Let us know about the speed.
Was it the right speed?
Was it too fast, too slow?
Also about the level and we know that especially on day
one, it's difficult to find the balance of the right level.
Over the next days, things will calibrate a little bit better.
But really, our goal is to keep everybody engaged.
Let us know how the exercises went, and tell us one thing that was really good, and one
thing that was maybe not so good.
And we really want to hear also the things to improve.
Yeah, I'm filling in answers here.
What about discussions and issues versus discussion and pull requests?
Yeah, that's a good question.
So if this is something bigger, a bigger change, or I'm not sure whether the repository wants
my change at all, I often start with an issue and first ask around like, is this a good
idea do you want this what is the right place which file so sometimes it starts
in issue but there can be also pull requests and then in a pull request I
can refer to the issue but there can also be pull requests which did not
start in an issue and it just appears there and then then maybe we continue
the discussion in a pull request the discussion in a pull request is maybe
more about okay how do I improve this thing and in the issue it's more about what is a
good starting point is this the right approach is this something we want at all
and sometimes discussion up here on both places and that's okay too and then but both can cross
reference each other so the issue can then refer to the pull request the pull request
can refer to the issue.
Under feedback for something to improve for next time,
there's this concept of Git push that wasn't introduced.
And I think that's partly our thing.
So we will introduce it properly tomorrow, I believe.
So today, we only introduced enough
to go through the GitHub web interface.
And of course, people could do more.
There were instructions there.
But we, yeah, like it's sort of this like dependency thing.
But don't worry, we will get to it all.
Yeah, so some things are a little bit vague by design,
but they will get clarified.
It's like looking at a blurry picture
and it will get clearer tomorrow
and even clearer on Thursday.
and it's all a balance to to not overwhelm with too many details as on day one but yeah concepts
like what is really happening when we push what is happening when we pull we will do more of that
tomorrow and really we will get an understanding of it on thursday yeah feedback positive thing
cute cat very often we have this wanting to improve more more cat
it's usually there on days the cat doesn't come by anyway yeah yeah and
thanks also for the feedback about that maybe some examples need more detail
maybe more screenshots more detail for the command line oh one one cool thing
about this workshop is that by Thursday you will all be able to send pull
request to this repository and also maybe send us improvements for the lesson.
And an improvement can also be opening an issue and telling us about there.
But thanks a lot for telling us here.
So we look at this feedback and the thing that we can improve for tomorrow we will.
The things that we can improve until next workshop we will as well.
Under one of the things to improve for next time, it goes back to the question of using
Git for things like Word documents.
Also, by the way, can you please not select everything on the page?
Because there's a risk of it all getting deleted and it highlights it for everyone.
Yes.
Thanks.
So, Word document.
So let's say you have a file that's not a traditional code file or whatever.
So in that case, you don't edit it through the GitHub web interface.
So yes, you can upload it, you can download it, things like that.
If you're on your own computer, you can put it there, you can edit it with Word, and then
And you would basically tell Git, okay, now please update your memory of this file each
time you make a commit.
And things like comparing can't be done in the GitHub web interface.
It can't be done through the other editors.
Actually there are different extensions you can use for Git which let you compare different
types of files, but let's ignore those for now.
So what we'd say as far as this lesson is concerned, if it's not a text file, then basically
you modify it however you would normally, and then you tell Git, remember this new copy,
record the changes.
And that's the extent of what we'll talk about for now.
Yeah, really looking forward to tomorrow.
We will also then talk about how to ignore certain files, because maybe not all the files
should go into repository.
We left it out today, but we will return to it.
And really, my goal is that by tomorrow, everybody is able to share their work on places like
GitHub or GitLab.
Yeah.
Can you scroll down a little bit?
I'm writing news for day one.
Oh, thanks.
So tomorrow, we will do many of the same things but on our own computers.
Is that correct?
Yeah.
Being able to clone, so being able to copy a repository from the web to the laptop and
continue there, but also do the opposite.
Being able to share my work so that others can copy it and others can contribute it.
These are the goals for tomorrow.
Is there any special preparation to do?
Yes, there is, because tomorrow, since we will work locally, we tomorrow we will need
either something like VS code or the command line
to go through all the steps.
Now, if somebody doesn't have these and only wants to do everything on the web, I would
say that please still show up there is maybe a few steps that you can you then
cannot follow because they are about how to make a local commit yeah and you'll
learn what to prepare for in the future so yeah that's completely fine also yeah
okay so not much to prepare for tomorrow there will be something to prepare for
day three for Thursday which because then we want to collaborate and we will
make it possible to collaborate even if for individual participants. So then we
will the individual participants we will invite you into our exercise repository
and for this you will need to do a few quick clicks but we will send them we
will send a message about this.
Yeah, so as soon as this is done, if not already, the replay will be available on Twitch and
last there for 7 days, and probably by midnight Eastern European time, the videos will be
processed and on YouTube. So, yes, you can catch up with everything we did today.
And what an amazing time management we have. So it's half past the hour. Thanks so much
everybody who contributed and there were many people, not only those who we've seen here
video but also people in the background preparing things managing exercise teams answering questions
so thanks so much everybody and we will see you tomorrow yeah great okay so see you later then
yeah thanks so much bye okay bye