bit of intro and see how it adjusts and then we can check more later. So, welcome everyone
to day two. Hopefully you all are as excited to be here as we are. What's the plan for
day two. So today it's [name] and [name] teaching. So what do we have in store?
It will be more git. I'm just setting up so that I can also see what we are actually streaming.
Are we now sharing the notes?
Yes, your screen is being shared.
Good. Yeah. Yeah, so there will be there will be morgit. And we will today move
Both from from the web to our computers and from our computers to the web.
So really the two goals are being able to take somebody else's project and continue
working on your computer.
Goal number one.
Goal number two is then be able to share your work with other people through places like
GitHub, GitLab.
And in between, we will learn a really nice set of tools to navigate in a project created
by other people, because that's the situation we are often in.
Yeah, so basically it's all about reaching, like someone said yesterday, connecting your
computer to the web, and then tomorrow is about using multiple people in projects.
Yeah, tomorrow will be a collaboration.
And I'm sharing here also two icebreaker questions.
One of them is more just for fun, and this is so that you can,
we actually want to see that people are able to edit the document.
So that's one thing we want to see.
and if you are unsure how to find it and how to edit I will say something about that once we
officially start in a couple of minutes. But the second question is really important for us
and that is which path did you use yesterday to interact with Git? So please let us know
and I will come back to this question. So this is really important for us that you vote here
and that you also let us know about paths that we should offer in future.
Yeah, and maybe you can even help us add some of the extra paths after you've done the course.
Yeah, so what was your overall outlook of yesterday?
Um, I think it went pretty well from I was really happy with what we achieved a day.
The first day is always tricky because we have a lot of us who are completely new to
getting it up.
We have learners who use it since quite some time and the day one is to really find the
the balance of getting everybody on the same page
and get like an understanding of what Git is.
And we try to find this balance
by offering these different paths,
like GitHub, like VS Code, like command line.
And we offer these different paths
because also we know that there is not this one tool
that will work for everybody.
we want to meet learners where they are.
And also among ourselves,
I'm sure that we use different tools.
And so, yeah, I was really happy with the progress.
Yeah.
I guess the main thing I got from the feedback
is we should have clarified the different paths
going together.
and made recommendations for which one to take.
So yeah.
And today we will do that because we need to do it.
So today I will spend a little bit of time at the beginning
to clarify that and also since today some of us might experiment with a different path
and we will show how
how you can set it up if you haven't done that already.
That's why also the first exercise will be a little bit longer to give people time to
set up and configure.
Yeah.
Okay.
I'll just rearrange my windows a little bit.
Great.
So looking at the icebreakers here, what do we see?
of interesting animals there. The person who wrote Homo sapiens wins, especially if it
counts ourselves. That's probably actually what most of us should have said.
I saw a moose yesterday.
Oh, nice.
I was driving in the dark and then it jumped over the road.
Okay.
Oh.
Yeah.
Yeah, so I guess from the second question, it's about what we would have hoped and the
people who tried a combination of different paths,
that's actually good.
So I agree with what people said.
It's hard to do basically all the exercises twice
unless you're already really good at one of them.
But this is what we want people to be
able to see in the end, how these are actually
pretty similar going together, and they
can all do the same things.
and seeing what is the common thing there, but maybe we should also clarify that there was no
expectation that people now go through all the paths so that they choose one path. We can also
see that we will need something for our studio. The good news is that today I think we will have
some options for that. Do you have a preferred path you work through, [name]?
or are you using all all types so now for my own work yeah
for my own work it's most of the time it's command line
but if i can do something quick on the web i will do it quickly on the web
so it's command line and a little bit of github um yep have you tried this trick with
pressing the dot and then getting an editor on github yes that's a nice trick we should maybe
show that uh yeah we could have mentioned it later uh when we when we edit files yeah yeah
maybe let's remember to use it um then also today uh it will be possible to to do most of
today just with github but there is one portion that
for this we will need something to work locally but if if it doesn't work it's not a problem
you can then skip it and like 70 percent of today can be done in github alone okay
but i think we are ready to start three minutes past so maybe i'll head off and start watching the
questions again and leave you all to it yeah okay good great thanks a lot see
you later yep it's maybe it'll start by introducing ourselves and then I will
introduce this notes document that we are looking at on because that's an
important tool for us to so that you can interact and ask questions and give us
feedback. But first, yeah, hello here from Northern Norway. My name is [name], and
I've been doing these kind of workshops since many years and I really enjoy it. The rest
of my time I work with high performance computing and really supporting researchers and students
with everything around computing and programming. And with me is my colleague [name] from Tonheim.
Yeah, good morning. My name is [name]. I work at the high performance group at the
Norwegian University of Technology and Science. So I've been part of cold refinery for quite
some years. And I like doing these workshops. So I'm really looking forward to today.
Yeah, so let's get started here first.
If you joined today, I just wanted to very briefly explain this document here that I'm
looking at.
And first of all, how do you find it?
You find it when you register to the workshop, you either got an email from me a couple of
days ago that contains the link.
If you registered after, it's also not a problem,
then it was in the automatic reply during your registration.
So there you can find the link to this document.
It's a document, it's like collaborative notes,
we can all view and edit.
I'm now looking at it in the view mode,
but there is somewhere an edit button, edit pen, so if I click on the edit pen it switches
to edit mode and in the edit mode I can then edit and please try it so please try to to
add something for so I also saw some neighbor cat walking by so test it out
And then below here we have this other question that is really important for us and that is
which path did you choose yesterday to interact with git.
And it's not a problem if you were not here yesterday.
You should mention that we try to stay anonymous so we leave out your name so don't add your
name to the document.
Oh great point yeah.
So here I don't use any names, but please ask lots of questions.
We will, after each day, we also publish the notes as part of the workshop.
So they become part of the workshop outcomes.
And I will scroll back to this question here, but below, you can then always find a link
to where we will be.
will now just post the link on where you can find today's material. So we will be very, very soon
starting here. Start today at here. And as we then go through different episodes, we post links to it.
it. And what we would really like you to do is to ask lots of questions. And the best
place to ask questions is at the bottom of the document, because we will hopefully get
I hope that we get at least 100 questions today. You can number the questions. I will
make an example here, for instance. Let's start with the question number one. Is this
the way, is this the place to ask? And somebody can answer. And somebody's answering. And
this is also why we are here, two instructors, plus we have our colleague in the studio,
so that we can, we are several people, we watch these questions. We will answer all
of them. And some of them we will then lift and we will discuss them in voice. So the
more questions, the better. And no question or too simple or too stupid
to ask. Ask anything about anything, really. Yeah. If you have a question is very likely
that somebody else has the same question and was too afraid to ask. So please ask it. Also
Also reminder, we use a code of conduct, so let's be all nice to each other.
This is like in any other professional setting.
And if you see something that is not right, please point it out.
We will also be...
We just want to create a really welcoming and nice atmosphere in this workshop.
But now that we got the housekeeping done, I will now navigate to this link.
can navigate that with me. So maybe the best way to participate today is to on one half of your
screen to have the nodes open. And this is also why our screen share is portrait mode and not
landscape mode. And on the other half of the screen you can then either have the GitHub open
or your editor, or your terminal.
And I will now navigate to the lesson material,
which, well, you can open somewhere else on your screen.