So from the notes that [name] was very kind to explain
that [name] was very kind to explain.
There's this link access request report which is also very well explained in the email
and there are links. So you should go to this report
and open a new issue. So what you should say is that
please add me as a collaborator. That's the only thing we need.
The reason that we are going to do is to get your username. So once you get the
username,
so we are going to work as a team or
have this feeling that if you are in a
team or that you want to contribute to
something that you don't have access.
So please open an issue if you have not
opened it yet and our Code Refinery
colleagues because I'm not I'm going to
to now switch my tab.
I might not see the issues.
So I'll be very grateful if you could help me
to add new people if they come.
Does that explain, [name]?
Yes, so one thing I want to add is
if you are working as a team, that you don't need
to send an access request here.
So there you will be working with your team
and your team leader will create a repository for you to work.
that's if you're an individual learner this is what you would we would like you to do
to participate in the collaborative exercise okay then maybe in the notes our colleagues could help
include that task for the voting as well like if there isn't a team i'm in the background here and
and accepting requests.
Thank you very much.
Thanks, [name].
And then from the collaborative document
or from the Code Refinery website,
you have today's course, the September course.
And we are already done with day one and two.
We really hope you got some new knowledge from this
and enjoyed what you learned.
So we are in day three.
So I'm in this collaborative distributed virtual control
first part, one of two.
So that is where I am here.
So on the first page, we are summarizing some introductions
and summaries about the things we are going to learn.
And on the menu side, you could jump into different sections.
But what I'm going to do is click the Next button
to start the new lesson.
So the concept around collaboration.
So what are the motivation?
Why do we need to learn this?
So as mentioned here, someone has given you
access to a repository online, and you want to contribute.
Let's say the Code Refinery website.
It's also in Git.
And myself, and [name], and [name], and [name],
and everybody, they were invited to contribute.
So we became contributors in that.
But it might be not that it's not you who created it.
It's somebody who created, maybe it's an organization created,
and you've been invited.
And we'll learn how to make copies of repositories.
So let's say there are so many instances that you
might want to have a copy.
So let's say if you're working on your laptop
or your local computer and you want to modify the code,
then you have to get it down to your computer.
That one example. There are other examples that we talk a little later.
Then [name], this Git as a technology,
there are different companies are involved.
For example, the GitHub,
you have the GitLab, there was GitBucket,
and so many other smaller companies.
And also, you could have this Git hosted on your institute.
For example, in University of Oslo,
we have our own Git, which is github.uio.no.
In our entries organization that we work,
we have gitlab.sigma2.no.
So there are different places.
So because of these different companies,
you might find slight variations of the terminology.
For example, we will be using the word pool request.
another company might, GitLab would use merge request. So pool merge, we might switch between
these terms when we move between companies, but because we are mostly following up in GitHub,
we will use GitHub terminology more in this lesson. So once we know how to contribute,
We will be going through a concept called code review.
So this is to make sure that something that, for example,
I want to contribute something, but I unknowingly
broke something.
And then we don't want to go that into production.
There should be some other people just having a look.
For example, [name], in newspapers,
people publish a lot of articles.
So this has got to an editor.
and there's some proof-checking going on.
So it's something like that, but it's
more a peer-assisted process, like you
have your co-developers, or maybe a supervisor is doing
that, or maybe one of your peers doing that.
So we'll talk about that as well.
Does that cover the things that you're going to do,
the reason for learning Git collaboration today, [name]?
Or do you have anything else to add?
Yeah, you covered most of it. Thanks. And I just want to mention all these workflows.
You mentioned about GitLab, BigBucket, and GitHub, everything, and there are slight variations in
the terminology, but the workflow is same for all this version control cloud in web interfaces. So
when you learn Git, today we are going to discuss on GitHub web interface, but the workflow you are
learning would be applicable to other.
If your university, if your organization having a GitLab,
then you can implement all you learned today on that as well.
So there is not much changes, slight variation
in the terminology.
That's what I want to mention.
That's a great point.
Like, if you know the core concepts,
you can apply it across different companies.
And I will try to explain a little bit about the terms,
[name], so you have to help me that I don't go over time.
Because the main focus of this lesson
is for you to practice, so the learners to practice.
And this lesson is redesigned, actually.
I think it has matured very well since we started.
That learn by doing, and then we discuss.
So it's not about me talking a lot,
but we tell you, inform you the things you need to know.
And then you have to learn a bit more by yourself.
So please help me to keep track of my time
because these two could go into tangents
and we could discuss so many things.
Now we are in the third day.
So if you had followed the course already up to now
or you're just joining today,
you know a little bit quick.
The concept that we're gonna talk,
We expect you to know a little bit of Git by this time,
which means that you have followed the course last two days or you are joining today,
but you have some knowledge.
So a repository.
So when you mean a repository,
it means it contains all the data,
the history, the commits that you might now remember what a commit is,
the branches, everything included.
This is the complete package.
Then a commit would be that the snapshots you saved with a message that you remember that
hash is included to sort of unambiguously identify the commit. And then you could tag it,
you could give some label or like some placeholder that you can find later.
And then other terms that we might focus more,
cloning and forking.
So these terms, I don't think memorizing
would help these terms.
But when you work, you get it naturally,
get into your muscle memory, what these things are
and how you do things.
So I'm not going to spend too much time
on describing each term.
And also, [name] with Git, what I found out
is that rather than learning what is a commit is,
learning the overall process and find out
where a commit fits helps me to understand better.
For example, now we're going to talk
cloning and forking and using templates
and copying repositories.
All this we will try to kind of learn together,
but there are different concepts.
So there are many ways to get a copy.
So one way is to get a clone.
So that is how you work specifically
when you want to get a copy of something
to your local computer.
I could give you two examples.
One is that I want to get some code from computer code
from somebody who is hosting on the web on GitHub.
And then I want to do some modifications.
And I want to maybe contribute back.
or maybe for my use, I need to do some modification,
then I need to get this code to my computer.
When I want to, when we're preparing for this lesson,
when we want to modify some text on CodeRefiner website,
I made a clone of the CodeRefiner website to my laptop.
I made the change, and I send it back requesting,
can you please incorporate this?
you could do the same thing in the cloud,
which means that without cloning to your laptop,
you could clone it inside GitHub itself
and have the copy in the cloud.
So the way I kind of understand the difference
between a clone and a fork that we'll talk next
is that the clone is in your computer,
but if the clone is in the GitHub itself,
it's we call it fork.
So when you have it on your local computer,
there's total disconnect while you work,
unless you explicitly take measures to synchronize it.
But in a fork, because it's inside GitHub,
these repositories somehow have some knowledge of each other.
So you could, like, if the upstream, which
means where we copied the repository from,
If there's an update, it could inform,
GitHub inform that it has happened.
And in addition, issues.
So when we talk about issues a little later on,
these issues could be referenced from your fork.
So there is some kind of a connection
because it's in the same place, same cloud.
There's more connection between the copy
that we make in the cloud
than the copy we have in our laptop.
Does that make sense, Daryan?
Yes, I just want to mention I will clone some repository if there is some program I want
to just run.
It's my data.
So I sometimes I won't contribute back.
I just want to have that program with if that's a library or public repository, I will clone
it and do my work myself with this different data maybe.
That's a very good point.
we want your software, let's say if you want to compile it, compile software on our systems,
we clone it. And that is a very good example of a clone. Yes.
And then when you want to create a repository, but you don't want everything, but you want to
create something that looks like something else. So these folks and clones, they could
they could make entire copies.
But don't worry too much,
but if you know a little bit Git,
I would also like to mention something
that you could actually explicitly define
how deep the copy is.
For example, you don't have to copy all the branches.
You don't have to copy all the comments.
So I'm just trying to place some commands
in the HCI documents later on.
You have commands like depth.
No, you could define, even in forking and cloning,
you could also define how much of,
how much, how deep you want the copy to be.
But when you don't want to like explicitly mention that,
you could use something like a template,
which means the example given here is the cookie cutter.
So what is a cookie cutter, [name]?
I tried to have the same shapes of the cookies,
I would say.
Like I can make cookies without cookie cutter,
but if I want the same kind of pattern in my cookies,
I will use this cookie cutter.
So I will get the same shapes.
Okay, so what does this mean in Git world?
Git world, you take a similar kind of pattern
in your repository.
if you're taking from a template,
you get the repository, you take a template,
it will be similar, but the history will be flattened.
That's what I would say.
But I think we will go through this.
If you are working with a team,
you will take a template from our CR
collaborative workshop repository.
Yeah.
So we will have it in our exercise, but there is one question about question number six.
You want to take it?
Maybe we will come back to it when we have the exercise, but do you want to mention it
[name]?
What was that, Dhani?
Because I want to finish it in four or five minutes now, but if you can read me the question,
we could see what it is.
Yeah, how to push us to local fork compared to synchronizing to the upstream source where
you fork from? Is there a way to commit and push to the place one forked from?
So a good question, very good question. And it has become much easier to do that now,
but we will demonstrate that later. And then I would say that as a question you could ask,
if you don't know, maybe one of our instructors, our colleagues could ask as well.
There's a command called squash, so that command we need to, it's good to understand when we
talk about templates, the command called squash, we could discuss a little bit in the
HackMD. So here we get a copy. What if, [name], let's say we talked about different companies.
You have something in GitHub, but you want to transfer it to GitLab. And you said in the
morning that if you learn the concept, it's easier to move between these things.
Is it possible to move something from GitHub to GitLab?
I assume so, yes.
Yes, yeah.
So for that, you could use commands like import.
So it's possible to import a GitHub repository to GitLab.
But there might be functionalities
that will not be fully copied.
And things which are metadata, like issue connections,
that might get not copied, but they could also synchronize.
Because, [name], as we said in the morning,
our main attempt today is to learn by doing.
So what we'll do is we go to an exercise.
Would you be kind enough to maybe take my screen
and explain what we are planning to do
and the timing, and a little bit about the exercises.
Yes, I will try to take over the screen.
Yeah, my screen looks OK.
So I had to stop my sharing now to [name].
Is it safe for me to stop the sharing?
Can [name] just take it over without you stopping?
I am sharing from my side.
Can you?
Okay.
Then maybe Sarpreet should stop.
Zoom changed.
Yeah.
Okay.
There it goes.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, we are going to prepare for the exercise, but you have had a lot of them in the last
15 minutes, commit branches, pull request,
or merge request, template and everything.
Don't worry, don't get overwhelmed.
And we are going to really do the hands-on
and then we get the practice.
So now what we are going to do is
we are going to collaborate.
Last two days, you did your own repository examples
and you try to fork or clone.
So today is as a team,
we are collaborating on this code refinery workshop,
collaborative workshop repository.
So if you are,
there are two ways to participate in this exercise.
One as a team,
and you, I assume you are in an exercise room.
And if you have a team member, team leader, that's great.
if not, assign someone as the team leader
so that they can create a template for you to collaborate.
So what we are going to do is,
if you are in a team or an individual learner,
we will contribute to a repository via a pull request
that [name] mentioned.
Pull request, I would say,
is the way to communicate between,
pull and push are some words I would use to communicate,
and pull request is suggest changes.
And someone, as [name] mentioned,
someone will review it and accept it
so that your changes are there in the repository.
That's what we are going to do that.
So if you are in a group, if you have a team leader,
there are some work for the team leader to do
is only one person.
If you don't have a team leader assigned,
one person can take the role and create a template from here.
We have these screenshots here, and you
can create the template, use the template,
and then add everyone in your group in that repository.
So you will have a repository under when
you create a template from this repository,
you will have one repository under your namespace
as a team leader.
Then what you have to do is other team members
have to give their username to the team leader
and the team leader should give access
to your team members to the repository
and then you will be able to contribute.
So that's one preparation as a team leader you have to do.
And I will come back to you about a little bit more
it, but please create a template first. Then we have many individual learners. We are here.
What you are going to do is you are collaborating with us. So, we are a collaborator, and there
are two repositories. One is not recorded and recorded. Recorded is what we will show
on the stream, and if you don't want to show your usernames and things on stream, you use
the not recorded one, and the recorded one is for those we will show on the stream.
But the first thing is you have to have access to this repository.
That's what we were mentioning in the beginning, that please ask for access, and we will give
you access.
you are the team member of this repository, and you can collaborate. That's what, as an individual
learner, if you want to do this exercise, you have to do, if you already haven't done it.
So, yeah, if you did that, when you accept, you will get an email notification, and on this
this same email you have GitHub know about your username.
So you will need to accept it.
Then only you become part of the collaborative repository.
So just send an access request.
Then you get an email notification.
You have to accept it.
And there was something more.
It's both for the team leaders, teams,
and also for the individual learners,
that you are supposed to watch this.
If I can go to my GitHub and you see that
there is an eye icon with watch,
you can click on the participating and mentioning.
Otherwise, if you have it as all activities,
there will be more emails coming to you.
It might be overwhelming for you and I, do you think that is a good idea to have an all
activity?
[name]?
Yeah.
So the, because we, because there might be a lot of learners, we are doing a lot of,
many people are joining at the same time, there might be overwhelming.
So what you recommended is better.
Yeah.
So that you can do as a team lead,
also you can mentioning the participating and mention
that then you will get notified when there is an activity
on that you are involved in,
or someone mentioned you on one of the issues
or pull request or something.
So we expect that you take only the participating
and mentions.
Otherwise, it's not a problem, but you will get a lot of notification.
That's why this is recommended.
So these are the setup we are expecting for you to check before that.
But when you are added, I wanted to give you some information about the
background, what we are going to do about it, this is the recorded repository
that we are going to show you on screen.
So, if you go to the settings option, there is collaborators and teams.
Stream exercise participant is where we add all of you who request access to this repository.
And I will change the role, the default role is read.
So we will...
So, [name], before you go, you show that settings menu how to come in.
So if you are working on a smaller screen,
this might be hidden.
So you might have to zoom out or zoom in.
Sometimes the menus could be hidden, but those are there.
Yes, yeah.
Good point, [name].
That's one reason I am a bit zoomed out,
because I wanted to show the settings part.
So the default role is read, but we
wanted everyone to collaborate, all these members
and the stream exercise participants.
We have 44 members now.
So if you haven't done it yet, you can give it.
This is something the team leaders also should do.
When they accept members, they have
to give the right access to those members.
So go to Settings and Collaborates and Teams.
Then you find your members and give right access.
It's default, it will be read access.
And the other point is you have to protect your main branch.
So you have to create a rule for your,
we already create one rule for our main branch.
You can edit it.
And what it means is you cannot forcefully push changes to it.
you have to have a pull request before merging it
to the repository so that the maintainers or other people
can review the changes and approve it and then merge it.
So otherwise, if main branch is not protected,
anyone can push changes directly to the main branches.
That's not a good workflow when you collaborate together.
Anything you want to add, [name]?
Yeah, you explain it very well.
So the main branch or the master branch, sometimes it's called.
Or in some companies, they have this production branch,
where the actual product goes out.
So there are some branches that are protected.
People can't, without anybody else knowing,
just make a modification.
So when you protect it, other people
must be made aware in order to have this accepted and integrated. So it's become like a
team awareness protocol rather than kind of policing things. It's not like making
things difficult, but it is to make sure that all changes go through some review process.
Yeah, good. We have already done this for you, those who are individual learners
and participating with us. But the team members, if you're working with a team, the team leader
is expected to do this on their repository. So we are working on this workflow exercise
recorded version on stream. The individual learners, they don't need to do anything.
We already have done it. But if you're working with a team, the team leader or the responsible
person who would create the template from the CodeRefinery repository. You are expected to
protect your main branch and also give right access to your collaborators. Yeah. So I think
we have the setup mentioned, and then after you have done this setup, that's what we are going
to do is we are going to collaborate. We have all these terms explained, but you can find,
if you create the commit locally, how to do that, and everything is linked in the exercise part. So,
if you don't remember things, that's okay. You can go back and see. But what we expected you to
do during this exercise is that you open an issue where you describe the changes you want
to make, for example, on this for the individual learners, you can create an issue here and
then create a new branch from there and make changes in your branch, commit there and push
your new branch to the repository you are working on. So, [name], when you said issue,
you explained this. I'm just trying to iterate it just to make sure people understand it.
people could work on three places now, isn't it?
So they could work on our centralized workflow
recorded, where their names will be visible.
And then they could work on centralized workflow not
recorded version, where they'll not be shown in our videos.
Or they will work on the repository
their team leader creates.
So they have to select where they work,
and then the issue should be created in that location.
Is that correct?
Yes.
So yeah, for those individual learners,
you create an issue on this workshop exercise
recorded or non-recorded according to your preferences.
And this is what you want to change.
And then create a branch, make the changes,
and push your new branch to the repository you are working on.
Then open a pull request after pushing your branch.
Then you can see somebody else pull request there.
You can review it if you have enough time.
And then we will come back, and we will review it together here
as well on the stream.
At least we expected to do that until step five.
OK, so when you create a branch, [name],
there could be different ways to do that as well.
Maybe people can do it in the GitHub itself.
They could use VS Code.
They could clone it and create a branch.
So there could be multiple workflows people follow.
So there's no exactly one way to achieve this.
But the concept that we are going to learn
is to open the issue and make your changes in the branch,
not in the main branch.
Because now the main branch is actually so protected.
So wherever that you are going to work,
on the terminal, on the web, on ID,
like integrated development environment
like some other program, you could
follow this, the same things.
And maybe, [name], it's better to create a new file,
I mean like a new recipe, than editing an existing file
because multiple people might edit it.
So that's a good concept to learn
if you know a little bit Git.
But in order to learn today's concepts about contributing,
and maybe we could try to avoid little bit complications
like conflicts, for example, which is OK to happen.
Those are good concepts in Git.
But while we learn the basics, it's
better to maybe create a new file.
What do you think?
Yeah.
But I really like if someone changes something also.
but that's a good thing if you want to review
and add a new file is a good thing.
But in reality, you will have sometimes some conflict,
but the best part is if you create an issue
and you describe the changes you want to make,
and if you're working on it, assign it to yourself.
So then the other people know that you're working on it.
So mention it, but we will come back to it,
how to show it after the exercise.
But now we expect at least until step five
in the next 20 minutes.
What do you think [name]?
We will give it 20 minutes to exercise time.
Yes, 20 minutes and we'll have like a poll.
If you want five minutes more, it's okay to take it.
But in the shared document,
we will ask whether you are finished or not.
If many people want more time, it's okay.
We can be a little flexible
because exercise are the most important thing.
We'll do that.
And [name], one thing is now we're going to break for exercise, which means that we're
going to stop talking and the learner is supposed to do the exercise and there'll be some microphone
silence.
Yeah, and actively contribute to this collaborative document and let us know how it goes.
It's very important for us to get your feedback.
Maybe we could write the exercise time, 20 minutes until 10 here, at least.
Yes.
Yes, please.
Please also mention our colleague who's editing it that if they want more time, please ask.
So it's no point like rushing or like doing it halfway.
Yeah.
So 20 minutes is the sort of target, but if you want a little bit more, we can adjust.
[name], I think we should give them some time now
to wrap this around and then do the exercise.
And we'll see you on the other end in that case.
Do you want to keep your screen shared, [name]?
Or do you want somebody else to take it?
OK, we'll do [name], probably, share the notes.
Yes, I'm ready to do that.
Thank you.
Say bye when you're ready.
Bye.
Yes, welcome back.
I see that most of you have done the exercise and we have received a lot of cool results
requests.
[name], what we do now is that we are
to discuss the answers a little bit
and also the questions in the shared document.
First, we shall have a break now.
I mean, break means you should stop working and walk around
and maybe have some coffee or tea.
And then we'll be back.
How long should we take, [name]?
10 minutes break.
10 minutes?
OK.
So we're going to break for 10 minutes,
and then we meet here again to discuss.
So see you in 10 minutes.
Welcome back, [name], did you have some rest or were you working?
Yeah, I took my break.
OK.
So [name], before I go into this, the request,
the viewing the pull requests, I forgot
to show that this insight.
So that's something very exciting to see sometime.
So on the inside, you have something called the network.
Here, it will show what's going on in a graphical view.
So these are the people who are these different colors
are like different branches.
And then they work, for example, this yellow branch.
Let me make sure that I'm in the recorded version.
Yes, I'm in the recorded repo.
So this yellow change now incorporated
into the main branch, white one.
So the green one also here.
So the purple one is also here.
So the yellow and the purple are not the same
because they are two different recipes,
but both of them are now in main.
And once we accept pull requests,
this one is not accepted yet,
so this will also go back into the production.
So [name], our aim is to contribute to a repository
that you have access to,
but not without modifying the main branch.
So a pull request was sent, as you described,
and people have sent the pull request.
And I have sent the request as well.
I see that you have also sent it.
I'll just give a quick glance of what is next.
So that is the code review that we'll talk a little later.
But [name], while we are here, in this exercise,
we'll talk a little bit about the review as well,
and then summarize later on.
Is that OK?
Yes, and I just want to say thank you
to all the requests as well as all the issues created.
That was very good to see.
And we will discuss some of the questions here as well, [name],
that I suppose we will have time.
OK, OK, let's do that.
Is there anything very interesting to take first?
Very important?
All these I see an answer.
OK, so there are some technical questions.
Our colleagues, do you see anything
that we should discuss here?
OK, working in the areas code.
OK, so this is also a very specific technical question
that has been answered.
Yeah.
And there are some questions about where can you add that source answer fixes that we will show.
OK.
Yeah, so if this happens, sometimes you clone it and you start working on it,
and then you realize you're in the main branch. So the answer given by our colleague is to
Yeah, so the two things are given.
So I like the second way that because you are not
saying your request yet, although it is your main
branch, you could create a branch from that main branch
and send it to the pull request.
And then if you send only the branch
that you want to be evaluated in the pull request,
it will not make a difference.
You could also reset and do again, yes.
VS Code, to be honest, [name], I don't use regularly.
I know how it works.
So if there's any questions, we need some help
from our colleagues with that.
And if you see in our documents, we have these tabs.
For example, this is VS Code, and this is command line.
So we give the side-by-side comparison.
So if you show something in the command line,
it shows how to do it in VS Code.
It doesn't mean that you are doing
VS Code and command line.
You can select which one to follow.
One thing I want to mention is if you
are working on command line and VS Code,
you have to authenticate with your SSH key to push the changes.
Otherwise, you will have permission issues.
Do you want to comment on that, [name]?
Can you describe a little bit, [name]?
So if you are working on command line
and you push your changes to the repository,
if your SSH authentication is not right,
you will not be able to push the changes to the repository.
Yes, yes.
So I think if they have set up the keys, it should be OK.
If you face such an issue, please ask here
and we'll try to solve this for you.
Yeah, two things you need to have.
you need to have a permission to push it to this repository
where you have to be a collaborator
to push the changes from your local command line.
And the other thing is you have SSH set up.
OK.
So I see that somebody got this error
as which means that they are not requested that access issue.
They are not open the issue that we discussed.
So they are open an issue asking access.
And then another thing is it doesn't matter really
what you call the branch.
But for myself, the pull request I sent,
let's see if I can find it.
I used the branch I used.
I used my name in front and some indication.
Because it's easier for me to find,
and maybe it's easier to locate with that.
So the default, the name that was used
is that unfinished work, new branch, something.
The branch name doesn't really matter,
but it should kind of indicate what this is about.
Then shall we go through your pull request?
[name], are you ready?
Yes and I have added one more person to the reviewer and I got a nice comment on that but
you can review again [name] and accept it. Where is it? Your 31 was it? Yeah it would be a chia seed pudding.
Okay so I think it's close maybe. Okay. Let's see. Open. I'll just try to get it with the
the number because I think it's the other random reviewer.
Yeah.
Okay, it's merged.
So now, [name], we are in a predicament.
So we have like a unplanned event now.
It's been accepted.
So I can't, you know, I could open it and do it.
But would you like to take my screen
and review my pull request instead?
Yeah, that I can do.
Yeah, when you're ready, just grab it.
Okay.
It's not a random person, maybe it's one of our learners.
So thank you for doing that.
Yes.
And thank you for the comment.
That's not something we were just going to discuss.
Where is your pull request, [name]?
My pull request?
I think [name] needs to stop screen sharing now.
Okay.
So I will stop and my request is 16, pull request number 16.
Sorry, the issue is 16, pull request 26.
Okay, yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
So I see you made some changes
and from your pull request I said made it sweeter
and there is fixes 16 and 26.
You created some issues, I assume.
Shall we go to the issues just to see that what is it?
Or you want to?
No, you could go to the issue.
And before that, I would like to mention
that we should have actually mentioned.
So this is public.
And we were supposed to follow the code of conduct
and make sure that what we type here and where to send
is ethically correct and not sort of breaks those rules.
So I hope you already knew and you did that.
So sorry, we should have mentioned that before,
to be considerate about what's being shown on the internet.
Yes, I opened an issue.
Why is it needed to open an issue, [name]?
What do you think is the?
I just wanted to see what you are going to fix it.
I can check the file changes and see, but maybe what was the issue?
So the issue, the reason I opened the issue, [name], is that to inform the developers or
the people who are involved that I'm working on it.
One thing that could happen is, let's say I'm going to suggest this thing, but it's
not necessarily in the plan, so that doesn't necessarily fit the main repository or the
the main developer's plan or the team's plan.
So I don't want to work on something for a long time
and then send it.
And then just to say, you know, this doesn't fit.
So start early, before even like making this first change,
open an issue, say that, you know, I have this idea,
I'm going to start working on it.
So that has two, maybe more advantages,
but two advantages are there.
One is people will know that I'm working on it.
If somebody really think doesn't work,
they should mention it.
And the other thing is if another person,
if another developer, another colleague
planning to do the work,
that person could collaborate instead of,
you know, starting on their own thing.
So now it is well-informed.
Okay, the issue is here.
And this will also create some metadata
about what we're going to do.
So later on, this will remain forever.
So it can be closed, but it will be there.
So in later on, you could come and check,
you know, what things happen in a chronological order.
You know, these are submitted.
There was some, were there any changes
who accepted the pull request?
In addition to the pull request,
there'll be some documentation or a paper trail,
we call it, you know, the issue.
So the issue was open.
Yes, then that was it.
And one thing I can add is that you can open an issue if you find something is wrong or
something is there and you are not working on it, but let your other members know that
there is an issue.
So you don't need to assign it to yourself, but if you find something needs to change,
there is something we can fix.
You don't need to fix it.
Someone else can fix it to let that there is an issue.
So that way also you can open an issue.
not necessary that you need to work on that issue that you open. Yes, and also the word issue,
it doesn't really mean something broken, it could be improvement. So on the GitHub world,
we have issues. In the GitLab world, if you're working with lab world, you have issues and
incidents. Now, there are slightly different ways to indicate what you're doing. The main thing is
the word issue does not mean that, you know, there's a problem, it could be an improvement,
it could be some new feature, it could be something broken as well. So it's not just
for reporting bugs. Go ahead, [name]. And I could show that the issue that you are
having a sweeter version of sweet pumpkin pie. I assume that there is a sweet pumpkin pie
somewhere and you want to add a sweeter version of that. Yes. So what do you think about this?
is like, is it enough information here?
No, unfortunately, I have to assume many things here.
Yes.
So if one thing I can ask you, if I see that you haven't
assigned it here, but if you want to work on it,
you can assign to yourself here.
And there are some levels we could add.
If it is bulk documentation enhancement,
I assume that you are supposed to enhance something already there.
Yeah.
So there's also a good way to add here, assign labels and et cetera.
And if I don't find things, maybe provide a bit more context on this.
I, we can have a conversation if it is not, if you are not working on it also,
but on an issue, as a collaborator, we can have a discussion and find out a
common ground to further develop this problem or improvement
or anything.
So now you found my issue, and the quality of the issue
is not that good.
It's not descriptive.
So that should be more mentioning.
And you found that it's better to add a label itself.
So could you add a label for me, a suitable label,
so it will be the next person who
will see the issue as better?
Yes, and I just want to mention that this label
is different for projects, you can edit labels.
You can add labels according to your project needs.
So you can add like in progress or whatever you want,
that there is an option to edit labels,
but this is already mentioned some labels.
So I will use an enhancement.
Maybe I will ask [name] to give more context to this.
I can mention him here.
So [name] will get notified whenever I mention
and comment it here.
So we can have a conversation.
And then one more thing that might be a little confusing
is that the question 21,
the question that asked about this permission issues,
opening an issue will not give you permission on this repo.
So what I mentioned in the beginning about opening issue
was there was this repository
that we were giving permissions, adding you to a group.
So you had to open issue there, so we can manually
take your username and give you permission.
So opening an issue in this report
does not mean you get permission to push.
So just a clarification.
Yeah, good point, [shari].
So we can have a conversation here,
but just let us go to your full request.
Yeah.
So I can see that you have one commit and one file changed.
Shall we go?
Yes.
So I purposefully made it extremely sweet.
So maybe it doesn't fit.
Maybe you could see whether that's OK.
And I could change if it doesn't.
So this is now we are actually in the review process, which
is the next topic that we're going to talk about.
But we'll start from now itself.
So how do you make a suggestion, [name],
in addition to being polite and being considerate?
Yeah, mostly I see that this is all these plus signs.
That means it's only addition to these changes.
Normally, if there is plus lines,
I will not have much to look at it.
That's how I work, because it's.
But if you have some changes here,
then you will see that there is a red color rather than
a green color, right?
That's a good point, [name].
So if it is an existing file, and it has a difference,
the things added will be green, things deleted will be red.
But because this is a new file that Kit didn't know before,
everything is green.
Yeah, you can see that here, plus 37 lines added,
there is no line changed.
This is something I will look into it first.
Mostly there is something changed.
Then what about line 17?
What do you think in this file?
40 cups sugar.
Yeah.
So yes.
Yeah, I will click on this plus sign or on this line,
and I will.
OK, yeah, it's too sweet, isn't it?
Then when you, yeah, so just send me the,
when you click the button, I'll also get the message
that you informed that.
Yeah, so I see that you're using like maybe words like maybe, could, you know, the feedback
should be, you know, it should be, you know, positive in a way that, you know, the changes
are sent, but it should start kind of like a negative conversation saying, you know,
this is bad.
Can we change it?
You could use the same thing.
You could convey the message that it
has to be changed in the polite language.
I see that you are being extremely polite.
What does beta mean?
Oh, by the way.
Yeah, OK.
Yeah, thanks for the recipe.
And then I will add this single comment or start review.
Where do you do?
What do you do?
So you could start the review.
So, yes.
Yeah, so then let me check whether I got that message.
Let me see.
Yes, you have done that.
Slight delay on my part.
I'm still waiting.
OK.
Yes, I've still not got it.
But until that, my side refreshes.
Let's say if you want to make a change directly, how would you do that?
So I will answer this, the 40 cups sugar in a moment.
But let's say if you want to change, for example,
salt amount, is it possible as a reviewer
for you to suggest a change directly in addition
to asking me?
Yeah, I can directly suggest that.
For that, I usually go to the branch and do the changes.
But there is the, yeah, go ahead, Sudhir.
Yeah, so I mean, during the review process,
that let's say if you want to change something,
you don't have to necessarily like open a new pull request
or close it.
So that's what you are trying to say maybe.
Yes, yes, yeah, that's right.
So if I'm a collaborator,
I have this permission to edit [name]'s branch
that he put, that's this pull request.
You can see that main from [name] sweet pumpkin.
So I can go and edit that.
So I will have the commit there.
And then the pull request will be updated accordingly.
There is no need for me to change anything there.
Yes.
Another thing we can do in the interface itself,
I see that because I'm not getting this, because you
are not finished your review.
Maybe we could, in that, yes.
If you can finish the review and make a commit
without approving it, then I might get the message.
So that is also a good thing that we
so that until you finish it, I don't get the message just
by answering that question.
So I can make this change?
Yeah.
Yeah?
Yes.
So you could submit that.
Okay, now I got it. So I'm going to.
Meanwhile, I will check if there is some questions that we need to answer.
Yeah, so then I, I replied to that, did you, did you see my reply?
Maybe a refresh of the pull request itself.
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay, so then somebody else has mentioned that as well.
What I'm saying here is that, okay, no, thank you, indeed, you know, you've found it, but I'm on a flight, you know, this is this internet on the flight. So let's see later whether you could change it for me. So the way, you know, the web interface that we could you do this easily as a reviewer is that if you go back to the file itself.
If you go to that 40, the number 17
Maybe on the on the last, yeah, yes, okay, when you click that, what happens?
Nothing happens.
That's strange.
Okay.
Yeah.
So that's, that's another another good catch as well.
So what I will do is that maybe if you go further downward, you see, yeah, so it's other
part of this fight.
So what I will do is, I will resolve this conversation.
You want to take over the screen?
No, no, no, no.
We have to find out how to do it properly,
because it's not happening as I expected,
but we'll figure it out.
If you refresh it again.
OK, now if you go to plus again, the yeah.
And you see that you have Google,
not that one, the plus.
And then after right, you have the button called review.
After that, you have this plus sign.
You go to right again.
After review, you find a small button.
If you click that, you could actually change from 40 to four
if you, yes, you could do a space
and then you could start the review.
Or like, you know, you could actually add the comment there.
And then you could finish up the review process.
You could actually approve it now
because now you have changed it.
Then now what happened is that
without even going to the terminal,
so you managed to find some issue
and you informed with me in a very polite
and very positive way, the positive feedback.
And then I couldn't change it for some reason.
And then as a reviewer, you managed to do the change
without even making a branch or anything.
You were in the same branch,
were in the same pull request, same narrative,
the same discussions going on,
on, the issue would be updated.
We did that there.
Yes.
And I need to commit the suggestion.
Correct.
Yeah.
And you could have a commit message there,
saying this was actually [name] who
tried to make it sick, not sick, too sweet.
So we had to reduce the sugar amount.
And oh, maybe it was a typo.
OK.
Assuming.
Yeah.
And then commit changes.
So one thing I want to show you here,
earlier it was only one commit.
And I did change this suggestion commit.
You can see that there are two commits.
And let's go and see that.
So first, once [name] mentioned and in that commit [name] mentioned the issue as well
that he was working on and then I fix, I committed the suggestion that I made.
Okay.
Shall we go back and merge it?
Yes, please.
So do you have, you have mentioned two issues here and let's see what happens when we merge
the pull request.
to the issue.
Have I mentioned two issues?
I think.
Uh-huh, yes.
That's actually a typo.
So before you close that, let me edit that title a little bit.
So you can do that with the edit?
No, actually, it is actually the, yeah.
So yeah, so that's a good point.
So it is not actually referring to two issues.
That means that it is the pull request number 26.
Oh, yeah.
In the title, I have mentioned the issue.
Yeah, yeah, of course.
Yeah, that's a good point.
Yes.
Yes, and I reviewed.
And maybe what you usually do, you say thank you message.
And I see [name] all the time saying thank you.
And he mentioned something.
Yeah, so he's too polite.
So yeah, we could mention that.
OK, now it's solved.
Thank you.
Yes.
And there are some questions in the HackMD,
The shared document, we'll come back to that a little later.
I see a lot of discussions going on with our colleagues.
OK.
Yeah, that's where we'll come back.
Now it's done.
So it's done.
And maybe we could just delete the branch as well,
because otherwise it'll collect a lot of unnecessary branches.
Yes.
That's done.
It's gone.
Deleting the branch doesn't lose any information,
because everything in that branch
is now integrated into the main branch.
Yeah, I just want to check what happened to the issue you created.
Yeah, it's closed.
If you click on the closed one and click on number 16.
Yeah, take one issue and type 16 at the end in the URL, maybe it's easier to
anything and at the end type 16.
Yeah, because it's a bit difficult for me.
Okay.
Let me see.
Closed.
Yeah, it's further down now, under closed, yes.
Yeah, you have one closed tissue.
Yes.
So I can get it.
That's a good.
Okay.
Can you, can you briefly explain what, how you found that again?
Yeah, I can.
issue. So I filter it. Yes, that's a good. Can you briefly explain how you found that again?
Yeah, I can. So we have issues and I was trying to see if [name]'s issue is here and I was not
able to find it. So I know that [name] was created with the issue. So he is the author. So I clicked
His name and I see there is no open issue on under his name and one closed issue.
So this is the one I found it like that.
You can use GitHub for many other like this, but it's not necessary that you need to find
everything today.
This is for you to have a hands on and we will.
I think when we do things only, we will find many ways.
I think I have to find many functions on the GitHub yet,
because I use GitLab every day.
Sometimes it's a bit difficult to find it here.
But that's OK.
It's the matter of time that you practice.
Yes.
And you can also see in the issue, [name],
the commit message, the commit that you did,
the hash for the commit, and also the merge request.
Everything is linked.
So you have some paper trail here as well.
Yeah.
Yes, OK.
I think that sort of summarizes what
we will plan to do for that part of the exercise.
Shall we have a look at the shared document as you add it
and see?
Let me check our chat to see whether our colleagues found
out something.
Yes.
There was supposed to be a mic option like yesterday,
And I didn't see that, so.
Question number 20.
Can you score what was it about?
Let's see.
Our colleague [name] is mentioning about it.
OK.
Interaction.
How to push and pull from local repository to GitHub, maybe.
OK.
So I think what I'll do is I can show that,
because we were doing on the terminal a lot.
Sorry, on the web page, because we
want to make it a little simple.
But I can show how to do that on the terminal,
if that makes sense.
How are we on time, Daniel?
I think we have almost 18 minutes till lunch break.
OK.
So is the next one we are starting after the lunch?
Yeah.
But I would like to discuss a little bit on the review
process and things.
Would be nice that we talk a little bit about the review.
So do you expect that if we collaborate,
only the owner or admin will review?
Or how do you explain the reviewing?
because I reviewed it, and I just want to say that all of you
can review each other's pull request
and comment it just like that.
It is not any hierarchy here.
And this is, we all are collaborators
in a collaborating repository.
So there is no senior, junior,
no differences with reviewing.
And you can see that what I was doing,
you learn by reviewing many things.
So, actively participate in code reviewing, that's somewhere you can learn a lot and it
should not be anything role-based or any supervisor or anyone.
Any collaborator should be able to review things and have a conversation and one thing
to make sure what I would suggest is to have a good collaborative environment on your repository.
being polite what we said.
Anything you want to add [name] regarding that?
Yeah, I think that's a perfect explanation.
The
one thing actually like in companies
also like in the working environments like we are
is that it's okay for a junior person to review let's say if there's
as a new colleague, that person could review experienced
persons' commits as well.
So that's also a learning experience.
So I set up my terminal, [name].
So I could just show these things
because there's a very specific question about it.
Yes.
I'll take over the screen.
Let me fix my terminal a little bit.
Is my terminal font visible?
Is it enough or should I make it a little bigger?
OK.
I am sharing, so.
Yeah, [name], you need to stop.
OK.
After [name] stops, I'll do that.
So the question is that this pooling and pushing
and the terms that we used.
We used the browser to show you the setup,
so we didn't come to the terminal.
but what we can do is that,
let me adjust my screen a little bit.
So I don't want to show my desktop.
Yeah.
So this is the repository we have.
So here I go to the recorded one
because I don't want to show the private one.
centralized template for centralized workflow.
So this is the exercise report that we had.
So there's an issue.
So I open another issue.
I'll be a little quick,
but these are not good comments.
We have to, so I opened an issue and then submit it,
but that we do it in the GitHub interface,
not on the terminal.
So that's done.
And then I go to the code.
I take the SSH and I clone it, copy.
And I could also show one more thing here is that I already cloned that repository before.
So I have something with the same name.
So what I will do is I will clone it, but I'll give a new name.
So when you are cloning it, you could specify which name to give.
If you don't do that, it'll use the name of the repository.
So I have two folders now.
So that is the cloning process.
I got a copy down to my laptop.
So I go to my new repository.
Let me go up a little bit
so I have more real estate to show you.
So I have these folders.
Maybe I'll go to deserts.
So I went to that desert and I'll check the branch.
Git branch, this commands we learn.
So I'm in the main branch.
I will check the git status.
So status is clean.
So there was the, one other question was to accidentally
start working on the main branch and what to do.
So I will imagine that, you know,
I forgot to create a branch, but I start working.
Let's see, I'll copy the chickpeas recipe
because I don't want to create a new one, new chickpeas.
So this simulates that I create a new file.
Then I edit that.
Let's make it two.
And when you edit that,
my muscle memory opened the Vim editor.
So you could be the editor of your choice
that we learned yesterday.
And now I did something on the main branch.
But there's still more time to create a new branch.
So I ask git status.
There is a modified file here.
But I could still create git.
If you learned the commands, the practice yesterday,
you could do this in one command, actually.
I'm going to check out.
a new branch called, I'll call it the piece, with an S to make it a little funnier.
Then I'm in the new branch, git status.
So it says that command was not found because I misspelled it, status.
So a new file is still there.
I will ask git branch.
So I'm in the correct branch.
Now I can commit.
So I created the file while I'm in the main branch, but still there's room to switch to
a new branch.
I will git add new this video learn, then git commit with a message, this fixes issue
42.
So I did that.
So then I ask it status, again wrong spellings, status, now everything is clean.
but I can do is do that push. I pull
push it again, git push origin. So the origin is the
the place I copied from. So there's a label given to that origin. I want to do it upstream.
It depends on your setup on your local computer, but this is safer to make mention
that, you know, I had to send upstream
a pull request now in order to incorporate it. So we pulled it to a local computer,
we made the changes, we pushed it, and then we're going to send compare pull request.
Then I will send fixes. Okay, I'm going to get it here.
I think I spelled it wrongly, but I can check the spellings because Git is good at checking
the spellings.
So now that thing happened in the title
will not happen now with more details.
Create a pull request.
So we're seeing the word pull again.
But in GitLab, you will see the merge word.
So two different uses of that.
But this is a pull request, and earlier was a pull.
So that's what we meant by push and pull.
So, our colleagues, is that clear enough?
Yeah, I think it answers the question.
And what are we going to do next, [name]?
Are we going for a break or?
We are supposed to have a lunch break,
but do you want to take, we have some time left for that,
but do you want to take some question?
Yes, yes.
You still see my screen, so I'm going to open the notes.
I'll hide the terminal, so we don't need that anymore for the time being.
Maybe I can show you one more thing before I close the terminal, [name], is that, you
know, now we mentioned that the disconnection, the clone.
So now our local repository, main branch is,
I will clear this, we are in the git branch.
Again, I'm typing wrong spellings.
I mean this, my branch, but if I go to git checkout main,
main branch, my main branch would not have the same recipe
as the file I sent.
For example, let's see, was it in the cheat piece?
But if you see the file, what was that name?
I'll go back to my branch, let's just see.
So you see there's a new cheat piece,
it's not in the main branch.
So what I should do is I should go to the main branch
branch and do a git pull again.
Git pull, origin, main.
I'll increase the terminal a little bit.
So you see, what I'm going to do is get down
all the changes to main.
And then that command would bring down that change.
So this is how you synchronize on the terminal.
Yeah.
Just a comment on that.
You have seen push and pull.
That's something we use to communicate with the GitHub
repository from the command line.
But pull request is something different,
where you suggest the changes.
Sometimes it might be a bit confused.
You have pull and pull request.
So pull is the communication way.
Pull request is you are suggesting the changes
to the repository.
Yes.
So we are actually asking the owner to pull from me.
So I pull from the owner first, I push back,
and then the pull request is the request,
can you pull from me?
So I give you this, pull it up.
So any other questions that we want to mention?
Let's see.
About what type of files can be tracked, okay.
Which question is about file tracking?
Let's see, can somebody give me the number of the question?
29, thank you.
29.
Yeah.
Yeah, the word files.
Yes.
So the thing with the word files, [name], and also the colleague who asked the question,
is that the word file to the computer is not the word file the human sees.
So there's a lot of metadata.
So if you create a word file, and if you try to look at it on a terminal, for example,
with a less or a cat command, it will show so many things.
So it's possible to track it.
But let's say a small change of making a text bold would change a lot.
So it is not that convenient to track that.
But if you're using Word, then you could use, you know, people ask whether they could use
Git.
You know, it's okay to use Git, you know, to have it version control.
For example, you can go back into certain versions.
So you don't necessarily need to read the code, the bytes,
in order to do that.
But you can't do a diff, for example.
So let's say if I have a Word file,
and if I made a bold text, and I save it and commit it,
the difference between the two commits,
very difficult to see it's a bolding text,
no bolding character.
So for that reason, you could use other version system
that Word is good at, for example, Microsoft 365,
or upload it to Google.
And Google Docs, there are other setups.
These are really personal opinions.
So there could be many opinions.
So it's better not to do that.
But you could do that technically.
Yeah, and text files and all the code, R script or Python,
Everything works quite well with the version control.
Markdown is kind of a text file, but it
has a specific, what you call, speciality with the headings
and all other marking.
You can just have similar text files and readme files.
Those are simple text files.
And ASCII data sets, that's very good with the version control.
Yes.
Let's see, anything else?
Commits in a conversation.
Yes, so you could.
Yeah, so this is actually a good question
that we have an answer for that.
So how to mention a commit.
This is a good answer.
Another way, like I would say, you
have to think a little bit opposite way.
When you think of like this, you showed that, [name],
is that you could mention a commit.
But let's say if you're referring to a certain commit,
and it's even better to be more specific.
So you could specifically refer to the line
that you are mentioning.
Or you could have this commit text.
Let me go to the recorded version.
And then when you see the, because my screen
is a little shrink, I had to find the commits.
That hash number, that you get the short number,
so that git is capable of figuring it out.
So if you can copy that, copy to the mouse
or right click or Control-C, as mentioned,
you could always use that.
But usually, what we do is the opposite.
So as I mentioned in the beginning,
rather than mentioning copying the commit to an issue,
we refer to an issue in a commit with a hash.
Yes.
So I think, [name], we should go for the break now,
the lunch break.
Yeah, I just want to mention thank you for all this push,
pull request, and creating the issue,
and actively participating on the stream,
as well as I assume that you are participating as a team.
But if you have questions, please keep it coming.
And next, what we are going to do, [name],
we are going to have a forking exercise, right?
After the lunch.
Yes.
But before the lunch, there's some technical issue
that I need to solve with the director.
Let's see.
Is [name] still around, or is [name] around?
Yes, I'm here.
So we are going for the break now, [name].
OK.
And then let me say it's mentioned.
Yeah, maybe [name] can help us to mention the break.
I couldn't find it here still.
It's until an hour break, right?
Yeah.
Was it one hour, 15 minutes?
How?
One hour.
One hour, OK.
Yeah, so we'll meet again.
And yeah, so then have a break, have a great lunch.
And we will meet afterwards.
And we will work with the repository
that you will not get access.
How would you contribute?
Anything else, [name], before we break?
No, thank you.
OK, see you then.
See you.
Welcome back. Did you have a good lunch or good rest?
Yes, yes. I just finished my lunch and get ready for more GIT for dessert.
Okay, you will get some more dessert today for sure.
Thank you for participating earlier.
Now, we collaborated earlier in one repository.
And you know how to create an issue and pull a pull request
and how to record a new code review.
Do you want to comment on anything on that, Sabdee,
before we go for the next session?
No, I think it's all good.
Some questions are answered.
I think we can go for the next one.
So now we are going to contribute changes to a repository that belongs to others.
Earlier you had write access to the repository where you contributed,
and now there are many, many open source repositories that you might use,
and you might find some bugs or some improvement,
and you are not a member.
You don't have write access, and you want to contribute, and how to do that.
That's what we are going to see, and [name] will mention the exercise setup before we
go for the exercise, but I just want to show you how, given initial thoughts on it, how
it works.
I will go to my repositories, and you can see that I have a lot of fork.
So when you want to contribute to someone's repository where you don't have to access,
you don't have the access, somebody mentioned that you fork into your namespace.
And you could see that I have many repositories which I forked.
I will just show you that JAX, for example.
So, [name], you mentioned that the term namespace, what does it mean?
Oh, yeah, that namespace here means it's under my namespace.
That's a good question.
I shouldn't have used that new, new intents.
So the actual repository, that's the upstream repository,
is under Google's namespace, I would say.
But when I fork it, it's under my namespace.
Does that answer your question?
Yes, so this is a copy of what Google has,
but it's in your repository.
You can edit and do whatever you want,
but the Google will not see it unless you explicitly ask.
Yes.
And I just want to show you that this is what you see.
That's what I forked.
And you could see that I forked from Google Jax.
And if I want to contribute, what should I do?
And I will go to this Google Jax, the original repository.
And there are issues.
You could see many issues.
and it's an open repository, and I created just like what we did when we were collaborating.
So, this is what we are going to do and how to do it. We will have this exercise set up
and we will fork it from our code refinery,
a forking-recorded repository and we'll work on it.
Where you don't have any write access,
you will fork it and make changes
and make a pull request to us the upstream repository.
Upstream means the original repository where you fork from.
Is there something you want to add on that subject,
that the motivation, or are you muted?
Can you hear me?
Sorry, I just lost my sound a little bit.
What were you asking?
Is there anything you want to add on it
about the motivation of something?
Not necessarily.
I think you explained it.
It's just that you can't edit because you are not
part of that organization.
And it's unlikely that unless you are a heavy contributor
that you become a part of that organization.
And you don't have to be part of Google in order to contribute.
I mean, not contribute, suggest contributions.
So I think you made yourself clear.
Yeah.
And you could find about all this, your repository
and your teams under your namespace,
which organization you are part of. I'm not part of many on GitHub. You could see which
organization you are part of. But what we are going to do is we are going to contribute
some changes to a repository. We don't have write access. You can read the repository,
but you want to suggest some changes,
and the maintainer or admin of the repository
will review the changes.
That's we are going to practice.
And this is the way that open source software
developed so much.
So this is something we always want to contribute back
whatever we use it.
Do you do that mostly, [name]?
I mean, I have contributed for certain projects, but you know, not much.
So one thing I would like to mention is that when you fork a repository, it could go stale.
I mean, I see a lot of repositories here, maybe they are not properly synchronized with
the original version.
Yeah, that we will maybe come back or you want me to show it now how to synchronize
with my original upstream repository or?
Yeah, yeah, maybe we can show that after the exercise.
Okay, yeah.
You will see that if it is on sync or not.
So you can see that I didn't look
into it for a long time, so I'm 794 commits behind.
But this is the option, you can sync fork,
But [name] will show you later when we do the exercise.
Shall we go for the preparation for the exercise?
Or do we have any questions to take before that?
So there's this question about why fork instead of cloning.
Maybe we can touch that a little bit.
So a cloning will involve even if you fork.
So if you clone directly from this Google's JAX repository,
you can make changes locally.
But you can't send your changes back to Google,
because then it will be rejected,
which will say that you don't have right access.
Because you are not a collaborator there.
Yes.
In the teaching material, we have some screenshots
of what exact message you get.
Because of that, you should make a copy in the cloud itself.
You fork it in your namespace, and then clone it, and make
your modification, and send the pull request via the fork.
OK, shall we go to the preparation of the exercise?
And shall we have our hands on it?
Yes, so I think we should go for the exercise.
I could explain that.
And I have a slight problem with the sound.
Maybe if I lose my voice a little bit,
you might have to explain if you don't hear me.
I'm going to start sharing the screen.
You could stop.
Then maybe my screen will show up.
Yes, I see that.
Let's see one more time the questions.
Just please keep the questions coming.
And we are in this, let me go up very slowly, this we did.
And we move on to this lesson called
how to contribute changes to repositories
that belong to others.
So if others give you permission, that's fine.
But this is how you would contribute when you are not
part of that organization.
As with the previous exercise, there
are two main workflows here.
The first workflow is that you are part of a team.
As before, you are in a group somewhere,
and you have a team leader who will provide this repository
for you, created from our template,
and you will follow that instructions from your team.
The other instruction is that you don't have a team,
you're on your own, and you'll be in our team,
me, [name], and the code refinement
that we are going to show.
So we have created that repository.
It's called the, if you click this link,
you'll land in that repository.
Workflow exercises, I actually need
to show the one that is not recorded.
Central logs for recorded.
OK, so I had to show the one that is recorded.
The difference between the recorded one
and the non-recorded one, as before,
is that the recorded one will show up in our recordings.
So if you don't want your names appear here,
you should use this one.
So you will land in this report.
So as before, we have like two main workflows
and how this works.
And even in that workflow,
we have like three ways of working.
So one is that you have your team,
your team leader provides this report to fork from
and you fork from that
and you contribute, and you're on your own,
you're following code refinery,
you know, the fork that the report we created for you,
you fork from that.
If it's okay for you to show up your name in our recordings,
you can use the report that ends with the recorded.
And if you don't want your name to show up,
you should the one which does not have recorded at the end.
You should use only one.
And you could select and follow that procedure.
And then, so the idea is that you would be provided
with this repo that you would fork,
you would make a copy in the cloud,
but inside your own workspace or namespace.
And then what will happen is after you create that,
you're going to contribute back something.
Before you contribute back, as we discussed before,
you should open an issue and inform the developers
that you're going to do that.
So [name], the issue, do we create the issue
in the organization repo, or do I create it
in the fork that I created?
The upstream organization repository.
That's where you are telling that there is some improvement
or issues that you want to, or you can mention,
as I mentioned it earlier,
that issues on this open repository,
you can create it even though you are not working on it.
And it would be always on the upstream repository.
You need to create the issues
if you want to contribute back to changes to this,
like for example, JAX.
I will go to the Google Jax.
There, I will create an issue.
Yes, so you'll create the Google.
So although you don't have access to the repo itself,
you can create issues.
So that is where the Google people will
say that improvement is coming.
Let's say you open an issue in your repo,
they don't know about it.
So that communication never happens, although in the cloud.
Yeah, and one more thing.
Here, you don't need to ask for the access.
So when we were collaborating earlier,
we asked for access, we added your username to our team
and made every changes.
So here you don't need to do that.
Yes, so you don't need to do that.
So here, let's say the centralized workflow
recorded exercise.
So depending on how your screen setup is,
not every menu will be visible.
So there is a menu called Fork.
Where is it?
I can make it a little smaller and see whether it shows.
As you can see here, I don't see it.
But when I zoom out, I can see this fork repository.
So this button, where you click depends on the pathway
you selected in the beginning.
If you're in a small team, you should
go to that small team's repository and create fork.
And if you're in a code refinery,
and if it's OK for your name to be
visible in the recorded version, you could create fork.
So when you click the fork button,
you will be given an option.
So this is my namespace or my Git repository,
my organization, which I am the only member.
And it will give this option.
And you could also mention that copy the main branch only.
You don't have to copy all the branches.
Usually, when you're working with copying and forking
from a very highly active program, NumPy, or JAX,
or PyTorch, or very active projects,
or maybe the Linux compiler, you don't want to copy everything.
It will be a huge repository with a lot of commits and all.
So here only the main and I'll create a fork.
And then the fork will be created.
So you should do that.
So after the fork created, the workflow is as before.
Now you clone from the copy you made,
not from the original one.
So the one that creates under your name.
You create a fork.
Then you clone it, or you could, if you
want to edit in the GitHub itself, you can edit TASL.
Or if you want to clone it to your local terminal,
then you clone it.
Then you would create a branch.
And then you make the change, or the suggestion,
or the improvement.
And then you will add that to that new branch.
And then you will commit.
When you're committing, you can mention the issue as before.
But this time, you are mentioning
an issue which is not in the repository
that you are pushing to first.
So you are referring to an issue that's upstream,
which means this issue is not something in your repository,
but it will make sense when we merge it or accept
the full request in the original repository.
And yes?
These are the steps you want to mention, [name]?
Yes, so I think this is very clearly written
what you should do.
And if you get in trouble, and error messages
are also like anticipated error messages are here.
And let's say that something goes wrong.
For example, you copied, instead of copying the fork
you made, you accidentally copied the original one
from your team leader, what the team leader created,
or you directly clone the repo that CodeRefinery created.
If that happens, this recovery box tells you
how to fix that.
Yep.
And then as before, the pull request,
you have to request the pull request.
So this time, you would select,
you have to make sure that when the pull request is made,
that it's going from your repository,
your repository that you have the changes to somewhere else.
So this arrow would point, there's a small arrow here,
if you notice closely, it will show you where it's going.
So you have to make sure that it happens that way.
And then I think, without we spend too much time,
[name], because it's everything explained very well here,
we will go over the exercise now.
Yeah, before we go to exercise, I
would like to take one very interesting question, 36,
about the difference between issue and pull request.
So an issue is like a discussion thread.
So you discuss things.
The pull request itself is the change.
So you discuss about a change in the issue,
and then you send the actual change.
So that is the difference.
Yeah.
And if I can add issues as something,
can inform that there is something that can be improved. It's not always to be in discussion.
Sometimes you can mention there is something going on and you are going to work on it. But
there is no changes. It's only part of the initiation about these changes and you can
have some feedback, some other colleagues or someone from the organization itself.
And the pull request is the changes that you ask the maintainer to pull the changes from your suggestion.
So this question, question 37, it's asked what is the difference between if you just say quick push or like you be more specific git push upstream origin branch name.
So this also depends on the configuration
that you have in your Git.
So you have this Git config.
I think you learned it in the first few days.
That if you had configured default branches,
et cetera, et cetera, Git push will just
push everything to Git, what you have in the branch you are in.
But if you are more specific, it will
push the exactly, the branch that is connected in the remote and yours. So you're specifying
push exactly from here to exactly to there. So I always use this exact commands, not generate
git push, because sometimes when you're in a wrong branch or like, it's always make life
easier and less error prone when you're more specific in Git.
But you could, of course, configure your Git
to understand when you say Git push do this.
But I would recommend be specific,
and then you would exactly know what you are expecting,
and Git would understand it as it is.
So now, Darya, is there anything else you want to mention?
No, maybe we can go to exercise and come back and discuss
a little bit more on this.
Yes.
So the difference between last time and this time
is you first fork and then clone.
Everything else is almost the same.
And the issue is created in the original upstream repository,
not the one you copied.
How long do we have for the exercise, [name]?
Was it 15 or?
25 minutes, or maybe we could give it 22 minutes,
45 minutes past the hour.
We can come back.
OK, 45 past on the hour, we'll be back at 8.
So we'll be muting our microphones
and go back in your exercise and tell us
if you face any problem and also keep on asking questions.
Good luck.
Okay, I hope you had the time to do the exercise and if you need a little bit more time, you
can indicate here on our notes.
[name], shall we go through it, how we were working on it?
Yes, if you could show how you send the pull request
with the correct branch, from correct branch to the task,
correct target branch.
Yes, I can show that, and then you
can see how my pull request is.
So I am on the upstream repository
forking workflow exercise recorder,
and I am listing out the issues,
and you see I have two issues listed out.
And one of the issue,
there is a pull request already linked to it.
And here, this is the other one,
the other issue I am working on.
But I forked this repository and I created branch.
I made some changes.
Now I want to open a pull request.
Just wanted to show this, that when you open a pull request,
you are suggesting the changes
towards the upstream repository.
So if you are trying to open a pull request,
you see the base repository,
see our workshop exercise and base main,
and head, this is my namespace
and the branch I created for this changes I suggest.
So what it do is it will create a pull request
on the upstream repository where you forked your copy.
This is, I want to show this.
When you pull request, you just check it.
It is doing on the right path.
And you create a pull request.
Before that, allow edits by maintenance.
That means the maintainers can edit on your change suggestions
on your branch.
I would like to add [name] as the reviewer,
so I can ask for review from [name] here
and create a pull request.
So it's create a pull request on the upstream repository
where we fork from.
Shall we go to the pull request?
And I see that there are a lot of pull requests.
Ravi, you want to take over the screen
and review my pull request and others?
Yes, I'm going to start sharing.
Yeah, all good?
Yeah.
Then you could stop.
Yeah, I could see it, yes.
So here, I see that this is the centralized workflow
and the recorded version of the exercise
that we are going to share with you.
And let's see the issues a little bit first.
So I have a full request.
Okay.
Yeah, you are on the under your namespace, you are on the forked repository, so you don't
see the issues issue label there.
Yes.
So, when you when you forked it and if you want to see the full request and the issues
it will not be there.
to go to the place where I poked it from,
which we call upstream, right?
I go there.
And now I see some issues.
There's one issue.
You are showing the template.
Correct.
OK, so that's also a good point, actually.
So we created this repository from a template.
And from that template, I made a fork.
So I went two steps back.
So I should have stopped here.
So this is the place that I should have stopped.
And then I'll go to the issues.
So, do I have an issue by you or maybe closed?
You are in the wrong repository, [name].
You are centralized workflow exercise.
We are doing forking workflow exercise.
You are correct. Thank you, [name].
Forking workflow exercise recorded.
Now it looks correct?
Yes.
So maybe too much lunch.
Here, let me search [name]'s,
maybe I can find it.
No, maybe your username is,
okay, let's see again.
Do you remember your issue number?
Yeah, but what you see that you should be notified
when I create a review request,
but you can number seven.
Yes, so let me search again
because I think maybe I've wrongly spelled your name.
Let's see like this.
I think when you filter,
you have to filter with order or something like that.
So that's what I was thinking.
Okay, let's try that again.
Let's just copy your name exactly it is.
So if you if you click on the order down.
Yeah.
Yes, you're correct.
Then you can find. Yes. So you have two ratios. So I would, I would like you to review the
Chia seed pudding first, because the next, yes.
The next one is something interesting
about the workflow, GitLab action, but this one, okay.
So you have this Chia pudding request is number seven,
and you are talking about issue number eight.
So this issue number eight is in the upstream repository.
Yes.
So then I see that you have send a pull request,
and then your pull request has arrived
into the correct place.
And all these green buttons look green, the checks.
So here, what we wanted to mention
is that we are also showing something that is not
necessarily needed to understand what we are doing
with this cloning, forking, merging exercise
is that the automated testing.
So there are some tests that go through.
So when someone sends a pull request or makes a commit,
you could check whether it's as expected.
So you could do it at commit level,
or you could do it at merge or pull request level.
So time to time, I miss this word.
I mix this word merge and pull request
because I mostly work on GitLab.
So we use the word merge request there a lot.
So the pull request, when we send that,
you could run the test as well.
So what happens is your code get checked by a script.
So the GitHub can spin up like a virtual machine
with a container and it'll run some scripts to check
what you have submitted.
So here, what it means is that it's all checks are good.
So I'll go and check the change file.
So it is a new ingredient.
It looks all good.
Nothing extraordinary.
I would say, I would approve it saying it looks good.
what's good, thank you, and I submit that.
And in the pull request,
then I see this merge pull request button,
so I will merge it, confirm the merge.
So one check passed and it merged,
And your changes you made in your fork,
in the copy you made, is now in the main repository.
So as the maintainer of this repository,
I accepted your changes and there was no issue in that.
So the second one that you said,
was you sent two requests, so let's see.
Yeah.
It's chocolate pudding, is it?
It is.
Yeah.
So this one, no descriptions are not good.
So there should be some description here
and you send it and which issue
are you referring to this year?
Let's see.
The issue is not tracking here for some reason.
Let me go to the pull request and see.
Centralized workflow exercises recorded.
Pull requests.
And authors.
Yeah, this one. So, this one has failed. So, we could check, you know, what has failed.
Where should I click to see more details on this? Do you know?
There is already a details button. You could check details.
This one? Yeah.
I just want to specify that this test is something
we included in the GitLab action.
You will learn how to do this mostly next week.
We get the automated testing episodes.
So this is a preview of that, how it works.
So in the test, usually it should print some messages
and it shows some log files, which should
indicate what was exactly wrong.
Let me check.
So there are five missing ingredients section.
So the ingredients section is missing.
So that's why it failed.
So let me go to the pull request again.
Search for that.
And then I'll go to the files changed here.
So it's showing some details.
I can go to the review chain.
Okay, no, no, not yet, not yet.
I had to find the heading, maybe it's,
maybe you forgot like a hash or something in the heading.
No, the check was to test if there is ingredients
and instructions on the files,
but you see that I haven't done it.
I said recipe to be updated.
Aha, so here you didn't have ingredients.
So I don't have any recipe.
I just tried to push it,
and this is not the way it should be,
because when I try to add some recipe,
I should add ingredients and instructions.
That's what we put it on the test,
test.check.py function, right?
What was the name of the test?
The check, I can show that in a moment.
So it means that it figured out that this heading is missing
and also the instructions heading.
So did you have only three lines in your?
Yes, I had only three lines.
Yes, I just wanted to show this that it can be failed
because I didn't follow the automated testing thing.
So can I commit this directly to see whether it works?
Yeah.
Okay, I'm going to commit that.
I'll add these two lines.
Go to the headings.
So, when that happens, the pipeline will run again, and we'll go to the conversations and
we'll see it until it runs.
I think our colleague [name] is mentioning about 40, question 40, let me have a look
at that one first.
Could you explain why I have to set my fork repo as upstream
if I can push?
Current branch has no upstream branch.
So I think our colleagues are answering the question,
that one, properly.
So I don't see that we have to explain it much here.
Yes.
So it's about Git configuration as well.
How you configure Git could also change.
But if you're very specific, if you're explicit
when you do push and pulls, it will be more convenient.
Then we'll see the check.
It has passed.
Now, how can I check back again what has changed?
The file changed?
Yeah, file changed.
And the commits?
Also, you used last time the two commits.
Yes, so this is my commit and this is the original one.
And also file changed.
And now it has passed the tests.
Then what happens is, then I could go and approve this.
I don't want you to approve it, because as a matter of fact,
there is only ingredient and instructions,
but there is no real recipe for the chocolate pudding.
But you can suggest that, can you please
update the recipe or something?
OK.
Yeah, but the function we want to show
is that there are checks we can automate.
So if you see that when you do a pull request
and all the checks are not green,
that's something you have to check
that you follow all these checks updates.
Sometimes we use spell checker.
So if there is a spell error,
it will show spellchecker failed or something like that.
Yes.
But usually maybe it's like if you're developing Python,
for example, you might have PyTest
that you could check whether it pass.
Yeah.
Or if it's like C code, there might be checks alongside that.
So it will be more or less programmatic testing
in the real life.
Yeah.
More on to more about this next week.
Next week, okay.
So if you are curious about what Postgres is about,
you could go to this repository before next week.
You can click on this GitHub workflows
and then check this file.
What does, you know, how it is, you know, summoned.
How do you summon the check test to be done?
So it is a program that runs the check Python recipe.
This is how GitHub knows that it has to run it.
And then if you go back, you will see that file here.
Check recipe file, it's a Python code
that checks that there are certain things included.
Yeah, and yeah, it's-
Yeah, I will try to merge all the pull request,
but Saby, you have a forked version
under your namespace, right?
So since you pushed,
as you approved the pull request from my side,
there might be some changes in the upstream repository
that is not there in your forked one, right?
Let's check.
So, okay.
That fork, so I don't have a fork actually,
I have not created that one.
It was the centralized repository that I had a fork,
which I shouldn't have created.
I could create one actually now.
So after I created the fork from that repository,
you could merge so we could show the synchronization.
Now it's being created.
So now it's created.
Now it's in the, let me check the status of it.
Since I copied it like now at one past, it'll be in a frozen state from that place I copied.
Yeah, you can try to review some other pull request as well.
Yeah, let's do that. 4K exercise recorded.
Yeah, which looks good.
So, it failed. Let's see why it failed. Okay, it was some temporary glitch in Git. Let's
see again. Maybe you also tried to merge the same thing?
No, I merged something else.
So you can go to the urnamespace.
So you will see that your fork is not up to date
with the upstream repository.
Yeah, I think now it's OK.
Checks pass.
So now let's go to my fork.
So here, so these are the commits that I have.
Let's check the graph.
Traffic, code frequency, dependency graph.
Okay, that's not the one, commits maybe, yeah.
So I am here, four commits.
Yeah, if you go to the code, it says [name].
Sorry, which one?
Yeah, now you could see
that this branch is four commits behind.
Yes, yes.
So if you want to sync to the upstream repository,
repository, what you are supposed to do?
Yeah.
Yes.
So I could click this button, and it'll
synchronize with the top button.
I could compare also.
Let's see what it shows.
OK, so actually, I have not made any changes.
So let's say if I had made some changes while that happens,
the synchronization might probably fail.
Let's go back and sync fork update branch.
Yeah, this branch is up to date.
So let's say if I had done some modifications to the main branch in my fork,
then it might have made some issues,
But it's always good practice to not
to do it on the main branch, but on your own branch.
Because once after you form, you could even
modify your main branch if it is not protected.
OK, I think those are the things we are planning to mention.
Maybe we can see whether there are any questions that we
are going to take up in the stream.
Yeah, and thank you for all this pull request.
I will try to merge it later.
But thank you for the active participation
sending pull request and creating issues.
And I hope you had fun while creating recipes.
Yes, so there are some questions about how to directly do it
from the command line.
For example, send a pull request.
Usually, it doesn't, with the git commands itself,
As far as I know, you can't do it, but you could.
There are APIs, we call them APIs,
which means that you can programmatically access Git
and do that if that is needed using programs like Curl
and Git and put instructions, but not directly Git.
Yeah, and maybe something I usually do
is I try to keep my fork up to date,
then pull my fork when I need to update.
So that's what something I do,
but it is maybe the optimal way someone wants to do it.
Yes, yeah, so keeping up to date
without becoming stale for a long time will help.
Otherwise, if you're not done any changes locally,
you could always update.
But if you're keeping on updating locally
without syncing, it will create a lot of conflicts.
And then this hash and the number, that is the trigger.
So you could also refer to pull requests.
So there are about the, there's another symbol.
I forgot the symbol.
So you could say that's at the rate,
and there are the symbols.
You can refer to other commits.
You can refer to pulls.
You can pull requests.
you can refer to issues.
There seems to be many questions discussing
around linking between issues and PRs.
So I could, again, maybe test something,
show something here as well.
So the link between the issue and the pull request
is the issue is where you discuss the details.
That is a discussion.
The pull request is the code that you send.
So that's the difference.
And why we are linking it is that it's
important to have a discussion before you suggest changes.
that makes things, the development pipeline
and the workflows less, I would say, more friendly.
Yeah, it is when you work with many people,
it's always nice to have a lot of feedback
and let other people know about things.
So having issues as a workflow is very good.
Yeah, apart from that, I think let's see whether any other questions or go to final colleagues
do is there anything more that anything very specific that we don't talk during the questions
the shared document.
Yeah, I think it's all good.
So we have, I think, 20 minutes left, [name], is it?
Yes, it was supposed to be on discussion,
but if there is more question to discuss it,
that would be nice.
Let's see whether there's anything we can discuss more.
Okay.
Yes.
Maybe we could go through the whole process again,
because there are some questions about the issues and all.
Yeah.
So what I will do is we have this repository forking exercise,
but I have a copy now of that in my namespace as well.
I will do it again to show what's happening.
So before I do that, working flow exercise recorded.
because I have too many tabs open,
I just want to make sure it's the correct one.
So here, I'm going to open an issue.
New.
I've got the spelling all this.
CP.
Sorry, recipe, recipe.
So what should I, for something.
Okay, so this is where things started.
So I went through this repo and I found out
that there's something I want to contribute.
So this is start, and I submit that issue.
Now, this is the original repository
that I copied folk from, not copied, copied folk from.
So then I submit new issue.
Now, this is the discussion.
And then if you could, in issue 28,
if you could mention something, OK, please
go ahead or something.
Done?
Yeah.
I don't see it yet.
Did I comment it?
Yes.
Okay.
Yes, that would be great.
Please go ahead.
So now I see that, you know, I should be able to see it.
I don't see it yet.
Did I comment it?
Did you see it?
Yes, OK, now I could.
Yes, that would be great.
Please go ahead.
So now I see that I should be working on it.
But there will be a longer discussion on what's
and what's not.
Now I should be going for that.
Then I'll go to my repository.
I mean, the fork in my namespace.
I'm going to load it.
I could, of course, do it in the Git, on the web page as well.
But maybe it's easier to show the details on the terminal.
So I'm in my terminal.
Let me see where am I. So I'll go to steps.
Yeah.
So then, now it is the cloning.
The issue is open.
the forking has done.
Clone
repository. So as you can see, it is
cloning from my namespace not from the original place I forked from.
git branch.
And then after working on this kind of repositories,
especially when forked, it might be very useful to know git
the which remote I've actually connected to.
So if you type the command with remote verbose,
it will tell you the origin refers to the fork you made.
So if it is the repository that you don't have access to,
then you should change that.
So it's all good.
Then I'll create a branch.
Because I'm on the main branch, it
will create from the main branch.
Or you could specify it from what?
I will use my name, so I could track it easily.
So then I can ask again git branch, but then it will show that I am still on the
master branch, because I created the branch, I didn't change it. So git switch or git checkout
the branch, then get branch and this branch.
So I'm going to make the change now.
Let's go to the salads.
So I'm going to now invite a new salad.
I'll start from an existing one.
New mixed.
So here I will add, what could I add?
Yeah, some random things.
Four cups of oil, right?
Then I will save the file, and I will ask git status.
So that file is modified on my local computer, git is not tracking that.
So let's say now if you accidentally delete that file, you can't recover it.
I will add git new file, git add the new file, now at least the git knows it now. If it gets
deleted you can get it back, git commit. Now this is where the commit message comes.
So we are going to say that I'm going to, what I'm going to say is that the commit I'm going to make
is talking about this issue that we have been talking.
So issue number 28.
So when this file ends up in the main code base,
it will fix us this new change fixes issue number 28.
So now it is locally here.
Now if I lose my laptop or somebody steal it,
still it's gone, because it didn't reach the cloud.
So now what I want to do is to send this change
to the fork I made.
Then git status again.
But then I will do git push explicitly.
So it doesn't matter how the configurations are.
So I would say git push listens to the origin.
So what is the origin?
That I'm going to hash it up and stop it by executing
to show the origin again.
So the label origin refer to this URL.
So I could have used this URL instead.
So I could even use this complete URL if I want.
Git push origin for that URL.
I want to go at upstream, and I want
to create a name branch in my fork with the same name
and connect both together.
I'm going to change that.
So now this goes to my branch, right?
So it's here in this repository.
So then what happens is now this is
in my fork, and the main developers don't know about it.
So that is when we talk about the fork.
Now we have to send the request, which
we call the pool request, so the developers can integrate
into the main branch.
So did you mention all the terms, [name]?
Do we need to explain more?
Yeah, I think it is OK that we have mentioned it.
but if there is any questions you want to,
I think everything is us.
I'm trying to merge in between,
but I think that will help me.
And there are four more pull request.
One is from my side,
but thank you for all the pull request,
but we will merge it.
And you can try to sing your folk
that there are more merge is already there.
Is there anything we missed to,
anything from our colleagues? Maybe [name] or [name] wants to say the summary and ask
for feedback. Should we do that? We have 10 more minutes. And you can ask questions.
Yeah, I think we could take maybe one more question here.
Yeah.
Have a look.
Is there anything specific you want to take up
with [name] that we missed during the discussion?
Yeah, so sometimes it's branch creation,
sometimes send from the main,
so from the main of the home to main of the upstream,
it also could work,
but it's better to create your own brand first.
Okay, so please, I think it's been merged.
Yeah, one thing is my issue is resolved
and the pull request is accepted,
but I can't find my recipe.
Oh yeah.
Uh-huh, so that actually, you know,
maybe we learn git blame or git annotate at some point.
I think we have already done that.
Okay, let's see.
So this, in this exercise, so this is the main workflow.
And the file, the commits that were made.
Let's see if I can find those settings and whereas the list of commits, it's not there.
Let me go back here and see.
That's not the list.
There is a list of maybe insights and commits, that's it.
So it just shows the number.
Let's see the traffic.
Okay, that's just a number, contributors.
It's taking some time.
So one way would be, you know, I have these four commits.
So I made four commits.
If I click those commits,
I could see which files they were referring to.
Then in that way, you could find, you know,
if you forgot everything about, you know,
which recipe it was or file name or all the details,
you could still find out.
So if I go to that recipe, that file,
then I would see that, you know, what I have done.
So that is one way.
So this you could do in the terminal
with the command called git show
and the commit message, it'll show that.
Apart from that, let's see a file, maybe a desert.
this file. And if you go to a specific file, you will find this tab called blame. And in
that file, it'll tell, it'll detail who contributed what, at what point. So this is not really
to blame people, it is to show that who did what. So those are different ways that you
you could find out what you did.
Also, I think there is this pulse or something.
Let me check that one inside.
Yeah, people is one thing.
Then, where is that?
For frequency, it gives the number of contributions
by each person, maybe contributors.
Yeah.
So here, I think we showed that earlier, how many lines,
how many commits that has been contributed.
Yeah, I think that's all, [name].
Anything else that we have mentioned?
For tomorrow, is there anything that?
Next week.
For the next week, the next day, day four?
Yeah, we can start talking a little bit about next week.
So this week has been the version control week.
So basically, everything about Git and these very, well,
artificial but somewhat, yeah, if you
can share the feedback form, that would be good.
That would be good.
But next week, we really change tracks.
and we begin looking at much more applied things. So if I remember right,
Tuesday is social coding and reproducible research, where we talk about how to build
larger projects, how to license your code, encourage feedback, how to share things,
and so on. Reproducible research is making, well, computational research more reproducible.
Wednesday is Jupyter and documentation, and then Thursday is automated testing and modular
code development.
And basically all of these future lessons somehow use Git in more applied things.
So if some things you see today seem a bit abstract, if you come next week you can see
the real use cases as we do things.
So on the other hand,
since these are, so we
used to have a lot of exercises
for next week and we still do.
But next week is all focused on demos.
So during the courses,
we'll give demos on the topics.
And then, and yes,
so we give demos,
but we leave it up to you to do the exercises yourself after the workshop.
So it'll feel a little bit different, but we still have plenty for you to do.
Just with a 20 or 25 or 30 minute exercise break, it's just not feasible to have enough
time for everyone to do everything. So this is what we've settled on.
But definitely... So [name], we have the feedback. Could you mention a little bit about
Yes.
The feedback box.
So we have the feedback here.
I guess you've seen this from past weeks.
We're writing the news for the next day, which
will also be emailed out.
Please do add in all your comments and so on.
Yeah.
And also things to improve.
Please give honest opinion.
Improve next.
there are something that we can improve by next week,
maybe in future courses,
and we don't take that personally if something can improve.
So please provide that in a positive way, of course,
positive feedback on how to improve it as much as you can describe,
not too much either.
But if you saw something that we should improve,
please let us know.
We don't take it as negative.
We take it as a positive thing for us to improve next time.
Yeah.
So go ahead.
Yeah, and there was a question about how to interact with us.
Join the Zulip chat, as mentioned in the chat.
So we will be there most of the time, most of us.
But you are welcome to join the community chat.
That would be great.
Yeah.
And also, if you want to re-deliver this,
please join the Code Refinery team.
organize local workshops in your workplace if you like the workshops and also [name] you know
since morning they were seeing us a lot but you know there's a lot of people behind this
yeah the organizers and the people who coordinate this for example [name] was managing the
the stream with a lot of balls juggling he has you know in addition to the work he had some
issues he has to attend to and all the [name] was really helping and without also the team
leaders who are working with the team that was very good that we have that kind of different
type of learning teams that everything all all behind the scenes you you saw only us today but
there were many people behind the scene and just want to thank you thank you for your participation
and thank you for all who work very hard to make it possible behind the scenes. Thank you.
So [name], as a final thing, if somebody wants to let's say thank us, what is the best way to do
that? Tell people about this and then in a few years, if you're still involved in this,
help mentor the people who take the course in the future.
And if you're really interested, then come join us later.
But starting local with mentoring others is, I think, the most important impact.
Do you know more about this ambassador program?
Do you have any more information about it?
There's something called Code Refinery Ambassadors, which we're starting.
where basically it's people that know a lot about these tools and want to go and support people at
their own institutions or areas a little bit more in these things. Maybe we can hear more about this
next week. I think it's on the website. Maybe someone can add it to the notes down there.
Yeah. I would like to say one thing. So earlier in the day, there was a comment about niceness and political correctness that we removed. So this wasn't a bad thing. Like, there's nothing wrong. But it's something that we didn't have time to go into more depth at the time.
time. And actually next Tuesday in social coding would be a good time to talk more about these,
like bringing more people on boards. So in hindsight, us, the people that had been managing
the notes and answering the questions, I think we would have liked to have left it there but
pointed out to resume this next week. So us in the background would like to apologize for that.
But we do, like, in general, like even off-topic cheering and other things like that.
Okay.
Anything else?
I think, yeah, that's it.
It's in your hand, Rijat, now.
Yeah.
Okay.
You have to take down things.
So, yeah, I guess we've said enough.
We hope to see you next week, and we hope you like the change of pace then.
So maybe we can hang up now.
Thank you.
Okay.
Bye.
Thank you very much.