Hello. So we are back online. Quickly check with the people in the chat if they can hear
us and see us. Excellent. So everything is working. So we still have it's still our day
day four. And we are still going to cover topics somewhat related to the reproducibility
that was covered in the morning by [name] and [name]. And now here with me there is [name]
who works with me at Aalto University. Hello, [name].
Hello everyone. I'm [name], one of the RSEs at Aalto University. Happy to be here.
Yesterday was a special RSE, Research Software Engineers Day, because basically, except me,
all the others were Alto RSEs. RSE is actually a great profession if you want to stay in research
but not exactly becoming, you know, a professor or whatever you will become. But anyway, to
To the topic of this afternoon, it will be about social coding, this lesson used to be
called licensing, software licensing specifically, as you might know when you release something
you want to attach a license and that of course doesn't even, it's not just limited to software
because honestly anything you basically create, whether you want it or not, it comes with
license and the lack of license basically means copyright but sometimes you might not even know
that let's say what you write in social media has a certain license so that the owner of the
social media platform can do almost whatever they want with your content but today we will focus on
these coding aspects. So [name], what do you feel about social coding and open software?
I think it's a very important aspect because a collaboration happens all the time and you should
be able to understand the basics of it and how to share your code and what kind of licenses to add it
and to take care of all of these things. I remember reading this blog post from
a random blog, I don't remember the name, but it was about Google Docs and about the licensing
I think that you probably agree and you are giving almost the ownership of the work that
you are doing on Google Docs to Google because you don't read the licenses and you don't
take it seriously.
So I think it's very important to know about the licenses and how to, yeah, how to manage
them.
Yeah.
I agree.
And here for some motivational example that you find some great code, but then you are
unsure, can you actually, you know, use it? Can you actually cite them? Or you need to
modify the code a little bit, as we will call it later, like remixing, maybe, even with
some data. But then what happens, especially in academic journals, that they require you
these days to also publish the code. And the reason is not just the reproducibility reason
that we heard from the first part of today's, but it's also related to basically the research
integrity, the transparency principle of research, that you should be transparent in all the
steps of the scientific, of the research process. And being transparent with the code is getting
more and more popular. So you will see these type of code availability statements that
you need to attach to your paper that you submit or data availability statements for
the data part. And when it's time to write this statement, you need to basically have
a license to your code, attached to your code and attached to your data.
Yes.
So let's, hopefully this was motivational enough, all I'm saying is keep in a look at
the notes document, so please, if there's any questions and if you feel writing any
comment related to the topic, just write to the notes and then also please let me know
if there's anything interesting to highlight.
So as I mentioned earlier, at the beginning,
this lecture used to be called software licensing,
but then it expanded into social coding.
And the reason is that coding is not just something
that happens in isolation,
that especially in the topic that we are discussing here,
especially in the topic of research,
at some point you are asked to share the code with others.
And as we've seen during the first lecture
and also during the first week,
sometimes you wanna share the code with yourself.
So the social part is not just, you know,
me collaborating with those saying on a project
and I don't know, sharing the GitHub and so on,
but then it really goes, you know,
me collaborating with the future self
and more in general me trying to share what I wrote
as a code to create an impact on other papers.
So [name], what about you?
I guess maybe that in your work
as a research software engineer, you've been helping people
kind of reaching this objective
to basically be social with their code
and sharing it and make it citable.
Yes.
Was it a easy job or was it?
To my experience, people start it a bit late, they usually come when they have to publish
the code because of the publication or a specific requirement for a journal.
So they didn't start with social coding and like trying to have it online for more collaboration.
So yeah, I think maybe if you started from scratch, it would be easier in the end.
Yeah, this is a very good point. In a way, you could even pretend from the day zero when you
start the project, when you start your Git repository, even though it's a private repository,
even though you're not already sharing it with anybody else, you could still pretend that,
you know, you are actually, that it's already live, that it's already public,
that already will improve the way you relate to the repository, because maybe you will write
meaningful messages if you know that you're being watched, if you know what I mean, even though maybe
it's still a private repository, but that will also make your life easier when it's time to
open it and share it with your paper, that you don't need to, I don't know, go through the git
history trying to delete commit messages that you were not happy about because you were very angry
with your code on the day and so on. So in this social one think about if and how you share.
There's a question that can have multiple answers and I believe you have pasted it to them
Yes.
Or can you paste it to them?
Yes, I already did.
Someone had a problem with Twitch, but now it has been resolved.
So maybe we can go to the questions.
So basically, as we did in other polls, if you are able to write a, like an O, so that
we can get this type of ASCII, ASCII, ASCII histogram.
So
So for the first question, you can answer as many as you want, but for the next ones,
you can only choose one. So Sam, I'm gonna ask you the question. Why would you want to share
your scripts, code, and data? Which one would you pick of this?
So for me, it's very good for your reputation and for your CV. If you want to change your job or
or maybe in the future, which is a good thing because you can showcase what I was doing
in my previous job.
Another thing is, at least for me, when I start to publish my code, I'm a bit more careful
on the structure and try to be more clean, which is also a good thing.
Another thing that at least I use is, because the code is more clean, it's easily more reproducible
for me at least.
So I think these three are the main aspects of why I use social coding.
What about you?
Do you have any preference?
Yeah, I agree with you, especially that you mentioned this kind of CV idea, and this also
goes with the, in my opinion, what I like about the Code Refinery workshop, that the type of
skills that you learn here are skills that are reusable in other fields outside academia.
So if the majority of the people following this workshop right now are doctoral researchers or
postdocs or whatever, but already learning it and starting with whatever, little by little sharing,
it will also open doors for maybe other jobs in the future that might not be related to academia.
Me, of the options here, I really like the reproducibility part. I'm biased. I'm a
reproducibility fanatic so that other people can truly rerun my code. But sometimes I publish
code that was really ugly, but I still thought I'm going to put it out there because no one had
that type of function in whatever language I was publishing it. And then I saw that my ugly code
was actually reused by so many publications completely in different fields. Sorry to
interrupt. Someone is mentioning that. Oh no, sorry. Go ahead. There was a comment that they
cannot hear us, but it was from the computer. Sorry, go ahead. Yeah, that's good. Yeah. If
I was muted it wouldn't be nice. But basically let's have a look at what our people online are
answering. Looks like that to my eyes at least A and B seems to be very popular. So the reproducibility
and also the trustworthiness. Exactly. It's interesting that the H doesn't get any votes,
not for this year, also for previous years it didn't get any votes either. But yeah it's
interesting it's it's nice also this that maybe the kind of social thinking of the people here
is not that we are in a competition even though the grant system makes us believe that we are all
competing with each other another thing that i wanted to add is maybe another aspect that i
think about is being part of the community so there are like a lot of codes that you can use
and they're open source so you can try them and if you try to also publish your code you become
part of this community which is very very interesting to be part of and like you can create
like collaborate with others and after some time you will be known for some of your work
although they not might be exactly your expertise for example like I have this it's not exactly a
source code on GitHub, but it's about like how to do something like more of administrative work.
And at the moment, I'm known for that work among like non-expert people for like research software,
which is an interesting thing. Yeah. Yeah, that's great. And in my opinion, it's also,
I mean, it's exactly this that it's, even though we will talk about this later,
that sometimes maybe code, you might feel that you're not recognized in citation or whatever
impact is the measure in academia. But at the end of the day, people will notice it and people will
see it. Maybe you start getting new collaborators or reaching people that you would have not just
reach with your papers.
Yes, maybe we can go to the next question.
Yeah, so it also had some downfalls a bit, right?
So when you publish your code, do you have any concerns?
Well, I would say initially I felt this kind of B, that my code is ugly.
I was never really afraid of the A, because actually by publishing it with the timestamp,
I could eventually prove that, you know, you scooped my code, I have a timestamp that shows.
But then at the end of the day, would I really see you, someone else like me, or for what?
Just, I mean, at the end of the day, I'm happy if people scooped whatever I did,
means that it was something good. But what about you out of these answers, which one?
I think for me, B, like having an ugly code was the most concern.
I never thought about like A or F, about like a lower quality copy or even F, like the code
could be stolen because you can add licenses. And it's also true about your original paper,
right? When you're publishing your idea, it can be also stolen, but it's completely okay.
You have patents and everything to have this protection. And here I think it's
the equivalent is licenses, which we will talk about.
Yeah, it looks like B is also the most popular.
Exactly. Another thing that I have some concerns about, which is not here, is like,
because no software is complete, right? And as a perfectionist, I'm always thinking about is
it complete? Is it good enough to be published? Not from being ugly or not following the clean
code structures, but just as a whole, with all of the functions and is it complete to be published
or not? Yeah. I personally like the release early, release often. And so I rather just publish
something that is even half broken but already there's an idea out there and then I will improve
it and then maybe someone will try to reuse it and I realize that I completely missed
I don't know one exception in the conditions and so on. Yeah so like based on age I can see like
other people have this perfectionist idea as well and it's good that I like I had some votes on
about the licensing which we are going to talk about in this course in this section.
Then we have question three and question four which are kind of free form so please
expand on that and now we will have a look why software often treated differently than from
papers because some people for example also have a ugly english ugly way of writing why wouldn't
you be ashamed of your ugly paper rather than your ugly software and then the fourth question
is when you find a repository with a code or with a library that you would like to reuse,
what are the things that you look at to decide whether you will use it?
So let's have a look at question three. Yeah, I like the first answer because it's this
overly fixation with citations and metrics. It's also true about one of the comments is
it's usually seen just as a tool, not a scientific product. And it's kind of true,
right? Because in my opinion, papers are more about the results and the methodology that you
used and the code is just a tool that you did it although like there are some aspects about like
optimization of the code and how fast it is how much memory does it use but in the end
it's just a tool to achieve your goal right yeah it's true
it's nice too that now this or at least i think that it's nice i'm sorry for some people maybe
this would be more work, and maybe they don't have the resources to ask for help. But this
making, or I wouldn't say forcing, but at least trying to have the code attached with the paper,
with this software availability statement, is a little bit step towards this reproducibility and
transparency, so that it's clear that maybe the method section is more meaningful if I can just
read the code rather than try to infer from a very short paragraph in the method section
which filter was actually applied or which machine learning algorithm was used.
In question three, do you agree with the last comment, not peer-reviewed?
Well, kind of yes, unfortunately, because I often review papers and if there is a code,
I spend a bit of time in giving some feedback that, for example, usually the typical feedback
is that the license is missing. And so in my feedback, I say, please add the license to your
code. But then on the other end, I don't have the time to actually rerun unless they make it very
easy for you that it's just one Docker pool, whatever command that you can easily rerun the
whole pipeline and test it. But even though I would be kind of an expert to peer review the
code, there's just not enough time if I have to run fan review in the paper. But of course,
there are journals that are actually focused on this, like the Journal of Open Source Software,
JOS, where the peer review is actually on the code. The actual papers that come with JOS are
one or two pages. We are a bit behind time, so maybe we can continue. But
But a short comment that I wanted to add is,
it's a bit complicated than papers
because if your repository become popular enough,
other people would come and do contribute to it, right?
So it's not exactly peer reviewed, but somehow it is, right?
Because other people are trying to make it better.
But yeah, maybe we can-
Yeah, then the question four is about
when you find some code, you know,
I've seen that many are writing about the license,
which it seems that it's already clear
that the license might set the rules
of what you can do and what you cannot do.
And also this type of, not just the reusability,
but what we will talk soon is these changes
that you can do to the code.
So the so-called derivative work.
Do you have any comment on this, Orsan?
Personally, I see like the activity and the number of,
like when it has been updated recently
or is it deprecated already?
And also another thing which I usually look at
is the number of contributors that the repository had.
Yeah.
All right, so basically the rest of this
social coding part is what we just discussed
that compared to sharing papers,
sharing code is somewhat different
if the paper is just, you know,
sharing your ideas and maybe winning citations.
Code is a little bit more complex feature.
Sometimes people will just reuse your code ID.
Sometimes it will form some sort of base in basement
foundation for something else to build on top.
And so, you know, with this, of course,
this makes it a little bit more complicated
that papers to evaluate what could be the impact,
what could be the metrics.
Eventually there are some metrics that we will also mention later when you can actually
track the downloads of a package of a software for example.
And then another aspect that is covering this page is what we touched already that the journal
policies are basically going towards the, I wouldn't say forcing, but at least making
it clear that there should be a code availability statement attached with the paper.
as we have a data availability statement. Maybe sometimes you can't share the code because
you're, I don't know, working with a company or it's a dual use case or whatever is the
reason that you're not allowed to share the code. But it's clear that the journals and
not just the journals, even the organizations that are the funding organization, whether
it's the European Research Council or whatever country organization, they are clearly making
it's stronger that the scientific code should be published and public.
Maybe out of one last part that we can look from this page is also this aspect that we
touched on in the question above, that sharing software can also be scary. We touched a little
bit on this. We didn't really cover the aspect of bugs and mistakes. Of course, we might
be scared that what I did was wrong. But on the other hand, is it so bad? Maybe I should actually,
from the perspective of science, from the perspective of ethics, I would actually be
very happy that someone finds a bug in my code. Of course, it's sad for me that I need to ask for a
retraction of the paper if it really changes all the results. But in theory, if science should be
be, you know, what's the word, self-fixing.
Maybe this publishing the code will also improve this type of process.
True.
I would say like sometimes fixing a bug requires a lot of work and it's good that we can collaborate
and help each other on that aspect.
At the same time, it can be a bit overwhelming for the publisher of the code, that you kind
of feel that you're responsible for fixing those if they're just raising the bug, not
a solution.
Yeah, that's a very good point.
We don't have time to discuss this, but in the page, for those who want to spend some
time reading the whole page, there's also this question that, you know, how do you feel,
do you feel the pressure that in the moment that you put your code online now suddenly people will
start asking can you have this improvement can you make it work on this whatever older version
of this operating system maybe i actually think the other way around that at the moment that i
put it online i'm actually removing the responsibility that that i'm saying look i
managed to do this i don't have time to work on this anymore for whatever reason please continue
you make it better, or ask for help.
Basically, we're slowly moving towards the licenses, and we still have now 30 minutes
to talk about that, which is basically how our work connects to the works of others.
So I'm turning page now, and now it's the page dedicated to software licenses.
And I guess more or less everyone is familiar with the idea of copyright.
There are different types of copyright.
There are trademarks that protect the name of a brand, for example, from impersonation.
There are patents that patents usually are not related to software as an algorithm, but
you can patent a system, for example, or in general, so-called technical invention.
And then there's the copyright that is basically protecting the creative expression.
And this can include a little bit of everything, whether it's music or photographs or writings
and so on.
It's also nice what it says here that this copyright is practically forever because it
persists for 70 years after the lifetime of the author.
then maybe on the what you will hear as a term if copyright feels like you know protecting
your intellectual right i also see a point of having a copy left basically making sure that
other people can actually reuse your work and build on top of your work again in a in a in a
legal way. So this brings us to the topic of derivative work, which is a term to say that
from something, let's say Osain made something and put it in the open and I want to reuse bits
of it. I want to maybe reuse some bits as they are, some Python functions, because I don't really
have any improvements to go there or maybe I want to, you know, remix, resample, invent my own flavor
on some whatever visualization part of the script that Ossane did. And of course I can do this or
like the question that maybe would be for myself, am I actually able to do this? Would Ossane work
allow me to do this type of derivative work or is it that, you know, I can't actually even touch
or run on my computer or saying works. So this derivative work is actually when it comes to
software is not intuitive at all of what constitutes derivative work and me myself when
i was attending my first code refinery many years ago i was actually kind of surprised
that some of the options here are considered derivative work. So in this question for you
please don't spy to the to the solution box can can you try to answer in the notes document
which of these are derivative works so derivative you understand that you are basically
remixing reusing the existing code that you have found you have found online
Okay, so maybe we let some time to answer because we don't want to spoil the fun.
Yes, and we have some questions on the note I'm trying to answer.
Is there anything to highlight?
I think two of them are coming from previous sections and copy pasted here.
It's about Docker and Kubernetes and the Conda environment, which I think we can pass.
But a question is, when you license your code, does it belong to your employer or to you?
How does it work?
Yeah.
So, as usual, what I learned from the lawyers that the best answer is it depends.
It depends on what type of agreement do you have with your employer.
Actually it's flexible in a sense that sometimes I've seen, and I'm not specifically talking
about my university, my employer, but I've seen people writing, you know, copyright.
In my case would be [name]-Alto University.
At the end of the day, because software per se cannot be turned into patent unless you
build a system around it. The employer, at least this public organization like universities,
they don't really care much. But it's a different story if you would be working for a company
where you can clearly understand that you as a coder for a company, you don't own anything
and the employer clearly writes in the contract that whatever you produce.
But the same is also, and it's not intuitive, it's also for data. And this is a discussion
that I often have with our researchers, that they think, because they collected the data
in their views, measurements, whatever, that it's their data. And it's actually very rare
that it's their data in the specific context of Finnish universities. If you are on your
own money, on your own grant, then it is your data. But 99% of the time, it's actually
university owns the data. So yeah, in this sense, it's complicated.
Yep. I just want to add that it depends on the policy of the company that you are working.
And I know even for some companies, if you are an employee there, even if you develop some code
out of your working hours, still the code that you produce, it belongs to the company. So it
depends on the policy. Yeah, so you can't even code as a hobby.
Unfortunately, yes, it depends on the company's policy.
Yeah, well, fair enough. Maybe it's the same, you know, you can think of musician that if you're
making music outside of your contract with your record label, maybe the record label manager gets
Alright, but question 5, there's some answers here and basically A to D, they are all to
be considered derivative works, that you know, you download some code and then you donate
or you change the code and modify the code.
Maybe what kind of was surprised for me, and of course it depends, that E and F can also
be considered derivative work. So even though I'm taking our same repository that's on Python package
and I just rewrite it in R, I might still be doing derivative work you know if I follow the
same logic, the same function structure, the same. It would be different if I say would sit down with
me without showing any code, tell me what the package is doing and then I would try to you know
code it based on the description. So it would be like that I would read O'Sane's paper
on the description of this package and just put it in the paper and try to write my own version.
And so yeah, this was a bit unintuitive for me, but on the other hand,
it makes sense when things start to be kind of literal.
It's also interesting, we don't have the... I would add another option here that,
I don't know if you're using some chat GPT or co-pilot to generate code. Is it derivative
work? Because this chat GPT, large language models, they actually have ingested lots of
software from whatever open repositories, but then they don't tell you who originally
wrote a function very similar to the one that you asked. But then again, it's complicated.
Do you actually do or saying if you if you use copilot or GPT to get help let's say with the function would you start searching if.
That function if beats of that function would already exist on the internet that you would find.
Not not that you have to because this is also the thing that when you generate something with this large language models you are actually become the copyright owner of what is generated.
which is counterintuitive in a way because you feel that ethically it's not you that made those
things, but just some machine who has read many, many code scripts. But how do you feel as a user
of course, I guess you use now sometimes these copilots or... Yeah, all the time. Yeah.
Yeah. But I think it's something that as a society, we still have to think about it,
like what should what should we do because it's generally a new concept that we are
facing and I think it would resolve and we would come with a bit more macho ways on
how to cite it and how to use it. But personally if I use something and I get some ideas or like
use the whole functions that the generative AI generates, no I don't go and search like what is
the original repository that produced this one? Yeah. This is, of course, I don't have an answer
myself. And if people want to give their own opinion, in my opinion, it's nice anyway that
people discuss this use of these new tools, generative AI, and how people are using them,
because maybe then we can come up with a consensus on an ethical and responsible way of using them.
We also have a question about these generative AIs. You said if you generate something like
piece of code, you would become the owner of the code, right?
Is that correct?
Yeah.
The default policy is that whatever you generate with the large language model, you are the
copyright owner.
Do you add any citations or anything that I use generative AI for these codes I created?
So the journals have expanded on their policies on the use of generative AI, and so now publishers
like Nature or whatever, many publishers, they would now basically require you to add
a statement, how generative AI was used in the process. I'm not too strong. When I teach
about these things, I can tell that if you just used it for, I don't know, fixing your
English grammar, maybe. There's no point. But if it's clear that that work would have
not been able without the use of generative AI, then of course it must be mentioned.
so if i if my level of coding is very basic for whatever reason because i just started
and i get help from the generative ai and i'm basically not able to judge myself is this code
that the generative made right even though i see with the tests that i you know add that it feels
right at least i can be transparent that you know i got help or i used chat gpt for generating the
code for this and the code is published at this and that repository.
All right, so yeah, when it comes to software licenses, so now we are a bit focusing on
software. I've seen some people in the notes talking also about Creative Common. We will
touch a little bit on so-called data licensing later, but in general there is a taxonomy
of software licenses, this was from the European Commission, yes, so it's a publication that
basically talks about the EU public license, the European Union public license.
And so when it comes to software licenses, there are different, basically there's a continuum
of things that would basically, they are very dark green, that you could basically do whatever
you want with that type of license, so if you find a code and with that code in, I don't know,
GitHub, there is attached a license that says MIT or BST and so on, it means that most likely
you can reuse it and you can do anything you want, you can build on it. In some cases,
you don't even maybe need to tell who was the original author. On the other end of the spectrum,
we have the so-called strong copyleft licenses, and so here the idea is that if I find, let's say
that Ausen writes a package that I want to reuse, but it comes with a strong copyleft license,
it means that whatever I derive from AusenWord should also be released with that strong copyleft.
So I need to use the same license and in some cases, as they say, this license infects the rest
of my code. So it's not just the code that is using OSINT's StrongCopyLeft work that needs to
be released with that license. It might attach my whole project and now
I have to also release it with the StrongCopyLeft license. And in between there are this more kind of
sharealike. The idea of sharealike is that, okay, I make this software public with this license,
but I wouldn't mind that if you improve the software, you are kind of allowing me to
basically get your improvement so that I can also reuse. So it's kind of in between the two,
the very permissive one that lets anybody else to do whatever they want, and the very strict one
that forces everybody else to do as you decide to do.
What is your feeling from a research software engineer perspective?
Have you worked with the projects that have all sorts of licenses or do you feel that
in general it's more towards these permissive licenses?
Personally, I'm more like of the more open licenses like MIT or Creative Commons ones.
My idea is I'm using other people's code and if I'm able to publish the code, it's not
something confidential or it's not an ongoing project that I cannot publish yet, I would
go with more open licenses.
I totally understand, for some of the projects, it's better to have more copy-left licenses
or even a strong copy-left licenses.
An interesting thing is about this picture that we have, is about that arrows that we
have.
Can you also explain what are the arrows and how does it work?
Yeah, so here they talk about that the arrows represent compatibility.
And so that in some cases, you know, some licenses can kind of leave can be can be compatible
with other licenses, but in some other cases, the compatibility, you know, when the like,
for example, here, so if I remember correctly, this red block is more the proprietary licenses.
And so the very permissive licenses are compatible with proprietary licenses, meaning that you
can release a software that it's not going to be open source.
and inside it uses some of the permissive libraries,
but then here you see there's no compatibility
between if something is released
with a very strong compileft,
then nobody can use it in a proprietary software.
There's also here for those who want to explore more,
there are this nice set of links
that help you, for example,
comparing licenses and choosing licenses.
There are different,
There are many nice tools that given you might even answer some questionnaire or what you would like to do with your license and then they can recommend you
with whatever type of licenses.
All right. So maybe I think we agreed that we will not do this exercise for the sake of speed and we can now talk when should I add a license.
So the best, of course, is as early as possible, like with everything else, that if you agree
at the beginning that you want to choose a certain license, then you choose it at the beginning.
It's funny that with the GitHub interface, when you create a repository from the web interface,
immediately it asks you, which license do you want to attach with it? So it's clear.
Any year I can see citations to myself, what I was saying also earlier that if you work from the very beginning as if your project is already public and open,
then you can already think at the very beginning that there's a license, that there's a policy,
because of course in this social coding part we didn't really mention this earlier but you might also want to recommend how people can contribute to the improvements of your code,
of your code, you can create a community around your project
and tools like GitHub allow you easily to create issues,
create discussions around your code.
So basically, when should you add a license?
As early as possible.
And how to add a license if your work is derivative work?
So basically, these tools that I mentioned earlier
that could check the compatibility
would allow you to see that if you reuse some specific package that might have permissive
or strong copyleft licenses, then you can see what type of license you can basically
attach to the code.
In general, maybe one comment that at least when I was asking you or saying that you are
in favor of more permissive licenses. What I wanted to add is that sometimes you have
to think that the users of your software, those who will reuse, is there other people
like you. So the permissive licenses, even though you might feel you are donating your
code to the Google, Microsoft, Meta, whatever, at the end of the day, you're just making
it easier for other people like you to reuse your code if you have a permissive license.
With more copyleft licenses, they're of course very ethical and it's nice that some projects
are strong copyleft and they demand that whoever uses those projects also become strong copyleft.
But when it comes to researchers like us, sometimes we might just make the life more
complicated when the researchers need to publish their code with their papers. So at the end
the day. If you aren't sure which one to pick, go with the most permissive licenses. Do you have any
comment on this? No, it was perfect coverage. Thanks. Yeah. All right. So something that I
think I got to see, like it's not an exact questions on the HackMD, but I get a team that
it's happening. Let's say sorting algorithms, right? So do someone own the sorting algorithms
and have license on them, or only it depends on the implementation and the code has been published?
Yeah. As usual, I'm not a lawyer, so I don't take my words for legal advice.
But in my understanding and in my discussion with legal experts,
add the idea of the algorithm the pseudocode is not patentable so if i write a book with pseudocode on how to do this whatever sorting method,
nobody can patented but in the moment that i make an implementation.
as a system that is reusable, kind of as a standalone system, so not just writing the pseudocode into some code,
then it can be patentable. So let's say that I have a web application where you copy-paste your vector of numbers and then press a button,
and then my web application sorts your number in a very whatever fast way then this is a system and
I can patent this web application for sorting numbers but if I would just have the code that
does the sort I would not be able to patent that but I can still protect it with the license so
that I can say okay you want to use my sort fast sort algorithm then I don't know use I'm going to
attach a very copyleft license you have to make everything open if you use it.
Yep, thanks.
Let's see if there's any other question to bring up.
It's nice that there's many answers already so that we don't have to.
Yeah, that's why I was a bit silent. I was trying to
to rest of my knowledge, but our other contributors to thanks everyone.
In general, this there's also sometimes what could happen is that things might change in
time. So that may be a project start with a certain license, but then for whatever reason
you realize that, I don't know, you really need to adopt, change the license to a more
copy-left one because you started using some software that has a more copy-left license.
Of course, licensing can change in time. It's not preferable in a sense that if you would
really need to apply this, you would kind of need to contact, you know, your user base
and tell them, okay, you've been using my code as permissive license, but from today
license is not permissive anymore, it becomes copy left. So of course, you might be familiar
yourself that the terms and conditions of whatever service that you use change in time so often that
nobody even reads what is the new change. So the same would also go here. So changing the license
is not retroactive and if someone is still using the code, does it apply to them or how
does it work?
Yeah.
Well, again, it depends because I would hope that it's not retroactive in a sense that
if a release of a certain version of a certain tool was released with, let's say, a very
open permissive license that i can still allow to use that you know open version of the software
because maybe the company decided that from version 2.0 they went full copyright you know
so maybe i'm still allowed to use version 1.0 but 2.0 i need to buy whatever the license from
the company but then there are also some other aspects maybe this is more related to data
that can be changes to the license of data that can be retroactive and the general data protection regulation the GDPR is one example of this so that if I released open personal data 10 years ago actually GDPR would affect the license of that data and would not allow me to keep it open anymore.
So, again, it depends, but it's clear, for example, for those who really are into these
legal matters, I would really recommend reading this paper from the European Commission where
they describe this type of license, the European Union Public License.
It's a bit of a, it's a share-alike license, so it's not in the most permissive, but it's
also not in the most strong copy left.
And what is interesting is that whatever projects related to the European Commission, they are
being released with this license, so that it's clear that it's for the benefit of everyone
that those who will reuse this code kind of make also their code in this public licensure
like public license.
And then you can basically get what other people made with your code and improve your
code.
work of course to to make sure that also the new code that you release also follows this
the same type of share alike license but this is kind of the best balance between you know being
permissive and letting other people to use as much as possible and also being more ethical
to kind of you know also get back from from what you give. Yeah we also we have a comment from a
user that like the more open licenses cannot be closed retroactively and also like if you have
different versions or you release a new version you can change the license but as a standard for
the free software you cannot change the existing license without changing that version or the code.
Yeah so that's what I was saying as well. Yes and one thing that I wanted to ask is
Do you have any comments or thoughts on multi-licensing, or do you usually use one-line sense, or what
is the best practice here?
Well, I mean, I see the point of having multi-licenses, dual licenses, because sometimes some businesses,
maybe in the context of academic research, maybe there's not much point, but if some
of the research turns into a business idea or, you know, if companies want to have a
mixture of copyright, private code and public, there is a benefit that, you know, if something
is used for, I don't know, commercial purposes, then maybe you follow a certain license. But
But then again, I'm also a bit conflicted with these dual licenses, because if one really
looks at the open source and open source software licenses, it is clear that you can't really
impose what people can do with your code.
One of the advantages of the open source software licenses is that you're not liable yourself
with whatever people will do, but also you can't control if people, for example, will
use your code for doing something malicious. You can't block them with these licenses.
Yeah, but I guess that the takeaway here is like you can use multiple licenses and
which is a good, which can be a good practice if it's suitable for your case, for your data,
or for yourself files. You can add a different license than the general license that you have
for the whole repository. All right, I guess it's time for a little break. We can come back
and maybe we can come back at the 14 o'clock or 14.01, 14.02. Yeah, maybe 14.02.
All right, so let's have a little break and we will be back in 10 minutes.
How about one on welcome back?
to the social coding section. We already talked about social coding and sharing your code and
also a bit of about licensing. Now we want to talk about software citations. We talked about
how code is a bit different than papers and why there are different things that you have to
consider and citation is one of the things which maybe is more similar and also a bit different
then paper citations, I would say. So here in the screen, you can see we want to talk about
FAIR principles first. So [name], what is FAIR principles?
Yeah, so we touched on this FAIR principles also in the morning when it comes to the reproducibility.
And basically the FAIR principle is like, you know, the acronyms would be findable,
accessible interoperable and reusable and now while this maybe is kind of easy to understand
when it comes to data because of course you want your data set to be findable by whatever search
system accessible whether it is fully open or open on request so but at least there is a way
to access it interoperable which means that you can work with other tools it's in a format that
other softwares can open it and read it and reusable so that there is like we just discussed
a license that would give some principles on how to reuse this to reuse it the same
pair principle for data they can also be extended to software and so again that people can find
your software that they can access it they can download it interoperable so that it works with
data system and that there is a clear way on how to reuse it with clear licenses attached
to the software, for example.
So again, because sometimes people you might think, okay, I put my software, my scripts
that I've done for this paper, I put them in my university homepage or they are on GitHub
and that's it.
always need to think a little bit long term. And I have to mention actually that me, myself,
I decided to use some GitHub repository from the university and then that repository is
not there anymore. So now I have published paper that are pointed to some Git repository
hosted by a department that doesn't exist anymore. And so once in a while I get questions
where is the code now, you know. So there was a mistake on my side that I didn't actually
create a so-called DOI, Digital Object Identifier, or PID, Persistent Identifier,
because if I would have done that, another organization would have taken care of preserving
my software for as many years as we can think of. And so what we see here in this make your code
citable and persistent, the persistent part is exactly this. It's not enough to put it on your
web page or to put it on github because github maybe will change your account will be i don't
know maybe you decide to delete your account and with that all your repository or by accident you
even delete a repository because you thought that that was just a side project so there are services
like zenodo which is hosted by cern and with zenodo you can basically get a digital object
identifier for anything digital it can be the software release for example or it can also be
used for for data sets that can be published. And so what is nice about this Zenodo repository
is that it automatically can be linked with your open with your available GitHub repositories
so that whenever you create a release on your GitHub project repository Zenodo can actually
automatically basically pull the new release so that you can basically have a permanent copy of
your GitHub releases stored in the CERN data center. Have you ever published this type of
DOI or have you helped anyone with this type of getting a DOI for a software or SANE?
Yeah, we were helping a researcher to publish the code and we had to use that and also explain
the things that you already explained about why it's important to just have a DOI and
it's not enough to only host it on your personal GitHub account because in 10 years GitHub can
go down, right?
We don't know.
Yeah.
And people and researchers are already familiar with this because it's also a very similar
aspect in publishing your paper as well. It's not enough to publish your PDF or
PDF of your research on your personal website or Google Drive. You have to have a DOI
to make it persistent for the future. Yeah, it's also nice that the interface that
comes with the Zenodo website. If you see, if you search for some software, you can actually
look at some metrics. Again, we don't do this for the metrics, but sometimes the metrics help us,
whatever motivate our bosses, that you can look at metrics like number of downloads and number
of citations so that, you know, you can also kind of quantify a little bit impact that your
software or scripts might have. What is here now it is a checklist. Checklists are always useful
because they're practical and you can basically see what is needed to make your software citable
and so assigning appropriate license like we mentioned before the break then we want to
to have a description of the software so that there is appropriate metadata format, clear
version numbers, authors are credited, we get this persistent identifier like the DOI,
and then even sometimes we won't tell in the software which publication to cite, because
in some cases some publications might be related, the so-called software packages publications,
some other cases the main publication is about let's say some application of the software but
still you release the software along with the original publication. Recently there's
there's also the way that through your on your github repository you can also like a so-called
machine readable software citation file so cff citation file format and it basically looks
something like this. So machine readable means that a computer, another computer can automatically
read and you see that these are like variables with the names and the values and some can be
you know structure. It looks a bit like this yaml files and so this pre kind of fixed
metadata about the software makes it easier and makes especially if you have you know search
and genes or or specific publication and genes that it's easy for these other tools to basically
index your software and make it findable and accessible and so on with the FAIR principles.
GitHub now supports this citation cff files so if you name the file with this
exactly like a citation.cff it can already be automatically interpreted by by GitHub and here
there's some like a video how to create it and even a web but in practice if you are from if
you're fine with that with using some text editor it's you can even take just this template and
and reuse it so anything else to add was is there anything in the notes document worth
uh no we don't have any questions or comments till now all right well then in general also
So this is one way to get your citations with the software.
But in some cases, maybe your software, the contribution that you and your research group
add to the software can be substantial so that there can be papers that are truly about
software.
So full papers that they describe software packets.
And then there are specific journals that accept this type of software papers.
So then if I can kind of call back of someone was mentioning that sometimes software is
not peer-reviewed, with this type of work you can understand that it's the software
even more important than the actual paper.
And so it might go to more extensive peer-review and checks and compatibility and so on.
At the end of the day, like Jose mentioned earlier, it's maybe not the actual work of
the two or three peer reviewers,
but it's really the community
that is around the software project.
So if these larger packages,
they have a big community around
and we can all be part of that community,
whether it's just fixing a typo in the documentation
or working on a new release with the main developers,
so that the peer review is truly a dynamic process
that basically never ends.
not that when this software was published in 2021, it has not been touched. I'm sure that
it has improved in the meantime and it has evolved and gotten better and better.
One note that I wanted to add is like the papers that only talking about the software are becoming
more popular nowadays. And at least for a lot of Python libraries, all libraries, you can see
they publish the paper. And it's also good for the researchers as well, because they get
many, many citations, which is maybe not the case for your scientific papers. So consider
on publishing the paper for your code as well, which is becoming more popular nowadays.
Yeah, and it's true. And it's nice that maybe this type of metrics like, you know, maybe
right now in the CV, in some standard CV that might not yet be space for your software packages,
but these are catching up. So I can mention in Finland, there is the tank CV, which is
one format used by the Finnish grant agencies. And already they would have a section right
now they have a section right now that where one can add this type of extra non-typical
paper type of publications or like software.
All right so we still have 10 minutes left and then of course we will ask about the feedback
of the day. The last part is about sharing data. Now there are many and better and more
extensive talks online on sharing data because as you can understand when it comes we discussed
a lot about software sharing and contributing and reuse it but all the same could be said
about data that sometimes we might wanna have a data set that is truly copyrighted and so
nobody else can access and they need to ask you for a license or maybe they need to pay you
you. But some other times we might have a data set that you can fully release opening
whether because you decide to do so with your employer with your supervisor and of course
everything in between where you might want like we had this share alike for the software
the same would be for the data that you share the data but any derivative work done with
and the data should also be released with a similar license, for example.
So when it comes to this, where to actually share the data,
what type of options are there, this Zenodo repository is also mentioned in this case.
In Zenodo, it's not just about sharing the release of your software,
but you can share all sorts of data and it's really nice that you can also share
slides and white papers or anything that you feel like that can contribute to your scientific
community. But Zenodo is not the only one and so there are these other services. I'd like to at
least mention the Open Science Framework that allows to do this type of sharing of nice dataset.
But in international context, the Open Science Framework is hosted in the United States,
Ferrari members, Zenodo is in Switzerland, Figshare I think now is bought by Naturespringer,
EU.is basically EOSC or European platform, and Dryad is also, I don't think it's public
anymore, or they might give you a non-profit, like a small, how do you call, freemium license.
But here then we will not go through this, but different countries, at least in the Nordics
where most of you are right now, there are different national services for sharing the
data and there are also resources for the so-called data management. Now again we will not expand
much on here but if you think that if git was using for keeping versioning versions of your code
the same could be done with data so that you can version the version of the data set because you
had version 1.0 that had some I don't know outliers but then you have version 2.0 where
where you clean the data, remove the outliers and so on.
So these type of tools like Data Lad,
Data Stewardship Wizard, Git Annex,
that is not mentioned here, but it's Prattix Data Lad,
so they can help you basically keep also the versioning
of the data and not just of the code.
And then when it comes to the licensing of data sets
and databases which are a specific type of data set,
there are different legislation that can cover this.
And similarly, as we had for software,
we can have something that is in the full spectrum
from completely open public domain
to completely private copyright.
So the type of licenses that you hear about data,
there's so-called creative common licenses.
There are different flavors
with the CC0 being the so-called public domain
where it's as open as possible,
people can reuse and they don't even need to cite you.
And then more kind of restrictions
on the reuse of the data,
which could be that people need to cite you
or people cannot do commercial work with that
or this share alike that people need to re-share
what they did with the data
as you are doing with the data and basically so on.
When it comes to the machine learning and AI,
things are of course getting a little bit more complicated.
Machine learning models are impracticed data,
so the model, the weights on its own,
they can't really be,
you can't do much with those unless you
have a system to basically run the models and whether you
are generating data or
classifying whatever you're classifying but what is tricky and at least what is
a bit blurred right now here in the context of AI and machine learning
models is that sometimes you hear things like open source models or open source
language models but if one really would kind of look at the definition of open
source they are actually not open source they sometimes people call open weights
so that the models, the weights, the actual file,
you can download it and reuse it,
but you have no idea of how that model was done.
So everything else basically around the model
is actually not open at all.
Here, it mentions this Artificial Intelligence Act,
which was became entering into force
on the 1st of August of this year.
And the AI Act adds some basically restrictions
on what the researchers even can basically open.
If you're not planning to open anything
related to your AI models,
basically the AI act lets you do whatever you want.
But in the moment that you need to start sharing your model,
you need to basically see if your type
of machine learning model would fall inside
of this so-called high risk or prohibited AI systems.
And of course, there are different, how can I say, obligations. There are different legal
obligations depending on what type of artificial intelligence systems you might be working
on. In general, we have some material on these new topics that we will expand on this page.
But if you have questions, of course, please write them down in the chat. And then many
nice links here that would be nice to browse together, but our time is soon over.
I was saying, do you have any comments or is there anything to highlight from the notes?
No. In the notes, we don't have any direct question to sharing data. We had some questions
about software citations and some about like accounts, but not about sharing data.
And yeah, it was completely good. If you want to pick, if you need to choose one of these
further readings and you have time to go deeper into all this reproducible research, opening data
and opening software, I really recommend this Turing Way, which is an open book on all these
topics. It's a nice read. You can read it. It's open. You can read it on your mobile phone during
your commute. So if you really need to pick one, I recommend the first one. And in general,
I mean, it's nice that we are building a community together through Code Refinery.
If you explore our pages, you can also get access to a chat. And in the chats that we use,
is called Zulip and through the Zulip chat you can join discussions. We can continue discussions
on these topics and we have all sorts of discussions there so that is something nice.
We already saw some participants from this workshop have already joined the Code Refinery chat.
All right, so we still have eight minutes which is a good moment for asking for feedback.
so it would be great if on the notes we could paste the usual feedback for the day
if this was too fast too slow
and i see that they are already there i could actually switch
to the notes view with my movie director interface
And so yes, as usual, even though we give similar lessons over the years, they're never
exactly the same, the phases are changing, we might update the lesson a little bit, and
of course what makes this unique is your questions and your experience, so please give us feedback
and if there's something you want to you think that we could have covered more or
less please write it down. Then tomorrow we have we have the fifth day of the
workshop and tomorrow the topic will be documentation which is kind of somewhat
related with the topics of the day so because along with the license you also want to tell
people not just how to use your code but also how to maybe you know expand it, contribute to it
and so on. And then the second part of tomorrow will be about Jupyter notebooks. Maybe some of
you are already familiar with this way of interacting with code and data and hopefully
for those who have never experienced this, it's something you can try out. Again, tomorrow
will be like a demo day, so you're not expected to actually, you know, run things, but if
you want to actually do and see what people are doing, whether you want to build the documentation,
and it's not just about documentation, because with the same system that will be introduced
Tomorrow you can also, it's the same system
that we use to build our web pages,
our training materials,
they're all built with this same system.
And so, you can also learn how to create your website,
for example, under this github.io if you want.
And so, if you wanna test these things,
you please follow our installation instructions
if you're planning to do that.
All right. I think I see that people are commenting. Is there anything to highlight? Let me have a look at the chat.
Um, based on the feedback, uh, I think a place where that was on track,
if I was satisfied with the speed and although like some, we have some
comments that, uh, it was a bit too fast and there were like many topics
that we had to cover and, uh, unfortunately maybe it was a bit too
fast if you don't have the required background or if you're not familiar
with it, with the subject, it can be a bit overwhelming.
This is exactly why we decided almost a year ago to not having exercises in this week too,
because sometimes not only there's lots of new topics, on top of those try to run snake
make locally or building a Zenodo repository or how do you call it, getting a DOI through
there's another sandbox so we hopefully this is a little bit more digestible and useful
and of course we provide you with all these links and other resources that those who really
have time can can try themselves and please join our Zulip chat so that we can continue
discussing there and helping you there if you want to try these things and you need
further help.
All right.
So hopefully this was a good day for and
I can maybe add also a reminder that day six will be more about
coding related things. We will cover things like automated testing
and modular code development and then again if you want to do or if you want to try the exercises
that the instructors are going to show on the stream you can also you should basically also
install what we recommend in our installation pages but then again it's just fine to participate
through the questions and thank you again for the many questions there's almost 50 today so
it was great that you were so active. Also, thanks for the participants who
were active in answering other questions. Thanks. I see one question that is for me that is related
to the one ECTS credit. And so, yes, in this case, I tried to be as clear as possible on that page,
but if something is not clear, I'm happy to expand it. In practice, this means that if you
you are sure that your supervisor or study coordinator or whoever is able to accept a
kind of an official paper from me that says that this person has completed the Code Refinery
workshop, there are very simple homework to do for getting the certificate, then I will
give you this document and then you can convert that into a credit.
And if you are at Aalto University, you just need to give me your student number and I
will add the credit for you on our system.
But in general, we don't track if you were attending, you know, whatever days you were
attending.
As long as you do the homeworks, we can, you know, we can give you, we can give you the
credit.
Okay, so let's see if there's any other quick question to pick.
We still have one minute and a half.
Yeah, I think most of the things are uncertain.
All right, maybe we can call it a day, one minute earlier, and thank you for watching.
The recordings will appear immediately on Twitch TV and later on the week on our YouTube
channels and so see you tomorrow for day 5 of Code Refinery.
Thank you [name] for being here with me and thank you everyone for watching.
Thank you everyone for joining.
Bye.
Bye bye.