All right, so now it's 10 a.m. in Finland, let's start.
I will first introduce you and then I will let you do the show.
So let me switch to [name]' screen.
All right.
Welcome, everyone, to the fourth episode
of this Code Refinery workshop, September 2024.
I'm [name], and I will be the host for you,
with you today.
And today the topic is reproducibility,
specifically more kind of the computational reproducibility.
So trying to replicate the results of other people
or even try to replicate what you did
a few months or a few years ago.
The first part of today,
which will last for a couple of hours,
will be presented by [name].
[name], do you wanna say something about yourself?
a research software engineer at Aalto, which is the scientific computing group, same as [name]
essentially. And then [name] will be joined by [name]. [name], do you want to say something about
yourself? Hello, I'm [name]. I'm also a research software engineer at Aalto. So we are basically
all colleagues here now. Thanks. And then later after the lunch break, which will go from 12 to
one finish time. There will be [name] and I talking about social coding and licensing.
[name], do you want to introduce yourself?
Yeah, sure. I'm [name]. I'm also one of the RSEs at Alto. Happy to be here.
So it's a full Alto team this time, all based in Finland. So apologies if I will use the finish
time zone as a reference, but I guess you can convert it to your central European or wherever
you live. Just a reminder that the materials for today are linked in the main page of the workshop
and if you keep the notes document open we will also post the links to the materials that
the instructors are showing. This week compared to the first week is a week where we will not do
actual exercises. But of course there will be lots of questions for you and discussions. So in
practice the notes document is our main tool for interacting. We decided to do it like this for now
a couple of times. The reason being that sometimes all the material that are presented in the second
part of the week, in the second part of the workshop, it can be overwhelming to try to do
the exercises and also understand what's going on. So there are exercises written in the materials,
and of course you're welcome to try them later if you have time. But in general, try to follow
our demos and our discussion and try to contribute with lots of questions,
because that's the best that we can get out of this experience.
So I think, yeah. I'd like to add one thing here. One of the reasons that we don't do the exercises
also because some of the tools that we are showing this week are very specialized tools and not
actually useful for everything and going through the exercises if you think yeah think it's useful
for you yeah it's definitely a good idea but some of the tools can just be skipped
yes all right i think this is all for the introduction so i'm gonna leave the scene
and the screen to [name] and [name] and I'll be back later for the break.
Okay so yeah this week and particularly today is about reproducible research
and it essentially starts with getting files in order. You have already last week seen a lot about
version control. No, sorry. It's about how to code, what to use as names for your functions
and so on and this will be done. We'll mainly focus on tomorrow and on Thursday.
As mentioned earlier, documentation is a very important part of reproducible research because
without documentation it's very difficult to redo what others have done
and that will be covered extensively tomorrow. The last week you've already
had a version control of code of text and how to do that, how to do
collaborative and distributed version control and what are the challenges
there. You further have things like stabilizing your computing environment
so that others can more easily reproduce what you have done
because they know what your environment actually looked
like, and part of this is covered today.
And other ways to do this are shown in more detail
tomorrow and on Thursday.
And it's, of course, also about how you publish your research
outputs, how you publish your code, your data,
your documents that you need.
And social coding and open software
will also be discussed later today.