Okay.
Welcome back, everyone.
Yeah, welcome back. Hope you all had a refreshing break.
And you are ready to continue with Jupiter.
I'm [name].
I'm going to be teaching this lesson together with [name],
which you've already heard earlier today.
We'll go through Jupyter Notebooks.
And yeah, hope you're all ready.
Yeah.
OK, so the idea is this session is, again,
a good number of demonstrations.
We'll look at Jupyter and JupyterLab
and talk about notebooks in general.
So you might already know what notebooks are,
how they are used.
They're a common way of sharing research software
and sharing the results of that software.
So they are a good way of doing,
of implementing reproducibility and collaboration
for usability of code.
Exactly. And if I may add, I mean, for those of you who are already very familiar with
Jupyter notebooks, you might find this very basic. So, [name], if you scroll down a little
bit on this page, so under optional episodes, you'll see some examples of more advanced
Jupyter features, which you may find interesting. So again, if you know a lot about Jupyter,
and you might find that still interesting enough.
But yeah, so, I mean, we'll see relatively basic usage,
but the thing, I think the main take-home message
is more about how would notebooks work,
how they are useful and how they're not useful,
like what are the caveats?
And it also, this is about Jupyter,
we'll be demonstrating with Jupyter,
But these points mostly apply to all other notebook interfaces as well.
Yeah, exactly.
So maybe, I mean, we are going to demonstrate Python codes in this lesson,
but if you're working with other programming languages,
it's still possible to use Jupyter and we'll talk a little bit about that.
And maybe one comment, so let's address the big elephant in the room.
why actually use JupyterLab instead of other codes like Visual Studio Code that we've already touched a bit upon earlier.
So, I would say it's really a matter of preference.
If you are coding in Python, then JupyterLab is fairly common.
You can use it again with other programming languages as well,
but in the end it's really up to you what you have available on your computer. You might even
like to try different tools and see which one you like the most and you find most useful.
Okay, so yeah, I'm not 100% sure this is true. I think I've heard it actually in
code refinery somewhere, so maybe it is. What I've heard is that Jupyter, the name comes from
Julia, Python, and R. So Jupyter definitely supports Julia, Python, and R.
Exactly.
So the kernels exist for those languages, and you can run any general commands in Jupyter,
but it is designed around those languages. Yeah, I mean now there are also kernels available for
Fortran and C and Mathematica, whatever. There are really like more than 100 different kernels
they may use, but some, I mean, Jupyter notebooks may be more useful for Python or in Julia,
if I may choose. But again, there are lots of different options.
Okay. So, what is Jupyter then? And what are notebooks?
So, I'm not sure how visible this is. Well, you don't need to actually see the code,
but which one is easier to follow?
Here's a description
and then example one here
that gives the code to follow this
gives the code
that does runs this example
or here another option where instead of essentially a script
script with some comments. You have some formatted text explaining each of the sections of code.
This is a rhetorical question. I mean, almost certainly, this is easier for most people
to follow, it looks nicer, it has some formatting, and the code is still displayed as code and
runnable as code, but it's interposed with these formatted text blocks that explain what's
happening.
Exactly. I mean, I like a lot the syntax highlighting. Well, now you have it in both examples, but
sometimes you need to do some additional things in order to enable code syntax highlighting in your
regular editor. So Julia Peter Lab does already that for you and I do like that a lot. Also,
I like the fact that you can really add documentation to your code together with the
code lines and also the fact that you can break it a little bit into pieces. It makes it much
much more readable, in my opinion.
So it's great for, definitely for, well,
for shorter scripts or programs.
Okay, so that is the basic idea.
There's, it renders text and then includes your code
and the results of that code in between.
So it's like a notebook.
You write down, actually, I think, is there,
Do we have that image of the notebook?
No.
Oh, well, I mean, if you're doing this old-fashioned way,
you would be looking through a telescope, for example,
and scribbling notes in a notebook,
and then maybe drawing a picture,
and then writing some equations and so on,
like solving the equations as you go.
So this is the same idea.
You can write text, and then you can do computational stuff
and display the results of that computational stuff
in between the text.
It really looks like a notebook and behaves like a notebook.
OK, so this interface, this notebook-like interface
has been used in a lot of other places.
Jupyter doesn't have any sort of exclusive right to it
or anything.
So there's plenty of places that use that, and it really works quite nicely.
I know you can edit Jupyter Notebooks directly in VS Code, so I'm not sure if this means
that or something else.
Yeah.
So you need to install an extension, but it's easy, I would say, or it's well-documented
as well. And in principle you can do the same thing we are doing in this lesson in VS Code.
So it's again a matter of preference and what you have available to you. Because in VS Code
essentially everything works by extensions. Installing another extension is not a problem.
Okay, so there's some case examples here. You can look through these also in your own time.
but for example, is it true here, you can take a look at an existing notebook.
Here is this binder link. So we will actually have a section where we
demonstrate creating a repository and then looking at it through
binder, but here you can quickly take a look once it, not quickly because it takes a while to start
the kernel, but it will install all the requirements from the requirements.txt or
in other languages as environments and runtime.txt. Yeah, and I think this is
yeah, this is actually one of the strengths I see when it comes to working with Jupyter
notebooks, the fact that it's easily shareable to other people. You can make sure that you can
ship your code together with the requirements that you need for that to work and you can
easily show it to someone else and you don't even have to have your own computer with you.
You can just grab it from GitHub or some other place where you have your code. So that
It makes your code very accessible.
Okay, let's check back on that later.
But yeah, so they have actually, they've created these notebooks
and then they have set up a repository on GitHub
so that you can essentially, you can repeat their results
and you can read through their description
while you are repeating those results.
So that's really nice reproducibility.
Here's another example, so you can also launch this in Binder and a gallery of more examples.
There's a lot of these.
So what is Jupyter good for?
What are notebooks good for?
So if you're describing a linear workflow where you want to describe it and at the same
and demonstrate what's going on.
You want to display your results, your research results.
That's a very good showcase or a script that
reproduces your research results.
It's also really good for experimenting.
So you can go and change a piece of a part of the code
and rerun parts of it without having
to do the entire analysis from the beginning.
And yeah, it can also be an interactive development environment for code and visualization and so on.
It can also be, you can now have it running on a server, or you can run a server and then multiple people can edit at the same time, which is really nice.
So yeah, it's great for sharing your code, sharing your workflow, sharing your results,
teaching and so on.
So students can go and change the code and see what happens.
That's also really nice.
Yeah.
I especially like it when producing figures because I always find it takes a lot of time
to find good settings for a figure and the fact that it's so interactive makes it very
useful.
So now this example is done.
There is an index.ipython notebook, which I'm opening.
Yeah, so maybe you can comment a bit how you actually got to this window.
Well, I mean, once I, I mean, I clicked through here and clicked the Binder link, and once
it was done, it actually automatically went into this window.
Okay, so now you are having...
I'm on Binder now.
Okay. So, I mean, yeah, it kind of did it automatically. So, I will open my own local
version of this interface. This is JupyterLab in a moment. But now, I guess the point is to
mainly to display this, to show everybody this notebook about gravitational waves.
So, I'm not going to run anything here, but the results are already there.
So, you can have, there's some titles, some description, and then you can see the data,
the raw data, and how they progressively, they work on the data and get a final result.
So, okay, I'm leaving that.
So this is the first gravitational wave discovery, looking at the original data and the result.
So from the raw data, you can reproduce the plot in the paper, which is really nice.
Okay.
So some pitfalls.
So if you have nonlinear code flow, which basically means calling functions and for loops and
functions calling functions and so on, something complicated,
then Jupyter is probably not going to be very clear.
So I mean, you can still use Jupyter,
and you can define most of the functions
outside in a module that you import.
And I mean, we will do that, I think, in this demonstration.
So the main thing there of course is to explain what the function is doing and have a good
readable name for the function so that people reading the notebook understand what's going
on.
It doesn't really work well with large codebases.
Essentially when you're running one Jupyter notebook it does not interact with another
so you have essentially just one file and everything else you need to import as a module.
Tomorrow we'll actually have an example during the modular code development
lesson on how you actually at some point need to leave the Jupyter notebook interface and move to
something else, be it running in the command line or using other tools which make larger codes.
Yeah. So, for Jupyter notebooks specifically, they are JSON files and they include images
and so on. So, it's not straightforward to write one in a text editor. And of course,
you cannot run the cells in the pure text editor. The text editor has to support running
well, Jupyter notebooks directly. So that can be a limitation.
Notebooks can be version controlled, but if it includes images or big data files,
there are some limitations for version controlling notebooks.
And specifically for Jupyter, JupyterLab, notebooks are not named by default, you need
to remember to name them, otherwise you just have unnamed.ipython notebook, which is unclear.
So yeah, there's a bunch of, there's a bit more pitfalls listed here.
I think the biggest one though is that you can run cells out of order, which does make
development easier so if you change something in the beginning you don't necessarily have to run
all the cells but it means that the state of execution is not clear or the state of your
program is not clear from the text what that you see especially if you while you are developing it
so that can always cause problems if you run if you write a bunch of cells and then you run them
in some random order, you will get weird results. And you can do that.
Okay, so it is a good idea to, before saving your notebook and before sharing any results,
it's a good idea to run all the cells in order and then save, so that when someone else opens
the notebook and tries to run stuff, they will get the same results as you get. And if there's
a problem, you will notice. Okay, so should we go to start? Yeah, and maybe I can comment that,
I mean, this will become a bit clearer during the lesson. It's a bit hard for newcomers to
understand what cells are and so on, but we'll demonstrate this, so bear with us a little bit.
Yeah, we'll come back to it and clarify. Okay, so I will
go to the terminal and start JupyterLab. So first, let's make a new folder,
JupyterLab demo,
and then I am in the CodeRefinery environment, so I have everything installed already,
so I can run the command jupyter lab oh there's many of these okay jupyter lab
now it opened okay I do not want to receive news so it opened automatically in the browser window
that's most recently open it will do whatever your system's default is to open a browser
window. Let's look through the interface. I will get the notes to the side again because I
again forgot to do that. So here we are. JupyterLab is here displaying in the browser.
There is a notebook server that's running essentially the process that's running in
the terminal here and you can see it's printing out some information that I cannot read.
But yeah, that is not so important to understand. So the main focus is the browser interface.
Yeah, so yeah, essentially it's running on my, everything's running on my laptop here,
but yeah this you see you interact with it through the browser um okay so now what do we have here
we have a file manager we don't have any files currently but uh this it lists all the files here
there's also um a list of well i guess list of kernels maybe we'll come back to what that means
There's a tab for git, so if it's a git repository, you will see some information here.
You can initialize a git repository, or clone one into this folder.
Table of contents of the currently open notebook can be useful.
And then extensions, which we will use at some point later.
But I think the first thing to do is to create a notebook.
So let's go create a notebook.
OK, the plus button just creates a new launcher tab here.
So we already have one.
So let's then start a notebook.
OK, and this has no name.
So what would be a better name for this?
Example, demo, demo.
It's always best to rename your notebooks the first thing
you do when you open them.
Who doesn't have lots of, well, who
once the untitled file is on the computer.
Yeah, and it's easy to forget because it doesn't even
ask you for a name by default.
OK, so now we can type stuff into these cells.
So let's start with a markdown cell.
So this is a cell, first of all, and I can type stuff in.
So I'll type some markdown in.
So how do you choose whether it's Markdown or if it's a code cell?
So actually this is currently code, but I'm typing in Markdown.
So I need to go and click through here and select Markdown.
So now it is a Markdown cell.
Okay, I'm not going to repeat the entire example notebook. I think we get it from
a repository later. So I'll just write some random equations here, not random.
I'm not actually sure how to write an equation here, but it doesn't matter that much.
So, dollar signs, in between dollar signs.
Okay.
Okay, I'll just run this.
So to run this, I can press play here and it creates a new cell below.
So when you run a Markdown cell, it renders it.
It displays the result of this Markdown code.
And then I can run Python code or write Python code.
So let's do, what should I do, import a module, import random, and what should I do, random.
Let's get some results from this.
Yeah, I would copy paste from our lesson material.
I would suggest this to our participants as well if they want to play around later on.
So you don't necessarily have to understand everything that is in the code lines but just
the general idea.
Again you can use it later.
We have Markdown cells.
So yeah, there is an example of Markdown cells here and so I'm going to just paste into this
but we have already talked a good bit about Markdown.
Here's again examples of Markdown equations.
understands this format for equations, this format that is, and some more
formatting. So let's run that one. It's nice you can also include figures, I mean
images of any kind. Yeah. That's cool if you want to present something for
others and you just want to show... Well yeah, let's just do a
hello world here that's a good example okay okay so that cell is now a code
cell can you show again I mean how you change well when you create a new cell
it will by default be code so yeah you can again go from here and make it a
markdown cell, or you can make it a code cell.
Yeah, and in this case, our interpreter is Python.
If we use some other extension, then we could
write code in, I don't know, Julia or R,
but right now we are using Python as an interpreter. Yeah, so I started
this from Python, installed it from PyPI,
so it is by default, it's defaulting to Python.
But yeah, you can also have other kernels and choose other languages.
Okay, so is there anything more on this?
Anything else that's important in here?
There's a keyboard shortcuts that are, if you start using notebooks extensively, Jupyter notebooks
extensively, then these are useful shortcuts that you will probably learn sooner or later.
And then we have some tools for debugging, testing, and writing code in notebooks are useful.
Yeah, I only know a couple of shortcuts which I use all the time, and then
then many other things I do by clicking, which is not optimal, but then again, I mean, it's
maybe I don't use JupyterLab enough so that it's super useful. But yeah, creating new
cells and running things, that's good to have shortcuts for.
So, yeah, essentially, I know one shortcut, which is Ctrl-Enter to run a cell.
Yeah.
And maybe it's good to point out that this may be different on different operating systems.
Right.
So, it may be Ctrl-Enter or Shift-Enter.
Yeah, so it's...
If you don't know, you can check the settings you have on JupyterLab, and I think they will
be listed there.
At least here we have command in parenthesis, but here we don't, so I'm not sure which it
is.
But it is either control or command, depending on your system.
Okay.
But I suppose we can move forward.
So in this example, we essentially do what the notebooks are good for.
write a narrative and we get some results and then later we publish this so that everyone
else can view it and run the same code. Okay, so should we explain this or how much should
we explain this? So this is a way of calculating pi, but it is more useful as a demonstration
than it is as an actually fast way of computing pi.
So we're essentially on the computer we're throwing dice on a square and then we are
checking if they land inside the circle or not.
And use the area of the square compared to the area of the circle to figure out what
Pi is. Okay, so we start JupyterLab. We already did that. We created a notebook, which we also did.
And right, okay, so you can also start JupyterLab without automatically opening it in a browser.
and then what you would do to open it in a browser is go to this address, localhost 888.
Yeah, so the moment you add this option, no browser, then you're going to get as an output,
well, among the output lines, a line with a URL that you can then open in your favorite browser.
If you do not specify the no browser option, it's going to take your default browser,
but if you want to have control over the window in which it opens, then that's a good option to use.
Okay, but yeah, let's go in the demo. So the first thing I'll do to make things easier is
copy this iframe display, and this is the address that I'm currently looking at.
So I will basically open this current website in a Jupyter notebook. Let's get rid of this
hello world cell and also this cell oh um i guess that one test will cut let's make it a
code cell yes and then run okay so now we have a browser in jupyter lab in a browser
great and uh start recreating a cell below that so and this is where we were
Okay, so the first thing we do, well, we have a header in Markdown, so let's make a Markdown
cell.
We have a cell, but turn it into a Markdown cell.
So calculating pi using Monte Carlo methods.
Okay.
Yeah, so now you're basically copy pasting from the content of the cell above.
Yes.
Okay, so and here are some the relevant formulas, I think we can put them in the same cell if you don't mind and an image that explains the concept which we had on the website.
Yeah, I would put them in different cells, but that's just my preference.
Okay, we can do that.
I think maybe at the beginning it's better to use different cells and then if you want
to condensate a bit your...
So I made a mistake.
What was the mistake?
I'm asking more the audience.
It's actually like, this is not a very useful error message, I guess.
Well, it looks like, let's see if anyone answers actually in the notes.
Should we give them a minute so that they get the chance to tell us what the mistake is in the notes?
The error message is really not useful.
I guess this is the key.
Syntax error.
Unexpected token.
Right. Yeah, exactly. So someone did tell us it interpreted this as a code cell. So basically,
it's trying to interpret that using Python and that is... Yeah. I don't know why this is the
first error. Is this Python? Okay, fine. The first part is interpreted as comment,
right? Yeah, this is a comment, but then there's this exclamation mark and it's trying to take
darts of that explanation.
Well, okay. For some reason,
this is the first mistake it found.
That's not proper Python code.
Okay. Well, let's turn it into a Markdown cell and try again.
So here's the image.
So we're actually taking this square and then
throwing random coordinates inside the square.
If it is inside the square,
than it is in the area of this quarter of a circle and otherwise it's only in the square.
So the area of the quarter of a circle is, so the area of the quarter of a circle divided
by the area of the circle is pi over four, is that right? I think so, yeah.
Okay, now we are far enough down that I no longer see the examples. I will start
copying from the side, but I think you still know what's going on.
So I will copy some. Now this is supposed to be Python code? Yes, this is Python
code. So what we're doing is importing modules that we need. We need random
because we want random numbers, and then we also want to be plotting things.
So let's import matplotlib, and I run that.
Yes, and if you're working in the code refinery environment,
then you will have matplotlib installed as a dependency.
Yeah, okay, and then we, well, okay, we decide how many points we will create for this test
or for this example, and then we start throwing darts.
So let's, there's a comment first, we'll throw darts, which means we draw two random numbers,
an X coordinate and a Y coordinate.
So first, initial list of points and the number of hits.
Then we do a for loop that just runs the same thing as many
times as the number of points is.
We draw two random numbers, x and y.
So x and y equals random and random.
And then if it is inside the circle,
so if the sum of the squares, which
the distance from the origin is smaller than one, then it's a hit, and we append a point.
The reason for appending these points is to create this plot. So we are keeping track of
the x-coordinate, y-coordinate of the point, and also the color. So inside the circle it's red,
otherwise it's blue. If you cannot follow this, then it's not very critical. Basically, we are
copying different parts of the Python script that we have and interpreting these different cells.
The main point is not exactly what we are doing with the code, but rather how we are explaining
the code and displaying the code. So the code is divided in these cells and we are,
right now we only have these comments here between them, but we could have much more
formatted text and description between them. Yeah, exactly. I mean, I could, in principle,
add a cell at the top of this one where I exemplify more in a markdown cell what I'm
actually achieving or trying to do with these different cells.
So turn it into a markdown cell and then we could have more explanation.
So something like this comment, but much more detail or more formatting at least.
This is especially useful if I'm going to share this later on
with people that don't actually understand Python.
they still know more or less what this code does and what are the different steps.
Yeah. Okay, so yeah, I also added this that adds a blue point when it doesn't hit,
but it doesn't count it as a hit. Okay, and I run it.
And finally, we have another section that plots the results.
So we take the x, y points and colors and we create a plot and show it.
Well, actually this actually finally creates the plot.
So this will actually return a plot and that plot then will be displayed here.
Okay, so it has the points inside the circle and outside the circle.
And then one final step we haven't done yet, we haven't actually calculated the pi.
So, to do that, according to the equation above, you take the fraction of hits to the
whole number of points and multiply by 4.
Okay.
So, pi is 314 something, I don't know actually so many digits, but this is fairly close.
It's 314 at least, so close enough.
So how can I improve?
You can always rerun and see.
How could I improve on this number, for example?
Oh, you'd make it more accurate?
Yeah.
Increasing the number of points, I guess, is the best thing.
So this ran fairly quickly, so I suppose we can add a zero.
But then, well, now if I just run this, nothing happens.
So at least I need to run everything below.
So what should I do now?
And I could run all of these cells below,
and that will work, right? So now I've made a big plot,
and lots of circles. This is closer, but I don't know if it does.
But, I mean, it's a bit of oscillation
until you get this number converged, so to say.
But really I guess what I would recommend doing, if I add another zero here, is clicking on this
restart kernel and run all cells. So this will run the whole notebook from the beginning to the end.
Yeah and also it's especially useful to also restart the kernel and not just running all
the cells from the top to bottom. In case you have some variables that you have defined but
but then you remove the cells where they were defined.
They may still be kept in the memory
unless you actually restart the kernel.
So restarting means erase all variables from memory
and run the cells in order.
And it's very good practice to do this
before you share your notebook with anyone else.
Yeah, so essentially I consider this now essentially done,
although you could add a lot more story in between here
to actually explain what's going on.
But at least the code is done.
So at this point, it makes sense to rerun the entire code again
from a fresh state.
So what do we get?
What's the point?
We get the plot, so we could send that to someone, or we can send the entire notebook
as a single file to someone.
If they know how to run JupyterLab, then they know what to do with that file, and they can
reproduce everything.
They can even tweak the analysis a bit and then send us back the notebook, or even better,
use version control, and then we can edit it together to get some final result.
Exactly, and that is what we are going to be doing in the following,
see how we can actually version control our notebooks.
Yeah, so the essential point is this is the whole story, this is not just a code,
and this is not just a plot, and also it's not just a description we write in the email,
it contains all of those in one place, so that's a useful thing.
Okay, so here I have the materials open and the next section is notebooks and version control.
Okay, sorry.
Okay, so I'm guessing we will then use version control to put this notebook into version
control and then maybe put it on GitHub or similar.
Exactly, and in order to be able to show different, I mean, sorry, to show the differences among
different plots, then it's very important that we do have some packages, additional
package installed, and that is nbdime, which is a dependency in our code refinery environment,
and that is the reason why we have it, so that we can show these different
changes in the notebooks in a meaningful way. Yeah, so the notebook is stored as a JSON file.
You don't necessarily exactly need to know what that is, but it's a text file. So it is a text
file. You can version it, but let's just take this notebook and open it in a text editor.
So this is what it looks like and mostly it looks fine. It looks like something that would
go to version control, although you probably, maybe you still wouldn't want to look at this
changes in this. You would rather look at changes in this format, but this is the bad part.
This is the image. It's this image and changes here will just be one huge bunch of changes.
That makes it quite unclear. Of course, there's a lot of metadata and all of that.
Looking at changes here might look very unclear and you do want a better interface.
So, should we try the nbdime interface, or do we just look at the comparison?
So, at least I think we should show how we can initialize this directory as a git repository
in JupyterLab.
Yes, so here is JupyterLab again, and here where we have this folder view, we also have
the git section, and I guess we click initialize repository.
Exactly.
So let's see what happens.
Yes, I do.
Okay, there's a checkpoint file. I don't know what that is.
Yeah, so checkpoint is a temporary file that Jupyter Notebook uses,
and I would actually ignore that file.
So there is an option just to click on that and add it to git ignore.
So right click and add to git ignore.
Okay, that's nice.
Yes.
That's convenient.
Okay.
So, I've created a new file, because I didn't have a gitignore file before, and added it
here.
Exactly.
Okay, so that's nice.
We'll close the gitignore file for now.
Okay.
And then what we'll want is to track this change.
Yeah.
To demo.
So, now these are both untracked, so I guess, is it this one?
No.
This one.
Plus.
Button.
And also, I suppose, this one.
yes for an initial commit okay so now we can write our commit message
and the description if we want yeah i'm doing two changes at the same time but
also this is the first commit so it this is the whole repository
okay okay so now there's nothing staged nothing changed nothing untracked it's all there
Okay, so we have our very first commit on the master branch.
Yes.
It may be the main branch for you.
Yeah.
Okay.
Is that all?
I know I should make a change to the notebook.
So what should I change?
I guess like this is a big plot.
There's too many points.
Yeah.
I want to make it smaller before I...
do that. And then rerun the whole thing. You share this with someone else, you don't want
it unnecessarily heavy. Yeah. I could also remove this iframe. Let's do that too. And
I didn't change the code, but still I do want to rerun the whole thing. Yeah. Oops. It's
always a good idea before saving. Yeah, then save and yeah it looks nice. Okay, so now
I have some changes and here is div this file. So what does this look like? Maybe, okay.
So one difference is that the iframe is gone.
Yeah.
So what is this saying?
So it's the difference between your current version
to the right and then the head, which
was your previous commit.
So that is what we are doing.
I wonder if it was wider, would this look better up here?
I don't know.
Yeah, it's always tricky with narrow windows.
Yeah.
OK.
now. And then there's the change in the number of points. Everything else looks roughly the same,
but then there is this plot that has changed.
Yeah. And also the result. Exactly. So the green one is the current version and the red one,
the red labeled one is the one of our previous commit.
Because that is what we are comparing against in this case.
Yeah.
Useful, useful to have this embedime for plots.
Okay.
So now here's the Git interface.
Let's add this.
Reduce the number of points and commit.
Okay.
So yeah, now we're tracking this on Git.
and we have a nice interface for looking at the changes in the files. Okay. There's also
a point here in the notes. Well, first the point about GitHub. So, do I have a GitHub page open?
Not right now. I will open one. So, GitHub has a feature. Oh, no. Not there.
No, it's on your picture, so if you click on your picture.
And then you need to go to Feature Preview and reach Jupyter Notebook diffs.
Yeah, so this is uncommented by default. I mean, no, sorry, it is disabled by default
and then you can activate it if you have reference containing notebooks.
So if you don't have this active, it will look like a diff of the JSON file, which is
not easy to read.
If you have it enabled, then it will use the nbdime to display the difference.
So yeah, it's good to enable this one.
is also here. We have an example in our lesson material. Just higher up. I think it would
be nice to show it. So yeah. Right. Just above the Jupyter notebooks. Notebook diff.
This one. A bit higher up. A bit higher up. Yeah. So I mean you have the link there where
you have this comparison between the two. Okay. No bits, just 35% from the top. Yes. Okay.
So this goes to a GitHub, a comparison of two different notebooks
and they have changed red to orange and changed the size of the plot and then the plot does look
different. Should I demonstrate this with the rich diff off? It might look like this.
If you see a difference between notebooks looking like this and it's hard to read,
Then, this is a big one, loads of image data.
Okay.
Imagine if you had several of these fingers.
Yeah.
So I'm turning it back on.
Okay.
So that's a useful feature.
So you can turn the same thing on in Git on your command line by default or I think this
essentially applies to most places where you use Git as long as it is Git that's actually
opening the difference and displaying the difference.
So you can run this command on the command line and it will use nbdime when you do differences
of notebooks.
I will not demonstrate this, though, because I have nbdime in the code refinery environment,
but it might break git otherwise. So, you need to have nbdime installed for this to work,
and I don't. Okay.
So, yeah, there's also this git-friendly Jupyter notebooks from the nbdev, which is a nice
option, a different way of essentially achieving the same thing, and this JupyterLab extension
that records history. So that's also useful. Okay. Should we, what do you think, should
we have the break before the sharing?
Yeah, I think now it's a good time to have a break, and then we can go into sharing notebooks
and working with Binder just after the break.
So I suggest 10 minutes, and then three past the hour, then we are back with that.
So there was just a question of what is NBDIME, which I guess...
So we showed this difference in Notebooks, but we did say that it's nbdime, but most
of the time it's hidden.
So nbdime is what is actually creating this difference between the Notebooks so that it
looks like this and it looks like this rather than looking like this.
So this is nbdime.
Yeah.
So it's actually a PyPy package,
but in this case, actually, you can also install it
with Conda.
So it's one, a dependency that we have in our environment,
which allows us to show these differences in the plots
in a easy to view way.
Visually nice way of doing the differences.
Okay.
Should we say, well, let's do 10 minutes, so back at four past, or five past?
Why not five past?
11 minutes.
That's fine.
Okay then, let's give them an extra minute.
Yes.
I'll do that.
All right.
So, have a good break.
Bye.
I will come back hope you had a good break so anything to bring up in the notes so go
ahead.
Yes I mean we do need a couple of dependencies to make this lesson material work so as we
mentioned we have JupyterLab and also the nbdynmi package that allows us to do the diffs between
different plots and maybe you do not have that installed and then we recommend that you just
just watch this as a demo later on.
Maybe you want to set that up if you work a lot with Python,
and then you can try again on your own.
So essentially, what you might be missing
is JupyterLab Git, JupyterLab minus Git, and then nbdime.
so you can try installing those later and then redoing the demonstration yourself.
Okay, so the next section is sharing Jupyter notebooks or sharing notebooks.
When have you shared code?
you think of situations where you have had to share some code
so have you shared code to yourself so that you can work on two different computers
that's of course a common issue
have you maybe shared to a larger audience on a website or in some other way
or to a colleague where you possibly both want to make some changes.
So, of course, last week, the whole week, we were talking about Git
and that solves exactly this problem in all of those situations, right?
And nbdime is helpful and you can use Git with Jupyter notebooks.
But one thing that Git doesn't allow you to do is editing the same file at the same time.
You will at least need to be editing on your side offline and then sharing, committing and sharing.
And yeah, there's a bunch of, a number of different ways of sharing these notebooks that might be useful in some of these situations.
So what should we say about this?
So I think there are many different options and different ways to share a notebook and
we have listed the ones we know about in the lesson material.
I would say that my preferred way is putting it on GitHub, but of course you can put it
on other platforms that you prefer. And then I would like to use that in connection to Binder
and share notebooks that way. Yeah. So we'll demonstrate Binder. That's nice.
There's also Notebook Viewer, very similar. And yeah, JupyterLab now does support this
collaborative shared editing, so you can edit the same notebook at the same time.
Yeah, that's also nice. That is useful.
But yeah, for long term, definitely a good repository with Binder is also what I do.
But yeah, there's a bunch of options that you can look through and see what works for you.
Okay. Oh, here's some other options, the commercial options that have free plans.
Okay. But let's go to Binder. So, the first thing, if you want to share your code so that
people can edit it on Binder, I think the first thing you have to do is you have to
share the code. You have to get it online. So, let's do that.
Yeah, so we'll use GitHub to create a repository and track this Jupyter Notebook, yeah.
I guess I will go, oh, there I can create a new repository, okay.
So the idea is that I share my new notebook that I wrote in the last hour.
I will share it to this repository.
Okay.
So what should I call it?
Let's just, this was called, oh, the notebook I just created was called demo.ipythonnotebook.
So.
Yeah.
But you can have binder demo or whatever.
Yeah, bind to demo makes sense, and I'll add a readme file.
I already have a gitignore file in the repository, so I don't want that one.
I'll just use MIT license. I'm not going to keep this for very long, I think, so
adding a license may be a bit extra, but I like to do it.
Okay, so then we upload the files that we already have, the notebook files, if I find here.
Yeah, so we click on that plus button next to code and upload files, because we already have
these saved on our local computers. Otherwise, you can edit it on GitHub as well. Yeah.
Yeah.
OK, then choose files.
And then I have to find source, code refinery, JupyterLab
demo, demo notebook.
It doesn't list the gitignore.
Oh, what is happening?
OK.
It's a hidden file.
Because it starts with a dot, so it's a hidden file.
So here we go.
There's also a dot git and dot.
OK.
Can I upload two files?
I think you can only do one at a time.
I'm not sure.
Yeah.
Let's try.
Okay. Very good.
Upload demo notebook.
Okay.
And now we have the two files, demo notebook and gitignore.
And a pretty empty readme file.
Okay, so what do we need?
Well, what do we need? We need a requirements file, right?
Exactly.
So that Binder knows what packages to install.
So let's create a new file.
And in this case, we'll create a normal text file and not upload.
Okay and at matplotlib the specific version for actually I don't know if this is the version I
have there. I guess in the code refinery environment I assume we have this version
because this is in the nodes but probably the exact version doesn't matter.
Oh, this needs to be called requirements.txt.
Yes, or you can also work with environment.yaml, but then the syntax is a bit different.
Yeah, so if Binder sees a requirements.txt file in the repository, it knows this is Python code,
and then it will install the libraries mentioned in the file.
In an environment of YAML, for example, you can add Python as a dependency or you can add R or whichever you want, as long as it's available on Conda.
And I'll quickly show in the notes, so for Python Jupyter Notebooks, this is what you
need or environment.yaml, but there is also R Markdown, RStudio Notebooks, and there you
have this runtime.txt instead. So otherwise it's similar. There are some different requirements
for the notebook because it would use different plotting libraries, our libraries. Okay.
This is the notebook. This is the github page. Okay, so comment changes.
okay is that all we need i think so it is so now the question is how then how can we
link this to binder or how we can use uh to show this uh this notebook in binder yeah so for that
we need to go to, I'll start opening a new browser, a new tab, and go to mybinder.org.
It's trying to fill in something, another repository, but I'll just go to mybinder.org.
Okay, and then here you can fill in your GitHub repository name or URL.
So, maybe you could show that you can actually work with other platforms.
If you click on the down arrow next to GitHub, yeah, so you can choose from different ones
where you have your notebooks.
There's another ones are nice because you also have a DOI, a digital object identifier,
that may be useful, especially if you want to refer to them in papers.
Yeah, but we'll use GitHub today. Yeah. Yeah, right. Okay. Yes. It's good that you can connect
to a lot of things. Even a general Git repository, you just need to have an HTTP server
at that point to that Git repository. Okay. So, I will use the URL from here.
Let's go to the main page first.
Okay. So then you just copy paste the main page of the repository.
Yeah.
Please make sure that you don't have the branch name.
Yeah. Right. That comes later.
Yeah. Sometimes, especially if you create a new file,
it actually goes to where I just was, which is tree slash main.
And that I think will not work.
Because that is actually defined in the next...
Right.
Yes, you can give a branch name or a tag here or even a commit ID, anything committee, anything
that points to a commit.
By default it will take whatever happens to be the default when you clone it, which is
the main branch.
Yeah, exactly.
Exactly. You can define the default branch, but in our case, it's the main branch on GitHub.
And the head is just the latest commit.
Yeah. And then you can give the path of the notebook file that you want it to open by default.
You can have multiple notebook files, and it will have a file browser.
But in this case, we have a single notebook file, so we want to open it by default.
default. So demo.ipythonnotebook. Okay. And I can launch it from here.
And then also, so exactly. So this URL that you get is very useful actually if you want
to share it with others. And I suggest that we also add it to our readme on the GitHub
repository and that way whomever is going through your code can also see an instance of this.
Let's go back to GitHub and we can edit the readme here.
Yes.
There is also a badge that does the same thing because in the previous session we were talking
about batches a little bit. So this is for Markdown.
So let's add it again. And this is a URL.
And the batch is actually a link that points to the same URL,
but it's an image.
Okay. So now it looks like this. Both of these are links, so it doesn't really matter. They
point to the same thing. This is just, this looks a bit nicer. Well, it depends on what
you prefer. But yeah, so from here you can then directly launch. So I could click the
launch button here, fill in the information, but instead I'm going to click the launch
button from here. There we go. And again, it might take a while. Now, it only has one
dependency to install, but it actually sets up the whole system. Actually, it's pretty
quick. Now, it's installing Matplotlib, so it's pretty far already.
So this will fire up a container on the cloud with the vJupyter
and vJupyterLab and the dependencies
that you have in your requirements file.
It also has a preview of the file here.
Yes, for the impatient ones.
That's very useful that you know.
I just can't run it yet.
Yeah, you know what to expect when it's going to fire up.
OK, so what do we do while we wait?
Am I also too impatient?
Well, we can check the preview.
Yeah, this one.
Yeah.
So it's basically what we had in our local notebook.
Any questions, comments?
So they are all answered, but I mean, of course, the question is when to just have the notebooks
on your own computer and when you actually want to have them on Binder.
And I think that it is always good to have your codes or notebooks saved on some other
platform.
And maybe you are not ready to share them with your colleagues yet, but it's good for
you to reference later on.
And when you are ready to share them with others, then you can do that.
Yeah.
I guess essentially, of course, I've been using these tools for a while, but at this
point I would never really have a code that's at least more than an hour old that's only
on my laptop that feels very insecure, like it might crash at any moment and I might lose
all of that hour of work. So, I will push it to some online repository.
Now, there are options for private repositories.
Many institutions will have their own GitLab instance, for example. So, it's a good option
to check that out. And GitHub does have private repositories, and so does GitLab.
So those are also options.
Or you can run a server and push your changes to that server.
That's always also an option.
Yeah, so now what's opened is a browser window
and the backbone of this is actually the cloud instance that you have on Binder.
It's just that it's using your browser interface to visualize the notebook.
So we can inspect this notebook, and what happens if we make changes to this notebook?
Let's say that one of the collaborators comes, he or she got this URL from you and wants
to make changes to the notebook or just play around, and maybe, I don't know.
So yeah, I mean, it's the big thing in Binder is that you can run the code, first of all.
So I can go through and run the process.
It's somewhere, running somewhere on the cloud, and now I'm just redoing the same thing.
Yeah, so the advantage is that they don't even need to have JupyterLab installed on
their computer.
They can just run it on the cloud.
So that's fun.
went wrong. Something went wrong in the plotting.
Could we miss dependencies?
It's complaining about NumPy infinities somehow. It happens every time though. Oh, so here
There's a deprecated thing.
So I think the dependencies we have installed are conflicting with each other, the matplotlib
and the numpy.
Yeah.
Well, we have not really listed numpy as a dependency, so we would need to go back to
our requirements file and add that.
Yeah.
So we don't really have time to do that, I think.
But this will clearly demonstrate that we did run this on the cloud.
And interestingly, it didn't actually work, but we did get the result in the end.
I can try to add something to the code.
And the advantage, what?
And then run it.
So yeah, it is actually, you can make changes to the code
and it will run the code that you see.
Exactly, and this is not going to change
your original file on GitHub.
So this is all done in this cloud instance
and you may modify it as much as you want.
But if you do want to save changes to this notebook,
how can you do that?
If I do want to save the changes.
I have a great idea and then you want to save it.
It looks like I can do something with GitHub.
I think there is a file.
If you go to file, the top menu and then save as.
Okay.
Or download.
You can also click on download.
Yes.
And that will actually save it.
almost certainly actually downloads the notebook.
Yes.
So that is one way of saving it to your computer.
And then you will still have to open that notebook in an environment which has the dependencies that you need.
Right. So I only get the notebook.
I don't get the environment when I download the notebook.
I mean, really.
Yeah.
This is restore from browser storage.
So actually, I can save it to browser storage, which means it will be saved in this web browser
and then I can get it from there.
So I can save it locally relatively easily.
Then I can reload the page, my changes are gone, but then I can pick up this one and
get the notebook.
The download option is also here.
visible so it downloads the currently visible notebook.
Although if you only store it in the browser storage and then you
clean up your browser data every once in a while then
you are going to lose that.
Yeah so it's not permanent storage. One thing that I would really like actually
is to be able to just save this to a GitHub repository but that's
not here yet. Yeah, so of course you can visit the GitHub repository and you have a link
to that from the top menu and you may clone that repository or fork it to an instance,
is to fork it to a repository in your own GitHub.
So then you can change it and version control it as you need.
OK.
Well, we are running out of time very quickly.
So I think that's all for the Jupyter lesson.
and feedback is already happening in the notes.
So let's go to outro and talk about what's up tomorrow.
Thank you all for all the questions
and sorry we didn't bring all of them up,
but we are very, very glad that you're active.
Yeah, I think this went.
[name]?
Hi, can you hear me?
Now you can hear me.
Yeah, I think this went very well.
Yeah, so hopefully you enjoyed this day.
I guess you saw a lot more ways to use version control
in different things.
So I guess the pattern here is basically
once you're using Git or really any version control,
there's all these other things you can build on top of it.
And tomorrow, this continues.
So it's sort of the capstone days, I guess you could say.
The first lesson is automated testing,
where we see how we can write things in the code,
which will automatically check the code
and see if it works for other,
like see if it works,
like basically find problems automatically,
which is really useful,
especially when we're scientists and stuff
really needs to work.
And the last one is modular code development,
where we'll basically take one of the simple toy problem,
and we'll go through a whole process
of we start with Jupyter, and then
we make it a little bit more modular with functions
and discuss why.
We do a little bit more.
We move to the command line, and so on.
Yeah, and this sort of is a summary of many of these things.
So again, tomorrow is demo-based, so I see one of the feedback things says more hands-on
things would be nice.
Unfortunately, there's so many different variables here, we can't make an exercise
that would work in a short enough time just by answering our things. But we really recommend
you take the afternoon now and go work on some of these different exercises. You can even write your
questions in the notes and we'll keep seeing it by tomorrow at least if not already today when we're
answering it. Or ask your colleagues and so on to be the mentors to do these things.
Is there anything else?
Yeah, okay. Someone's writing in the news there. Yeah, is there anything else? Or should
we call it good?
No, not really. I mean, just mentioning again that if you have another tool which is your
favorite, you can do most of it using that tool. I mean, be it Visual Studio Code or be it
Pluto, I think it is for Julia. I mean, there are many different tools and you don't have to
use our Python examples. You can work with your Fortran code or you can work with a workflow
that you want to develop, so it's very flexible in that sense when it comes to the language that
you're using. Yeah, following up on that, it's like this question number 46 down below,
are there any tutorials for these things? So we're basically inspiring you for what you can look at,
and for most of these tools they have their own tutorials, and probably other tutorials around
you can find and you can, yeah, just look and see what you find that fits your needs and all.
And exactly. So both JupyterLab and Binder have good documentation. So I would, I think
the first thing to do if you don't know something is to Google for it and see what you get and
And then, or ask your colleagues,
but Google is a very good friend most of the times.
Yeah.
Okay.
So should we call the day done?
Is there anything else we need to address here?
I think it's good.
Thank you all for being with us
and thank you for the feedback
and hopefully you're going to join us tomorrow.
Yeah.
OK, sounds good.
See you tomorrow.
Bye.
See you.
Bye-bye.