Yes.
Works for me. Yeah.
Okay. So yeah.
Let's get started. We'll talk about documentation today or in this lesson like [name] mentioned.
Let's start with a really broad question. Why do you need documentation? What's the point?
Can you take us?
Yeah.
Why do you need good documentation?
Probably the most important reason to write good documentation,
at least when you're working on your own project, when you're starting out,
It might seem that you know how everything works in your code when you're writing it,
and you probably do.
But then a month later or even a week later or sometimes even a day later, you come back
to it and it is very much not clear what is doing what.
So that is – we said about version control, one of the main reasons you need version control
is for yourself.
same goes for documentation. One of the main reasons is for yourself. Probably also a good
rule of thumb of when your documentation is good is when you think you could actually read it and
figure out what's going on. That's a big reason. Of course, another big reason is that it helps
other people use your project and therefore it helps other people then make contributions and
makes your project more useful. Shall we go into this lesson but?
Yes, I think the icebreaker is covered essentially.
Like the introduction, so let's go to motivation and wishlist.
Yeah.
Sure.
I mean, we already started talking a bit about motivation, why is it important.
So should we start, so there is now a documentation section at the bottom of the notes.
So should we start a quick question here?
I'll write down the question.
And then a lot of the lesson will
be these kind of discussions in the notes.
So I will write, why documenting code?
Or why should you document your code?
And just, yeah, please write some answers.
So write down why you think documentation is useful.
And also, what do you need for good documentation?
So what do you think would be useful for yourself
if you are working in your own code?
And what would you actually want from someone else's code,
someone else's project in their documentation.
And assuming you are working with a research group
who's using the code,
how do you motivate your colleagues
to contribute to the documentation?
That's also an important question.
So let's wait a few minutes
Before we go into this, some answers we have already given,
but these are now by no means correct answers.
Your answers will be more correct.
So please go ahead and write down in the notes.
Indeed, everyone's.
We'll wait a minute or so to see what answers come up.
Yes.
I got a video.
You
A lot of good answers.
So what do we have to make it possible for other people to use the code?
That is important.
That includes of course your colleagues.
So one option is if you have a normal average-sized research group, what would that be, five people
using your code to some extent. One option is to write down the answers to the most obvious
questions in the beginning. The other option is to tell everybody one by one, probably a couple of
times. That is a big reason to write documentation. But then also, of course, not just your
colleagues, but if you publish it, then other people might also benefit. That is, of course,
was good. To know what it's doing, what is needed, or the outputs, it needs to be sufficiently
clear so that I'm able to tweak it, yeah.
That's true.
Yeah.
Sometimes.
Yeah, so this is, I see a function, it's several lines of code, 20 lines of code. It's nice
if it has good documentation so that I don't actually have to try to read the code to figure
what it's doing. Yeah, so that it's usable. What's the point if it's not?
Yeah, if you're not only writing for yourself. I hear a bit of an echo again. Did something
change the microphone settings? Oh, well. Yeah.
Yeah, so if you're only writing for yourself,
well, even then you should document
because you will forget,
but it is your kind of in a way wasting effort
because someone else could also be using the same code
and that would be more efficient.
Remind myself what the functions did, yeah.
like putting frozen food in the freezer.
It's not labeled, it's hard to figure out what it is, right?
So you come back in a month or a year
and it is pretty much impossible to figure out
what your code is doing unless the functions
and all the parts are properly labeled and explained.
Prevent having to rewrite, yeah.
So yeah, that's true.
If you don't know what the code is doing, then you probably need to just rewrite it
later.
That happens.
Explain the code to myself and others.
people in the research group do not have the same skill levels. Essentially, either you write
documentation for the people in your research group to use your code or you end up teaching
them probably a few times before they are confident in how to use your code.
That is a big reason for documentation. That covers way more than what we had.
then what we had in our short answer. So that last point, shield your limited time, is essentially
that you don't have to keep re-explaining the same thing to your colleagues and other people.
Okay, so what is documentation and what would you actually want it to look like?
This is pretty much the same question really. There's a few different types of documentations
that are useful. There's tutorials. These show a new user how to do a thing with the code and
these are kind of like the exercises we have in these lessons for example. You have a specific
goal and then the tutorial gives you some lines of code to run. It's not necessarily the goal that
the user actually has, it's more there to show how to do things. So these are
learning oriented. Sometimes they look a lot like lecture materials.
Then, you can have how-to guides, goal-oriented, well, I just said that the tutorials kind
of usually have a specific goal, but they are doing a specific thing in order to show
you how the code works.
Goal-oriented here means how-to guides show you how you should do a specific thing that
is probably something you might want to do. A tutorial is how to train a machine learning
model to recognize handwritten digits. You wouldn't probably actually need a code that
does that because that's been written a million times. But a how-to guide would be how to
train a actual big large language model, how to fine-tune it. That's something you might actually
be doing in your real life, in your work.
Explanations, just essentially telling you what the code is
doing and how things work.
That's maybe the most straightforward.
When you say documentation, that might come to mind first.
Then there's a reference.
Something like a list of functions, a list of classes,
is and what each of those does, why they exist.
So there's a lot more here, but these are the basic parts.
If you know what these are and figure out
which ones you actually need in your project and write those,
that is a pretty good place to be at.
But it all depends on the project.
So a small project, just a readme file
that contains some explanation of what the code is
and maybe some very short example
that's basically a tutorial and how to guide in one.
That is probably enough.
Maybe some in code documentation
that kind of functions as a reference as well.
So, yeah, in a small project, you don't need much.
but in a bigger project, in something like NumPy or something big that thousands of people use,
you probably want all of those and you want to think about them separately.
Let's go back to the collaborative document and let's make a wish list.
So, what would you like to see in documentation when you open, when you go looking at a piece
of software, in research software, that you might want to use?
It sounds like a library that would do the thing you want it to do, but you don't know
yet.
What would you like to see?
Oh, maybe I'll copy this to the, to the notes.
So does it make sense to say that now the question is how do we write and maintain it,
like where do we store the documentation?
I guess this is still more about content, like what would you like to see in,
I mean, I guess someone else's work in this case, that's at least how I think about the question.
Okay.
It's talking about research software. It could be about a big library, but I guess what I have in
mind is you have a relatively obscure research problem and you do some searching and you find
a Python library or some library that sounds like it could do the job.
job. What would you want there to be in the documentation so that you would actually use
that code rather than just write it yourself? Because quite often you still end up writing
it yourself. This could be about a bigger project. It could be about something like
what would you want to see in Torch documentation or some other really big library behind us?
Do you have any comments? I think I'm talking a lot, but that's just me.
No, but here we have like very good answers from the learners.
So there are talking about assumptions of the nitty-gritty details.
And then there is someone saying that one should add a detailed way of the code so that
with examples.
So examples are often very useful.
So yeah, dependencies can help when
someone is installing the code for the first time.
Gallery with examples, yeah, sometimes
adding a lot of some images, which shows what it does.
quite useful so that it's not a lot of text. That's true. What else do we have here?
So examples, examples, yeah. Yeah, there's two big things. I mean, there's like the details of
how you use it, inputs and outputs of functions and so on. And then there's this under the hood.
code. What are the assumptions? What is it intended to do? What's the big picture? Those
should be there. Those should be easy to find. That's a good point. Where is the code? How
do you actually get the live? How do you install it? How do you get it to run? That's a very
One part of it, of course.
And yeah, dependencies kind of goes to the same thing.
Yeah.
Easy to find good points.
Good structure.
Yeah.
That's useful.
Okay.
So we have a lot of points in the answer in the lecture materials.
Um,
that are mainly taken from years of answers to this question from the notes, so that's
a good read. But I think we shouldn't go through all of this. Mostly, this is repeating what
we've said or something that we will go into later.
We will talk about licensing later, but one important point is including a license file
and making sure that people know you can actually use the code. It's not there just for show.
Actually, that is one of the answers. That is the last answer in the notes.
So, am I allowed to use it? That's a very good point.
So, okay.
Should we go to the next section?
Yes, you can do that.
License.
Oh yeah, there's a next button.
Next button at the bottom of the page usually.
Okay, so in code documentation, this is probably the easiest thing to maybe in readme file
is equally easy to add because it's just adding a file, but yeah, essentially this is writing
something into the file that the code is in, writing some comments, doc strings.
Sorry. Okay.
Okay, so what is the upside – sorry, I was coughing and then I lost my train of thought.
So the big upside is, when you look at the function,
you see the documentation.
If you're a programmer and you take
a look at what there's a function you want to run,
you can immediately see the documentation.
Then, so it's version controlled with the code itself, so you can commit it into Git.
It will then follow the code around.
And if the doc string or the comment is in the beginning of the function, it will actually
just follow the function around wherever it is in the code, so you can always find it.
But if you're a new user and you see just a bunch of code files,
then that is not the best starting point. That's the disadvantage, which is fixed by readme files.
So a readme file is something that's obvious to look at and often automatically opened
side-by-side with the code. If you look at the code on GitHub, it will display the readme file
directly, for example, and GitLab, I think, as well. Readme files are also version-controlled
in the same way. It's a file, so you have to add it and commit it separately. It doesn't
code directly with the code, but it's text, it works the same way.
So what are the disadvantages? It doesn't, essentially the opposite of in-code documentation
and also it cannot be very complicated or long because it's a single file.
It doesn't have structure in the same sense as a website might.
Okay, so we suggest that you use either RST rich text, restructured text or markdown
to write documentation. These are mostly automatically rendered by different tools.
You can use them relatively easily.
You don't have to generate anything.
And you get some nice structure that you get a good looking documentation out of it.
Some headers and subsections and so on.
And of course you are currently using Markdown to write the notes.
So, you roughly know how it works.
Okay.
So, we don't have to go much into this because we'll come back to it later.
In fact, we'll come back to everything about here.
Everything here we'll come back to in a moment.
So, here's some.
So, HTML static site generators.
generators. That's another option. So, if a README file is not enough, if you want something
bigger, so you want multiple pages or you want more structure into the documentation,
it's a big enough project that you need that. Then static site generators are a good tool.
they can turn this RST or Markdown code into nice looking websites. So we will demonstrate with
Sphinx and it can use Markdown or RST. It's well demonstrating it because we know how
to use it but also it is very general and relatively easy to use. But there are other
options too and so there's package down which is popular in our community. These often are tied to
the language for understandable reasons like it comes with the language or it's written for that
language so that it's easy to use in that language. Sphinx is very general though it's not limited
It runs on Python, but it's not limited to Python in any way.
But yeah, there's lots of good options here that you can check out.
Also, Zola is what we use to build our project website, so it's another option that we like.
At least the popular Git repositories all allow you to directly serve static HTML and
actually build your HTML sites using Sphinx or something else. You don't have to have
a web server to post your documentation pages.
But okay, so there's also wikis,
which are very similar to a static website.
The wikis would exist outside.
So a static website is written in Markdown and restructures text.
It will be in your code base and version control with your code.
So that's nice.
And wikis tend to exist separately.
But also wikis allow a kind of
collaborative editing
that doesn't require
the users to know Git. It requires
them to know wikis, so
that's a trade-off.
But they are also useful.
So yeah, the barrier
to write and edit is very low.
There's
people often use LaTeX
and PDFs.
You can also version control that with your code, it later is code.
A PDF format though is harder to share and it is not something you would probably
want to version control with your code.
Yeah, so the ODE oxygen is a way of generating API documentation which I
will demonstrate with Sphinx how to do API documentation if we have time.
time. I saw quickly, yeah, there was a point in the notes. Can you use the documentation
that's included in your code, the InCode documentation, to automatically generate this sort of API
documentation? That's what Doxygen is for. There is also a tool in Sphinx to do that.
So, yeah, I mean, one upside with using in-code documentation is that you can then automatically
also extract it into a separate website.
It's much harder to go the other way around, right, to go from a website to having documentation
that kind of links to your code.
So this is, it's a nice way of essentially getting both at once.
And the good thing is like, it's always up to date with the code.
So if you change the function or take it away, the documentation is often kept updated.
So it doesn't go old.
Yeah, so whenever you change the function, you hopefully also remember to change the
documentation because it's right there, whereas if the documentation is separate in some other
markdown file, you might forget to do it or you might not do it at the same time, and then
it will not be up-to-date.
That's a good point.
Yeah.
Okay, so we have a bit more detail in the next section about in code documentation.
So we have already talked a good bit about this and about, well, all of the other sections
I think let's do the exercise so that everybody gets to chip in but then I think we'll move
relatively quickly. So I will add a poll on the notes.
And the question is, which one of these comments is more useful documentation or is which one
of these is better?
And you can also say why.
So, info block here.
And we'll vote for either comment A. So, maybe can you share the notes so that I can
So, I will explain what I'm typing in.
So, like in the polls that we've had before,
either vote for comment A or comment B
by adding some character in there.
At least in the edit view,
it will be clear which one has more votes.
has more votes. It's kind of a bar graph.
And then I'll also add the question why, so that you get a chance to explain yourself
if you want to. I think people are pretty clear on this question, but why is the second
one better.
And I guess, what are the good, in what way is the first one good, in what way is the second one good?
Yeah, so essentially in the first one, if you know Python or if you know, I mean, it's
two lines of code is relatively clear. If you know almost any programming language,
you can figure out that these two lines are checking if the temperature is below
minus 50 and printing an error. So the comment is not giving any new information really,
unless you are completely new to coding and you don't know what this smaller than sign
of what this if statement means.
In the second one, it tells you why it's checking that the temperature is, if the temperature
is smaller than 50.
So it is actually providing useful information in that case.
It's telling, so if you are thinking of changing those two lines of code, you know what you're
doing if you read that line of comment.
So it's actually useful in that sense.
OK.
Now in the next part, a couple of ways to not use comments.
These are something that, well, OK, I'll just
say ways to not use comments.
So often you'll see someone comment out
a couple of lines of code.
You don't need that check anymore.
It's for some reason it existed in an old version of the code,
but it really shouldn't be done anymore.
You can just delete those lines of code
and use version control instead.
If you need those lines back or you
need to see what happened there in the previous version,
then you can check out the previous version of the code and actually look at what it was
doing. Whereas in this one, it often happens that then the code around those commented
outlines evolves so much that uncommenting those will just break the code. So, there's
no point in keeping them around in the later version. So, yeah, comments should not be
used instead of version control.
Another one is emulating comment messages. You are telling people why you are making a change,
which could equally well be a comment message. This might actually be slightly more akin to
documentation. You're telling people what the lines of code are doing, but
but this could be written differently to be better documentation and you could use the
comment message to have your name attached to the change and tell people when you did
it and why.
I was a bit hesitant of saying that you shouldn't do this
because sometimes you might end up making a small change
and going back, and then you know you do want to actually
comment the code later, for example.
Yeah, using comments to replace version control
is usually not a good idea.
Okay.
Then there's some examples here of docstrings.
So why should we go into this?
Because we already talked a good bit about this.
Let's just leave this to the level of an example then.
So here are examples
of how you write docstrings in different languages.
So in Python the first one is of course in each of these examples in all of these languages
the first one is a regular comment and it doesn't exactly attach to the function.
It's useful to have when you look at the code but then the second one is a doc string
docstring. That's something that will be a property of the function in a way. You can
extract it from – if you have the function, you can use some command to extract this docstring.
You can use this to build and automatically create API documentation. This is kind of
In each of these languages, this is a point about syntax.
How do you write a doc string versus a comment?
Is that clear?
I think to myself, I don't sound clear.
Maybe I can also add, when it comes to comments, it's mainly meant for the user and the programming
language, the compiler or the interpreter usually skips it. And doc strings are like special comments
which has some sort of standard attached to the programming language. So there is one way to write
it. So it tends to be useful for the user, but there might be a tool which can understand it and
process it in a way when you're writing in code documentation.
Yeah, so something like Doxygen or Sphinx or some other automated thing can pick up
this doc string and build a website that displays all the functions and all of the doc strings
for those functions, whereas the first example is a comment and, well, it doesn't have the
the same structure, it cannot be used in the same way.
So for example, in Julia,
you would write a long multi-line comment
in Markdown format,
and that is understood by the Julia's Markdown library.
Whereas let's say in Python,
there are certain formats of writing the doc strings,
and you'll have headings, which for example,
say, parameters, which refers to the input,
and the returns block, which tells you what the output is.
So there are some standards which dictate this.
And when it comes to Fortran and C++,
it has some things which has, there
are some special keywords, which are specific to Doxygen,
which is widely used for documenting such code,
Fortran and C++ codes.
OK.
I've been babbling on, and we are a bit behind schedule.
We should go get to the Read Me section
and then talk a bit about Markdown
before we get to Sphinx, maybe after the break.
But there is a good question.
Did you write the docstring entirely yourself?
I don't know, of course, who wrote this example,
but when I write code, I have an extension to my editor
that actually fills in a template almost entirely.
So it takes in the parameters and adds in.
So here, for example, in the Python docstring,
there is the temperature that's defined as a float. You could use a tool to extract that
information and write everything except this actual comment line. The temperature in Fahrenheit
is this. Something you would write yourself. There are tools that take care of the syntax.
That is true.
But at the very least, like a single sentence
is also a valid docstring.
So sometimes.
Yeah, yeah, true.
You don't have to list all the parameters, the return values.
OK, so readme files.
Oh, so yeah, OK, so in the readme files section,
we don't really talk much about syntax.
And we have talked about what you need in documentation.
So this is mostly an exercise or a discussion.
So let's quickly think, which one of these do we do?
We probably don't have time for that, multiple.
There is one.
So the first one would be a pure demonstration.
We have had some discussions.
Okay, let's just do the first one
because the other ones would require people
to pick up their own readme files
and then have a discussion probably in the notes,
but with someone.
Okay, so this is some more markdown syntax essentially,
something that you can do in readme files
most environments. Do you have a GitHub account logged in where you can easily create a new
repository or just a readme file that you can show or make edits? I guess it's probably best
just to create a new repository quickly.
So let's say readme demo, and it's me.
And I create one empty readme.
Okay.
And then we edit the readme file.
So there are a couple of effects in the notes.
So let's take a look.
So there is a note, which highlights information, I think not especially strongly, I think it's
a blue box.
Oh, preview probably works for that.
Yeah.
It's a blue box.
Then if you do essentially the same, but write important instead of note, it will be a different
color slightly more visible and warning I think is then red I think important is maybe yellow
oh it's okay um and then yeah then there's import a warning which is yellow
uh sorry warning which is red so this is something like this is meant to draw people's attention of
course. Okay, then let's try these description tags. So this is details and then summary.
So details here, these are like, if you know HTML,
the section goes from the details tag to this end of slash details.
But it contains a summary section.
So details, I guess the idea is that you don't necessarily need to read this part.
This is like extra details.
So it's not showing it by default.
And then when you click on it, you'll see.
So it could be like read more to find out kind of section, yes.
And then there are also batches that you will see in a lot of projects.
So let's just try one.
So the idea here is that a batch is an image you get from some website.
They would usually be at the top, but they show something about the current state of
the project. Actually, when you load the page, it will check a website, and that website
will return this image. It could, for example, depend on whether your tests have passed.
It might show that tests are currently failing.
and can add also hyperlinks to the bench.
Yeah.
Or, yeah.
Right, so the first one, the example,
I think you copied is with a link.
It's with a link, yeah.
Yes, so it has, in parentheses at the end,
it has a link that goes to example.org.
And you can also do the same without a link.
Yes.
Yeah, it looked the same, but then, yeah.
Yes, so those are some tricks
that you can do.
Does anybody know any more good tips and tricks on
or readme files on different systems or different
different repository websites?
Okay, let's do one more at the very bottom of the page.
There's the table of contents.
Oh, oh, sorry. So you're on GitHub. GitHub actually automatically creates a table of
contents for README.md files. You just need to add some sections and then it will have
a table of contents.
Let's try something like installation and then
contribute.
Contributing license, something here.
MIT license, let's say.
Does it show up here?
I don't know.
Maybe we need to commit this.
Yeah, I think you need to commit, and then
to the preview, it doesn't actually
generate the table of contents.
Unsafe changes?
That's strange.
Because in the preview.
OK.
That was probably a previous commit, then, or?
No, this is a new.
OK.
maybe copy everything and go back to the, so that's weird.
Yeah, maybe it's, yeah, okay.
Oh, okay, yeah, you did save.
It did save.
But yeah, this is the library.
Yeah, good.
Okay.
Okay, now we could do the break now
now and then go on to Sphinx.
Yeah.
Could you explain why one wants to use patches?
So yeah, it's mainly, so if you would want to, for example,
show on, have in your read me just a section that says,
all the tests currently pass.
so this version of the program works.
So you could do it as just something that checks a website
that returns whether tests have passed or not.
And that's essentially what we're doing here,
but what it returns is an image instead of a piece of text.
So, when you go to a project, the batches will tell you that this version that's currently in
this master branch, that should work, for example. It can also have other information,
like the digital object identifier. So, it's a link to a Zenodo, for example,
a link to some place that actually stores the object
identifier.
So that DOI is essentially for citing your code,
citing your work.
Another thing is to show the most stable latest
version of the code, which is uploaded in some index
like PyPI, for example, so that you know which
is the current version.
And because often the code on the GitHub
would be a development version.
So we are going to static site generators,
I think, after the break.
But since the section title is writing good README files,
maybe we can go back just mentally for a moment
in your mind, go back to the beginning of this hour.
And we talked about what we would
want to see in good documentation, so
the wish list.
So essentially, if all you have is a README file
and in code documentation, then a good README file
is short, but it includes all of those sections.
It includes a summary of what the code is,
like a top level headline summary
at the very top of the readme file.
This project is for x, and then it
has steps of how to use it, how to reproduce some.
So a tutorial.
This is how you install it.
this is how you run it to reproduce the results in my paper or if it's research software then
probably reproduce my paper is the first thing or a simpler example but something that gets
people running the code and shows them how to use it and then some more detailed description of
of how the whole thing works,
however much detail you want to have there.
And the rest would be in code documentation.
I think that would be a good readme file.
I mean, of course, all of this,
giving the information visually makes it nicer,
makes it quicker.
But as long as the information is there,
that's the most important thing.
Do you have anything to add before we go on break?
No, that sounds good.
Okay, so after the break we'll come back to static site generators and especially Sphinx.
Sphinx, so we will essentially be writing an example documentation website using Sphinx.
So, let's see after the break. Let's do, well, 10 minutes, but it's 57, so let's just do 11.10.
10, is that? That makes sense. So, yeah, see you back at 11.10 or whatever your time zone
is, 10 past the hour. Bye.
Okay, hello, welcome back.
So now we're going to static site generators and specifically a Sphinx example.
Oops, I did not scroll back up.
Okay, Sphinx and Markdown.
you can in the how to document your research software you can find this in the sidebar and
okay so let's go so yeah so the idea of this is mainly a demonstration it will be a relatively
long demonstration and the idea is to understand what these static site generators are what they
do and know how to build a documentation website with these text files that you can then
version control. And along the way, we'll create an example of Swing documentation using Markdown.
So, I'm going to assume that you're just watching essentially the demonstration,
but you can also try it yourself and I mean if it's hard to keep up then I would maybe recommend
watching first. Of course the video is also available later but the
notes and the questions are available now. Okay, so let's get into it.
it. So before we start, I will actually move this notes window out of the way to show a
terminal window. Actually resize it a little bit. There we go. And there's some unnecessary
test here that I was doing previously, so let's get rid of that. Okay,
rid of that as well. Okay, so the first thing we do is conda
activate code refinery. This is the environment you may have installed
following the installation instructions for week two.
Okay, so now we have the code refinery environment active.
we'll check the python version this is essentially checking we have python 3.12 is the latest
version and then let's check that we have sphinx build oops build okay and check the version so we
have sphinx build and the so the the notes the lecture materials have relatively older versions
but I think everything should work. We'll figure it out as we go if something
fails. So there should also be a Sphinx quick start.
And yes, it exists. Okay. Finally, we are going to use mist parser.
So what I'm doing here is I'm running some Python code that I write in the terminal. That's Python
minus c and then I'm going to import mistparser. So this checks that the library is there.
If you import something and it doesn't print anything like it didn't, then the library is
there. Okay, so we have everything we need for the demonstration. Now I'm in an empty folder.
It's my CodeRefinery folder, so I'll create a new folder called doc.example, documentation.example,
and go into it, and then run Sphinx Quickstart.
And it will ask me a bunch of questions.
So the first thing, do I want separate source and build directories within the root path?
I will say no.
So it's asking for a project name.
Let's just call it test. I'm not being, I'm not feeling creative right now.
Author's name. That's my name. Project release. So which version of the project is this?
This is 0.1. This is the first one. And project language. Let's keep English as the default
option. Okay. Now it has created a bunch of files. Let's see. There is a underscore build directory.
Underscore often in Python means that you ignore it. You don't print it and
well, you ignore it in a lot of contexts. So, it's something that Python will often not look at.
Same goes for templates and static. Sorry. Okay.
So, I think the most important ones at first are index. This is the main page of your website.
I keep mixing that up, it's in the restructured text format, RST.
So we'll see a little bit of that, but mainly we'll be working with Markdown.
Then there is this conf.py that includes the configuration for the documentation website
and for the building process.
Build is where the actual website will go when you build it.
MIG contains files, images, static files that you don't build every time and that are essentially
served with the website.
If you have done web development, then this is very familiar, but images go there mostly,
some other files.
Templates, you might want to create your own templates for these HTML files, but we probably
will not go to that here.
file is the instructions to actually build the website, which you can essentially just invoke
or make.bat for Windows. Okay, so the main things though that we will be looking at are
index.rst and conv.py. Okay, so let's take a look at index.rst first.
a second. Okay. So what do we see here? Do you see the whole page? This D, does it cut
away? Okay, good. It's cut away a little bit, but not by much. So, yeah. So this contains
a table of contents or defines a table of contents and then it defines some indices
and tables that are a default there. We will not use the indices and tables section.
So let's remove that one.
Then these top four lines here starting with two dots that's a comment.
Sorry, restructured text has this interesting syntax where dot dot means a command, but
then if it doesn't start with or doesn't have this format of a comment with these double
colons at the end, then it's a comment. So this is a comment. And then this section is
title and this is a special pre-structured text command that generates the table of contents.
Okay, so one more change that we will make is
add a section to the table of contents called somefeature.md. So this is a file name
And we don't currently have this file. We'll need to create it in a moment.
It needs to be on the same level as this caption section. Okay, it seems to be.
Okay, let's save this and go back to the command line. And in order to use markdown, we will need
to use this missed parser that we checked that it exists. So let's go to conf.py and make sure
sure that we're using that. This has essentially the information that we added in the
in the auto generation when it was asking questions. And here we have extensions. So
MistParser is an extension that allows us to use markdown files. So we will add it here.
Okay, so here we use MistParser and I think that's the only change we need to make to
the configuration, so let's go back and then we can create this sumfeature.md and add some
contents to it.
So the title, this will also be the title in the table of contents, so it will actually
get it from the file itself and not just the file name or the title will not just be the
file name. There can be subsections.
So we document some useful and exciting functionality.
Let's make a list.
You do need the empty line here for the list to work.
Item one, you can have nested items in lists.
But then you do need the, I don't think you need an empty line here, but the example has
some.
So just to make sure, I will add it.
So if you are currently typing in the notes or looking at the notes, that is also using
Markdown.
It has exactly the same syntax.
This one is using this Mist parser.
There's many flavors of Markdown.
it has some special syntax for some special things,
but mostly it has the same syntax.
OK, so now I exited the file and saved it.
And now we can build the site.
So first, let's check what files we have.
Just what we had before.
Nothing in the folders, in the build folder.
And then let's do Sphinx build dot and so dot is the current folder and that contains
this index.rst and count.py and we will place the results in the underscore build folder.
Okay. And again, let's look at, actually, nope. Okay. So, I was thinking I could make
a list of all the, like a tree structure of what is in each of the subfolders, but it's
only lists of all the names, so let's look directly at the build folder.
We have some new files in the build folder, mainly index.html and then somefeature.html.
are the pages we wrote and then there's some useful extra features that are included in this
page. So okay, let's then go ahead and open this. It should open in this
web browser when I type in the code. So let's see.
So when I type in the command so xtg open and let's go to build and find index.html.
Okay let's open that and here is the whole website. So it includes the sum feature in the table of
contents and then it actually lists the subsection as well and if you click through here you will get
you will see what we wrote it has the list and the main text so it's all there
you can so it has used a default option for what it looks like for the theme of the website
but there's multiple teams to choose from, some extensions that add additional themes.
You can also build your own if you want to, although of course that's more work.
Okay, so let's go back and continue.
Okay, so actually we have finished the first section of the exercise.
and we have one page in the documentation. So
any comments, questions so far? Let's give some time for that
and decide where we go next.
Is there a specific document generator that's used for PyPy?
I think PyPy just takes the README file, actually you need to tell it where the README file
is, and then it renders it on the main page.
So mostly you can add a link to your documentation, whichever way you generate it.
So why do you want the Sphinx page rather than just a readme file, that's a good question.
Mainly because then you can have multiple pages, if I show this again.
So I could have a second feature here, and each of these has their own page.
I only have one feature or one subpage here, but you can have a whole collection of pages
explaining different parts of the software.
So just a readme file is often enough, but if the readme file is way too long and it's
hard to find the information you want, then you can use something to build a more extensive
documentation with multiple pages that's easier to read and it's easier to find the stuff you're
looking for. It does also have a search feature. So if I search here for feature go, I find the
some feature page. I don't really have a lot of pages here so it's found the same
page twice essentially. Someone also added that things can also do API
reference so that's a good point. It's the in code documentation part which we
talked about previously using doc strings to generate documentation. Yes, so
So there's a section here with some more, essentially,
markdown syntax and misspecific syntax.
We could experiment with that.
Or we could actually do the auto-documentation section next.
That might be because people have talked about it.
Maybe we should do that.
And then we go to a different section.
let's do that next. That seems like people are interested in it. Okay, because unfortunately,
we don't have time to go through everything, but if you want to, you can do this Sphinx,
adding more Sphinx content section to learn more about mist syntax and markdown syntax.
so it's adding you can show this again just for a moment so in addition to lists and different
levels of headings and so on or you can add images links to websites and code blocks
so this is of course very useful when you're documenting code
okay
So, but now I will go through this Sphinx auto-documentation section.
So in order to generate auto-documentation, the first thing we need is some Python code
or some code that has in-code documentation.
So let's create that first, and I'll just create it directly in this folder, which is
usually not quite what you would have. You would usually have a separate documentation folder
and a separate code folder but let's keep it simple for now. So we will call this multiply.py
and it will contain a single function called multiply. It takes in a which is a float
and b which is also float and it returns a float.
Okay so this will add the docstring. First let's do the implementation
which it will multiply these two functions so a return a times b.
Okay and then the docstring. So this will be extensive for this function but this is
an example. So, I want an extensive docstring that documents all the parameters and so on.
Okay, so we multiply two numbers that tells you exactly what the function does.
We have a parameter a
which is the first number to multiply.
we have another parameter B
multiply okay and then it returns so return the product of A and B okay
That's probably enough. So I save it and exit and then I will need to add a new file called
api.md markdown file that will actually this will be the main page of the API reference.
So let's give it a title API reference.
then it will contain, oh, this is, yeah, so the module in the demonstration was called
example, but I called it multiply. This doesn't matter. This is just the title of the section
but I want it to be correct, so make it lowercase because it is the name of the module and the
name of the module is lowercase.
Then we add a command that will create this auto-documentation, so three ticks like that
to start a a command section in this mist flavored markdown
and we'll call it eval I mean the command is evaluate rst restructured text
the reason for this is that
that there is an auto-module extension to Sphinx, an auto-documentation extension, that
will actually generate this API documentation, but it needs to be invoked in restructured
text.
But as far as I know, there's still no way of directly invoking it from Markdown.
So let's write some restructured text here, auto module.
And the name of the module was multiply.
Okay.
So now it's looking for a Python module called multiply.
And then I will tell it to document all the members of this function or of this module.
Okay.
It's called multiply with a Y.
Oh, yes, it is.
Yeah.
So that would have caused an error.
Okay.
And I guess I'll fix that one as well.
It is called multiply with a Y here.
Okay.
Then we will need to add something to the configuration to
conf.py.
So we now have this missed parser extension here.
We will also add Sphinx.
It's spelled correctly, yes, .extextensions.autodoc.
So this is included in Sphinx,
but it is not automatically included in the project.
So you need to add it to the configuration here.
Another thing we'll need to do
is a trick to get it to look into this current directory,
because we added the module in the current directory.
So we will add it to the Python path.
I guess we need to import.
Import OS and system.
And then add it to path, insert.
So this gets the current path.
and then adds it to where item looks for modules.
Finally, we'll go to index.rst,
and we have some feature that markdown here in the table of contents,
we will add this API.md, API documentation.
So that's all. Now I need to run sphinx build current folder and the results go to build folder.
And the changes should be visible here. So I need to reload the page probably.
Oh I need to go to the main page. Okay.
What went wrong?
any ideas? I think we are showing the search feature but you can try to open it again.
Oh, I was looking at the search page. Yes, okay. So this is the main page, sorry. So yeah,
so now it has the API reference section and that section contains this multiply module.
so let's go there this shows the multiply module and the multiply module contains a multiply
function and it has a much more nicely structured view of this of the text that I wrote these
parameters and return value okay and you can from this link you can go directly to the multiply
module although I think we are there already oh no sorry this copies a link that um highlights
this section okay yes okay so now sorry there is also a comment on the notes that someone
pointed out that there is a mismarkdown equivalent of writing the same okay so maybe yeah maybe
there yeah maybe let's test that so in the api.markdown instead of evaluating rst here we can do
so this is a section
call author module and then we have multiply here and members.
Okay, let's see.
One thing should be intended.
Sorry?
Should not be intended.
Yeah.
And then there was.
Yeah, that looks good.
We can try that.
Okay, let's reload the page.
Seems to work.
Okay, good.
Okay, that was actually good to know.
I guess we'll update the website with that.
Now let's go to a related but somewhat different topic.
topic. GitHub pages and how to get your documentation easily visible to everyone so that they don't
have to get your code and use things to build it and then look at the website, but rather
that they can just go to a single website and take a look at the documentation.
Okay, so we've been using GitHub for a few things so far, so we'll use GitHub here, but you can also
of course do this, basically the same thing or very similar things on almost all of these,
at least all of these popular repository websites.
Okay so let's just go into it so that we have about 10 minutes to do this that should be
enough. I'm sorry not quite showing the whole because I want to also show where I'm going to
to the GitHub website. Okay, so there is this documentation example project template which
I'm opening here and this will create essentially a copy of this documentation template repository
but it will be my repository. I will call it doc example. Okay, and make it public and that's all.
So let's see what's included here.
Okay, so here we have a license, a README file, we have some example Python code.
No, actually we don't. We just have a README file on this page as well.
Here could be some source code for your project.
and then we have, in the documentation, we have some feature, another feature, and the configuration
file. So we have everything we need to build the documentation locally, but we want to actually
do it automatically on this github page. Okay, just a second because I haven't actually opened
this on the side. Okay, now I have so then so the next step is okay browse to this repository and
I showed you what the contents are so now to get this to happen automatically we need to do
a couple of things. First is we need a recipe or essentially a program that GitHub follows to build
the Sphinx website and that's called an action on GitHub. So we'll create a new file
and it needs to be in .github
and then we can give it whatever name, so documentation.yml, it needs to be a YAML file.
And then I will mainly just copy the workflow file from the lecture notes to this file.
So there are a couple of things that I will look at and possibly change, but mostly this
is just copy paste so I essentially would never write this on my own I would just copy it from
somewhere so the name obviously you want whatever the workflow name is you might want to change that
this will run every time you push to the repository every time there's a new pull request and
and also it can be, you can decide manually to rerun it.
And then well, there's some like system,
it runs on Ubuntu, it does some,
it checks out your repository,
installs Python, installs dependencies.
And here we see missed parser.
And we actually have a theme that we're using,
read-to-docs theme, which is nice.
It's a nice looking theme.
and of course swings and then we run build command and then there's an information on
how to actually deploy it how to get github to actually display it on the github pages
okay so we'll save this file commit changes
okay
So now I wonder if the workflow is actually running.
So I hit this actions here.
Yes.
So we made a new commit so it should run.
It is running.
Okay.
And you can get some more details from here.
So it is following a set of steps here.
It's actually done now.
Okay, let's do it in this order.
So what it has done is it has created a new branch called githubpages or ghpages and that
just contains the website.
So everything needed for the website is there and it will automatically update whenever
you push to the repository.
more important thing we need to actually turn github pages on so i went from here to settings
and then to pages deploy from a branch and then we select github pages here and save
okay and now it should work i think it has
somewhere here it usually tells you what the
URL to your website is. It is always the same so I know it off the top of my head but
of course you might not remember.
Oh well, I usually also add it here so there is this about section and it is actually
it is your username dot github dot io not com but io and then the repository name
doc example okay so it is always the same structure oh okay
use your github pages website is it's an option here so you can it it can automatically fill in
the URL. Okay. So slightly changed interface, but it is still at least as convenient as before.
Okay. So now I have the link here and I don't have to remember what exactly it is.
Okay. And it displays. So this is not exactly what we wrote locally because I copied it from
the template. If we had done exercise two instead of exercise four, then it would look like this.
So it has the documentation,
it has a nice sidebar here because we're using
the read-to-docs theme instead of the default theme,
and then it has the actual contents of the page here.
So this is what we wrote in the example.
So now it is online for everyone to see,
and this works as long as your repository is public.
If you have a private repository,
then I guess you probably wouldn't want it to be displayed here anyway, the documentation.
But then I don't think it's a free feature. But in any case, as long as it's public, this works.
And yeah, you can do the same thing on GitLab. The steps are different,
the interface is different, but the principle is the same.
I think we have a list here of alternatives. GitLab CI and GitLab Pages. Read-to-Docs is a
commonly used hosting alternative. This is separate from these repository websites so it will
need to have access to your repository. It needs to be able to clone it
and then it will build the documentation for you.
So, yeah, and you can, of course, build them manually or create your own workflow to build
them and host them anywhere.
Sorry.
Okay, so here's some steps for migrating to Sphinx if you already have some documentation
to migrate.
I think we should go to the wrap-up section,
to the summary.
Yeah, let's take a look at the notes quickly.
There's some questions that were answered, I think.
There are a couple of them.
Does Sphinx work with GitLab?
Of course it does.
So you can do the same approach using GitLab API.
GitHub CI is essentially the same as GitHub Actions and GitLab Pages is the same as GitHub
Pages essentially.
So you can do essentially the same thing.
And then there is this question, how do you connect or link the Sphinx documentation
you report to your repo on GitHub?
So I think there is a Sphinx setting somewhere in the conf.py, I can't collect it from the
top of my head, but it specifies where the repositories or where do you actually intend
to publish.
So then when you render it, it links to the source.
But this is very specific to the theme.
Am I right, [name]?
Yeah, so there is a setting, if you look at the config file, config.py, I think there's
a setting for the URL somewhere in here.
Oh, I guess not.
I guess you have to add it.
Okay.
Well, then I don't know off the top of my head how to do it exactly.
I wonder if that is what the question was about, though.
I guess the same, it's this edit button which comes up.
Yeah.
So one thing I did just show here is, so in one direction,
it's straightforward.
So it's straightforward to add the link from the GitHub
to these GitHub pages.
Going the other way is less straightforward.
But you can, of course, manually add this is the recommendation.
So you can manually add on the main page a link to your code.
Oh, there is a view page source.
Seems to know where it is.
I wonder, actually, where it got the information.
Yeah, Sphinx actually saves a copy of the.
That's why it comes in the generated version, so it's actually there, but there is actually a way.
You can always add it as text here, the repository is at an URL, so that's always a solution, although not automated.
Okay. Let's go to wrap up. Oh, hosting websites. So, I mean, yeah, I just, I did show you this
very quickly. There is, there's a branch called GitHub pages where it actually pushes the
new version or the most recent version of the documentation. So you can also use GitHub pages
to just directly write HTML and host it there. So if you're using GitHub anyway this is a
straightforward way of hosting a website. Same goes for GitLab and all the other alternatives.
but probably not spend more time on that unfortunately because we don't have that much
and we want to go for lunch in time so yeah just the general wrap-up for documentation
and yeah I guess the most important takeaway is you well you should have documentation
for yourself and for others in your team and for other users outside your team
him. But there is no one right way to do it. Like for a small enough project, a readme
file is enough. You probably want some in code documentation. For a bigger project,
the in code documentation should be really, especially if it's meant to be used by users.
If you're talking about a function that's meant to be used by actual users, then it
should be really well documented. And you should also have some sort of static website
at least for the documentation.
But then there's everything in between, right?
And it's really up to you to decide where you
go from one option to another.
If that readme feels too long, then it probably is too long.
But yeah, I mean, there's no one right way to do it.
So, any final thoughts?
Yeah, and then there's always progressively different ways to improve it, like adding
more user-friendly sections and yeah.
Yeah, of course, whatever decision you take, you're not stuck with it.
can always at least add more. So you can add a static website and copy stuff from the README
to the website and have a nicer structure with a table of contents.
Well, the README does have a table of contents, so you can create one.
But the main thing is that the readme shows all of it at once and you have to scroll or hyperlink
to different sections of it. On a static website you can split it into multiple pages
and it should be easier to read in that sense. Yeah another consideration is like
ask yourself who you are targeting this and is it someone who is new to the
code or is someone who is already into the code and needs to know the
nitty-gritty details so you should have something for both and it can even be a
future maintainer who should know how to publish the code and keep it updated.
To me, that's kind of the minimum. If you want the code to be usable or maintainable
in the future, then you should have at least enough documentation for the future maintainer,
which is likely, it might be you. But still, you will not remember. So, that's kind of
minimum. But then if it's really a big library and you want it to be user-friendly then you
should have a lot more than that. Is anyone rethinking how they're doing documentation
right now? Is anyone not doing documentation but is thinking of how to do it?
You could add your thoughts in the final summary section in the notes, you're very welcome
to do that.
Okay, well, there is a good amount of recap, of course, on the page that I'm showing.
So there's, we talked about readmes and static websites.
We talked about in code documentation
and how API documentation, how those two work together.
And of course, there's several options.
We didn't really talk about how to write tutorials,
but that's also a very good addition.
If you have slightly bigger program,
or just examples of how to run the code.
So yeah that is the general summary of the documentation section. So next we'll talk
about Jupyter but before that let's have a lunch break. So we will see you in one hour
on the hour and yeah, have a good break, find something to eat and see you. Bye. Bye.