Hello, we are back and hopefully you can hear us out there.
Should we do an audio test?
One.
Yes.
Two.
Three.
Four.
Five.
Six.
Okay, let us know if the audio sounds okay.
So we are resuming now for the last lesson of the day with what is called modular code
development.
So this is sort of an example that puts together a lot of the topics of the workshop.
We'll see us using GIT and who knows, maybe some testing, but in particular, how we evolve
some code from being this small, what do you say, how we would actually evolve some code
from being this small, how do I say this?
have prepared a small script doing some typical scientific data analysis for us.
Yeah, let's see. We'll start from there, and let's see how it will evolve.
Yeah, exactly. Okay, so it's like the real or a realistic example of it.
In the meantime, we have some links here in the notes or some questions here in the notes
that you can start filling out while we begin our discussion. So please think
about that. In the meantime, [name], do you have the lesson opened or should I
open it? I can share my screen. Okay.
Can you see it?
That's the questions we put in the notes.
Yeah.
There we go.
Yes.
So when we start off, I guess we can discuss these questions ourselves.
So [name], what does modular code development mean for you?
Well, as a person with some medical education background,
to me modular is something that actually exists in the nature.
We humans are modular ourselves, I would say.
Because if you look at our body,
there are multiple systems like circulatory system,
the nervous system, and the respiratory system.
Each system actually performs its unique function,
and together they form our body.
At the same time, if you look at the microscopic level,
one single cell is also composed of various tiny,
tiny components, and those components
are all performing their own functions,
and together they will form a functional cell.
So it's not just about code,
it's in the nature.
Yeah, I never thought of that.
So I guess there's two types.
One is there's, from what you said,
there's different systems doing
different things and they're separate,
so they can be understood and, well,
I won't say developed about humans, but can be understood and function separately.
And then there's the hierarchy.
Yes, exactly.
And, you know, that matches up with what I think about code also.
And whenever the systems start interfering with each other is that when stuff goes bad.
the really difficult diseases start happening.
Yes, I think that's true for both human and the code.
Yeah. Okay. What does
modular code development mean for you then?
Well, I would say that's also a hierarchical concept.
In the lower level, I would split a functional block of code into functions or I will create classes for them.
If you look at a little bit upper level, then I will organize functions or classes that are related with each other to a single module.
module. The module could be reused in different projects. That's how I understand. How about
you?
Yeah, I mean, I guess it depends on the kind of project. But basically, I start off with
something and then usually it starts off a bit chaotic. But once I get parts that I think
are self-contained, I'll start splitting them off,
whether it's functions or other files or classes
or something like that.
But yeah, basically, like picking off
little bits that are standalone and other things
can use as an interface.
Yeah, I guess that has partially answered
a very natural second question, which
is why do we want modular code instead of a block of code
line after line to do our tasks?
So is there any other reasons we want
to develop modular code?
So let's see.
Well, the first thing comes to my mind is
If I want to share my code with the other person or put it to my paper,
I would like it's well-organized.
Then the other people can use part of it or use the,
if I make a whole Python package,
then they can import it or they can install it.
I would like a code in the package module.
Okay. We have seen some answers,
so please fill out the questions with your comments.
Maybe we can come back to this later and have a look at the material first.
Good idea. So what's next? Let's check out this. Okay, the learning outcomes.
So should we discuss this now or come back? Maybe we do some hands-on stuff and then come back to
this when we have a deeper understanding. Yeah, sounds good. Yeah, I guess the main
thing we might bring up is this first point about pure functions. So basically
we'll see which of our functions have side effects and don't. So basically if a
function is only evaluated by its arguments then that makes it easy to
write, and test, and understand. And we'll maybe get there. But okay.
Let me go back to the notes. Yeah, another thing I would like to emphasize is that
in this session, the main idea will be we will do the typing together. It's kind
of like a live tapping demo.
I will be using the keyboard, and [name] will be helping me,
giving me guides.
And also, you will participate via the notes,
giving us comments, suggestions, or questions in the notes.
So we will do this coding together,
but I'm the one using the keyboard.
OK.
Yes.
Sounds good.
So what is our task?
Let's have a look.
OK.
So this is our task.
We will use some data downloaded from FMIs open database.
It's some records of temperatures in year 2022.
It's the temperature measurements
from the observation station in Wanda Airport.
Yeah, FMI has the observation station there.
That's the data we are going to use.
And as I mentioned before, we have prepared some scripts
for our task. So we will use this as a starting point and try to make it more modular.
Yeah. So what does it do?
Should we move to a Jupyter notebook first?
Yeah, sure. I guess we can look at it as we copy it there.
Yeah. Or maybe while you're getting it set up I can talk about it some. So it's
a simple analysis that reads in data from the CSV file. It computes the
average temperature over the specified range and then makes some plots. So it's
a fairly typical, well, little analysis. So it starts off like it has the read, analyze,
write out results sections. So even though it's simple, it provides some good stuff that we can
use as a good example of the whole analysis workflow.
So, while we're doing this, we'll basically be doing it live.
So you can, and please do, write in the notes and make suggestions on what we should be
doing next.
So we won't really do stuff until someone suggests it.
And we'll just see where it goes.
So do you want to see if it runs first?
I guess that's the first step, right?
Yes, let's try it out.
I have already imported this package,
so I can run directly this one.
Oh, we got some fail not found.
Oh, I haven't downloaded the data.
It should be in this repo.
Yeah, we can see, we can have a glance here.
We can see that the record is there's
one record for each hour from 0, 1, 2.
We will download from here.
So you copied the link.
Yeah, I will use a Jupyter magic command.
That's clever.
So basically from the terminal you're using the wget program which downloads the file and saves it,
I guess. Yes, I think yes. Okay. It's running. And the exclamation mark there is the shell magic,
so it runs something. And yeah, we see it saved temperatures.csv.
All right, let's run this again. Okay, it works, so I will delete this.
You know, this is a question that's come up some past days, like how do you include data
along with an analysis? So there could be something that says if the data doesn't exist,
it runs this command to download and saves it. So just an idea.
Yeah, especially when you're working with a Jupyter Notebook, it's very convenient.
Yeah, okay.
And it works.
Yeah, should we go through this line by line?
Yes, please.
What do the parts mean?
Okay, so the first line is kind of a hard code.
It's number of measurements we want to analyze and visualize.
And then by using appenders, we read some data from a CSV file and then extract the one column.
We have done some computation, which is the mean of these temperatures and then some plot.
So very simple, but typical process.
But also, sorry.
In the notes, I put a question to the audience,
how is this not modular?
But there's no answers yet.
So maybe I can ask you, how is this not modular?
Well, we can see there's a file reading, data extracting,
and the calculation and the visualization,
all stuff together.
If next time I want to use just the plot,
what should I do?
I copy and paste?
That doesn't sound like a good idea.
So I would like some single functional unit.
of code that I can reuse. I don't need to copy-paste, just call that function.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, I guess that's right. So one of the first tasks suggested in the
workshop is to create plots for 25, 50, and 500 measurements. So if you want it
be very unmodular, you'd copy and paste the code block three times and then rerun it,
and that makes a lot of code duplication.
So you can just copy the cells. Yeah. So if we want to be slightly better than that,
how would we make three different plots? I will use a for loop that I don't need to
to repeat all this stuff, so three times, should we try that?
Yes, let's do it.
Okay, I will say, well, number of measurements in the list.
in the list. So 25, 100, and 500. Okay, let me run it. Okay, it works. It's better than
than three cells.
Yeah, OK.
But since it's not modular, we forgot
to change the file name it was saving to.
So this is always a risk.
So should we fix that first?
Maybe we can either define unique names for them
or we can use some other variable to generate the file name automatically.
Maybe we can use the number of measurements. That's exactly what is being used here, 25.
Yeah, makes sense.
Yeah, okay. Let's do that.
Okay, yes. So, use string formatting in the variable, make defining out file. And this
is also good because in the future when we need to, if we make it more modular, we have
variable already defined, so it's good. Yes. Okay, so what should we do next?
I'm waiting for chat messages. Let's see. Let's see if anyone suggests something.
Is there anything we should extract out and pull from here?
Well, I don't like the visualization and the calculations together.
So would you like to pull one of them out? Yeah, at least I would like to pull
the plot part out. Yeah, makes sense. And it really makes sense that once we have
all the plots working well, so we define all the axis labels and format and stuff
like that, we'd want to be able to use the same plot format in multiple cases.
Someone says we need an underscore and out file.
Oh, yes. Thank you so much.
So I will move this out.
Yes. Okay.
See, I will define a function for this.
It will be plot and temperatures.
So do we need some input? Yeah, so what should the inputs be? Well, outfail should be here, I guess.
I guess.
Should the temperatures be an input?
Yes.
And the mean, I guess.
Oh, right.
Yeah.
Should we give alt file some default value?
Yeah, why not?
So default to none.
Then we can use the number of measurements
as the output file name, or a different idea.
Yeah, what should or could it just
be something like plot.png, so not take any stand
and it basically always, like, it minimally works,
but always needs to be something.
Or maybe we should just call it good enough
and accept you need an output.
Otherwise, it doesn't make sense.
So we will use the out file.
What if the default was none, and then the save fig only
ran if there's a given out file.
Yes, yes.
If out file, then we save.
So now the function is usable both for interactive kind
of work, and then if you want to save stuff later.
Although there are still some problems with that,
But we can get there later.
Yes.
OK.
And now we need to put this back into num measurements.
Yes, we will.
Or we just this.
Okay.
Yeah.
And mean.
Oh, but it should specify the outfile.
Yeah.
If we want, then.
Oh, yeah.
But we could also not give it right now.
Yeah.
Yeah, we could comment this out.
Okay.
Should we try without saving firstly?
Yeah, let's try.
Then we don't need to specify this.
Okay.
It won't be saved.
Should I run it again?
Yeah, let's go.
Okay.
It's still working.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, what's next? Should we extract more functions out? So, something, one of the
files says one of these suggestions is to remove the compute statistics and
reading data functions out to set yeah move these two separate functions yeah
that sounds quite reasonable to me yeah okay so this part will go to another
function which will be let me name it get get data maybe so should we make the
input file we can we can flexibly use different input file yeah so the
function shouldn't, should be able to work on different inputs. Yep, okay. Yeah, see, then this
will be an input fail. Yeah. Number of measurements, maybe a second argument. Okay, yeah, I guess
that has to be specified from outside. Yes. So what if we didn't have it as an argument?
So I think the code would still work because of how Python goes, but is that
good? You mean, well, if we don't specify this number of rows, I think
it will read all the rows. Yeah. But if we leave it like this, then
And we probably will get an error.
Yeah.
So yeah.
OK.
That's good.
So we've got that.
So I'll put it back.
It runs successfully.
Is that the file name?
I think so, yes. Okay, is it still working? Okay, yeah, okay, good. Now we have two functions.
Is there too much data being plotted? Did it read the whole thing if you scroll down?
Sounds weird. What I would do usually is to restart the kernel because there might be some
variable names polluted. Good point, yeah.
Okay, there are some typos, I think.
Okay. Oh, yeah.
Yeah, okay, so we need to store the output of the getData function.
Yeah, we need to return.
Nasty. Okay, now it looks okay. Yeah, okay, this looks like it looked okay.
And then should we extract out the statistics function?
Yeah, I would love to do that in case I want to do something different.
So that means we will have a third function. I'll call it getName.
Someone points out that infile isn't specified.
Why do you specify it?
Oh no, it is specified, yeah, in git data.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think it is specified here.
I mean, it worked, so it had to be there.
When the question came up, though, I got confused.
So I wondered, how is this working?
Yeah, so the input will be temperatures.
But do we want to use this number of measurements,
or we can get it from the input temperatures.
Yeah, it should probably come from the input temperatures.
So we could pass it as an argument,
but then we have to basically pass redundant information
because the column knows how many rows are there, right?
Yeah, and there might be some risk
that we input a wrong number.
So this might be better, I think.
Yeah.
OK.
Let me rerun this.
OK, still working.
Yeah, OK, good.
So let's talk about which of these are pure functions
or not.
So is there any parameters other than the arguments?
And does it have any side effects?
So plotTemperatures, it's based only on the input arguments,
but it does have side effects, but only saving files.
So is this function easy to test?
I think, yes, at least for getMean,
we can easily test it by using test.
Oh, git mean, oh, it's talking about plot temperatures.
So let's start with git mean.
That's the easier one.
So for git mean, this is the easiest thing
to test because there's no side effects.
The only input is the, the only thing that affects
the output is the input.
Should we make a test now for it or later?
would like to, well, I usually test, I usually do unit tests in the Python script other than
Jupyter Notebook. Yeah, you're right. Like, if we did the test, then how would we know if it even
worked? Yeah. Okay, so let's not test it yet. But git main is easy to test. Is the function
get data easy to test?
Get data, I think there are several things we can test.
For example, we can test the size of data.
Is it matching with the number of measurements?
Something like that.
Can you say that again?
was reading the stats. I mean because the input is number of measurements and we pass that to the
read CSV method, we want to verify that the extracted data has the exact the same number of
records we want. That could be something we can test. That's a good idea. So start with like
Yeah, so include some sample data, like this one, and then we can, well, there's not that
much that can go wrong, but test that, okay, yeah.
Yeah, usually for computation functions, I would do some tests, like getMin.
Yeah, okay.
a question. Maybe it's better to put the get mean function call inside the plot
temperatures function. So should we compute the mean outside or inside the
plotting function? Well, usually I would make them stand alone instead of...
yeah it depends yeah like like what do you want the plot temperatures to only
plot means or maybe it could plot other statistics too like it's yeah right now
basically a general function that plots the temperatures and a line and the line
can be different things yeah let's imagine that we define a force function
that we'll get not an arithmetic mean, but a geometric mean, then we can plot a different thing.
Yeah. There's also a good suggestion, why not use statistics.mean instead of creating a custom
function? And yeah, I guess that would make sense, but this is a demo and this is an example of
something that would be more complex. So yeah, yeah, we want to go to a very,
very complex Python stuff. We want to make it more general. Yeah, someone suggests testing
if the column for air temperatures is numeric, and that sometimes they've done things and it
writes it as a different type of data. Yeah, yeah, yeah, true, true. Let's get to that later.
Okay, so we have the loop, we have means. So how modular is it now? So what benefit have we achieved so far?
I think so far we have split the whole block of code into three single purpose functions. All of them could be reused.
Yeah, you can
Well, if it's a Python script then you can import them to a different Python script or a different notebook
Yeah, that's I would say we have improved the code
Yeah
Okay, what should we do now
Should we
make it a Python script or is there anything else?
Yeah, I would like to make a Python script.
When I come to this point of coding,
I have done some interactive work.
I have seen some visualization of data.
A Python script will make it more convenient to
to do more exploration.
Yeah.
OK.
How do you make a Jupyter Notebook to a Python script
usually?
Hmm.
I haven't done it that many times.
I think you can use nbconvert or export it.
Or maybe in the end, I would just
copy what I need over since usually whenever I do something,
There's like, it's too messy for me to want to do everything.
This seems a bit cleaner.
So what do you recommend?
Yeah, this one is not very long.
So maybe we can use the simple way,
because Jupyter Notebook has this save and export
Notebook as executable script function.
So yeah, we can do this, I think.
Okay, I will save it.
Okay, temp visual.py, yep, okay.
Okay, let's see. I think it's here. Yes.
Yeah, okay. So, it looks like Python code.
So, yeah, how do we start fixing it up?
Well, I will remove this redundant stuff from Jupyter Notebook.
Then maybe we can simply run it to see if things go wrong.
Good idea. Yeah, so yeah. Yeah, I suppose it could work. Yeah, I mean, probably. So maybe
this is the first time, well, we've seen examples of command-line usage before,
but can you explain what it means to be running it on the command line now? Well,
it means you will use Python. You will use Python and specify the name of the py file, which is a
script. Then the Python interpreter will run the program. Yeah, okay, so we give it the program
name. And right now there's no argument, so it just runs it from top to bottom.
Yeah, everything is entered in the script itself. Let's see.
Okay, the importing will take time. Okay.
Okay, we are supposed to have...
It's showing. Okay, so now here the command line program is opening a graphical window.
Is this what we want? It depends. If we are working on HPC,
we don't want it to show because there's no display. But if it's locally, I don't quite
demanded to see it show.
Should we make it where, this is what we said before, right?
So if it, maybe we could say if you give it a file name,
it saves the file name.
If you don't give it a file name,
then it shows it with plot.show.
Yes.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, I think if we don't want it to be shown,
then we probably want to save it.
Yeah.
So that would be around line 10 we adjust.
Yes.
So we can comment out this line.
Then it won't be shown.
But instead, we would like to input output file name.
Then it will be saved.
Should we say under the if out file then else
And then do plot dot show if there's nothing.
Oh, yeah, that's a good idea.
Yeah, I see.
OK.
So is it good that it does two different things
depending on the argument?
I guess.
It's good, I think.
Yeah, it's a reasonable compromise for now.
It's a pattern people might want.
Like, if the plotting function was actually
relatively difficult, then maybe this
would be a good way to use it two different ways.
Yeah.
OK, so if you run it now, does it show anything graphically?
Yeah, because we didn't input any output first.
So it goes to the else.
Right.
OK, so we need to give it the output file again.
OK.
Then we need to modify the script.
Yeah.
Is that something you want to do?
Yeah, should we give it a way to specify,
should we hard code the output file,
or should we make it a full script with arguments now?
Well, I'd like the argument idea.
OK.
don't want to touch the script that much. Yeah, okay, good idea. And someone here
suggests disconnecting the loop, so maybe we can do this at the same time. So before
the script would run it for all these measurements, now the number of
measurements should be an argument. Yes. Okay, so do we make a main function here?
is it? Yes. Okay. Let's make a main function that can take a number of
measurements as an input. Okay, yeah. Okay. And what other inputs should we give it?
Info, I would say. Yeah. The output file? Output file. Are those the three main
things I guess yeah yeah okay so whenever you make a command line program
what do you use for parsing the arguments there are several different
And tools, they are pretty much similar, like arg parse or click.
Well, the example solution says using click, so maybe we should do that.
Okay.
I can't remember all the commands, but...
Well, I'm reading here, so I can tell you.
So, okay, above death equals main, then at sign click dot command with parentheses.
I remember it's a click option.
Dot option, yeah.
And then dash dash the measurements.
Does the order matter? Should we specify infile firstly?
Oh, maybe we do infile first. I often do that also, so sort of go the input arguments first,
then the analysis ones, then the output ones, but it parses it in any order.
Yes, so it's required, I guess.
Ah, there's a good point here.
Is an infile an argument and not an option?
So it should be an argument.
So maybe we can say what's the difference here.
So option is usually something with the two dashes on it, and is optional.
But positional arguments don't need the dashed things, and you are just taking the first
one on the command line as the first one, and second one as the second one.
But our example we're following has everything as options, so maybe we should follow the
example rather than make things ourselves.
Okay.
But we should specify it's required, right?
Yes.
There's no default, but definitely some help.
Yeah, okay.
it's the input file name. Yes. So a second one is number of measurements. I think the
convention is dash instead of underscore.
This is also required and it must be a int.
Yes, okay.
And also when you specify the type like this,
it will automatically convert it to that type.
Yes.
And give a warning if it's not.
So help, that would be the number of methods to use.
Then, another one will be the output.
This is not required.
Okay, yeah. In the example it says it's required, but I guess we can leave it as
not required and it will show it on the screen, which is possibly nice.
Yes. So not required, right? Yeah, not required.
Okay, output file name, okay.
Yeah, but in the main function, we didn't reflect anything about the output file.
Okay, yeah, so we should add that to plotTemperatures, I guess. Is it the last
argument? Yes, I think so. Yes, it's the last argument.
So, it should be like this, I guess.
Yes.
Okay.
Do you think it will work?
We need to specify the namespace.
Yeah, it has to actually run main.
So what you're about to see is the typical pattern you see at the bottom of Python files.
So this means if it's imported, then it just imports it, and all the functions can be used.
But if it's run as a script from a command line, then name is equal to this main value
here, and then it should run the function.
So this is just basically the pattern you use all the time.
So let's see.
Does it work?
I think I forgot to import.
Yes, we have to import click.
Yes.
I'll guess you have it installed from the Code Refinery.
Oh, yeah. I haven't activated the environment.
I guess everyone has created this content environment for the workshop.
I also created it myself.
Activate. Yeah, but it worked before.
Yeah. Let's see.
Okay.
Yeah, it should be better now.
Yeah. What if we run without arguments?
Can we see help text or something?
Yeah. Missing option, yeah.
Okay, so it basically will guide us through everything that's needed.
Yeah, but let's check out this.
Yeah.
Oh, we need Python on it. Yes. Yeah. Okay.
Yeah, we can see this help message reflects what we specified by using click.
Yeah, okay. So let's see, can we then run it with all the options?
Let's see, we give it an input file which is
temperatures.csv, if I remember that correctly. Yeah, I think so.
So number of measurements, that will be, let's say, 25.
Let's try without output file.
It's supposed to show.
Yes.
And if we change the number of measurements, does it do more?
Let's see.
Great.
That looks correct.
Yes.
OK.
Good.
And if we give an out file, does it save it to somewhere?
Let's have a look.
Out.
Let me see.
Just an example.
.png.
It won't show, I think.
Yeah, okay. Let's see if it's saved. Okay, it's saved here. Maybe I can open it. Okay.
Yeah, and it's there. Okay. Yeah, that looks good. Should we summarize and then go to the
break and then we can do a little bit more when we come back? Yeah, I think it's a good
point to break. Okay so what did we just accomplish and what's the benefit of what we've done? Also
people can comment in the notes about what you think. So there's a lot more code but
also to do different analyses we don't have to edit the code at all. The code is basically
Basically just that.
And if we save these command line lines we run, then we can reproduce our analysis in
different ways.
If we want to run this automatically, for example with what we learned for SnakeMake
on Tuesday, we could easily plug this
into a SnakeMake workflow that does things.
We can script it to run many, many times on the cluster.
We can send it to someone else, and we can tell them,
use these options.
And they don't have to understand the code.
They only have to understand the help text here.
So by making this more modular, do we call this modular?
Yeah, I would definitely call this modular.
It could be reused.
It could be reproduced.
It can be easily scaled up.
So it's modular.
Yeah.
And the outsider using it has this clear defined interface
for it.
So I guess let's take a break.
Please keep suggesting what to do next.
I can think of a few things, like adding the test to it.
And we can see what we do then.
So there will be maybe 15 or 20 more minutes of working
on this.
And then we'll have a quick wrap-up of the whole workshop.
Okay. When should we come back?
I guess four past hour.
Okay.
So 10 minutes break.
Okay. Thank you.
Okay.
See you soon.
Thank you. See you soon. Bye.
Hello. We're back. So, the last half an hour. In the notes, we had votes for, the most votes
were for adding tests. So, we're thinking of doing that next. And that really does seem
to be about the right time to do it. But before you do that, would you like to make it a
Git repository, so we have some record before we start changing a lot of stuff and risk breaking.
Yes, yes, when it comes to this point, when you have a script like this,
we would like to do some check. You have learned in last week, so I guess we all have Git installed,
so and yeah okay so it's not yet a git repo so I will initialize it
so git init I usually will specify the branch name so okay now it's initialized
and so we can check out with the most commonly used command git status so we
can see all the files are unchecked okay yeah but we don't want to check all of
them. I will check the code, of course. So, git add temp pool.
Yes, it's frozen. Okay, that one has been added. Do we want to add the notebook?
Maybe.
Yeah.
Well, yeah.
Why not?
I mean, I guess maybe it's being replaced now, but for a development project, we may
as well keep track of it and we can do something different with it later if it was ever needed.
Yes.
Okay.
So I won't track the plot.
Yeah, because you probably will have plenty of them.
Maybe at some point, I'll track the most important ones.
That depends.
But the idea is to show how we use Git
for the version control.
So I will commit to the...
Yeah.
OK.
So this is, well, usually I will,
it's the initial commit.
Or you can use some other meaningful commit message.
Okay, now we have checked the files we want to check.
So that's a version control you have learned in last week.
Yeah.
Okay.
So what else we can try?
Should we add a gitignore for the things we don't want?
yes yes that's a good idea yeah if you list if you list the hidden files you
will see there's a .git but typically we will add a gitignore file it's also a
hidden file, gitignore. And we add in all the stuff we don't want, like should we
add asterisk.png? Yes. And what else things like the pycache and the ipynbcache?
Yes, pycache, is that correct? And dot ipy. What's the ipynb cache? I forgot it, but let's
check it. It's the ipy and b checkpoints. Checkpoints, yes. Okay, yeah. So ipy, checkpoints.
Okay, with this git ignore, if we run git status again.
Yeah, gitignore itself. But I guess we'll add gitignore. Yes. Yes. Okay. How about the data?
Yeah, should this data be included? Since it's open data, not something sensitive,
and it's a small data we use as an example, so I would say it's fine to add it.
It would be good data for our tests, basically.
Yeah, yeah.
OK, sounds good.
So let's add it.
Yeah.
OK.
Now everything should be there.
Yes, but we needed to make another commit.
Yeah.
Let's see. Add the test data. Okay. Now it should be clean.
Yes. Yes. Okay, great. Okay, but now tests. So, which of these three functions would you
like to test, or which do we test things that aren't in a function?
I would test a function, like, well, if the first function I want to test is getMin.
I don't want the calculation wrong.
Yeah, yeah.
That seems like the most likely to go wrong without us noticing it, so.
Okay, should we add the test to this file or another file?
If there's only one test and the file is not very long,
I will add it here.
Otherwise, I will use a separate file for multiple tests.
Yeah.
So should we use a separate one?
Yeah, I mean, whenever I start with one really small thing
like this, I'll also often start just
inside of the like yeah just inside because yeah yeah it's small enough yeah yeah okay okay then i
will, uh, we need to import pytest. Yes, okay. Yes, so test min,
so min will be something calculated by using this function. Yeah, okay, so we basically run
the function. Yeah, maybe just a list of floats? Yeah, that's a good idea. So we basically give
it some of our very own data, and we know what the mean should be, so we can see what it is.
And this is sort of the best possible case, so we write in some values.
maybe another one yeah and then we could do yeah there and then for pi test we
would write assert mean equals 3 I guess 3.0 yes okay and then to run it how do
do we do this? We use pytest. So pytest. And since this file isn't named test, we
need to give it the file name. So temp visual. Yes. Yeah. Let's see. Importing syntax error.
Ah, yeah. Is it saved?
Dev, lantern, table.
What's wrong with this? Maybe it needs to be saved.
Okay. Oh, yeah.
That's something Jupyter Notebook doesn't do for you.
Okay. Sometimes. Yeah. So now it says
there was
one test collected, so we know it actually found it. If it said zero tests collected,
we'd be a bit worried. And it worked. And this time it happened to work, and there wasn't any
floating point error, which caused it to make problems. So that is good. If there was this
floating point error, it would say error 3.0 is not equal to 3.0000 something.
pytest has this proxy method to avoid this kind of accuracy problem. Maybe we can use that.
Ah, good idea.
Like this.
Yeah, good to demo anyway.
Let's see. I'm sure this will work.
because it's less strict than before. Okay, yes, okay.
Yeah, do we want to test some other things? Like should we test if it works with negative numbers?
Would we test if it worked with no inputs at all?
Would we test that it works with one input? Or maybe this is a good stopping point.
What do you think?
Yeah, there is something else we can test.
Oh.
But we're also almost out of time, so.
Oh, yes.
We can talk about how we would test other things.
So how would we test the getData function?
GetDataFunction, as I mentioned,
we can test if the size is correct.
As it's mentioned in the notes that we can
test the data type of temperatures.
We want it to be float.
Right. Yeah.
But sometimes from CSP file,
it might be stored as a string.
Yeah.
That's also something we can test.
And since we have some test data included,
it's easy to run or do test data or test test data
because we just give it this thing we have already.
Yes.
What about plot temperatures?
Is this easy to test?
I mean, I guess we can test if it runs and makes a file.
Yes, if the file exists.
Is it worth testing to see if the file is correct, or is that trying too hard?
That's not something I usually do, but it's definitely doable.
And yeah, it's valid, depends.
Like same for me, so I would usually not test the plot temperatures unless I know I really need it
to. I think there are things for testing matplotlib plotting, like you would define
what you expect it to have and can test it without saving the file. But I would usually
try to do all the stuff that needs testing outside of the plot function to make it easy
and plot just does the bare minimum.
Yes. Okay, should we move to the outro and wrap-up of the workshop, so people can keep asking questions here and we'll keep answering after the outro part?
Do you want to have a look at the learning outcomes?
Yes, yes, this one.
Let's go back there.
I think we have achieved most of them.
Yeah, so we talked some about pure functions,
not as much as some instances of the course.
But basically, when it doesn't have these side effects,
then it's easier to test.
The second one we didn't talk about too much.
A single-purpose function we talked about a bit.
So split apply combine is a different kind
of thing, which we haven't talked about.
It's another way of basically dividing and conquer.
The command line interface we did extensively talk about
And to me, that's when the code really starts getting reusable
and I start becoming proud of sharing it.
It becomes actually like a thing.
So, yeah.
And I think we saw how this connects to the other lessons.
So we did the tests, didn't really do documentation.
We talked about version control.
We talked about how the scripts, making the command line
interfaces lets us make it more reproducible later on.
So yeah.
Yeah, we have there's something we haven't covered,
but we can continue the discussion in the notes.
Yeah, and also I see some suggestions
regarding the code script.
Yeah, we use it as a demo.
It's not perfect, but the idea is the modular coding.
Yeah.
OK.
So I'm going to switch to my screen if I can.