Yes, it worked.
So we're going to the concluding remarks.
and where to go from here, also known as the workshop outro.
So thanks to everyone who was attending. This was a fun course to give. We had
a lot of new people and new instructors and we're getting closer to the sustainability
point of view. Thanks to everyone who attended. I don't know how many people were working in
teams here, so basically had people in an organized group together attending. But anyone
who was able to do that, thank you for coming. That's really good, exactly what we want.
We would like to thank all of the instructors who are listed on the workshop webpage.
I won't say their names again here, so I don't have to remove them from the videos. But yeah,
I mean, instructors have put in a lot of work to go and make this happen.
We also had a bunch of people answering questions in the notes, as you may have seen and found.
These people took a lot of time to do that, and the local partners who organized
any possible in-person things and so on.
We'd like you to keep giving us feedback, so in the notes, you can keep adding things.
It is in there now.
We see it's here, please keep adding stuff.
You can send us by email or you can join our chat if you wanted and say some things.
So you can always use Git itself by making issues or pull requests to help update our
lesson materials.
In fact, you could say that our whole course is a way, our whole course is a way, is teaching
you how to update our materials, because everything we use, we teach in the course.
And we keep developing based on your feedback, so let us know.
In about six months, you may get a post-workshop survey, which will basically ask how your
work has been changed and updated based on what you learned in this course.
is really important to fill out because it really provides the best indicator to
the people that fund us that we've done something useful and they will keep
funding it. So I'd really encourage you to keep studying and asking for support.
So this is a starting course but these are very applied and not theoretical
topics so most of what you'll learn will be on your own after this. So I would
say, starting off, you have the course and it gives you some ideas, lets you do some things.
But the next step is to work on things along with someone else. So someone who can be there
and help you answer your questions locally. We have these partners below we can talk about,
but even if it's just another colleague, do talk about the things you've learned here and
ask for help because it's new. And then, even after that's done, there's still plenty more
you'll be learning yourself. Never start doing web searches or whatever to find
new things that you can use based on what you've seen here.
We have these things called bring your own code sessions. And it's basically a way you can bring
your code or well I guess other questions and come talk to us instructors and we'll look at
things together with you and it's basically like a follow-up Q&A mentoring kind of session.
So this is a way we can help with the follow-up ourselves.
You can continue to review everything that we have here. The lessons stay available
indefinitely and get updates. As you know we have videos published. The main point of these videos
is for you, our learners now, to go and re-review things during yourself, afterwards. And you can
reuse these materials as much as you'd want. So there's a bunch of different partners that are
are part of the Code Refinery project.
I think, yeah, did we have, yeah,
I think we had people from all of these here.
Maybe not Denmark this time.
But anyway, the point is that locally in your country,
you have people that hopefully want
to answer questions about these things
and then help you follow up.
If you're at Aalto University, we have plenty of things.
basically come to our daily sessions anytime and we can follow up and help you do these
things.
And I think probably is the same for more of the stuff.
We just have listed the Nordic countries here because we're a Nordic project, but there's
more in other countries that you need to find yourself.
If you want a certificate, that's on the course webpage.
I don't really know much more other than what is there.
So please read it yourself if you're interested.
Tell people about us.
So let people know that it's a good workshop and they should come in the future.
Or even recommend to your institution or yourself, join us as either a team leader or become
part of a team, an instructor in the future, a supporter.
There's all kinds of people doing stuff in the background, which we need help with to
keep stuff working.
So, yeah.
We already talked about these things.
The newsletter is a good way to hear of what's going on, other interesting tidbits, and so
on.
And if you really like the kind of things that we're talking about now, you can look
into this thing called research software engineers,
which is basically people that are researchers,
but they're focused more on the technology.
So they're more interested
in making the research technology better
rather than getting as many citations
as they can for themselves.
So it's a different kind of career path
that has a different kind of focus.
So it's still sort of a new thing in some places
but it's something that would be worth reading about.
Okay.
Any other comments or things from the notes?
I will switch there.
Let's see.
Please give feedback.
This is not much feedback and we need more
in order to see how it went.
Yeah, okay, there's a question here.
Are there any good AI tools which can automatically generate a test code?
I think there are probably some, but I don't know them myself.
I think someone will probably come in and fill in the answer later.
Yeah. Is there anything else?
Are there any other instructors around who want to
join the studio and say any final words?
Yeah, I'm very happy I'm here today.
It's a very good time to learn from each other.
I saw quite good answers and comments,
suggestions in the notes.
I will read them through later.
Yeah. I think today went quite well overall.
So we had some good sessions.
And, yeah, the most sincere thanks to everyone who stuck with us all this time.
And yeah, I really hope that this will improve your work and that you can reteach these to
other people later on.
Okay. So, I guess I will turn it off for now.
Is there any final news? So, I think most of the news was in this outro session.
And there's no future session. So, yeah, that's that.
Okay. Thank you, everyone. Bye.
Bye.
Thank you.