CodeRefinery.org
you
Test one, two.
Does anyone hear us out there?
I can hear us, at least.
Can anyone hear me?
Can you hear us through Twitch or through?
Through Twitch.
Okay, good.
Yeah, I'm still slightly adjusting things here.
Okay, I got a report saying our audio is somewhat balanced.
Okay, yeah. So, hi everyone. Welcome to this course.
So, we have a few minutes to talk about practical details
and initial thoughts before the main program starts at an hour.
But yeah, my name is [name] and with me here is...
[name], hi, from Aalto as well. Yeah, yeah, so we're both from Aalto University.
And yeah, so what about this course? So is anyone as excited as we are?
Yeah, there's lots of new material. So if you have joined us in the previous years,
there's lots of updated materials. And if you haven't, well then, welcome.
I hope this is going to be a good course for you.
Yeah, so what we have here is what you're seeing on the stream, I hope, is what we call
the notes document.
So in this course, notes is only for registered participants.
So if you haven't registered, you won't have this link.
If you are registered, please open it up.
So as you've noticed, this is live stream.
So that means we'll have hundreds of people attending.
We can't answer questions by chat.
It just doesn't really work.
So instead, we have this.
And it's like a shared document.
So you write in questions, and we
have a bunch of people that can be answering them
all at the same time.
But you'll learn more about that later.
For now, what I'll do.
I think in the intro, we're probably
going to give the user a spiel of how the CodeRefinery way of teaching works, right?
Yes, so we don't have to worry about that now.
Should we look at the icebreakers?
Yeah, let's see. If I scroll down some, we see down here there's...
Okay, I have so many windows on the screen that I have to balance. It becomes a bit tricky.
Okay, so here we see people testing stuff, so if you write something it will appear here.
We see some questions, but let's skip through these to icebreakers like [name] said.
So you can come here and I will come up to my other screen, I'm in edit mode, and I will
change Finland-Helsinki from plus one to plus two, and you can do the same.
But while we're doing this, so what's this course about, if you had to explain to a non-technical
person?
Well, I'd say it's like this kind of like, you know, there's languages and there's languages
in programming.
And some of these languages are more commonly used than others.
And I think Python is the kind of like thing that like, if people try to, it's like a boomerang
that even if people try to like dodge it, it still comes back and hits them in the head.
So people end up using Python at some point in their career and in their life.
I think this is the kind of like, okay, like you're now at this point, how do you move
forward?
And I think we try to make it as simple as possible.
It won't hit you as badly as you.
So, okay. Are you saying this is sort of like a general intro course? So, you know, people
that need to use Python, maybe they've used it as a normal programming language, how to
manage it for science, since you're probably going to have to sometime, whether you want
it or not.
Yeah. I think your answer is a bit more like elegant, but yeah, yeah. So the point is something
like that.
Yeah, so the point here is that we don't teach Python itself, but if you know some Python
like you take in normal programming courses in Python, you'll see the most common tips
and tricks and stuff like that, which you need to know for scientific work, but aren't
taught in normal Python courses.
So basically, we're teaching the science behind.
OK, we're not teaching science.
What I said.
Let's go on.
We're teaching a very special set of skills
that you can use to make your life a lot more easier.
Yeah.
And I guess you could say that we're not even
teaching the skills.
But with a few hours for a few days, the most we can do
is give you an intro to the different skills.
So we give an intro, but it's up to you
to follow up the ones that are important to you.
I have to say that there's a huge number of people
from different places.
Like the list is growing and growing,
and it's still not stopping.
Let's check the stats.
Amazing.
Yeah.
Yeah, so, wow.
Yeah, we've got quite a good set here.
Everywhere.
OK, how much do people use Python?
Let's see this.
So we have different beginners.
OK, this is the fun part where people
are editing the document so much that it becomes all crazy.
it's hopping around. But it's okay. It'll stabilize. So, we have people who've used it a
little bit, but not enough. So, yeah. Like, most of these answers look like they're about at the
right level. So, you know, used it some. Yeah. It looks like what you said, that, like, not
necessarily, we're not necessarily teaching Python, but we're teaching, like,
the how do you use Python in a specific context. And I think, yeah, like, for the people who are
answering in the chat, like, it looks like this might be really helpful.
Yeah. How much have you used Jupyter before? We see never. Very briefly. Okay. So, we do start
off discussing Jupyter, not because it's what you have to use, but because it's a basic user
interface for most people to get through the course and we don't have to worry about how you're coding
stuff. But you can of course use whatever environment you want to use, like a programming
environment or IDE. Jupyter is just one that is very commonly seen when it comes to this kind of
like. And we'll talk about that later. Yeah. Okay. We see here under where do you store your files,
people write plus one whenever you agree with something. That's a good practice to use.
It's, yeah. And here you see. In some other cases we might do this kind of like
O-polls or we put like this kind of like you add the same character to the list of characters that
makes it a bit more easier to count out the like this kind of histogram poll. But we'll talk about
that as well a bit later. Yeah. And finally down here we see a preview. So ask more questions.
people have written questions in these bullet points, and other people have given an answer,
not us. So that's our whole army of other instructors and helpers that are watching
and answering questions. So you'll get answers pretty quick like this when you write stuff.
But with that being said, I think it's time to start the intro. So I will...
So any final words before we do that?
No, let's go.
Let's wrap in and let's get rolling.
So if this works, I will switch to my screen here.
Yes, OK, so now you see my screen.
and you see... Okay, let me just size some... Yeah, so this is the course page and the way you find
where you are is you would scroll down to the schedule and we start at intro here. So I will
open intro in a new tab and it says we have 15 minutes for this. So welcome everyone to Python
for scientific computing. So what is this course? So as we said in the icebreaker session,
this is a course that's not about Python, but about how to use Python for science. So we give
some of the general tips and tricks and practical things that people might learn. So we don't teach
Python itself, and we don't go and we don't teach everything in great detail like you might learn
an academic course, but it's an overview, an introduction. You hopefully get some hands-on
stuff you can do, and then the things that you need for your own work, you should be prepared
to go learn about them yourself afterwards. So that's the basic idea. Who are we? So,
as we said in icebreakers, I am [name], and with me here is [name]
but we have a bunch more instructors going on. Just look at the schedule and you see we had
almost 15 different people listed as taking part in instructing, which is really amazing for
the course of this size. We have so many people watching the stream saying 163 now and so many
people teaching. And many of the people who will teach on different times, they will be answering
in the notes when they are not teaching. So if you ask questions in the notes, most likely
Maybe one of the instructors will answer you quite quickly regarding whatever you ask them.
Yes, definitely.
And we have many different partners.
So many of the instructors are coming from different institutions, universities in Sweden
and Norway.
And I think beyond that, but I'm not sure.
Oh, I had updated this, but I guess I forgot to push the update.
Well, I would say that the overall thing stands. We have a bit of a different, like,
bit of a different, like, focus on different days. So this first day is mainly going to be
about the basic building blocks of scientific Python, I would say. Like we're talking about
NumPy, Pandas, Visualization, and also some advanced tools like X-Array, which are really nice.
And then on the second day, we'll continue on with that.
Yeah. And it's completely okay to mix and match when you're here. So since this is a stream,
we won't be offended if you say this lesson is too easy and drop out and come back for a later one.
But for most people, for some people the beginning might be a bit too basic and for some people the
end might be a bit too advanced or specialized. So don't worry about mixing and matching as you
would like. And also the course page it has a lot of materials that we are not
going to go through through this course and this is because we have in the
previous years we might have gone through it and if all of our courses
will be recorded and they are released in our YouTube channel so if you
want to see the previous year's course lectures you can see it from
there and of course you can view the materials in the course page. Also in the course page there's
lots more material than that we will probably go through in the course because like it's not very
fun to go through just like speak about text in the wall like wall of text so instead we usually
have this kind of like a co-teaching approach where we go through it in the like a natural
discussion kind of a way, so that we have a bit more structure on it and it's easier to listen to,
so it's not like a reading monologue of just reading through text.
Yeah.
So, but if you feel like you learn better from a written material,
I recommend reading the materials as well.
Yeah. Yeah. So, like [name] was saying, how to attend. So, it's live streamed. You can jump
on and off as you want and there's different pathways so some people want to pay close
attention and do all the exercise as we do them ask lots of questions be totally active
some people may watch and listen to what we say but you don't do the exercises right now instead
you do exercises like you'll come back and do stuff later reread whatever that's completely fine
Some people may watch a little bit but mostly go and read it later or watch the videos later at a
faster speed. All these are fine and it's designed so that you can do all of these things at the same
time. Okay and now the course page is updated and we see the right three days here. So choose what
want. Practicalities. How does it actually work? This is more like a TV production than a course.
So we have a studio, we're broadcasting, you can join and leave when you want.
We have pauses, so like the commercial breaks. And during these times, we'll give you time to do
exercises yourself. So, then you, yeah, like we'll say, okay, exercise time, you go work and we come
back. And now it's a good time to do like the scream quality check. We'll get there in a minute.
Okay. Yeah. Okay. Something down below. Okay. And the types of things you might see are talking and
demos where you're just listening, sometime when we're talking, but then you are typing along with
us at the same time. There's exercises where we don't talk, we give you time, and you work on
things alone. And this is where we try to focus. And then there's breaks. Okay, chat and communication.
So we've already seen the notes document here. It is this thing here. As you scroll down,
you see questions and answers. So if we go to the edit mode, then
And you can go to the end and say, this is a question.
And if we wait a minute, someone will reply and say, this is an answer.
So this is the main way of communicating.
Okay, no one's answering yet, but under normal conditions, someone would answer very quickly.
Yeah.
Okay.
But this is the basic idea.
Q and A. You need to switch to edit mode at the top.
If you're not asking stuff, if you can switch to view mode, we think that keeps the performance
up a little bit. Okay. Yeah. The view and edit modes here. So, we also have people watching
this, and when that happens, if we need to, we will raise the question by voice and answer
it for everyone. So, there is definitely feedback to us here. Please don't include names or
any identities inside of the notes. It's public, it will be archived. We'll try to remove names as
soon as we see them. And it might be streamed and recorded into videos also, so just don't do that.
Okay, screen arrangement. So as you notice, we're streaming in this vertical mode. The idea is that
it can take up half your screen, and the other half you have a workspace, you have a web browser,
are all of these different things here.
Like [name] was saying, we need to change the settings of Twitch
to the highest resolution, the source resolution.
And this will force it to stay at the full complete
resolution.
Yeah, so you can do that by clicking the gear icon,
then quality, and then put it into the source.
And like [name] has written here,
You want to hide the chat, because we are not really looking at that chat, we are looking
at the notes chat.
So what you usually want to do is put the browser that has the Twitch stream into theater
mode.
And then you might want to, depending on your display, you might want to like increase or
zoom or zoom in or zoom out so that the stream goes like from side to side.
Yeah. Okay, so where do you focus? There's going to be so much information being thrown around here
and the biggest problem is that people get overloaded. So where should you look? First,
focus on the screen share and the lecture, if it's going on. That's probably the most important.
Then, if you have spare mental cycles, you can focus on your own type along as we are
demonstrating things. If we don't have that, or you still have more time, you can
look at the notes and see the other questions and answers being put there.
Our recommendation only look at the bottom, so questions should always be
added as low as possible because that's where we are looking in order to to
answer. If you ask things, you can also come back later and read it during a
break, so don't let this get you caught up. It's an option but not required.
During exercise times focus on the exercises and then as you have time you
can be scrolling around the lesson web page yourself. So the more boring what
we're doing is the more time you can spend on the other things at the bottom
to keep everyone excited. Okay what can go wrong? So we have so many people there
will be a lot going on. The lessons are too simple. In that case, later lessons will become
more interesting, read notes, ask advanced questions, read through the advanced material,
all that kind of stuff. If the lessons are too advanced, then take a step back, watch
passively, don't worry about doing the exercises and type-alongs, and you'll learn a different
way and you'll be prepared to come back later if you want. If instructors make a mistake,
by design. We try to make it so that not everything works all the time. So you can see us try to solve
the problems. If the note document stops responding, we have so many people, maybe it's lagging,
wait a bit, and we'll try to reduce the size some, archive it, and hopefully it will pass.
If the stream dies, that basically means my computer or internet connection has stopped.
In that case, wait a minute, it'll reboot. Usually it takes around five minutes to get everything set
up again and we will resume. Worst case you'll get an email saying that something big has happened.
One year the internet actually died so a major content distribution network stopped working
and Twitch couldn't load. So if something like this happens well just wait we have videos we'll
figure it out. If a cat interrupts one of the instructors this is actually the opposite of a
problem. So my cat usually starts coming by later in the day, so stick around to the end if you want
to see a cat interact. I always put it on stream if it's there. Okay, we have videos. So videos
are being recorded. There's no way that your voice or whatever can be in it because that's why we're
streaming. Videos are available on Twitch for seven days and then on YouTube after we process them.
So, unlike other years, I haven't promised to process all the YouTube videos the same
day to have them up by midnight.
But I think other people would like to work on it, and they will try to get them there
by the, well, within a few days.
So we'll see how that goes.
If you want to volunteer, well, get in touch.
Okay, being respectful and helpful.
there's many people here on many different levels. So this is okay. Please
try to help everyone, no matter who they are. Everyone is both a teacher and a
learner, so the attendees can help each other in the notes, and also some of the
instructors are here because we want to learn new topics. Please be kind to
everyone. We'll try to take time to check in with people and ask, how are you doing?
are we going too fast or too slow? But if you're with other people in smaller groups
and so on, do the same. Ask people, are you doing okay? Are you getting what you need
out of this? And so on. And when anything is not going right, speak up soon. So, in
this case, write in the notes. If you can't hear us, if the screen share is not working
right, write something saying, hey, we can't hear, we can't see, or we just completely
lost this, the volume's too low, and we'll solve it. Okay, final notes. There have been a few times
we have come back from the break, started to talk, have talked for a few minutes, and then realized
that nobody can hear what we have just said, and then just repeat everything afterwards. Yeah,
okay. So, certificates. You can see information about this on the course web page. I think
there's not much more to say here. There's many ways you can keep in touch, including joining this
chat. And we have a stream here where we, us, our instructors, are talking. And we'd be happy if
learners or whoever would like to come give us feedback there and even start helping out some.
If you like this, there are other workshops going on. So, in particular, our main code
refinery workshop has a lot of complementary skills to this for scientists. So with that said,
we're not too late. [name], is there anything that important that I missed? No, I think it's
important to just have fun, try to learn, and not don't worry about it too much. If you
know something already, like throughout this course I've learned a lot of new approaches to
various things. I'm certain that I will learn new things through this course, because I haven't
looked through all of the materials that have been updated. So, have fun. And whatever point
of your coding life you are in, I think you will get something out of this course. So, just have
fun and don't worry about it too much. We are here to help. Yeah. Okay. That's a good way to put it.
just have fun. Just enjoy the experience. Okay, with that being said, if we come back to the main
course page, if I can find my cursor, we see next up is Jupyter. And this is
[name] teaching and me supporting. So thanks, [name]. I think we'll see each other after lunch.
Yes.
So, okay.
Have fun.
Sounds good.
Bye.
[name], are you here?
Yes.
Hello.
Welcome.
Would you like to introduce yourself to everyone?
Yes.
I'm [name].
I'm working at Uppsala University in Sweden.
Very happy to teach this lesson together with [name].
I'm [name].
I'm working at Uppsala University in Sweden.
Very happy to teach this lesson together with [name].
[name] and [name] have already told many things
that stand for this lesson as well.
So for Jupyter, we are really just going
to scratch the surface of it.
We are not going to go through a lot of detail
and we are doing that just so that you all get
And on the same base, it's perfectly fine to use the command line if you prefer that
or your favorite ID.
That's of course also an option.
So it's really up to you.
But for those of you that like to learn more about Jupyter, so what is Jupyter?
So you can...
Wait, I need to switch to your screen first.
Yes.
Thank you.
And now it should be visible.
Okay.
Great.
Yes.
know if the font is not big enough for you. We should adjust it in any way.
It looks like it's probably big enough. Okay, yes, so please begin. So maybe first
from the voice of the learner. So my understanding is that the point of this lesson is to provide
one user interface so people can do other course stuff. Basically, you know, a person
completely new to Python can get started enough to do the other exercises.
Yeah, exactly. The nice thing about Jupyter is that it's very interactive and you can
and you can execute pieces of code in the interface
and it's going to be clearer in a little bit
when we fire it up.
And you can integrate figures, code, equations,
if you want to stylize the text
so you can have documentation along your code
in an easily accessible matter,
and you can do all that in the Jupyter Notebook.
Yes.
So,
I have already said this.
I'm going to start it up,
and if you still have problems with installations,
then my colleagues
We'll be able to help you, hopefully.
So the way I started is I first activate my MiniForge, the base environment for MiniForge,
and I do that just as it's described there.
You are demonstrating on a Mac computer.
I'm demonstrating on the Mac.
it's going to work the same on the Linux and if you want to see how you can do that on Windows
then you just switch to this tab for Windows. Yeah. And I am going to use MiniForge in this
case. If you have Anaconda you can do that or you can use the Anaconda Navigator, it's up to you.
but I am going to use MiniForge. So I'm going to go back to my terminal and I will activate MiniForge
and I have a different location for MiniForge and that's why I have an extra
directory there but then it's just the same MiniForge being activated.
And I have to do this as I have not done any Fonda in it. I prefer not to have the base
environment activated by default. Okay, so now I have the base and I do not want to work in the
base environment and the reason for that is that for the rest of the course we will be needing
other packages which are not in this base and in order to do that I'm going to activate the
environment that I have created for this course specifically, and that has the name Python for
SciComp. So there's a question in the chat, what is being activated here? And I guess the follow-up
is why? Yeah, so by doing source, miniforge.bin activate, I just activate the base environment
for MiniForge and that is very basic. So what is MiniForge and what can we explain some sort of
the bigger picture here? So MiniForge has limited its lightweight by construction. It has a minimal
set of tools like Conda and Mamba and some basic Python packages.
But, yeah, I mean, in order to use additional packages, then I have created this environment.
And the reason why they don't come with MiniForge is because there is such a large number of
packages and everyone wants to customize their own environment.
So it is easier if you build simply the environment that is suitable for your workflow.
You could work with Anaconda, and I think that has most of the packages, if not all.
I think it does have all the packages that we are using in this course, but there has
been licensing issues with that.
So we are going to go for a free alternative, which is...
So this is like the way we, how do we say it?
you can install plain Python but that doesn't include everything needed for science. So
MiniForge allows you to make these other environments and the environment is a thing
that has a bunch of scientific software installed in it. Exactly. So I'm going to show quickly what
this environment has. So it has JupyterLab that we are going to be using in this lesson,
them, but it also has NumPy and SciPy, Matplotlib, and some MPI4Py, which we'll use in the parallel
lesson and, yeah, so, and in order to make sure that all these different packages work
together, then we build it in one environment, which we'll be using throughout this course.
And I guess there's more questions about how do we make the environments.
So making these was done as part of the installation instructions.
So we see the link up here in the purple color.
So if you're not ready and set up, you probably don't have enough time to do it now.
So in that case, what I would say is during the exercise time and the break times, work
on this, work on installing it, and then hopefully you're ready for after lunch or tomorrow.
And also we'll go into more detail about what this actually means later on, in, on day two
or three, we have a whole lesson about how the environments work.
Exactly. If you have Anaconda, you can open JupyterLab from there, otherwise you can create
this environment when you have some time. But you can just follow the lesson along and
try it later on if you prefer. So that is okay. So I'm going to go back to my terminal.
So then I am going to activate this particular environment
that I have created.
So now I am in this one.
And here I'm going to start up JupyterLab.
And I'm going to do it a little bit different compared
to what I wrote there.
I'm going to add the option No Browser.
And what this does, No Browser, it's
going to provide me a link, a URL that I can use in order
to open this JupyterLab session.
So this way, I have control over which window
I'm going to be using or which browser I'm
going to be using for this.
So I copy this link from here.
Either of these two will work, so that I'm
I'm going to paste it in one of my browser windows, tabs, sorry.
Okay.
So now I have Jupyter and when one starts it up, then we have a main page, which is
the launcher.
And I can open up a notebook from this launcher, and the important thing to know is that you
can use different kernels, so you can have different programming languages which are being
used in order to interpret the code that you are writing in the Jupyter notebook.
And what they have in this particular environment is only the Python kernel, but you can also
have extensions that work with other programming languages.
You can also have additions, or you can have additional packages in the Conda environment
so that you can work with different Conda environments
in the same JupyterLab session, but not the same session.
So you can have different notebooks
or different environments if you prefer.
But in this case, I'm just going to open up one for Python.
And good practice is always to save the file, the notebook
that you create.
So I'm going to give this a name.
So Jupyter Notebook, then Jupyter.
Here what I can have is,
so I have different cells.
This is one cell and this cell can be
either a code cell or it can be a markdown cell, for example.
So I, why it has disappeared, it's still there.
Yeah. So I can write, for example, let's see,
I'm going to copy paste something from the lesson as it's a bit more well-thought.
So I will just scroll a little bit here,
and I'm going to copy this text which has a markdown format,
paste it in myself, and I'm going to run this.
on my Mac it's a shift enter but it may be different depending on your operating system.
So now the output is shown here so it's just a stylized text with italics or
highlighters or links in fancy colors. The cells can also be figures or as I said they can be
the code as well.
So let's see if we can just show some example of a code.
Yeah, so let's just do a simple for loop in Python.
So note here that now I have changed from a markdown
set to a code set.
So then the kernel, which is Python,
going to interpret this as a Python cell. So I'm just going to print the numbers in the range
up to 3, which is 0, 1, 2. So I can just move it more with this.
And the way, again, the way I execute this cell is by pressing Shift Enter on my Mac.
So, if I choose to print several lines, I cannot actually do that in one cell because
only the very last one is going to be printed.
So then what I would need to do is actually to break this down into two cells if I do
wish to have both some sprinkled.
So this is one thing to remember.
In addition to using the, to running code,
you can also run some bash scripts if you want to.
And the way you can do that is by using these magics.
So here we have one example for bash.
What's a magic? What does that mean?
So magic is a way of telling the Jupyter notebook that
that this cell should not be interpreted as being Python code or code written in the programming
language that the kernel is for, but it is actually bash. Or it can be something different.
The way to tell that it is bash code is to have this double percentage followed by bash
And then, yeah, just another simple loop in Bash.
There are many different magics.
We won't really go through them.
It's just a way of letting you know they exist
and then you can check some more.
One nice magic is the timeit one.
And what this does is going to run this cell
to run this cell for a couple of times
and then provide an average of the time
that it took to execute.
So in this case, it's 60 milliseconds.
It's a nice magic for if you want
test how much time different cells of your notebook take. You may want to find ways of
improving that and you want to see, I mean, how different algorithms or different, yeah,
different ways of programming can impact the result. And I mean, of course, I mean, it's
It's, well, this has just taken milliseconds,
but it is questionable how useful it is
for code that runs over many minutes or hours.
But you can use that for a quick estimation.
And let's see.
You can use line magic if you want as well.
So this starts with one percentage and there are many really that are out there.
So I'm going to just show you if I remember correctly, yes, these are many different magics
that you can use.
And the focus of this lesson is now creating this magic.
So if you want to learn more, you can just play around with that.
So [name], what do you think we should say more about Jupyter?
Yeah, maybe I think you gave the pretty good intro there.
So there's a whole lot more about all of these topics and many things to do.
But for the purposes of right now, the only thing is, can you activate the environment
with the libraries needed for this course?
And can you do some basic printing?
And if you can get that far, then through the rest of the course, you'll be seeing more
tips and tricks with Jupyter as we go on.
So don't worry too much.
Exactly.
And I think now it would be nice if you try it on your own.
So we have an exercise that I'm going to share a link to and try to do it for the next, let's
say 15 minutes.
If you're very fast, you can jump to exercise number three, but that is really optional.
So it's really, if you do have the time.
And if you are very experienced with Jupyter and you don't feel like doing these exercises,
then just share what you like about it or dislike about it in the notes document.
And then we convene at nine.
I propose we come back at 50 past the hour, and then if we can take five minutes to wrap
up, then we can take the break, and then the next lesson starts five past the hour.
Yes, right.
Okay.
So, please continue asking questions and all.
I will switch the screen to the notes here.
Yes, you see.
And you see down below, there's...
We're having notes about the exercise here.
And we'll keep answering questions.
Um...
And try to clear up all the
little bits of other things.
Okay.
So, with that said,
good luck, and see you later.
Okay, bye.
you
So, welcome back.
I hope you got some time to try out the exercises.
We have had some questions in our collaborative notes, so keep them coming.
For example, one person asked that if you
can have mixed data types in the same array to store metadata.
But maybe that's not the best approach.
So for that, we have other libraries,
such as Xarray, which will be presented later on
in this course.
We'll quickly take a look at the exercise
one, what the answers were.
So the first question was the comparison
between A-range and linspace.
So as you can see, A-range gives you integers.
And in linspace, first thing is you can set the start and stop.
And you get floating points equally spaced
based on the start and stop and the number of elements
that you need.
If we want to create a random array of a given shape of three
rows and two columns, you can do that using random.
And then if we go into use as type of it,
it does not round everything.
So it doesn't round, for example, 0.95 to 1,
but it just truncates it, casts it.
Then integer, losing all the precision,
so you only get zeros, because this function produces
random floats between 0 and 1.
If you want random integers instead,
there is the randint function instead,
where you specify what range and then the shape.
So that's question two.
No, question three, sorry, for random integers.
If you do reshape, we need to be careful,
making sure that the number of elements are the same.
So for example, we can have a reshaped array consisting
of six rows, so still six elements, or two rows instead.
But if you're going to try something very strange,
like 12 rows, you will get an error instead.
Now the last question is just a check
of what we showed, which is how to save it using np.save.
and to get it back again.
So that was exercise one.
Keep the questions coming if you have any doubts
and we'll move on to the next part,
which is vectorization.
We'll continue to talk about the arithmetic calculations
for these items in a read.
Yeah, 10 or 20 minutes ago,
you see that you have saw that if we use NumPy
for this arithmetic calculation.
Transformation from one array to another
is quite super fast than the regular Python.
The mechanism is that the code in NumPy
is implemented in the C or Fortran code.
That's why it is a low-level programming language,
which enables the fast calculation
for this data manipulation in this array.
That is why we prefer to use the NumPy for the scientific computing.
Besides this, we also have other arithmetic calculations,
something similar to the ones in regular Python and also in the other programming languages.
We will show how it goes right here. For example, the addition,
subtraction, multiplication, and the division right here.
So actually now it's generating the two arrays, A and B, and we will do some arithmetic calculation
for these two arrays.
Yeah.
Right.
So you get A plus B, and you get the sum?
Yeah, quite simple.
You can see it's the addition of these two arrays
element by element means for the first element
is a one in A and the first element in array B is five.
And then one plus five is a six
to get to the first one in this new array.
Yes.
And you can see if we use the add method in the NumPy
get the same results? Yes. But for matrix multiplication. Okay, matrix multiplication.
So we have A and B and then we multiply the first row against the first column. So 5 and
14 becomes 90. This is the way for us to handle the matrix multiplication and the other problem
language for the first line first row and the first column and then go on but we have another
one, the NumPy dot, to see what is... Yes. For this particular example, it gives you the same result.
But it can be useful where you're actually interested in dot product system.
Yeah. If you make the efficiency of these two methods, you can see the difference. You can
time it some magic method you can play the gold later less or minus transpose
for example yes much more functions to try out
now before we go to exercise 2 we will also present we can we continue to talk
about indexing and slicing. These two functions means how can we extract one element or one
block from this array. Yeah, because we can to extract some, some items from the sysarray
to further usage or the for the data visualization, or the other calculations. Let's see where
can generate uh this array one by one to see we can so that we have more space to to extract
so we had a two by two array and if we give a zero we get the first row
and how can we extract the first column
the first column would be
like that so we get one three yeah that's good now here is a better example
with a much bigger area we can use that
if you need and let's let's take a look at how it's what's this stuff yes if we
need this part then we can do in square brackets one all in three so yeah one
from one two three is then the from the first row to the third row but in the
third row is not included right hmm and also quick note in numpy rows starts
are indexed from 0 yeah so this is row 0 and this is 1, 2 and then the third row
skipped 0. This is the C type. If you are familiar with C, you know what
you need to do. It is somewhat different to the fortune version
because the fortune started from 1
and if you need a very fancy slicing here like this one then we do
So here, we are trying to get these two.
So we can also, instead of using the colon slicing operation,
we can also mention the coordinates.
Right?
Yes.
Boolean indexing, what's that?
Boolean indexing means we can get the,
we can set some conditions, and these conditions
apply to the array, and we can get a new array
for all these items that follow this condition right here.
We just look at that.
yeah we generate a mask because there's only one element which is zero
then we can pass on that mask and then we get
everything else you can see when we remove that the first
atom here we started from that the atom to start from one but not
zero although you will lose the shape because
yeah the shape is somewhat different but you can do it in one go as well single line
the same result all right so now is the time for trying out the exercises
Let's combine the exercise 2 and exercise 3 together and let's see some basic arithmetical
calculations using NumPy and also the summation of this and also the indexing and slicing
how to extract some item or one block of item from the from the array. Yes. Yeah, nice.
Nice. Take probably a minute, because we are wrong. A little bit behind the schedule. Right?
Sounds good.
Yeah.
In 10 minutes, we come back at 11 o'clock, or 12 o'clock in Finland.
At the hour.
Yes.
See you later, in 10 minutes.
Bye.
you
All right, so welcome back, everyone.
I hope you had some time to try out the exercises two and three.
We'll quickly take a look at what the questions were.
So the first one was to compare NumPy multiply and dot.
What's the difference?
So here I built, used the same A metric, A array that we had,
and then identity array.
Then if we try numpy.multiply on that,
we get element-wise multiplication.
So everything which is 0 cancels out,
and then you are left with a diagonal.
But instead, if you're going to do np.dot,
it does matrix multiplication.
this case. So that's the answer for the first question. And about the access
parameter, if for, oh sorry, numpy.sum, yeah you can look at the
documentation as well if you click there.
So np.sum, if you pass access parameter as one, it does summation over
the along the rows for every column so it aggregates and you get 3 here 22 and
so on if you use access equal to 0 it does summation along the rows instead so
that's why here you get a different answer if you skip that you get the sum
of the whole array in one scalar.
And finally, exercise number three, we are asked to
create an array which is an identity array.
Fold by fold, we create b. Now, note that we did not copy b
here. It's all this. You don't get a message. You need to
understand that this is actually a view, not a copy.
So if you're going to modify this here in a cell above,
we're going to set B as the first element of B as phi.
Then it would have an effect on A as well.
So when we do this, take care of that.
All right.
So now we go to the remaining parts.
Yeah, because we are a little bit behind the schedule.
So we will have a short wrap up, but this episode.
Yeah, besides these standard operations we mentioned before,
there are more types of operations.
For example, the ufuncs, this is the universal function,
which enables the users to have more control
or for this of this array.
And you can see that previously, the arithmetical operations
is element by element, which means that the two arrays
your handle should be the same size and the same shape.
But in NumPy, you can have more control.
For example, you can have this addition
of a one-dimensional array to a two-dimensional array.
How to handle this?
you can use the broadcasting method right here.
And this means that you handle this array from a small array
to a large one.
And the worst precise is also applicable.
And you can do this from a large array to get the smaller one.
It can be a candle for the slicing part right here.
Besides this, we have more other functions right here.
You can see the max, mean, sum.
These functions are building functions
in NumPy, which you save lots of time to handle the data.
So due to the limitation, we're not
going to talk too much about these functions.
There are more or less materials,
if you scroll down a bit.
But there's less materials for the linear algebra
and advanced math.
And there are two accesses right here,
accesses number four and number five.
But if you like, you can take this as a homework
and to see how these accesses and the solutions
for the accesses are provided below the frames.
Yeah, that's it.
And then also accesses five,
it's a bit more of NumPy operations introduction to those.
to those and if you found this episode too simple of course you can there is a another episode in
the same material which won't be covered in this course which is called advanced numpy and that you
can find it just after this course material something for later yes in seeing case right
time for us to stop here and we will continue after the lunch break. So see you in one hour.
Bye.
you
Hi, we're back.
Hello.
So now we are going to a new direction.
We are going from NumPy to Pandas.
So I hope everybody is feeling refreshed after lunch and so that we have lots of energy to
maybe a cup of coffee to boost your energy for this lesson.
Yeah, so I guess the first question that everyone wants to know is what is pandas and why?
Do you have any initial insights? Yeah, so on the initial insights. So pandas,
like we previously talked about how NumPy solved the problem in Python, where Python has
various objects like lists and stuff like that that can, of course, be used to represent numbers,
but it's very inefficient because, well, NumPy is written in C++ whereas Python objects are
like Python objects and they are much slower. So NumPy solves a problem where you can store,
you can use, create these number arrays. You can create number arrays and stuff like that.
Like you can store lots of numbers and do operations on these numbers. But usually,
Actually, in science, we don't usually just deal with numbers.
The numbers usually mean something.
So unless you're in pure mathematics, I feel like that.
But in most of the cases, you have numbers that represent some quantities.
You have numbers that represent something.
So you have numbers like, let's say, temperature or height, or if you're in social studies,
You might have a height or in a medicine, you might have a response to a drug or whatever.
You might have all kinds of quantities that are represented as numbers, but there is some
concept or something they are related to.
So then you have some variable.
So you have things that have numbers associated with them.
And keeping track of this kind of stuff can get quite tedious quite quickly if you always
just use NumPy arrays.
So let's think of a situation where you want to, let's say a simple situation, you want
to keep track of, let's say, temperature and pressure at a certain time.
Like you're doing, I don't know, weather forecasting or something.
You want to have a time dimension and then you have a pressure and a temperature at different
times. You, of course, could do it in a way that you have a NumPy array for each one of these,
and then you index every one. If you want to find a certain time range, you find from the
time array and then you index the temperature and pressure. But it gets really tedious really
quickly. So if you have these kinds of data that is related to each other, but it's not like you
have multiple variables, multiple different arrays that you want to show and they are related.
So in these cases, you don't want to go off from NumPy because NumPy is very good for speed-wise,
but you want to add more tools to the toolbox so that you can easily handle these sorts of
related quantities, related variables to each other.
So what do you say? It's like normal Python objects are inefficient for having lots of data.
NumPy arrays become efficient for a lot of data, and then Pandas lets you tag the different
NumPy arrays, so it makes it like tabular data where there's rows that represent something
and then columns, and one column could be times and one column could be an integer index
and one column could be floating points, things like that.
Yes. And I think we'll go into how the data is organized in a bit more detail,
because there's a specific way that Pandas does it. But I think it's better to first get a glimpse
of this sort of data, what we're talking about. But you are exactly right. Pandas is about
organizing your data so that you can handle this more complex data that has some sort of meaning
inside of it. And the data relates to each other. So, the different data points relate to other
data points. So, let's... There's a question in the notes. It's the same as SciPy is built over
NumPy with more functions. So, yes. So, Pandas is also built over NumPy with NumPy being the
data storage for each column. So, SciPy, which I don't know if it was mentioned previously,
but SciPy and many of the scikit things, which are like scikit-learn is probably the most popular one
for machine learning, like traditional machine learning. These are all built upon NumPy that
use NumPy as the basic building block, because the NumPy arrays are so fast, you can use those
to build different functions. Also in case of SciPy, like, I don't know, Bessel functions or
or like sparse linear matrices or whatever.
Like you can do lots of stuff in the SciPy stuff,
but Pandas is all about like organizing different results.
So yeah, so let's move forward
and let's look at the actual code.
And okay.
So I have my Jupyter open.
I'll scroll this down and try to make it smaller.
We do have these fancy run code buttons here,
but this is sort of a test and it might not work
and we don't recommend you doing it that way.
Also, we might overload the service that's running these.
Yeah.
I would recommend just, if you have your,
if you've managed to open a Jupyter setup,
so you have your own Jupyter,
most likely it will have the Pandas installed as well.
So I recommend getting a Jupyter notebook open.
Yeah.
Okay, so
So, here we go.
We see Pandas, the lesson at the top and my Jupyter at the bottom.
So if now, [name], I'm in a Python place, I'll make a new notebook and yeah, okay.
So [name], what should I do?
So first step is, of course, like importing NumPy.
We want to use the library, so we import Pandas.
And with pandas, same as with NumPy, nobody wants to write pandas, pandas, pandas, over
again.
So instead, we import it with the name pd.
So this is common.
If you see documentation, it's just like in the internet, everybody does this all the
time.
And let's load some example data.
So in the example, in the next cell, we read from the internet.
So this is from the pandas internal.
They include in the development side,
they include this famous data set,
which is like Titanic passenger list.
And we can use that as an example for what sort of data
do we have here.
So let's load that in.
OK, so the first line sets some URL
where it's already online and the second line
makes a data frame.
Yeah.
So you notice that we have used this pandas read CSV.
We'll talk about data formats and data,
like different data structures,
but pandas already supports a myriad
of these different kinds of data formats.
So in this case, we just load a CSV file.
So comma separate values, we read it in.
And now we have it loaded
And let's use this titanic.ed to this function
to view the first few rows of that thing.
So OK, so now we can see that, OK, we
have this kind of like a table now of data.
And it's organized by this name column.
so the name is like on the left you can see that it's like bolded so that's like every passenger
is organized by their name and for each passenger we have a passenger ID, whether they survived,
what passenger class they were, what is their sex, what is their age
and so forth, like how much they paid for the Titanic fare and so forth. So we
have lots of these different values here. And what we have here is a so-called data frame.
So, Panda stores the stuff in these objects called data frames, and it stores each of these
columns into an object called series. And each of these series is wrapped around a NumPy array.
Okay. So, each column is one NumPy array. So, all these integers are one NumPy array.
Yes. And you notice that some of these columns have different kinds of data types. So, for
example, the gender or the sex field that can be male, female, and same with the ticket.
And some of these are integers, such as survived or a passenger ID. And some of them are floating
point values such as fair. So we have different data types stored in the same data frame.
So there was a question previously about, can you store multiple data types in a NumPy array?
And that's not possible because NumPy arrays are fast because they only have one data type
in them. So many of the functions that are written in NumPy, they know that, okay, whatever
I'm getting in, it's floating point numbers, I can just know that it's floating point numbers,
so I can do stuff like square root or addition or whatever. And I know what it means and I can
do it very fast. And that's why you cannot in NumPy mix and match these different types unless
you use this object type. But that just means that it's very slow. It's basically like Python
list again. So I guess pandas automatically detected all of these for us. Yes. So the read
CSV function, it basically went through the file and it checked, okay, like can I convert all of
these into integers or floating points? What is the kind of type I need for all of these?
So let's look at the describe. Let's get a quick description of every column that we have here.
Yeah, so over here, we can already see what sort of features the pandas provides us.
So for different kinds of, well, what we have here for different kinds of values, we get
already like we can get quick descriptions of, okay, what sort of data do we have here?
So you notice that none of the string values are included because like, how do you calculate
mean string or like how do you calculate the standard deviation of a gender? I don't know,
like it's very hard. So, instead those are like discarded because those operations are
not defined for them. So, instead we have like for the integer and for the
the, for the, for integer and for the floating point columns, we get descriptions of what
is.
Yeah.
So, for example, the mean of survived is 0.38, so I guess that means 38% of people survived.
And so on.
Okay.
So, we have this quick overview of data.
Yeah.
Let's do another quick overview that's in a different order in the documentation.
But let's quickly look at Titanic.info function.
So that provides us a bit of information about how the stuff is stored.
It shows a bit of the insights of what's happening here.
So we see here that we have 891 entries.
So it had 91 rows, and then we have 11 columns.
And each of these columns have a different name,
and then we see the data type of each column.
So we can see that, OK, some of these are, let's say,
the strings are objects, and the others
are floating points and integers.
Yeah. So, this looks a lot like the NumPy data types.
Yes. And, like, why do we want, like, what do we get from this approach? So, the approach,
like, why do we want to do this is that, like, some of the columns are related to each other.
So, let's say we want to ask a question of what is the mean age of a survived person.
Like now we need to relate like the survived column with the age column.
And we need to like, based on the value of another, we need to answer
something from another column.
So, so we, we suddenly have a situation where like, of course we could do all of
these, we could store these as individual arrays, each of one of these.
But when we want to ask a question of, okay, like I want to, I want to get
something from other, like one array based on the values of another array.
it gets really tedious to first index, let's say, one array based on values of that array,
and then index another array with that information. So, it's super tedious. So, let's do it.
Yeah. So, if I can, I think I can, if I understand this right. So, using the same
metaphor before, if you're doing it in pure Python, then you basically have a list with
with one column and a list with another column.
I mean, you need to make a bunch of code that
finds the values from one column,
get the data from another column,
and that's a lot of work.
With NumPy, it's more efficient because you
have arrays of columns.
And there might be functions that find different bits,
but you still have two separate arrays
and have to correlate them together.
And there's lots of stuff that can go wrong,
you're writing more code. But now here, since it's one table, are we going to learn some
functions that let us say, well, just like you said, for every survived passenger, what
was their average fare? And then it knows that these two are related and each row is
the same person and that kind of thing.
Yeah. Like we usually, when we want to answer questions, like scientific questions, we usually
want to answer questions that are like, okay, given this time level or whatever, what happened
or given the survived, if a person survived, what is their mean age or stuff like that.
Or let's say given the gender, how many survived, we want to see answer questions like these.
When I asked those questions, I didn't speak about indexes or anything at all.
I didn't mention that, okay, I want to know what's in the index zero of this array.
And that is the scientific question I want to answer.
No, I want to answer a question that can be formulated more in this natural language.
And I want to ask a question based on the contents of the data, not based on how it's
organized in the memory.
Yeah, can we see some?
Yeah, let's do this quickly.
Quick example of this grouping.
Well, we can talk later about how groupings work in Pandas.
But basically, what we can do is that in Pandas,
we can take a data frame, and we can basically
split it into sub-dataframes based on some values.
It can go multiple levels deep as well.
Like, you can, you can, yeah, so in this case,
we basically say that, OK, like, OK,
get me the original data frame, group it by the survival value,
and then get me the age column of each of these,
like split groups and then calculate the mean of that.
Okay.
So let's run it and let's see what happens.
So group by, this makes two separate frames
for the values that survived.
Yeah.
What it creates is this group by object
that you can iterate over or you can like get stuff,
but it's like, that's black magic, like what happens.
So you don't necessarily have to know that.
Yeah.
We get the mean value, and we print it.
So we see here survived 0, 1, and then 2 means so.
Yeah.
So let's say if the children were at the,
hey, I don't actually know.
Is survive dead, or which one is true?
I'm guessing one is survived.
I think so, because above we saw the mean of survived was 38, and probably around 38% survived.
Okay, yeah, so the survivors were on average a few years younger.
Yeah, younger. So that would mean like women and children first, like maybe the children were the, I don't know.
But we can, like, we don't know about the results, but we can show, like, this already
shows the power of it, like what pandas can do.
But pandas can also do, like, you can, like, if you want to explore your data, you can
also do this kind of, like, quick plots with it.
So we don't, like, there's many of these kinds of plots, but let's just run this one example
plot here, which creates a histogram based on one column.
So that's just copying.
Yeah.
So OK, so making a histogram with a column of age,
survived bins.
Oh, there we go.
So we see like a histogram of, so we
notice that in the survived one, there's this big bump at the lowest number, so babies basically.
I would assume that that means that a lot of those survived, a lot of babies survived.
And this is really the power of like we are here showing one example here and one kind
of an example that you can do.
But if you look at the code again, quickly, at no point did we reference any indexes or
any kinds of stuff like that.
We just referred to the columns and the data in the columns and that sort of stuff.
referenced the data based on the names of the stuff. We didn't, we weren't interested about,
okay, like, how are they, like, are they sorted in a certain order? Are the rows sorted in a
certain order? Like, none of that matters, because in this kind of data, like, and you might,
yeah, like, in this kind of data, like, it doesn't really matter. Like, what we want to do is we
we want to calculate something based on the,
we don't care about the indexes.
We really care about how they relate to each other
and that the relationships are like set correctly.
Yeah.
So what's next?
So let's quickly look, if we scroll a bit down,
we can view what, again, like what is a data frame?
I already mentioned this,
This is quite important to say. Previously, when we were talking about NumPy arrays,
and we were talking about rows and columns in multidimensional NumPy arrays,
Pandas isn't like a multidimensional NumPy array in that in NumPy, all of the rows and columns,
like the speakers already mentioned that NumPy can have multiple dimensions, and each of these
you can create a three-dimensional NumPy array or two-dimensional NumPy array,
and all of these have the same data type. And you would think that, okay, if I just have
numbers in a table, that just means that, okay, this is the same as a DataFrame. But that's not
the case, because in Pandas, the columns and rows have a meaning. And the meaning is that
each column represents a variable, and each row represents an instance of that variable existing.
So, like a measurement. Yeah. So, if we thought about previous example of the Titanic
In each row, we had an individual person.
And for that individual person, we have different variables that correspond to that measurement.
And we had like specific features.
And each of these variables has the same data type.
So each of these variables is a NumPy, like it's the NumPy array, like each column.
And each row is one measurement that belongs to all of these different columns.
And what it means is that pandas can then identify and match the different columns for
each observation.
So it can handle the arduous task of matching, let's say, pressure and temperature at this
and that time.
It can match, keep them in sync, these different variables.
And this is important because all of the tools in Pandas are designed around this.
And it's not only Pandas.
So basically every major language that uses just this kind of like scientific, or not
even scientific, like does this kind of data analysis kind of thing, uses the same kind
of idea.
So if you think about big data analysis, if you think about SQL databases, if you think
about R, if you think about extensions of Pandas, if you think about like how big data
is handled. All of these use the same kind of idea, where you have columns that have data,
like in variables, and then you have rows that are measurements. The underlying implementations
might differ, but the same idea is across all of the data landscape.
Maybe we should move on. Are there any alternatives to Pandas, or is it basically
what everything uses under the hood, the higher level stuff.
So there are many alternatives to pandas. For example, nowadays, there's lots of talk
about Polars, which uses the pandas API because it's so everybody uses the pandas API. It
has the same kind of like functions, but underneath it, it uses the same kind of tools. Dask is
another option that also uses the same underlying structure, but it uses parallelism and that
sort of stuff for big data and there's others, but they all basically use the same kind of idea.
So you really, if you want to do this kind of like data analysis, you really want to make certain
that your data and your, basically your measurements abide by this idea, because
otherwise you will, you cannot use the tools because they're not like designed for it.
Like you cannot, it's not, it doesn't mean anything, for example, to calculate the mean
across a row, because how do you calculate the mean across like when you had columns like gender
and columns like, like survive. So, so what should we do now? So let's quickly look at how do we,
now that we know that the data is organized like this, how do we access the data? Like how do we
access the data in different ways. So previously we showed the group by method, but there's other
methods that you can use to refer to various things in here. So are we here where we look at the
age and so on? Yeah. Okay. So let's look at a few ways that you can access the columns.
So, the first one is to use these brackets.
So this, if you have used Python dictionaries, this is a very similar kind of a thing.
So you refer to it by name.
And this is especially useful if your name has spaces or some characters that don't really
work with the other option, which is this dot, which is like this Python attribute
kind of a way to access the different columns.
And you notice that what this returns, like this titanic age, for example, it's a series
that has the same index.
So again, the names.
So it's not only like, it doesn't just return the numbers, it returns a series.
So it still knows, okay, who is this related to.
There are functions like toNumPy or toList that you can use to convert it into basic
NumPy array or Python list if you want to, but the columns are this kind of like.
Yeah.
So it knows.
Okay.
Yeah.
And I guess this next one is the same.
Next one is the same.
So it has some shortcut there.
Okay.
Yeah.
And if you look at the, below there's the type, so here you notice that it is a series.
So it's not a NumPy array.
It's NumPy array with additional information,
basically, still in it.
You can look at type, titanic, age, and dot values,
if you want to, and check what is.
So this is the NumPy array here.
And you notice that there's many other numbers
and stuff like that over here, but yeah.
So inside of this series, there are the values,
but usually you don't need to mess up with those.
Usually you can access them in other ways.
So for the data frame itself,
you can view what columns you have there
with like titanic.columns.
We already view them with the info, but sometimes you want to like iterate over the columns
or do something like that.
And then you want to do that kind of stuff.
Then, yeah, okay.
And the same for rows, you can see the, what are the rows with index.
So index is the name of the row names, columns is the name of the column names.
Yeah.
And quite often, of course, you might have a situation where the index is just like a
number that runs and then you use some other thing to basically index the stuff.
You can use a column to index it, but quite often you might have a situation where you
You want to put one of the columns as the ID of the thing and make it an index.
In this case, for example, the name column has been specified as the index column.
What describes the row, basically.
Why is this important?
Why do you want to put something as an index?
Well, it's again for references.
If you want to reference stuff, you can reference by the same as in NumPy, you can do references
based on a row and a column, so you can then search the data.
And the recommended way of doing these searches is usually using these functions, this lock
function, especially, to find stuff. Let's look at a few examples here. Remember, our rows are now
named. Our rows have a name of a person. Over here, we want to find location of
of what is the row, lam, Mr. Ali, and what is the age.
So we want to find one column from this row.
And we can now use the name of the person
instead of a random index or whatever.
Instead of saying row one or row two.
If the names meant something, now
we can look up stuff by name.
And this is very important, especially if you do a time series analysis, because usually
the time is a natural way of organizing the stuff.
You want to organize the stuff based on the time, or maybe you have some other index that
you want.
You have some natural way of organizing the data, and that's why you might put it into
the rows so you don't always have to do very complex searches.
But let's look at other things.
So we can, of course, ask for multiple columns.
So in the example, you can ask for a range of columns.
But I would say that this is pretty weird way.
You can do this kind of thing.
But again, it's like, OK, it depends on how the columns are organized.
So I wouldn't probably use that.
So instead, what I would do is put brackets around it.
So let's say we want to know survived and aged age.
So if you put the brackets around the survived age
and make it the least instead.
OK.
Let's see.
So.
So survived comma age.
So now we're using loke, and one of the arguments
itself is a list.
OK.
Yeah, I've got two things out.
OK, yeah.
Yeah, sorry, my computer is frozen.
Just a second.
OK.
Yeah, yeah.
Too many windows open.
I'll be right back probably.
Yeah, the Firefox crashes.
At least I can still hear you and see you.
Yeah.
Yeah, Zoom is taking over.
Yeah, no, but it seems that too many windows open.
Yeah, so you can do stuff like this.
So you can refer to the columns,
like you can index by the column names
instead of like where they are,
because it's much more like natural way of,
at least for me, of thinking about the data,
of, okay, what's in the data
instead of where is it stored.
For, you can also use these indexing things.
So you can use this iloc.
OK, so 0 to 2 gets the first two rows.
Two rows, yeah.
3 to 6 gives the fourth to seventh columns,
following the Python conventions.
Fourth to sixth columns.
Yeah, OK.
But this is, again, pretty arbitrary.
What do these mean?
I don't know.
I rarely ever use these, but it's
good to know that they are present.
You can also, for individual values,
you can use this at to modify individual values
and get individual values.
But I don't think we need to set or necessarily show
all of the examples here.
But it's good to know that you can get these.
They are useful if you want to get a specific value
something. But the power of pandas also comes that you can do operations for a whole column at
time. Because all of the columns are NumPy arrays, you can create new NumPy arrays. You can set in
entire columns at a time. Or you can do like mathematics calculations for
and do all sorts of like indexing tricks for the whole column. So if you show
the... So [name], you're breaking up maybe. Your computer's slowing down again.
Yeah, I think it's the HackMD chat is probably, or the notes check chat is probably, or could
it be the stream previews that's causing the problem?
Might be.
I'll probably have to restart some of my browsers.
Yeah, no.
Maybe it eases up.
Yeah.
So, so, but yeah.
So, if you.
Age.
Yeah.
Sorry about the technical problems.
Shows ages.
Yeah.
Titanic age greater than 70 shows a false and true
for people whose age is greater than 70, I guess.
Yeah.
So when previously, in the previous session,
was demonstrated how can you use NumPy to create
this kind of like, in NumPy you can do these Boolean arrays.
So basically you have a condition and then based on that condition,
you get another array that either says true or false based on that condition.
In this case, we can use the column age to say that, okay, which rows does this apply to?
and then take only those rows.
So, the inside, like we are sorting or going through the data row by row based on the value of one column.
So, you can do these kinds of things to hone in on the data that you're interested in.
So all automatically, it's doing these complex data operations in one line.
Yes.
Which is pretty cool.
And the other one is also very cool.
So there's also like this many of like, you can, the inside can be also like a function
of the, of one of the columns.
So because the index is a string column, so its name is a string, we can run this contains
function.
So it tells, it produces true or false if there's the substring inside that string,
and then we can use that to index the data.
huge bunch of these, so I wouldn't expect anyone to necessarily remember that this exists,
but it's good to check the pandas documentation for various of these, because there's so many
of these kinds of tricks to sort through the data. Yeah. Do you even know all the tricks,
or do you basically find them when you... No, I would say that it's like wasted
that brainpower. If I remember one URL, not even the URL, if I know how to Google pandas
documentation, I can go there and then I can search there. Okay, how do I do this? Because
somebody has written a great explanation there and I just have to know that there exists
away, and then I can find it. I don't have to remember it. And there's also multiple
of different ways. People use different kinds of syntax they want. The Pandas ecosystem
supports many types of these kind of indexing things. Either use indexes, you use columns,
whatever. You can do different kinds of tricks. And it's more about knowing that there is
a way of organizing the data. And what do we get when we do these searches? What Pandas does,
it doesn't create us copies of the original data. It creates this so-called view of the data. So
when we do this kind of stuff, we are basically like splitting pieces out from the original data
and we are like limiting ourselves to a subset of the data and pandas will like cut out the rest,
but it won't do a copy. It will just show us a different view of the data. So that's very
important when you're dealing especially with big data and you don't want to do like,
you don't want to do copies. You want it to figure out everything from the same data.
Yeah. Okay, so basically, if you have big data stuff, this is not the worst thing. It might work
and it's not going to eat up all your memory more than it has to.
Yeah. There's, of course, even more specialized tools for these, but all of them use the same
kind of idea. You first figure out what is the important data, then you get that, then you do
some operations with that data. You usually need to describe how do you get to that data.
There's also plenty of pandas functions. For example, is not a number,
to go up another number and this sort of stuff here.
So you can get different views of the data
where some of the data has dropped out.
And this is very useful,
especially if you have noisy data,
historical data or something
that you don't know how to deal with.
And especially if you have,
in some cases people want to put,
instead of using another number,
they use minus one is another number
And now you need to modify everything
where a number is minus one into another number
so that you can drop them out.
And if you need to do data cleansing
and this sort of thing, these functions help a lot.
But I think we should go to the exercise
and let people try it out themselves.
Yeah, so what's the goal here?
So I would say, yeah, many of these are a bit,
this exercise a bit, how could I say, free-form, so maybe not. What I think would be important
is probably if you can do the steps that we have done previously and try out them yourself,
because it really helps to look at them yourself, and try out the third one at least,
which is the compute the mean age of the first 10 passengers,
and try out different things as well.
Like try out switching different columns, see what you can,
like explore the data, because in lots of cases,
the science is really about how do you view the data?
How do you explore the data?
And in that case, you need to know, like,
how do you select a certain amount of the data
and what data to select?
So if you try that out, maybe you can answer and check the questions in the notes in the meantime and answer them afterwards.
So by the time we come back, there should also be a break. So should we go for 20 or 25 minutes and there's break time plus the question time?
or break time plus the exercise time.
Is 10 minutes enough for these exercises?
Yeah, I think we can move forward and explore more.
Yeah.
OK.
And I guess there's probably not enough time
to do everything from scratch.
But get started a little bit and see how it goes.
Okay, um, yeah. Okay, see you later in 20 minutes. Okay, bye.
you
Hello.
Hi.
You're back.
Yeah.
So we had lots of interesting discussion in the notes, which is really great.
So we want to highlight a few of the, like, because there's lots of stuff still to come
that we could go through, but it's really nice to have this kind of discussion and really
focus on, okay, what sort of questions you had, because it really shows like, okay, what
kind of stuff is still, well, maybe left out of the discussion.
One thing was that, okay, why aren't we using the PD anywhere anymore? In NumPy,
we did a lot of NumPy something, NumPy something, like np arrange, np whatever.
We used a lot of stuff from the np module, so the Python library. This is because in NumPy,
Well, the NumPy array objects themselves, they have a lot of functionality themselves,
but the NumPy module or the library provides additional functions, a lot of functions that
operate on these arrays.
Whereas in Pandas, well, it's the same case.
Pandas has a lot of these things.
But in most situations, we have a situation where we want to use the data frame.
In Pandas, when we read data in or when we create, we create these data frames.
And this data frame is the NumPy array on steroids, which is a bunch of these NumPy
arrays. And it also contains a lot of this information. So, what we usually use are the
functionality in the data frame itself, and sometimes in the series. So, in each column,
we use functionality of those columns. So, for example, we calculate the mean of a column or we
calculate the mean of the data frame. So, we use functionalities of these objects themselves. So,
the coding style is a bit different. So, we have a lot of dot something, dot something, dot something,
and then we have the brackets to limit ourselves to some stuff. So, the pandas, it's quite often
the case that you have import pandas as PD, and then you have PD read CSV, and you never see the
PD and ever again, it's just all open, working on the data frames afterwards.
Another thing that was interesting was that there was this kind of location
where a question on indexing the data based on, with the same rules as you do with the NumPy
arrays. And in the question, the person was trying to do the same sort of indexing as you
would do with a NumPy array. But again, it's a great question because this is something that
you might do quite often. But here, the NumPy array is, let's say, a two-dimensional block of
indexes. It's a two-dimensional table or block of indexes. And in Pandas, it's not that. It's
individual rows and individual columns. And you use one or more of these columns as the
indexing columns, so as the indexes. In the example there, if you're indexing with this
colon colon 10, you take every 10th row and that is defined, but when you take from 0 to 10,
10, what you get is range from 0 to 10, and now it's looking for numbers, like indexes
numbered or named 0 and number 1 and number 2, but the indexes are named after the persons,
so you don't get that.
So then you need to use the iloc.
And this is what usually, when you're doing these kinds of indexing in Pandas, you often
search by what is the index contents, like by some condition, okay, give me rows where
something's happening.
This is why you rarely use, or you can use the iloc to use the exact indices, but you
rarely do that because, again, you get the random numbers, yes, but you didn't have any
specific reason why those were better than the others.
It can get quite confusing.
people stick to the, like they use the contents of the rows or contents of the index to search
for the data, not necessarily the, not necessarily like the indexes because that's like, you
can switch columns, you can order them around and you can order the rows around and like
suddenly your indexes are all messed up and that's no good.
Yeah, another great question was like, okay, so which one is better for if you have like
2D, like lots of data that is in the same data types and do you have it in the,
do you have it, I'm confused by the cat, I'm like
So, yeah, if you have mixed data types versus non-mixed data types, and again, there's multiple
ways of thinking about it.
So if you have 2D data where it's actually meaningful to have it in multiple dimensions,
it's very good to have it in NumPy format.
But let's consider a case where you have 2D NumPy array where the first column is temperature
and the second column is pressure.
And now you calculate the mean out of it.
What does it mean?
What does it mean to calculate the mean value over temperature and pressure that are in
the same array?
You cannot do that kind of stuff.
It doesn't produce any meaningful results.
in Pandas because Pandas knows that they are like suffix quantities. Can you multiply height and
width or can you add kilograms and meters? It doesn't make any sense. And if you store them
in the same NumPy array, you even often have a situation where that happens. You just
accidentally multiplied or maybe added meters to kilograms or seconds and then you're like,
okay, what's wrong with my analysis pipeline? Why am I getting really strange results? And the reason
was that the independent quantities or the quantities that are like different variables,
they are mixed and you don't want to do that. Like in Pandas, you can also have like NumPy arrays
stored in each row. So you can have like, but that's a bit more advanced, I would say.
But so, and especially for people who are doing like natural sciences, who might have
like large datasets and they might think that, okay, I'm never going to use like a, I will
never need to do my data in this sort of format.
But in papers, like if you have data that you have X and Y axis, that's two variables,
right?
Like you have two variables and you need to plot them, right?
You need to keep them in check.
you even have a table in your paper that describes like, okay, different values,
all of that, you can manage that in NumPy arrays and whatever, but it's much
easier to manage it in a table format.
And it's in this data frame format in pandas.
And then let's say do a plot on that instead of having it done in NumPy
arrays, and this is like, it's a bit of a mind shift coming from NumPy.
So, it's even bigger, like, you have already gone through the mind shift of going from Python to NumPy.
Okay, now everything is a big block.
And now you have to think about, okay, like, there's big blocks, but all of these are, like, separate variables.
And it's a bit of a mind shift, but the reason why it's constructed in this way is that then you can do, like,
you can correlate one variable with another variable.
and it's very hard to do that in NumPy without this sort of machinery.
But yeah, so maybe we should quickly look at the document. We'll quickly look at this
in a bit more detail. I might harp over this, but this is basically why this has been designed.
So the original idea of Pandas was that the developers basically designed this for banking
world. And there you really don't want to keep your stuff for data analysis in banking world.
And it's of course used in scientific fields ever since. But they really want to keep their
ledgers in check. They really want to keep their data in check and make certain that
everything's correct. This is why it's been designed like this and why other data analysis
things are designed in the same way. It all goes back to this concept of tidy data that I
I would describe where the rows are variables,
sorry, rows are measurements
and each column is a variable.
So let's look at this dataset that we have here,
like this runner dataset.
So here we create the DataFrame explicitly.
We don't create it from CSV, but we create it explicitly.
Should I be typing now?
Yeah, if you can copy that.
Okay, let's.
look a bit busy. Maybe it will sit there. Okay, so I'll copy this and I paste,
and this makes a data set called runners. Yeah, if you show the runners, like if you just
go with them. Yeah, okay. And you might look at, hey, look, this is like a nice looking table.
what's wrong with this? And the idea behind the dataset, like the tidy data, is that again,
like every row is a measurement and each column is a variable. So let's say you want to calculate,
like in running, you often have this concept called pace, so which is like how many minutes
per kilometer, like how fast are you running, like how many minutes does it take for you to
And in this case, if you would not want to calculate something like that, you notice
that the distance is actually baked into the column names.
You have extra information here that is baked into the column names.
And some cases it might be fine, like this might be fine for analysis, but it's not in
this tidy data format, which means that you have stuff in the individual rows.
So it's wide instead of being tall.
It's often said in this way.
So what you can do is you can use this pandas melt to basically take the columns and then
make it into rows.
I mean, yesterday I thought that this melt function, the naming of the melt function
is probably because brains melt when they try to get a grasp of what's happening here.
And this is sometimes what happens with data wrangling.
I remember once dealing with this kind of data set from World Bank or what was it, that
had like Excel data where each like column name had huge amount of information in it.
And it was like one Excel spreadsheet, but it had like lots of information encoded into
the column names and row names or whatever.
And in order to create like a data set that can then be used, you need to like do a lots
of wrangling for it.
And this is very common, especially in economics and stuff like that, where lots of information
is hidden into the columns.
So let's say if we want to now calculate the pace, we could do like a simple like runners
column, like new column called pace, if you put brackets and yeah.
And there you put runners, and then you take the,
what was the speed?
It was time.
Time over distance.
Yeah, they are, like, pace is a weird one.
It's often written this sort of way.
Yeah.
So now you can calculate the pace.
I'll make it lowercase.
Yeah.
And now you can show the runners again.
So now you can calculate the pace.
And you can see that, let's say, runner two is very consistent.
So every runner is very consistent
that they can run with the same pace at different,
even though they're running at different lengths.
So it's not very realistic.
Artificial data.
Yeah.
OK.
But yeah, this sort of situation,
And this maybe demonstrates to you how it's easier to work, because all of the workflows
in Pandas and in these kinds of libraries is designed around this tidy data, where you
have these...
In order to do the same calculation in the previous format, where it was, we would have
to divide each column by the column name.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And that's like the general idea.
Yeah.
And that creates it, makes it a lot more complicated.
And of course, like your data might,
like usually it's a good idea to store your data
in this kind of tidy format all the time.
So it's easier to then use the tools.
Because the tools are designed around this concept.
And it's good to know the concept,
because then you know that, OK, like there
tools that probably work with this. Yeah, like, since I learned of tidy data, suddenly everything
started making so much more sense to me. And like, yeah, okay, I should always use this,
and it makes everything easier. Okay. And the same concept is used widely in different fields,
so on different tools. So R, for example, uses the same format, or same idea. And like I
Like I mentioned, the SQL users, so if you want to deal with databases or big data like
Hadoop or whatever, they all do the same kind of stuff because it's efficient and it's possible
to handle huge amounts of data with this sort of format.
Okay.
What next?
We have about eight more minutes before we should move on.
Yeah.
So I think what we could do is in the, yeah,
I think we could quickly show at the near the access
two. I quickly mentioned that if you scroll a bit up, there's lots of these functions
in Pandas, so we cannot go possibly through all of these because there's so many. There's
a whole chapter on time series analysis afterwards that we unfortunately don't have time to go
through. But there's lots of these functions. If you scroll a bit down.
Okay. Tell me when to stop. Yeah. Yeah. A bit down. Yeah.
Yeah. Like a bit down even more. Well, I can explain over here. Yeah. So, there's lots of
these different numbers that are already defined in Pandas, like standard deviations and means max
and cumulative sums and medians and whatever, like statistic functions and that sort of stuff.
And of course, you can do a more complicated analysis on different rows as well. But one
important thing in Pandas is also this kind of grouping idea that you can group the data based
on. Like I mentioned previously, you can group the data into sub-sections, like sub-arrays.
So, instead of doing a for loop, where in, like, the alternative is to, like, create a for loop
where you for loop values of a certain, unique values of a certain row, and then you,
for each row, you select the subset, and then you, for that subset, you calculate something.
Instead of doing that, you can do these groupings, these group bys, and you can do multiple levels
of this.
So, for example, you can do stuff like that, that you can split among gender and check
whether they're a child, and then you can calculate the mean survival rate.
And there's lots of different values like this.
And I think it might be good to maybe let people have a bit of a break.
There's lots of stuff coming here.
So test out the exercises, exercise two.
And also, in the next session, we'll
talk a bit more about this same kinds of stuff as this one is,
like data and the metadata joined together.
But this time, we are dealing with this kind
of multidimensional data.
So if you're doing, I don't know,
natural sciences or whatever, you
are definitely interested in this next one
because it's the x-arrays that Magan will be talking about there, really, really great.
But I would say, try out these different functions on the dataset in the examples and yeah, hopefully
this answered many of the questions about them.
Should we go on to the x-ray lesson, then?
Wasn't it at 30?
Yeah, but do...
I think we could have a bit of a break.
Okay, so...
So people can try out the exercises.
We'll quickly break for now.
Okay.
um yeah okay see you shortly bye
you
We are live right here for the next section, the next session.
I hope you all had a great break.
This session is all about X-Ray and helping me learn about X-Ray is [name].
But I am [name].
I'm also at the University of Aalto and together with [name] and maybe [name], you would like
to introduce yourself.
Yes.
I'm [name].
I work at UIT, the Arctic University of Norway in Troms and I have been working with xarray
during my PhD and postdoc quite extensively,
so I hope I'm able to answer most of the questions.
Looking forward to it.
That would be great.
I think to dive right in, we've just seen NumPy,
and then we went to Pandas, and now we're
going to add another library into the mix that
deals with data.
Why X-Ray, and why should we learn about X-Ray?
So X-Ray is really handy if you work with data where
have a higher dimensionality than 1D or 2D.
So if you have tabular data, then probably
we'll never need X-Array.
You can just use pandas.
But if you work with data which has three dimensions or even
more, then X-Array is by far, at least what I know,
the best tool that is out there for Python.
It might also be valuable if you have 2D arrays or 1D arrays,
time series, and so on.
But really, the major selling point
or the major advantage of X-Arrays
is multiple dimensions.
Exactly.
That's what I thought as well,
that when your data fits into a table
and it looks like a table and you could build it in Excel,
then Pandas is probably good.
But what if you have multiple dimensional data?
So you have three dimensions, four dimensions.
It doesn't fit neatly into a table anymore.
That's where X-Ray comes in.
Okay, so but then I can create NumPy arrays
of three dimensions and four dimensions
and five dimensions, I know that.
So what does X-Array then give us?
So the biggest contribution of X-Array
is to introduce coordinates.
So in this example that you're showing here,
which we have in the document,
you have this 3D non-plane array,
but if you want to get a data out of it,
a specific one at a specific point,
you first of all have to know which dimension refers to
which coordinate and you also need to know which index
refers to the exact position that you need.
And this can be highly unintuitive
and it's like data or like this information
that you typically don't really think about
if you want to explore a dataset.
So when you use X-Ray,
instead you can actually access these dimensions
by the name of this dimension.
We'll see how it's implemented in X-Ray soon.
And you can also choose it
by the specific value of the coordinate.
So that's very similar to what you've seen previously
in Sway and Pandas,
but we will now see how it works in 3D.
So working with X-Ray makes it just so much more intuitive
for us humans to work with data.
Exactly. So say if our data here is temperature data,
but I want to say, okay,
I want the temperature at London, for example,
then yeah, this is going to be tricky
because then I need like the numerical indices
on wherever London is in my data.
It would be nice if it could just say to the data,
hey, just give me the row corresponding to London
or give me the row, column, and even Z
like corresponds to something.
Okay, so let's take a look at an x-array then.
Let's do this.
So let's load one up.
I'm gonna load this data here that we have here in example.
Yeah.
What is this dataset, by the way?
This is a dataset from like a temperature
and pressure measurements, I believe.
It's open access, anyone can download it.
And in this case, we have four dimensions
as we already see here in the document.
Yeah.
I see here that this just gives me the file path,
but not just the name of the file, I suppose.
So now I'm gonna use these two lines
to actually load the data in that file path.
That gives me now a variable called ds.
So this must be the data set.
So let's check it out there.
Oh, look, that's the Jupyter Notebook
actually gives me a very nice table.
Okay, wow, there's a lot of stuff in here.
So this is much more than a single array.
I don't think I've opened a single NumPy array now.
You have not.
There is much more in it.
So the first thing we see is already that it shows us here the dimensions on top and
it tells us how many dimensions there are and also how many discretization points each
dimension has.
So in this case, we have four dimensions or effectively three because time only has one
value.
one value. So it's effectively a three-dimensional data set. And we can see now there's multiple
things in this data set. So we have the coordinates here, which are then explicitly mentioned with
their name and also the type and also the values. We have the data variables, which then, if you
scroll further down, exactly. So here we have the data variables which are in this data set. So
one important point is we can group together multiple data arrays, or in this case,
these data variables into one coherent data set, and these can be then data which is then
from zero to four dimensions, and it shows us here along which dimensions these values
are measured.
Yeah, so I see here we've actually loaded in seven NumPy arrays, but these seven NumPy
arrays, they are related to each other, because you see that I have two arrays, but I see
their dimensions, they have the same names. So the dimension in one array is probably like matches
the dimension in some other array. And so all these arrays are now tied together. I think we even
now have a nice example of this. So yeah, so officially our data was four-dimensional,
but we only had one time point. So let's say it's actually three-dimensional, three dimensions
actually matter. And of course, the role NumPy array is just a block of numbers. So that's
now our blue thing. But I see that with X array, we can annotate this array and say,
okay, well, but this dimension, this is our X coordinates in kilometers. And even every
step in this dimension, let's maybe call this columns. Every column has a name or, well,
a name, a value associated to it. And then we have the same. So if we go up this dimension,
this is the, I don't have to call it the third dimension or the second dimension, I could
just call it, hey, this is the isobaric pressure dimension. This dimension encodes isobaric
pressure. And this has a unit even assigned to it in, what is HPA, I don't know, Pascal
or something.
Yeah, Heid Pascal, I assume, right?
Pascal, yeah. And it gives me like the numbers for each. So now, instead of just having a
block of numbers, this block of numbers now is put into a certain context. It describes
temperature at certain heights and the heights are indexed by something and it's located
somewhere on this actual planet earth of ours and we can index it by actually giving it the
locations on the earth or where do we want this data. All right, so let's give that a try.
So maybe you talk me through it. Yeah, so we can now. So now can we slice up this data? How do I
I select pressure data from this?
So if you want to take the pressure data,
or like in this case, we have the temperature data,
you can access each data variable
the same as you did in Pandas.
So it's this kind of syntax that is similar to dictionaries.
So we can do day s, and then we use
the name of the variable in these square brackets.
And that will then return the data array.
So it only is this one data variable,
but it still contains all the other metadata
that you've seen before.
So if you print this out, there's probably a typo.
Yeah.
Temperature data.
Exactly.
Let's get this out of the way a little bit.
Okay, so now I've selected, yeah,
because we saw we had seven NumPy arrays in there,
seven X-arrays in the dataset.
We've now selected one of them, the temperature.
Yeah, and I can see it's a four-dimensional array.
All the dimensions have names.
And even coordinates. Okay, so now we have temperature. Okay, cool.
Can we slice this up now even further?
Yes, so we can select now specific data out of this data array by using the SEL method.
And in this case, we can specify the exact value at which we want to get the data from.
So remember in NumPy, we had to use an index, which is really unintuitive since we don't really
care about which position in the array this data is stored, but we can actually get it by its
physical position, which is much more useful. Yeah, so instead of having to index like this,
we're now going to index like this. I can index with a name, like okay, I want the selection of the
data where our x-coordinate is a certain number, and this is in kilometers. Yes, and you can
see now also that the dimensionality has changed, so the x-variable has now, or the x-dimension has
disappeared, or like it's only one's value. If you look up there, then you can see it's now
it's a 2D array, effectively. So now I only have Y subarachnothyme left there.
Sorry, why is this a string? I'm now confused by this.
It's the way how the coordinate stores the values. So in this case, if I remember correctly,
if it's sorted strings.
Right, every...
Oh, no, actually, yes.
Every name was a string.
Do coordinates, so the coordinates,
do they always have to be strings, or?
I'm not entirely sure how it does it under the hood,
but it kind of casts it into floats that I don't know,
but we can quickly test it.
I'm not sure where it would work.
We'll test it later when we create our own.
For now, the coordinates are strings.
We can also use the index by using ISEL instead of SEL, so ISEL.
Right, so if we actually wanted to do, because sometimes in algorithms and things we do want
to index by number, so just give me the first x-coordinate and I don't know actually what
sort of string label that was, but just give me the first one.
And it's actually the second one since it still uses the
numpy, sorry, the Python dimension.
Yeah, exactly. Yeah, this is the second one.
Okay, so we can do it both ways.
That is useful. Okay, now we come to the real
power of X-Array, and this is that we can use now these
functionality along dimensions by name.
So we have here as an example sum, mean, median, the minimum, the maximum, and so on.
There is more to it, but these are maybe the most common ones.
And what you've just typed now, we now calculate the mean along a certain dimension.
Which in NumPy, if you would want to do the same thing, it would be really cumbersome
because we would have to use the mean function, the NumPy.mean function, and then specify the axis.
Like axis. Now I have to remember which one was the
pressure axis, and I don't remember. I think it was axis two or something.
But they don't have to, because I can just now say, well, give me the isobaric mean along
the isobaric axis, and we'll do so.
Exactly.
Yeah.
Okay.
And which is also super min-max.
All the standard NumPy array stuff is there, it's supported.
Yeah, so the plotting is also one thing we should mention quickly.
Yeah, let's show, because we have that.
as pandas, it was not really mandem, but pandas has some rudimentary plotting features. So
is X-Ray. So there's a dumb plot and that allows me to do some rudimentary plotting
to say, okay, so this is actually a slice we've now selected along the X. So now we
have height and the Y-coordinate still and we see the temperature plotted here. So we
and we can quickly pop like different things.
And note that you didn't have to specify
any of the plotting, the labels at each,
here at each axis, or all of this was,
is the met information that the dataset already has,
and then the plotting function takes all this data
and puts it into the figure.
So this is maybe not the type of figure
that you want to include in your publication,
but if you quickly want to have a look
at the data for data analysis,
or quickly check whether you set up the right slice
and so on, this is extremely handy.
And it also, if you scroll further down,
we will see that also it detects
the dimensionality automatically.
So now if we choose,
where we also specify the Y position,
we will get now a 1D box.
Yeah.
So if we quickly do that.
You get that.
So now it just draws it as a line
because now it's one dimensional data.
It makes sense to draw as a line, no longer as a figure,
and no longer as a heat map.
Yeah, and it's filled in all the dimensions,
like all the annotations that the X-ray had,
all the labels and all the coordinates and everything.
It's all there, so.
Okay.
So I think...
So there was one question in the HedgeDog document
about 3D plots.
So if you have data which has more than two dimensions,
then x-array will interpret it as a histogram.
And this is actually also included here in the document.
Oh, okay, so let's show it.
Okay, yeah, so what if we just plot
the entire three-dimensional array?
What does x-array do then?
Aha!
It will give us, indeed, a histogram.
The histogram of all the various values in there.
How do I interpret this histogram?
Yeah, it's all, yeah, it's showing
distribution of all the values of the data set.
Very often, at least when I was working with data and I got a histogram
but it was not what I wanted and it turned out that I haven't really
understood how to apply it or like which dimension I wanted to follow.
But it does tell us something. It tells that there seems to be
a sort of a binary distribution here. There's some
values here and some values there, so there are probably two hot spots.
Okay, but I think it's time for a first exercise.
So we've now shown how to load data.
We've quickly shown how to select some of the data.
We've quickly shown how to plot something.
So now for this exercise, we're going to turn it over to you and do a simple exercise with
it.
So load this data set, select some data and call the plot on it, just to give you a taste
of what it is like to work with X-Ray.
Let's give them...
One.
Sorry.
Yeah, since...
Yeah, sorry.
I'll let you finish.
There's just one comment I wanted to give
since in the hash document, there was a question.
Oh, okay.
But maybe we can get to it, but that's why I want...
If you want to do the exercise, we have to do it now.
You have until, I think, 55.
Let's come back at 1455 here.
And we'll discuss the question and we'll wrap up, we'll show you some final things, but first let's do the exercise.
So, I will see you back here in seven minutes.
you
And welcome back everybody. I hope you all managed to do this exercise, and otherwise
we will leave it as homework, but we have to carry on. We have a few more minutes left
and there's a few more things we would like to show you. So, [name], why don't you talk
me through it. So we have now got an overview of how to use X-Array to work with data but of course
probably the most important thing for you is if you want to use X-Array how do you transfer your
own data into an X-Array data set and the syntax for that is now shown here where we create it
with the xset.dataset method here and this then contains the data variables that we can pass into
the data set. And these are typically non-player arrays. So in this case we have pressure and
humidity as an example and we have to coordinate. And in addition to that we can also give attributes
which is like metadata which doesn't really fit into the format of the remaining data. So this
can be for instance the time that the measurement was taken, if it's a simulation data it could be
the compiler and the software version that you use for running the simulation. So you can basically
keep all this extra information that you typically always want to have close by in these attributes.
In this case we have here simply a 2D dataset and of course you need to you have to make sure that
the dimensionality fits. So if you then create your own dataset at some point you will get
some weird errors if the data you try to glue together has different dimensions. So this is
is maybe the hardest thing to get that right at the beginning.
But I mean, I shouldn't say hard because I wouldn't say it's hard. It's just like
one of the typical sampling blocks at the beginning.
So if we do, let me run this just to show that this works.
Okay, so now I've created my own data set with this.
Yeah, and we have time, we have location, so we have two-dimensional data.
And we have two variables here now in our data set, and they're linked together.
So we have a pressure array with humidity array, and they both have two dimensions,
time and location, and they are the same ones.
So X-Ray knows that they are the same.
We should mention how to transfer data from X-Ray to NumPy, Pandas, or like a binary format.
This X-Array is built on top of Pandas and NumPy.
It's really easy to convert the data,
and it's shown here how to do this.
So the NumPy arrays can simply be accessed
by typing dot values after the data array,
but there's also a toNumPy method
if you prefer to use that.
And similarly for data frames,
there's a pull-down to that as well.
That's interesting.
I want to try this one.
Okay, so that actually gave me a data frame in tidy data format, as we saw in the last
lesson.
And then NetCDF is really handy if you have very large data sets, since NetCDF is a binary
format.
So, I've used that mostly when I was working with gigabytes of data from simulations.
So there was actually a question there about this.
What is X-Array the same as NetCDF or is it built on top of it?
It's built on top.
It uses NetCDF as a backend and it's really easy to store the data as NetCDF and load
NETCDF files but it adds additional functionality like group by, masking and all sorts of things
that pandas for instance does like x-ray builds that on top of NETCDF. So basically we actually
have the best profiles of NETCDF and pandas. And just a quick comment, there was someone
on running into an issue of NetCDF not being installed.
If you install NetCDF, the Python library
with Conda, Mamba, whatever you use,
it will be automatically detected on the deploy run.
Yeah.
Just a comment to this one question we received.
Yes, there are multiple backends to this.
So with that, we come to the end of this session.
We have barely scratched the surface of what XRA can do.
It's a pretty large library.
It can do a lot of things.
And there's a lot more to explore.
So we've included an exercise number two,
which you can do in your own time
to explore a little bit more about X-ray.
And otherwise, I think it's time to move on.
Thank you a lot, [name].
Yeah, well, thank you.
Thanks for joining everyone.