CodeRefinery.org
you
Test, test, hello, can anyone hear us out there?
Let's see, I think we should be audible.
Yes, I could hear you.
Okay, that's good. Okay.
Good.
So hello everyone, welcome to day two.
Let's scroll this down a little bit.
So we have the notes here open as usual.
If you're new and you're registered,
you should have this page.
Here there's a link to the archive.
So basically all the questions from yesterday are put there,
and you can keep reading them.
And then here is the feedback from yesterday that will eventually be archived.
If we keep scrolling down to the bottom, we get to day 2, and we have some initial stuff.
So yeah, we've got questions.
So the way this works is if you, if the statement, let's see, if you want to vote for a statement,
O there, and we make this sort of live bar graph. So, yeah, what's the plan for... Actually,
let's wait a few minutes before we talk about the plan for the day, so more people can arrive.
Let's answer these questions ourselves, together. Here we have a lot of the day's
instructors. So, how big is the data use with Python?
Depends. It even depends on what you consider data. So, yeah, we have some
large language models which are huge. I have seen and handled datasets with terabytes
of data, but it really depends. It can also be as small as a megabyte or less, you know,
just processing some small stuff. Yeah. Okay. Who else is here? [name], how big of data have
you dealt with? Well, recently, I was dealing with this kind of Retriever Augmented Generation
project for using large language models. The data was about 20 gigabytes plus or minus 10
gigabytes, let's say, or plus 10 gigabytes. So it was like about 30 gigabytes of data.
So, a relevant amount, let's say, if you don't want to crash your computer,
you don't want to load it all at once. But, of course, it can be smaller as well.
Yeah. [name], how big of data do you use, or what's the most?
So typically it's, yeah, I will answer both.
So my maybe most frequent use of data with Python
is below one megabyte.
It's often short CSV files, comma separated values.
Sometimes it's more than,
sometimes it can be like gigabytes,
but I never went like beyond like 10 gigabyte.
And about what's the most chaotic data,
so one line I answered there is like messy data
and messy meaning that either some sort of missing values,
so data that needs to be cleaned,
values that are missing or that are not ideal format
or the date is not in, I don't know,
year, year, year, year, month, month, day, day,
but it's in something else
and you need to then do something with the data.
So that's what I was dealing with.
How about you, [name]?
Hmm, I mean, I guess a lot of the data I deal with is small, but occasionally, like right now I have a data directory of 15 gigabytes, no, 15 terabytes, that's social media data and it has the original data and pre-processed in different formats put into databases and
It's all with Python, but definitely the time factor is the limiting thing here.
And the most chaotic is, to me, is mostly things where the data formats the data is
stored in is just completely inappropriate, like, before we went online, a model that
was provided as a PDF, which is kind of, okay, great.
Do I now have to type down that PDF
or how do I process that?
Yeah.
One of the most chaotic datas that I've seen
is probably my old data that I did
when I was doing my master's.
So, because over there, like the situation was
that I was like constantly doing new things
for folder to get the data. And it was constantly evolving. So
and of course, I didn't have any versioning scheme I didn't have
I didn't use. I didn't think about using even pandas to
manage like, like get out like a table of what data I have with
what versions I've done. So what you end up with is the dashes
underscore scheme of having the different files managed. So suddenly you end up with a huge amount
of files, huge amount of folders. Then I ended up targeting those folders up and then I have like,
I think it was like something like 30 gigabytes of data that is like
entire folders. So if I need to get access to a one file from one thing, I need to unpack a whole
tar for all to get a hold of that. And I would do things differently now. If I would choose to do
the same project again, I definitely would not do the choices I have done. But that happens when
you're living at the moment. You're solving one thing at a time instead of looking at the bigger
picture. Yeah. So, are we learning today all the lessons you wish you had known?
when you started your work?
Well, I don't think we can encapsulate all of that
but hopefully the best practices are
what's at the end.
It's definitely a course that I wish I had when I started
with Python. Just when you also mentioned Pandas, Pandas is a library
that I also wish I had known
And I wish, like this is something we might bring up later, but I really wish I would
have understood that, hey, like these data management or data, like these tools, they
can be used for things that are not like, let's say, big data, like you can keep track
of your workflow.
Okay.
Like what simulations have I done?
let's make a table out of it instead of just have a big folder with all of the
different parameters specified there. So, to use the same tools that I would have used for
the analysis to do the housekeeping, I definitely would have benefited from that. But I didn't,
because I thought that, okay, these are different tools. These are not tools for management of,
let's say, like I made this and stuff like that.
So has everyone here had the not invented here syndrome
when you started work?
Which basically is, OK, existing tools don't exist.
I'm going to recreate everything from scratch myself,
or almost from scratch, and not using good stuff.
Because I know I certainly had a lot of that.
Admittedly, I still sometimes have.
I mean, the main reason why I often
tend to somewhat reinvent the wheel
is because the wheel that I find online
has exactly not the feature that I want,
and about 20 other features.
And when I'm taking that wheel, I
need to essentially remodel a lot of things
to have my feature present.
Yeah.
Okay.
Fair enough.
Also, I mean, there's something pedagogical
about when you're starting off,
making sure you understand it well enough to do it yourself.
But anyway, it's 10 o'clock now.
So maybe before we all go,
we can give a summary of what we can expect from today.
So the first session is working with data.
So [name] and [name], how would you describe this?
We will, I think, mainly give an overview
of what are benefits of certain data formats.
To consider when storing, loading, and working with data.
And yeah, that's, I think, the main theme of this session.
Okay, and then we have-
in the second session.
Go ahead.
Yeah.
So then right after we will talk about data visualization
and we will demonstrate it using a library
called Vega out there.
And I will also demotivate why we do that,
but it will nicely interface to the discussion about data,
but also to the Pandas lesson from yesterday.
So it will be a library that will very nicely interface
to tabular data.
Yeah.
OK.
Then is our lunch break.
And then we have scripts.
So [name], what's the motivation there?
Up until that point, we are mainly
working with Jupyter Notebooks.
And one issue with Jupyter Notebooks
is that they tend to be dependent on the state
that you currently have.
So if you rerun a Jupyter Notebook,
they might, you might end up with a different result
because you started somewhere else,
or you run, in your previous time,
you ran some cell in between that didn't think about it.
And putting things into scripts,
putting things more into functionalities,
encapsulates these and allows you to run those
in a non-interactive way, for example, on clusters,
if you have to run this a couple of thousand times and so on.
So, yeah, yeah, good.
Yeah, let's go on, not take too much time.
Okay, then profiling and Python productivity tools.
So.
Oh, yeah, right.
So that will be again us, so it will be [name] and me.
We will introduce a couple of really nice tools
to profile Python in order to find out
where is most memory spent,
where is most CPU spent,
we will have a discussion about
when to optimize, how to optimize.
And then also introduce a couple of tools that
like for auto-formatting, linting,
we will explain what that means
and also have a short discussion about AI assisted coding.
Yeah, okay.
So with that being said,
let's head to working with data with [name] and [name].
and [name]. So, I will switch to your screen, I hope, and see you later. Bye.
Okay, then let's start working with data. In general, we want to kind of address the
questions how you store your data, how to clean up data and pre-processing and learning some
drawbacks of and benefits of common data formats that are being used
and how to most easily or most efficiently read write data in a different variety of formats.
And I personally like this xkcd quite a lot because it somewhat encapsulates the problem
of data scientists where but I did send you the data and it's really like yeah but that is a data
data format that is completely unusable.
This is a Word document containing embedded photo
you took off your screen with a spreadsheet open.
But that's how we normally do it.
Doesn't your computer use these type of files?
Maybe you need an update.
And it just encapsulates the problem that
in some fields or in collaboration with some parties,
you just get data that is in a very specific format that is used by one tool that's common
in this field but that's potentially even a proprietary format that you normally or often
just can't really use. Then you need to find a way to actually make it usable.
So I think first we want to kind of go a bit over what are the different things we are talking about.
what is a data format? And here already format can kind of mean two different things. It can either
be the data structure, so how you're storing the data in memory while you're working on it,
or how you're storing the data on the disk. And that's two different things that are essentially
considered as the kind of same with the same name and that often also leads to some confusion.
and an example could be a simple data frame with various different columns.
So you have a data set that consists of strings, timestamps, integers and floats.
And how is this data then stored in memory? It's one potential thing that you might need
need to consider for efficiency of operations.
And this data frame already is structured
in a so-called tidy data format, where tidy means that we have
multiple columns of data that are somewhat collected
and where each column represents a value of a specific type.
So we can at least be sure that anything that's in this column
is of this type.
and that allows us to run several operations
more efficiently because we can apply the same operation
to all elements of one column at the same time.
You can think of this in a sense,
like if you have like a toolbox,
let's say you have a toolbox
that has lots of different screws around,
like you put the different kinds of screws
into different boxes.
So you have different compartments in the whole box that you have the different kinds
of screws around so that you know that you will always find these kinds of screws in
one box.
So it's basically like you have many different kinds of things, but they're all stored in
this one big box, which is the data frame.
And essentially, if you think about that screw box,
if you would have some screw in the wrong box,
that can be really annoying
if you are just grabbing a few to do something
and then notice, oh, this is useless,
this was in the wrong box.
So having this tidy data format
allows you to work a lot more efficiently, essentially.
And here's another example of a data structure
that is relatively common,
data array from NumPy and we have a two-dimensional array of numbers and that's somewhat different to
a data frame because now we know the type of data in this array so each individual element of it
is of a certain type and the advantage of this is that we can pretty efficiently store that data in
memory because we know that each element has a specific type thus a specific size and if it's
if the type actually has a certain number of bytes that it's always being stored in
then we can even pre-allocate the whole memory for for this specific data structure and we can
very easily jump to different places in memory because they are directly, they are clear from
the indices. While for example in a data frame you could still have something that has a different
size like a string. Strings are inherently of different sizes and you might need to first look
up okay where is this string actually stored and then go to that location while in a numerical
array, you can directly go to the position where the data is in the end, and you can also load that
quite easily. If this sounds quite abstract to you, to bring it back to reality, if you remember
from yesterday's sessions, when we talked about NumPy, why is NumPy so fast? It's fast because
underneath the hood, it's C and Fortran. Underneath the hood of all the NumPy functions,
the C and Fortran there. And same with the X-array, for example, that we also demonstrated
yesterday, that used these kinds of blocks. So in X-array, all of the stuff was in NumPy arrays
inside of it, where there's big blocks of these numbers. And because the numbers are all the same
type, they pertain to the same variable. So they are related to a certain variable. It's very easy
to calculate let's say a mean or histogram or let's say calculate like matrix products or
something like that or dot products because those algorithms can be written now
with C and Fortran for these like fast things. So if you have this kind of like uniform data that
is stored as a cube it's very easy to write an algorithm in C that let's say calculates the
mean for it. But if you have it all over the place, it's much harder and that makes it less
efficient. So when you have this kind of like data that can be represented as this kind of like a
cube, let's say like temperatures at different coordinate locations or whatever, then you can
also write efficient algorithms that can calculate quantities from this data. So the data and the
algorithms are and the calculations are like intimately interlinked and the speed of the
like the stuff is intimately interlinked how it's stored in the memory.
Essentially by knowing the type and knowing the structure yeah you you essentially get around
having to having to have a look kind of lookup table where each element is stored.
Now, the question is, can the data be saved to disk without changing the data format?
So can we have an efficient data storage of this data?
Because that would make it a lot more efficient to also load this data because we can essentially
directly read this from disk into memory and we don't need to reorder and allocate different
places in memory and so on.
And that's where we have this data type
versus data structure versus file format question.
And commonly we say that the data type
is the type of a single piece of data,
so one integer, one float,
the kind of atomic units
that we have in a computer
or the basic data types.
Then we have a data structure
that's, for example, an umpire array or a data frame
where this is how it's stored logically within our program
and where this data structure gives us
certain options how to access it.
And then we have the file format where this data structure
needs to be stored to disk in some way.
And that's essentially the question,
how do we get this done in an efficient way?
For example, for images,
you have essentially an array of images
if it's black and white, of black or white values
for each individual pixel.
And you can have that as a n times n array.
If you have a multi-color picture,
you would have multiple of those arrays, potentially.
So what to look for in a file format?
What do you want to use here?
Well, you should remember the following.
There is no file format that is good for every use case.
So even if you have something
that is really, really convenient,
there will be cases where this is not the best format
to store data in.
However, it's also very likely that there is a good format
already existing for your use case.
And based on that, don't try to build a new file format just because, because then you
end up with the situation that is described in this XKCD, where you have a couple of formats
that are commonly used in the field, and then someone says, oh, it's ridiculous that there
are so many, we should all use one file format, I will design the perfect file format.
and what comes out of it is really just,
yep, there's one more file format that is being used.
So it gets more messy.
Standardization is great,
but to get a standard really accepted,
it has to come from the community.
And you have to have enough people saying,
saying, yeah, okay, we will only use this in the future to slowly but surely drop other
formats in the field.
And that's a whole new thing of a whole new project on its own.
So usually like these kinds of formats, they arrive as a solution to a problem.
you have a problem and somebody notices that, hey, we cannot communicate in the internet
effectively. We cannot send information from one place to another. And then JSON is born
as a format for communicating message, basically sending stuff between different web endpoints and
and this kind of like standards, they just appear because people realize that, hey,
I cannot understand what this other service or thing is doing because we don't speak the
same language. And that solves a problem, but then that problem might not be your problem.
Your use case might have a different problem and that might be solved by a different thing.
So it's always like it's impossible to have one thing that solves everything and every time
somebody tries to do this it usually ends up in failure. And also one thing to I think remember
here is that they essentially with all kind of communication patterns if you go to a certain
common format you very often also lose something in the on the way that your original code was
able to do that this format does not support. So having common standards always comes with
compromises like so many things. So if you look for a file format what do you need to consider?
So, I think, yeah, the most important that it is good for the data structure that you
currently have, so that you, this, but this again also depends on the use case, whether
this is the most important, this is very important, so in some, in some situations, reading and
writing files can be very important, so having an efficient data structure that is easy,
that is fast in being read and fast in being written is, can be very important, but it
can also be completely irrelevant. That really depends on the use case. Is there a recommended
format? So is there a de facto standard for your field of work? Then it's very likely
that it's best using that format. Is it necessary that humans can actually look into the file
and understand what it's doing?
Or is it something that where you could say,
well, no human needs to look at this.
This can be completely binary.
And when we talk about human read,
like in this case,
like nobody just goes and look at the bytes
in the computer disk of memory.
What we mean is that you can open it with an editor.
Yeah, like you can open it with typical tools.
Like you can view it with the file viewer
and you see what's in there.
Like it's a text, yeah, it's written,
encoded in text basically, like [name] said.
So human readable here means that instead of like
being just bytes that you need like special tools to open.
And I think the last is to me,
one of the most important questions,
is this something that I want to share
where I want others to use it
or is this just a temporary storage for preprocessing,
processing, checkpointing, or something like that.
So, Pandas or other libraries often support
quite a large variety of different formats.
Pandas supports a lot of tidy formats,
but even some non-tidy formats,
and I can convert it, we will be coming to that later.
NumPy supports a couple of different formats for array data,
but there are many other formats that can be used
other libraries. And here's a very, very short thing of formats that are commonly used. And
we actually, just by looking at it, I'm already seeing some things that I'm somewhat missing,
like YAML instead of JSON, which is relatively similar. But this is just a kind of an overview
table of what formats can be useful for what kind of data transfer. And to very quickly
go over that, so PQL is essentially the binary dump from Python that comes with the benefit
of it's, you can essentially dump almost anything.
The problem with that is that wherever you load this,
you have to have the same libraries.
Otherwise you can end up with corrupt stuff
because it assumes that the environment
that it's loading it into is the same
as the environment that created it.
So it's a bit frickle.
CSV, I think everyone knows comma separated value files, is
human readable format, is a textual format, and convenient
for a lot of data transfer or just a quick visual inspection
by humans.
Federer is, I can quickly say the next two, like Federer is a
format that is designed for this like inter-process
communication. So it's, it's, it uses this Apache arrow kind of
like ID. So it's for tidy data, but it's meant for like, how you
can communicate stuff from let's say, Python to R very
effective, effectively, so that, like, you can use the same, get
the same data, exact same data to load on a different process.
And then you can, like, continue working on in a different
process and then move it back around.
Part K is a bit of a bigger format that it's
mainly used to store a huge amount of data,
so it's a big data format.
It's this file format that is commonly used to store
in big data in this columnar format,
like a tidy data format,
but really for big data,
and it's highly used in world data sciences.
And NPI is the NumPy file format, HDF5 is another binary format for, I think, also tabular data.
No, no, HDF5 is for big arrays, but it stores, basically, it's a hierarchical file format.
So, it basically has lots of folders inside of it.
of it. And NetCDF uses HDF5, and we talked about that in the X-array yesterday, but it basically
creates a certain kind of like structure inside the HDF5 that you find the same things in the
same places, coordinates, times, and so forth. But overall, there's more in-depth description
of all of these file formats that can be found on the page that we've linked here,
where all of them are explained in a lot more detail and what they can and partially cannot do.
I'll quickly add also what [name] mentioned about YAMLs, that this also applies to, let's say,
configuration files. If you're writing a configuration file for your machine learning
project or whatever, you want to store parameters into configuration files. We'll talk about
configuration files more in the script section, but there people are also using standards or
they, well, everybody has their own, but people are using different kinds of configuration files.
Some people use XML, some use JSON, some use YAML, but anyways, they usually use
these most common formats and some use any files as well, because you already have existing tools
that can read these files. So it's much easier to manage like configurations for your simulations.
So do also remember that those are also like important because they save a lot of work if you
use already existing formats. But I think most important is that you understand a bit of
what are the pros and cons of the two major kind of types of formats. Binary formats versus
textual formats. Binary formats have the real benefit of, they represent for example floating
point numbers with full precision. So you store the floating point number in a binary format,
you don't have to convert into a textual format where there is a certain cutoff. So you are always
rounding to a certain position or it gets really really huge. It can
potentially by doing that save a lot of space because the storage is more
efficient. Data reading and writing is coming a lot faster because often the
data can be directly transferred into memory and memory allocation can be done
a lot more efficiently because we know what kind of data is coming in and we
you do not need to read on and see what is going to happen.
They can provide you with a more explicit specification
for storing multiple datasets
and their metadata in the same file
and making that read-write more efficient.
I think one of the biggest benefits for binary formats,
especially in heavy computation,
is that they often allow you to partially load data.
Because if you know how the data is structured,
if you know that, okay, this is a huge array of numbers,
you can say, okay, I want position whatever
and up to position, up to the next one,
and load only that block into memory.
And I don't need to go through all of it
to see when do I reach that point,
but I can directly jump to that point on the disk.
And that makes it a lot more efficient to,
for example, also do things like memory mapping,
where you essentially tell the operating system that,
yeah, this file is another bit of memory,
and it's not as efficient as memory itself,
but reasonably efficient for getting the data
and getting parts of the data.
The disadvantages is that often you need some specific library to read and write the data.
While this is handled if you have certain standard file formats,
it can still be problematic if that file format doesn't have support in some programming language,
and then you are somewhat stuck.
If it's a proprietary format for a,
or a format that is binary,
but for a specific library
that can be dependent on the library version.
So it might not be,
it might be that what you just stored
cannot be used in two years
or cannot be used with the latest version in two years.
They are not human readable.
So it's almost impossible to investigate
what's actually in that file unless you read it in.
Sharing can, therefore, be a bit more difficult.
And it might require additional documentation efforts.
But in the end, the last point is, yeah,
you should do that anyways, even if you have a textual format.
The advantage of textual formats is really,
the huge advantage is it's human-readable.
You can look at that file and understand,
okay, this is what's in there.
It's easy to, or relatively easy to check for errors
in the data itself because you can look at it.
It's either supported by many tools
or you can easily write something to read the data in
and it's relatively easily shared.
Disadvantages, it's very slow or comparatively slow to read and write because you have to
read through it and you don't know what's going to be there.
It potentially increases disk space usage a lot if you need to use multiple bytes instead
of one byte for certain data or represent it properly.
As we mentioned, it's prone to losing precision for floating point numbers.
Multidimensional data is often difficult to represent and if you have data where the data
format can be specified, the data structure might not be clear when you start to read
the data, so it's just potentially more difficult to use from the computational side.
One thing that I tend to think of is really this, how am I going to use this? Is this
something where I really start more as a checkpointing, as a temporary format, then I'm almost always
is going to go for binary formats
because they are more efficient.
If this is something that is my final results,
I am more likely to use some kind of textual format
because it is easier for others to see or to understand it.
I think, given the time, we will skip the exercise here.
[name], do you want to go over this?
Yeah, I don't know.
Yeah, we're quite tight on time, so I don't know.
I think Erano mentioned that we are allowed
to go over time a little bit.
OK, so maybe I could quickly go through an example of how
does this happens in practice.
This is kind of stuff that can happen in practice.
Do you have a Jupyter open, [name]?
No, not at the moment.
Okay, I wonder, could I take a share
or should I just explain what's happening here?
Maybe.
I think explaining in this way.
Yeah, maybe explaining in this time, time scalers.
So let's consider that we want to,
like, it's a bit unfortunate we cannot view the data,
how it looks, maybe.
Yeah, so, well, you can try this on your own Jupyter, like running the example and viewing
what the contrast is, and you just have to trust me, bro, on what the data looks like.
So as an example of like, what can happen if you don't like, what sort of things can
happen if you don't go through, you don't necessarily think about what is the data format
and how can you convert it into the format that you want to use.
So let's say we want data from this JSON or this API endpoint that provides information
about countries.
And if you run the first commands there, it will produce you a JSON file, and the JSON
when we call the JSON loads,
it will load it into a Python dictionary, basically.
So it's a list of dictionaries for each country, basically.
So each country is represented by a dictionary that has various values.
So it's basically very deep.
And this is very common for, let's say, JSON files,
that you have multiple layers of deep going on.
And if we want to ask a question from this data, okay, you got it, got one open, yeah.
If you want to...
I just need to...
Oops, that's the wrong thing.
Yeah, that helps.
So, if you want to ask a question from this data, okay, like what country has the most
population?
The...
Yeah, sorry about this.
Sorry.
Yeah, no.
Yeah.
So if we, do you want to close the sidebar on the JupyterLab?
A bit more space.
You can press the folder on the left side.
Yeah, right.
Yeah.
So, the data, if you type the country's JSON over there, we can view what is the data.
So we have this sort of stuff, and this is, of course, not tied in any way, or it's not
organized in columns.
But this is something that you might see quite often.
And what you might first think of writing, to answer a question, you might quote something
like this.
So this is a questionable way of solving the problem, which country has the most population.
So basically we for loop over the whole structure, we check if the population is bigger, and
And then we like, if it's bigger than, like, which one, like, if it's bigger than the previous
biggest, then we, we mark it, yeah.
And then we get, but this, like, if you run it, run the code, this will of course, like
go through the whole data and it will throw out all of the rest of the data.
And it will only answer this one question.
And we had to write a lot of code to do this.
So now our data analysis, of course, this might look very natural, but once we have to do this
again and again, it gets super complicated quite quickly. Another option that often I see
is that you could pick a few columns from the data and then append them to a list and then
used at least to create the data frame. That's already like a better solution in a sense that
you get a data frame at the end, so you get something out of it. But if you look a bit
deeper in the documentation of pandas, there's like two functions at least. So there's this
So if you want to run the JSON normalize one, for example,
that basically load the whole thing in
and make it into a tidy data set.
So there's two options here, but the JSON normalize,
it basically goes through the depth of the whole JSON
and it will create you a nice data set.
So if you want to now view the country's data frame
and what it looks like,
you can do that by clicking on this button here.
Yeah, so this is a bit of a quick demo, but now we loaded everything.
We didn't only check the population, what is the maximum population, we just got everything
in one line of code.
And this is the question, like again, a thing that happens quite often, like there are usually
tools that people have written because they have encountered the same problem.
And quite often, if you end up writing these large pieces of code that basically go through
data and they shuffle around and they pick the relevant pieces of data from a data set,
and then they are collected into a grab bag of stuff, basically like all you eat buffet
and collect it into a plate, like all kinds of stuff, then what happens is that the big
picture is lost and what the data actually represents is lost and you lose most of the
data.
But most of the time, there are tools that can immediately do all of this for you and
make it into a tidy dataset or like, let's say, a NumPy array, like a big dataset that
can then view all of the data from different angles. You can look at different checks and
you can view the data as a whole instead of like this complicated list. So this is just a demo,
maybe a bit scuffed one, because it's quite a new one. But now we could save this as a CSV
or a parquet or feather or something. And now it would be in a tidy format if you want to save this
data. So these kind of data conversions, when we take data and then we convert it into another
structure, it's usually a good idea to stop and think for a second, what do I want to do with
this data and what format would best represent the data? Is it best represented by the JSON
format or is it best represented as a table? Because the same data is in both formats.
It's just a question of, okay, did I convert it into another one?
And usually there are tools to do this conversion for you.
So I think as an overall thing to remember from this lecture, there is no file format
that is good for every use case.
Depending on your use case, it really depends what kind of file format you want to use.
Basically your research question determines what libraries you use and therefore also
to some extent what formats you're going to use.
It's commonly good to use a previously existing framework or data format and you should prioritize
that and use the formats that are common in your field instead of inventing something
new.
always a good idea to have a look around when you start a project. What are the data formats that
are being used? Can I already clean up my initial data so that it's being that it's easier to use
later on? Store it potentially in an efficient format if I need to reprocess it a lot of times
and thereby save a bit of time. If you have this cleanup as a script you can
reuse that script and you can reuse that even on new data. It's good to
have important data also in a human readable format. It depends a bit
on, this is a bit tricky because it sometimes depends a bit on how precise your data needs to be.
So sometimes a human readable format might not be a good idea if you are working with numerical
data and you need a very high precision. But at least the data that doesn't necessarily need
need high precision or can be represented in a precise way in the
human readable format, it's always a good idea to have that also in a human readable
format to have an easy inspection. And finally, when you are done, provide the
data that you have in a format that is easily used by other people and that
commonly means by formats commonly used in your field. Even if they are not
necessarily the best formats. You could for example think about I will be providing this
both as a CSV and also in a binary format so that if someone really wants to get the
exact things they can use the exact stuff while the CSV will be something that most
people can use because it's commonly used in my field. So yeah I think with that we should
hand over to [name]. Yes, definitely. We'll try to answer all the questions in the chat.
There were lots of great questions. We'll try to add there an answer. But now we are
going to hear a lot about plotting. Yeah, thanks a lot for this. Just give me a second
to take over the screen share here. Just a moment. Here we go. And so thanks a lot for
the session. Hi, everybody. Good morning. My name is [name] and we will stay in of course
in Python, but we will also stay in with data.
how the screen share is only black.
This is the first time this has happened.
Do you want to try re-sharing?
Yes, let me try that.
So technical difficulties, please stand by.
Of course, we have tested this.
but give me one more attempt here.
In the meantime, there's lots of good questions
about the data processing stuff here,
or working with data.
And I guess the other instructor,
[name] and [name] will go through and do more.
And yeah, the screen's still completely black.
Is it still black?
that's fascinating yeah this is it worked earlier today when we were
preparing hmm is this some privacy thing that zoom okay just a sec here is the
still black or anything change no still black and it doesn't show your name as
the person whose screen is being shared so. Should I rejoin? Is there any other instructor
here that can try sharing screen to make sure it's not? Can you stop the share and restart
maybe? Yeah. So I stopped it. Sorry for the problems. Right now what you're seeing is
the notes that's shared from my computer, not [name]'s computer. So, yeah.
So should I try a reshare? I guess so. I actually have my other computer joined here.
So it looks pretty normal on my side here. Okay, I have two computers that are showing
black. Is anyone else in the instructor Zoom? Can you comment on what you see?
Only black as well. Do you want somebody else to share the screen and run the try?
Yeah, I guess [name] could give it a try. If [name] can...
Okay. Yeah, so someone has the idea we could have a break now and then resume
10 minutes. I propose we do the break now.
Good. Okay, yeah, so I'll update the notes and see you in 10 minutes and hopefully
we solve it until then. Yeah, okay, sounds good. See you. Bye.
you
Hello, we are back.
Hi, everybody.
Welcome back from the break and in the meantime, we found a workaround.
I'm now hopefully sharing and you can hopefully see it and it's hopefully not
just black. And we might adjust a little bit the sizing. So [name], my co-instructor
here, will tell me if I need to add a little bit of space on the left or on
top just that nothing is cut off. It should be made a little bit narrower.
Okay let's do that. Yeah that's probably good. Okay yes so next is plotting with
Vega-Altair. So what can you tell us about this? Yep so we'll talk about plotting
data visualization. And so this is another way to look at data. But here we
will plot it, visualize it. And we will spend so just slightly over over one
hour on it and we will talk about the library called Vega-Altair, which is not
maybe the one that you would expect. Maybe you expected
that we talk about Matplotlib. Good news is that we have here lesson material for
both, also exercises for both. So if you want to read up, if you are interested
about Matplotlib, you can later. Here we will focus on Vega-Altair and I will
also in a little bit explain why we do that,
or why we try this.
This is a bit of an experiment.
This is the first time I teach this lesson in this context.
One tool that we will need is,
we will now work again in the JupyterLab, Jupyter notebook.
So this is this interface that we have also used yesterday,
but I now want to spend two minutes
on reminding how do we start it up.
So, if you have installed the software environment and activated it, and if you are now in the
software environment, then now you can, with me, start up the JupyterLab.
And I will do that here as well, JupyterLab.
And this will open up a JupyterLab in my browser.
worry if you haven't done this if you don't have the environment if you are
unsure how to start it where to start it you can you can also participate in this
episode and I will tell you how but let me hit enter and start up the Jupyter
lap suspense I also took a surprisingly long time to start up when I was testing
so mm-hmm that's interesting in the meantime what can you tell us about the
different plotting episodes I will try something different I will here I will
try this thing, because that worked for me earlier
when I tried that.
Oh, here we go.
So what it does is I actually need to click on the link.
And here I have it.
Okay, yeah.
Here I have the JupyterLab.
So.
Good, and now back to the plotting episode.
Yeah.
So maybe I want to tell people how,
what to expect now in the next one hour
and how to participate.
So what you can expect is if we,
we will try to do is two exercise sessions,
two sessions where you can really try something hands-on,
15 minutes, 20 minutes.
So two times, maybe 15 minutes.
Here before we will do a little bit of introduction
and I also wanted to answer the question
like why they got out there.
And at the end, we will do a bit of discussion Q&A.
We will do this in the, in the JupyterLab.
So one, so then you can type with me
when I paste in examples, you can do this as well.
Another really nice way to participate is
please ask us lots of questions in the collaborative notes.
I will just scroll to the end.
because the more questions here, the better.
I'm in a different browser window on my screen.
I'm looking at these and [name] is looking at these
and we can, this will help us to keep this really engaging.
So even if you don't want to like plot and type,
you can ask here.
Okay.
But now let's talk about plotting.
So the goal is here, having a bit of an overview
of what different libraries exist on Python.
And here we want to be able to read a data set from disk
or from the internet, load it into a Pandas data frame.
And we remember Pandas data frames from yesterday
and then visualize it with this library
called Vega out there.
And one, so one nice thing is that also if you get lost,
Also, if you get lost, if something doesn't work or something was too fast, all the steps
that I will do, you can also retrace them here in this notebook.
I will now not open it up, so spoiler alert, but everything is in there.
And one aspect that is really important to me when doing plotting is reproducibility.
and Python and JupyterLab and Vega out there
is a really nice combination to get reproducible plots
because then all the steps are scripted.
And the idea is that,
so what I'm trying to do when I create plots
is to minimize manual tweaking.
I want to have all the steps scripted.
All the steps should be part of the notebook.
So at the end, I get the plot that is in my publication
or thesis or report.
And this is important because sooner or later,
we all get into the situation that we now get new data.
We need to recreate these 50 plots.
And now I don't want to do it manually.
Now I just want to read the data
and the 50 plots are updated.
And yeah, so Vega-Altair is not the only plotting library
nor is Matplotlib.
Matplotlib is the potentially the most popular one,
the most standard one.
There are many libraries in Python that can do plotting.
Here I listed the ones that I know of.
I'm pretty sure that I have missed a couple of them.
There is not the one perfect one.
Vega-Altair is not better than other libraries.
It's really a matter of your preference.
One thing I encourage you to do is to also browse these
and see which one fits your workflow,
which one do you like best and then choose it.
But now why do I want to present Vega-Altair
here in this workshop?
The things that I like about this library
is that it's modern, it's concise, it's very powerful,
but the interface, so the API,
the interface is relatively simple, it's consistent,
it's predictable, and I like to think
that it lets me focus on the data visualization part,
and I can get started without too much Python knowledge.
I have a feeling that some other libraries
require more Python knowledge.
I like how it combines visual channels with data columns.
So in our Pandas data frames, we have data columns.
And I will try to show you that the connection
between data columns and visual channels
can feel really intuitive.
And this is really motivation number one for me
to show this library.
I will hopefully be able to motivate that it's,
we will see that it's easy to change figures.
There is very good documentation, it's open source.
You can then save figures in a number of formats,
even as websites.
And you can even create interactive plots
and save it as a website and then display it in your,
I don't know, personal webpage or group webpage.
So, usually, and in the past, we've taught matplotlib here.
So I guess maybe that's a question everyone wants to know.
So why Vega-Altair right now instead of matplotlib?
What's the advantages and disadvantages of each?
Yeah, the advantage is that I wanted to have a library that understands Pandas DataFrames
natively, so that we have a nice connection to the tools that we learned yesterday.
In Matplotlib it is also possible to use Pandas DataFrames, but it is not, like I feel you
you have to do some extra steps.
Yeah.
Okay.
The, what I've also found with Matplotlib was that, that you need maybe more Python
knowledge to be able to tweak plots and change plots.
Okay.
Yeah.
So, so maybe in short, I, I find Vega-Altera is maybe simpler for beginners in Python.
So it's also declarative as opposed to matplotlib, where you might be spending a lot of time
making it look just like you want.
Correct.
So Vega-outer is declarative, meaning that we describe what we want and not so much like
do this step by step, like this step and that step.
But then to get, I think we need to also be fair that to get like publication quality
plots where you tweak the font size and you tweak everything absolutely to your liking,
you will spend time on it, independently of which library you use.
Yeah.
Okay.
So I'm interested.
So how do we begin?
I would like to start with our example data set, which is weather data.
I think this is data that we all can relate to.
I wanted to have a data set that is relatively easy to understand.
And it's a data set that contains weather data from two Norwegian cities.
Here is some documentation of how I obtained it, but if you want to look at the data set,
you can open up this link and I will do that here.
The data set is in CSV format, so there are two Norwegian cities, one is Oslo, the capital,
the other one is Troms, this is the place where I work, it's in the north of Norway.
There is some monthly data, some daily data, I will now just open up maybe the monthly
one.
And it contains information about weather station, the date, and some like temperature
temperature, precipitation, like how much rain, minimum temperature.
Here it's presented in a tabular form, but really the underlying format is CSV, comma
separated values.
So this is how it is really stored.
It's values separated by commas.
And the first row describes the rows.
So now we will try to, we will read the CSV file using Pandas directly from the web.
So we don't have to even save it on our disk and try to plot it.
And now if you want, so if everybody wants, you can now do this with me.
But if you just want to watch, you can also just watch what I do.
And then in the exercise session, you will have enough time to retrace these steps.
So I will now copy this block which imports pandas and then it reads these two data sets,
the monthly data set for the city Tromso and for the city Oslo into a data frame which
I called data monthly.
So I will now copy it into my notebook, and we will then have a look at this data, we
will try to plot it.
Okay, let me just rearrange here a little bit the window so that we see both.
And the first thing I will do is I will rename the notebook from Untitled to Plotting, Rename,
And I will copy paste this in.
And this line lets me like look at the data.
So I will now run this cell.
What I do here on my side is shift enter to run it and create a cell below.
And yeah, here's the data.
And just to make it a little bit more readable, I will now make this larger.
One modification is that, so something I like to do with data is, here data monthly, I like
to actually look at the types, .dtypes, this is a little recap from yesterday.
Because it tells me what is the, for instance, I will see here that it actually doesn't understand
that the date is really date format.
It thinks that the date is a number.
And so it will now, for instance, think that this is one point and these are some decimal
points.
But of course, this is January 2023.
So I want to do a little modification to tell pandas that this is, that the column here
is in date format.
And if I print it again, it will look better.
Now I see that the date is year, month, day.
And so far we didn't do any plotting yet, but now we are ready to do some plotting.
Here plotting the data.
And I will copy-paste a little bit of code, and we look at the result, and I will also
explain what's happening here.
So let me copy this code block here into the notebook.
Okay, so this does, out there, a chart, monthly data, mark bar, code.
and maybe I should make it larger.
So we got a bar chart.
It's actually not a great bar chart
because here for different months of the year,
I got the precipitation.
So how much rain in millimeter, I guess.
Here, Tromso is in orange, Oslo is in blue.
The one thing that is not ideal
is that it stacks them on top of each other,
which makes it now very hard for me
to compare an amount of rain between months for Oslo.
But before improving it,
I want to explain a little bit what's happening.
So what did we do?
I imported this bigger Altair plotting library.
I gave it a shortcut name.
So I renamed it as Alt.
So then here I can refer to it.
Instead of typing Altair,
I only have to type ALT.
And I did that because when you then browse the internet,
this is what you are likely to see as examples.
So I want it to be close to that documentation.
So we import some functionality to plot,
and here I use it.
And this module comes with a bunch of functions.
One of them is here a chart.
So I want to create a chart, and here I put the data in.
This is the pandas data frame.
And then I do a couple of things with it.
This here, I decide I want to have a bar chart.
And later I will show you also
how do you get other types of charts.
And this part is the part where I link or encode.
So I connect the columns of the table.
And the columns of the table are here.
so there is a column called date and there is a column called precipitation and a column called
name and i connect them to the visual channel and the visual channel is for instance the x
coordinate y coordinate color and i will do a little improvement here
and I will explain why I did that year month this is month this is a function
that Altair provides okay so it's like pre-processing the column value it will
into it will now tell me that this is October 22 it will plot both the month
and the year at the same time.
What does this T mean here is that I tell Altair that this is a temporal data.
And there are other types like quantitative, ordinal, nominal, GeoJSON.
I will now not go into details and explain all of them.
I only wanted to tell you what this T means.
I wanted to tell the plotting library that this is a time series.
And does it have different presets for the different types of data, I guess?
Yes, exactly.
And we will see that in action.
But now I want to improve this a bit.
One improvement I want to do is to not have them on top of each other, but have them side
by side.
And the improvement that I will do is I will add another visual channel called column and
connect it to name.
And if I run, if I run the cell, now the names of the cities of the stations appear in different
columns of the plot.
And you can already guess what will happen if I change this to row.
Maybe that's a question to my co-instructor, and what do you think will happen now?
Does it put two plots on top of each other?
Exactly.
So that's...
Yeah, okay.
Ah, so yeah, now it lines up vertically.
So you used the word channel here, so is this basically you take different columns and you
connect them with different channels, whether it's color, or x or y axis, or stacked next
to each other, and so on.
Precisely.
And this is really what I like about this library,
that it makes it intuitive to me.
So all I do is connect columns of my data sets
to visual channels.
Of course, I need to know what kind of visual channels exist.
And I will, in a moment, show you
an overview of the different visual channels.
Here, I will do one more modification,
which is instead of column,
I can, there is another visual channel called X offset.
And if I use that one, I get a stacked bar chart.
And now it makes it easier for me to compare
the rain amount between the two cities.
So, yeah, maybe a couple of more examples
examples and then I want to show you what
what different visual channels exist and also what different
mark options exist. I want to now show you an example where I
change from a bar chart
from a bar chart I go to what happens if we do
mark area
we make it a little bit transparent 0.5 and now I will have to why I want to
have min temperature no max max temperature min temperature does it mean
we're making well I guess we'll see what comes out of that yeah ah okay so
So what I did, I took now different columns from my dataset.
And now there is a different chart type called an area chart.
And I connected the visual channels to those different columns.
One thing that you can try in the exercise block will be to separate now, okay, what
do we see here?
We see, like, what our temperature range is for the different months for the two different
cities.
So how do you know all of these different channels and so on?
Is it something you look up?
Because this seems almost like magic, but I wouldn't know the magic words to say to
get it out.
Yeah.
So I admit that I don't remember them.
I cannot remember them.
And the goal of this session is not to remember them,
but to know where to find them.
And here I link to an overview
of the available visual channels.
Let's have a quick look.
I will open it up.
So there is, we have seen X, Y,
we have seen Y2 for the area chart.
We have seen X offset,
But there is a lot more.
There is, you know, angle color.
You can, you can do like different shapes.
Or if you do circles, you can have a different radius.
There is really a ton you can do.
So these are visual channels.
And I don't remember them, I looked them up.
Then we have used two different marks.
One was bar chart.
one was an area chart. And also I don't remember there what are all the available marks.
So does a mark basically say like this is how we want it to be? Like we want it roughly like...
Yeah, it's like the type of the type of the plot.
Okay, okay.
And here I list them. For instance, an area chart, a bar chart, or you can have a scatter plot,
line plot, box plot.
Yeah.
OK, so it comes in, we make the chart object,
we mark it with the general class of plot,
whether it's bar or area or something.
We can give it other annotations,
and then we connect columns as data channels to outputs.
And the data has to be tidy. I guess that's the whole point here.
It helps a lot. Thanks for reminding this, because it helps a lot if the data is tidy.
If the data is tidy, and there is some discussion on it in the notes,
about tidy data, and also it has been mentioned earlier today and yesterday,
then you will see that it's very easy now to change the type of the plot.
And I like to do that, so I can then experiment until I find the plot that I like the best.
And here, at this stage, I also admit that what I really do in when I do these plots,
I often start from the gallery of examples.
And I like this, this thing here, I guess, just like with matplotlib, or with any other
plotting library, I normally look at gallery of examples, I will find the one that looks
closest to what I have in mind.
And this is this will be my starting point.
And we will try that later.
What I would like to do now is that to give here
workshop participants a bit of time, maybe 15 minutes.
And in these 15 minutes, the goal would be that
if you want to catch up,
if you want to try some of the plots that I did
here in the notebook, you can try that.
Then, to practice a little bit, to have a bit of understanding of these visual channels,
I will ask you then to, instead of having a stacked bar chart along the x-axis, try
to get it along the y-axis, with, and you will only have to change two lines of your
plotting code. Then some more questions. Try to ask the Internet or your AI tool how to
change the x-axis from precipitation to precipitation millimeters. So you can try that. And then
you can also try to split these temperature ranges instead of being on top of each other.
Try to split them so that they are next to each other. And this will give us a really
good understanding of good control over these visual channels.
And don't be afraid to use the solution for this.
So also one way to go through the exercises to actually open up the solution and, and
try to go through these solutions step by step.
Yeah.
And then we will, so you will get 15 minutes, we will then come back, talk a little bit
about it.
I will then tell you a little bit more
and then we will go into really imagining real life.
We start with, I will show you how I start
from a gallery example and get my own data into it.
That will be a second exercise block later.
So here in the notes, we will add exercise.
It will be until 40 minutes past.
So we will resume XX40.
And in there I will also paste the link to the exercise and a short description of what
we expect.
And then we'll be back.
So the goal is to explore some, whatever you feel like you have time to.
Yeah, this exercise here, I will paste it into the notes.
Also try, here there are questions one, two, three, four, try some of them, all of them,
and the solution is there.
And also just question one is already good if you manage that.
See you in 15 minutes.
And in the meantime, I will catch up with the notes so that we can answer some questions.
See you then.
Bye.
you
So, if we look here at the notes, we see there have been some good questions there.
Yeah, the most interesting to me was this, can you define a visual channel?
Because somehow I think that's like the most, well, the most unique thing I see here.
And the answer here is it's like the different ways eyes tell things apart, whether it's
color or size or offsets or position like x y position something like that um
do you have any comments on that i think that's a really good explanation
um i can only add to it that those of you who maybe program in r the r
language if you plot in r you likely plot so
there is a library called ggplot2 and the philosophy there is very
similar. So those of you who come from R, maybe come from ggplot2, maybe you feel at home this
philosophy of visual channels. But that was a good description of it. I'm not sure I have a
better one. It's really about like shapes, placements, sizes, colors. And like while it's
sort of the same in matplotlib, which I've tried to use before, here it seems like a much more
natural mapping, instead of having to add a bunch of other lines to get the matplotlib
ones connected.
Anyway, I think most of the rest of the questions are answered here somewhat well.
So I'll head back to your screen.
Thanks.
My plan is to have a little bit more fun here with visual channels.
discussion I will then, we have this one more exercise session but we decided
that the second exercise plot I will do as a demo here. We will do it
together but on my screen. So I wanted to show you a few more examples. Here I will
not copy-paste it into the notebook, you can you can try that on your own time.
It's very similar to above, but now I use the daily data.
So again, I load tabular data from the internet, again to cities, now daily.
Daily data, I will be now interested in snow depth, so how much snow is on the ground.
And here, in this example, I did a preliminary plot.
Again, how do I read it?
I use this library.
I want the chart.
This is my data.
I want to have a bar chart.
On the x-axis, I want to have the date.
So this was December 2022,
and then a couple of months.
There was less snow here in Oslo, more snow in Tromso.
You can also see that we have then snow well into April and May.
I connected the y-axis with the snow depth.
Snow depth is a column in this data set.
And then I wanted to have them side by side.
So the name of the station, left Oslo, right Tromso.
And here I wanted to, I can then add additional visual channels.
I wanted to add a visual channel color.
I wanted to color the bar chart with the maximum temperature, the daily maximum temperature.
And then it starts to look really interesting.
This is done temperature from, I don't know, minus five to 15.
I also wanted to show you that you can modify
the color range.
Here I got some default color scale,
but you can modify this.
So in this example,
I changed it to a color scheme called plasma.
And here I have a link,
which links to the available color schemes,
and there are many.
So there are very many color schemes,
and you can then choose one that is appropriate
visually pleasing for your example. And what I like about this plasma plot is
that so there is no depth. Let's look at Tromso. Snow goes up one meter, one
meter, 20 centimeters. It melts and it disappears. What I like about this plot
is that I can see that on the warmer days, which are then more yellow, so the warmer
days I follow they are typically followed by less snow and the colder days
they are often followed by more snow. Nice visualization. And then if I realize
that I'm not sure about the bar charts I want to have how does it look with with
a circle scatter plot then the only thing I changed here was from mark bar
you can change to mark circle and then I get circles. So it's a really nice way
of experimenting until you find the visualization that conveys the message
that you want to convey. Now we have 15 minutes left. Yes, I wanted to tell you
that you can change also the overall theme. So if you like, so with the one
line I could change everything from like light background to dark background. You
You can also, there are many teams
that other people have created from different newspapers.
You can also define your own team
for yourself or for your research group.
And here's a link to a long list of themes
that other people have created.
I will not go there.
I only wanted you to know that this is possible.
I wanted to spend now the last 15 minutes of the session
to discuss how do I really approach plotting in real life?
because in real life, I don't remember anything.
I try to plot something every month or every few weeks
and then I already forgot all the details.
So I often start with, I go to a gallery
and this is not only for Vega out there,
this is also for Matplotlib or any library.
I normally go to their example library
and look for something that looks similar
to what I want to do.
And now you can just watch and maybe ask questions
and give me tips on through the notes.
I'm watching these notes here on a side screen.
And I really encourage you to then later go
through this exercise on your own time.
I think it's incredibly useful to go through these steps.
So now let's go through these steps together.
I will now take something, I will take a starting point
and the starting point that I will take is,
I just want to be close to the example.
Are you taking, do you have some data you want to plot
and then you're finding an example?
Are you getting the data from the example?
So my first, my starting point will be
that I take the example that is there.
And my first step will be to try to run the example as it is.
Of course, now I already forgot what I wanted to,
the example that I wanted to show is this slider cutoff.
Slider cutoff, where is it?
Here, this one.
I just want it to be close to the material.
So let's imagine that, hey, this looks interesting here.
I want to do something like they did, but with my own data.
But before I try anything with my own data my first step always is I first try
to run what they do. So here's some actually random data and they it's
interactive there is a slider and I can move the slider around. Is this
interactive and only HTML? Basically. Possibly. So I it will be interesting to
see if we export it to, if you save it as a SVG PNG,
maybe try it out.
I mean, maybe the learners can test it out
and see whether it's still interactive there.
I would hear probably only when we export it to HTML
and hopefully in the notes,
I have a, I describe how to export to HTML.
And it's also interactive in the notebook.
Okay, so my first step is always,
I want to just run what they do with their data.
And then my second step will be try to understand the data
and replace it with my own.
I will start a new notebook here
and rename it to gallery.
And I paste, not this thing.
I paste their example as is.
And try to run it and try to get I want to see what they see on the gallery.
And indeed, I do.
So then I'm already pretty happy.
What is my second step often, my second step is that, okay, there is a lot of code here,
I don't understand everything.
And I kind of squint my eyes, I don't even have to, you know, understand everything.
I try to focus on what we know and what we know is this part.
We recognize it.
We read a data set and here we do a point points.
So it's a scatterplot.
So we already know that this is probably the data.
And I don't have to understand the rest here,
but the second thing I will often do is I print it.
to see how does the data look, what is in there,
or how is it structured?
And if I print it, it's a data frame, it's a table,
it's a table with 100 rows,
and it has two columns, X and Y.
And X goes from zero to 99,
And this is the Y value is somehow random.
Yeah, I don't fully understand it,
but I don't need to because
now that I understand the structure of the data,
the next thing I will try to do is to change it,
replace it with my own data.
Okay, great, I see.
Yeah, so you take this, you find where the data is
and you start inserting your data in here.
Yeah, yeah.
And, yeah.
And I will now switch to,
so here I have a walkthrough
and I encourage everybody to test it out later.
So now that I printed the data
and I got a little bit of insight on what it is,
something I find useful is to save it to file.
And I will now, just for the sake of time, I will now not do it on my computer, but with
the help of Pandas, Pandas has a function called toCSV.
So I can save the table into a file, and I call it, I don't know, data.csv.
And then I can look at it in my editor.
Okay, so this is like just to understand what the data is.
Yeah, to understand the structure of it.
And then what I often do next is then, aha, now that I understand the structure, I can
put in my own data.
And this data here is now I wanted to plot for the January until October, some number
and this was maybe max temperature I guess.
And then I save it to file, I keep it on file, then I can read the data from the file.
And once I read the data from the file, so this is now my data CSV, I also recognize
is that there is now a couple of things
that I don't need anymore.
I have commented them out.
So I don't need this.
I don't need the random data.
I don't even need NumPy anymore here.
It was only used for the number,
for the random number generator.
So I would remove all the stuff that I don't need
and then tweak it a little bit.
And if you are interested in how that looks at the end,
I also have a notebook on where I did these steps.
So we can look how would the result look.
So here we have this original data.
I now write the data to file, I read it from file.
All this stuff I can comment out and throw away.
And I wanted to also adjust the slider
because I am looking at temperature.
So instead of zero to 100, maybe zero to 30.
And I'll define default.
So the default is now 15.
And now in my notebook, I can use the slider and look at my temperatures in maybe that was
Oslo.
So it looks like too warm for Tromso, not true.
So back to.
So let's again take a step back here.
So this, please try this out
and it doesn't have to be Vega out there.
Try it out with your favorite Python plotting library.
But going through these steps of
reproducing an example of somebody else,
maybe you find an example on the internet,
get an understanding of what the data is that they plot
and then replace it with your own data.
This is, I think, key to adapting examples
to your own projects.
And then you can also tweak.
So once I get this working,
I will then maybe change the font size,
axis annotation, axis title,
and then it goes into publication.
Yeah.
So now that we have a few minutes left,
let's also look here at questions.
Let me summarize key points.
Yeah, so hopefully, go ahead, um, go ahead, I guess, read this first.
Yeah, it's very important to me that the outcome of this one hour episode is not that they
are there is that everybody should use it.
It's something that I like to use, but find the library that fits your work and your style.
And on top of this page I list many galleries and libraries that I know about.
Really try to minimize the manual post-processing of the plot and try to script all steps.
And what that means in practice that all the steps from data to the finished plot should
be in your notebook or in your Python script.
This can be some work.
So this doesn't come for free.
It can be days of work,
but the nice thing is you only have to do it once.
And then half a year later, you get new data in
and you can reproduce all the plots in two minutes.
CSV is a really nice format.
It's often a good format to store data
that we wish to plot.
Of course, it has pros and cons,
and we remember the lesson from before
that discusses it nicely.
And Vega-Altair is all about connecting tables with visual channels.
Really nice library. Give it a go.
Give it a try.
Yeah.
Okay.
Should we look at the notes for some stuff?
Yes.
There was one really good question. In what situation should we not use Vega-Altair?
That's a good one.
So I have...
So it works really well in the notebook and in a script.
I think I don't know how to use it inside
if you write your Python code in VS Code or in Spyder.
It's maybe possible, I don't know how to do it,
so maybe then take something different.
Yeah, I don't know if, otherwise, so.
Yeah, like I can't think of many.
Is it good if you want complete control, like you want to define every single element, element
position and style yourself?
Is that?
Yes.
Okay, so that still is possible.
You can.
It's possible.
You can tweak everything, as in Matplotlib.
So you can have full control over all the details.
And as in other libraries, it is work to do that and to figure out how these things are
called and how to do it.
It has sort of library has a very extensive reference manual.
What what I often do when I need to tweak things is I ask a web search, I ask an AI.
So I paste in, here is my code, but I would like to modify the, instead of precipitation,
I want to have precipitation in millimeter, what do I need to modify?
So again, I don't remember these things, but I use the knowledge of the internet to...
Yeah.
Okay, I had at least one other question, or actually, let me scroll up and see what else.
it use matplotlib as a back-end? No it doesn't. So it uses, and here I'm also
admitting that I'm not a Vega Altair expert, so I'm really just a user, but
my understanding is that it uses Vega underneath. If I'm wrong, please correct
me. It doesn't use matplotlib as a back-end. There are other libraries, if
If you like the kind of high-level, nice interface,
there are other libraries like Seaborn,
which use the Mappletip underneath.
Okay, got it.
Yeah.
Okay, well, now it's lunchtime.
If we don't see many more questions here,
should we break?
And when we come back, we have, what is it?
We will talk about scripting.
we will talk about profiling and other productivity tools.
And I want to say, thanks, [name].
Thanks everybody for understanding
with some technical issues at the beginning.
Also, thanks so much for all the questions here.
And I will now also spend some time
and go through all the questions and add more answers.
Don't also hesitate to ask more questions
also later about plotting.
It's really one of my favorite topics.
Have a nice lunch break, see you in one hour, thank you, on stream, bye!
you
You
And we have put in a short question for you, whether you have used the command line before for anything. That's just a bit of a statistics for us to see what kind of experience you have, have had before the course. So, if you could just put in your previous usage, then that would be great.
put in your privacy usage, then that would be great.
Thanks.
Okay.
Most people are familiar with the command line.
Yeah, it looks very much like it.
So this lecture is mainly about scripts and why it's,
well, how to get from Jupyter Notebooks to scripts
why scripts are useful and how to generalize scripts so that they can be used for multiple
purposes or with different inputs. And we are essentially trying to show you how to get from
Python notebooks to repeatable Python scripts and how to streamline that process
and how to potentially import other Python files and how to parse input
commands because that's, if you want to run scripts on the command line, that's
what you normally have to do and why you are creating a script from this. So far
we have had essentially a Jupyter notebook where you were running
individual cells and it was quite convenient. You had the results right after, right in the notebook
and it let us easily experiment with the Python code and see okay what changes if we
change something and so on. But if we have developed something that we want to use and we
want to use this analysis script for multiple inputs, Jupyter Notebooks start to become a bit
inconvenient, because what do you do if you have multiple inputs? Do you create 10 different,
well, however many inputs you have, different notebooks, one for each of them? Or do you have
a very long notebook where you have multiple input cells? And this is essentially also the
problem where, yeah, which cells did I actually run before now and which cells didn't I run?
So you end up with something where you are, where you can easily run into,
I don't know if, what the inputs actually were because, yeah, I ran some cells. I'm not sure if
I had this thing still on and there were some other cells that I had run before from the day
before something and it becomes potentially yeah not reproducible. So let's assume you have
created 10 notebooks for the 10 different input parameters and well now you want to do that for
a thousand different input parameters then it becomes completely infeasible because you can't
well, it's a complete replication of the code a thousand times and b it's just a
mass of notebooks that you can't really handle anymore. So here we will show you
how to configure or how to change notebooks so that they can be run with
different parameters or rather how to convert them into scripts that can be
run with multiple parameters, and how you can easily
run these scripts also on non-interactive systems
like computer clusters.
Because that's where, essentially,
if you have these 1,000 runs, you will end up,
at least if the 1,000 things you are doing
is a little bit more than a few seconds of time.
Because it just takes too long on a normal PC.
Okay, so.
Yeah, one question.
Why we call it a script?
Because sometimes I call it a program
or sometimes a script,
but what's the difference between these two or?
So I would say the difference between a script
and a program is that a program is essentially
a self-contained unit.
So it doesn't need anything,
or it doesn't need anything that it doesn't kind of supply
when you install the program.
While a script is something rather smaller
that you normally run in some kind of
in so-called interpreter, Python is an interpreter.
So it's somewhat a smaller unit.
It's a bit less complex.
If you want to have it as a program,
you need to create an executable out of it.
and that is all stuff that takes quite a bit of effort
depending on the program.
It is entirely possible, but we are here not focusing
on this more software architecture
building side of it,
but really more on the how can I get my functions
to be run on multiple inputs.
And you can also somewhat say that a script could be a function, a function call, somewhat.
While a program is just a lot bigger, normally, and has multiple potential function calls
that it can run.
But even that can be done with scripts as well, so yeah.
somewhere similar but slightly slightly different. Yeah. So the
first thing that we
Yeah, yeah, go. Let's see how to convert this notebook to to the
script.
Yeah. So the first thing, there are things like paper mill that
can help you in using notebooks with input parameters or to parameterize notebooks. But
this is still something where it becomes more difficult to run this on cluster systems,
because it still needs Jupyter, which might be a bit of a problem. So the simplest way
is essentially to convert the Jupyter notebook to a Python script and Jupyter already internally
has a command that's called nbconvert that allows you to take a Jupyter notebook and convert it into
a Python file. You can also, if this doesn't work for some reason, you can use save and
export the notebook as a executable script that also exports the notebook as script.
There is one important thing that I want to mention for all these exports.
If you have magics included, all of these Jupiter magics that were mentioned yesterday,
they don't convert nicely.
So I would personally always remove magics before doing something and converting it into
Python script. So, I think we could go to the first exercise and give it like 10 minutes or so
to just get your first Jupyter Notebook into Python script conversion here.
Maybe we can show how to download this Jupyter Notebook in the
I would copy link here and then in file, what was it, URL and paste it in there, then open.
I already have that.
You have this.
I can overwrite it and then it downloaded the file here.
So that's relatively simple.
Okay, we will be, I think five minutes should be sufficient for this.
So let's return at 15.
you
Okay.
I'm going to stop sharing my screen.
Let me know if you guys want to share your screen.
Okay.
I will see you guys next week.
Bye bye.
Bye.
you
Okay, and welcome back.
So one option for how to do this is mentioned here in the solution, where you have a fixed
input and fixed output. These are positional arguments. Then you have these variable arguments
for the start date and the end date. You could also do something where the inputs and outputs
are also positional arguments, starting with a minus or minus minus, but that's essentially up to
what your use case is. So what was the point of doing this? The point of doing this is a you can
have you now automatically have a small help so that tells you okay how is this to be used.
You can run parts of these or actually you can run all of them.
So, you can run something which has a specific input that is potentially different and has
a certain output.
You can say, okay, I want a different start and end date.
You can, yeah, create plots for individual month or stuff and you don't for any of those
changes need to modify the code.
And that allows you, for example,
if you have a script that you want
to test different parameters on, to run exactly the same script
with different parameters.
And the good thing is, you can be sure
that it is actually the same script that's
being run on the different parameters
and not something else, because you're
running the same file without modifications.
We can also then start to build loops over file patterns with this,
where you can run this for multiple different input parameters
at the same time.
And we have made it with ArcParse a lot more robust,
so that user input errors are essentially grabbed
before the actual code is being run,
so that it's much clearer what the problem with the call is.
Now, as was somewhat mentioned in the HackMD already,
this of course comes with some limitations
because putting in this huge file name for the input data
or for output things is very inconvenient.
You don't really want to do that
because it's a long string that's written there.
However, you might have the situation
that you have these long configuration options
and that's where potentially
using configuration files come in.
And [name] mentioned that this morning,
that where you have kind of two main form
or two to three main formats,
how configuration files look either JSON or YAML.
And essentially all the configuration options
are then defined in there.
And we could also add more parameters here.
add more parameters here.
We might want to have
things like the color of the plot or the style of the plot
or something that can be changed or have specific x and y labels.
And if we add more and more and more input arguments
then the command line call that we are running here
gets more and more inconvenient to use.
So, what's often done is instead of giving 20 different input parameters, you give one
input parameter, which is essentially the configuration file that you want to run.
And you set up these configuration files.
And that can be done either with YAML, or with JSON, or in any other structured format
that's easy to use.
We have a small options parser that takes a simple YAML-style options file and then
runs it similar to ArcPars.
They need to define a certain type, optional arguments are derived from those values and
so on.
You would essentially end up with something where the input and output are defined in
a YAML file that can be then extracted.
Do you want to say something more to this?
Yes.
And I think you mentioned this before several minutes ago,
but if you each time you run the script,
you have to type a long in the command line.
And a better way that you prepare another script,
for example, a shell script, you copy paste everything there.
If you're not quite familiar with shell,
then put everything there.
and define several variables and either the input or output or the new the name for the output file
you can define there and using a for loop or yeah one loop or multiple loops 2k so that you can
automatically get the result just around this shell script the shell script we call the person
Python and run this. This is much more convenient for to run the code.
Yeah, completely agree. So especially also if you think about running potentially these kind
of things on a cluster and you want to put in some additional arguments, that's also an option
that you essentially call your scripts with some shell script that's being run that then calls the
submission script for the cluster and submits that script with specific parameters.
That's also an option. So I think we can, we do have the time to do this option parser exercise
here and I think it's actually a good exercise to
see how these yaml files are used how the how
these kind of configuration files can be used in a script
and I would give this another
maybe we don't have enough time yeah we need to several minutes
10 minutes, but then we are already in the break time. So let's see what questions we have here.
Maybe there's something we can discuss about this.
Yeah, maybe we can clarify a bit again what the input arguments here for arc powers are.
So, there are different types of arguments.
These first two, they are fixed arguments.
There's an input and there's an output.
And that's essentially the first and second non-named argument, or yeah, non-named in
the sense that it doesn't have a prefix like minus S minus minus start or so.
And these arguments have to be always provided.
they are non-optional.
And then you have these prefix arguments
where you can specify that what's
following after a minus s is the start date.
And that can be placed anywhere.
And it doesn't matter where it's being placed.
So you can throw around different values.
And depending on the settings,
this can have a default
and commonly though these arguments are optional arguments,
they don't necessarily have to be provided.
So they normally should have a default value.
And that can also be omitted.
What else do we have?
Yeah, I think we have already covered all this content.
Just trying to see.
There was also the question for this very long format, which we essentially heard that
You can set this stuff in environment variables as well and then use environment variables
to call the or to put it in there because it gets unreadable.
And then the metavar value here, a little bit further up.
So this is just what this value here will be looking like if it's being set so that
this is called n for this purpose.
and what it should look like in the usage description.
Okay, but I think this is mainly what we wanted to say for this lecture,
and showing you how to essentially convert into a script,
get some basic argument parsing set up,
so that you can use scripts with multiple different input arguments and I think this
essentially is how you get a script ready to be run on a in a non-interactive way.
Any other anything else from you Yonglei? No, I think it's fully covered from your aspect.
it.
OK, then.
It's 48, maybe.
Then let's do the break till 2.
And see you then.
Yeah.
See you.
Bye.
you
Hello. Hello, welcome back everyone and welcome to our next lecture. In this case we will talk now
about profiling. So we have just had this nice lecture about scripting, so how do we turn our
code into Python scripts and now we will discuss the topic of how to figure out the bottlenecks
of this script. So whenever you care about the time your code takes to run or whenever you care
about how much memory it uses, you will look into profiling. But before we have a deep dive into
profiling, luckily I don't have to give this lecture on my own, but [name] will be joining
again. Hi [name]! Hi [name] and really looking forward to this really important topic. So what
I will do in the first part, when we talk about profiling, is I'm looking at the notes.
please ask a question.
I will try to lift them up into a discussion.
And we really try to keep this interactive
and try to keep it in like a discussion-y format.
And there will be one exercise block.
So we will discuss here for 10 minutes.
Then there will be a 20 minute exercise block
where you can try this out.
And then we will debrief again with a 10 minute block.
Exactly. Okay, so the most important question probably at the beginning is, when do I actually
need to care about profiling and the performance of my code? Like, is this something that I
need to worry about every time I create a script? Or is this only in specific cases?
Yeah, and this is a great question. And for maybe most scripts, we don't need to worry
about it you mentioned performance and performance can be two things it can be
speed so the time time for the script to complete and if you are happy with the
speed and happy with the memory consumption then no need to optimize and
no need to do any of any profiling so then so when we talk here in this
Sessionable optimizing, we really mean
it could be two different things.
It could be that it just takes too long,
or it means that I fill up all my memory.
And then we maybe need to do something about it.
So the next question is then,
or maybe before we go even into profiling,
should we even optimize?
Yeah, that's a very good question.
And I think as a rule of thumb,
I would suggest not to be too concerned
performance and optimization at the beginning, but focus on having a code that computes exactly
what you want it to do, like if your code has errors and it gets some wrong results it really
doesn't matter how quickly you get these wrong results. So the first priority should be to have
a code that does what it's supposed to do and that is readable and then if you come to the conclusion
that it needs to be faster or needs to use less memory then you can worry about profiling and
performance and all these other things. But nowadays since interpreters like Python or
compilers have gotten really really good it can be like super unintuitive which part of the code
takes the most time or uses the most memory and that's now when profiling comes in. Now there's
also this famous quote which is standing here, premature optimization is the root of all evil.
You might have heard this before and it basically means that if you've spent too much time
optimizing things that turn out to be not relevant, you just maneuver yourself into a dead end and
create problems along the way. So you would really only care about optimization once you
know that you need optimization and once you know which parts of the code require optimization.
Yeah and somebody asked in the notes what is profiling because we know we mentioned it and
and we will show it, you can practice it,
but how would you describe profiling?
I would describe it as such that profiling is the process
of figuring out which parts of the code
require the most resources.
So this can be computation, so CPU hours,
or it can be also memory usage.
So profiling is taking a script,
going, we discuss afterwards in detail how this is done,
but like taking a look at every section of the script
and measuring how long does it take
and how much memory does it use?
Yeah, like I like to think of it
and maybe it's a helpful analogy.
It's imagine like an X-ray for the code
and imagine you are like a surgeon.
You want to, like before a surgeon does a surgery
on a person, they will first put the person
into an X-ray MRI, which will then identify
where exactly is the problem
before we start to do the optimization code surgery.
So that's how I like to think of a profile.
Yeah, so the fastest way probably how to profile your code
is by measuring yourself,
how long these sections of the code take
by basically stopping the time
at different parts of your code.
This is better than nothing.
Of course, you will get a lot of information out of this,
but it has some downsides,
like it doesn't provide you any information
on the memory usage.
And also you have, it's a lot of manual things you need to add to your script.
So luckily there are tools out there that are significantly easier to use than doing this
manually. And the other one you've listed quite a few profilers now here in this lecture. So we
have profilers which focus mainly on the CPU, so the time, and we have profilers which are
optimal, like which are designed in such a way that they are good at measuring the
memory usage of the code. But there is one specifically that you recommend and this is
scalene, right? What does scalene do better than all these other tools that
people might have heard of in the past?
Yeah, so the reason why we added scalene here and also this is
the one that we will try out in a moment in in the exercise
is that, so I wouldn't say that it's like
necessarily better than the other profilers, they are all fine and they
have all their use case, but what I like about scalene is that it's
may be the the one that is easiest to use. We will be able to use it and we don't have to change the
code that we want to profile at all. So for some profilers you need to edit your code and add
certain so-called decorators or similar. With scalene we don't have to do anything. I can
Instead of running python myscript.py, I will run scalene myscript.py and the
other thing I like about scalene is that it does both CPU and memory at the
same time, line by line. So we will be able to see, line by line, where is the
bottleneck. Where's the CPU bottleneck, where is the memory bottleneck. It can
also analyze the GPU, it can also do GPU profiling.
So I think it's a good starting point.
Then some of the other profilers
that can do more details if needed.
It's, okay, what is the downside of scalene?
One possible downside, but we might discuss it or not,
is that it's a sampling profiler.
So there are sampling profilers,
there are tracing profilers,
well, not necessarily downside,
but both have pros and cons.
And sampling would mean that
after a certain time interval,
it will record where in the code it is,
how much memory is allocated.
And what does it mean in practice?
So what does it mean for the size of the problem
that we want to profile?
Yeah, so, when you profile your code, you typically want to use a code that represents
your real-world problem.
Like, typically, it should be something that is similar to the actual code that you want
to run in the long run.
Now, I can give an example, during my PhD, I was running a lot of computational simulations,
which took multiple hours on a supercomputer, and at the beginning, I wanted to have a
shorter version of the code, so I wouldn't buy that many resources for the profiling,
And then it turned out that most of my time was going on initializing the simulation and
not actually running the simulation.
So when I was profiling the code, it was telling me, oh yeah, you're setting up a simulation
takes so much time and you should really focus on optimizing this, which of course was the
completely wrong conclusion since what we actually care is the computational part, which
a real simulation takes much longer than setting up a simulation.
it should be representative for the problem that we try to solve at hand.
Okay, so we now slowly go to our exercise. In this case, we will now use scalene to
count, or we have a Python script that is shown further down here, which takes an input file,
which is a text file in this case, and counts the number of unique words in this text file.
The instructions on how to download it are presented above. So you can download it from
this link and then you can run scalene inside your terminal as shown here. And
you can see here there are three different implementations for counting the number of
unique words and before you actually do the profiling maybe have a look at the code and
have a guess or like think of which of these implementations takes the most time and takes
the most memory because you might be surprised when you actually do the profiling sometimes
it can be really unintuitive. Okay so I think with that we will now have a 20-minute
exercise session and we'll be back then and run Scalene here on the stream and
discuss the results together. Okay, see you in 20 minutes. Bye!
you
Okay, welcome back. We saw there were quite some interesting questions in the HedgeShop
document. One was about R, so a different language. So, we should highlight that profiling
code is really nothing Python specific. It's something that exists for pretty much any
language you can find out that, whether that's R or Julia or C++ or whatever, like there are always
ways how you can do this type of profiling. Scalene is Python specific, but you will find very
similar tools in other languages. So we really want to focus here on the concepts so that you
can apply them in whatever language you want. There were also some other technical difficulties.
Shall we quickly comment on this or shall we jump straight to the result of the profiling?
Yeah, maybe just a quick comment that please don't get discouraged if you hit technical
issues.
Really, our goal was that you all know that this is a tool that exists.
And it wasn't a super easy exercise because we asked people to also download a file, rename
file. Yeah, so a couple of steps. But maybe it will also help. Let's show how it looks
when it's working. So I spin up my terminal and I have here the book.txt file, which I downloaded
earlier, and the example.py script. So this is the code that is also shown here in the instructions.
So now I'm going to run scalene.example.py like this.
This will take a few seconds,
and then it will spin up a page
where it shows us the results of the profiling.
That opens it in the wrong browser,
so I drag it over here.
Okay, here we go.
So here we see the results,
and you can now, by default,
it only shows you a number of lines,
but if you want to see all of them,
you can here tick this box,
and then you can see the whole script.
So I think the script is short enough that we can do this.
Okay, so let's have a look at the results.
What should we focus on at the beginning?
So how do you look at this?
Like, how do you read this thing?
So on the right side of the screen, I see our code.
So this is a line-by-line profiler.
It will give us a profile with a line-by-line.
And then there are lots of symbols,
But what are the things that you look at next?
Yeah, so depending on whether I'm interested in the time
it takes to run a program or the memory,
I will focus on these two things.
So the first column here gives us
the time that is taken by each role in this program.
And we can clearly see that the culprit in this program
is the second implementation of counting words.
So we can see that more than half of the time
is here taken by this line here.
Yeah, and I think what happens
if you scroll all the way down,
do you also see the summary?
Yeah, so then I know that that function takes most time.
And then if I want to know which line in that function,
then it's the line 21.
And maybe we can even help answering why is it so,
Like why does the code spend the most time in line 21?
So if we compare, sorry, do you?
No, go ahead.
Okay, so if we compare like our best implementation here,
which is the third function to the second one,
we can see the main difference here is that we use here
a list to store our values.
And in the third function, we use a set.
So in the list, we have all the values
which are then saved one after one.
So this if statement that we have here
is going for every single element in this list
and checking whether the new word
is already existing or not in this list.
And if it's not, then we append the list.
But this is arguably a very bad implementation
since it requires us to go for the list
for every new word that we find.
And that's why it takes so much time.
Now the third function here is significantly faster
since we use a set, which is a different data type.
since it doesn't store every single element one by one,
but it's using something called hashing.
So it uses a fancy function,
which gives every element a hash.
So that's a specific identifier,
which is really easy to compute.
And then it can look up in the set
what it's already done or not.
But it's kind of a very, very fast explanation.
We can also see if we take a look at the memory footprint
that the first function here takes a lot,
much more memory than the other two.
And this is because we load in the whole text file
and then perform this regex for here on the whole,
the whole text file at once,
whereas in the later ones,
we then actually go, we have this four-open addition
where we can go word by word through the elements,
which then, sorry, here, line by line,
so we don't load the whole dataset at once into memory,
but we do it line by line,
which then results in a lower memory footprint.
Is this a sufficient explanation, or did I miss something?
No, I think this is really good.
So what we really wanted to show all of you is that,
yeah, we have a tool here that we can really identify
the line where most memory or most CPU is spent.
And that is also good to read a little bit
about different data types,
I mean, data containers like sets and lists
because they have pros and cons.
And here we have seen one disadvantage of lists.
And the other take home message that we wanted to convey
is that when processing big data files or big texts,
it can be good to go, I don't know, line by line
or in batches instead of reading the entire thing.
Because the function number one,
if we go to larger and larger books,
it will consume more and more memory.
One additional thing that we get from scalene is the time which is used inside of python and then
other libraries and how much time is then used up by the system that we run the code on and the
same is here for the memory. So the python section here refers to the time that is actually taken by
the python code itself and the native one is then by code that python calls. So if you remember from
the NumPy lecture, for instance, we've learned that the one reason why NumPy is so fast is because
it calls functions that are actually implemented in C and Fortran under the hood, so it's not running
native Python code, and this will then show up in Scalene here as the native part. And then the
system part is the one which is just taking time from the operating system, so there's always
something running in the background which then has contribution to the overall time.
And also we have here the timeline of the memory, so we can see here that almost all of the memory
here was used up at the beginning of the program, which makes sense since that's when we, at the
beginning, when we call the first function, and then afterwards the second and the third uses
much less memory, so we can also see here in this timeline that afterwards the memory footprint is
negligible compared to the first one. So there's a lot of information that scaling provides.
Is there anything else that you look at typically around the one?
Not really, where is the bottleneck, but also like the profile of the memory allocations.
Because the bottleneck will show me like the high memory watermark, but it can be interesting
to know like is everything allocated at the beginning and then nothing later.
If it's like that it can sometimes mean that I should split up the script into two scripts,
one that needs a lot of memory and then the rest of the script that needs no memory at
all.
I'm also looking at the questions and some people don't see the same result as we do
and I wonder whether it's different defaults, different versions.
and it might require some extra options.
Yeah, so if you open the terminal
and you type in your name on its own,
it will give you a lot of information
with a lot of flags that you can use.
And you might need to use some of these flags
since you might have a different version
and then you can specify all these things here.
So you can specify what kind of output format you want
where you want it to be printed out to the command line.
And it also, you can also specify
whether you only want to look at memory
or whether you want to take the memory part off,
what kind of threshold you want for the memory footprint.
So if you have a piece of code
which doesn't show any memory usage,
it might be that the default threshold
for scaling is too high.
So you might want to lower that.
We don't have time to go through all these options here,
but if you want to learn more about it,
you can find, of course, a lot online,
also here in the command line itself, you can find a lot of information about these flags.
So I'm quite sure that almost all of the technical difficulties
that are shown here can be solved by using the right flags.
Okay, is there something else to say? We are at the end of our slot, 40 minutes.
let's move on to the next.
Yeah, let's, the remaining 20 minutes in this,
for today we will spend with productivity tools.
Maybe for this I will take over the screen.
Yeah, so I stop sharing.
We might again then need to adjust the screen crop.
Let's see.
This is the screen, and I will just verify how that looks.
Okay, I'm switching to it.
Yeah, looks good.
Because we are using a little workaround, but that looks pretty good.
So we will leave profiling, there is a lot more to say, of course, and a lot more to ask, and please do ask.
Now, 20 minutes or less on productivity tools.
We also want to leave room for feedback.
Productivity tools, this will only be a demo and a discussion.
I wanted to mention a few tools that I like to use or I see people using that help me be more productive.
they helped me focusing more on the Python part and less worrying about the
typesetting let's say I mean the like auto formatting for instance so it's
about consistent styling so format of the code but also about spotting
problems sometimes small problems and sometimes they are called like lint like
when you take laundry out of the dryer. So little particles hanging together, small issues
that are maybe hard to spot. But now we have tools that can help us spotting them.
So they are called linters. And again, there are many, many of these tools.
Here we list the few that we know about.
The tool that I will demonstrate is, I will demonstrate only one of those, it's Ruff.
It's part of your software environment, so you can also test it out in your Conda environment,
in your conda prompt.
The reason why I chose to demonstrate rough
and not the other tools is that it's a tool that can do both.
It can do both linting.
It can check for small problems,
but it can also automatically format the code.
and you can also configure these tools so they have good defaults but you can
configure what what they should detect what they should ignore how you want to
format your code let me demonstrate it so for this I created an example which is
here and it's somehow maybe familiar it's one of these I took one of the
functions from our previous episodes from the profiling episode and I
introduced three problems in there they are highlighted with yellow background
one problem is that I import a library that I never use and that can happen
because sometimes you import something, you use it, and later you improve the code
and you end up not using it. But now I forgot to remove this.
I also forgot there is a forgotten variable there that is unused.
Not a big deal, but it complicates the code and maybe it will confuse the next person.
Here the problem is that there is a parenthesis too much.
And now I will try to find these issues with the tool rough.
Here is the example code on my computer and you can type rough.
So this is something you can try now or later.
You can type rough check and the code.
Like this, but you can also leave out the file and it will check all the Python files
that it finds in the present directory.
And in the meantime, I also see the question
that many IDEs, integrated development environments,
offer some form of linting and auto-formatting,
and yes, they do, and I will comment more on that.
And indeed, running this,
it found that in line 10, there is something funny here.
So there was this parenthesis too much.
I will now open up the...
So this vi is my editor here that I can edit the file.
I will open it up and remove this wrong extra parenthesis here.
I will save and exit and run rough check again.
And now it finds these two other problems.
imported but never used, this variable is unused, can be removed. So that's neat.
It can help me declutter code. The same tool can also be used for auto-formatting code.
So here I took this function and I removed some spaces,
added some spaces.
So this code still works, it runs.
So Python doesn't mind, but it makes it now easier.
It makes it harder for me to read it, actually.
And with, well, let me do that.
I will copy this to my computer.
And paste it in here, this badly formatted one.
And the way I could now auto-format it is rough-format again, either with the file name
or please auto-format all the files.
And what you then get is, it will automatically format it according to recommended Python
style guide, which you can then configure.
So if you don't, if you really don't like four spaces
and you really want to have two spaces instead of four,
these are things you can configure.
There is a question in the chat.
What, what, can you define what is auto-formatting?
So maybe it's a quick kind of definition.
Yeah, so what it means is that I want it,
I want automatically to change the spaces
and line breaks to reformat it automatically, not by hand.
So I don't want to go here.
If you want to do it manually, it would look like this.
So manual formatting would look like that.
Like, oh yeah, there's too much space here.
This should go, this is manual formatting
and I don't want to do this manually.
So then I have a tool that will just do it in one shot.
You can even configure your editor to do that for you.
Some people let it format every time they save the file
and this has pros and cons, we can discuss them.
For instance, I have a key here on my keyboard
that I've configured.
If I press the key,
it will automatically format it for me.
This time with a different auto formatter.
So black is another popular auto formatter for Python.
Good.
There is more.
I will not demonstrate these because I admitted personally
I don't use them, but I want you to know that they exist.
So they are also tools that can check.
For instance, if you have type annotations
like this function expects a string
and it returns an integer.
There are tools that can help you check,
they can do analysis on types and help identify problems.
problems. You can integrate these with your editor. Many environments come with this already,
batteries included, but you can configure your editor to do formatting, linting for you.
Some editors then kind of underline problems like typos in a word document.
and you can also do this in your Jupyter Notebook.
So if there are three packages,
if you have them in your software environment,
then in your Notebook, there is an extra button
that you can press and it will auto-format your Python code.
If you use version control,
and version control is a way of
saving snapshots of the code as we develop.
You can even tell your version control
to please run these checks before I archive a new version.
Just looking at the questions.
But also they get good answers.
I might return to some of those.
So, I want to mention one more thing now that is AI-assisted coding, but before I do that,
I want to not forget, at the end of the notes, there is a feedback form.
And before you disconnect for today, please leave us feedback.
Tell us how it went today, tell us one thing that was particularly good, and one thing
that we should improve, change, remove for next time.
And I will use now a few more minutes to mention and discuss AI-assisted coding because it's
at least since for the last two years these tools are very popular.
I use them.
They come with risks.
I wanted to mention here. So what are the tools that I use? I use AI-assisted coding.
So this can either happen in the editor or I ask
the tool. In this case this was JGPT. I can ask it questions and then it can help me and we refine
the code and I can ask follow-up questions.
I use these in,
so sometimes I use them and I'm the,
like,
I use it as a kind of an assistant, an apprentice.
So I basically, I know the answer,
but I ask it to complete some task
or write a test for an implementation.
or if I have a test, I want to write the implementation for me
or I ask it to write the documentation.
Sometimes I'm the apprentice and I use it as a mentor
to explain a concept to me, to improve my code.
And sometimes it can show me a different
and possibly better way of implementing
than what I came up with.
So here, you know, kind of a chat format.
At least another way to use AI is this.
So this video that we see is,
that was me typing something in the editor
and AI suggesting of how it could continue
and then I can accept the suggestion or reject it.
So here I was implementing conversion
from Fahrenheit to Celsius.
And then if I like it, I press, I can kind of accept it.
And you can see that without much typing on my side,
I could come up with a pretty okay solution.
But I wanted to mention here that, of course,
these tools open up a box of questions, problems,
or sometimes they cost money.
There could be, they open up a box of legal
and ethical questions.
Definitely, there is a concern about privacy.
So I don't use these tools when it's about sensitive data,
personal data.
So if I need to open a file that contains
these kinds of sensitive information,
I don't open it with an editor
that then potentially sends information somewhere else.
And this information is processed
and I don't even know how.
Then there are more philosophical question.
I mean, will we still need to learn programming?
Yes, I think so, because it's still good to know the basics.
It's still good to know whether the answer
is that it's presented is reasonable or not.
How will it affect learning and teaching programming?
Are we going to learn better or slower?
I think these are questions for a different discussion.
Just having a look here at the questions and we are otherwise at the end of today's session.
So again, a reminder here about the feedback.
This is incredibly valuable for us.
Let us know how, how was the level, how was the speed?
Was it too easy, too difficult, too fast, too slow?
And the things that we can change already until tomorrow, we will try to.
maybe we can use the last few minutes to give a little outlook of what what
people can expect tomorrow at the third day of the workshop yeah so compared to
today is there any extra preparation for tomorrow and my hands are a bit full so
if someone can write it in the notes there yeah any particular wrap-up or
anything to do next. Yeah, your preparation. And this goes also to the other
instructors for tomorrow. Let us know what what people need to prepare. As far
as I know, if you can do today, tomorrow should be basically a lot like this. So
various topics, a little bit of intro to different things, nothing going too deep.
should i have a quick look of what topics we come up tomorrow and since i don't remember
all of them and i want you to know where you can find this information if i scroll up to
the top of the page here is the program and tomorrow we will have we will talk about libraries
how to choose libraries, when to decide,
how to decide between importing a library
or implementing it yourself.
Super important topic about how to manage dependencies
in Python, but this topic goes also beyond just Python.
So there we will talk about Conda environments,
virtual environments, environment.yaml, requirements.txt.
And then we have a longer session about parallel programming in Python. Yes it's
possible. So different techniques on how to do it and then how to package Python.
So this is when you want to create a Python package that other people can
conda install or pip install. And we will conclude with an outro. And these are all
all the really good things. Some are semi-important to scientists, some are sort of tangential,
but good things to know about. So, yeah. But yeah, if you like today, you'll probably also
like tomorrow.
Really looking forward. Thanks, everybody, for all the questions and for being here with
us thanks to [name] for the 40 sessions thanks to all the instructors but also
local helpers who are not visible here but really make this happen behind the
scenes and do a lot of local help yes okay back to the studio yeah okay so I'm
sharing the notes here, I guess. If there's nothing else to say we should
call it good, right?
Yeah, looking forward to tomorrow. Sounds good. Thanks everybody. See you next time.
See you then. Bye.
you