CodeRefinery.org
you
Hello, can people hear us out there?
Hello, hello, good morning, everybody.
And as usual, if you've registered, you have this notes document.
And there's still feedback from yesterday there, if you want to read.
Towards the bottom, we have day three icebreakers.
Yeah.
Hello, everyone.
I'm here with my co-instructors who you probably know.
Are you all ready for day three?
Yeah, I'm at least like I feel like it's been like an eternity
already.
Like there's so much stuff coming up.
I guess that somebody said yesterday in the notes that it would be fun to have it as a whole week
course or it could be a whole week course and I agree it could be because the ecosystem is so large
but I think our mental health wouldn't improve from that. It's a lot of work for everybody
especially for [name] and [name] who have done a lot of the work on the background.
I'd argue that the broadcasting side is actually one of the easiest sides by now. It just takes
time, but it's not that hard. Yeah, and in this case also the background work was [name] and
[name]. I did very little here, but I agree that it is a lot of work. It's much more than it looks like,
because there are so many people involved, and it's not easy to make things go smoothly.
But yeah, as stressed as you might be for this course, we're more stressed, I promise.
And do give us feedback, like yesterday's feedback was really great, and the day before
as well, because it really helps us hone in on what do we want to teach, because we really
want to make this as approachable to everybody as possible and get people invested or interested
and get everybody motivated about the ecosystem and the tools and the things so that they can
do their best work and the feedback really helps us hone in on what do we want to do
and for next iterations and so forth.
We are, for example, we were discussing yesterday after a couple of operating system specific
problems that we have seen, how we can improve on that, how we can make at least parts or
everything more adapted to the individual operating systems, maybe change some approaches
that we are currently using, but that's not coming this year, that's coming in the next
iterations of the course.
I really loved the question about what are your ideal winter holidays.
That was cool.
The ideal winter holidays, enough snow.
Yeah. Of all of us, let's hope [name]'s not the only one that gets enough snow.
Yeah.
But okay, so for the people here, what's the most surprising thing you learned so far
in this course? And for me, maybe it's the Vega Altair from yesterday. So not that there's
There's something better than matplotlib because, like, I knew there had to be.
Just because of... it's matplotlib.
It's old and all that.
But this way that you could connect the channels to the visual... or the columns to the visual
channels seemed like such an elegant way of doing things.
I'm still thinking about that.
[name], what about you?
It probably shouldn't have surprised me, but again, it always somewhat surprises me when all of the installation stuff is so complicated.
It's not because of anybody who's doing the installations, it's because of the ecosystem.
If you remember the XKCD yesterday when we talked about the data formats where somebody
creates a new one, with the installers and everything, it's still very much like that.
There's new stuff coming all the time and it's still very complicated.
us it's very like we have gotten used to often in the cases to the ways that we have done stuff for
years and then there's still so many different experiences but by different people and different
kinds of like workflows so it's sometimes yeah like surprising when you remember that okay like
why is this so complicated sometimes? And of course, it at least lets me into usually this
rabbit hole of Googling, like there has to be a better way. And we'll talk about that,
this kind of like approach a lot today, like how do we find better ways when it comes to
these problems. But I think Altair was also, for me, a great lesson.
Okay. I would say it's most interesting or surprising, but I noticed again how
kind of actually bad we are in trying to figure out what the problem is when we probably should
should be asking more questions because there was a couple of the issues with some setups
not working properly is probably because of the software as such and interactions in between,
for example, in that case, Windows Subsystem for Linux and Scalene, where there are existing
issues noted and we try to throw commands at people and help them. So here's this, here's
that, try this, try that. While it's probably just not solvable at the moment because there
is a kind of bug in the underlying system. And yeah, probably we need to get better at
and finding out what kind of issues we will expect
or we will have to expect.
Because, yeah.
Yeah.
Okay.
[name], did you already answer?
Not yet.
So yeah, what did I learn?
What was the surprising thing?
So I think every time preparing the workshop,
I learn a lot.
I think the best way to learn is to teach
or to promise that you will teach amazing learning
because you, so I learned a lot in the last few days
before like preparing material.
Yesterday, we also, after the workshop,
we had an interesting discussion about these like tooling,
these, how did we call it?
We called it productivity tools
because yesterday I showed a couple of productivity tools
in the command line.
And then we had a discussion later
that actually nobody uses the command line.
Well, I do, but that people like to use it
inside the editor.
So then I spent some time improving my editor
so that I can use these productivity tools
directly out of the editor,
like language server, formatting, these kinds of things.
And I was surprised how nice, how easy that is
and what all the amazing things you can do in your editor,
whatever the editor that is. In my case it's Vim, but it's it's possible to do in
any editor. So that was good improvement for me.
Yeah, okay, well it's the 10 o'clock in Helsinki now. Should we begin?
Maybe if we can give the outline of the day. So first we quickly talk
about library ecosystem. And the point here isn't to talk about specific
libraries, although we might, but sort of a general discussion on when to reuse
things that other people have. We've had fascinating conversations in the
pre-stream instructor room thinking, what do we even want to say here? So let's
see what comes up there. Then dependency management. So this is where we talk
about what conda is and what this Python for sqcomp environment is, how you would use it yourself,
why you would use it, and so on. Then before and after lunch we talk about parallel programming
some. We see how you actually can do it in Python if you adapt the problem the right way.
And then we end with packaging, which is basically if you have some code and want it to be reused,
how it's actually not that hard to make it where it can be pip installed by someone else,
and how it can be used even locally. So with that being said,
library ecosystem is a panel discussion, so should we all stay on here? And should I change to whose
screen? If you change to mine, but I will at least initially stay on the notes so that
we can directly interact with the audience when they have questions.
Okay, it's there.
Okay, so yeah, the library ecosystem is, I would say the library ecosystem in Python
is huge. There are loads and loads of libraries that provide many, many functionalities.
some more common, some less common. I think we have kind of covered at least some of the
libraries that are usable by almost anyone when it comes to data analysis,
but for a lot of scientific questions you will need to have some functionalities that are
not covered in these packages and one thing here is that we can't cover everything we can't cover
every single field that is available so going into individual package descriptions is
maybe interesting for the few people who are exactly in that field but potentially relatively
useless to anyone else. So we thought it would probably be better to discuss a bit how do we
search for libraries, how and when do we use libraries, when do we re-implement things or
implement things ourselves instead of using a library, and how do we kind of judge what
libraries we are using. And yeah I would like to kind of open this up to
to the panel. Let's start with [name]. How are you using or in what case would you be using
a library versus when would you rather implement something yourself?
Yes, so I'm very much of the opinion that I reuse libraries. I prefer that because I
this kind of idea usually that in my mind I'm very optimistic usually when it comes to all kinds of
things and that brings a risk with it and risk is that I think that I can implement something
and that is a major risk when it comes to programming because when you dive deep into
something and you try to implement it yourself you realize that okay here are the problems
you encounter the problems. You first make much of success, you think that it's going well,
and then you realize that there's problems. You encounter a wall, and then you realize that,
hey, somebody else has tracked this road. You notice that somebody else has done the same kind
of thinking, because I'm no unique individual. There's lots of people who can do the same kind
of thinking. And then I realized, okay, somebody has trekked this road and tackled those problems
that I encountered, and maybe I should use that. At the same time, I agree that it's a nice
ego booster when you manage to do something hard yourself. But at the same time, usually that
involves lots more than unknown unknowns that you don't know about. So I'm very much of the
approach that I usually try to, especially when it comes to hard stuff, I try to use stuff that
other people have created. And especially things that other people depend on. So for example,
like NumPy or Pandas that we talked about previously, they are libraries that are like
at the bottom layer of a lot of other stuff. So those must be really sturdy because the other
stuff is built upon them, right? They must be really good at what they do because otherwise
other people would encounter problems with those libraries. And that's why I often, especially
if it's a library that I find that, okay, other people have built upon this library,
I think that maybe I can trust it as well, because I see that other people are using it.
How about [name], when do you use libraries and how much would you use them?
Yeah, hi everybody. I'm also so much looking forward to this discussion session here.
This is really cool and really also nice that we get questions in.
And I will also answer your question in a moment,
but I also just to have this like fireside chat ambience,
I created this cozy light lighting here.
Fully agree with you, I will almost always use a library
rather than re-implementing it myself.
I think the challenge that many people have
is to sometimes not knowing that a library exists.
So how do you find out what is the name of the library
that has implemented the thing that I have in mind?
And earlier, I was more tempted to just program it myself
and then later figured out that it exists.
Today, I would probably describe what I want to do
in like a search engine or some AI tool and ask,
can you suggest me the three typical libraries
that do this, and then I would browse them and look at it.
And just to offer a little like a different opinion
also on different experience, little devil's advocate,
there is one situation where I'm sometimes
not reusing a library.
And that is when I need one function from it,
one function from it, one single thing,
and I could implement a function in 10 lines, five lines.
Let's say I could implement it in five lines of Python.
And then I'm thinking, well, should I write these five lines
or should I import the library?
And it's a question that not only affects me,
it will also affect the next person
who will then install MICE, who wants to run my script.
They will have to then also install the library
and the dependencies.
So sometimes I re-implement,
but only then, only if it's like five lines,
otherwise always reusing.
How much efficiency are you willing to sacrifice
by re-implementing yourself
contrasted to using a library
that potentially uses a lot faster underlying methods?
Yeah, great point.
I mean, if efficiency counts,
it will, I will most, I will reuse it.
it will be very difficult for me to,
or not difficult, it will take me time
to come up with an efficient implementation
and then my time is maybe best spent somewhere else.
So I would only implement it myself
if it's very little code
and if the efficiency doesn't matter in that place.
Great point.
I have something similar, I'm recently doing quite a bit of web programming and
the biggest issue that I commonly encounter when trying to use libraries or use library classes functions
is that they do almost what I want them to do.
But then there is a small thing that's missing
and this small thing is buried somewhere in the code of that library.
So there's very often just not an option to change
this specific part.
And then I'm really at this,
should I essentially copy paste the source code
of that file and use it?
Because I want to use essentially 99% of the code
for this specific class,
and I don't want to re-implement it
because it's completely pointless to re-implement it.
Do I just copy-paste that code at the license
and say, well, this is how it is,
and then change my two lines that I need to change?
Or do I inherit from that and then say,
well, I override a certain function in there?
But this is always quite tricky,
because if you do the letter,
so you just overwrite a function,
maybe the library changes at some point
and then your code is no longer compatible
with what the library did.
And then you can also run into quite annoying problems.
Yes, I think you really named it
because one thing is you also mentioned it very briefly,
but it's licensed.
So as soon as when we copy code and adapt it,
we have to think about licensing
and this is maybe a little bit outside.
but really important topic and then the other problem is that the moment you copy code
and change it you disconnect yourself from the development of the library
and how do you then keep up because the library keeps being developed and adapted
to later versions and bug fixes and you disconnect yourself from all of this.
Before this stream started when we were like checking audio and screen share we had a
fun discussion about, like, should we build our own tools? [name], you had a cool analogy on,
like, libraries and building tools. Maybe we can repeat that. I really liked that.
Yeah. So basically, like, let's say you are a, like, wood craftsman. You do woodworking.
Like, a lot of people who do woodworking, they could, in principle, like, do their own tools.
so many people do and iron metalworking people like that they can like create their own axes
like they can like take take a good piece of wood and a good piece of iron and make make their own
axe it's it's in principle shouldn't be that complicated but of course it is more complicated
like it you need to harden the steel so that it doesn't like fly into your face and you need to
sharpen your axe and stuff like that. And of course, you can buy artisan axes from the internet
and you can create bespoke versions of axes that are unique and special to you. But in many cases,
it's much cheaper and much more efficient to get the market axe that you go to your
general hardware store and there's a company that creates axes. And then they have a testing
schedule, they have a routine that they make, these kinds of general things. And then you know
what you get. And you know that there's lots of things probably involved in the process that you
don't necessarily think about. After you have had the axe fly into your face a couple of times,
maybe realize like a thing or two about like, okay, maybe I should, for the next iteration,
I should modify it a bit or something like that. But that might be a lot of work, whereas
companies and big entities or big communities, they usually have to test it out so that they can
like mass distributed. And I think when it comes to libraries and stuff like that, like
it also comes like what [name] said about the self-implementation, I agree with most of the
points. Like the idea that do I really, am I really interested about this? Like am I, if you
want to, if you find it relaxing to create your own access and your own tools, of course, it's
is a good idea to do that.
But if you feel like, for example, the editor thing,
lots of people like to edit their editors.
I don't like it because I know that I would just
get stuck doing that, and then I don't do any work at all.
But if you really like what you're doing,
if you like crafting your tools, of course,
that's a really great thing to do.
But if you're not interested in how JPEGs are created or something,
it's better to use a library that can open you the JPEG than re-implement the things.
And, for example, with image processing, there's lots of security implications
when you need to open, let's say, images and stuff like that,
that are included in the image libraries.
Now, I'm not interested about knowing anything about that.
I will gladly give that to other people, so somebody who's interested about those aspects
can focus on them, and I can choose which tools I want to craft, which tools I'm really
passionate about and interested about.
I think this plays a bit at least into one question that we have in the notes about how
how we determine whether a library is correct and reliable.
And I just, what I want to say to that is,
of course, there is the problem
if it gives the right results.
If it doesn't give the right results and there are,
well, the only way to do that
or to check that is by reasonable testing.
But irrespective of whether it gives the right results,
whether something is reliable
is a really difficult question to answer.
Because especially in open source projects,
people can contribute and there could be something
coming into a code base that shouldn't be coming in.
And that has happened in the past,
but very often it was detected early enough.
To me, on the other hand, if you start to worry about each individual piece of software
that you're using, you essentially have to start worrying, okay, how much do I trust
the operating system that I'm using?
How much do I trust whatever company that I'm buying something from?
something that at least we currently encounter quite a bit is that in the end a lot of questions
are liability questions in that respect, where it's really more the can I point to someone
that if something happens, can I point to this is not me kind of and that's what also
universities are of course trying to do to say okay well no no I it is not our
responsibility we were just buying using a product and it's something that I'm
not sure if there is any real solution normally what I try to do is I have a
look at the code I have a look at what it's roughly what it's doing I will not
go through thousands of lines of code to check if everything is correct but that's
So a good point.
So what are the things that you look at?
Let's say you have like three minutes to decide
whether you like experiment with the library
or whether you move on to the other library.
What would you look at?
So commonly how recent is the development
is one big factor.
One other factor is also a bit number of contributors.
So if it's a single person library,
I'm more inclined to skip it, actually, than if you have like 10, 20 contributors.
That's a bit my opinion, at least.
If you have multiple people working on this, you have multiple people interested in it,
and it gets more difficult to sneak something in because you have more eyes watching.
If it's a single person, I have to kind of rely on that person not doing anything while
if I have a larger group, I do have more eyes that normally have a look at and would kick
someone out who has malicious intent, for example.
Then potentially number of stars on GitHub, so how many people are actually using this
or at least indicating that they're using it
is also, I think, a reasonable indicator.
Yeah, that's-
I can also mention that on like Python package index,
we will mention it later today what that is.
You can look at statistics, like how many downloads.
And if I see that there are 200,000 downloads,
it's 200 people, 200,000 people using it
and probably it's reasonably tested.
How about you, [name]?
things that you look at when.
Yeah, like I like most of the things that you also mentioned,
but but like, you brought me flashbacks. Like when you were
talking, like I got got some like, flashbacks of like, like
one one thing that often often people forget about open source
is that you can actually go and look at the source. Like,
because, like, that's part of the like, the appeal, right?
like it's open there. And quite often, like in a recent project that I was working on,
I've just gone to the source. Like if the documentation, for example, isn't up to date,
or like if I don't understand, like if it doesn't have, it has functionality I need,
but it doesn't yet have, like especially fast moving new projects. Now with the like age of
like AI coding, you can see a lot of projects that will have massive amounts of code created
and massive amounts of functionality created by AI, most likely, or AI-powered coding.
And it can create this kind of enterprise code that looks pretty promising. But often,
let's say the APIs or documentation might be a long way off from what the codes shows.
In those cases, I've often just went to the code and see what is implemented in the code
and follow that through.
For many cases, the documentation doesn't explain a parameter or something.
Then I just go to the code and see how it is implemented there.
Is it reasonably implemented there?
Are there something in there?
Of course, that can sometimes be a rabbit hole as well, but nowadays, let's say GitHub
has good search functions for that. Sometimes I just download the whole repository and then I use
some editor with a good definition following so that I can go through the file and see,
okay, where is this actually implemented? Where is the actual meat of this meal?
When I call a class or whatever, it's usually like, okay, it calls a super class and another
a class and then there's like classes all the way down and in the end there's like a function,
that small piece. And it can be like, okay, like this small piece is like, I could have
implemented this myself as well. So like diving, sometimes diving into the code is also useful
because then you can actually like see, like basically see the ingredients where the meal
has been constructed from. So are the ingredients good for the meal, basically? You can go to the
kitchen and check, are the ingredients good? And then you can decide, okay, do I actually want to
eat this meal? But of course, this is when you have already somewhat invested yourself into the
ecosystem or the specific package. But sometimes after these kinds of deep dive, you notice that,
hey, actually, I don't like what they're doing here. Maybe I shouldn't use this.
I like the analogy with the meal, and I think libraries sometimes also work. It's also about
social trust. If you tell me that a restaurant is really good, I trust you, and I will go there
and test it out. If I'm invited somewhere for dinner, I trust that you don't go check out
out in the kitchen, how the meal is.
So it's also about that.
I had a look, one thing I would like to mention,
I had a look in the, what people wrote
as their favorite libraries.
And there are actually two kinds of libraries.
And one is libraries that we have to install,
you know, pip install, conda install.
But a couple of libraries that I mentioned there
are also libraries that come with Python.
They are standard.
And some of them are not well known.
and they could use more love.
And for instance, one library that I use a lot
is Collections or IterTools or Bisect.
And what I want to say here is that I encourage,
like when we ask what to do on a,
what do you like to do on a winter's day for relaxation?
I don't know if it's bad weather
and you need to stay inside.
I also recommend to browse standard Python libraries
because there is a lot of cool stuff
I wish I knew before and many of these things I have accidentally re-implemented in a bad way
only to find out that it comes with Python. Installation, nothing to install, it's there.
Yeah, one good example of this to say I completely agree with Rono and one good
example is also data classes in base Python. So if you have to a class that has like various
kinds of like data in it like this kind of like it represents I don't know like a generic thing
configuration or something like that it's very powerful as well. There's multiple of
other implementations or similar concepts from various libraries but Python, base Python has also
a great one. Yeah there is the question about how do you keep code easy to reconfigure
particularly in the light of recent developments with, for example, Anaconda, and suddenly
saying that, yeah, we now want academic institutions also to pay, and so potentially
having a service set up and once enough people are using it saying, yeah, now we would like to
have some money at least. To me, I think to some extent it's relying on open source tools
because yes, Anaconda has suddenly changed their billing or their licensing scheme and
they can do that. They are providing a service by essentially providing the infrastructure.
However, the tools that are being used to use that infrastructure are open source.
So you can use the same tools to point to a different index at which point you are out
of there, out of the dependency.
And if there is something like that, it's very likely that alternatives will come up
from the open source community and essentially mirror what Anaconda has done so you can get
around this at least to some extent. If you would have a closed source program that does
this, so if Conda would be closed source, this whole dependency management system, then
dependency management system, then you're stuck.
So using open source software allows you to,
makes it much more likely that you will be able
to reconfigure and change to a different place.
While if you are in a closed source environment,
yeah, you are dependent on, especially nowadays
since it's very often no longer,
I'm buying the product and paying one price,
but I'm buying a subscription and I pay yearly
and I have no influence on how much
they will charge next year.
And this brings a great follow up question
I would want to ask from you, which is like,
in which situations would you actually go
with a closed source alternative?
Like, in which situations you would use
a closed source code?
Like, mainly if I want to not be responsible for anything
that happens due to the software.
So if I can essentially say, reliability, yep.
I'm using this tool.
I have a license with them.
That essentially covers that if something
goes wrong with the tool, I can push the liability away.
I would always prefer open source.
So if open source doesn't exist, then closed source, unless, I don't know, the closed source
has so much more like reach, exposure, visibility.
It's maybe more about services than libraries.
For libraries, I would prefer open source.
And I would also like you to answer the question.
I just want to remind all of us,
we have like two, three minutes left in this session.
So let's all think about like some closing statements.
But how about you, [name]?
Yeah, I would say the same as you did.
Like if there's a specific tool,
like it's a Python interface for,
I don't know, like a simulation suite or something
that is tied to like a closed source product,
then yeah, then in those situations.
But yeah, I wouldn't build upon that
because, like again, it costs me money
and it costs everybody who wants to use it money as well.
One question I would want to ask,
that is, somebody asked about
whenever do you branch your repositories?
And I would take that question and move it a bit
and ask, have you contributed to the pot?
Like, have you contributed to open source projects
And how do you feel about contributing to open source libraries?
And that's a great question to conclude this session, we can maybe all answer, because
with the libraries, we should think not only about taking, but also about giving back.
It can come in many different forms.
It can come, I don't know, buying people coffee, or sending a contribution back.
So not only like branching off
and keeping the improvement for myself,
but also maybe suggesting the improvement back
or giving feedback or sending like a nice message
or thank you and citing their work.
And for companies, startups,
those who use open source libraries and have the money,
I think it would be also nice then to sponsor the work.
Very important question.
[name], what do you think?
Yes, I have and yes, I do
try to contribute back.
Admittedly, I think most of the contributions that I'm
providing are less the actual implementations,
but more suggestions and
potentially bug reports.
I sometimes, at least for more complex libraries,
I often just don't have the time to go through all the code
of the library to find where I need to fix this.
And there are people who have worked with that library
for whom it's probably a, yeah, okay,
a couple of lines of code that I need to change,
while I would really need to learn the whole infrastructure
and depending on what it is,
I don't even know what the basic infrastructure of that is.
So, I think contributions in forms of issue reports
and stuff are also very, very useful
to a programmer that has created a library.
And while some people think that open issues are a problem,
I personally think a library without any open issues
or without any issues happening, yeah, is a dead library.
because that essentially indicates no one is using it
because there is nothing that doesn't have issues.
Yeah.
And the contribution doesn't even have to,
it doesn't have to be code.
It can also be one can contribute back with documentation,
with helping with tutorials.
So even like learning a library
can be a really good useful perspective to contribute
and how you use, how you get started,
how contributing back with a tutorial.
I can see that we are now two minutes over time.
Any final statements from this session
before we give the microphone to the next episode
where we will talk about dependency management,
which is having very related.
Maybe some final words from [name].
Oh, I don't have much more, let's just go on.
Okay.
Yeah.
Then let's send it over to the next one.
I wish we had much more time.
This was really fun.
Keep the questions coming.
We will be following those
And we wish we had more time,
and we would love to talk about this for hours.
Thanks a lot for this session.
Okay, thanks.
Okay, I've shared my notes copy again,
so you can, yeah, it's [name] and [name].
Yeah it's [name] and [name]. Yeah I can give a screenshot if you reach out again like
can you feed it to the... You have the full thing. Can you feed it to the right side?
Yeah. Okay. What do you want it to do? Yeah it should be the left side. Okay I
I can, is this?
Yeah, a bit narrower.
Yeah, we didn't realize to do the technical checkup before.
Great, so see you later.
Yeah, bye.
So, hello, we have a new instructor.
[name], do you want to introduce yourself?
Yeah, hi, [name].
I was just following your library ecosystem
and it was a great discussion.
Well done, and now we have a good basis
to start this lesson as well.
So my name is [name].
I'm joining you from Oslo, University of Oslo,
and I'm also part of the ENRIS training team,
and also the Code Refinery training team.
Yes, looking forward, [name].
Yeah.
So yeah, let's jump right in.
So if you, [name], put my screen on there.
So let's talk about dependency management.
So in the previous session,
we talked a lot about library ecosystem
of how we have so many libraries in Python.
And that can of course like create a situation where,
okay, we need to use those libraries.
How do we manage this?
How can we install so many different libraries
and how can we manage this thing?
And here we are going to go through like the basic things that happen in the Python ecosystem
and the basic words. So previously during the installation, like discussions and so forth in
the previous days, you might have heard a lot of terms thrown around that might be like a bit
confusing, a bit new for you. So, we'll go through those and we'll talk about dependency management
well, in basically two different kinds of ways that we'll go to in a second.
So, let's start straight up. So, where do people get stuff from? Where do we get those libraries
from. So, yes, from, you know, pip install, for example, or the conda, that's usually the places.
Yes. So, there's like two major players here or two major things that are not completely
separate, but they are the major things. So, there's the Python package index,
the PyPI index, which is a collection of huge amounts of Python packages.
And these have been crafted so that they can run on most of the operating systems, usually.
And basically, anybody can publish their packages in Python Packaging Index. So,
there's a huge amount of packages, like small packages, large packages, and stuff like that.
And they are often installed with this tool called pip. I'll talk about the installation
tools a bit more in a second, but let's first look at the index. The index has a lot of Python,
like pure Python code, but it also has some libraries that have some C code, for example,
like NumPy. It has some C code inside of it so that it can run the stuff fast. It has all of
those in these so-called wheels. It's all a Monty Python joke, like Python is a Monty Python joke,
and the wheels are wheels of cheese and whatever. The names are strange, but it's basically like a
big collection of these packages. Another layer that we have been talking about is the
Conda ecosystem. So the Conda ecosystem is a bit different. So why Conda? Why not just the Python
packaging index? And the reason is that, like I mentioned, many packages require external libraries.
And what can happen is that you suddenly realize that, okay, the amount of Python code
is quite small compared to the amount of libraries
that you need to bring with the Python code.
So, and then you suddenly can get into a situation
where in order to get like a actually working ecosystem,
you need to bring a huge bunch of like libraries with it.
And this company called, it was Continuum Analytics
previously, now it's Anaconda Incorporated.
they created this ecosystem that they,
it's an, they create the open source tools for it.
And what it does is that it packages
the older dependencies as well.
So basically like you can have like a Python package
and it can have the dependencies to other packages
like C packages and like other kinds of libraries
And it can manage all of that mess of which Python packages you install and which dependencies
for these Python packages you install.
It's basically almost like a fake operating system kind of a situation where it contains
basically all kinds of packages from a whole operating system.
And it's like also it's published for Macs and for Linux and for Windows.
So there's different so-called builds of these packages for different kinds of operating systems.
The packaging in their side is a bit more complicated, but anybody can as well contribute
to that ecosystem.
So it's an open source ecosystem.
So that was, I think, a very important analogy you made, you know, not just dependencies,
or operating system level dependencies. For example, when you work with Unix operating system,
we feel we encounter this more. For example, if you want to install NumPy, NumPy comes with a lot
of header files and C code. So that PIP can actually install those code. So what happens is
we have some wrappers in Python for the C code, but the C code itself could compile. But if you're
If you're using Windows, it will pull down the wheel
and it will set it up for you, even in Mac.
But some operating systems, you feel
that when you install PIP, it takes longer time.
It would do some compilations, so it compiles the C code.
But when it comes to Conda, it actually
not only the code, the NumPy code that's being compiled,
but it's also compiled some open SSL libraries, for example,
OS-level dependencies, and it packages
binary file compiled for your system. So which also brings up other challenges. For example,
if you use very exotic versions of certain OS, that package might not work. But for Windows,
Mac, and Ubuntu and most of the versions, Conda is capable of providing this pre-compiled sets.
Is that a correct way to look at it?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Basically, like Conda tries to answer questions beyond Python, like many
of these harder questions. That can happen when you have dependencies go further and
further away, and Conda can solve some of these. But this brings the Conda ecosystem
at the same time, even though it sounds like, okay, this sounds great, it has its own
complications. And the complications, we'll get to that right now. So the complications are these.
So first off, maybe last year, you might have heard the Anaconda Incorporated, they made
like a change to their licensing terms. So they provide certain tools or certain
ways of installing conda ecosystem that they wanted to basically get money from universities
and well at least in my opinion that was the situation they wanted well people to pay for
the resources that they provide and it created like lots of confusion in the ecosystem and now
they have clarified their stance in that. Maybe we should go through them in order.
So the Konda installation tool and these community channels provided by repositories
that Anaconda provide, they are free. But the Anaconda repository and Anaconda's own channels
and the Anaconda installers and so forth, they are free for universities and companies with 200
or fewer people. But non-university research institutions and national laboratories require
licenses. Then there's also tools like Miniconda are free when they don't download Anaconda's
packages and like MiniForge and all of this open source stuff is free. So this affected our course
as well. So we didn't want to, we previously recommended people to use Anaconda to install
the course environment or just get Anaconda. But now we have switched to recommending MiniForge
because it's well free for everybody. And this can bring this kind of like
complexity to the ecosystem, because now you need to be mindful of the licenses and whether
you can use certain tools.
And maybe we can, yeah.
Sivak, can you explain a little bit about, you know, we are talking about two things,
the conduct, the package manager or the thing or the program that installs the packages
and we have the place where the actual packages are.
Yes.
So when this license issue came, especially in our setup, it was very difficult to explain
this because some of the users, they are used to modifying the Conda environment itself,
the base environment.
So they just keep on installing things.
So can you clarify a little bit more, what is the Conda command and what is this package
you're talking about?
Yeah, that's a great point.
And let's do that right now.
So there's these packets repository.
So places where packages come from.
So there's this Anaconda community repository, which is this Anaconda cloud.
So the free versions or the free channels, so it houses multiple channels.
So some of these channels are free and some of them are not.
So for example, Anaconda's own channels are not free, but it houses like lots of different
installation locations.
And then there's Anaconda's own repository, which is all Anaconda's stuff.
Then inside this repository, there's channels, and these are basically installation locations
or folders, and there are these Anaconda's proprietary ones, but then there's free ones
as well.
Forge is the biggest free channel there is.
It's like 27,000 packages right now.
And we would recommend that probably in most cases
for everybody, because if you get it from there,
it's community managed, community built,
and it's definitely free.
Then there's the tools that are used to install the stuff.
like Anaconda. When we talk about Anaconda, we say that it's a distribution of conda packages.
It's a distribution of conda packages by Anaconda Incorporated. Miniconda is this kind of like
smaller installer that they provide, but by default it uses the Anaconda's channels.
So it uses the proprietary ones. But Miniforge is the same as Miniconda, but it uses the free ones.
So, and there's also this micro-Mamba, which is like a smaller installer,
especially useful for automated installations, which you can create environments with.
And all of these distributions, they use this installer or package manager called Conda or Mamba.
And Conda is the original one written in Python by the Conda people,
and Mamba is an alternative, which is faster in most cases,
because it uses a different kind of package solver.
But Conda nowadays, they have switched to using Mamba's solver.
So in many cases, Conda can be similar kind of speed,
but only for the most recent versions of Conda.
But this brings this kind of situation where there's the proprietary one and there's an
open source alternative.
There's a proprietary repo and there's open source repository.
There's proprietary channel, there's open source channel.
There's proprietary distribution, there's the open source distribution.
There's the proprietary, well, not really the package managers, well, proprietary created
package manager and the open source created package manager. So there's always these options,
how could I say, with these. So now you said, mentioned many, many things. If I don't want to
think about this too much and if I just want to create my environment, can you give me a default
package manager and a default channel I could set up without thinking too much?
Well, what would be the easiest?
Yeah, so the easiest one would be to pick MiniForge and use
CondaForge and use Conda or Mamba.
And that's the easiest one to use as a default one,
I would say.
But let's talk about, OK, we have
talked about the ecosystem.
Okay, there's PyPy and that uses pip to install packages.
And there's the Conda ecosystem with all of this stuff.
How do we actually use it?
How do we actually use this?
Like now we have gone through maybe a lot of the legalese,
I'm gonna say it on this.
So how do we use these?
So why even use these?
Like why can't we just install Python in other ways?
And the reason is that we want to use environments.
So we want to have usually a situation where we can separate a project or a thing we're
doing from all of the other stuff we're doing.
And for that, we often want to install stuff in these environments.
So we want to install our Python packages in specific versions of Python packages we
want for the specific project that we want into its own world where it doesn't affect other worlds,
because otherwise it can quite easily get into a situation where stuff doesn't work anymore,
or you need to use a different package version for a different project that you're working on,
and suddenly it gets cumbersome and hard. And also the other one brought a great point about
but like you cannot really replicate it.
You don't have the receipts of like what you have built.
Like you don't know what, where are you?
What sort of ecosystem are you in if you don't have,
if you haven't created an environment for it?
Like you don't really, it's very hard to know
what packages your code actually needs and what uses
if you don't start from the point of,
okay, let's start with the documentation
of what packages we need to get something done.
So I also have so many environments.
So as you said, without modifying the same environment
for all the work, even when I'm sharing my work
with somebody else, it's easier to communicate
rather than shifting my laptop, not the entire thing,
but this is the libraries that you need.
But one thing I encounter a trouble, like I face a lot
is that sometimes I have my environment
and I do install on top of it,
but I don't know what exactly I have installed.
So I think people will also do that.
So they may start with the environmental file
or like a requirement file and then they might modify it.
So how could we also navigate this complexity?
Let's first check, I will answer that in a second,
but let's first check,
how do we even create an environment?
So let's look at what is an environment?
How do we specify it?
Like, how do we specify what is an environment?
So if you're using Conda,
an order-related ecosystem like Conda, Mamba,
all of that jazz,
you might see this file called environment.yaml.
It can be called whatever,
but it's often called environment.yaml.
And what it has is this YAML syntax
where you have the name of the environment,
then you usually define what channels you want to use.
And this is important because otherwise,
like whatever installer you're using
picks the defaults of that installer.
So if you're using miniconda, it suddenly uses defaults.
If you're using miniforge, it uses condaforge.
And you don't want to give this sort of ambiguity
of where do you get the stuff.
You want to define that, okay, use, let's say, Conda4.
And then you can specify what dependencies you want.
And these dependencies are like the library names
that you want to use.
And how do you create this environment?
Usually, these can be created
like from an Anaconda Navigator and tools like such,
but from the command line,
which is often how you would run these,
it would be like conda enable create dash dash file,
and then you give it the environment file,
and it will create you the environment.
If you're using Mamba, just switch Mamba
to in the place of conda, and it would do that.
And this is how conda manages.
Like this specifies, okay,
I want python numpy matplotlib and pandas.
Like you can specify what your code needs,
and you can create your own environment
on the packages you need.
If you're using virtual environments,
so virtual environments are similar to Conda environments.
So they're like their own neat boxes of code
that have their own libraries.
And they use this file called requirements.txt
or PPUs this requirements.txt.
So in many repositories,
you might have seen this requirements.txt file.
And it's just a list of packages, basically.
And if you create a virtual environment,
then you run this python-m-virtualenv,
and then the name of the environment.
Then you usually need to activate this environment.
So you basically make this Python
and this environment your current one.
and then you can use pip to install your packages inside of it.
So we are talking about two things here, isn't it [name]? One is the Conda and one is
Python environments. But I think you're mentioning this together to maybe understand easier that you
could do either way. Yes.
So what is your purpose of describing like one with the YAML format and one with the text format
and one with Konda and Pip. Do people need to know all these things?
That's a great point. So do you need to do both of them? No. You can choose whichever
ecosystem you want to use. The Konda ecosystem has... If you have a bigger project with a lot
more complexity, especially if you're doing something like deep learning or stuff like that,
the Conda ecosystem provides you usually maybe easier to manage this kind of very complex
ecosystem, as long as you define what you need there. And in the Pip ecosystem, it's much more
lightweight, I would say, but it also can install many of the same tools, and it's much more
straightforward. But yes, you can do either or. So you can either use these virtual environments
all these conda environments to create your own world where you're installing stuff.
So, sorry for a short disturbance, because in the HackMD, there's a question about what is
a dependency? Maybe some people might benefit if you could explain a little bit what you mean by
that.
Yeah. So here, dependencies basically mean, same in the requirements.txt, they're basically
name of the libraries that you're using, name of the library packages that you're using.
So in the environment.yaml specification, you have this list called dependencies.
So it's like you have these dashes that describe each entry in that list. And it just means that,
okay, I want this stuff here. It can be all kinds of stuff. It can have compilers or different
installation tools or other packages. The Conda ecosystem provides huge amounts of different
kinds of packages, but mainly what you are looking for when you're creating these environments,
how do you define or decide on what to add here? Usually look at the imports.
If you have a code that does import, it does import pandas, import numpy, import whatever.
if you add that as the dependency, that usually solves the import. Because if you install that
library, then the import will work and then you have that package in the environment.
So usually what you want to do is, if you don't know what packages you need,
just look what your code uses and then ask for those. And then for Conda and also for Peep,
there's an internal solver that will solve, okay, what does Pandas need? And then it will
solve all of the stuff from there on out. And you should really specify only the stuff that
your code actually needs and let the tools handle all of the busy work of solving,
okay, what does Pandas need? What do I need to get NumPy and so forth?
Yeah, I think that explains.
And now I think we can answer the question that you asked, okay, like how do we then
update these or how do we manage, like how can we create more packages to these environments?
And here comes the tricky thing that sometimes makes stuff confusing or complicated.
And it's that because all of these tools, the tools are meant to help you install a
complex list of dependencies, so a complex list of different packages.
And because they can come from various sources and they can be very complicated, like the
installations can be very complicated, there's lots of packages there, and they need to figure
out what packages play nice with each other. This is why if you do manual installations,
you can do manual installations into these environments, like install packets,
like just put something there. But what often happens is that because the solver doesn't know
about what other stuff is needed here, it can mess up the environment because it doesn't have
the knowledge of what other stuff was required here. The best solution in most cases is to
update the environment based on an updated specification. You add a new package to the
dependency list. Let's say you want to install Vega Altair or something. You would add that to
the dependency list and then you would update the environment and let the solver find you
the package and then install it to the environment. Sometimes there can be mismatches in the solve.
So let's say you want to install one package and then you want to install another package,
but there's no compatible way of getting these two working. Then the only solution is usually
to remove the previous environment and create a new environment or alternatively create a new
environment with a different name that does a fresh solve, like from a fresh starting point,
because then it can find the versions that actually work together. And that way you can
get a fresh installation that definitely works. And the problem with these packaging tools and
this is often like you might feel with the installations that, okay, you don't want to
to mess it up. Once you have it working, you don't want to wreck the boat. You don't want
to mess it up because it was so complicated to get it rolling. And here, the specification
really helps you. If you have created the environment YAML or the requirements TXT that
actually describes what your code needs, it's usually very easy to replicate the recreation
of the environment again. And it's also for your colleagues. If you have the receipts,
have the knowledge of what your program needs, then you can usually recreate the environment
on a whim. You can let go of this fear of, okay, I will break everything if I do any modifications
to the environment and I don't know how to replicate this environment or how to replicate
my workflow.
So in this environment, let's say if you want NumPy, when you use for the PIP installation,
you could specify NumPy equals two equal signs and 1.23.1, for example. And on the
conda file, you could also specify NumPy single equals or they use equal signs to mention
versions. Is that a good practice or what do you recommend?
Yes, so you can do stuff like this.
So let's look at the example,
what [name] was talking about.
So yes, you can specify version ranges
because like we mentioned, these package indexes,
they have multiple alternative versions
of these packages installed in them.
So in PyPy and in the content channels,
there's like hundreds of versions of the same package.
So hundreds of versions of NumPy, for example,
with all of the different major and minor versions
of the package installed.
And you can specify version ranges.
So if you want to make certain that the,
or specific versions,
if you want to make certain that you get a certain version.
And the reason why you might want to do this
is that like about the versioning scheme.
So most of the packages,
they apply a semantic versioning scheme
where the first number is the major version of the package.
The second version is this kind of like a minor version
and the third one is like a patch version.
And usually it's like the patch version
shouldn't affect any functionality.
There can be additions with minor versions
and major versions can like throw everything out basically.
So what you might want to do, for example,
is to limit yourself to some major version
or some minor version maybe, and this might be useful,
especially if you want to create a consistent environment
for a research project that you want somebody else
to be able to replicate later on.
So if you specify, okay, I want around these versions,
it's good, then they can later on replicate
same exact environment that you were using with the same exact versions. Of course, there might
be small differences in the builds and whatever. If they're using Mac and you were using Linux or
you were using Windows, they will always get different packages, but the functionality should
be the same because they have the same versions. That way, if you pin the versions, you can make
it possible to share the exact environment that you were using. But the problem with the pinning
of the version can be often that if you pin yourself to the version, you basically pin
yourself in time as well. So, if you lock yourself into a certain moment in time,
and the time moves forward, you're now still in that time. So, if the code changes, if there's
new changes in the code, if there's upgrades, patches, if there's fixes, if there's security
bugs fixed, you won't see those because you're still living in the past. And if you want your
code to be reusable and if you want your code to live instead of being stuck into a certain time,
you usually want to have it unpinned. So what you might do in a library, let's say,
if you write a project or something, you might want to have one environment file for replicating
your results and one environment file with three versions that just define, okay, these are the
versions that you need. And then when you see in your GitHub issues or wherever you have published
your code you see somebody say that okay now the code broke like now some dependency came along and
now it doesn't work anymore then you can say or maybe do you have you already have a test to check
for version updates then you can then say that okay like okay now I need to pin the version
because now there was a breaking change so in that case maybe shall we should mention a little
bit like best practices here for example if you can keep your requirement file together with the
code version controlled so that version of the code is for this requirement file because there
are i have used many times for example even simple numpy like way based the syntax which deprecates
so it will it will break in another version of numpy so if you can keep the code and the
the requirement file together. And also, if you can go to the next step, there we have
like a continuous, like a CI-CD pipeline, they call it, you know, continuous integration
delivery pipelines where we test the code with that requirement file and produce some
results. Do you think we have to think that deep or is there a simple way to do this?
How do we keep the requirement and the code closer?
Yeah, so one thing you can do is like you can use these continuous, like if you have a product that
you have created you can use this continuous integration to check the versions and if there's
something coming from upstream so-called, like if there's something coming from the dependencies
that okay like now they have changed something. Usually in Python people they do these deprecation
warnings. So if you see ever these deprecation warnings when you launch your code, that usually
means that stuff is going away in the next version. Usually people give these deprecation
warnings beforehand and you can use those to see that maybe I need to do a small modification
for the code because stuff can change in the future. But this is, I would say, for the people
who really want to maintain their own libraries for those people.
In the notes, there's lots of interesting talks about like, okay, should you have one
environment to rule them all or should you really have one environment for every package,
every project that you're working on? And that is, of course, a matter of opinion.
But my own personal opinion is that it's usually better to have an environment for a project
because then you can specify what exact things this project needs and other people can reuse it.
Because if you put everything, all of your packages into one big environment, you will get
an environment that works with many of your projects. But then if other person asks, okay,
what do I need to use your code? And you have to provide them with a document of like, you need
these 500 packages, then they're not going to be very happy because they think that, okay,
your project is using way, way too many packages. Like it looks unwieldy and maybe they cannot even
replicated. So having like separate at least four different projects is usually like a good
approach. One thing that I probably didn't mention is that Conda and Pip, they cache
many of the package installations, especially Conda does it so that like if you install the
same package into multiple environments, it's actually not using any Modak disk space.
It creates a new file, so in some faster environments it can be problematic, but it doesn't use
any more disk space because it can reuse the same package that was installed in another
environment.
So, it does this caching kind of a thing.
There's lots of magic underneath it, but it's not usually a big problem to create multiple
environments.
usually have something like, let's say, 20 environments.
And whenever I don't need these environments, occasionally,
I clean up most of them.
And if I need to recreate them, I
have the environment YAML to recreate them.
So I don't really worry about deleting the environments ever.
I just delete them when I don't need them anymore.
Of course, for research projects or long-term projects
that can be not tenable, you want
keep the same environment for a year or more. But usually it's every now and then it's a good idea
to maybe recreate it to verify that nothing has changed. Like it still works and then other
people can reuse it. Because it's all about also sharing. Like we rarely do projects just in our
own world. We often need to have other people verify our results, share our results. And for
For that, we need to be able to tell them how to install stuff.
And these tools make it possible to install stuff.
But if you don't know how to share, like you can give them instructions, of course,
like you can give, write them instructions, but wouldn't it be, it'd be better that
the machines understood those instructions and those instructions, like the machines
would handle it for you.
So you used, you used like a very interesting word there, delete.
So, the ability to delete an environment without breaking everything else is also an advantage
when you do it separately.
So that's also an advantage with PIPen and also the Conda environments that you could
actually delete things without breaking your like the whole operating system.
How do you delete, do you use the Conda to delete or is it even safe to just delete the
folder?
Does it make a difference?
Yes, so you can delete usually the folder.
It's using the condice.
I would prefer that one.
Usually, you don't want to put stuff
into your work in the environment itself,
because if you delete it, then you lose that.
So you want to keep your own code outside
of that environment usually.
But I think we are past the break time.
So I think we should probably close the session.
There was a lot of interesting discussion in the notes.
I will try to answer as many as possible.
Hopefully this was helpful for you,
this kind of like a rambling talk.
Sarpike, do you have any closing thoughts on the?
Yeah, so I mean, I would like to focus maybe on one question
that there's a mentioning of containers.
So what is the benefit of following up this kind of packaging practice than a container, for example.
So even in a container that you set your environment and you could distribute it.
But even in that case, let's say in the example of Docker, for example, if you are creating your environment with a Docker file,
not getting an image and then doing random modifications and saving the image where you can't reproduce.
That's more closer to how, what you explained, but the Docker environments and other, it
takes it to another level of isolation.
In addition, there's a question about, because we used a lot of terms like libraries and
packages and what the differences are, with the basic understanding of this, maybe you
could understand more, but is there like a quick way to sort of distinguish between a
library and a package? I'm not sure you're ready for that question.
Yeah, yeah. I think that's a good one. So the library and package, like library can mean
something that is not a Python package as well. So if you think about, I don't know, let's say
NumPy uses plus libraries underneath it to do the matrix calculations and all kinds of stuff.
So those are like, people don't probably know what plus libraries are, but you don't need to know
because they are like dependencies, but they are written in C++ and Fortran. And like library is
like a generic term, I would say for any kind of installation that provides you with something you
can import maybe. But package is usually like means that it's a Python package that you can
like import. So with Conda, you can install both of these kinds of things. So sometimes you need
these low-level libraries, sometimes you need these high-level libraries, or high-level libraries
like Python packages. But it's basically indistinguishable. The words is a bit of a
salad. Python packages are basically the same as libraries, but there's also more libraries.
So it's like a Venn diagram where libraries are bigger than packages, and the packages are inside
the libraries diagram. But yeah, it's a bit hard to... Yeah, I know. But for this lesson, I think
it's okay to say both are more or less the same. One last question, because of time,
does the order matter in the YAML file, the requirement file or the Conda environment file?
Does it matter whether you mentioned NumPy before Matplotlib or after Matplotlib?
No, no, it's a list.
It's a list. Okay. I think that was very nice. We have a basic understanding
of what we should do if we want to avoid trouble in the future.
Yeah.
After the break, we can probably jump to the parallel, but if there's some really interesting
question, we'll maybe talk about that.
But let's have a break.
You all deserved it.
It's been a lot of new stuff for the start.
So should we have a 15-minute break, or what's the schedule?
Let's see.
We can see.
Yeah.
I think we need a 15-minute break before we have the next session.
So thank you.
Thank you for all of the questions, and I'll try to answer them in the notes as well.
OK.
See you after the break.
you
Hello, we're back.
with me here is [name]. Oh hi, hi, hi, [name]. So, now we begin a session. This will start
before lunch and end after lunch. So, by the way, according to our current plan, lunch
would begin and end 10 minutes later to fit our exercises and discussions a little bit
better.
And it's about parallel Python.
So what does this mean?
What do we have here?
I've often heard that Python is not very good for parallel programming, but in fact it can
be done.
Can you tell us about that?
Yes, thanks [name].
So you are right there,
in part because Python itself was not constructed
to be, I mean, for high performance
or in order to be parallel.
However, over the years,
a number of frameworks have been built up
so that one can then offload compute-heavy stuff
to other components, which then might have been written in a language like C or Fortran.
I guess that's the whole like NumPy, Pandas, all these other libraries we learned, they're
all written there. And that's one form of offloading to the efficient code.
Yes, precisely. And for fast computation in general, nowadays, it's so that it's very
important that one can strive to make whatever that algorithmically can be done in parallel
is good if and then also implement it to be in parallel. Because it's mainly so that the
hardware development and Moore's law has for a CPU type of processors, it saturated around the
year of 2005, so then clock frequencies came up to around 5 gigahertz and yeah you can press it up
up to three gigahertz,
you can press it up to five gigahertz,
but it's not,
we don't have this exponential growth anymore.
So what we'll see here is that Python has very good support
to run them on multiple cores in hardware.
Because a modern processor has a few cores
that can be anything from two, four, or eight.
at a big cluster or at the supercomputer you might have as many as 128 cores on one processor.
So coming here to what we'll talk about today. So the objective here is that you will get a
little bit introduction to what are different strategies for parallelizing code. We will
explore a little bit the so-called multi-processing package and also get an idea for when to
use more advanced packages or approaches.
Yeah, okay.
So how do we begin?
The modes of parallelism I see here.
So here,
how do we think about this?
Yeah, importantly, before one gets started to write code
or to make use of some libraries,
one need to understand a bit,
how is your compute problem algorithmically.
And this, sometimes it's, so to say,
just looking on the code or on your algorithm,
You can think of this might be rather straightforward
to figure out, but it's all too easy actually to misjudge.
And here are some five questions.
I will not read them up in full,
but here are different strategies
for reviewing a code or an algorithm
before then get going with parallelization.
here you have links to some frameworks in Python where you can actually compile your
code into Python. So that if you have very generic code that you want to run faster,
I mean also in a serial fashion, you can have a look on these.
So basically the idea is try to make your Python code faster without paralyzing by using
other tools, other libraries. Like okay, so if someone's done a lot of array work in pure Python,
first they would always use numpy first and try to use the built-in numpy function so you don't
need any python loops and that will give you a tremendous speed up and is really what you
should do anyway and then once you've done all of those you get to this question we're at now so
what are the parallel computing methods yes okay so here are some important regimes of parallel
compute and this is completely agnostic here to the specific programming
languages. So starting here with embarrassingly parallel that can be if
you have some task that you want to compute and you would like to do it for
might have some parameter and that parameter can take on say 200 different
values. And then whatever you do, starting with that parameter value, you
can do independently of each other. So in principle, you could launch it on 200
different computers. And when it's all done, you just collect the results. From a
technical point of view, this is an enabling factor, because then you don't
need to use any fast interconnect. You could just communicate, let's say, over
regular internet. There's been earlier sometimes screen saver programs that
distributed work and you would do a little task and then it was sent back to
some server. That's an example of it. On the other hand it's then a little bit
dull because it's so to say it doesn't enforce you to make the hands-on work to
get to make things to run efficiently. So we have here multithreading and
multiprocessing. Those are two important concepts. So multithreading, that is when
you have one instance of a program which operates with some amount of memory on
like your whole local computer or on a whole compute node if it is on a
cluster and the work within that task or process can be spread out over multiple
so-called threads and typically you would like to have one thread per core
in the processor. There's a little bit more details to it because sometimes you
would like to overload it to have twice as many threads as you have cores.
multiprocessing is that you launch more than one instance of your program and
this can then operate well it can be on your same computer or it could also be
on on separate computers that do not share the memory and in order then to
access data which is on the other nodes you need to explicitly pass data in
between and this is used in the particular libraries which are taking
part of this and here in Python we have one which is the multiprocessing
library. We will later here after lunch see also the so-called MPI library. Okay
So, to summarize this in my mind, in Bearsing Parallel you have completely separate stuff
running that might save different output files and everything, multi-threading you have something
running that uses multiple cores and it's all the same process of sharing the memory,
and then MPI is separate stuff running but everything's communicating with each other
well it's running which I guess is the hardest to use. Yes it can be hard and it requires a lot of
code to be written also in order to use it. So there is something in Python which is called
the global interpreter lock, DIL, and that restricts that the process can only run one
thread, and that has to do with that some parts of Python are not thread safe, so one
has to restrict it like this because otherwise non-deterministic execution could occur.
So we will here take a little bit look on an example and the code snippet here which
I have copied and here you don't need to type this you can just follow along and I have
put it here in a Jupyter notebook, paste it here and execute it.
this code is doing is that it's inverting a large matrix with random
elements so it's 4,000 by 4,000 square matrix okay here we got a time of 9
seconds you might have noticed that it was earlier stated 13 seconds so this is
one typical thing with parallel computing or okay this is not parallel
yet. But the actual performance can be quite dependent on your environment and on the load
of other processes on your system. So here are, and this is a bit difficult to display
here in the notebook, but there are some environment variables which you readily have available
if you are on Linux or on a Mac OS.
And that's OMP num threads.
Or could be here in Windows context, MKL num threads.
So that will then specify how programs are,
I mean, how many threads they have,
they should see or be able to set.
So we will now have an example of the use of the multiprocessing library of Python.
So this we will work with in, I'll actually do it in a terminal.
So, we can define this function, it calculates the square of an input argument and we can
And then we used this list function here, we used this map function to input to square
an array here of six elements.
So this is not parallel yet but can be used.
needed an extra blank line after the def square it was still doing the function
definition oh okay I'm sorry do I need to restart here or oh if you do this
yeah I'd say you probably need to do the square one def square and then push
enter twice yeah yeah here we go great so this all worked but this was still
then serial. We will then import a so-called multiprocessing library and
we use here the statement from multiprocessing import pool
And then I write it with pool as pool and I use pool and then the map function
square and then the same same list of arguments as earlier okay so this pool multi-processing it's
making multiple runners that can run it separately
and so it's sort of like automatically dividing it up and recombining it
all without us noticing. This was parallel right here. Yes and from a technical point
here this was by means of launching multiple processes. Here's a little warning
here that if you run interactive in a Jupyter notebook or through an
Python, IPython terminal. It could be that this will not work as intended. So, I actually
had some problems here when I was preparing. So, that's why I resorted to use it in the
terminal. One option here is to install and make use of the so-called multiprocess library,
which differs a little bit in implementation under the hood.
So we have now already come here to the first exercises, which will be on multiprocessing
and also on multithreading.
So tonight, we will go through a little bit what the exercise is about, and then we will
let you work on it.
So this is a bit more a different kind of compute problem.
We saw here earlier inversion of a matrix and also just squaring a function.
we will use a rather, I would say this is a rather neat way of calculating pi. So [name]
can you explain how do we do this? I forget who was the one that started this, but basically
it's you have a, the metaphor is you're randomly throwing darts onto a square. So we're generating
random points in a 1 by 1 square, and inside of that is a circle, and we can compute that
by squaring, like Pythagorean theorem.
So as we pick random points on the square, we know some proportion of those will fall
inside of the circle, and that's related to pi.
So by doing a little bit of math, we compute pi by generating lots and lots of random numbers.
So it's not an efficient way to compute pi by any means, but it is quite useful to show
multiprocessing because, basically, the more random number you can generate in parallel,
the faster you can do it.
And you can see the code here yourself.
It's a good exercise because it can be done in different flavors and also in different
programming languages.
So we could actually demonstrate that this works first.
So if you walk through the code here, first you have that you import the so-called random
library then we define a function here sample function and this is what then
throws all the darts and the central statement here this is the
statement here that checks then is the x and the y points this coordinates are
they within the unit circle?
And if so, then they increment this n inside circle with 1.
Here you have code one can calculate,
then how long time does it take?
And the final thing is that in order to get the value of pi,
we need to multiply with 4.
It's a normalization constant.
And then also to divide with the total number
or a dot thrown.
So we could demonstrate that this works.
Yeah, so that's the one that says,
is this random point inside of a circle?
So first, I copy here.
the import statement and the definition.
Yes, so note here that if you copy all of this here,
it might not.
So it's better you copy it piece by piece.
Right. Yeah. Okay. Got it.
If you copy it like this,
then you have first imported
the library and define your function.
Okay.
Then we can, with this statement here,
using the time it magic,
we can calculate we can measure how long time it takes to throw 1 million
darts guess we can hear about what half a second however we did here not assign
anything to do it again it assigned to the variables properly okay and then we
calculate pi and now with that little math we get the pi value okay well
that's not it's not it's not too bad but but still it's only it's only correct
with the first three digits.
Yeah.
So all of the zero here is wrong.
That's an aspect of this algorithm
not being that efficient.
We have 1 million darts to get three digits of accuracy.
Yeah.
Okay.
So now coming to the actual exercise
that you will work with.
And you will then use the multiprocessing pool.
And you can also try out the so-called
multiprocessing thread pool.
And that will then do this parallel work,
but instead of going over multiple processes,
it will go over multiple threads.
So start with the multiprocessing variant and if you have time you can then have a go on the
multi-threading variant and the idea now so it's now 10 to the full hour and the idea is that
we let you work for 20 minutes then however it's lunchtime so we will then go for the break and
And then [name], how do we do, do we reconvene
before lunch break on stream?
We could just go for an hour and 20 minutes lunch break
and let people decide how they allocate
the time themselves, maybe.
Yeah, I agree.
I think that sounds best.
And then, I mean, we will be then,
some of us will at any given point of time
be on the shared document.
So you can post questions there.
So perhaps, should we look on the shared document to see if there's something that we can bring
up for all?
There's been a lot of good questions there.
There was one with someone whose pool code, they tried to run the pool code, and it made
a problem I can switch to my notes share here let's see yeah so I said yes though
that we can see if there's some questions that directly relate to the
exercise yeah okay and then we can actually go through a little bit these
questions after the lunch break yeah I think there's nothing that we need to
answer before the exercise. There's this one that's semi-related about separating
or about separating the calculations but yeah I think we're good to go. Okay great so
and one last thing here so yes as usual there is a template solution but yeah so yes it is
naturally that don't don't look and it's too early so to say so it's nice if you
try it ever yeah good okay so see you then at 10 past the full hour well now
it's I put 15 past the full hour yes perhaps and that also because it's
You need to specify what hour, actually, because it's more than 20 minutes.
Yeah, I wrote it there in central European time also, so yeah, okay, great, great.
Sounds good.
See you after lunch.
Yep, see you, bye.
you
So, welcome back.
We hope that you, yeah, both had some, made some good progress with the exercise and also
that you've had a refreshing lunch break.
So [name], perhaps we can have a look on the HackMD to see where we, what we have.
I'll switch it here on my screen.
Yeah.
So what do we have going on here?
Right.
I think we'd like to, you can scroll up above this blue box because there were some questions
about or do you want to share so you can scroll directly maybe one thing we
should say is that there's lots of things that can go wrong with this so we
see there was a problem with using multi processing on Mac and a different module
multi-process worked. We had problems running on the cluster when we just
tried. So there's all kinds of stuff here and a normal course on parallel
computing would be a week or even like a whole graduate degree becoming really
good at this. So we don't expect that you can do everything right now. This is just
the basic introduction. So one reason why the behavior here is not always the side one is that
it's implemented a little bit different on different operating systems and it also that
you might have different defaults and whatever program that you're launching, let's say Jupyter
Lab, can only live within its box with a given amount of memory and a given amount of hardware.
So if you have launched JupyterLab and it has upfront only access to one CPU core, then
it doesn't matter if your programming is multi-parallelized because it will anyhow only have one core
available.
Right.
Yeah.
So, but yeah, so the questions from the screen now are on that theme, but if you just, yeah,
Now, if you scroll down and we could then say a few words
about the distinction between processes and threads.
So further, load the blue box.
Here we go.
And yes, exactly.
If you put that up to the front of the window.
Yeah, thanks.
Yeah, so here we have been working on it asynchronously.
So there are multiple answers here
and that's really nice
because there are different aspects of it.
So one person here also in one sentence,
what is the difference between processes and threads?
And I can highlight here that in one of the answers,
if you put the pointer down here in the middle [name],
then for example over like four computers
with each having two CPUs each and for these CPUs we have 10 cores per
CPU. That means that your hardware available
is a total of 80 cores but the 80 cores are
then spread out on four computers or you can
you can call it four nodes.
And here it's rather clear that
it's only via the interconnect network
in between the nodes that you can
exchange any information at all.
And with multi-threading,
you can leave them within one node,
but in order to pass information to the other nodes,
need to do it with explicit message passing.
And threads is then something that you populate on the course.
So in general, the product of the number of processes and threads, in general, that should
match the number of physical cores available.
Sometimes you can go up to double, which in this case here would be 160 threads.
it moved out to the bottom block you can keep the screen but if you move the
pointer to the second last peg yeah okay just another sorry sorry no no no it's
going no no go up I wanted just to highlight the processes yeah here here
Yeah, keep it there. So, here are the definitions that I wrote myself and a process,
they can also be called ranks or tasks in the context of MPI.
They are indices of a program that execute independently of each other within the
runtime that is provided by the operating system and each process uses a chunk of the memory which
is available so even though I mean that's then part of I mean the complete set of RAM memory on
the computer it will be logically separated so one process cannot access the memory of the other
processes and if you think about it that's that's nothing other than that let's say you run five
completely different programs on your computer then clearly the desired functionality is that
they do not interfere with each other and that you can be able to start them and to
close them down independently of each other. Threads they are spawned
with the index execution of a process and by construction they then do share
memory and obviously this is attractive because you don't need to do any
explicit parsing of memory but there can also be a number of pitfalls so for
instance if you would come if it comes to that more than one thread tries to
write or read to the same address in memory then you would have a race
condition where it's not deterministic. For instance if you read before or after
another thread was writing to an address. So a concept here is that we talk
about the programs being thread safe or not thread safe. This connects back then
this CIL, this lock which is implemented in Python for the beginning. So this is to avoid
this unsafe thread situation. Good. And there is actually, this is on modern hardware and
and there's actually a lot to this aspect
of processes and threads.
And we will not go into it now though.
So instead we can, if you go back
and share my screen, [name].
Okay.
There you go.
Yeah, okay.
So what does this mean in practice?
Yeah, in practice, it means that it's good to be aware of this, that threading can be
done only what, I mean, really physically on the hardware is thread memory.
So you will always be limited to the number, I mean, to the amount of memory and to the
amount of CPU cores that you have on one node or yeah or one computer. So I think
we can highlight a little bit what you were working with in the exercise. So
here I have here in my notebook here I have opened up the notebook I mean
following the template solution. So the first thing I will do here is that I
restart the kernel and clear output of all cells. And then I also increase
light to this window so it becomes easy to see. And here the serial code, you've
seen it already? I executed now cell by cell. I'm not seeing any changes in your
screen. Could the screen share be paused or something?
I'm sorry, yes, you're right, I'll stop sharing and re-share.
Okay, so here's the notebook and I'm executing the cells one by one, so first was only the
definition here, this function, and we time it.
Okay, so this is the normal sample, so no parallel.
Okay, so it takes about one second.
It was rather many milliseconds here, 900.
milliseconds here 900 yeah then exclude again to put it here in the
to the variable
and we get the answer so 954 is our reference value
then we will make make use of the multi-processing tool
So, here we use this statement, import it, and then we create one pool.
How many processors does your computer have, or how many cores?
That's a good point.
So, I do have as many as 8 processors on my Intel i7, however, often it somehow behaves
as 4.
In this case here, the performance, I get it, seems as if it's using 2.
We got here a result of 336, which is, so we had got a 900 a minute ago, but 650 something
would be more the representative value.
So it's on the order of a speedup of two.
Yeah, okay.
It's quite neat.
It's part of the reason it's slow is it takes the time to distribute the task and re-collect
them all and so on.
Yes, in general.
But in order for this to have a smaller spread in executing times, you need to work in as
clean an environment as possible.
Right now, my runtime is not clean because I have Zoom, Twitch, have our Zulip chat,
and that slows things down.
I mean, only the screen sharing over Zoom will impact the execution time here.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, yeah.
What?
Yeah.
So, yeah, what?
Yeah, so this was multiprocessing.
And here we got a speedup.
We'll now highlight here something
which is something we can do here in practice,
but we will not gain anything from it,
namely to use a thread pool.
Okay, so now this is using things in the same process, so sharing memory.
Yeah.
And all.
Okay.
Yes.
And this thread pool is no big that we then create.
It's from the same multiprocessing here, but just a user thread pool.
Here it took 800 milliseconds.
okay so that's longer yeah it's about the same time as for the serial code
then we close it and
yeah this closing statement here what what does it achieve
It's a way of giving back the resources to the runtime.
Okay.
Yeah.
So, it's like deallocating the threads or whatever.
Okay.
So, we have three different ways of doing it and multiprocessing was fastest thread pool
and normal were fairly similar.
Yes, indeed.
And we can note here,
and that's written here also in the lesson material
that this implementation here of the thread pool
will then not release the JIL lock.
In contrast to the very first thing that we saw
with the inverse matrix calculation
which was done with NumPy
which can launch multiple threads.
Okay.
So here, just to highlight here,
running on a cluster or running on a multi-core computer,
where you might have set up then an environment
for general parallel computing with,
let's say, OpenMP, well, yeah, OpenMPI from Mesopotamia.
We will not explore this because I actually tried it out
earlier in the week, and I actually did not manage
to set up the environment for the runtime
to actually launch it properly.
So I, but we will instead move on to the next section here
which is MPI and that's where we'll spend
most of the remaining time of the lesson.
So message parsing interface is a framework
which is almost 35 years old.
So that's even then preceding the invention
piting or coinciding, plus minus, around 1990.
I didn't know it was that young, okay.
So this is a fairly low level means
of letting different processes communicate
communicate machine data during their simultaneous execution. So this is
something which is used a lot in the context of high-performance computing so
often here you are having programs written in C, C++ or Fortran and you
will then use this explicit function calls in order to send data or to receive
data. We have here some references we will soon come to an example of such
code but I can highlight here that they have some references here on GitHub and
and also here some blog posts where use is made of MPI
in context of Python programming so here you have complementary material
what we'll do now is look into a code snippet here where we are using
a specific library namely the MPI for Python library so that is
a library that provides the MPI framework to Python programs.
Okay, and is it like a close mapping to MPI libraries?
So I don't know MPI, but if I knew MPI, would this be pretty similar?
Yes, I mean you would recognize if you learned MPI and first in the context of C programming
or Fortran programming, you would recognize that many of the keywords and concepts are
essentially the same, it's just that the syntax is then distinct in each of the languages.
So yeah, we will run a few examples here,
but just to highlight, walk through the code here.
So it is the same program as earlier,
namely the calculation of PI, by means of throwing darts.
The yellow lines of code here are highlighting the MPI
for Python specific statements.
So first of all, an import statement,
Then we get available a number of functions.
So these three lines here you will see in pretty much any MPI program.
So here is a handle to the opportunity to interconnect between the processes.
Is this sort of like a representation of how many processes are involved in the calculation?
So com world means everything that's running as part of it.
Yeah, so this com here is actually an object so that in principle you can have more than
one of them.
And sometimes here in other languages you will have an explicit like initializing initializing
statement there which you don't have here.
These two lines here size equals get size and rank equals get rank.
They will then provide you with information about what you have available and how many
ranks will you use and yet again this is a matter of configuration so size is
often corresponding to the number of physical cores on your system is often
reasonable to set this so that you cannot go beyond this because you will
simply not gain anything however sometimes it's just set free so that you
can oversubscribe and run let's say five times as many ranks as you have course
in the system okay here here is something interesting so you can see
hear that if else statement here that you can often you will have with
MPI programming that you would like to do something only for one of the ranks
typically then the rank number zero is standing out because algorithmically in
a program is often so that even if it's some kind of computation perhaps most of it can
be done in parallel but there will be some some part of the code which not I mean naturally
cannot be done in parallel so for instance you would like to have reading of input file
often convenient to read it only once only by one rank and also writing output often
you would like to aggregate it so that you don't write it in parallel for each and every rank.
Yeah sorry okay this if else statement here this is actually setting the number of tasks here from
yeah like how much we're dividing it up so if there's multiple basically multiple processors
we divide the work into numbers okay yeah yeah and this rank state this if
statement here if rank is equal to zero then you will do well first of all this
calculation and you will get density printing of the output okay and that's
saying that only one processor should be doing the printing out but everything
else is the same for all of them?
Yeah.
OK, yeah.
And the thing that's actually being running is the or OK.
Yeah, and OK, so this is basically
it looks like in this example here, most of the code
is running separately with this extra decoration,
but the gather step is where it takes the output
from four separate processes
and brings them all together as one.
And does it basically sum them up together?
Yes.
And inside circle equals con that gather
and inside circle.
Yeah.
Okay.
That's great.
And you mentioned gather here.
And one thing to be aware of is this,
that as long as the processes are running in independently
and then exchange data with each other
in a sort of symmetric way,
let's say pairwise exchange data
or do it in so-called round robin
where you, let's say, you pass it,
you send something to a rank which is one higher
and you receive from what is one rank lower,
that's efficient.
But when you gather thing to calculate,
let's say the sum of partial sums,
then you sort of feed everything towards
what in the end becomes sort of like a bottleneck.
That's actually a really intricate thing
to get high performing.
Okay, but now we want to see some operations of this.
So I will then do it here on,
here I have a compute node on the supercomputer
that I have here in Stockholm.
Okay.
So this, the individual nodes here on compute CPU partition
have many more cores than I have on my local laptop.
So it's as many as 128 cores.
Yeah.
Yes, then I have put all of this code into a program calcmpi.py and you can see what
happens if you just launch it. Oh yeah right now I need to check yes that's
because I opened a new session here because I'd closed it down over lunch in
order to hold on the resources yeah so so basically now you're running it on
the real supercomputer and we'll demonstrate it's actually using MPI in
in a lot of processors.
So, yeah.
Okay, so here it ran, rank zero.
And this is running on just one processor
because I see-
Yeah, yeah.
I sort of, you can see here,
I started Python and then in the program.
So I'm sort of launching it as a regular Python script.
Okay, yeah.
And it's nice that the program executes
even if you do like that.
Yeah, I guess it doesn't have to run in parallel.
Okay.
Yeah.
And the right time here.
And it takes 2.2 seconds.
Yeah.
Now we add something here,
S run and two.
So S run is a program which we're using
on the particular computer that we have here in Stockholm.
Often it's called MPI run instead.
Okay, what did we get there?
1.49.
1.49 real seconds or 1.1 seconds in the Python code.
Exactly, and I think that's the number
we should concentrate on.
So we do like this.
We type, use the grep command to filter out that specific line in the output and we go
back to having it with only one rank, then we get 2.2, and I remove this time because
it's redundant. Yeah. Now we've got to 2.2 and 1.1 seconds. Yeah. So this is your perfect
speed up. So yeah, it was actually exactly twice as fast. Okay, if we add more. Point
Oh, still still crazy. Much more perfect than I would have expected. Yeah. Point to eight.
Okay.
We lose a few percent.
Yeah.
Okay.
So how hard is it to design code to use MPI?
So, this isn't even a Python specific question, but when would you recommend people to look
into MPI and similar things?
Yeah, so my experience is that to write MPI code, it's good if you know really well what
algorithms do you want to implement, that you know that upfront, because if you're doing
prototyping with your, let's say, serial code or just like in pseudocode, at the same time
as you're writing the actual code, then it can easily be that the code then becomes difficult
to read and also that it's not, will not be able to reach the highest performance.
Of course, this is a matter also of experience and training.
Personally, I've used OpenMP threading quite a bit more in larger programming projects and
that has the advantage that you can, you have your serial code and then you can decorate
it with statements that enable the runtime to fork into multiple threads.
So that's very convenient,
but then one is also a bit more dependent on the compiler
or in this case, if it Python,
more dependent on the runtime to do a good job for you.
Okay, yes, one last launching here,
we go all the way up to 128.
Oh no, it's 118.
I will still gain a bit and then we put it to some large value and here you see
more processes requested than permitted we were not allowed to do that yeah
Good, so we will now come here to the final part of the lesson which is on coupling to
other languages and this also in turn connects rather nightly to the MPI for Pi because that's
That's actually one of the good constructions to do so.
So how much time should we spend?
It's almost 50 past the hour.
I suggest we use around five minutes.
Okay, yeah.
We can quickly summarize this and go on.
good. So yeah, what about coupling? So I guess this goes back to the original
thing we said. You can use libraries that do the speedups and then you don't need
to make your own parallel. So these are all ways to somehow connect to other
languages where things might be implemented more efficiently? Is that why we're here?
Yes, precisely. And we can note then that
the NumPy library, it already has the Python MPI. So we just import it in Python,
and then we can run it, and benefiting them from all the functionality, and also that it can run
and execute really fast, also in parallel mode.
If you haven't got it all yet in a library
because you're implementing something
which is completely custom,
so which really is your code,
then let's say you would like to do that in C++ or Fortran,
then you need to deal with the API
between the languages on your own.
So, a very important one here is the PyBind11 for C++.
So you can then write code in C++ and you can, I mean, interoperate it with the Python
code.
And algorithmically so that you typically let the Python code be what binds us all together.
So you will then launch execution
and also so close wrap up execution with the Python code.
You can do similar things with Fortran,
but then it's a bit more intricate
because you would then need to have like PI binding
or a CFFI or something.
And then also this ISO C binding.
So it becomes only in two steps.
So that's a little bit
is something which is holding back Fortran in modern day programming because it's more
intricate to interoperate it with other languages.
This variant here is what I know is has become very popular and you let compile languages
to Shared Memory Parallelization. And then you let Python do the message
parsage interfacing by means of mpy4py. So it's sort of like
you're using numpy on each node and mpi4py to communicate the results of
that numpy across the nodes. Yes, precisely. So that would be one
variant. I mean, here I'm calling numpy with test and Python API. It could also be that
you're within on each node run an instance of a C program, which you have connected
to your Python by means of these bindings.
So one thing to highlight here is that this approach here, this is actually scaling to
good performance on really large amount of resources.
So I know now, and it actually happens to be my roommate here at work, his code can
fill the whole Dodel code running with MPy for Python.
Kotel is your cluster?
Dodel is our cluster, yeah.
So they run in a Jupyter notebook using MPy for Py and then run with C++ and also Qt or
HIP in order to run on GPU.
And now in the coming months or so, there's a prospect of getting a special time slot
to run it on all of Lumi.
And Lumi is a computer in Finland which is like one of the top five computers in the world.
Okay.
Well, I guess that certainly gets the idea that Python is slow, it's just a matter of
connecting it the right way and using the right stuff under it yeah yeah okay
precisely so I think we could actually wrap things up so there's something
here which is called task and task queues and that you can read up on your
own but you can perhaps go quickly to the shared document to see if there are
or something, you can bring up your stream.
Can you share or should I share?
I can share.
Okay, yeah, then you can scroll.
Okay.
Yeah, there was some good questions here.
So these questions like what is speed up compared to the number of cores, in some sense
it's an easy answer.
If it's perfectly scalable, it's one divided by the number of cores.
But also, there's so many different things that can affect it that it's somehow quite
a hard problem.
The numbers we got 10 minutes ago when we ran the MPI4Py code on the Dredel node, that
was sort of like ideal scaling.
In reality, you often get a bit less speed up.
Right.
Yeah.
If you get hyperscaling, better speed up than that, it's because when you run with only
one rank, then you have somehow exhausted resources somehow, so that you are having
to paging memory down to hard disk or similar.
Yeah.
Algorithmically, it's not possible.
Okay.
Any other final questions? I don't see, okay, there's one coming.
I think to keep the time, I think it's better we do this asynchronously.
Now it's five to the full hour, so that would mean that we have a ten minute break and be back five past, I think.
Yes.
Okay.
Good.
So, yeah, please keep asking questions, and if you think this is relevant to you, keep
exploring yourself.
There's some stuff you can do that has a high impact for not too much work, so, yeah.
Okay.
Great.
So, see you later then.
See you.
Bye.
you
Hello, welcome back to all three instructors here are greeting you.
Um, so now we go to our last real lesson,
which is packaging.
So I'll open that up here.
And yeah, so what is packaging?
Like, what does this even mean?
Right.
So in the previous episodes,
we have been introduced to a whole bunch of libraries.
We saw how to write scripts and work with Jupyter notebooks.
So that's how typically a study
or a research project starts up.
But at some point it would become much larger
than a script and you will have a lot of code lying around
unorganized and you will feel the need like,
okay, I need to have some structure for this.
Okay.
Yeah.
One way to do that is to create a package.
And by package, this means like the package you would do pip install for on the Python
package index or the conda packages.
So basically something that you install.
Yeah.
So.
How often do you make packages yourself?
Like how relevant is it really?
What kind of, do you have some examples?
I think usually I don't start off with the goal of making a package.
Usually it's a bunch of code lying around in a Git repository, for example, or in my
own laptop, but at some point you realize that, okay, this is for myself, I can use
it in my laptop X and let's say this remote supercomputer that I'm locking onto and I don't
want to send it back and forth. That's one way, one reason when you realize. Another reason is,
okay, you have friends and then they really like the code you write and you want to share it with
with your friends or your colleagues at that point.
So the summary is it's useful when other people,
when you want other people to use it
because it is easier than saying download this
and put it here and it's all this other stuff.
But you also use it just for yourself
if you're using it on multiple different computers you have.
Okay, so I guess that means it's not too hard.
So maybe you can tell me a bit about how you do that.
Right, so to have a good package,
you need Python code, of course.
Typically, these are not scripts.
They will contain classes or functions.
or functions.
So I'm not sure.
In the scripts episode, did we import some functions
from a script?
Oh, did we in, hmm.
I think there was, well, it could
have gone as far as making a separate file
and importing there, but.
Right.
Well, at least it imported standard library functions
and things like that, so.
Yeah.
Oh, all right. So the way import works in Python, it has a bunch of,
it looks at some other standard directories, but it also looks at your current directory.
So if you have a file name, for example, here underneath you see a file called adding.
So if you say import adding, then it
will load it into your console.
It's adding.
So yeah.
And the reason why I said it should not
be a script, because when you do this import,
it executes everything in that file.
So if you have, for example, a print, hello,
I am adding audio, then it will show up.
that it's not a good sign of a module.
Yeah.
OK, wait.
So let's try to summarize what this is.
So when you make the package, you
have to have the self-contained files there.
Usually, they'll be used by importing to other things.
So that means that it should be structured like a module.
So when you import it, it doesn't have any side effects
and doesn't affect, it doesn't run anything directly.
Although you can also package scripts
where it becomes a command line utility.
But I think we're not talking about that here.
But it's important to note.
Yeah, that's another thing.
So you can do that as well.
But yeah, try not to.
Yeah, but our demo here will be only packaging
in portable code.
But realize you can package the script also.
Absolutely.
OK.
Yeah, so to do this, what do we do?
Do we, should we start with the demo?
Yeah, I guess we can do that.
Okay.
And we'll talk through the rest.
Yeah.
Okay.
Unfortunately, Katz has to go.
Somehow he knows.
Okay.
Let me get my screen set up here.
And hope Katz doesn't do any typing for me.
It's sitting right here, occupying all my space.
OK, so yeah, so should I make a new directory for the?
Yeah, that is good.
And here, it's called project folder, but it can be anything.
OK, so should we call it calculator?
Is that what we're doing?
I think that can get confusing.
You can maybe call it CalculatorReturn, maybe.
OK, I'll call it this, I guess.
Yeah, that looks good.
Actually, I'll call it Calculator
because of a reason you'll see later.
OK, so I'll go into this directory.
And do I start adding these different files here?
Yeah, you can do that.
Okay, so I add a new Python file here.
So I'm clicking down here.
This shouldn't be a notebook, but should be an actual Python file.
So this should be called add.
I'm adding.
Let's come to the launcher.
another new Python file, rename it to Subtracting.
This needs to be saved.
Okay, close them and integrating.py.
Oops.
Rename.
OK.
And that is saved.
Right.
And I guess I'll close it.
Now the fourth file.
So can you tell me what init.py means?
This is an interesting name for a file.
Yeah.
So we haven't given it a good location yet.
So we'll have to add one more directory.
Maybe we describe that after that.
Should I be doing something different here?
So let's just fill in this init.py.
And we will move all these four files
into a subdirectory called calculator.
OK, I see what you mean.
I think I know.
OK.
So I make a new directory called calculator.
You should be able to drag and drop if I'm right.
Hey, it works.
OK, so I dragged it there.
So now this, what I see here, calculator archivist
would be like the project repository or the Git
repository.
Exactly.
Calculator contains the code.
Okay.
Right.
Yeah.
So the name of the directory here, the calculator, is important.
So the top directory can be anything.
And like I said, init.py, if you open it, and we can see it on the top as well.
Yeah.
Okay.
When we do import.calculator, we can also access these functions that init.py imports
it for us.
Okay.
Yeah.
So.
There's a good question in the notes.
Do we always need the period here?
So what does this mean in particular?
So there are two ways to import modules.
The first way is called absolute imports.
So that would be like writing from calculator.adding import
add.
But I think it's recommended, if you can,
get away with relative imports.
Do that in one of the Python pet beads, I think.
The reason is down the line, you decide to, OK,
calculator is not a good name for this package.
Then you don't have to go around and changing in every module
that you have.
So this is called, the one on the top
is called Relative Imports, and this one on the bottom
is Absolute.
OK, yeah, so I could do this instead.
But that means that it has to know what the package name is.
And if it's renamed, then everything changes.
This means import a module called Adding from right
next to where I am.
And don't look at, like if someone else installs
package named adding that's unrelated to yours without the dot it would try to do that yes okay
so okay i guess we don't need to go into details there but no it's something you can read about
more with python if you want okay exactly yes so now here we have a rough package ready although
though we have not installed it anywhere.
But still, if we go one directory up in the Jupyter,
and then we can open either a terminal or a Python console.
Let's see, terminal.
Terminal is good, yeah?
Yeah, there I am.
So I'm in Calculator RK Darst.
OK.
So here we can.
There is some example code just below in the...
Oh, okay.
Yeah.
Should I try running this from here?
Yeah, in a Python console, of course.
Yeah. Okay.
So there is Python.
I guess I just copy the whole thing and paste it.
Yeah.
Hmm.
Oh, there it goes.
All right.
So it worked.
So I have a folder called calculator
and it knew to import abstract and integral and it worked.
Exactly.
So like I said before, it looks at some places
but also the current directory, where to import from.
But this would not work if you are in another directory,
let's say, import calculator will just fail.
Should I try that?
Yeah, you can quickly show that.
OK, so I've gone up.
Yeah.
OK, because it's not in the Python environment,
but it could be there.
OK, but I guess let's not dwell into that,
because there could be a huge amount of questions there.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So when you are doing serious research,
you want it in your Python environment.
You don't want to think about where you are.
So in order to do that, we make it installable.
So that's about the next section.
It's about that.
OK, so we're going to make it installable with, I guess,
this one here.
Right.
OK.
Should I do it, add the new file?
Yeah, we can do that.
OK.
So I think I'm in the right place here.
OK, this extra file got added.
My shell makes it automatically.
Let's delete that.
OK, so I'm adding a new file, a new text file.
I will rename to pyproject.toml.
And I copy and paste.
So what did this just do, and why?
So this is a new specification, relatively new,
a few years old, actually, which tells you
what the package is called.
For example, this particular format is called a TOML format.
So it contains some tables, which, for example,
build system is a table, project is a table.
These are the minimum that you need to describe a package.
You need to at least say what the name is,
and maybe also the version, that's good.
Yeah, so it's good to rename it as well for the demo.
Yeah.
You can also describe who created the package,
where can you contact them
if you decide to upload this package
to a public index such as PyPI.
And I've seen that I can leave off my email
and it still works, so.
Right.
And the dependencies part is particularly useful
because that ensures that when you're installing this package,
you bring along whatever you assume exists.
For example, we have this integrating module
where we actually import scipy,
so we need to ensure that.
Yeah. So this is how all the things fit together.
So installing this, it knows it needs these other things,
just like we talked about in the dependency section.
So I guess every other Python package
says it needs thumbpy or sidepy or whatever it may be.
Exactly.
OK.
Yeah.
What now?
There are other details like readme, but it's OK.
Maybe you can create an empty readme file
because we specify that.
Sure.
It's a text file.
I'll rename this.
readme.md.
So just a short note, it's good practice
to give a good description so that people know.
And this gets automatically shown when you upload it.
We will see that in a while.
The other important file that we mentioned here
is the license file.
And it's, although it's not mentioned in the SpyProjectTerminal, but it's possible to link
that this is the license file, but we don't go into that now.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, shall we, yeah, there are some more notes.
I try to do something so there's a node right so this is this is a if you run
into a small bug and then let's say you found a bug in x-ray and it got fixed
and then you want to use that latest bleeding-edge version of x-ray yeah but
it's they haven't released it yet so that you can do something like that as
So this is installing it straight from GitHub
without it being released.
OK, yeah.
Exactly.
And you can find more of the syntax on these links below.
Yeah.
OK.
Right.
So now it's time for an exercise so people who are following
can try this out.
Should.
OK, so basically they would do everything that I just did.
But OK, should I demonstrate this installation step
to see if it works?
Yeah, yeah.
And maybe some might have forgotten
how to create a virtual environment.
Oh, OK.
Yeah.
So I'll make a new terminal here.
Close some of these things.
OK, so here I am in my Python 4 scientific computing directory.
The ls command lists what's here.
Here's the calculator.
So I should make a new virtual environment.
So that would be Python minus vn and then vn,
just to keep things in.
And then now we need to activate it.
So in Linux and macOS, it will be source vn slash bin slash
activate.
OK, like this?
No, just you don't need to activate it.
Never mind.
Yes, yeah.
Yes.
Yeah, OK.
And if you're on Windows, it will be vn scripts activate,
I think.
without the source.
Yeah.
And now I try to pip install it.
Right.
We can just quickly show that pip list
before we do that to show that it's completely empty.
OK.
Yeah.
And now you can do that.
Pip install editable.
And then that should work, I think.
Yeah.
It says obtaining file, downloading SciPy and NumPy.
So there it just found the dependencies
and installed them automatically.
That's good.
Yeah.
And it also makes sure that it will install setup tools
on the fly, although we didn't have setup tools to package it.
So setup tools is one of the building packages.
Yeah.
OK, and should I run pip list now?
So now we see that numpy, scipy are installed,
but our calculator got installed in another location.
And it has the name that we specified in myproject.toml.
Yeah.
Yeah, OK, so is this enough to begin to exercise?
Yeah, right.
OK, yeah, I'll try to write it here.
So the goal is basically do what I just did
and get it to a point where you can pip install it,
like this here.
And then there are some, the same test commands that we tried out before. It's mentioned there.
Okay, yeah, yeah.
Okay, sounds good. So let's go to a break. How long do we have?
I think we can do, I don't know, seven minutes? Ten? That's too short.
Okay, 30. Should we say until 40? Until 40, yeah. 11 minutes. 12, yeah. Okay, sounds good. Okay, see you later then.
Yeah.
Yeah. Okay.
Bye.
you
Okay, now you can hear it.
me. Okay, so we see the notes here, and we see there's lots of good questions going on.
Which one should we focus on answering first?
Maybe there's this question, why is vnvair twice? So the first one is the name of the module that
that Python's running.
The second one is the directory that's
being created with the virtual environment.
And it's kind of not great that there's like this
is a duplicate here, but it's a bit confusing,
but it is what it is.
But you can have any other name if you wish.
Yeah.
Okay.
This editable one, I think, is also asked below.
This one here, does pip install install my package in another location or is it making
use of what's already been made?
And I guess this gets to editable and what that means.
So if I installed it without editable, what would the answer to this question be?
It would take all the code that you have packaged, put it in a special directory called site
packages.
You will be able to see that if you write pip show calculator RKDOS for you.
And then if you have the editable flag on, then it would create a small file which points where
the source code actually is. So it won't make a full copy. Yeah. So for example, when I'm doing
developing, like when you're doing developing, you don't want to have to edit a file and then go and
install it and then test it and see if it works and repeat this over and over again. That's just
annoying. So when you do this editable, as you modify it, it's directly being taken into use.
Well, to me, I look at it as useful for development kind of things, but are there
other times it's useful? Maybe. Yeah, it's only good for development, I would say.
Yeah.
OK.
Here's another good question.
So when you're making the pyproject.toml file,
it gives the name.
So name here is the name that it will have on pypi, basically
the name you use for pip install.
that can be different than the name of the module itself,
as in what you use to import it.
And these days, it's usually the same.
But there are a few big cases where
you use one name to pip install it and a different name
to import it.
And that is confusing, to say the least.
Yeah, there are a lot of popular packages which does this, PyTorch, Torch, scikit-learn,
sklearn.
So it's very common, much common.
Yeah.
So, it's worth taking some time to try to come up with a unique name that other people
won't be using.
But, yeah, so that's the basic idea there.
The actual directory name you make is what, or is where it gets the import thing from.
Okay.
There's this other question. Calculator not installable, neither setup.py or pyprojecttoml
found. If pyprojecttoml is found and you made it, maybe it needs to be up one directory.
So there is this very particular arrangement for how it should be structured here. I'm
scrolling up. So there's a project folder. In it is one directory named calculator with all the
stuff. But it's in project folder that it has pyproject.toml. So yeah, it can be confusing.
I'd say look for an example and copy it because that's what all the rest of us do. You know,
It's like some standard ways and you can know why or you can copy and I'm always copying stuff.
Right. In this example, you should point to project folder to pip install it.
Ah, yes. Then you should pip install with this folder's name, not this name.
Yeah. Not that one.
Right. Yeah. Okay.
OK, hmm.
Should we go to the remaining demo?
Yeah, OK.
So there is one more demo we had.
Let's see.
Back to my screen.
OK, yeah, after this, so sharing packages with, whoa, sorry.
sharing packages with PyPI. Should I start typing it while you're explaining it?
Absolutely. So, now we have this package. So, we're going to try to upload it into a
test PyPI server. So, we're going to do this demo. You don't have to type along. Try to go fast.
I'd say please don't type a lot. It requires making an account and setting up a bunch of stuff.
It's just not needed.
Yes. Right. So first, I think in your terminal, we can try to go outside of this VM. Deactivate.
Yes. Okay.
Right. So this build module should be installed in our Conda environment.
Okay. So we go into, yeah, into the core directory and then press enter.
So it will, once again, on the fly install setup tools. Create a wheel file, it's called.
And this is the format. One of the formats for distribution. So if you look at test
directly, you'll get a source distribution, which has the extension tar, and the wheel
distribution, which is essentially a zip file.
Yeah.
So, this is exactly what PyPI is installing when you do pip install from somewhere else.
Right.
So, our goal is to then put this wherever it belongs.
Okay.
Exactly.
Yeah.
The tool to upload it is called Twine.
OK.
We can try by installing it.
So I'll just directly pip install Twine here.
That's a lot of stuff it's doing.
OK, but I guess it's installed.
And it's, since we are not serious about this package,
we are going to upload it to desktop by BI.
Yeah, I guess this is important to say.
if you do a Twine upload, then it's permanently out there.
And anyone that uses, like this package name
can never be used by anyone else in the future.
And it will always be out there.
So that's not what we want to do for a course
and probably not what you want to do
when you are here testing stuff
or if you're not really serious.
So that's why they've conveniently made a test pypi.
Okay.
So should I run this?
Yeah.
So I copy and paste.
Are they asking for a token?
You need a token.
So there is this link where you can go to just below them.
And this is test pypi.
Right.
Okay.
Because this is a security thing, they always ask for the password, even if you're logged
in.
Okay.
Yeah.
So
And you can call it something useful here, Python for Cyclone, maybe.
And
Okay.
The scope should be all packages,
because we are uploading a new one.
Well, I can do this, and then I can delete it.
I guess the other option is to make a new project, and then.
But to do that, you need to upload it through this.
So you have to upload it first.
Okay.
First, and then you can make a fine-grained token.
Hmm, okay, well, yeah, let's just do it.
Let's create a token.
I'm going to move this out
so people don't see the token for obvious reasons.
Yeah.
Okay, I see something here
and it looks like a three line thing.
Yes, and it starts with PyPI, and you can copy and paste it.
Yeah.
So just to be sure, I'm going to move this out of the way, paste, okay, I hope it's pasted,
and now I push enter.
Yes.
And voila, now it's up, and if you go to that link, which popped up, you can see it's up
there. Okay. Let's see. Due to this link. Yeah. So I will. With installation instructions,
the version number, the small description that we had just below. And even what we wrote
in the readme, which comes as project description. Yeah. Yeah.
And it shows me with email example at example.com.
Do you think I can install it from here with these instructions?
Almost. You can try that. Because it will not find scipy.
Because scipy is not in test pypi.
Yeah, exactly. Okay, so there is another parameter that you need to add and I
think it's listed in the course documentation. It's called extra index
URL. There you go.
Here, okay, yeah. So this means Python 3 and pip install, this tells it to
install from test my API and if it can't find a package there it will install
from here right yeah okay I guess I'll give it a try yeah
should I activate the virtual environment yeah the one you're using
before okay yeah but then uninstall it just to make sure okay I want to
uninstall yes I'll say yeah okay
So, testPiPiSimple, and then normalPiPi, and then RKDARS2.
Right.
Hey, it works.
Okay.
Right.
Yeah.
And if I do pip list, well, now it's not showing my local path here, so it's just installed.
OK, that wasn't too hard.
Yeah.
But there were some manual steps involved, and in recent years there are other tools
which helps you generate a PyProjectToml, for example,
Poetry, Flit, and there are many more others.
Yeah.
And for this token, you can create a .pypirc file
so you don't have to enter it every time.
So you can read about that in that link over there.
OK.
Do we have time for the conda package?
don't think so, but right. We can read about what I hear. It's pretty easy to do a content package
also. Right. So we can try it out later on. But the idea there is you have an existing PyPI package
and then you use two tools for fetching it, creating a something called a content recipe.
and building a conda package.
So that's what we show there.
So just to summarize,
like when you have a good enough project going on
and you want to share it,
either for yourself in for reusing it
or for your friends want to upload it somewhere.
PyPI is a good place.
Yeah.
But conda is also popular.
And also, if you don't want to use PyPI,
there's sometimes I've made things basically just for me,
and I install it from a GitHub URL.
So I'd publish it somewhere myself
and say, install from here.
But that's something you can read about later.
So yeah, I guess I'll switch to the notes here.
And notes, notes, where are notes?
Here.
So if we go up some.
So we have an outro and feedback of the day.
[name], are you here to give the outro?
I am here.
Hello, hello.
Do you hear me?
OK.
So in the meantime, you can keep asking questions
about packaging or also please answer the feedback questions.
Okay, go for it [name] or do you want to share your screen?
Maybe if you since you already have the page there if you wanna
just open the outro page.
Oh, I think I'll go into the shadows. Okay, see you later.
So basically, I mean, most of the things that we already
mentioned the previous days, the materials we stay online, we
will most likely revise them next year for the next session.
What is nice is that you can explore them through GitHub.
You can submit fixes, ask for new features, for new lessons.
So it's really nice if people want to contribute and why not even join the development of the
course.
Very briefly, there is the possibility of getting one ECTS credit.
So there's the rules on the website, on the main page.
The deadline is the last day of November.
have any questions you can get in touch with me directly but that's nothing it should be basically
just you just an occasion for you to show that you are able to run some of the examples that
you've been running in these three days and then more in general about Code Refinery and
Alto Scientific Computing. So Code Refinery is a Nordic e-infrastructure collaboration
sponsored project to support computational research.
We've been running Code Refinery.
I don't even remember how many years we've been going on.
Seven, maybe more.
But the so-called Code Refinery Tool Workshop
is the main workshop that we have already mentioned in the notes
at least during these days.
We run it twice a year and we usually teach kind of the basics
of computational reproducibility, Git version control environments, like conda environments,
but also containers and other things related to basically kind of good practices, good enough
practices for scientific computing. And then Alto Scientific Computing, which is basically based at
Alto University. We support our people at Alto, of course, but we also organize various courses.
and it's also important to mention our partners and for this time I especially want to mention
and thanks the people at ENCCS Sweden and CSC, the Center for Computational Science in Finland
and of course many universities in the Nordics who have been helping whether they were instructors
or they developed the materials or they did communications. For future events we will have
our so-called kickstart course which is basically kind of the abc for using hpc systems most likely
will be in february 2025 and the reason is that it corresponds to a big increase of doctoral
researchers in finland with the new year so it's an opportunity for new doctoral researchers to
get get started quickly in using hpc systems the code refinery workshop that i already mentioned
will be happening in the second half of March 2025 and as people already asked about other
courses that will be running in the past you can request a rerun of previous courses. We are very
happy to you know if there is an interest of course we we will be there. We are very happy to
rerun new old courses and usually this means that they get updated with new materials, better
exercises and so on. So to stay in touch we have the Code Refinery newsletter that you can visit
the Code Refinery website and from there you will see it and we also have the Alto Scientific
Company newsletter for more Alto related courses. There's some relevant links there
that you can explore and maybe we can end with this how can we work together. Do you want to
to reach or do that? How can we work together for it?
Yeah, if you're interested in these kinds of courses, like there's no obligation of course,
you can of course come to our future courses, but also bring more people with you. So we try
to design these courses where one person could bring a bunch of people from their
research team or friends or so on and come together and then basically you're
the local support for the exercises and things like that. You can keep following
the exercises later on, like help with homework, advising on homework and things
like that. If you're part of an organization like you work at your
university or something, you could come and basically advertise it as one of your courses,
run the local breakout rooms and all that stuff, and then really make it an official thing you do.
And Code Refinery is right now looking for more partners. So basically we're opening up,
it won't be a closed project anymore. But if anyone wants to join and do teaching with us
and make it part of your own course program and reshare the courses you do, that is something
that we're interested in. And probably the best way to learn more about that is the Code Refinery
newsletter. So as we find that, you can join. You'll hear there. Or join the Code Refinery chat
and talk there.
Yeah.
All right. I think that
it was nice to spend three days with you.
Very interesting questions.
Hopefully this was useful.
And please leave feedback as you
I see you're already writing comments
for the third day, but you can also
write any type of comment.
Yeah.
Yeah, you can give feedback for the whole thing, whole time.
Is there any feedback we would like to discuss with people now?
I guess my biggest lesson here would be we can't, like we know that what we've tried
to do here can't be a full course or lesson in any of the one things we're saying.
all so big, they could all become their whole time. But we hope that we've inspired you and
shown you a bit about how it works and why it works so that when you need to, you can go study
more yourself. Maybe our material is the starting point, but you definitely need more than that,
more than just what we have. So, yeah. Yeah, that was our philosophy here.
Okay, anything else for the news?
There's some question about the credits, but I will write.
[name] knows that.
I think we'll try to update all of the web page stuff with what it did.
Should we open the course room on Zoom so people can join and talk about it?
Yes. So after party, bring your own tea.
I will paste the link soon.
All right. Thanks a lot, [name], for being the director from your studio.
It's easy compared to the teaching.
Well, you know, it's a big effort.
And thanks to all the instructors, of course.
Excellent job also this time.
And thanks to all the participants
for being with us for three days.
Okay, great. Thanks.
So in a little bit, there'll be the Zoom link on here
and we'll talk to you later.
Okay. Bye, everyone.
Bye-bye.
you