are. We're live. Hopefully, every will get lots of people coming. We're in the icebreaker
time now. So let's see, what do we have for icebreakers?
I've got a couple of generic demographics icebreakers.
Let's see what people are.
So how does this work?
So if you are registered, you should have a link to this
note.coderefinery.org document.
You should be able to switch to edit mode.
and then basically write stuff here.
So this is the way we use to communicate.
So instead of the Twitch chat, which is linear,
you can come here,
you can ask questions in any order.
We have a section for questions which is appearing down here,
and answer and ask anytime.
So yeah, let's see what people say.
There was a good icebreaker from last night, what was it?
How would you explain HPC to someone from a hundred years ago?
Should we add that there?
I'm adding it.
There we go, we see it coming.
is so difficult. I mean, in the 19th century, there used to be some calculators. So maybe
that would be the metaphor. And they are probably steam-operated, right?
Steam machines that keep this going. And then we need a mechanism to send messages from one
steam factory to the other, like some conveyor belts or something. That's the network. And
all just work together. Maybe the industrial revolution, is that like a metaphor for HPC?
Yeah. Or the printing machines that, you know, that you're able to
in parallel print the same book. Yeah. I guess the high performance part,
Well, computing part, do we have to explain what computing is to someone from a hundred
years ago?
I guess there's probably some mechanical calculators as an analogy.
I think so.
These ones with the, you know, the wheel that you could sum and subtract.
So can we say we made that much, much, much faster?
all using electricity. And then, say, for the high-performance part, say, we can't make
one of these fast enough, so we make a lot of them, and then they communicate together
really efficiently.
Electricity existed back then, right?
Like saying there's electric lights.
Technically.
Technically, as electricity has been there before us, but yeah.
Did telegraphs exist back then?
I think it's the last few decades of the 19th century, I think, let me check.
No, actually, it was 1835.
Okay.
like the most or yeah no that was the [?] coat
but anyway yeah it's exciting to be here because we've been planning and discussing this course
for maybe i don't know two years or something like that and today finally it's happening
so what would you say is the spirit of this course like why are you here what do you
what's the thing about what we do?
Well, I don't know.
At least I've never seen something like this
that we are putting together in this four episode
in a sense that we've been running
and I'm sure we've been taking part
to introductory courses to HPC,
but at the end of the day, okay, good.
You learned those commands that you need to run,
but it's the daily struggling with working
with these clusters and remote and local
And so something that I guess everyone has just learned by doing on their own or by watching
others.
So I wish I had this type of introduction, I don't know, 15 years ago when I started.
Yeah.
I'd say it's best practices filtered by people at different centers, so really taking the
most common, most useful.
And I think what is so fun is that we will see that many, many things are really similar
across all the centers.
We will also probably see that some things are not a little bit different.
As instructors, we hope that they are not we will not.
We are a little bit afraid that some things that we assume to work works everywhere might
not work everywhere.
But it's also to me the first first time that we try something like this cross border trying
to distill out what is what is it that is common?
And what can we learn from all of us?
And can we somehow abstract away the details and focus on the big picture?
So for me, the course is really about the big picture.
Do any of you know about other courses which actually use multiple, like is taught and
have participants with access to multiple different clusters by different organizations
and the course might work for them.
Not across borders.
No.
I guess maybe our June kickstart course is the closest then.
Yeah.
Even that is.
But yeah, so during that June kickstart course, something we always heard was people, it was
a basic course where people saw, well, how to get started.
But then there's a lot of people who want some lessons about how we actually use it,
like what's the advanced side of things, which is a little bit hard to teach because if you
have basic people just learning the cluster and command line and advanced people, you
can't really easily serve both audiences at the same time.
So here what we've done is, this is not a basic course, and in fact a lot of things
you see might be too advanced to really fit in one thing together, but, I mean not too
advanced for most people here, for everyone here to do, but instead it's cool demos.
how we actually use it, you can get some ideas, and then go back and study yourself.
Okay, did I finally say that properly?
Yep.
Okay.
So, what are the topics for today? Who are the teachers? Is it [name] and [name]?
So the first part will be [name] and me, and the second part is [name] and [name]. And today
we talk about resource use. We will do a super brief intro into what is high-performance computing,
but really like in one minute, in two minutes. And then how do we, how do we use resources
really in a good way. How should we approach it? And what are the different dimensions
there? So we'll talk about number of cores, amount of memory, time, and then input output.
So how should we think about reading from disk and writing to disk?
And I saw some really cool pictures last night, which were like, well, made by [name]. Such
an amazing metaphor for what the cluster's doing.
So...
Yeah, and there are different possible analogies.
We might mention some of them, just to get a real-world analogy to what's going on.
Okay, should we get started then?