So it's me, [name], and my co-teacher, [name].
And we're here for the first part of the
workshop, which is the introduction to version control.
Yeah, I love everyone.
So, yeah, so I'm a staff scientist at Aalto
University working in what's essentially the high performance computing and
research software engineer team and I'm [name].
I'm an application expert at Upmux and nice in Sweden.
Very happy to be teaching it for you together with [name].
Yeah.
So let's see.
So if we start on our schedule here,
and we scroll down or the course page, we scroll down to the schedule.
Note that the schedule translates the times to what the browser thinks is your
time zone, so don't get confused with that.
And we come to introduction to version control.
I'll open that and switch here.
So, yes, so this is where we all start.
So the whole workshop is somehow
all about version control.
So the first week is more using it.
And then the first week is more learning how to use it.
And the second week is really applying it in a lot of cases to really drive it in
and see how it can benefit the actual work.
So the first
week,
starting about a year ago, we reorganized the lesson sum.
So previously, we started from the command line and did everything in some
sort of like basic order, but now we have a different plan.
So now the general idea is the first day
we get used to just the concepts by using the GitHub web interface.
The second day we go to the command line or VS code on your own computer and we
repeat the same things and show sort of a more realistic working.
method where you're editing code and things locally.
And then on day three, we sort of combine them.
So we do some editing ourselves, but then we also do collaborative work.
So we use GitHub and then we all contribute to the same exercise
repositories and practice making bigger projects.
But every day you'll see in the lessons we have these tabs where you can choose.
Do you want
to try to do the exercise from the GitHub web interface or from the command line or
from VS code or from R studio?
And I think that's the main options, but there might be even more added later.
Yeah, exactly.
And if you already have a preferred ID that has integrated, you're free to use that.
So that's that's perfectly fine.
Yeah.
Yeah, so that's a.
Yeah, so so even though we have
this general workflow, you can look at the other things and try
to get a preview of what comes before or use the older method
like the GitHub web interface if you're not set up for the local work.
There's a lot of options here and we'll
try to make it clear what you should be doing at each point of time.
So with that being said, are there any other starting notes before we begin?
Let's see.
Yeah.
So just to mention that today you only need a GitHub account and a way to actually
sign into your GitHub account and you can follow along just using that.
So no need to have VS code or or anything else set up.
Right. Yeah.
And I guess at the end of the day, we should talk a little bit about how to prepare for day two.
Yeah. Yes.
Okay.
Let's not forget that.
So with that being said, I will scroll down a little bit and we begin with motivation.
Yeah, [name], so tell us, why do we actually want version control?
Well, my favorite example was part of the icebreaker.
So the fact that several times a year,
my friends, as in people that I would think would know version control, come to me and say, yeah,
I've just lost some code I've done.
And now I have to go spend a lot of time to figure it out or make it again or whatever.
And it's just a bit unfortunate.
Like, I feel bad for them, but also I understand because I've been in those places, too.
I used to often lose my code because I didn't have this code time machine to go back or I did.
But I only wanted to use it when it was.
Perfect.
And not when it was.
There
are not when not all the time, but let's see.
So basically what we get here when we.
Scroll down on this page, it is about keeping track of changes
and the changes are what makes the time machine.
So, for example, this is a screenshot from the GitHub Web interface and you see here there's
dates, so
something made on June 22nd, 2023, October 21st, 2021 and so on.
Going back, we see a quick description of what it is, who did it and then
some other things so we can copy link and identifier for it and things like that.
So this is the history actually of a GitHub repository.
Yes, correct.
And this is our ultimate goal.
So once we have the history in the structured form, it becomes really easy
to say, oh, I want to go back to what we had in twenty eighteen
and see if it's any different than what we have now and so on.
So by the end of today, we hope that you can make one of these
histories yourself and understand why it's useful.
And when we scroll down more, this is what it looks like from the
command line from the terminal.
So it's the same kind of information.
We see a commit ID, author, name, description of it, and it sort of goes on down.
Same data.
So why do we keep track of versions?
I think this is probably something I've already said, but.
Yeah, I mean, basically.
If you want, you can see all kinds of
problems here, which you probably heard before or will hear here in your career,
but which can be easily answered with having this kind of history.
Are there any here that are especially bad?
This my laptop is gone.
Where's my thesis gone?
That's I mean, I remember here.
Yeah, like when I was doing my thesis, I remember hearing stories of
yeah, my laptop's been stolen and my thesis is gone and just like, well, nothing to do.
So I was very how would you say it?
Strict in using version control and pushing it to make a copy on another server.
So I know that no matter what happens to my laptop, I'd be able to get all that stuff back.
And there's plenty more.
I think that identifying a version that authors use in a certain paper is very useful.
As I mean, especially with the larger
software that is being developed constantly and new features being added,
it's important to know what exactly has been used in a different in a certain version.
Yeah.
So, yeah, that's important.
And we'll teach you actually how you can refer to a particular version of your code
or repository doesn't have to be code.
It can be whatever really.
Okay.
Well, that reminds me.
So when talking about an old version of the paper,
one thing I usually hear people complaining about is I've got my
paper reviews back and now I need to do some updates.
But they've kept working on their code for other projects and now they can't
reproduce what's in the paper anymore and they're getting different things.
And that's just
well, tragic, maybe like,
how how is it different?
So we have to think something's probably improved there.
But if you can't easily find it, then how can you be confident in what you've got?
So once we have this version control, it's not just the history.
So there's other things.
So rollback is kind of obvious.
So we have an old version we want to go to and we can say revert me to that version.
We can also do branching and work on two things at the same
time, merging and collaboration.
So, for example, if you have a project where you're working with multiple people,
two people add different features as represented by the hat and sunglasses.
And you can combine them later.
I have a feeling that part of the how would you say, not problem,
but like one of the barriers to good scientific collaboration is that it's hard
to share code like this.
Many people aren't good at it.
So you end up having two copies of the code and they don't really sync.
I know that's been a problem with some of my previous collaborators before.
Yeah, so a bit on branching, so one can see branching as a kind of like
a different line of work for the same code, maybe a new feature that you're
trying to implement and you don't want to keep it in your main branches.
You're maybe not sure if that's something
that's something actually you want to keep.
So you can view all the so you can view
the sunglasses as like a feature that that your project may have.
And you will show you later how you can
actually merge these together on your main branch.
If if you're happy with it.
Yeah.
So kind of like an experimentation.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay.
Once we have this more reproducible, just like with the paper review thing,
so you can understand where all the changes are.
So this view here, I guess the picture is kind of small,
and I can't really zoom in.
You can open the link, browse this example online,
and then it's going to have it.
Oh, this works very nice.
This works.
So what we see here on the right side is all the code.
And on the left side, we see exactly when each line of code was last edited.
So this is a file that has been opened.
One file in this repository called NetworkX.
Yeah.
I mean, what you see in the code doesn't matter right now.
So this is just an example.
We're going to go into more depth for all of these things later on.
Who's ever wanted to send someone a bit of code so they can see it,
but it's annoying to attach it to an email and tell them where to look or copy and paste.
With GitHub, we can do things like paste it into
like paste a link that highlights a certain bit of code.
How do we use Git?
What do we use it for?
So obviously there's code and software.
There's other scripts.
There's documents.
For example, if you're writing a paper in LaTeX, it works really well there.
But even other files that aren't plain text files, you can, in theory, track with version control.
Configuration file, website sources.
This lesson.
Itself that you're reading now is itself tracked in version control.
So you could say that the whole workshop is a lesson in how to use
the teaching tools in the workshop if you want to be recursive about it.
One question.
So what would be the advantage of actually using version control like it instead of
using different zip files which are dated?
Yeah.
So, yeah, you could always go and make a backup copy manually like this where you
basically, well, are archiving different things.
But with all these archives, you can go back to a certain time.
But what if you want to see what the differences are?
That's sort of hard.
What if you want to compare over time?
What if you want to see what's in each of these?
What if you want to search for a certain change you've made and so on?
That's more difficult.
So this is better than nothing.
But compared to being able to run one command and save all your work in the same
place, it's not quite so convenient.
Yeah.
And one thing I would add, if you actually have a project which is quite large in
size, you don't want to make all these different copies of your project.
This actually is going to save only one version of one change to a file.
So it's going to keep
so it's going to ensure that your tracked project is actually light in size.
Yeah.
One big advantage, especially for big projects.
And this provides nothing with the branching and merging and things like that.
If I send someone a zip archive and they work on it, now I have two zip archives
and that's a bigger problem.
So.
Yeah.
But we know that not everything is perfect, so there are difficulties.
And the point of our lesson here is to try to make it easier.
So it's another thing to learn.
But I think everyone here would agree that it's well worth the time spent to learn
it.
If you want to do anything else in your career with code and so on, it's better
to learn quickly.
If you have collaborators that don't want to use version control, well,
I'm sorry, but, you know, that is a pretty common thing.
When I was doing my academic work,
it was always hard to find someone that wanted to take the time to do it.
But I mean, if you help them, maybe they will begin working.
I've often done a thing where I've had version control of a manuscript
and I would send my advisor a copy by email, but I would track locally
what version they last got so I can merge it myself on my end.
And this last point here about advanced
things being difficult is definitely a bit of a problem somehow.
But I think that our philosophy here is that
the basic things should be easy and don't worry about the advanced things.
Even if you use Git in the most basic way,
it will save you time compared to other things.
And you don't need to worry about advanced stuff.
So we are really trying to make this a user friendly and practical starting course.
And to be honest, when you need to do something advanced
and you don't know, you can ask someone else or learn it when you need to.
There's no need to for everyone to know everything.
Yeah, exactly.
I think, I mean, it is so beneficial if you just even if you use it in a very basic
way, so you don't have to know all the commands.
I don't know all the commands.
You can just take it slow,
learn to do some things, and then you'll grow from there.
So there is no need to learn everything from the beginning.
Yeah.
And there are other things besides Git for version control, but
we focus on Git because it's the most popular one,
which means that it's in the most places already.
And well, in the end,
teaching the more common thing is more
useful because that's what you're more likely to use.
We want to be practical and not pedantic.
But it does have some good features like the distributed nature,
although it's not the only one that's distributed.
Right now.
So with that being said,
should we check the notes and see if there's any questions?
Yes.
There should be a motivation section here.
Most of these, is there a limit to the size of files and documents?
No, not really.
I mean,
there's only the practical limit of how big of stuff you want to control.
Yeah, maybe.
So one good point is that
if you have the repository on your laptop, then it's not really a size limit.
But if you put things on a different platform like on GitHub or GitLab or
anywhere else, there may be a limit for private repository.
Private repository.
So that is something that you may want to consider.
There is no limit, as I know, for public ones.
But if you are not ready to share it
with the world yet, then there may be some limits there.
And there is actually one link in the answer there.
So you may check.
And this also, so this limit actually changes over time.
So I think, well, one is more and more, I mean, this usually goes higher.
And higher over time.
Yeah.
Storage.
There's a really good question here.
Number nine, can I use Git for Word and PowerPoint?
So it's, I wouldn't even, it's designed for code and text files,
but you can store any kind of files in there.
So Git would look at the Word and PowerPoint things as just binary documents.
And you don't get things like the
differences and merging to look so good.
But I've done this before when I've worked
with people who want to write a paper and they're only using Word.
I have my own private repository where I'm tracking things.
And you can also use extensions that let
you show differences between versions and things like that.
Yeah, exactly.
So the difference between GitHub and GitLab.
I think that's probably being
answered there and we'll answer it later.
So maybe we should go on.
Yeah.
So I think, yeah, everyone wants to know how they actually get to work with Git.
So maybe I'm going to get the screen share from you.
And let's look further into a repository.
And we are going to start with a repository on GitHub.
So I hope you can all see my screen here.
So you find this lesson.
So we are going to continue with modifying an existing project.
And I'm going to now zoom this in.
And the very first thing is copy and browse an existing project.
And as I said, we are going to look at something which is stored on GitHub.
And what we will be doing is to make a copy.
Of an existing one that we have prepared for you.
And in GitHub terms, when I say making a copy, what I mean is making a so-called
fork of this repository and the one note here.
So usually when we refer to a repository,
so a copy of our project on a cloud platform like GitHub, we usually refer to it as a remote.
So if you see remote, then think of it as a repository in the cloud.
So what we're doing now, are we looking at GitHub to see something that exists?
And we make our own copy, which is the fork.
Exactly.
And we will share exactly which repository we look at.
And throughout these lessons on Git, there will be different ways you can follow this along.
Some parts can only be done on GitHub.
But other times you can do this via the command line or using other IDEs like
VS Code or other IDEs which have Git integrated.
But what we'll do in this first lesson is to show you how you can do it on GitHub.
And throughout the lesson, I'll let you know if other options are actually more suitable for the things that we do.
But again, now we'll be focusing on GitHub.
So the first thing we will do is to create a copy of an existing repository.
So create a fork of this repository.
And so think of, again, I mean, as there is a repository as copies,
different copies taken at different times of our project.
And the project we will be working with is called Recipe Book.
And it's under a GitHub user organization, which is called CR Workshop Exercises on GitHub.
And so what we'll do by forking is to make another copy of this repository.
So with all these different commits and branches that it may have,
but not residing in this user space, but in our own user space.
And so we'll copy this
under our own organization or user space on GitHub.
So which is the repository that we are going to copy or fork?
So it's this one here.
So github.com CR Workshop Exercise Recipe book.
So you may just open this.
This in in a browser and
for the sake of.
So I will be working with this repository instead,
which at this point is identical with Recipe Book.
And the reason is because, well, I don't want some some
other usernames to want to show up as we are now streaming this.
But no worries, these two repositories are identical.
At this point.
So I am going to open this in a new tab and go to that tab.
It's a bit tricky.
Yes, so so I have CR Workshop Exercises Recipe book recorded
and I am going to just check a little bit what this repository is is all about.
So I will just decrease the font size a bit so that you see that.
This looks a little bit I mean,
being zoomed out, you lose some of the information that is on the page.
But basically we have a content
of the repository.
So all the files and directories that we are tracking with git.
Then we have some information about about the repository by default.
GitHub is actually going to show the content of the readme file.
And it's usually nice to have a readme
file for your repository so that people know, oh, what is this all about?
So this is just a repository that tracks different recipes and it's categorized.
Well, they are all stored into different directories, and I can see that if I go
to these different directories, then I may find different files.
So so what we are going to do now is actually
not to work in this repository.
And why, you know, why, why, why wouldn't I want to work on this repository?
Yeah, so this reminds me like what you're
showing here seems like something I do quite often.
So there's some new project, new code.
And I want to see, OK, like, do I want to use this person's project in my own work?
So I go there and first I'll browse it and see what's in there.
And then I decide, yes, OK, I want to try using this myself
and maybe I want to modify it.
But I guess I can't modify someone else's work on GitHub.
So I make my own copy.
Yeah, and that's what is going to happen here.
So what we are going to do is to fork this repository.
So make our own copy of this repository.
And actually, GitHub is very smart in showing
what different tabs do if you just hover over with the
mouse over them. So I'm going to click on this fork.
So I click on fork.
And again, I mean, you should not use this
recipe book recorded, but you should use the recipe book.
So then I am prompted to choosing an owner.
So under which
user space do I want to have this copy
of this repository? And I'm going to choose mine.
OK, first I'm going to rename this because I already have a copy of this repository.
I'm going to call it 25.
And so let's choose.
Oh, I cannot fork twice.
OK, maybe I should remove my other fork.
Oh, OK.
Yeah, this is.
So bear with me.
So what I'm going to do.
I'm going to delete my other fork.
So basically what happened is when you were practicing.
Exactly.
And I wanted to do that because I, you know, I pushed something.
So then you know how to actually I'm going to click on settings.
No.
Oh, this is a bit.
These settings.
And somewhere here there should be a danger zone.
And then I'm going to click delete this repository.
And you should be certain this is what you want to do because there is no going back.
And then so this is a bit more advanced than.
Then we intended.
At least.
Step.
You really need to be sure you want to remove repositories.
So, yes.
So sorry for this.
And then let's go back to to these original.
Repositories are for this, I have.
So, yes.
So now I'm going to fork this from C.
Our workshop exercises.
And I have the owner selected a reposter name, which I may keep the same or I may change.
And then the description is taken from the original repository.
And I'm going to keep that.
I think it's a good one.
And then I'm going to deselect this.
And the reason why I do this, because I want to copy all the branches that this
repository had and then click on creating.
So what then what happens is I'm going to have this recipe book in my under my
GitHub username and then it looks exactly the same.
I even get an information that this is a repository which has been forked from
another one, but the content is exactly the same.
The advantage is that I actually have control over this reposter.
I can change this as I want.
Do any modifications I may wish and share them back.
As we'll see later.
So, yeah.
So then this is yeah.
And this is possible because it's on GitHub and because it's public.
Could I do this with a private repository?
So
you can not do this with a private
repository unless you have you have permission to fork from that one.
So you have to be.
You may need to be added actually as a member to that.
OK,
to that repository before being able to fork.
Yeah, yeah.
So you still have the permission things going on here.
OK, yeah.
OK, OK, then so.
So, by the way, I'd like to say there's a emergency update of the notes document.
So it's offline right now.
I've been watching this in another chat, so don't don't panic if you can't ask
questions right now, but hopefully we will be back in five or 10 minutes.
Yeah, so then
so now that we have our fork.
What we are going to do is to investigate this repository that we have forked.
And one thing before we.
Do that. So these copy.
So now this repository that we have copied
from, we usually call it the upstream repository.
So it's just another fancy name, GitHub term for or a git term actually for
four repositories that we have copied from.
So upstream.
And and then so the exercise that we'll be doing in the following is to browse
through this fork that we have copied, investigate the commit history,
check, I mean, how we can find different different
different terms in in different files.
Check, I mean, who has modified the what in this repository?
And we are going to do this for 20 minutes, I think.
20 minutes and hopefully
the collaborative document is going to be back online fast so that you can get to
ask us questions, but yes, I'm going to time for a break.
Should we say maybe break plus exercise time?
Um.
And then.
Yes, so let's say that.
So break and exercise until
15 past or no, that's a bit short.
And that's 20 past to 20.
So that's.
10 minutes break and 15 minutes exercise.
I guess we can start with that, but the notes is working again.
OK, great. It works.
OK, cool.
If at any point you don't know what to do, please ask us.
It's in a collaborative document and.
And yeah, hopefully you will enjoy this first exercise.
Yeah.
OK, so we sent the notes and you can read further instructions there.
See you in a little bit.
Bye.
Yeah, we are back.
Welcome back, everyone.
I hope that you got to try the first exercise.
I'm sure it has been a bit tricky,
especially for those of you that are new to the GitHub interface.
But but I was thinking that actually
in the following minutes, I'm going to walk you through the solution.
And so I am now in this repository again
that I have forked the recipe book recorded and you are working with the recipe book
one, that's OK.
So the first thing that you were asked to do is to browse the commit history.
So then one way to browse the history is to
well, simply look at the.
Oh, looks a bit different.
Look at the commits.
I'm going to move the make this a bit larger.
So.
So here I have,
for example, the last the latest commit that has been done by us and
[name], I have lost the commits.
Where were they?
It was supposed to be somewhere here.
So
the history, could it be the.
The clock icon?
Yes. Sorry.
It's because whenever I have the the window smaller, then it just doesn't show everything.
So I have the latest commit, which was done seven months back.
And then clicking on this clock, then I can actually go and see not only
the latest one, but all the all the commits that have been done for this repository.
Let me scroll this back.
So then if you remember from the
motivation part.
So I see
the commit message.
So this is actually what is shown in bold here.
The time of the commit and the committer and also a hash.
And actually, it's only part of the hash that each command has.
So it's like a unique identifiable for a commit, which is think of it like like a snapshot of of the state
of the repository at that particular time.
So September 1st.
And then I can see the whole history from the latest to the first commit.
I can also change the branch.
So there are different branches for this particular repository.
There is a lasagna branch, which again, I mean, has its own history of commits.
So this is one way of looking at the history.
There is another feature that GitHub has in order to see the history of a repository.
If you go here, so the top menu and then click on insights and then network,
then there is a graphical visualization of of the repository.
So I.
So we have worked on the.
Repository.
So today, the 25th of March.
So this whole history of commits is actually
the one that has been on the original upstream repository.
So the one we worked from and then and then there are some some new
commits that I have introduced and we'll talk about them in the next episode.
But so all this line, so the black one with the different circles, it's like one line of
commits, one branch in this repository and time is going.
So from left to right is increasing time.
And then there is another branch here shown in blue,
a branch which is called Alex Fruit Salad, which has a couple of commits.
So it's a branch which has been formed at some point in time
and then it got merged back.
In version doesn't say the time.
I think I have to zoom in a bit, but we'll show you exactly how you can
actually form these branches and then merge them together in in the main one.
So that's another way of looking at the history.
So how can I actually find out when a recipe was last modified?
So I go back to code.
And let's pick up one.
Recipe.
So I go into one of the directories, let's see this vegetarian lasagna.
So then sorry, let's get back.
So I see that this particular file has been last modified.
So so on the last commit date, some time last year, if I do open it,
then I can also get a hash of of the commit.
So it has been modified by
Bust, which will tell you all about Collaborative Git, the third day.
So and then what these are the contents.
I can see the history, which will tell me
all the different commits that actually modify this file.
So it's not only the one on
the fifth.
It's not only this commit, but there has been some other changes before.
So
let's quickly see the guacamole recipe.
So I go back to the
so I go back to code.
So let's see.
I actually do not know where the guacamole recipe is.
Then I can click on this button, go to file and start typing guacamole.
And then GitHub is going to search for this repository and open this file or that
that
well, in this case is the guacamole MD file.
So what we were to do here is that to see how many changes this file had.
And then again, as for the previous one, I'm going to click this history button.
And I see there are several different commits by
different
committers. So both Bust and Jamie Garcia that has committed to
that has introduced changes to this guacamole recipe and committed it.
So
step number five, which recipes include the ingredient salt.
So, of course, if you don't many people had problems with this indexing.
Yes, exactly.
So
there is a search button at the very top
towards the right.
Of of the page.
So if you want, click that button, then I can search actually in many different
repositories by default, GitHub is going to suggest that I search within this
particular repository, but I can search through the entire GitHub.
But by default, again, it's this it's this particular one.
And then I'm instructed to search for recipes that include ingredients salt.
So this is
so GitHub actually needs to index the
repository before it can actually search for it.
So the very first time you do the search, it's it may take a couple of minutes.
So as it does have to index this repository.
So if I look for a search, I see that actually there are many recipes that include
this term, so in salads mixed and sides and so on.
So
that is one way to search
the contents of the files.
So if you remember before
clicking that button, go to clicking the button, go to file,
which sometimes actually shows like a search button, it doesn't check the content,
but it actually checks the name of the files which match a certain syntax.
So it is different.
So
so
so number six, again, we are going to go to the guacamole recipe,
which I remember now it is in sides, guacamole.
So let's say that I want actually to know who has
edited this file and who.
So we remember that if we check the history, then we got the
the name of the committers for this file and when they have committed.
But let's say that I actually want to know which changes they have introduced.
So one way of doing that is by clicking on this
name, sorry, on this tab called Blame.
And this comes from the from the git blame command, which is actually similar to the git
annotate command.
So what it actually does is to
to break this
guacamole MD file into different lines and showing each lines have been modified by whom.
So the top of the file has been
changed by Bust.
And and then and it also what says when and then again,
I mean, there are different changes which have been introduced at different times.
So it's going to show by default, so the last the
so when a certain line or a group of lines have been modified last.
OK, then, so
can you actually use these recipes yourself?
And this is something that we'll talk a lot.
Well, we'll talk about next week.
So licensing.
What can you actually do with a repository that you have?
So the important thing is to look at the license.
And you can see this either
on the right part of the repository or you can also
find it close to the README file.
So if the repository has a license file, which is recommended, then you can
you can check what you are allowed to do with the repository.
What changes can you do and how you can share them?
So I'm going to click on the license file.
And let's say that I actually don't know what this Creative Commons license actually means.
So GitHub does
provide a very nice summary if you open the license file.
So this is a so the Creative Commons zero is a very permissive license.
You can use it commercially.
You can modify it and distribute it.
And yes, basically, you can
you can do
you can do almost anything.
It's not so suitable if you actually want to use this in a pattern.
So depending on what is the ultimate
goal of your project, then you may think of different licenses.
And then again, in next the next week,
we are going to have one lesson which discusses different licensing.
So the very final thing to show before we
go further is to browse issues and pull requests in the upstream repository.
So remember, the upstream repository is the one that we have
forked from, the one we have copied from.
So let's say I don't remember what that link was.
So if I go to my main page of the repository, then I can see that, OK,
it has been forked from this repository.
So I'm going to click on that and then I'm going to see.
So the top menu shows the issues.
There are two issues to this repository.
And well, the recipe
book repository, I'm sure, has many more issues.
But this one in particular has two.
And
issues, you can see issues as like, let's say that you have some questions about
this particular repository, maybe some features that you think that you would
like to introduce, opening an issue is one way of starting a discussion on a project.
Then there are some pull requests as well.
And how to actually create these pull requests and why they are useful.
We will be doing that in the first episode.
So, [name], anything else that we should discuss before actually
seeing how we can do commits now that we browse through the repository?
There is a lot of good questions in the notes that
we're monitoring.
I don't see anything that
maybe it's better to go to commit because
some of the questions are starting to be about how you commit and messages and so
on. So if we go to that, we can start answering them.
Exactly. So
committing changes.
How do you actually commit changes?
So
we have started from this
existing repository on GitHub.
But let's assume that now we actually want to introduce our own changes.
In this case, we want to add some new recipes or modify existing ones.
So we can do that.
So I'm going to scroll down a little bit as we have discussed that.
So let's say that we have an existing repository with different commits.
Let's say we have a series of commits on the main branch, so the main line of development.
And then we want to create a new branch.
So let's say that we have some features that we want to introduce and we do not
want to do it on the main branch because maybe, well, we don't.
We still want to ensure that this main branch produces results that we want.
And we just want to introduce some experimentation to our project.
So then we can create a new branch
that we refer to in this case as your branch.
And so our repository is going to
look like this. So we have a series of commits that
we add on this branch that we call your branch.
But at any point in time, we can actually
go back to the main branch and do further commits on this main branch.
So then what we'll have is, so except the initial commits that we had,
we have the new ones on your branch and then we have additional commits on main.
So this is what the
we'll want to
do in in this repository recipe book.
And again, there are different ways that one can do that.
One can use GitHub and that's what we'll demonstrate.
But one can also use the command line or work in an IDE as well.
So it's up to you.
But again, we'll show how you can do this.
You can do it on GitHub.
So
we will continue with the same repository, the recipe book one.
And
and then
what you need to make sure is that you work on your fork.
So you work in your username recipe book.
And then what you will do is to create a branch and add a recipe in that branch
and then modify.
That
recipe in on that particular branch that you created.
And further on, switch to the main branch and
and add yet another commit.
So
[name], so let's say how long time should we say for this particular exercise?
So we have 20 minutes
until the scheduled lunch break.
Should we
say 20 minutes and then go to lunch and we don't say anything else?
Or should we say
we come back for a brief wrap up?
So let's do a brief wrap up before the lunch.
I think that's that would be good.
Or we do the wrap up just after the lunch when we come back.
That's also an option.
Yeah, let's do a wrap up after lunch.
People can go to lunch early and beat the cues and so on if they want.
So, yeah. OK.
Yeah. So exercise lunch and then we are back in one hour and 20 minutes.
Yes. OK.
Oh, so I'm adding the info
to the notes doc where the exercise is.
We will keep
answering questions as usual.
Keep asking.
Yeah.
Any final stuff?
So summary is.
Now we're adding commits to something.
And yeah.
OK, so see you after lunch.
You. Bye.
OK, welcome back, everyone.
I hope you had a good break.
So just before
this longer break,
we're supposed to do an exercise
on GitHub.
For this recipe book repository.
And I will quickly walk you through a solution.
So I will.
Go back to my fork.
And the first thing that we were to do is to make sure that
you are that we are on the fork and that is correct.
So I can see my username there.
So I'm not under the CR workshop.
So I will show you how to find it.
So as you can see, the users.
Let me find my name and my user profiles.
Let me see.
So let's see where from the rest of.
Open diggers.
We're going to have a detailed niec but it when we want to make sure
we don't go into all the different
?
We go to.
We can show OK that's it?
which actually is the name of our default branch.
And I can switch to a new branch, sorry, to another branch,
or I can actually create a new branch by just typing the name of it in the search one.
So I will call, how should I call this new branch?
I will just call it new branch, which is a very bad name for a new branch.
But I will, I'll give you this bad name so that I can show you later how you can rename.
So that's what we have.
I'm now on this new branch.
And then what I am to do next is to add a recipe.
So this seemed to be a common question in the notes.
So something about making the new branch and then committing.
On it and getting the commit to show up in the right place.
And I know this is also often a problem with doing it other ways.
So it's important that before you add changes, you do check on which branch you are.
So if you are working on GitHub, then you see this just under the repo info.
So in the code menu.
And then this is the branch of the, the name of the branch under this source control symbol that you may also recognize in other IDEs.
It's like having this, well, it's a symbol for, for actually merge the, merge the branches.
So, so yes, do make sure that this name corresponds to the branch where you actually want to introduce changes.
That's important.
Just because you created the branch doesn't mean that you are on the wrong branch.
But on GitHub, the moment you do create the branch, it will switch to it directly.
And, and, oh, and now.
Oh, what happened?
It happens all the time.
When I, when I click, it just goes to, I don't know, goes bananas.
So now I'm on the main branch.
Actually, that's not what I want.
So let me switch to this new branch.
You see, I mean, sometimes GitHub behavior.
It's funny.
So it happened previously as well.
That's why sometimes I don't like to work with the web interface because it just does what it wants.
So here I switch to the branch I actually want, new branch.
And then I want to add some changes there.
So I will follow the instructions in the exercise.
So I was to, to, actually,
I should have created a new branch.
So sorry for that.
But the name is not super important.
So, but I should do, let's see, create a site recipe.
And so, yes, I am now in these sub-directory sites.
I'm going to add a file.
So I find it just under, under the menu, add file.
And what can I see?
I can click the plus to create a new file, or I can actually upload a file.
If I have one.
I don't, I'm going to edit it on GitHub, which is okay for short files, but for longer ones,
I mean, of course it's more convenient to upload, but this, it really depends on what you want to do here.
I should also name my file.
So I'm going to use mixed nuts and I'm going to give it the same extension as all, as the other files in my repository have.
So when a Markdown file in short.
It has an empty extension and then I'm going to enter a recipe.
So let's see, I do have a template somewhere there, but let's call it, let's give it a title, mixed nuts.
And what should we have?
So I should have some ingredients and maybe some of you actually notice that unless I have this line, there, there are some GitHub actions, which will fail.
Then we'll see that later.
So, um, what went here?
What's your favorite nut?
Uh, cashews, pecan, walnuts.
Yeah, walnuts.
And then let's add some instructions.
Let's say, um, I think it's adding extra, yeah, those bullet points there.
Um, let's see.
Uh, yeah, nice and simple and typos is always.
So now I have my file here.
So the next thing to do is to commit this, uh, change, then I click on this red.
Um, uh, bottom here.
So I, and.
Uh, then here.
And something is not working right now.
Let's go.
it is with a pop-up window asking for a commit message and uh and uh i get the default but i can
also write my own commit message so let's say add recipe for mixed nuts yeah okay so you're
and there was a question about what or how to write it and this is a common one it's like
imperative you are adding this yeah yeah so um this is a short uh change to our repository so
so it does not necessarily need an extended description but for example if you
do a lot of changes in your file then you might want to explain actually why you've
done those changes and what those changes are so one can add
an extended description here. But it is important to have a commit message which will identify
in short the summary of your changes so that you can more easily find a certain commit
in your history of commits. So this also shows as a top line in the commit message when you
display the history of your repository. So it's important you have something concise
and suitable for these changes. And then I'm going to check that the branch that this should
be committed to is the one that I actually want. So the default is the one that we had
under code, but I can also create a new one. That is not the case. I do want to commit
under this one. And then I just click commit changes.
Yeah.
Okay.
So then I'm actually, I get this interesting message saying that my branch is ahead of
the upstream repository. So the one I copied from. This is a nice way to see, I mean, how
does your repository stand with respect to the upstream? Do you? And yeah. So now we
are one commit ahead.
That means that I have one extra commit compared to these, to these repository. And as you
have forked from recipe book, you may actually get a different, a different message here.
Okay, then.
Yeah.
Now I should modify this recipe with a new commit on this, on the same.
On the same branch. So I will what I'm going to open this file again, and I'm going to
edit it. So I click on this edit. I don't want to add a new file. I just want to improve
it. So let's see. Seasoning. I'm going to say that we should have some seasoning, like,
salt or chili. What do you say?
Yeah, sure. I would like both of those.
Okay. So I like that. I'm going to commit this, and then I'm going to say ah, actually update
is not very useful.
I'm going to say add seasoning.
Oh.
Ooh.
and then clear this one okay then so on the same branch commit changes so now what do i have i have
two new commits right on my new uh branch and then uh step four is to switch back to the main branch
and modify a recipe there as well so basically introduce a new commit there so i am going to
click on code go back to the main branch so select the main branch here it is and what should i do
here um let's open a recipe let's see what we have for salads here fruit salad i'm going to edit this
file um
and let's say i actually don't want fresh means i'm going to take some whipped cream instead
and commit changes and then remove
it
okay and then
again make sure i'm the on the right branch that i am so what do i have now
i have uh one new branch sorry one new commit on main actually it's not very easy to see
here but let's go to to this history view that we looked at before so i have this uh
this new commit remove mined at cream on the main one while on this new branch i had a memory and then I worked a lot with sepertiy can i take physical keys to this new
not very easy to see here but let's go to to this history a view that uh we looked at before so i have this uh this new commit remove mean cream on the main one while on this new branch i have just in the first moment as one of the stop
I had added two commits.
Actually, there was a branch which was called a new branch before,
but I have new commits.
I added two new commits here, add seasoning and add recipe for mixed nuts.
So what do I want to do now?
I want to actually compare the changes I have introduced
to the change on the main branch.
So in the repo, and I'm going to scroll down a bit here so you can see.
So I'm going to go to code.
So here, where I have the name of my main page of my repository,
I'm going to take that back and actually click and edit, sorry, write compare.
So GitHub, my username, the name of the repository.
And then the important name compare.
So this, as you will see, works a little bit like the git div command.
So it will allow us to compare different commits that we have in our repository.
And I can choose either a branch or a commit from the left here.
So let's say.
That I want to compare.
Oh, how did you get here?
You got to.
So the way I did here.
So from the main page of the repository, I am in the wrong one.
It's the.
I should have.
It's because it swaps between the fork and upstream.
Okay.
A bit widely.
But so under my username and the name of the repository.
So recipe book reported and then compare.
So, yeah, this is what one should get.
And then I am prompted with what I would like to compare.
Either compare against the upstream.
So this.
Is your workshop exercises and I can choose which branch in particular.
I want to compare from there or yeah.
And what I want to compare with.
So by default, it took my own repository, my own fork, and then, and then the branch name.
So actually I can see that compared to the upstream.
So the main branch has a change and that change is in.
This fruit salad file and the change is so in red is shown.
What is missing in my main branch and in red shows what I have added to my, to my commit.
So I added this line and I removed the other one.
So this is what is different and I can also use it.
So that will show, and I can also cookies.
And, and then I want to compare header to playing at
I have no youremp would say I want to compare a certain commits.
Then you want to do that.
I'm going to go to the history view again.
Okay.
So let's say I want to.
Yeah.
Two different commits.
the right thing here. And this is what I find a little bit annoying with
GitHub, because I can't see everything, first of all. Compare. Ah, this is so annoying.
So then actually you know what I'm going to do so that you all see what I am typing.
I'm just going to type it here.
Let's see. Bear with me for one second.
Okay. I see you opened notepad here.
I'm going to open a text editor so that I can actually see what I am typing. So
compare. And then I'm going to copy this hash, for example. Let's see. And then you don't see
everything.
Mm-hmm. But I see
So now, so I add the full hash, and I'll add two dots, and then copy another hash. So let's see.
Actually, what is in my...
So this is upstream.
So this is the upstream. So the problem is that this always changes back automatically whenever
Mm-hmm.
Whenever I am...
Whenever GitHub doesn't find the link that you are trying to
edit, then it kind of figures out for you what you should be typing. So let's
edit the right thing. So this is very annoying.
And maybe you explain...
I'm going to change this as well.
So let's go back to the end and add the other hash.
Okay. So let's go to the new branch and the latest commit on that.
Okay. I see your two commits.
Yes. And now I'm going to...
I'll copy paste this.
Okay.
This is not element, I should say.
Yeah.
I don't like this a lot, but it's a way to show that you can compare two commits on
GitHub, so...
Here we have it. We have a change between that commit specifies first and that was
on the main branch. And then we have another hash, which stands for the latest commit on the
new branch. And what is different is this new file mixed nuts with this content. So again, it's,
yeah, it is a little bit troublesome to actually add all these hashes, so I don't find it ideal,
but it is one way of doing differences. And the final thing is renaming a branch. So let's see
how we can actually do that. So going back to the history of my commits, I see, oh actually I should
see all, view all branches. Let's do that. View all branches. So then I have a list of all the
branches for my repository. So let's assume that this new branch actually had a bad name. It's not,
actually it is very,
very bad because it's not representative for what it includes. And I have to scroll a little bit
here so that I get to the most right part with these three dots, which, if I click on that,
allows me to rename the branch. So I'm going to give it another name, `[name]/hummus` [the branch name includes our name]. It's not,
it's quite common,
actually, to rename a branch. So I'm going to rename it `[name]/hummus`. It's not, it's quite common,
actually, that a branch, especially for a repository that has several collaborators,
that the branch contains the name of the person that initiated that branch. Especially if you are
the only person working on that particular branch. Okay. So that was it. I can also have tags and then,
again, go into code. So you'll see me going back to the main code a few many times. So I can add
tags, for example, there. And there are no tags right now. So what is a tag? Tag is like adding
another identifier to a certain commit. So let's see, I can
I can choose a new tag. Let's see, version 0.1. And then I have to specify which branch do I
actually want to tag. And then also the commit that I want to tag. So I'm going to take the
keyed node. It doesn't matter, so this one. And I will describe this as first draft of my recipe.
And then publish release.
Okay. So, but now what was it?
I have? So I have this new branch, `[name]/hummus`, which I may actually merge into the main branch,
if I wish. And then if I am on GitHub, I see that I am prompted with a compare and pull request tab.
So what happens if I click on that? So I can then incorporate the changes that I have in the Homos
branch into the main one. So I merge these two lines of work into one branch again. So what I
have to do is...
Is what we're doing part of the exercise right now, or is it going further?
No, it's not part of the exercise.
So we are now moving further into, so let me show you.
So we are moving now into merging changes and contributing to the project.
Okay, so is this a demo right now of this part?
Yeah, you can probably longer, you can better just watch
and then you can get to do this as an exercise.
Okay.
So what you need to be careful, especially when you're doing this on GitHub,
is to specify which repository you want to have a pull request against.
So because GitHub knows that,
this repository is a fork of the upstream one CR workshop exercises recipe book,
then it's going to have a pull request against this repository by default.
But I actually do not want that.
I want to do a pull request against my,
repository, the main branch on my repository.
So now you'll see that by selecting that I got back to my main one.
And then the branch that I want to merge into this one is the Anahomous branch.
So that that was correct.
And then it tells me, so GitHub tells me that it's able to merge this automatically.
automatically. I can add a title, so merging humus into main, for example, and I can give
it a description and create a pull request. There are different options. So if I click
on this triangle, I can see that I can choose the default, create pull request, but I can
also create a draft. This is if you still want to work on your branch before the final
merge. That is not what we want right now. We want to ask for a pull request. So this
is what I'm going to click on. So again, what this means is that I want to merge the humus
branch into the main one.
Okay.
So then
it tells me that, okay, everything is ready to be merged, but I actually have to confirm
the merge. And because I am the only person that is actually working on this repository,
I get to do this merge myself. But when you are working on a shared repository with several
people, usually the person that does the pull request is not the one that is merging.
Okay.
So that is just, yeah, it's just a practice. But for repositories that you are working
on yourself, you can do the PR and the merging yourself. So then I click on this and then
I can provide a commit message. So I'm happy with that. And I click on commit merge.
So then let's check actually our network graph, see how that looks.
And then I'll listen to your comments.
One second.
So we're insights.
Sorry, I clicked on settings instead.
So insights network.
It takes a bit of time when there are many new commits.
It's going to show up quickly.
So what I have is this blue branch.
It was my `[name]/hummus` branch.
And then what I did in this last commit is to merge it into main.
So GitHub is going to show it like, okay,
there is an arrow from the `[name]/hummus`.
Branch into the main one.
It also prompts me with the commit message for that merge.
And now you may wonder why there are so many other things under the main one.
So these are simply different forks that exist for the upstream repository.
So GitHub is going to collect all that information and put it all in the
network graph.
Yeah.
Okay.
So where are we now?
So let's see.
So what we did was to show how a merge can be done on GitHub.
So then what you can do now.
So you also had your several commits on a branch and some,
possibly some new ones.
And you are commits on main.
So your task is now to attempt to merge these branches.
So merge your branch into the main one.
So everything you just did with the pull request and the merge is now the
exercise where people do it themselves.
Yes.
Following the instructions.
Okay.
Yes.
And you can do it as I have done it using GitHub.
That's one solution.
And if you're comfortable with the command line and you've worked a little
bit with Git before,
then you may attempt this solution as well.
But I recommend that you try GitHub.
There's a good question.
Number 61.
Can you make a pull request from the new branch to the main branch of the
original repository?
Yes.
And I think that.
Go ahead.
Yes, you can.
Yes, you can do that.
And that is actually very common.
You usually do a pull request against the upstream.
And that is the whole reason why you actually do a fork.
For repositories, you do not have the right to modify.
You do some line work in your own fork.
And,
and then,
you may you may ask for a pull request and have your changes integrated in
the upstream repository.
So yes,
that is possible and very common.
Yeah.
And this is done as part of step seven of the it's an advanced step optional.
You can do it,
but also on day three,
we do this a lot.
But I'd recommend starting with doing it in your own repository,
because then you can merge it today.
We're not going to be merging stuff into the public repository.
No,
we'll show that more on day three.
Yeah.
Okay.
So then,
uh,
exercise time until,
10 to set a good time.
[name] until for 20 minutes.
Okay.
Or how long did you say until yes,
20 minutes.
Okay.
So until,
yeah.
Okay.
Sounds good.
Um,
I'm setting it up and so the exercise is this here and our goal is to do everything except the optional step.
And after that we have more discussion.
And stuff while you wrap up,
I think.
Okay.
Great.
See you in a little bit.
Bye.
welcome back from the break.
What the exercise break.
Uh,
so,
I.
Uh,
I'm going to show these very final,
So every final step, which was optional, on how to actually handle pull requests to the upstream branch.
And so for that, I am going to go to CR Workshop Exercises Recipe Book and click on Pull Requests.
And please know that this is the recorded version, so I will not see all the pull requests that you have done.
But in this case, there are three pull requests.
So let's take this one from [name].
So what do I get to see here?
I get to see the committer.
And also, let's see.
What I want to see.
Is which files have been changed in this version that he has.
So there is a new recipe for burritos.
So this is the file that has been changed.
There are several commits in this branch.
And I assume, well, one of them has, well, two of them have failed.
So then he actually proposed a new commit that solved some of the errors that.
That.
Were in, uh, in the project.
So, uh, I, let's see why I'm actually happy.
I am happy with this, uh, proposed the change.
So then what I can do is to merge the pull request that, uh, that, uh, [name] proposed.
So, um, I can also add the comments.
So it's, uh, especially nice to, uh, write the comments, especially if you don't, uh, need these
commits.
Um, and, uh, you only get to communicate with them via, via GitHub.
So thank you for your contribution.
And also I can, uh, comment, uh, to a pull request even before I merge and actually say,
okay, I would like you to change.
A certain file or, uh, or improve on a feature.
So I don't have to necessarily, uh, accept the merge in, uh, in its current state.
So maybe I want [name] to do some changes before that, but in this case I am happy.
So I'm going to merge it and I can, uh, write, uh, another commit message for the merge.
I'm going to take that and confirm the merge.
So then he's, uh, uh, recipe for the, uh, burritos is going to be in the main branch.
So if I go now to mains, then I can see that I have his recipe incorporated here.
I see.
Yeah.
So anything else that, uh, that we should add?
Let's see.
Uh, there's a question number 68, contributing to the original repository with pull request.
Um, you normally it's the other person.
So if you're contributing to someone else's repository, it's the other person that will
do the merge, but you don't need to have it in your main branch or anything.
It can be in your own branch.
Um, yeah, uh, there's Git switch versus Git checkout.
There's an older form of basically the same command.
So yeah, Git switch is the modern word for it.
That's been made a bit less confusing.
Um, should we go to our break now?
We can keep with the questions.
And then, um, we can do some final demos and discuss discussion afterwards.
Yeah.
Let's take a break.
And then we come back at 10 past.
Is that a good time?
Yeah.
Sounds good.
So back in 10 minutes.
So sounds good.
See you then.
Bye.
okay welcome back from the break
so
before we show
a final demo
[name]
is there anything that we should
bring from the
collaborative doc
there was
a question about
restoring branches
and all
and
how long
like
how long can you restore things
I don't know how long
the
github button
for restoring branches
is still there
like if you make other changes
that
wouldn't work
but all the history
is
in the repository
and if you do a normal merge
you can always go
backwards
so maybe that's the more
important lesson there
once you have the history
even if
you don't have the button
you can
go backwards
yeah you can always see
the
closed
pull requests
and if you get to your
closed
pull requests
you can see that
okay you can
you may restore your
deleted branch
yeah
and
usually want to do that
if you want to add some
some
additional commits
to that branch
so yeah
and also the moment you do
a
new pull request
with the same name
then
that will be
restored by default
so
and there's some of these
other questions
about
pull
pull requests
versus
what's it
pull requests
versus
pushing
and so on
these are good questions
but maybe
we'll
go into them more
later when we do
some more
other demos
and so on
yeah
I think there's some
reasonable answers there
yeah it is a bit
confusing also
it's
what different
what all terminology
that
that github has
github developers
have been using
and it's
a bit
tricky to understand
sometimes
but
if one should use
pull or pull
yeah
anyway
let's go to
actually
introducing a conflict
in our
merge
and
how do we get
to do that
so I'm going to go to
my own fork
and
so first off
what is a conflict
so
and
is this something
that we need to go into
now
like
where will
I mean
we want to go into it now
but
when does it become
important
so
a conflict
appears
when
you are changing
the same
portion
of the file
in two different branches
and then you want to merge
those two branches
and then
either you merge it
via the command line
or
or on github
it doesn't know
git doesn't know
okay
how do you actually
which changes
do you want to keep
from these two branches
because I'm having
contradicting
modifications
to the same
part of the file
and I have no idea
how to resolve those
so that's
that's what we mean
like a conflict
I am unsure
git is unsure
about how to merge
these different changes
because
they appear
in the same
file
in the same portion
of the file
into
different commits
that we want to merge
different
two different branches
we want to merge
so
I think it's going to be
clearer
if I
demo it
so again
I'm going to
do that
on github
so
I will create a new branch
let's call it
oh
what should I call it
creatures
hmm
good question
well
I'm going to make it
I'm going to call it soup
because my plan
is to
take some
are you modifying
your recipe
here
yeah
I'm going to take
an existing recipe
this mushroom soup recipe
and I am going to
to modify it
and then commit
these modifications
so I am
yes I am in
in the branch
soup
and I am going to
save this
into a new commit
and then I'll
assume
let's assume
that
yeah
let's see
that
um
what did I want to change
here
that I want to have
two cups
of
cream
okay
yeah
and then
I'm going to
save this
changes
into a new commit
so
more
cups
of cream
and then
I'm going to
save this
and then commit
this to
[name] soup
okay
and then
what I will do
is I'm going to
go to the
main branch
now
and
change exactly
the same file
where was the
main branch
here
I'm going to
change the same file
again
actually the same
portion of the
file
but I'm going to
introduce a different
change
so
soup
mushroom soup
edit
and then
I'll say that
okay
I actually
only want
half a cup
of heavy cream
and then
commit this
change
again
well now I am
on the main
branch
to commit this
so
um
I'll call it
less cream
this commit
message
and
commit
so
what do I have
now
I have two different
modifications
to this soup
recipe
in two different
branches
and it's
the same line
which is modified
in different ways
so now
let's go
to
let's try
to merge
this
so I have
branch
[name] soup
that I
want to
merge
into the main
branch
so I click
compare and pull
request
and again
I should be
careful
what I
want to
merge
so I don't
want to
merge
against the
upstream
I actually
want to
choose
my
repository
and
I
uh
want to
merge
the branch
called
the
soup
so I
can't
it's
not
in
my
web
so I
have
to
merge
this
is
a
common
thing
to
happen
if
it's
a
project
with
multiple
people
hopefully
you're
And I could still create a pull request or a merge request, but then it told me that,
okay, you have to resolve the conflicts before this can be merged.
So then what I do is to click on this resolve conflicts and I, so GitHub is going to open
this file, mushroom soup, which has the conflict.
And it's going to introduce these delimiters to indicate where the conflict is.
Usually when one resolves the conflict, actually one should remove these delimiters.
So I will remove them.
And it's the same if one does it on the command line, these delimiters will show up, but then
I have to decide which of these lines or well, how do I want this line to look like?
So what do you think?
I'm actually going to go for half a cup.
Okay.
So this is you as a human deciding which one is the more useful one right now.
Exactly.
Yes.
So I am going to scroll down and then mark, yes, it was actually up here.
So mark as resolved and then click on commit the merge.
So mark as resolved, it means that actually I have accepted this change, but I still have
to instruct.
GitHub that I want to merge these two branches.
So merge the, the Anna soup branch into the main one and I can add more comments.
Okay.
I don't want to add more comments and then just confirm this merge.
Yeah.
So yeah, that's one way a conflict can, can emerge.
And of course it's undesirable.
Yeah.
If there are two different people that have introduced changes and you don't know how
to resolve them, then some then might actually need to sit together or have some email communication
or GitHub communication to see how it's best to resolve that conflict.
Yeah.
So this is actually pretty useful because normally if two people were modifying the
same thing.
Yeah.
You would have to be human to open them both and figure out what's what and do a lot of
manual work here.
You still had to do manual work, but it showed you exactly what the problem was and was much
easier than some of the manual merges in my past when I've sent someone code and had to
get it back.
Yeah.
Cool.
I think this also makes us realize that if you have a branch you've been working on,
working on a long time and you're waiting for too long before you actually try to merge
it into the main one, it's more likely that you are going to encounter conflicts when
you try to merge.
So it's, it's good to, to think, well, it's good not to wait too long before, before attempting
a merge because otherwise it's gonna, well, it's going to take many days to resolve some
of the conflicts.
Yeah.
So it's, of course, very dependent from repository to repository, but yeah, it's something to
keep in mind.
If it's one person, then, well, you get to re to decide how these conflicts should be
resolved.
But, but the more people involved, the more opinions.
So
Yeah.
Okay.
So what now should we go to the notes and for a final discussion?
Looking at different questions and so on.
Yeah.
Maybe just the final thing is like, so we showed most of the things on GitHub while
we did say that, okay, you can do all these using either the command line or using VS
code or another, another ID, but what is your preference, [name]?
When should we use what?
So.
I definitely do use GitHub sometimes, especially for small updates and things like that.
And for reviewing and merging things that are relatively clear, I don't often go making
new files and doing like serious changes.
So like adding a recipe, like we've done, yeah, I might as well copy and paste there
if I don't have it locally.
But for all the real work, it's always done via my local copy of the repository, which
is what we will get to tomorrow.
But still being able to merge both of them together is very useful because one is easier
short term.
One is easier long-term.
Yeah.
It's the same for me.
If I have one change for commit, it's the same for me.
Yeah.
Then yeah, I'll do that on GitHub.
And also if I'm working on a different computer and I don't have a clone of that repository,
so a copy of that repository on my local machine, then I'll just work on GitHub instead.
But the moment I have many changes to different files, then I think that using the command
line is better.
But then there is also a threshold until you get comfortable enough and you know enough
commands to actually get to do these things on the command line.
Although I think that, yeah, it's, you can do a lot with just 10 Git commands.
So there are definitely pros and cons to these different ways.
And I think that GitHub and the features that actually GitHub has have evolved a lot in
the last years.
There are many things that you can do using the GUI interface.
Yeah.
And I think that maybe the interface compared or the web interface compared to how it was
five years back.
So, and I think it's still going to evolve.
So at some point maybe you don't need to do things in the command line unless you, unless
you prefer that.
Yeah.
But, okay.
Let's see.
Did I already say at the bottom there's a feedback section, so we'll keep answering
questions.
You can tell us if today was too fast, too slow, a good speed and so on, and then something
to improve, something good about today, any other feedback and what you can keep asking
questions.
In the meantime, I want to talk about this question number 74 for a conflict to arise
there.
Sorry.
I'm making sure my cat isn't eating some cables or something.
Yeah.
So.
The conflict to arise.
So if it's the same line, it's a definite conflict.
Does anyone know, is it the case if there's something that's on several adjacent lines,
if it detects a conflict?
I think there has to be at least a line in between so that it's not interpreted as a
conflict.
Okay.
Yeah.
Makes sense.
Because.
Yeah.
So basically it tries to be safer rather than risk messing thing up.
But of course you can change code so that Git doesn't detect a conflict, but the final
code doesn't work together with the two different changes.
And for that, the way to detect it is with automatic software tests, which GitHub and
Git can run automatically.
But that's something we cover on day six.
And that's really sort of the capstone part of it.
Yeah.
So we haven't really showed how to compare commits.
Well, we did show how to compare commits on GitHub a bit, but I would say actually before
every single merge, you should check what you are trying to merge.
What are the changes that I introduced on this branch and the branch app and what are
the changes in the...
And what is different on the branch I'm trying to merge into.
That is, I would say a must before attempting any merge.
In this case, it was a simple example.
I knew exactly what is different on those two branches, but usually, well, you do want
to check.
I mean, what have people been modifying on the main branch?
I know the changes I made, or I can recheck the changes I made.
And then once I compare that either on GitHub or using Git diff.
Yeah.
And I know, okay, this is what I expect from the merge and maybe you may even actually
anticipate some of the conflicts before you are attempting the merge.
So definitely test how the commits are different between merging.
Yeah.
This is a common pattern we'll see in future days.
So it's really easy to, in VS Code, command line, or even GitHub, you get to a place like
you're on a branch.
You're expecting, and you start doing something and things get messed up somehow underneath.
So we'll really emphasize before you do anything, you stop, understand where you are, and then
you do the next part.
Yeah.
So before we take any other questions, should our participants prepare for anything in particular
before tomorrow?
Yeah.
Yes.
Actually, there's this news here that's related to this question.
Do we recommend VS Code or shell-based?
So for the news, so we have the recordings available.
Twitch will have them immediately.
And probably I will have them on YouTube by midnight finish time.
Let's see how well it actually goes.
So since tomorrow is more local work, so not from the GitHub web interface, today you didn't
need anything installed on your computer.
But tomorrow, you need something installed.
So we have two main tracks.
One is with the command line, and one is with Visual Studio Code.
And you can choose either of them.
I'm not sure which one we will demonstrate with, but it does require stuff to be installed
and set up.
So definitely look at the installation instructions.
And either way.
And then the one thing that I'm going to add, is that the shell crash course will be useful,
because it will prepare for today.
No matter what you do, you're going to need to type some things in a command line.
And it's better to have a little bit of familiarity with it first.
Yeah.
So if you're not used to the command line, then feel free to watch the shell course.
And in day three, there will be even more setup.
You'll need to join a team and request access to a report.
Yeah.
And then there will be the repository before you can do a certain part.
And as for what we recommend...
Yeah.
Yeah, sorry.
We will email you about the steps that you need to do before day three.
Yeah.
So no worries.
And as for do we recommend the shell or VS Code?
Really, I'd probably recommend whatever you're already familiar with.
already using if you're using VS code a lot use that because that's what you're more likely to
use later if you don't know well you can try it both tracks of the exercises do it in VS code
and then do it in command line or vice versa and then you see how they relate and will learn even
more because even though I use both of them sometimes well I use the shell more and it's
important to be able to put them together yeah and also if you have another ID that
you prefer that's also okay to use although we will not be demonstrating that but you can
still get help from from all the other persons behind the scenes which are helping us answer
all these questions yeah um is there anything else
um I guess the preparations for the next day is the most important part yeah I know I heard rumors
of there being a install help session via Zoom an hour before we start tomorrow I'm not sure if
that's happening but I guess you will get an email about it if it does yes and also many of the news
and important information is also
on the course website or will be on the course website uh shortly so uh we want to or actually
maybe I can show where to find all these of course I don't have the page open
so yeah just go to code Refinery and see a thing
what they say 25 25 Workshop yes
so news are going to be here and also you may find the past communication under this tab
communication so then all the communication all the previous emails are going to be there but most
important things
will be under the news
here
good to know
I think that's about
it for today and
hopefully you found this useful
and you'll join us tomorrow
and we'll continue with
it
yes
so
good so see you tomorrow
see you
bye