the schedule we have for day two a day two intro i'll open that up
so to recap day one we went through the motivation for version control mainly all the ways you can
lose code if you don't have good history and then on github web we made our own copies of a public
repository we committed stuff and we made pull requests and those are basically some of the
common operation kinds of things that you'd see so for day two it's similar but instead of working
via a web browser we clone from github to our own computer we do the same kind of things we
make commits we make branches we push and so on then since it's on our computer we can inspect
history in more detail to see how to figure out stuff in the past and then we figure out if you
have a new project on your computer then how you would um prepare this for git and push it
somewhere and a bunch of practical advice uh yeah anything else to add to the intro no i think that's
that's um that's it maybe i will just answer uh one of the questions we got regarding yesterday
and as i was a bit rushed when explaining it so so the question is why do we need tax
so why not yeah why tags at all so uh usually we can identify uh to a commit by either using
the hash of the commit if that commit is the top of the branch then we can refer to it
via the branch name also that will change once we push a new commit to that branch
So, one convenient way to refer to a certain commit, so a certain copy of our repository
at a given time, is by introducing yet another reference to a commit.
So then when I say, okay, look at this commit with, I know this really long hash, I can
just say that okay check check this commit with uh with the tag i don't know version 1.0
or or anything so uh so it's like a more kind of it needs a battery like easier to read the
the version name, simply.
So, and this is especially useful if you are,
well, if you are developing a code
and then you want people to refer to certain versions
and be able to cite certain versions
when they are using that in their paper.
So, yeah, referring to a version,
well, to a tag
the version
it's maybe better
than, well, it's not better
but it's just more readable
simply
yeah, anything you want to add [name], sorry
not really
I think
that was a good thing to answer
and
yeah, let's go
so should I switch to your screen?
yes, please do so