okay there you go so then what we are going to be doing today is to clone a git repository and
work on it locally so what we'll do is we are going to bring our work we have done on github
yesterday on our local machines so is font size big enough it looks okay to me does
anyone else have a comment well write in notes and i'll relay if you need okay so then whatever
we did yesterday so doing commits in our repository creating new branches merging
merging branches, we are going to experiment with that on our local machines. So then
a small recap from yesterday. So what is our Git repository? So it simply contains all the
files and the subdirectories of our project. It has the complete history of our commits,
so different snapshots of these files and directories at different times,
and it usually contains, well not usually, sometimes it contains different branches
and tags. Introducing new branches is to have a clearer line of thought, so whenever you're
experimenting with something new, you might want to create a branch so that in case you are
uncertain, if that's something you wish to have for your repository, you can simply discard it
or merge it in the main one if it's an important feature. So what about cloning?
So cloning is actually copying the entire repository with its commits and history to our
local computer. And it's yet another backup for the repository. Then you can work on your
local copy of the repository. You can do further tests and run the program if it's a program or
use your favorite editor to inspect different files. And one important thing to remember
when it comes to cloning,
is that if you do commits in your local clone,
so the local repository on your machine,
these will not appear automatically
to the repository where you cloned from.
And the other way around,
if the repository you cloned from,
which is typically called upstream,
so if that repository has new commits,
then they will not show up automatically
on your clone repository, on your local machine.
You actually have to use additional commands
in order to sync your local clone
with the repository on GitHub or GitLab,
if that is where you have it.
So it's not a full automatic syncing,
but somehow you tell it when to...
ago and i guess that will be the push and pull commands we learned exactly i think we had heard
and some some of the ids can do this automatically but i think it's important to remember that
generally this is not the case so you will have to do this pushing and pulling and we'll we'll
see how you can do that so i think maybe we should discuss a little bit why what is the difference
between forking and cloning and when do we want to do one or the other yeah well
is that a question to me if you want otherwise i i will answer so in my mind i think forking is
it's like making your own copy and cloning i know the command makes a copy on my computer
so i guess fork is like the well is everything a fork technically but when we say fork we usually
mean something on github like making the own copy of a github repository and then clone is well you
can clone your own repository your own copy of the repository or you can clone the upstream copy
that's not yours so yeah yeah so i would just add that so if i only want to let's say i i found a
repository uh on the web and i want to investigate further then i i may do a fork and uh and um
yeah maybe doing some simple commit on on github or something but if it's actually a code
that I may wish to run, then I'm going to clone that on my local machine,
install that software, run some tests, or run it with some input that I have.
So yeah, whenever I actually need to run things on my machine, when I want to do commits which
are maybe, I don't, doesn't necessarily have to be more advanced, but let's say I just prefer
to work on my local machine then then i would go for a clone instead of just forking it and
it's not wrong to do both or it's not wrong to start with one and add the other so um
that's um that's perfectly fine yeah okay so cloning gets you the actual files on your
computer that you can do stuff with which i guess is important for anything so yeah okay
Good.
Okay, so then let's introduce the exercise.
And again, I mean, we prefer you do this using either VS Code or the command line.
Still, I mean, there are things that you can do on GitHub.
So if that is the path you want to choose, that's perfectly fine.
It will not work for all the steps.
Actually, well, we'll see with some of the exercises later that some things can be done on GitHub, but now it's mostly cloning a repository which exists on GitHub and bringing it to your computer.
So, if you have not yet configured Git on the command line,
then we suggest you do that,
and in this step one,
there is a link to that.
Then in the second step,
you actually need to decide which is
the repository that you wish to clone.
If you were with us yesterday,
Then you may already have a recipe book, which is, well, a fork of the CR workshop exercises.
You may work with the fork that you have.
You may also work with the repository under CR workshop exercises.
It's really up to you.
For the purpose of this exercise, it doesn't matter what you choose.
Then we'd like you to create a new branch,
this time locally, and make a commit.
We'll simply repeat some of the steps that we have done yesterday,
but on our local repository.
Then step 7 is actually to compare your commits
locally with what exists on github and identify if these uh if the syncing has happened or not
so um that's uh that's about it [name] anything else that we should add before going into exercise
time if you can't do this exercise do you lose whatever comes later or is it okay like
do future exercises depend on this one no they don't depend so okay and if you if you cannot
so if you don't want to work or if you don't want or cannot work locally using either the command
an online or an editor, then you may just try this again on GitHub.
That's perfectly fine.
So no need to panic.
OK, yeah.
Can they come back in 45 minutes and we go to the next one, which they can do?
OK, good to know.
Yeah. And I mean, they can.
One option is also just to check the solutions that we have introduced.
That is also perfectly OK.
I think that there is still a lot of learning that can be done by just checking the solution.
And then there's a good question on line 105.
Step three, creating branches locally.
For this, do we need to be in the same directory of the recipe book?
And this goes close to, I think, what might be the biggest problem in this step.
so whenever you do the local work especially from the command line you have to know
you have to run things from the command line like the command line has to be in the same location
where your um where your files are currently stored and if you've never examined stuff from
the command line if this is still new to you don't worry like you'll probably pick it up quickly but
it will be hard to learn two things at once so in that case um don't worry ask the questions um
i do i did try to cover this in the shell crash course which i re-recorded for this workshop
that you've seen somehow as part of the setup instructions and if the command line
seems too hard I guess you could take time and watch that again
and see what you can learn there. So I'll just add
one thing so you do need to be in this directory the recipe
book because well git needs to know that
the directory you are in is actually a git repository
otherwise it will not understand that so
so the short answer is yes
yeah okay
is that all then
yes that's all
and then what should we say
20 minutes or 25
25 minutes I think we have
so in case you need to
set some things up you have
those extra minutes
yeah okay
great so see you later
good luck and definitely
write questions in the notes we are around to help okay bye
Okay, welcome back everyone.
I hope you had a good try for this exercise. So we have a feedback box in the notes document.
If you have missed it then please check that. But based on the existing feedback you would
like me to demo how to do this via the command line. So this is what I'm going to do in the
following. So the very first thing that one should do, so let's see, go back to the exercise,
is to configure git. I have done that already, so that is fixed. And actually, yes, in case you do
not have done done, then I should just show you that you find it under the first episode,
getting started and configuring git command line and editor. So that is what you need to do.
And then, if that is still unclear, add another plus to that part. And then the second step is
to decide which repository to clone. And I am going to use the fork I have done yesterday.
And how do I do that? So I need to have a URL for where this remote repository is located and then
copy that. So you may notice there is a green button here close to, well, on my GitHub repo
page and i'm going to click on this triangle and copy this link which is under ssh so just
a short comment on the difference between https and ssh if you do not want to push your local
changes to this remote repository which you are cloning it's okay to use https if you do want to
push back and you have the rights to do that, then choose SSH. And because this is my own repository,
I do have the rights to do that, so I'm going to go for this option. But again, if you're cloning
someone else's repository and you're not a member of that project, then choose the other option.
So I have copied that and I'm going to go to my terminal and the command to clone a repository
is git clone and then I have to specify the path where this, well the URL where this repository is
and actually it's not the URL but it has a certain syntax as I got instructed from GitHub.
So I have just pasted that. So this is what I copied from github and then I enter and now
I have this down on my reposter. So let's see. Okay, sorry, that was very bad. So I have
have cloned this in my home directory. I'm going to actually move this recipe book recorded into
another folder that was unnecessarily complicated.
Oh, okay. That was... Let me just do the clone again.
Oh, it's because I already loaded it here. Yes. Okay. Sorry. So then I have this clone recipe
book recorded. So it's a Git repo on my local machine, and I'm going to cd to this
directory. And what do I have? So I have all these different files that we have seen yesterday
as well. And the next step was to, let's see, is to create a new branch. And how I can switch
switch. So the command to do that is git switch. And the name of the branch. Let's see. What
should I say? Oh, sorry. New branch. And then the branch I want to create it from. And I'm
going to create it from the main branch and actually git switch is not enough because this
new branch or actually maybe it exists so let's call it
modif by super i also need to add the option create so what this is going to do is create
this ModifSoup branch from main and then switch to it. It's like a combination of two commands.
And to see that I am on the right branch I'm going to do git status and you should do git status
often so that you actually know what the state of your repository is. But now it just tells me that
okay I'm on this branch and I have a clean working tree that means that I have not modified anything.
but what I will do is to modify the mushroom recipe and I opened this file with my preferred
editor. You use your preferred editor and I'm just going to add for example this and
commit this change. So first I have to instruct git that I have modified this and I want this
modification to be incorporated in the next commit and I do that with the git add command.
So this is like adding the plus button in VS Code for example. You simply instruct git that you want
to incorporate these changes in the new commit. And then let's show git status again. So this
This will tell me, okay, you have modified this file.
It is staged, and I can now commit it.
So I can incorporate this change to the mushroom soup in the new commit.
And using the command line, it's git commit, dash M for the commit message,
if it's just one line.
So modify, edit, yeah, modified mushroom.
And then, let's just do git log and see how that looks.
So I have a new commit here, modified soup, on the branch modified soup, and then with
this commit message.
So I could also do git graph, for example, and then I have the whole history of my repository
in a graphical representation, and you can actually also see this in VS Code.
Okay, and then what else to do? So I should switch back to the main branch, so git
checkout main, or I could do git switch main. So let's do that. So either git checkout main
or git switch main so this is going to get me back to the main branch so i can check that again with
git status so it tells me that okay i'm on the main branch or i could do this using git branch
this is also going to list the branches i have the local branches i have and and add this asterisk
to the branch I am on. So merge. And then the next thing to do is to add two commits here. So I
quickly do that. So again, I'll just change some file. What do we have here? Bacamole.
so let's do just a quarter of this and then git add so again git add is going to
tell git that i want this change to be incorporated in the next commit
and i should do another commit so let's do
Okay, let's change this file again.
And now what I will have eventually is two commits that change the same file.
One would think that it would have been better to have one commit instead.
That sometimes is the case, but in this case I've done it this way, so I have smaller changes
in several commits.
What did I do?
Let's sort here.
No, let's...
So let's say I don't remember actually what I did, so let me open this file again.
I had less salt, yes.
So I am now committing that the additional change I did to this guacamole, which is not
that's less salt. So how does my
commit tree look like now so i had uh so now on main
i have these new commits uh less onion and less salt and actually you may see that i have another
origin main branch here. So what actually that means is the reference for the remote branch
that I have, which is actually behind on my local copy compared to my local main branch. So
um i can show this in a more concise form using it graph so i have these two branches on main
and then this uh sorry this still commits on main and then this modified the soup on on
this commit on the modified soup branch sorry so let's merge that those and how
how do i do that so i use the git merge command i specify the branch i want to merge
so motif soup and the branch i want to merge into and if i do not specify this secondary
month for the branch then it's going to take the branch i am on when it has the merge so
i click that and then i'm being prompted with a commit message for the merge i'm okay with that
will just save it and then these so these commit messages um are going to be opened in the editor
that you have set up um for git so uh you may have nano or emacs or or vs code and that is okay so um
um let's quickly do a gif graph again so i see that i have a new commit which is the merge
commit of of the main branch and modif soup so what about the history on the remote repository
so the one that i have cloned from so let's see do my changes show up there and the way i can do
that so i can go to insights and do for example and check the network or i could just see the
history of the commits. I can do that as well. This takes a bit of time.
So here actually I do not have
this new branch motif soup that I have on my local machine. So this has not been synced.
I can also see just by looking at the code and clicking on the commits. So the most recent
commit that I have on this branch is actually from yesterday. So the local changes I have done
are not yet incorporated on the remote repository. Final question number eight, where are the remote
branches. So how can I see all the branches? So if I just type the git branch command,
this is only going to list the local branches. So local branches that I
have defined on my local repository. In order to see the remote branches as well, I have to add
the option dash dash all so these are not only going to show the local ones but also in red the
the branches which are defined on the remote repository
okay
so there's getting to be questions to note some people have lost track of what we're doing
so i think the most important thing here is that this is a demo for the recording mainly
so we showed one of the paths um but it's not needed for what comes next so don't don't read
too much so don't let this um stop you from things you've sort of seen this command line
method and we will get more used to it later if it's the path you want to take but you definitely
can do your work with vs code or something like that that shows other stuff um
actually there is one thing yeah one thing so i did uh fail to show how you can actually track
a remote branch and so the command to do that so let's say that for example i want to track
the branch alex fruit salad so then i can do git switch
followed by i'm sorry
git switch followed by the option dash dash create the name of the local branch and then
the name of the of the remote branch so in this case origin slash alex fruit salad
and then i type that i type enter alternatively instead of using git switch create one can just
to, I'll show you that, so
git switch followed by the option track, and then just
the name of the remote branch, and then it's going to take
the same name for the local one, so that's
equivalent.
Okay then, but we definitely need a break now, right?
Yeah, so a lot of what Dana
of showed was sort of more advanced stuff that's not in the lesson so don't worry it's not needed
for the first day-to-day work and the stuff that you can pick up later over time there is one
question about what head means it's something that we've been seeing lately so the name head
comes from like the recording head of a magnetic tape or something like that and basically it's
where the changes are being made so whatever your head branches that is where new commits would go
and what will be modified when you run the git commit or git merge command
but yeah let's go to a break
we can add more into the
notes there
so with a 10 minute break we're back
at 9 minutes
past the hour
so take your break
keep the questions coming in
and let's
we'll talk then
okay
see you after the break
hello we are back um
um there we're going to go on now to the next phase of the lesson but yeah that was quite a
challenge what we just did there um seeing everything from the command line so if you
are sort of familiar with the command line then maybe you saw the general idea of what's there
but still even i if i see someone typing a bunch of stuff on the command line unless i already know
what's going on there's not much chance of following it it's always like uh okay here's a
general idea and then i need to go find the written material and understand it later so that's
basically what you can or how you should interpret the previous demonstration of the exercise so
it's what you can like it's how we would be doing it knowing things and now it will be recorded
for the video so you can review later but it's not something like if you didn't follow everything
there don't worry i mean that's that's normal it's uh um um yeah it will take time that's why
we have the different tracks for uh vs code r studio and whatever so over time slowly as you
do things um follow up and um learn more over time and with that we're going to go on to inspecting
history where i believe we so it doesn't depend on anything we did now and you start by cloning
a new repository so no matter how weird things have gotten now it's okay it doesn't affect
things later and in fact over the next few days of the workshop we do similar things to today
again from different angles and you will have more time to see it over and over again and we'll
slowly pick things up so that's just another reason not to worry so with that i'm going to
swap to [name]'s screen there we go and i will just add that if you if you are interested in
command line, you can go back to the lesson
yesterday and inspect the
tabs under the command line. Then
we'll get more insight into
these commands.
But it's okay
to do things in VS Code
or on GitHub.
But yeah, inspecting history.
So what we
actually want to do
when we
or when do we want to inspect the history
of a
repository?
Sorry, I was answering your question.
Sorry, so when do we actually want to inspect the history of a repository?
Yeah.
So maybe I'll start.
So for example, if I discover a new repository,
then the first thing I'll do is to check,
okay, what's the current state of the repository?
and then look at the history of those commits.
And we've seen some of that yesterday by, well,
clicking on the clock on the GitHub repo.
So that is helpful to get on some insight
on what has been done for that repository.
Yeah.
So for me, I guess there's two levels.
One is quickly seeing what I've done lately in order to know where I am, what I need to do next, and so on, or to see what I might have just messed up.
For a deeper history inspection, at the end of this lesson, I don't know if we'll actually do it as a demo.
You can try it as an exercise if you want, but there's a way to search all of history to figure out where a certain bug was introduced.
So if you find something that's broken and you don't know where it's broken or how to possibly fix it, using these kinds of things can point you exactly, okay, this is where the problem started, and then you can more easily solve it.
yes bug hunting that's a really good case for actually inspecting the history and this is what
one of the exercises that we'll show today so as usual I mean you can choose different paths
and some things can be done on github some can be done on vs code by far the command line is the
most powerful way to do that it's also the hardest one to understand and get used to so i think it's
not wrong to actually combine different paths for inspecting the history and and yeah choose
choose the one which is most usable for what you are trying to achieve but we'll introduce in the
following some tools that you might find useful.
And again, I mean, this depends on what you actually want
to find out about a certain project.
So let's start by looking at this repository.
So remote repository on GitHub.
And so I,
I'll just quickly open it here so this is a very large repository it has like oh I don't know I
think it has oh 7,943 commits so that's that's really a very big one so it can be actually
quite overwhelming to to look through through this whole repository and you might not even
uh want to do that but i'm going to let me open this particular link here which is going to
show a quite nice graphical way of seeing the repository so what it does it's actually looking
at one particular file the readme rst file and show the history of this file over time and this
is maybe not so easy to see on this black background, but it starts from the latest
change to this file done by a certain user and if I can use, for example, the left and right arrows
to go back in time and see snapshots of this file or changes in these files introduced by different
uh by different developers and this tool actually works not only with this repository it can
it works with any repository so you just need to change um the
the repository name with with yours so uh so uh where the so change uh let me show here is that
so change the location of the repository and the particular file that you are interested to
look in so it's one visual way to show a repository it's uh it's well not uh not
necessarily very useful when you actually try to find a bug but if you want to present a project to
to a person that may be useful. But what other tools are there to actually help us find
bugs or new features, new functions that have been introduced in a code? So one of them is
actually git grep, which is similar to the grep command that maybe some of you are familiar with,
and it's typically used with some argument. It can be plain text or it can be some expression.
So this is useful, for example, let's say you know that there is a function
somewhere in the code but you don't know where. You want to find it and then you can do some git
It can be used with some longer text, that's possible as well, it can also be used with
different arguments for this command.
This simply means that ignore the caps for the string that I'm trying to find.
Again, I mean, if you know that there are a bunch of lines,
PIXME, in the code where you or someone else
has introduced the code in order to help you remember
that there are some things you need to improve,
maybe some code documentation,
that in-code documentation that you should add,
then you can use this command to find that.
So,
Git grab, what it will do is going to search for the current state of the repository, right?
So how it will check the content of the files in their present state, which sometimes is
not what you want.
You want to go back in time and see, for example, you knew there was a function or a piece of
text that has simply disappeared from the code and you want to know who has one that has
gotten removed maybe the person that has removed that so the way you can do that
is with the git log command but by using this option minus capital s which is this so-called
pickaxe option and followed by the text that you try to find and this is again this is advanced
it's useful if you know what you are looking for in the code but yeah it's
It's not, maybe not so easy to remember.
So you can, let's say you did find a bug
in some version of the code.
You can, or you just want to inspect a certain commit
that your collaborator has done.
You want to see what are the changes introduced
with that commit.
In the command line, you can use the git show command, followed by the hash of that commit.
You can also do this, for example, on GitHub by having the link of the repository, the URL of the repository, and then followed by this text commit, and then the hash of that particular commit.
So that is going to give you some information on what has been committed.
So I'm actually going to just open this link.
So again, this shows all the changes introduced in this commit with this hash.
And one thing which is quite interesting is that I can click on this icon, browse files,
and then I can see the state
I can see all the files in this repository
at that point in time
so for S they look like
for the commit 75 and so on
so how they looked actually 5 years ago
so that's quite
a nice feature of GitHub
and then sure I can do this on the command line
But if I don't like to work on the command line, then I can view that on GitHub.
So we talked a little bit about git blame and git annotate yesterday.
And this is very nice to see.
So this is very nice to use if you want to track all the changes that have happened to a certain file.
So let's assume that I want to look at this convert matrix Python script from this NetworkX repository.
So let's just open this on GitHub.
So what we want to see, how has this file changed over time?
So then line by line, I'm going to see the person that has last modified a certain line.
There are really lots of changes to this particular file, some older, some newer.
One really nice feature of GitHub that does not have a counterpart in either VS Code or
command line is this icon here. So this is called blame prior to change. It's actually very hard to
understand what it is just from this name, but what it really means is give me the commit that
that is prior to the one that modified this line.
So we can see from here that this particular line
has been modified in the commit.
Where is the hash?
I don't see the hash,
but it has been modified February 22nd.
But maybe I find out some way
that this commit actually introduced the bug
and this bug is in this particular line.
I am not interested in this commit.
I'm interested in the commit, which was before this one,
because then I know that, okay,
that version may actually work.
So I want to start from there.
And the one way I can find that information
on GitHub is with this.
So if I click on this,
I get to the commit prior to this one.
This is rendered very funnily.
Yeah, sorry for that. So then, yeah, it's very weird. So I think it's because the window is so
narrow. So this is the hash of that commit, the prior commit that introduced that change. And
then again, I can investigate the files in this commit. In this case, well, it shows the
biometrics, but I can also
browse the
files if
I
go to
I could browse all the files
if I go to the
main one. So
am I going too slow?
Yeah, should we get to the exercise
soon? And then we'll have some
time before lunch to go over it.
So what
would we want you
to do in the exercise?
So I want you to explore some of these so-called archaeology commands on this NetworkX repository.
And this is where you find it. And let's see. And then what we would like you to try
is to find a certain line in the source code that contains this text, find out where this
line was last modified, and inspect that commit, and try to create a branch which points to that
commit and see how you can bring the code right before that commit. And this
may not be possible to do depending on the path that you are choosing but it's okay to skip.
So give it a try using your preferred path and then let's see should we do this for 20 minutes?
yes that's what it says so we'll return at uh 48 past the hour
okay good so yeah um do what you can uh and
and whatever we do after lunch doesn't depend on this so if you can't do everything that's okay
this is more of experimentation so experiment with whatever is interesting to you okay bye
Thank you.
Okay, welcome back, everyone.
Hello. Yes.
So now if we look at the notes, there weren't too many questions relative to before.
So that's hopefully a good sign.
Hopefully a sign of things were going well instead of there being many problems.
If you would like us to do something, you can write here which of the steps you would like to see demos of.
But there's not a clear question which one we should try to follow.
it did relatively good demos before anyway and i don't know if we can do better than that now um
one option is to do the advanced git bisect exercise to show um do you think we have time
to do that so i think yeah we can definitely introduce it and
And, yeah, sorry, I was just writing here.
Yeah, we can definitely introduce it.
Yeah.
So.
Or is there any general discussion we should do?
So, no, not before lunch.
I think, yeah, let's show `git bisect`.
And then if by the end of this, people, well, if we still have time and people want us to demo something,
then we can do that. I think, yeah, just some words on git parsing. So when is this actually
useful? So it's useful if you have a code that you can actually test and decide whether it's good or
bad. So you have some tests that you are running and then it tells you that
now there is a bug in this code you need to revise it or the test pass and then
you can deem that code as a working code. So this is of course not always possible if you have a
repository that may just be a collection of files so it depends i don't know
so the way to use this command git bisect is okay you go to the github repository
uh which is well the local copy of your uh github repository so your local uh local repo
and you do git bisect start so that this triggers uh this uh triggers um a certain algorithm with
with git. So
in the following
what you need to do is to find
a good and a
bad commit.
So you specify git
bisect good followed by
the hash
of this
good commit.
And you also need to specify a bad
commit. So a commit that
has some error
or
or anything so git bisect bad followed by that hash or it can be the name of the branch if it's
the latest commit on that branch once you have specified a good and a bad commit the order
doesn't matter so you have you need a good and bad commit then uh then you well automatically
Git is going to run this bisect algorithm and take you to a commit, which is between
this good and bad commit.
And then what you need to do is deem that, okay, this commit that I am on, so you can
check that with Git status, for example, which commit you are on, is that a good or a bad
commit?
do that by running some tests and and then you either say again keep bisect
good or bad and then once you do that bisect algorithm is going to run again
automatically and then you are going to a new commit and this this cycle
continues until you find the commit that broke your code so there is an optional
exercise that we are not actually going to do but you may try to if you are
interested in in the git bisect then you may try to do this on your own so this is
simply a python script that calculates pi and at some point there is an error which has been
introduced and your task is to use this command to find where this code has been broken. And there
are some hints on how you can achieve this. So again this is useful with repositories
used for co-development. And when you have a clear way of identifying whether your commit
is a working one or not. [name], anything else that we should say about Bisect?
Not really. How many times have you used Bisect before?
oh i i think i might have used it once but i don't remember what it was for so
yeah so i think it's been a very rare thing it is actually better to have tests
along with your code and we'll discuss testing during next week so that you don't even get to
push your code
before
you make sure that it is
working as expected.
But
I do use
it every once in a while, but it's
not very often.
Yeah.
Okay, so what can we expect after
lunch? I believe
that is the
preparing your own
so after lunch we are going to do the reverse of what we've been doing
in the morning so instead of cloning our repository
from github to our local machine
we'll take what we have on our local machine and put it on github
so that's what's waiting
for us after lunch and then we are also going
to discuss some best practices or guidelines
on how to use Git.
So we'll have a discussion around that.
Yeah.
Okay, great.
So let's go.
See you after lunch in about an hour.
Bye.
See you.
hello welcome back everyone i hope you had a good break so now [name] so we
watch that's uh that's good what next me too so uh
And so in the following hour, what we are going to do is to take a local directory we have on our computer, transform it into a GitHub repository, a Git repository, sorry.
And then we are going to share it online on GitHub in this case.
So we are kind of doing the reverse of what we did in the morning when we cloned something existing on the cloud and bringing it to our local computer.
So we do it backwards.
So this is basically the starting point where if someone's already doing something, they use the instructions of this lesson to make it Git and to make it where other people can see it.
Yeah, exactly. So let's imagine you've been working on your project for a while and at some point in time, you realize, oh, I should actually version control this and I should share it with my colleagues so that they can test it, run it, provide feedback, see how we get this forward.
So that's a good reason to version control it and share it with other people.
And then actually sharing it does not necessarily mean with others.
It's just having like an additional copy of your repository on a cloud platform.
So if something happens to your computer, you have a backup for you.
And once you are ready to share it with others as well, then you can add members to your GitHub project and evolve it from there.
So, but yeah, sharing it with your future self.
So you can put it on GitHub, but it's a private repository.
So it's only serving as a backup and you're not really, you're not sharing it.
Okay.
Exactly.
So you can choose, do I want this repository to be private?
Do I want it public?
So there are some restrictions,
how many private repositories you can have
and how big they can be.
But for small ones, it's really no problem.
You can have it private.
And maybe it feels safer to start that way.
And once you're comfortable,
then you can open it up to the public.
yeah okay but so how do we actually do this so uh i guess the starting point is you have
some files in a directory and yeah you know where the directory is exactly so that's uh that's
important uh so you uh you have a collection of files under one directory you may also have sub
directories in that directory but this top directory you want to that contains all the
needed files you initialize that basically as a git repository and then you may start tracking
different versions of your files you have different commits and at some point while you um you uh
push this to GitHub or GitLab or some other cloud platform that has version control.
The point of the exercise for this hour is to select a directory
that you have or create a new directory. You can call it My Project or call it something else.
create some new files in it or copy some files that are not so sensitive that you feel comfortable
later on to putting on GitHub. And that is going to be your GitHub project, right?
And so that is what the project that you are going to transform into a GitHub
project. So in order to transform it actually into a Git repository,
you have several paths to do that
you can either use the command line if you're comfortable with that
or you can use VS Code or GitHub
it's really up to you
but what we want you to do is to transform it into a Git repository
and then move this into GitHub
or GitLab if you actually prefer to do that
although we are not showing that in the solutions
so anything else that
that we should hint
when it comes to this
yeah so we want to give a lot of time for this
because it will be a while
is there anything we should
demonstrate before
yeah should I demonstrate
maybe how to actually do this on
maybe
I don't know VS Code
maybe you could do the
starts of it and then we give some time
and then you finish the rest
okay then I will start
and you should stop me
when you think I've gone
I've shown enough to get people started
so I have
a VS Code, open here.
What I need to figure out now is where is
the directory that I want to turn in a Git repository.
First, I need to make it a Git repository on my local machine.
I'm going to go to this Explorer bar and then open file.
Actually, I will do install from the top menu, which you don't see.
So I'm going to click on File, Open Folder, and I'm going to go to CRDate2.
And I have one directory there, which is called My Project.
And it's not a Git repository, so it only contains some files.
So I will select that as a directory to open.
So yeah.
Sorry, say again.
You made this in advance to get ready.
Yeah, I meant that in advance, but so what it is, is one directory, which I have on my local machine, which contains two files, and those files that it contains are called myscript.py, so it's some Python script, and there is a file which is called license, and VS Code is, yeah, whenever you have
a certain file name or extension is going to show this nice icon so that you know what programming
language it's in but in all honesty these files are empty so don't think anything fancy it's just
a demo but um but now so i have these two files under the directory called my project
and uh what i and this is not a repository yet i'm i have not version controlled these
files, but I plan to do that in the following. So then I want to transform this into a Git
repository. And the way I do that is I go to source control. So these commit lines of commits
which merge or
diverge. And then I
have the option to initialize this
repository. So initialize repository
means transform
the existing directory
into a Git repository.
Okay. So from the command line,
that's the equivalent of
Git init.
Yes.
So then what
I have, I'm going to open, close this.
It's distracting.
Then I have this window here,
which shows me that I have two files license myscript.py,
which are untracked.
That means that I initialized this Git repository,
but I am yet to do the very first commit.
These files are yet untracked.
Then what I should do is I should tell Git that,
Okay, start keeping track of these files.
So it's similar in the command line with git add
and the file name.
And then I click on these pluses,
which means that it's going to stage these changes.
So then these are staged, which shows as A,
like added to the index, in other words,
but just think of it as staged and ready,
ready to be included in the next commit.
And then I can now commit this modification.
So the inclusion of these two files
in whatever I am tracking with Git
into my very first commit.
So I'm going to give it a commit message here.
Start tracking my project.
And this is the equivalent of `git commit -m [message]`.
start tracking my project.
So instead of typing the commands, I click.
Yeah.
So, and I go to the stage
where I transform my local directory
into a repository tracked with Git locally.
So I can see, let me show one thing.
So there is actually a graph here,
which is similar to `git graph` ,
but I only have one initial commit yet.
So I am on the main branch,
which is highlighted in blue.
It shows the committer and the time of the commit
and the commit message and which files have been changed.
And also at the bottom, actually the hash,
the shortened hash of this commit.
So the next thing would be now to move this onto GitHub.
Yeah. And how do we do that?
Yeah. So should I do that as well? So if I were to do it in VS Code, actually VS Code
can do this for me by clicking here, publish branch main. And then what I need to do is
to tell VS Code, oh, but where on GitHub do you want your project to be? And it even gives me the
option to publish it to either a private or a public repository by default with the same name
as the directory name, but that can be changed. So the local directory name does not have to be
the same as the GitHub repository name, although it's easier to keep track of them if they have
the same name. So I'm going to make this a public repository. So then I click this,
publish to GitHub public repository. And the first time one does this, one actually has to
to authorize VS Code to publish on GitHub.
So it's going to,
you will be asked to authenticate to GitHub and yeah.
So that is a necessary step for the very first time
you use VS Code together with GitHub.
And then actually I want to show you those messages, but.
Is there a window open up that's asking about the authentication?
Yes.
So there will be a window opening up.
And actually, well, there will be a browser window on GitHub that will ask you to authenticate.
And if you, yeah.
So just follow the steps.
Well, read what is being prompted.
And yes, you're going to have to agree to allow VS Code to make changes on GitHub.
And if you're happy with that, then yes, you should authorize that.
So one thing I wanted to say, so when I created this repository on GitHub via VS Code,
then actually it
asked me if I
automatically wanted to fetch
things
from GitHub
and what does that mean [name]?
Can you ask it again?
I was looking at a question here
So VS Code asked
me if it should automatically
fetch
commits from
the GitHub repo
uh hmm so i guess that means it will automatically do a pool whenever you do things
on the on the remote repository yeah yeah yeah so that's really well it's for you to decide
what's best for your project if you should do these automatic pools or not so that's
And in general, it is a very good idea to keep track of the changes on the remote repository
on GitHub or GitLab with the ones on your local machine.
So that's generally good.
And actually, whenever you start working on your local version, it's good to do a pull or a fetch.
so they are almost the same
not really
but now I think it's good
if everyone gets to
try this
and you can choose
to do it in VS Code
or you
can
choose your preferred project
you can either do it in the command line
so it's really up to you
yeah
there is one
question about saying GitHub has removed password authentication. So in order to do this from
the command line, you need to use the SSH key method and not the HTTPS method. HTTPS can work
with an authentication helper or something extra, but that was sort of an extra thing in the install
instructions and i'd recommend unless you want to go dig into things use ssh for command line
otherwise stuff can happen and if you use vs code it handles it via the
https and web browser all automatically so you don't have to think about it so that's a that is
simpler in a sense
yeah
okay so we do exercise
until it says
25 minutes so
that's
40 minutes past
hour yeah
okay okay then
all right then I'll see you
in 25 minutes
yes see you in 25 minutes and
keep asking questions notes and we keep helping and yeah bye
Okay, welcome back, everyone.
Hello.
From the questions and answers, it seems you did have a try at the exercises
and most of you have been successful.
I think that it may be worth actually to show question 47.
And some of you have proved me wrong that you can do some automatic pushes
to GitHub if you install CLI, for example. So yeah, default it's not possible by design,
I'd say, so that it's kind of safer and it has an increased threshold to be able to create these
remote repositories automatically, but there are ways to do that, either on GitHub or
on other platforms yeah yeah yeah that's that was also a new one to me um question number 48 here
so there's lots of things that can go wrong if you don't do all the commands in the right order
and that's sort of unfortunate it would be better if it was more obvious and less ways
thing could go wrong but yeah like i'd say when you get these kinds of problems
try asking someone and see what you can do and yeah and sometimes yeah actually uh searching
for the error uh on google or or your favorite chatbot can give you some some insights on how
fix this yeah yeah um for deleting repositories locally i guess that's something we haven't
said yet i think so the git repository it's nothing magic it's basically a bunch of files
there's the files you see that are the code files you're editing and using but there's also a hidden
directory called dot git inside of it and that's where all the repository information is stored
so if you delete a folder then you've completely reset it you've deleted the history and you've
deleted the files there and you can clone it again and restart and try it a different way
and that's okay even like all of us whenever a project gets really weird we're just like okay so
So let's either move this out of the way or delete it and clone it again and get back to the original state.
Yeah, and actually the suggestion of, so if you have not actually changed anything in this remote repository, just redefining the origin, the so-called origin.
So the URL for the remote is better.
So we did get a suggestion.
actually we got the command here how to do that is git remote set url the name of the remote which
is by default origin but it can be called something else and then and then the
git at and so on the the github location of this
repository
so yeah
that's definitely better if there are no
changes to this remote
yeah
so
let's see I will
switch to
my screen here
I hope
yeah and while you do that
so I'll just
comment on question
50 or the
well the note in 50 is like trying vs code makes you actually drop the command line and i think
it's uh yeah it's it's true it does make life easier sometime um i also think that it's
the features that vs code is introducing are expanding when it comes to uh to uh using it
with GitHub. So for some things, I think complicated commands, it's
maybe easier to use the command line, but if you use it in a basic to intermediate way,
VS Code is already powerful enough. So there is no need to learn these commands. So yeah.
Yeah, it definitely has the most of the stuff you need to do with GitHub and Git.
Yeah, I also think it's a good balance.
So use your editor for what makes easy,
but you can always drop to the command line for extra stuff.
It's not two different Git systems, but one with two different interfaces.
Yeah, and I think one nice thing is that you also get to have a nice editor
together with your code. So that's one thing I like about VS Code as well.
Yeah. So here we have some remote repositories. So we're doing this with GitHub as the example.
a very similar thing works for gitlab so for example your university may have its own git lab
and things will be slightly different the website will look slightly different
and the paths will be slightly different but overall the same kind of idea
and there's other smaller ones you can use for example bitbucket is one i've seen
some people use you can also store git remotes on any server that you can ssh to so for example
when i was doing my thesis i didn't want to send it to any other place and not that they existed
at the time really but i could um store my work on some my work computer for example
okay um and this last bit here so by putting it on github you make it available for other people
to see it but these aren't permanent things so github exists as long as your account is active
but it can disappear at any time and when you really want to make code available for long-term
things like as part of a permanent paper you want to archive the code somewhere else and that's um
that's something we'll talk about next week with stuff like reproducible research
but now i propose if there's not much else we head to a break and see
what comes next are there any there's a few more good questions here but i think they're
answerable right here so let's let the questions keep coming in so after the break we talk about
practical things so what do we actually do do each of us actually use what we teach
we can talk among ourselves and any other instructors that happen to be around
and you can um you can hear the inside story so do prepare your questions go ahead and start
asking them and maybe you can see there is a tail on my desk so hopefully you get some
entertainment from cats when you get back okay great okay see you after the break see you after
the break bye
Welcome back.
Uh, there were a lot of good questions in the notes here. Um, but I propose that we first go through the practical advice parts. And then we, okay, you can see cats is roaming around here looking for trouble.
I hope I don't have to go get up and solve problems. Okay. Yeah. So we do the practical
advice and then we take the rest of the time doing Q&A, which can also be practical advice
questions, but we'll go over a lot of these questions here. So for practical advice,
are there any other instructors in the uh in the studio who would like to join us
so we're going here to this oh hello [name] hello
so [name] will be instructing next week with us i believe
um okay i'm losing uh my mouse cursor wasn't isn't working properly uh this is not good
let me fix something okay yeah so practically speaking
what should we and should we not do it's this part right here
so yeah the main question is of all the things we've talked about so far today
what do you actually use and not use
so should i go first since i asked the question you go first yeah so if you ask me um
so definitely i use git for almost every project i do if i'm making code editing files
i may as well have a record of what the previous date was and if i don't say more than half the
time i'm going to end up regretting it someday and it's really easy to make a git repository
either from the command line or editor and when a project is new i basically commit everything
like if by two days from now all the code would change anyway all that really matters is i have
something i don't care about every commit being perfectly atomic with a great message and so on
but as projects get older and it becomes more mature and like other people might be using it
then i make sure that every commit has a good message because other people might
pool and see what the new stuff is um i make sure that each commit does only one thing so if i break
something i can undo just that part and so on and it sort of usually comes naturally most of my stuff
somehow goes on to github or but not everything private stuff i don't not even in public
repositories what about you all uh [name] you're next in the list yeah i i might say yeah i i
tend to use git a lot even just for sharing data so it's possibly an improper use of git
but just to share data between different hosts um yeah i mean yeah and yeah um but uh but yeah
maybe there are some things we saw today that i don't use a lot uh like for example git bisect
but i mentioned i used it but uh a few times in my life it was actually a possible a bit of a
lifesaver um but yeah um yeah and uh i think uh a lot of uh we discussed a lot of things that
that I use rarely because I try to make my,
I try to make sure that the last commit I make,
like the current state of the repository
is the most important one by using testing,
for example, automated testing.
But yeah, but when I made a mistake,
then it's really nice to have a look at all the,
you know git annotate git blame or all the logs or what what the log can give you i think that
um i i learn uh every now and then something new that i think oh that's actually interesting so
it's i think it's a long journey to actually be able to use git efficiently and uh in a way
actually suits you yeah uh [name] what do you usually do so i use it for some very few private
projects but uh but usually in collaboration with uh with others uh and um i prefer to use the
command line but uh but for some of the projects i just find it easier to work on the web so if i
know that it's going to be
one commit, one file
then I just add it
on the fly on GitHub and
not bother about cloning it
on my local machine so
it's convenient
sometimes
and then when I do work on the
command line then it's
git status all the time
my most favorite command
my most used command
and
yeah I find I mean
the command line has
increased flexibility in what you are
actually trying to do
it's also
faster for me sometimes than just
clicking sometimes I get lost
in all this clicking
but it's really just a matter
of preference
and I do use GitHub as well
a lot so and sometimes GitLab
it really depends on
the collaborators
well we have some more
sensitive projects for which we want gitlab so uh yeah so that's uh that's great as well
yeah if we look at this page here let's see what it recommends so if you're working on
the command line use the git status command all the time so not using git status is like going
for a long walk and not using your eyes to see where you are so eventually you might make a wrong
turn and if you aren't aware that something is like you've turned off the wrong way it can go
really bad before you correct yourself but if you do see that something doesn't quite look right
it's usually pretty easy to take a step back and say okay yeah here's the command i missed this or
that whatever but you know even from vs code or other editors it's good to know what current
branch you have out and what's modified and not and so on so use the different status information
it has for commit messages um yeah so my best oh yeah go ahead sorry i wanted to say one thing
about using Git status.
So if you're using an editor like VS Code,
they can have their own status.
So it's better actually to compare the things
you see in your editor with the issue
if you plan to use it both at the same time
from the command line and the editor.
Sometimes there are some weird things happening
because the status is not the same in the command line
and in the editor.
So yeah.
OK.
Be aware of that.
Good to know.
Yeah.
here you see some advice for commit messages so um the convention is that there's one really
short line first like less than around 80 characters a terminal width that is used for
summaries and then any longer details here so it's well as i think we've said before
my philosophy is don't let perfection get in the way of getting stuff done there have been times
that i haven't committed stuff because i haven't wanted to make a good commit message and it just
keeps piling up more and more and it never gets done so there's times when i'll come back to a
project i haven't worked on in a while and i see there's stuff in there that's not committed
instead of saying let's see what happens i just make a new commit immediately that says
uncommitted changes that i found around and well then not perfect but at least whatever i start to
do in the future it can keep it organized um but the more stuff that's going on the bigger the
project and the more people that might be reading it including yourself in the future you can get
more and more advanced here like you can cross-reference relative relevant issues you can
explain what went wrong um and also practice makes perfect so just start small and then
you'll get better at writing commit messages so yeah and if you don't then that's also okay
yeah and i also would add uh there are also ways to amend your commits messages if you make mistakes
or to, you can do some weird, obscure stuff
with your commits if you really need to.
So one thing I wanted to add is that
about the content of the commit message,
for me, it's really important to mention the context
where I've done something.
For example, if I'm fixing a function,
I wouldn't just write the function that I fixed,
that I fixed, but also for example,
if it's a testing function,
if it's not so deep to make sure that
when I look at the commit log,
I'm able to figure out if a commit is relevant
for what I'm doing or not.
Yeah.
I guess one way to look at it is
pretend you're telling someone to do the commit
you just did.
So it'd be like fix bug of displaying the output
or add feature of such and such.
And then, yeah, this imperative case.
Let's see what comes next.
What level of branching complexity is necessary?
So branches is something we've gone over a little bit here, but not in great depth yet.
But simple projects might have only a main branch, and you put everything there.
If you mess something up, well, it's only you and you can go back and fix it.
And it's less work to fix stuff if it goes wrong than to keep stuff from going wrong in the first place.
If there's ideas that you think won't be finished or you need to be kept separate because it might break things before you can fix it, you can start using branches there.
or things where you want to make lots of small commits while you're developing but in the end
you might just say no i don't want this and then you go back to main and ignore everything you
branched tags are good for important milestones i think there was a notes question earlier about
when to use tags and that's something like um oh what's it called like okay this is the version i
submitted or this is the version yeah really single version for the paper that kind of stuff
yeah um and the more people that get added the more that you would use branches and things like
that so tomorrow we see the highest level where you use branches for everything and then there's
always someone or there's a chance for someone else to look and see a change before you start
before it gets accepted.
Have we talked about staging much yet?
I don't think we do.
Very briefly.
I just mentioned it very briefly
when I worked on the command line.
But yeah, tell us some more.
Yeah.
So staging is a way.
So I guess maybe you remember the git add command
where we say git add
and it prepares something to commit.
And when we type git commit,
it commits everything that was added.
So this is good when you make multiple changes at once,
you can decide what you need
or you can, yeah,
or you just want to verify things
or have a small checkpoint before the commit.
Yeah, and I would just add it's like,
oh, sorry, it's just,
It's the same as clicking on the plus button next to a file in VS Code.
So that is staging as well.
Yeah.
And it's useful.
I often add things first and look at it and then commit it.
But also there's plenty of times I just commit everything
or use the git commit command in a mode that adds it and commits it at the same time.
because stuff's so small
and there's not really any doubt in my mind
what's going wrong on.
And if I do make a mistake,
well, I don't really care
because no one cares about the project that much.
How large should commits be?
Or is anything else about staging you all have?
No, I think it's good.
So how large should commits be?
I think
in the beginning
it's better to commit
more often
and then as you get
more used to Git and more confident
about
how much to introduce in one commit
then they can be larger
but anyway it's good to have
no more than
one
feature or important
modification per commit so then
And as [name] said, if something went wrong in that commit, you have the possibility to revert those changes.
In other words, one could say you should have only one thing that can fail in a commit, let's say, so that you can tell which thing was.
yeah but without a doubt there's times when or what if i'd say for me as small as possible
but sometimes it's not possible just because i don't have time or energy and then i do a lot and
hope it's okay so yeah and it depends on who's gonna be looking at stuff if it's just for you
then you probably won't care
if I'm contributing to a project like NumPy
they probably do care
and need it to look
exactly correct
is that all?
so the next part if we go to it
is related, I'll click back
and it is what to avoid
so let's see what's here
so this says
commit message that that explained what's been changed but not why it's changed
so if it's not obvious like the code will show what has changed perhaps it's more important
to explain why something has changed again it matters more when projects gets larger
I think that being too pedantic just makes people not record everything yeah and also
what is obvious to you may not be obvious to others so I think it is good to make an effort
of explaining why why you introduce that yeah and maybe it's obvious to you now well maybe
three years from now it's i mean that's obvious why that change got implemented so
yeah i think much more important is this next one committing generated files let's say you're
working on your thesis and you have the latex source there and then you make a pdf out of the
thesis do you want to add your pdf to the git repository so there the answer is much more
strongly probably not because when you add it there every time you recompile it can show this
has changed and would update it and it can be made directly from the source already so there's really
no need to add that there it's better to have only the things you actually edit committed and
anything automatically generated gets excluded and you can do that with these git ignore files
so on the other hand i might save a checkpoint of the thesis if it's something that i expect
people to want to look at from the github web interface or something but that's not
that's a separate copy from the one that's automatically generated
i would add to this record it once any change git will want you to update it okay so i would
I add to this that, okay, so you don't want to store generated files and track them in Git.
But what you could do and you should do is to maybe write a recipe on how to get those generated files.
For example, if the process is a bit lengthy and complicated, then you can have a script that helps you produce those or at least some documentation that tells you how to get those.
So you don't actually need to store them there,
because there's a recipe to get them.
Yeah.
And that's something that we'll talk a bit more
about next day for in reproducible research,
how to automatically generate these things.
For huge files, it's usually not good to commit them,
because it tracks the whole thing and that inflates the size of your repository and even
removing them later doesn't um reduce the size of the history so yeah better not to do that
and this gets what we said about being too pedantic about things so if you think it's not
good it's ugly someone's going to judge me for this you'll usually stop committing and then
well you end up losing things later um committing unrelated changes together again if it's a small
project i think who cares the larger projects get they usually want one change per one commit
there's these some problems with branching workflows where things can well you can try
to make things too fancy too advanced or whatever and well either not checking what branch you're
on like with the git status or trying to make branches that are so big that it eventually
can never get merged back any other common things to avoid
yeah don't wait don't wait too long before uh merging yeah i'd say most important is don't um
don't try to be too perfect and let the perfect become the enemy of the good because i know
far more people that regret not having recorded their history than have regretted recording
bad-looking history. In fact, I've never heard anyone that said,
I wish I had spent more time making my commits look nicer. So, yeah.
Okay, back to the notes, I say. So, there's some new questions that are appearing here
that are pretty good. So as some quick reminders, we have feedback at the bottom. Please let us know
what you thought. Yeah. And if we scroll up, let's see, which of these questions should we talk
about if anyone sees one please let me know number 55 for origin that's the conventional name of
the it's an alias for the remote so basically origin means get at github.com slash your user
slash your project name that kind of thing yeah and that's the default you can name it something
Yeah. The names don't have to match on GitHub and your own computer, but it's probably nice if they do, because that reduces confusion later.
um vs code i think this is answered down there ssh keys shouldn't we talk about ssh maybe let's
come back to that if we have time i don't want to risk going over time and i think this is probably
answered well here
here's a question about WSL users. So WSL is windows services for linux it's basically a
way to run linux on top of windows so you have access to all the good linux tools but
on windows and this question is basically about how data is stored between them so you can put
some data in a place where it's visible to the linux side but not the windows side
on perhaps vice versa so it's always important to know where things are stored and think a little
bit before you make any project where is it stored and is it accessible in the ways i need it to be
accessible um python files versus the jupyter notebook we can come back to but also we have
a jupyter lesson next week um for codium versus vs code i don't use enough to really comment i
know for me i use codium and it seems fine not all extensions are there but it's okay
`git add -p` and `git commit -p` is a good one
If you use git add or commit with the `-p` option, `-p` means patch or
something like that and it means that when you run git commit it will show you
every individual change you've made and you can push Y for yes or N for no and do them separately
and add them to the commit separately. And in fact, it's probably the most common way
I use to commit things because it shows me everything before I add it and I can select
only the stuff that goes together. It works well for small situations, but if I think it's going
it complex, I'll use git add separately. Although it may be, for example, convenient if you have
different changes in one file and then you don't want to actually git add the file,
then you'll have to have this option. But it is advanced. Sometimes it's better to just undo
some of the modifications and and commit one by one yeah let's say this is a good question here so
it's about the not tracking generated files and the sharing with collaborators so let's say you're
working with someone on a manuscript that's written in LaTeX so if they want me to add the
results to the repository we'd have to be sharing the tech source file and not the pdfs if someone
sends me a pdf i can't really commit that because it doesn't do much i have to basically convert
it back to the source so i think that's not completely inconsistent and if it's word docs
and word docs is the actual source that we're using to modify things then yeah there have been
times that i've added that to get history because there's no other option permanently removing
things from history yes this can be done but it changes history and will um everyone else will
have to update their repository for this new history so it's a common thing to do people
accidentally commit things all the time but the recovery is definitely an advanced process so
So it's better to try to avoid this.
Just because you remove it from GitHub doesn't mean it gets removed from everyone else's repository.
Yeah, and what do you know?
It's right on time.
Let's scroll down and let's talk a little bit about this.
Where was it?
The reminder thing, which I'm moving to the bottom.
So tomorrow we continue with, oh, we have a visitor.
Okay, tomorrow we continue with Git Collaborative.
And in Git Collaborative, we are all contributing to the same repositories.
and we are allowing like so since we're contributing to some central repositories
you need to request permissions before it begins and that's done via this
this box here you'll also get an email about it but please do this in advanced in advance
So that way we don't have to rush to give everyone access during the course tomorrow.
Been used for day one or day, maybe someone else can write stuff here because my hands are full.
But it is the, so tomorrow is more practice for everything we've done now.
So if things are a bit confusing, don't worry.
Come back tomorrow and you'll see it again and we can do it more slowly.
And by seeing it in real life being used for something, it will start to become more clear.
So it has both command line VS Code and GitHub Web Interface tracks.
So you can still follow each of the different tracks depending on your needs and your interests.
So if the command line part is too hard, don't worry.
You have the other options.
Yeah, anything else? I'm forgetting.
Let me look in the chat here.
Yeah, I guess.
Can anyone else think of anything before we say goodbye?
Okay, [name], I think you said something, but you're muted.
No, no, I think we covered a lot of things.
Okay, all right.
So, yeah, let's go then.
See you tomorrow.
Bye, everyone.
Okay, bye.
Bye.