Let us maybe start
with concepts and here i will connect a bit to previous days and try to just do a little recap
clarification of some of the terms that came up in day one and day two which we will use now in
for collaboration and in the notes which i have open here on top you can still it's still
completely okay and really welcome if you ask also questions from previous days
So if you need a clarification about anything that came up in the previous two workshop days.
Here we try to distill, we have maybe six concepts that I wanted to recap.
So we will talk about the repository.
What is a repository?
repository is is the project that contains all the commits all the data all the history of the
project all commits all branches and all tags and i will clarify these now in the next second
so what what was a commit again commit was this snapshot of a project so as we code along
we create these snapshots and we give them unique identifiers so each of them can be uniquely
identified and compared and referred to and then we have also seen branches branches are
independent development lines and often the in projects you often have a main branch or
a master branch which is the like the default branch but then you can have many more branches
if you prefer so and technically in git technically a branch is implemented we can
think of it as like a sticky note a sticky note with a name on it and that's the branch name
and the sticky note then refers to a specific commit
and as we create new commits on the branch the sticky note moves with these with with these new
commits and maybe we have seen tags and tags are also sticky notes but they don't move
and they can mark a particular commit that i want to then be able to find easily
so here a typical tag could be called this is the phd that went to the printer or this was
the submitted paper so that later if i want to go back to how did the code look back then
I can find that particular tag
cloning and forking
these concepts we may have seen before
depending on whether you worked on
I think cloning
we have tried it yesterday
but depending on whether you worked on VS Code
or command line or browser
so cloning is
well maybe the last two terms
The easiest thing will be if I show them with a picture.
So cloning and forking are two concepts that we will need today.
And both cloning and forking create a copy of the entire repository.
So here is a repository with commits inside.
The commits are these little rectangles and branches.
These are the sticky nodes.
One is called main, one is called idea.
here is probably a tag version 1.0 here is another branch
so this whole repository i can copy if i clone the repository i copy it typically to my computer
this could be my laptop if i fork the repository i also create a full copy with all the all the
commits all the branches but the copy stays on in the cloud service so if we are here on github
the copy stays in GitHub.
And if I create a fork from a Code Refinery repository,
now suddenly it's a repository under my username,
under my user space.
So important to see the difference between forking and cloning.
Yeah, just one thing.
Forking is always on GitHub or GitLab, not on your local.
Yeah, it stays on the same service,
but you make the copy into your user name user space but on github
and we will practice both and we will collaborate using both mechanisms
and maybe the next question can be um
well okay i have a question in mind but it i will i will ask it in a moment but before that
But one important thing is that when we create these copies, so when we clone or fork, these repositories are related.
There is a relation between them, but they don't automatically synchronize themselves.
So if I clone and have the repository on my laptop, and in the meantime, somebody else is doing changes here, the changes don't automatically come to my computer.
we will have to actively synchronize and we will learn how to do that
and the synchronization steps are pulling and pushing so i can pull changes i can pull commits
from a remote repository or i can continue working working working but my changes they
don't automatically go back to github i will have to actively push these changes so pulling
and pushing is something we will practice
for those of you who work in VS Code or command line.
So we need a mechanism to synchronize changes.
And the next question that often comes up is,
okay, I understand now that there are two different mechanisms.
We can clone or fork.
So what should we do?
Should we clone or should we fork?
And it depends a bit.
so the first thing we will practice is
we will practice working within the same repository
so if all of you, if your research group
if all of you can have write permissions
if all of you are collaborators in the same repositories
you can all work in the same repository
there is no need to
to create a fork
so for small groups
no need to fork
we will all work within the same repository
this is the first thing
that we will practice today
but there can also be situations
where you want to make changes
to a code
or suggest changes to a code
where you
which is somebody else's project
some other university
maybe you are not part of that research group
you don't have right permissions
and then
forking can be a really nice mechanism
as we will see i'm just looking here at the questions it would be nice to explain origin
and dev streams again probably rather oh yeah and i think i just mentioned here in flying somewhere
where do we talk about origin because it will come again origin i will just search the page
we don't um oh here's origin yes on in this image so after if i see a repository on on github and i
want to have that on my computer i can clone and then you will see a term appearing which is called
origin and origin is so git will remember where it was cloned from there is a relation between the
to and origin then refers to it refers to the place where i have cloned from
so then we will if i want to publish my changes if i want to push my changes
i will push them to origin and if i want to if there have been new changes on github that i want
to have on my laptop i can then pull new commits from origin so origin will refer to where did i
cloned from and a little bit later in the exercise you can then find out like how do you if you clone
a repository and you forgot where you cloned from how can you find out where you cloned from
what is origin and you can even change it and you can even give it a different name
because origin is again it's just a placeholder it's just a shortcut it makes it easier for
humans to refer to a web address instead of using the full web
address. Just looking here at questions, and I really
appreciate that they're coming in.
Yeah, also good to mention that you mentioned Git pull and after
cloning if there is some changes on the origin repository. So
So that's commits that we pull towards our local commits, local repository on the laptop using pull.
Yes.
So again, as I said, they are related, but in principle, independent repositories, they can evolve independently.
And then to synchronize changes, we need pull.
Basically, imagine downloading changes and merging into local branches.
And then to do the opposite, that would be push.
if I have a local branch
that I want to make visible on GitHub
I will push it
and all of this will be even more clear
when we then practice this
we will go into an exercise very very soon
we will explain how to set up that exercise
the exercise will be collaborative
which is a really exciting and interesting challenge for us
because we will try to collaborate with you here via stream.
We will try to collaborate on a project together.
And this will be really exciting
because we are not really exactly sure what will happen.
Yeah.
And we say that we collaborate
where you also have direct access to the repository.
Yep.
But we will go through that step by step.
And just a quick mention, during the exercises, you will hear those of you who work in teams or in classrooms, you will see the term template, generating from template.
And generating from template, it's here in the picture, I just want to show what that is.
So that's another mechanism to create new repositories from another repository.
but generating from a template
flattens
the history into one commit
imagine a cookie cutter
so you have a cookie cutter and you
create identically
looking cookies
for baking and it's a bit the same
idea so this can be
interesting in your research group if you want
all your projects to have a certain
structure to start with
then look at templates
this is just for the
when we create the
exercise repositories you might
see this term appearing
I would like to now go to the next episode
and
prepare the exercise but we will
prepare it together
and it will be
here we will collaborate
we will all try to collaborate within the same
repository
so what is uh um what is the prerequisite for the uh the learners to collaborate
we already you might have a give uh get an email from us regarding this did
rather than you want to say again what they should do to collaborate to the to us on stream
so this is for so one prerequisite is github account
then if you are part of our exercise team or the classroom
you you will do something different and i will explain what that is
but for those of you who don't who are not part of a team we have many learners who
participate on their own but they still want to collaborate
so on top of the
I mean you got the info via email
but also on top of this document
this is what you need to do
so if you haven't done that yet
because this is a way to tell us
what is your GitHub account
so that we can add you
we will add you to a team
and in a moment we will also give
write permissions for the team
to our exercise repository
and then we will collaborate
and don't worry after the workshop we will then delete everything but we will today collaborate
on a public repository so the prerequisite for those of you who participate on their own is to
do this or have done this and then i have colleagues who then help me adding you to this team
oh just a sec getting a coffee here thank you
and did I even
mention that I'm here I have a
T-shirt and I'm
I will teach using a git mark just for
just for the
branding yeah that's good
but I couldn't see your
T-shirt run
oh good
exercise setup so we need to
we need to do that carefully we will do that
yeah
we will hear whole request
quite a lot today
and what is that
we'll clarify
but I think we want
you will hear pull request
25 times today at least
when you hear pull request
please think of
change proposal
if you use services like Google Doc
it's really similar to like suggesting changes
it's a really similar idea
so we'll do that a lot today
without without suggesting and without suggesting what will happen and what do you think
will happen i would like to know if someone is doing without suggesting changes updating on the
main or master brand branch and i think maybe most people do that this way um if you are so if you
are alone in a repository um you probably don't use any of this you just make changes and that's
good so you make commits commit commit commit commit and maybe you create branches but once we
are more people and or maybe even when if we are more than one person maybe we want to review each
other's changes before they go to main before they go to master and later we will talk about
like what is the motivation for this but we will have a mechanism to review changes because the
alternative would be we just make changes. But then we don't
necessarily know, we might. One person might not exactly know
what the other person has been doing. We might introduce
mistakes, because I might change something, but I might not have
thought about some side effects that [name] knows about. So
better, I asked [name] for to review my changes.
should we explain the exercise and should we try to set things up here yes um so if you
if you are part of a team or an exercise room or a classroom we have instructions for you
so one of you uh the maintainer the the team lead if you don't have one maybe
don't worry this will not be difficult then assign some of your team to be the maintainer
and this is the person who will create your exercise from this template so this template
is not our exercise this is this is the template where we create it from so this is for the teams
and the teams
and the classrooms
they can already
start doing this
preparing it
so and
the other
people who
will be
contributing
to this
team project
they have to
send their
username to
us to this
main
dainer who
will approve
you as a
collaborator in
the project
repository
yeah so
if you if
you are in a
group a good
group size is
four or five people, one of you will do this and you exchange usernames and add them as
a collaborator.
We have here good descriptions on how to do that.
You can also watch what we now do for everybody else because it's very similar steps.
So you can also watch what we do here.
And later you will have enough time in the exercise to do these steps.
So now let's get things set up now for everybody else,
for the stream participants who are not part of a team.
Yeah, but before that, I would like to remind that
when the maintainer of your team gives you access,
you need to accept the invitation.
So you will get an email and you need to accept it.
And also watching and unwatching,
do you want to show that on the screen share as well?
yeah i wanted to show it yeah so that so if you get if you get invited to our
exercise repository either by us or by your team maintainer there are two things you need to do
one is that you will get an email from github saying that you have been invited to this exercise
do you accept the invitation so then you need to click and say yes and then the second thing
and here i will go to our exercise so this is the one that we will use for the all the stream
participants and we have actually different versions we have one that's called recorded
and i will only screen share and only show the one recorded so
this is to give everybody the choice that they don't appear anywhere where they don't want to
appear but what [name] mentioned about unwatching is so once you accept and this is our exercise
repository there is this unwatch button and what this means by default it might be set to all
activity and then you get emails about when people send pull requests what was it again pull request
was a change proposal if they open issues you will explain what that means you will get emails
and we don't want you to get too many emails so you can switch to participating and mentions
and then you only get notified so up here i only get notified if if it's something i started
an issue i have opened or a pull request that i have opened or if somebody mentions me
if somebody writes
at past my username,
can you please look at this pull request?
Then I will also get an email.
Or you can just ignore everything.
So this is something that is good too,
especially for the stream participants
because I think we have 40 people
who want to collaborate.
So we don't want you to get
120 emails now this morning.
So I'm watching.
and one one thing i'm getting from the notes that if you don't know you are a part of team that
means you are an individual learner on stream so you can call you can select this part where
following on your own and select which recorder or non not recorded a version yeah
and then i wanted to screenshot one more thing that you can then try in the teams is that
i will we have a couple of branches but i will make the main branch i will write protected
and this will make sure that all the changes will come through pull requests through change
proposals i will make it hard to make changes directly on main and we will explain what is
what can be the motivation for this but i want to show you how you can do that so on settings
branches i will i want to set up branch protection rules but i was because i also
want everybody to know that this is something that exists this is something you can use for
project. This is not to make things more bureaucratic, but to prevent yourself from
making accidental mistakes. I will go to the classic ones because I know them a little bit
better. Classic branch protection rule. And then I can protect branches like the main branch here,
main. And what I will do is I will require a pull request before merging.
but i will not require approvals or then in in a real life you can for instance require that
two people should approve before something is merged here we don't want to be too
we don't want it to make it too difficult i will just go for this one setting
this setting make sure that i cannot make changes to main directly it
i will have to do it through pull requests and of course we need to first see what it is
save, create
so now my main branch is
protected
I will in a moment do the same thing
maybe I will do it on a different screen
I will do the same thing for the unrecorded one
the same branch protection
I do that now on a different screen, just to not screen share it.
Again, branches, bad protection rules, I protect main, and I require pull requests.
And then for our exercise, I need to do one more step.
And that is, we edit you all to a team.
And I will now give all the team right permissions.
I wanted to show you how you can add collaborators to a project, to a repository.
Collaborators and teams.
And here I can either add people.
This is relevant for those of you who exercise within a small team.
So then you add five different people by their username.
Here I will not use this because I don't want to add 40 people by their username.
I will add an entire team.
And it's this one.
And I can select what kind of permissions would I like you to have.
I want you all, because now we know each other, we trust each other,
I will all give you right permissions.
There are more permissions like maintain or admin.
These can be possibly destructive.
These can be permissions to be able to add people to teams
and manage teams but write permissions is what we will need for collaborating so now
now we can all arrive to the to the repository and this will be part of the exercise
uh i do the same thing on the unrecorded one
and maybe we should explain what will be the what will be the point of the exercise what what do we
expect from from people yes and again repeating that this is an exercise we we all have right
access as i mentioned and give right access to all the members of the project so we are
collaborating we all have right access the same repository and the ones who are working with
teams you will have a repository created from the template mentioned there that so you are
working on this repository you created from the template but in the individual learner
on stream that we you collaborated with us as instructors and those who are helping us
behind the scenes are part of this repository and you are collaborating with us that's the
the main important thing and you're going to do this and we would we will go for a exercise soon
but what we want to do from this uh there are some exercise tasks you want to talk a little
bit about issue or rather one or you want to take it as later maybe i can show it so there will be
so we will not go through all the steps but the first step will be opening an issue
and what what we mean by that is that in your exercise repository which is now
on my upper half of my screen there is this thing called issue and somebody already opened one great
so here are the issues you will open a new issue somebody here already working on a
loose recipe. Fantastic. And you will open a new issue and you
will describe here what you plan to do. Oh, what do I plan to do?
I will work on Oh, I will work on making the guacamole more
spicy. I really like spicy food. So here I have a mechanism so I
So I will create it and I will assign the issue to myself.
So I have a mechanism here to inform other people, not only about problems.
So I can inform them about there is an issue in the code, but here I can also inform everybody
on what I plan to do.
And then each issue gets a number.
So you take a note of this number two, because later in the exercise, you will refer to that
number. So when we when we talk about open an issue, that's what
we meant. And there are a couple of more steps. Should I talk
people through it? Or let people explore junior exercise? Do you
think?
Yeah, I think we may be people can explore on these
things. And then we can show after the exercise and merge the
request what do you think yeah but just a thing about uh issue and this is also not only reporting
problems or uh letting others know about uh what you are working on but also having a good
discussion issue is a good place to have this good discussion and develop further work together
with others if you go to your issue created rather when i have uh commented something on
issue that issue that you created so this is a place to you to discuss about these things
i can also collect feedback yeah so we can share an idea collect feedback figure out whether it's
a good idea but it's a good approach and uh before writing 5000 lines of code and here it's it's a
simple recipe it's a recipe book we already recognize it from the previous days the nice
thing is that now we will create this recipe book together so at the end of today we will have a
book of recipes cooking recipes that we created collaboratively here
but we have this mechanism to also collect feedback before doing all that work
all the steps will be written here so we try to summarize like what is familiar from previous
days but no problem if you don't remember or you went out there we link to where to find this
we also try to summarize what are the new things and if below we have solutions and hints
and it can be good to go through those so this is not cheating this is
this is the goal so go through solution and hints and go through it step by step
maybe one more big picture thing is that we're talking about cloning so you can do all of this
the browser and then you don't need to clone so this exercise can be done purely in the browser
but those of you who then prefer to use command line or vs code there will be there will be a
step where you clone and then if you don't remember how was that again you can then link back and
have a look shall we go for a exercise break then and people can do it and go for a break
so first thing is exercise right and then i'll break after and here we we thought about 25 minutes
which would which would mean that we will the exercise would go until
almost five minutes uh after the hour we will then we will then all return here
to the stream and on the stream we will just remind everybody to please take break so after
the exercise we will then go into a break yeah correct and then yes but don't worry if you if
people get lost we will then here also demonstrate some of the like highlights um so also [name] and
me will be busy collaborating here yeah and also uh please feel free to ask questions uh on the
notes super let's start collaborating let's create some fun recipes but let's be kind to each other
nice this is a public repository so remember the code of conduct looking forward see you in
let's go to exercises and then we will be back here on stream five minutes after the hour yes
let the exercise begin i will try to switch here
in the panel to the right thing hopefully now
Thank you.
And we are back from the exercise.
This is just to remind everybody to also take a break.
So we will now go into a 10-minute break.
I recommend really break away from the screen.
And in 10 minutes, we will then restart the other stream.
And [name] and me will then go through this exercise.
We will highlight some interesting parts of it.
We will highlight some of your questions.
And then there will be another exercise soon.
But first, 10 minutes break.
See you then in 10 minutes for more collaboration on Git.
See you.
Thank you.
We are back from the break, back on stream.
Welcome.
Yeah, welcome back.
I hope everyone had a good break.
Yeah.
Let us continue and go through the task, exercise task.
So, [name], you're sharing the screen.
We had some tasks, and thank you for the questions,
and we would like we will answer most of them on the live while we demonstrate all the steps here
so what question was i think somebody also asked that once they
push a branch or have a branch with new commits if they reload the repository some some people
saw something like this. And these are three of my branches that I created. I created one,
which is called Guacamole Improvement. Another one is Vegan Pumpkin Pie, and there is an unfinished
one. Okay. Yeah. On your repository, on your screen, you will see what you pushed, not what
your other one sees. So the changes you push towards the main repository, that way you will
see and you will be able to compare and make a pull request from the github web service yeah
because i'm logged in and here github knows that it's me and sees that i made three branches
recently so it suggests that well maybe i want to do a pull request and that's exactly what i want
to do um should we look at this one first or which one should we yeah let's just uh look at it but
just want to comment when when you create changes and push it that doesn't create a pull request
pull request is only on the github or gitlab whatever the service is so you create a branch
and you push change to the github repository then from here you start the pull request correct
so so far i only have three branches actually didn't i didn't open up the pull request yet
i can do it this way there are other ways in the material but i can click on here
and i created one commit i can maybe show you now what what i what are the things that i look
at before i create it before i click on the green button i normally verify from which branch to
branch is going so that that looks good from i want it to go towards main i normally verify that
i have a somehow descriptive title maybe more context here if needed i also normally scroll
down and see what are the commits here is my commit and what are the changes in my case i
I replaced Chile by a habanero, but without seeds.
And there was also this magic keyword here.
If I use close, closes, fix, fixes,
and if I refer to my issue, the issue number two,
then later, once it's merged, it will automatically close the issue.
We can later discuss what is the advantage of it.
Yeah, just a comment about referring issues on the commits
that you already done.
But the issue will close only when your changes are merged
to the main branch.
Even you mentioned it in the commits,
that issue on the GitHub repository will be staying
until it is merged via pull request.
So if you forget to refer the issue on commit message,
you can do it on the pull request.
So it's the same effect.
Yeah, because sometimes I forget
or I could have lots of commits
and none of them solves it individually,
but all of them solve it as a combined sum.
So if I forget, I can do it here.
If I forget it here,
can there is another way to do this uh under development i think i can i can do that once
it's open should i create the pull request like open it up yeah could you uh could you show that
this that um drop down and just before you create there is a drop down tab yes
there's the draft i think we have an example for a draft one i can show another one where it's
but here I can choose
so I will create
the pull request but in a second one
I will create the draft
and once you
open it up
you can also link it here
on development, you can link the pull request to
an issue
and even if you completely forget
it, it's not a big deal, we can also show
later what I do if I forgot
to do any of these
now
this is still not merged
it's still not on main
it's just an open pull request
and here
normally I shouldn't review my own one
so here normally
normally this would be
somebody else and in our
exercise repository feel
free to review somebody else's
pull request
and so i will now not not click merge but maybe somebody else can because i really like that
if somebody else reviews if use my changes not me myself and also if someone was discussing
these issues uh the issue uh on this um issue or the issue that refer you can suggest a reviewer
there that if you know that you were discussing with your colleague and you would like your
colleague to look into this yeah so if i know somebody who would be really good to review this
i can ask here and here somebody merged thanks a lot um you can also ask for somebody to review
here on the comment and mention with an at mention and is it safe now to delete the branch yes
because it has been merged if i delete the branch i don't delete commits i only delete the sticky
out, this is totally safe to do. We promised that we would look at this other one as a draft.
So I had some vegan pumpkin pie, but it's not complete. The first step is to remove the eggs,
but I need to replace it probably by something. So what you want to sometimes do is open as a
draft pull request and a draft pull request cannot be merged so nobody can click here
this is not an active button you cannot merge it it's not meant to be merged it's a draft
but it's a nice way for me to inform all of you that um this is something i'm working on could be
just for your information it could also be a way to collect feedback maybe i don't know how to
complete it or maybe somebody has experience with vegan recipes and i can ask for feedback and then
continue on the pull request in the next exercise we will show you how you can make changes to a
pull request that is open so if i want to make changes i don't have to close it and open a new
one we will practice that in the next step so that's a draft pull request and only once we
are ready then i can make it ready for review but we are not ready yet and we wanted to show one
more thing and that because somebody asked about tests because some we have sneakily put in a
script that runs automated tests and this was only to to show you that this is possible
we will go in depth next week where we discuss automated testing at this point we only wanted
to know that it is possible to do to couple testing with pull requests so that you can have
some checks automatically running and the person reviewing can be then confident that the code is
still continue to work continuing to work and i wanted to show this is some unfinished work and
this will probably break the test i wanted just to show you how that looks and what how you can
then look about what happened so i will open this not draft but and if i open it
it's unfinished uh now some checks are running so how this really works next week
Indeed, they are failing. So let's not merge this. Let's not merge this yet. And how can
I even make sure that this doesn't get merged? Well, I can turn it into a draft. How do I
I do that. Edit. Somewhere there was a way to make it a draft pull request. Convert to
draft. Here we go. I can convert it to draft. If I realize there is a mistake, it's unfinished,
this way i can i can be sure that this will not be merged accidentally but what i wanted
to show you is that okay something failed what failed and why you can inspect this i can click
on that and this is a silly test that we set up which will in in this case it looks it checks
whether the recipe contains
dash dash ingredients
and dash dash instructions.
So if your recipe fails,
it's not your fault.
We didn't explain this.
And next week,
we will learn more about
how does this work?
How does this part work?
How can you run tests
and build documentation
automatically on any commit?
So why, or maybe just a question before we go into the next thing, why do we put so much
value on pull requests and code review?
Is this, is this for gatekeeping?
No.
So what's the, what's the value of it?
It's a couple of more steps, but so what, what's the value of doing this instead of
Just everybody pushing directly to main.
To me, one of the main things is we have a good discussion
and then together there will be always something to add on it
when someone else is also going to review things and all.
And I don't break things.
Yeah.
So it's really about learning, mostly.
It's not about gatekeeping.
the person reviewing doesn't have to be the senior professor it's about learning from each other i
i haven't i learn about what's going on in the project what do other people work on
and i can also learn if i look at these pull requests i can often learn about oh that's an
interesting coding trick i didn't know that this was possible so you can you can improve your
programming by seeing either from the person sending the pull request or from the person
reviewing it also there is if if you know something else uh more uh to this pull request you can also
add it when you review these things yeah and that's what we that's exactly what we want to do
now in the next step so the plan we have now a little bit over half an hour left we will introduce
an exercise and we will then send you again into an exercise session and this is here we will make
it we will stay in the same
repository
still in the recipe book
but here we want to practice
something really really useful in real life
and that is
as a
reviewer
we want you to know how to
ask for changes
in a pull request
also
sometimes you see a small mistake
a tiny little typo
and then you can even as a reviewer you can suggest a change to a pull request
and we will practice this and below on the page you see screenshots and examples and some ideas
of what you can what you can try it on another really important one is that if i open a pull
request and i should make some changes to it i don't need to close it and create a new one
it's not necessary you can you can modify an open pull request
and how do we how do we do that and i'm not sure we have really
uh explained it yet so if i look at the pull request and here i will just open up mine
this one maybe
a pull request
is always from a branch
to a branch
it's not from a commit to a branch
which means that if I add new commits
to the source branch
they will get added to the pull request
so now we have a mechanism to suggest changes
or to implement changes
so to continue on this vegan recipe i don't have to close it and create a new one i will i will
add new commits to my rather one slash vegan pumpkin pie branch and they will get added to
the pull request yeah could you show that uh maybe before we go for a exercise uh how do you do that
you go to the branch yeah let's maybe i can do it directly here on the on the web
so i go i go to the branch and i make sure that i'm on i'm on the branch and here i can make
changes where was that this was a dessert pumpkin pie and let's make changes here i will create a
commit. I really don't know what is a good replacement for x for the vegan.
Good replacement here needed.
So still not finished but I will commit it.
Let's choose a better commit message. Add it a placeholder for x.
I want to commit it to my
Sadovan Vegan Pumpkin Pie branch.
Yes.
I have a new commit now on that branch.
And if I now look back at my pull request,
here it is.
Aha!
The change got added to the pull request.
No need to close it and open a new one.
If I now look at files changed,
both are there.
and I'm not sure we showed
because I think it's also fun to see
just to see this collaborativeness
on insights
and network
I think it's really fun to see
all the changes that we made
this needs now a few seconds to load
but we will see all the comments that we did
and all the branches
and we will see how they nicely merge towards the
so here are all the changes made in this exercise some of the changes are merged some of them are
not merged yet the the little black sticky notes are the branch names
and many of these changes got already merged here into the main branch and here they are
so this is beautiful and now exercise so here
here are the exercise tasks again below you will find help and discussion and
screenshots use them this is not cheating it's the it's the part of the exercise so go through them
you will a lot of this will feel familiar again we create a new branch
for anything new i want to do a new branch it's really a good
it's a good reflex
but
in there
try to introduce
a small mistake, maybe a little typo
you can also try to introduce
a larger mistake
open a pull request and then
then
switch your head, switch your role
as a reviewer
try to practice
suggesting changes
to somebody else's pull request there is a there is a hint on how to do that
and as a submitter practice how do i implement changes to um to open pull requests without
closing and opening a new one that's the goal
and uh how much time do we give
25 minutes which will then bring us back briefly before the hour we will do a super quick
just summary send you into a longer break and then after the longer break we will have another
one and a half hours where we can then rediscuss this revisit this and then we will take it to yet
another level after the longer break but the next 25 minutes they are for this exercise you will
find if you are unsure where this exercise is on the bottom of the of the notes we will post
a link to this exercise and what is also nice for us if you can let us know how this is going
we don't really see you on stream um let us know is this going well is this too much time
too little time too unclear so a little feedback of how this is going for you keep the questions
coming anything else i forgot to say no not really but we please ask questions if you have
stuck somewhere yes and we'll be back in 25 minutes yeah see you in 25 minutes good luck
with the exercise see you then see you
and we are back from the exercise
and this will be just a one minute summary
so first of all I wanted to say
thanks so much for all the
all requests and reviews this works amazingly well yeah also on the non-recorder repository
as well we are seeing that we will do merge later today but i'm really happy that you are
collaborating quite well and interacting with each other it's really cool i got 170 emails
because guess who forgot to unwatch your repository but that's nice i mean oh really
seeing this interaction live.
Many good questions.
What we will do
after the break, we will now take a one-hour
break. After the break, we will summarize the
session, so don't worry, we will summarize, we will highlight
some questions.
The one thing that
we will do after the break is
take this to even the next level
and practice on
how to
suggest changes, how to make
a change proposal per request
to a repository that is maybe not yours and it doesn't have to be a big open source project but
it could be just somebody else's project that maybe does almost what you have in mind but
and you have some improvements or some changes that you want to do and you want to
have a mechanism to to suggest these changes so collaborating
across repositories and we have now all the tools for this and so that will be then after the break
and then we will have a discussion session where we just want to discuss about many of the concepts
that came up and discuss like why do we do this and what is the what is the point of
all the things that we showed and what is a good balance for real life work
yes and in other words that we we were collaborating together where you have the
right access the next level is after the break would be that you collaborate you
contribute to a public repository where you are not having right access
super looking forward see you in one hour we will
also look at questions and answer those that are not answered yet
looking forward to more see you in one hour back here on stream and thank you bye
my side. Why is that? Oh, now it's Yeah, okay, good. Now it looks good. Yeah, welcome back from
the break. We have one and a half hours left. And let's get started. Let's settle back in into
GitHub. So we'll come back and we will give a short summary about what we did before the lunch
break yes so first we will summarize before we do something else i will just remove the
the break information here
so let's settle in with a little summary of the previous exercise
we really appreciate all the questions that came in and some of the things we will show here on
stream where should i start should i look at there was a question about what is this test
checks what is that should we look at that or should we look at should i try to suggest some
changes to your pull request [name] let us look at the test and briefly and people can learn a lot
about it next week but it would be nice why we are having these checks you know yeah
so up here under my mouse there is a green check mark and you have maybe also seen that on so if i
on the pull requests a couple of them have green check marks couple of them have a red cross
so what's going on there uh we we added the script here which
we imagine that we already run a test in our case it's it's a little bit of a silly thing because we
we verify whether the recipe has an instructions section and an ingredient section
So if you want, you can have a look at this.
This is written in Python.
It doesn't matter now what is really happening inside.
We wanted you to just know that this is a possibility.
Then some people asked, so how does GitHub run it?
How does GitHub know that it should run?
This is happening here in this GitHub workflows.
And we will not go through it in detail.
but we have here some instructions
where we tell GitHub that
on every pull request that is merged
to the main branch it should do certain things
and next week we will go in depth
next week when we talk about automated testing
and documentation we will use this
so this can be used to automatically build documentation
or automatically run a set of tests
and we wanted you to know that this is possible
so here it's not a catastrophe
if some of them fail
it's not your fault and it's also not a problem
if you merged some pull request
that made everything fail for everybody
not a problem
that's the nice thing here about this exercise
repository that it's good to make
these to just
experiment
so more about that next week
this is just a little like teaser preview
oh [name]
let's go and try to
suggest some changes on one of the pull requests to also edit something on someone else branch
maybe this is still like previous exercise um so we i will go
the pull request number 34 this is the one that [name] opened this is a recipe for mango lassi
it's work in progress it's a draft pull request i cannot merge it yet
but i can give feedback i can help out so there were two things that we we wanted you to know
that exist one is for me the ability to comment on the code and also suggest small changes directly
here so i could so instead of asking you to implement a small change i can suggest it to
you so i will i want to show you how that works if i click here on files changed
then i see the code
and here i can comment on the code
if i click on the plus you can even comment on a whole range but now just to keep it simple
Now, just to keep it simple, I will add a comment.
So here on this code line, I could add some comments.
But there is this plus minus here where I can add a suggestion.
Instruction, mix well.
So this plus minus symbol, I can, and if I now click on add single comment, it's interesting
because now in our pull request conversation, it will create a suggestion which we can commit.
So as soon as I click here, typically it would be [name] clicking here or somebody else.
if they like my suggestion
so as soon as one of you
who has right access clicks on this thing
which I will now
it will create a new
commit and I can even change
the commit message
so this is a nice way for me to suggest
make a suggestion
and I make it so much easier
and for [name] to accept this rather than asking [name] to
implement it.
Yeah. So it is [name] who is changing on my branch. So this
is this is possible when you have this pull request.
Yeah. So this was the tiny suggestion, I want to make it
maybe a little bit more explicit. What if I want to make
bigger change here if i want to we imagine that we are in the same research group
um if i want to help you out with this pull request i can also go directly on your branch
what i will i just want to remember is which file is it that is changed so i can find it
And the file is called Desserts Mangolassi.
You could see that down.
Where do I see it?
Oh, here.
Yes.
Here I see it.
So good.
So I just want to make a note of this.
Now I'm on your branch, Desserts Mangolassi.
And I can also make bigger.
So the thing that we want to show is that anybody with right permissions to the repository
can also commit changes to other people's branches.
It's not a problem.
As long as you have pushed the branch to the GitHub repository.
So what are good ingredients for mango lassi?
Mango for sure.
And then yogurt, milk.
Maybe that's it.
Yeah.
tubes. So that's pretty good. I will give it a better commit message. This is the right
branch. Commit. And if I go back to your pull request, we will see it there. This is the
commit that i just did and we have a way to make improvements until we are happy with it and once
we are happy with it then we mark it somewhere as ready for review i guess maybe we are ready
for review and as soon as i click ready for review then then it becomes mergeable
and both in this
in this
exercise repository but also in the other one
really
also practice
merging somebody else's pull requests
so you can really go in and merge them
don't be afraid of
nothing bad can happen
so go and practice also merging
yeah also those
working with the teams you can merge
each other's merge pull requests so you might hear merge requests in between because github
it is pull request and gitlab it is merge request so yeah it's the same yes exactly the same thing
two different names i think maybe the merge request is the better name it's more we are
really requesting to merge pull request is more the historical because this is how it's implemented
technically
yeah
I've been
there was
some discussion
long back
but what
is difference
between pull
and pull
request
pull is
you are
taking the
changes
locally
and then
pull request
is you
are asking
the owners
to
pull your
changes
to the
repository
that's
something
interesting
to know
if you
have pull
and pull
request
differences
we have
cat
yeah we were hoping for this so cat appearance and hopefully more
this is fun should we uh should we go to the next episode
yes i don't see many questions now but please feel free to ask more questions
so the next episode is here in the notes and i will navigate to it also
Before we go further with this exercise, [name], may I ask what is the importance of this exercise?
Why are we doing it?
Because we want to be able to not only collaborate within our repository, but also being able
to use these tools to contribute changes to and accept contributions from other people
when it's somebody else's repository.
So in other words, being able to contribute changes to maybe a tool that you use in your
work, it could be an open source project, you have an improvement, or you have an improvement
for the documentation, or you have a clarification, or you have a tutorial you want to contribute
to them. And we will see that how nicely this is implemented. And we will be able to do it
without even having to ask for right permissions. So many things will be similar, some things will
be new. But this is how we like to build things up step by step. So there will be few new elements,
but a lot of the mechanisms will be similar to the previous two exercises.
in this method you can contribute to any public repository
as long as you have a github account
so and it's really a lot of fun i think it feels really empowering like a really nice moment when
and it can be a small thing like a little typo in our documentation but
once if you contribute to somebody else's project and then it gets merged and then you are part of
it i think it's now like a nice empowering moment and also a good networking and you get to know
these people who works in this project and easy to communicate once you are in there yeah it can
be a way to start new collaborations like scientific collaborations that later lead to
to projects and papers
yes so let's see we will need we will now be in a different exercise repository which
will look very familiar it's still the recipe book but the address will be different
and again people have a choice maybe you are part of a team but then you need to create a
a different project different repository and we will explain why this is different
why why it is a different address and um if you follow on your own you can again collaborate with
us but now the address has changed it's working workflow exercise yeah so just since [name]
mentioned about changing the address so this is the same kind of repository but the changes you
have done earlier in the exercise that is in a different repository that will not be here when
you fork it it's precisely same template to make it maybe explicit so here i'm in this centralized
repository and i know that many of your nice pull requests didn't get merged yet but we
i will come back to it in the afternoon so later when i have some time we will go and
comment and follow up but now what i will do is i will navigate away from this
so in your exercise later which we will start around in 10 minutes you will navigate away from
this and you will be in a different place for the stream participants it's it will be forking
either this one if you don't mind that maybe your pull request shows up on stream and if you want
to make sure that it doesn't show up on stream you use this one so i will go in here it's a
now suddenly it's kind of a fresh recipe book it's still the same recipe book but now
we don't have any pull requests yet that's the goal of the exercise we don't have any issues yet
different address so that's important what is also different now is that
we are not adding you as a collaborator because that's the point of the exercise
to show that you don't have to be you don't have to have right permissions
so nobody needs to be added you don't need to exchange any only any usernames
but now this also means that you cannot merge so now there is somebody who is the maintainer
in for the stream that's [name] and me for your team that's one person from your team who is
the maintainer and everybody else can only read but not merge and that's fine
let us show how it will look like when you fork it maybe before we go for the break
exercise break yes so here what exactly so what everybody will do in the exercise will you will
make a fork and remind to remind what was the fork again it was it was a full copy
but it will stay on github so how do i create under your namespace under your username space
namespace may mean that your username but earlier it was under code refinery
when we did the collaborative where you have right access now it is under your namespace
so i will demonstrate how how to create a fork you can then practice that
first i make sure that i'm in the right place to fork from looks good and to create a new fork i
click on this button i can already see actually that one fork already exists so i will now create
second one so i click on the button here fork and then it asks me you want to create a copy
under this name i keep the name and then where should it be copied to so who is the owner of
the fork this is me now i keep it this doesn't matter much but you can just keep keep everything
and once I push on the green button here, create work.
Now it's copying the repository.
And now it created a copy.
And now I verify that I'm under my namespace.
So this is my namespace here.
This is me.
And everybody will see a different username here.
Notice also that the fork remembers where it was forked from.
There is a reference to the original repository.
And also there is a message that this branch is up to date with the original repository
Oh, that's interesting.
So my main branch is now up to date with this repository here.
If it is not, you will get a message here instead of, when you try working on it, you
will see that anyway.
Because we will see exactly that.
So the other interesting thing about the exercise will be that we will send pull requests and
then the maintainer, [name] and me, will merge them.
and as soon as we merge them
the original repository will evolve
so the main branch will change
there will be new commits
but all the forks
and now there are eight of those
and I can even have a look
which ones, where they are
here, eight forks
hmm here active
no they are not marked effective because they didn't make any changes yet but i will now
show me all of them
so there are already eight forks this can be also interesting for a project when if you want to know
who has forked my project this could be also future collaborations these are people who are
interested in my in my code project and so the central the original repository will evolve
but all the forks will stay behind because remember what what i said two hours ago three
hours ago was that they don't automatically synchronize we have to do it actively
and what you will notice is that
after a while
your main branch will not be up to date
it will be
behind and
this is what this button
is for and that will be part of
the exercise so part of the exercise will be
also to later
update your fork
and also
could you just also tell about
this main
tabs because you don't
see any issues there on the forked repository under your namespace, [name].
Yeah.
So where did the issues go?
No issues, no problems.
The issue tab here is gone.
We remember that there was something here.
And this is because I'm on a forked repository.
And the default is to track issues only in the original one, which makes sense for most
projects.
most projects want to have one place where they keep track of all the issues and their ideas and
their suggestions you can change it so i if i want if i would go to settings i could modify that
but if if i go back to the original one this is where the issues are so if if in the exercise you
see that you should maybe create an issue or not this is where you need to create it so we have one
central place where we track all the issues otherwise there will be confusion of like where
the issue tracking happening and i want to show just one more thing before we talk more about the
exercise one more thing that i like to look at before creating a fork of a repository is
and this is a little preview until next week is a license
and we have a session next week on where we talk about social coding software licensing and why
really matters for everybody. And I normally look at this. So if there is a project and it doesn't
have a license file, I normally first contact the authors and ask them to, can you please add
a license file? Can you add a standard license so that we know what I can do with this code,
so that I know that I can make changes to the code and publish my changes so that I can later publish
them in a paper. More about that next week. Here we are pretty good because the license
is very, very permissive. What is recipe book, it's, it's basically public domain, Creative
Commons, zero. Just looking at my checklist and also looking at
yeah one thing about this exercise you might see that open an issue in the upstream
exercise repository in this case upstream exercise repository is the repository where you clone
where you forked from that's under the code refinery yeah that's namespace yeah so there
is a little bit of jargon and sometimes we sorry i just wanted to go back to the back to my fork
so sometimes we we talk about upstream and then we talk when we say upstream we mean
the original repository and the idea is that changes flow like a river and there are some
changes that happen to you know upstream the river and then flow down to my fork
excellent one more thing if you are working on the command line
then you clone from your fork
your laptop
and work on it, push the changes to fork
that is explained here
yeah, that is an important point
so again, you can do everything in the browser
if you want to, but those of you who work locally
on your laptops
you will need to clone the code
onto your laptop and now you need to be careful where do you clone from you want to clone from
the place from your fork because this is where you can write to if you clone oh why is this
showing this what do i get out of the way from this if you clone accidentally from this place
you can still make local changes but then suddenly you cannot push anymore because you
have right permissions. If that happens, you don't have to delete everything and start again.
We have in the exercise walkthrough, we have a recovery step because at every workshop it
happens to a few people. And it's a good exercise that you can recover from this without deleting
everything. So a couple of things will be familiar. Fork, we've seen it actually on day one,
but also now I showed it how that works. And again, we will create a branch, we will make
new commits, we will create pull requests, but now we are getting this into our muscle memory,
it feels easier yeah so why do you need fork maybe this is because you don't have right
permission to this repository you want to contribute yeah so you cannot do what you
did earlier in the exercise in this without forking yeah and imagine here instead of the
recipe book imagine that this is a project that you want to contribute to this could be
this could be the library that you are using this could be somebody else's project that you
want to contribute to it could be it could be the open source code that that you depend on
and want to you know give back
so what will be new uh pull request this time the pull request goes from
across repositories so not within the same it will go from a repository to a different repository
oh this is actually not completely new because we now know that this is coupled to automated testing
Then the maintainer, [name] and me, will review merge and your forks will get out of date.
They will not have these changes.
So then your goal will be to update your fork with these changes.
And also this part here, which also will be really part of the discussion session, the
last half an hour of this
workshop day.
For those of you who
manage all of this and if you get a little
bit bored and if it feels easy,
one thing you can also try, just for
fun, is
create two separate
requests
which change the same part of the
code, the same part of our recipe,
but in two different ways.
So what you can try to do, try to create a conflict.
And then we can
look at
a conflicting pull request and discuss what we do about it and you have you have seen
what conflicts are yesterday but so we can we can also see a conflict in real life and see that this
is not a problem that's a good thing and also in this case you cannot merge this pull request
that the maintainer
has to
merge it or
accept this pull request.
Yeah.
So you'll be able to open up issues
and send pull requests
but now it's up to us to merge
them.
But the nice thing is that you don't have to ask for permission
and also the nice
thing for us as maintainer is that
we don't have to be afraid like nobody
just because this is an open source project
with an open source license
I don't have to be afraid
that somebody changes this
in a way that I don't want
we still have control here
and we decide what is merged
and what is not merged
but we will do it in a very nice way
so we
we will remember that on the other side
there is a human being
later in the discussion
we can maybe talk about
what to do about
controversial changes
without
so what to do about the change that you
you don't want to merge
but you also don't want to hurt the other person
let's discuss
that later
here are the
exercise tasks
again there is the help and discussion
use it
I will also let's paste
into
here we have this exercise block
25 minutes so
until
55 past
where we come back to the stream
yeah and please let us know how it's going
in the exercise part
also any kind of
questions welcome
to ask
in the
meantime we will be busy here
reviewing and merging. But see you all in 25 minutes back here
on the stream. I will just find the right button. See you then.
Bye. Bye.
hi everybody welcome back hi welcome back we were really busy here merging and commenting
We didn't manage all of them, but I think we managed enough pull requests so that the
original repository is then enough different from your forked repository. That was one goal.
Also for the non-recorded version. There are more pull requests, but you can see the changes.
And everything that we didn't manage, we will catch up later.
um we will now just spend like five minutes discussing some something that came up
and after that we will take another break and after that we will have a 20 minute discussion
session so what are the things that we should comment on
how to synchronize from your local fork on your fork yes that's very important because
and now in my example here
there is the original repository
which has lots of nice recipes, lots of changes
but if I go into
if I go into my fork
and how did I find again my fork
this is me
if I look at my fork
well my fork is 30 commits behind
And so 30, this is probably 15 recipes that I don't have on my fork here.
And that was also part of the exercise.
This used to be, in the past, this used to be more difficult because in the past, you
had to pull changes from the original repository to your computer and then push them to your
fork.
These days, it's much easier.
these days there is a button for it and it's this sync fork and the sync fork will work really well
and this is because i didn't touch my main branch and that's a good it's a good thing to do
so i will i will never make any modifications on the main branch anything i want to do for
anything new i create a new branch and then this will always work here so sync fork
this branch is out of date
and they mean the main branch
and if I now click on update
it will update
the main branch on my fork
so on the repository
that I own
update branch
and now I have
all these nice recipes
I'm up to date
for the moment I'm up to date
with the original repository until some new pull requests get merged.
There was, I think, a question about deleting branches.
Maybe we can show that.
We can also show a conflict.
Somebody created a conflict and managed to fix it also.
there was also a question about
what is this thing about
what is the difference between fetch and pull
we maybe
noted
we mentioned fetch only in passing
there is a difference between the two
what should I pick up next here
should we talk about this
should we show a conflict
what do you think
I think I'm muted
sorry yes i was sneezing so i mean oh yeah but uh maybe we'll start with fetch and pull first
and go off the conflict yeah so at the beginning of today
on the beginning uh in the concepts and i think it's only mentioned somewhere so there is
one way to get changes from
let's say from GitHub to your laptop
is you can do it by Git pull
but you can also use fetch
and they are different because
pull will download all the changes that you don't have
and it will
modify your local branch
so in a pull
there is fetch and merge
but sometimes you don't want to modify your local branch
you only want to download the commits
and then you can use fetch
so fetch will download all commits that you don't have
but it will not modify your local branch
and then you can look at the commits
and if you like them
then you can do the merge part as a second step
so usually I usually use pull to my main branch
that's a very frequent operation I do than fetch
I very rarely use fetch
same here
so 99.9% of cases pull
it's only if
I'm really unsure about
I don't want to modify my branch
I want to first look at them
with the git diff
compare them
if I'm extremely careful
then I will go for fetch
maybe we should take a break
and after the break
pick up some of the more things that we wanted to show and hopefully we get lots of more questions
so after the break it will be just us demonstrating uh and we have a discussion
session here and you can ask us anything about git and github or git lab yes um so then we would
be back 10 past the hour we'll just post it here 10 past the hour we'll be back for more demo more
discussion no more exercises but we will still continue reviewing your contributions and we
really appreciate them a lot see you in send you see you 10 past the hour just send us into a break
Hello, back from break. Welcome back. We have now 20 minutes left, which we want to use
to answer questions summarize. There are a couple of things I wrote down that I want
to discuss we also want to then invite questions so we will summarize a few things but what you
can do is please ask more questions please really try to overwhelm us because in a moment i will
then also invite other instructors to join for really a discussion here about code review
collaboration oh one topic i wanted to come back to because i think we we used it but we
we didn't really discuss why we do that was this the auto closing issues
why do why it's good to use these magic words like close closes fix fixes
what is the what is the advantage of
of relating changes and issues.
So do you see that there are one number highlighted
and one number is slash hash seven,
which is what are the numbers?
Yeah, so the first thing, this thing comes from,
this is the title of your pull request,
which actually comes from your commit.
no your commit this was your commit yeah but then this was the title of your pull request
and then what is this this thing which is a little bit different color
this is the number of the pull request so this pull request has the number seven
which means that we can refer to it somewhere else we could be talking about
oh yeah we did that already in pull request seven have a look hash seven it will cross link
and link to this pull request
so each pull request has a number
but also each issue has a number
here you refer to an issue
and this magic word
as soon as I
merge it
and now this was
so how do I review it
I normally look at this
I look at the files changed
looks great to me
and
I will merge it
and as soon as I merge it
maybe I can do that here
really clearly
I will open on the bottom side
I will open the corresponding issue
which was the issue number 2
and it's open
and then on the top side I will merge the poor
changes reviewed happy happy happy
and yeah okay before you
merge I just want to mention there was
a conversation someone would like to
whoops yeah
okay let's not so that's
maybe change
eight cubes ah let's do it
yeah
so
two let's do eight
and
then
me or somebody else can actually apply this
I will now do that
and then you can also do this
resolve, well now it automatically resolved the conversation
so that has been now applied
checks are running
I will now merge it
and as soon as I click merge
we focus on the bottom part of my screen
3, 2, 1, closed
so once it got integrated
into main
it read this magic word
and closed the issue
and why did we demonstrate this
This was not because I'm lazy and I would be too lazy to click on the close button here,
but the advantage was that it cross-references the idea or the problem with the commit that
fixed it. And that's really good for reproducibility, because then if later maybe
this was a problem in the code and I want to know from when was this in the code and until
went precisely, it was in the code until this commit precisely. Really, really important for
reproducibility. And I will now rearrange here so that I can see your questions, but also I see my
my plan so we can discuss now that now that we have the tools
how should we approach other people's repositories with ideas and changes and pull requests
And for very minor changes, so if this is a typo or it's a small change and there is
not much to discuss, what I sometimes do is then, well, we create a fork.
We know how.
We create a new branch.
On the new branch, I make a new commit and I open up a request and that's it.
I always create a new branch. So I never sent the pull request from main. Because that can create troubles later down the road.
That's one of the best practices. And you haven't mentioned about issues in this minor changes. So what is the suggestion? No issues for minor changes or what would be the best practices?
Here it's a minor thing. I don't need to really open an issue. Maybe there is an issue
open and I'm actually fixing it. It's more, what if you... So here I have about more like
large changes. So what if you see an issue and have an idea how to fix it? So what if
you observe a problem and then it can be it can actually be good to open the issue even if you
already have a solution in mind because you at least inform everybody else that i know about
this problem maybe somebody else will hit the same problem it's really good for them to see
that this is unknown so i don't keep it to myself we open the issue and uh if you don't know how to
fix it or maybe you can ask for maybe somebody else can or you can collect feedback and then
refer to it in a pull request and this can also be good so for informing everybody else about a
problem and for anything bigger so if i have an idea for a new feature it can be good to first
open the issue and collect feedback so that i'm sure that the solution that i have in mind
fits into the repository.
It is what the authors want
before I do all the work
and write 50,000 lines of code.
So talk about it in an issue
and then do the coding
because it avoids surprises later.
Yeah, discuss and get feedback
before you code.
When suggesting to an open project or collaborative project, some ideas and all, there will be
any code of conduct or something that what you suggest, [name]?
I think any project that is bigger will sooner or later maybe need code of conduct, also
contribution guide, or just a document where you can describe how would you like contributions
to be? How would you like them to be submitted? And also certain standards that you expect in
your project to be followed. Some suggestion about how to proceed from here, what we learned
this two three days yeah um i mean one way to that you can practice this and be also incredibly
useful for our project is that if i scroll up here in the lesson so i'll scroll all the way up
our lessons are on GitHub. All of them are open source. If you see things that we could have done
better here and explained better, maybe there is a better wording or maybe some exercise step
wasn't clear enough. If I right click edit on GitHub, this is the repository with the lesson.
Also here, you can open issues and you can see that there are a couple of issues that
we know about, two of them are from today
you can send us
pull requests with improvements
this
will
really help the project a lot
but then
for your own work
really trying to
team up with somebody
try to find somebody who
for code review
I would try to implement this
not with a lot of bureaucracy, not with a lot of
checks and
but implementing code review for repositories with two people or more so create a common
repository invite your friend as a collaborator and collaborate together try this out the like
the code review set the main branch as read-only review these are the changes it will it will delay
it will delay the changes a little bit until they are in main but with the benefit that we learn
about it, we improve our coding, maybe we catch a possible mistake. But now, up to you.
What are the things that you would like to know about GitHub collaboration? Which question
should we highlight there was Oh, there is this question around line 416. I'm just looking
you did. So it is this one? Yeah. That is answered.
yeah so the so the question is why should we create a new branch for every new change
and not just continue on main even if it's i'm the only person on my fork
and the reason is that and it might be already answered is that
pull requests are from branch to branch they are not from commit to branch
so if i now send a pull request on main and maybe the pull request takes two weeks to review
now i need to wait because if i now continue on my main branch all the new commits will also get
added to the pull request which might surprise me it might surprise the person reviewing
so now i need to wait if i created a side branch i don't need to wait i just send a
pull request and continue my work and wait until that thing is merged but there is another reason
and that is once it's once your pull request is merged it will typically create a merge commit
and that is a commit that you don't have on your main so now your it will the history will start
be weird on your main branch on your forked main branch so to avoid these trouble good to create a
extra branch i i personally like to have a branch for everything even the minor changes as well
because it avoids many my conflicts may come after i change something yeah
Yeah.
And somewhere there was also a question,
well, should we then delete?
So branches that have been merged,
should we delete them, keep them?
You can keep them.
There is no really harm.
At some point, maybe it becomes a little bit chaotic
because you see 40 branches there that have been merged
and then you can clean up and delete them.
And deleting branches in this case
means only removing the sticky notes so you will not delete the commits
so we have five more minutes but it would be nice to remind them about the feedback
yeah that's at the end of the end of the notes please let us know how how was the speed and
and please be honest we are not offended
this is
this thing is what we look at when we
prepare the next workshop in half a year
so we really want to know
how was the speed
how was the level
was it
useful what was missing
what was the part that you liked the most
what was the part that you liked the least
and then
we use this when we create the next
edition
so these
lessons are
really
continuously
improved
and we
really
appreciate
your
feedback
here
yeah
and also
this
notes
will be
archived
and you
will get
an email
it will
be open
after the
workshop
as well
yeah
so I
will
archive
these
later
today
they will
be part
of the
workshop
site
we will
also go
through
all the
open
request that got we didn't forget them we just were really busy here jumping between windows
so we will review and merge everything sometime after the event we will also delete the exercise
repository so you don't have to be worried that something will be left behind hopefully you know
are a bit more comfortable with these tools and are more comfortable in using github and gitlab
app for collaboration.
Also continue this
using this after
this.
That's the best practice.
You can inspire your
team, your colleagues
who works together
if they are not yet on GitHub
using version control.
This is the best way to learn together
and contribute together.
If you don't have
somebody to collaborate with you don't hesitate to i don't know ask me in a pull request my
username is [name] and i can give some comments and also don't hesitate to go to your favorite
project look at the documentation let's see if you find an improvement improvement to their
documentation and try to send the pull requests improving their documentation they will be really
happy about it maybe we should spend two minutes just to give a little teaser about next week what
what will come up
so next week
we will
we will still use
git and github quite a lot
but we will really
apply them to
yeah to
reproducible
research software development
so on tuesday we will
look at
social coding
software licensing and reproducibility
and I hope I don't mix up the days
we will then also discuss documentation
how to document code
how does useful documentation look like
but also how to set up technically
so that you have a really useful documentation
for people to read
automated testing
Jupyter notebooks
modular code development
and probably I forgot something
so these are
topics of next week
so I would like to thank you
for leading this session and [name]
for
doing this live stream
and there were people behind
the scene you might not have seen today
they all worked together
to successfully run
this workshop
yes many thanks to everybody so there is a lot of
work before and during the workshop happening that is maybe not immediately visible
yeah thanks to all who contributed today via pull request or issues and all
and we had a good time reviewing your pull request and suggestions that was very fun
so thanks so much so maybe we can stop the
yeah streaming recording and hopefully we see all of you next week
it's not too late for people to still join so tell your friends
next week it will be more applied more demonstrations
but still it's possible to then also go through these exercises on your own
yeah thank you thanks so much i will oh maybe [name] can help me now to tell me which button
i need to push here is it the break one okay thanks everybody okay okay bye