And if you get lost, this is where we are.
So if you visit this link, you will land on the page which I have on the bottom part of my screen.
So I'll just make that a little bit larger here.
And I know that the font size is maybe a little bit too small.
I will zoom in in a second.
I just want to show you an overview of today.
So today we have four episodes planned, really all about collaborating, using Git.
And the goal is to give you confidence so that you can confidently collaborate, that you have confidence suggesting changes to repositories, but also that you are comfortable reviewing changes and know how this whole change proposal and review process works.
we have four episodes planned and there will be three exercises today
so we have three exercises each 20-ish minutes where we really test out these different
collaboration models within the same repository we will practice code review and we will practice
how to contribute changes to really somebody else's repository
so before I go into the first episode
let me zoom in here
to make it easier to read
the central
I think the central take home message
today will be code review
being able to
make a change proposal to a repository
and being able to review it.
The most common scenario,
and this is what we will practice first,
will be that we all collaborate
within the same repository.
This is a really good fit
for a research group
that has maybe three people
or five people in it
or 20.
And then later we will practice
some other scenario.
And this will be
exercise-driven. We will practice this
on GitHub, but everything we show
works almost the same way also on GitLab.
Although we will here not demonstrate other services,
even if in your research you use GitLab instead of GitHub,
it will really work in a very similar way.