Hello, and welcome back from the lunch break, everyone.
I hope you had some time to get up, walk around, find some food, maybe some coffee.
We'll be spending now the next one and a half hours on our next lesson called social coding.
And we have already met this morning, but in case we haven't, hi, I'm [name].
I work as a research software engineer at CSC in Finland.
And with me here today is [name].
Do you want to introduce yourself, [name]?
Hi.
Well, I'm [name].
I'm a research software engineer at Aalto University.
And I think that's sufficient.
Okay.
Yes.
So we'll be talking about social coding and open software or what you can do to get credit for your code and to allow reuse.
And this is again, as in the morning as well, a, well, not even demo based, but very discussion heavy section of the material.
So there will be no exercises to do directly on your computer, meaning you also don't have any computational prerequisites for this lesson.
So we'll be discussing around the topics and there will be quite some questions for you also coming up in the collaborative notes.
So maybe, [name], we can show briefly for everyone who joined us now how the notes work.
So you've got the link to the notes with any of the last emails that you got from us if you registered for this event.
And if you go there, it looks something like what [name] is showing right now.
And then you can see there is already a question being answered here.
So how would I go about answering this question as well, [name]?
Yeah, so if you have this document open, actually you will probably be at the top if you go
through the link.
So you can scroll down past the break, past the lunch break, and here is the Social Coding
section.
And then I have this pen button here that will go to editing mode.
So this is the same document viewed differently, so now I have to go past the lunch section
again. So now this is the launch section, this info section. And here we have social coding.
So yeah, you can read the question and vote for any specific topic or vote for the answer
by adding a character. So add an O character. I just added one here.
if I think it's a good reason to share my script's code or data
if I think that to find and make it easier to find and reproduce is a good answer then I'll
press o here to add one volt and so yeah this is kind of this is nice because you can read
the vote counts
essentially from
even from this text based editing mode
I'll remove
my own vote from there. I guess I could go
through them and vote but maybe not yet
I will
zoom out though a little bit
so you
might have this view instead
where you have these three buttons
so the edit mode is the pen
and the eye is the
view mode
I guess, preview
should we stay in the preview mode why not yes let's let's stay in the preview and now I will
try to zoom back in and knock out okay okay let's give people still a moment to answer and talk a
little bit about why we have this lesson which might sound a little bit dry maybe to come
to come here and so why do we talk about software licensing and stuff around that so imagine a
situation when you are out there in the internet and you find some really great code or data
that you really want to use and or reuse for your own purposes for your own research for
another publication that you might be preparing so you want to do something good for the original
author you want to cite them and you will make their work also more visible
you might need to modify the code a little bit to make it useful for yourself or if you're using
like data that you're finding out there you might want to remix it with your own data
but then everything is nice and you're very happy that you found this code or this data
it makes a lot of sense for you to reuse it but then you realize that there is maybe no license
attached to the code and now you really have this situation where you are there okay you have used
you have done something with it, it solves an issue.
But then no license means you have no idea what the original author allows you
or agrees with you what you can do with that.
So basically, you cannot reuse what they have provided there.
And then it can be, okay, you choose to publish the paper,
but you don't publish the software data because you can't meaning also that others that find
your paper cannot actually build on top of your software on top of your data
or you maybe cannot publish it at all because your journal requires that the paper come
should come with the data and the software so that they are reproducible and this lesson is
all about avoiding this situation for you and for others so like if you take something from this
lesson it's about like when you find something on the internet look at it if it has a license and
what it allows you to do okay so let's go into the notes and see what we have there so we have
four questions to start with the first is about why would i want to share my scripts code and data
and there is a few options that you hopefully had time now to read through and i see that
many have already voted here maybe very uh interesting is that age didn't get any votes
yet discouraging competitors. So you're all very good sinned here.
So either it is that people don't believe it discourages competitors or
so it kind of doesn't count as publishing something in the sense that someone else
could still publish it as a scientific contribution. Or it means that people are
just fine with sharing their stuff and collaborating with people, which would be of
course the positive view of this lack of votes. I kind of suspect it is the other one though.
How about you, [name]? What would be a good reason or what is a good reason for you?
So what am I thinking when I mean, I basically do try to share everything from as early as possible
and originally basically the main reason was that i didn't want to lose access to my code
when i moved to another research group so um essentially if you work for a university in
many cases the university owns the license but they do allow you to publish it as an open source
library and then if you move to another university hopefully you brought a copy but even if you did
If it doesn't have a license, it's kind of legally dubious to use the code.
So you can use it in your new institution if it's a work product, you did it for work, if you publish it with a license, or at least add a license file for yourself.
So that is one big reason.
And then the other one is just if you have it online
and then when your computer crashes, which it will,
then you still have access to it.
For that, of course, it could be private,
but then including the other reason,
not losing access to your own code,
making it public is more useful.
um well the third thing is of course it is to actually try to share the research contribution
with so that other people can use it and don't have to redo all the work
um so like that is the altruistic reason but the first two are um more about why i'm like
yeah why I'm for myself sharing the code for me it's also here answer K it encourages me to code
properly from the start because for myself I'm like oh yeah I will remember and oh yeah like
it's clear to me now what's happening here and I don't need comments I don't need anything
but when i will add documentation at some point and i will add tests at some point and it will be
fine yeah yeah exactly but if you're working up in the open then it's uh it can happen that someone
finds your code and i want to make that someone happy i work that way i want to make other people
happy so i will add a little bit documentation at least and i will also add comments from the start
to make that random person that finds my code happy and then again when I come back like two
months after I wrote that code I will also be happy myself to to find the information there
okay then let's see question two the most concerning thing for me if I share my software
are now so if you're not sharing what's your reason or if you're sharing what are the things
that you're concerned about how it is for you yeah it's encouraging that there's a lot of your votes
here but yeah I mean actually it is the ugly code answer because if I'm not sharing something it is
because I'm essentially just trying something out
that is probably not going to work.
And then it's abandoned.
I'm not going to finish it, most likely.
Yes.
And so ugly code, definitely.
It's a big reason.
And I have some codes that are still private
where i'm thinking like someday i will clean this up for someone else to to use um yeah and
then there is this others may find bugs and mistakes what if the algorithm is wrong
yeah what if is the algorithm is wrong if you don't share no one might ever find out that's
maybe good for you because you have that paper published but in the end don't you want to know
like isn't it better if someone says okay like i've looked at your code and um how about this
is there is there some some some mistake here and then you can still fix it and then
if you have already published your code then you can publish a what is it addition to
to the paper or in any other way you fix it and then when people reuse it they have a working
code and they actually have something to reuse somehow like this is maybe not always the case
but if you have a decent number of publications and some of them have errata some of them have
corrections or you even have um pulled back what was the official what's the correct english word
for removing an article like it's kind of a drastic thing to do usually you would make a
correction but if you retracted an article like that should make you look better that should make
all of the other papers look so much more believable because mistakes happen and yeah I
know I've lost some data I know I've changed the code and not been able to reproduce a result and
so on so yeah those kinds of things happen and if your publication history looks like you've never
made a mistake like to me that's more suspicious than um than polished look right yes but um that's
um that's not still always the case right it's it is better to make sure that you don't have
mistakes in the paper before you publish it.
For that publishing the code before you publish the paper is
actually a good idea.
Yeah. And there is even journals that support that also. And then
we have A, it will be scooped or stolen by someone else. And I
think that's where we get to one of the topics that we will be
talking in this lesson which is licenses can actually help with that because you are sharing
your code and depending on like who owns the right is it you or is it your employer you can put
the the license and give the framework on how how your code can be reused in different scenarios
And that's what the license is for.
It's to protect you and your work
and make clear how it can be used in the future.
Yeah.
This is also a big difference
between how software is treated
and how papers are treated.
So when you're doing research
and you publish a paper,
I've never heard anyone say
you shouldn't publish,
I don't want to publish this paper
because then someone might
create derivative work based on it.
like someone might scoop it
and continue working on that field
because they will cite your paper
and if they don't, that's misconduct.
Now, if they use your code
and they don't cite you,
that's also, I mean,
it's not exactly citing, right?
It's not technically the same thing.
But if they don't mention
that they have used your code,
that is also misconduct.
Unless, of course,
you publish it under a license where you specifically say you can do whatever you want
this code those licenses to exist but you don't have to use that license
yeah and then uh point h also has quite a few votes here it is too early i'm just prototyping
and i will write version to this yeah that was my answer also i mentioned also earlier i'm also
guilty of that i definitely have some of those lingering around um and there also there is like
we all know the the expression um well i don't know the expression like a positive publication
bias so just is it just publication bias i guess it is so people publish positive findings and
they do a lot of work on a research project don't get a positive finding and then it doesn't get
published then the same thing happens with code you do a bunch of stuff um you try different
things and you never publish the ones that don't work so it actually would be useful to publish
the codes where you give up um not necessarily to um to give it to people to reuse but rather to
just tell people you've already tried this maybe they can do it better but you know it's evidence
maybe it doesn't work yeah and it might spark ideas for someone else to continue your work
and maybe that is something that in the end also helps you yeah and then we have uh i worried about
licensing and legal matters as they are very complicated and yeah i also have felt that way
and it is it is a big topic and there is many different licenses and so on but hopefully with
this lesson today we can also show you that there are tools out there that help you and
like maybe showing you a way on how you can still still do it even though you don't know
the whole context of everything
and still work with
the licenses
there is also just
well and I guess this comes out
in the licensing section as well
but one important point is that
common sense works here
so even though it is a legal thing
it's not just a bunch of magic words
that somehow interact with
some legal system out there
mostly legal stuff is
based on common sense
so if you put a license there
and it's one of the standard ones.
People should roughly know what you mean by it.
So it doesn't have to be complicated.
There's also a comment on,
I put it in Jupyter Notebook format,
which isn't suitable for anyone to reuse it
and never having time to update it.
Yeah.
Okay.
I mean, we'll come back to publishing notebooks.
So that might be useful.
What do we call that section?
Jupyter Notebooks.
And I guess we have Binder in the Jupyter Notebooks section.
Yep.
Yeah.
So that will be useful in that case.
But yeah, I mean, you can publish Jupyter Notebooks.
You can put them online.
it's not I'm maybe it's not as reusable but it's still it's better than not publishing it
yeah and there's even platforms where you can have them as executable notebooks so you don't
even just provide your code but you can provide the whole computing environment
often they live also in containers what we talked about earlier today so that someone could just
go to this platform, click a button to start a whole computing environment with all the libraries
already set up for them and run your code in that environment. So there is definitely ways for doing
that too. Yeah. Okay, question three. Why is software often treated differently from papers?
Have you experienced that, [name]?
So, I mean, yes, it's getting better, or at least I think it's getting better.
But I'm also now a research software engineer.
I interact with software way more than when I was a researcher,
although even then I was basically doing the same job.
I was also publishing papers.
and I think that at that time
at least in my field it wasn't even normal to publish your code
and that has at least changed
so it is getting better
I have a feeling there is now more journals that at least suggest
to also publish code and data
some may even require it
but the focus still seems on the papers themselves
Yeah. This is partly just an answer or a possible solution to that. Someone will scoop my code
or scoop my research and publish before me. If they were forced to publish the code, then
everybody would, of course, see that they have used your code. So in that sense, this
is a root of a of some of these problems
and he's also mentioned maintenance isn't funded like just putting it out there is often also not
the end of the line but it's still a good step to do even if you don't have time to maintain it
because like in the previous example it might still spark ideas or someone might find this so
useful that they actually take over the maintenance of your code that can also happen so it can be the
end of the line and i have published software that i used for one or two papers never got back to it
and they're just now like i haven't maintained them in five six years and that's like nobody's
losing anything because i don't maintain them if i was still using them i would maintain them and
somebody else has used a part of it then that's nice but yeah i mean you don't lose anything by
not maintaining the code that you publish yeah and i think also nowadays i don't know if people
here in the audience have heard about research software engineers before but it's a coming thing
to the world let's say in the uk and us maybe already a bit or definitely a bit more known
but it's also coming to the nordics now and there is associations like nordic rsc like uk rsc the
society for research software engineering or US RSE and these associations actually
like help with this they try to make it more public that like a lot of the research that is
then published in papers relies on the code and that it's an important part of the research
so that researchers also can get credit for that.
And if that's something you're interested in,
we will have a little bit about this
also in the outro of the workshop on Thursday.
I don't know how hard should I disagree
with someone who has written a comment in the notes.
I mean, it's great that you write comments
and I don't want to sound negative or anything,
but I do want to comment.
So because there is one comment
that essentially says that you need to you don't need to maintain papers and so they are eternal
but you do need to maintain software and um like
we we kind of it does seem like that but um if you publish software and never maintain it then
it's just like a paper right um then it doesn't change anymore and if when you publish the paper
it just it is frozen in time i guess that is that is the difference that this is pointing at right
um so when you publish a paper it's frozen in time and there's nothing to maintain when you
publish a soft piece of software like people do have the expectation that you maintain it
but you can also like make it an archive and essentially freeze it and then it doesn't run
anymore. But it is kind of the same thing as publishing an
algorithm in a paper. So it's not worse than publishing a
paper, in that sense. Yeah, that was kind of an interesting
different point of view. In a way, I feel about this so
differently that it took me a while to understand what it's saying but yeah
it's good to read about the different points of use here yes and thanks for your comment
then let's move on to question four when you find a repository with code or library you would like
to reuse what are the things you look at to decide whether to use it how is it for you I don't know
What is the first thing that you're looking at?
The first thing is, when was it last modified?
If it's more than two years, then I might use it for inspiration,
but I'm not going to use the code.
It's unlikely to work.
The other thing is if it has a license file.
I might not even look at what license it has
as long as it has a license file.
That's the start.
yeah I mean depends on how
restricted if I'm already using
other licenses in the same
same project
same software then you need to make sure
that they're compatible but
if you're just starting
make sure that there's a license
sounds like
you look at
quite specific things
already which are maybe not the first
things that come to mind
for a researcher just looking looking at the code I mean it sounds like you have some experience with
these things like we have here also how easy it is to use how fit for purpose it is for my project
of course those are also very important things like you don't even have to look at something
if it doesn't seem to fit.
And one way of finding out how fit it is
is to read the readme, read the documentation.
And that is also mentioned as one of the points here.
Is there documentation?
Sometimes there might not be documentation.
There is many projects out there where there's only code
and then maybe some comments in the code.
um so that's also a good way of uh where to first look does it have a readme is there
information how do i actually uh get the computing environment up and running
and then also test if that actually works
quick overview yes that's what uh the readmes are very good for
and the license yes you also mentioned that already yeah it's good if um so i guess readme
is the third thing and this is influenced a lot by what the github user interface looks like
like if you start from the top of the page you first see how old the files are and then you see
if there's a license file and then you see the readme so that's i guess one of the reasons i
mentioned them in that order but um but yeah so if the readme actually says that it is doing the
thing that you wanted the software to do then it's useful otherwise yeah of course it might not be
that useful yeah and it that might also have influence on i don't know if your colleague has
been using that code for many years and is happy with how it performs and maybe even the readme is
not that extensive as you would like to have it but you have someone there you can ask questions
about that could also be something to consider and if you are thinking about building on top or
contributing to the code that you find then also like looking for something like a contribution
guide could be good is there a code of conduct and how the violations to it will be handled
are there any open poll requests or have they been lingering for years because if you decide
to put some time in contributing to a code you also of course want someone to actually look at
your suggestions and potentially merge them so yeah that's a good list that you've been writing
here do you have any other um like often even like seeing a pull request that is open means
that someone else has used it and someone else is has found it well useful and is it's clear
enough code that they've been able to modify it which already is a good indication it's a positive
indication even if it has been open for a long time if you look at some of the old codes that
i mentioned that i have published there will be no pull requests there will be no uh no changes
in the code for a while and uh you probably shouldn't use those but yeah um but you can
still see if someone finds the paper um and they're curious on how you implemented that
they can still see like how you did that because you shared the code so in that sense it's not
useless out there no it is not it is not useless yeah
okay let's go back to the lesson material to the very bottom just one moment and
open here yes and are we in social coding yeah in the very bottom
Okay. So above this, you can find some more comments about also the questions that we have asked, if you want to reread some of them.
this last picture here shows also how our work in general as a researcher connects to the work
of others so we have our work here in the middle and we are already looking at other people's stuff
we are looking at their ideas the articles that they have published we might reuse the data or
the software that they have hopefully published and we give them credit we give them acknowledgement
of that by citing by citing them or mentioning in the acknowledgements or in what depending on what
you got from them you might find different ways there and then we want to make that also possible
for others that may find our work and that's really what this lesson is all about on how we
can all work together to like not have to always start from scratch okay and software licenses are
one part of that. And with that, I give over to [name].
Okay, so I just clicked next to get to the next section, which is software licensing.
So yeah, this is essentially licenses are for telling people that they can use your code
that you have shared, and what they can use it for and under what conditions they can use it for.
so at some point in the past
at least we had a version of this
social coding
section of the
workshop
or social coding lesson
that was called software licensing
but we decided to expand it a good bit
but this is still kind of
something
rather important
that
a lot of the infrastructure for
cooperation is built around
so first uh the first point is copyright so whenever you create something you write a piece
of code um you have copyright to that code uh and there's a few different related concepts that
people get mixed up um so copyright applies to creative work it applies to text that you write
um a painting that you make um i mean if you're in the kitchen because you use the kitchen metaphor
if you create a new recipe and write it down that's um it applies to the way you express the
recipe but it doesn't necessarily necessarily apply to the food itself or to the method of
cooking it right so a trademark is related concept but it protects the brand name so if you start a
restaurant and have give it a name then that name would be a trademark a patent is for
technical inventions so methods of doing things um i don't think algorithms can really be patented
but um a specific application of an algorithm or a technical um technical device things like that
um can be patented and then there's copyright so copyright is specifically for creative expression
so it's a bit complex i mean there's a lot of these terms it can be a bit complicated and i
guess the main point is not really to remember all the terms right the main point is to get the
basic idea that there is copyright that you have copyright to your code when you have written the
code and when someone else has written a piece of code they have copyrighted that code
so if you just take someone else's code well that's that's not legal like you you can't just
take it and redistribute it to or make copies of it and distribute it to other people you need some
sort of license copyright also controls derivative work and this is kind of then the
this is the important concept here um so derivative work is using someone else's work
and resampling it or creating something from it.
But importantly, it needs to include something
from the original work.
So say this copyright originally is a legal thing
that has been applied to artwork, paintings and books and so on.
So it's much easier maybe to apply there.
So if you take, for example, a piece of music
that someone else has created
and you speed it up
or just remix parts of it
and reorganize it somehow,
that's derivative work.
So you cannot automatically distribute that.
That doesn't automatically become your work
if you are directly using pieces
of someone else's work.
If you paint a painting
that includes a painting,
like you paint a picture of a room
and there's a painting on the wall
and that painting is the Mona Lisa that you painted into the painting.
That's not derivative work, right?
Does that make any sense?
Hopefully it does.
So, yeah, if you're remixing music, it's clearly derivative work.
Copying a paragraph from someone else's book is not just derivative work.
That's actually just direct copying.
But quoting someone else is not derivative work.
so that
there is
kind of
a boundary
there that
is
it is
fluid
in some
way
okay
so
one
important
thing here
is
you can
do almost
anything
to someone
else's
creative
work
when you
have it
in your
possession
as long
as you
don't
distribute
it
as long
as you
don't
publish
it
so if
it just
stays in
your
home
then
nobody
cares
But if you publish it, or if you publish any derivative work that you've created based on it, then you need to think about licensing.
Okay, so I don't know how much sense my examples made, so maybe we should actually go through the exercise.
It's already in the notes.
Let's see.
So what do you think, our audience?
What do you think of these is derivative work?
And now it goes towards like our actual coding experience
and situations that you actually might be getting into.
So we have download some code from a website and add onto it.
Download some code and use one of the functions in your code.
Changing code you got from somewhere.
Extending code you got from somewhere.
Completely rewriting code you got from somewhere.
Rewriting to a different programming language, linking to libraries, plug-ins and drivers in your code.
Clean room design, so somebody explains you the code, but you have never actually seen it.
And the last one, you read a paper, understand the algorithm and write your own code.
That's awesome, yeah.
So let's give people a moment.
I'm also at the same time thinking through
if there's any concept that's included in these examples
but I didn't mention, but I don't think so.
So, well, we'll come back to it at the end.
Is there anything you would like to comment
while people read through this?
no i think uh so this linked also back to the very beginning when we find out that
what we actually reused didn't have a license on it so we would not be
able to actually redistribute it and here also it was still fine that we like reused their code and
everything but then when it comes to publishing that's where we're getting into the into the
trouble yeah so there's some license slightly more slightly complicated or a little bit
complicated things about code in particular where you don't necessarily always even need oops what
did i do you don't necessarily always need the code to run the program um so for example if you
write a
written Python libraries in this
or written requirements files
a code can depend
well I mean we just did the
the
recipe for a
container so
the container includes a lot
of
software
you have commands that install system
libraries and install things like
entire
probably it installs an entire operating system and then it installs entire programming languages
and interpreters for those languages and so on so that is not derivative work
when you just have a dependency and you include the instruction to install that dependency
that's not derivative work right um so similar to using numpy in my python yes exactly just because
i do import numpy in my python script or import any library in any language script doesn't mean
i need to care about the numpy license yeah so okay let's go through this so the first one
download some code from a website and add on to it and i guess we're assuming that we are then
publishing the code or at least publishing something derived from the code like scientific
research results. So in that case, this is definitely derivative work. You're just taking
someone else's code and use it and make some changes to it. We're just using it, not necessarily,
but making changes to it and publishing those changes is derivative work.
And download some code and use one of the functions in your code. I mean, I guess this
depends on how you do it actually so if you copy the function and put it in your code then it's
definitely derivative work if you call the function and put the name of the library into
your requirements file or dependencies files um then it's not uh derivative work right
so that actually depends um well okay let's go on changing code you got from somewhere
what is this somewhere um yeah i mean just changing the code again not so much but
publishing the code using it in in research and publishing the research um yeah that is derivative
work. Extending code you got from somewhere. So I guess this means adding a function to
the code base. So yeah, I mean this, I would say it's derivative work. I guess you could
extend it by adding a function and then not publish the rest of it, but then it's a dependency.
Okay, completely rewriting the code you got from somewhere. So completely rewriting.
does that mean um so the rest of the examples are kind of well there's some related examples
so completely rewriting code doesn't necessarily mean that it's free from copyright
um so like the next one rewriting code to a different programming language so if you
essentially do it line by line or function by function you reproduce basically the same
programming and in a different language that is derivative work but then well the clean room
design age example so someone describes you how the code works and then you write it in a different
language or even the same language then it is not derivative work because you're just reproducing
the algorithm then again if they describe it in to you in too much detail like line by line what
does this line in the code do um you are actually pretty much getting to derivative work again
okay so that it depends on on what level the rewrite is but if you're just doing the same
interface but otherwise completely like doing it from scratch yourself is not derivative work
if you are rewriting it function by function then it is derivative work
so i skipped over linking to library static or dynamic plugins and drivers
um so i said that um having a dependency is not derivative work but actually um if you are
statically linking and then distributing the binary that is derivative work at least to some
extent like there are licenses that specifically are about being able to link to it as a library
or not being able to do that so it does count as derivative work um but if it's a dynamic library
you're linking dynamically then it is not derivative work so yeah i mean it gets
it does get technical at this point um
uh okay someone is saying i'm contradicting the solution which is great um
So, yeah, so you read the paper, understand the algorithm, write your own code.
So that is not derivative work.
Yeah, so maybe I was giving a bit too much detail and I should actually look at the solutions just to see.
So, yeah, derivative work is A through F.
It's not, is derivative work, so that's pretty clear.
Except I gave a lot, way too much details.
about situations where it might not be then g and i are derivative work or not derivative work that
is so statically linking to a library it is right it is considered derivative work
sorry in general it's also and someone wrote it here also in the later comment in the notes
that it's somehow realistic that you get different answers on who you ask yeah yeah um maybe our
questions or our statements here are also not clear enough to give this clear answer because
what you explained like in this static versus dynamic libraries and if you uh like share the
binaries uh or the source code that makes a difference and that's why it's like important to
like have a little bit of an overview now so that when you are in this situation you at least know
where to look and know where you can find information about the different licenses what
they are actually like are talking about but yeah maybe for the future we could look at
making the statements less ambiguous or then have a little bit more information in the solutions
yeah or i think this is also um these are more discussion points i guess i think like having
even having a solution there may not be maybe we should just make the solution more ambiguous
um maybe it should not be called solution but uh things to note or yeah take home messages
that's a good point okay well but yeah so we also shouldn't get should not get bogged down
the details in which case i'm the wrong person to be doing this but um the so the big picture is
that you should always look for a license and then you should basically do what other people
do in the same situation which is if you're using a python library you add it in the requirements
file you don't need to think about the license people don't think about the license if you're
creating a container and you essentially have the entire Linux operating system in there,
you still don't need to think about the license and you never see people talking about the Linux
license in there. But then if you are actually taking code from someone else, even if you are
rewriting it, you probably should think about the license. Technically, there are situations where
don't have to but it's still maybe better to just like take the license into account.
So yeah that is yeah that should probably be the more big picture answer.
So and on a kind of related note I already actually mentioned all this so
so now related notes here's a big list of different licenses and it's not really useful
to know all of the possible licenses that exist but there is a general sort of um grouping of
licenses starting from the bottom there's public domain licenses which basically say do whatever
you want with my code and you don't need to even mention where you got it so
So this is what you include when you just, like, I don't know,
when you don't care that much, basically, right?
And then there's licenses with a bit more restrictions.
So proprietary licenses are their own thing.
We don't really have examples of them,
but it essentially means you're not allowed to use it.
It's a commercial thing, and somebody owns it.
There might be some conditions where you actually can use it
and you have to kind of then go and understand
what it is that they're doing.
So if you're buying something from someone else, sorry?
Yeah, or you can buy licenses.
Yeah, yeah.
So if you're buying something like a license to MATLAB,
you are getting a proprietary license to use MATLAB, right?
But then on the right, you have open source licenses
and there's the more permissive ones.
the bottom um it's less conditions but usually they're in the open source section um they do
have the condition that you should tell people where you got the code or who did the work
so you should give attribution so kind of like if you know cc by for data um
it essentially so the buy here means um you need to have a sentence that says this was made by
this person right essentially citing essentially attribution and then you have we can go all the
way to strong copy left which means any derivative work has to be also open source it has to be under
a an equally restrictive license and here because i just because i mentioned libraries there is like
this library uh we copyleft licenses where you can use the library but you can't so you can use
the library in like a more permissive way but you um so if you link to it but then um
it's less permissive about using the code directly
so you don't need to know all of these but there is this important thing that where the arrows
are pointing so public domain you can use anywhere this let more permissive ones you can even use in
proprietary codes, but you need to tell people where you got it from. And then the more you go
to the copy left side, the more restrictive it is. So you cannot always code down. You cannot
use a more permissive license if you have included code from a less permissive one.
Yeah, that's where it's important that you look at the license early on,
because the license of a code that you are using
together with your own code
might define which licenses you can actually use yourself
for your own code also.
So one thing I want to mention or show
is this join up licensing assistant.
I should not have closed the original page.
Okay.
let's choose this one for now so yeah this is a
a tool created by i think european union funding it's it includes a big list of licenses
and has a nice description of like you can get quick at the glance see what you can do what you
must do what you cannot do and what it's compatible with you can search for a specific license if you
see it so with mit you can you do a lot of things you must include the copyright and tell people
who made it include license you cannot hold the person liable for writing the code it is
compatible with almost anything and um well interpretation of law is uh i guess something
you need to look at if you are interested and then it is supported well so people understand
what's going on if you use this license and I guess this is an important point by the way
so you should in general use a license that you didn't write yourself a license that people know
so that they understand what's going on so if you write your own license
no matter how clear the legal lease is there's going to be a lawyer somewhere who thinks it's
too big a risk to use so you should use a license that people already know so MIT is
well-known licensed as GPL is a well-known license and so on and this well-known license also you
might have encountered them in github for example it shows it quite nicely then on the top what you
can do and what you have to do with them. Yeah.
So this is helpful for choosing a license, especially when you
already have are using some work that are that is under a
license. We should soon move to a break.
I think we can have five minutes more here. Yeah, go to a break.
And so we already mentioned the licensing assistant.
But when should I add a license?
Yeah, I think we already answered this question, but let's answer it again.
So when do you, when you start a new project and you start working on some code, when do you add a license?
Well, nowadays, I do it as the very first thing.
I either if it's myself only I do that as the very first thing or if it's together with others
to discuss it also very early like what kind of license we want to put that under because then
you don't have to think back or contact old collaborators that might not be working where
they did before anymore or like figure out the whole bureaucracy behind it so you can start
start early on and have the terms clear so yeah one important point is you can add license even
if the code is private so adding a license doesn't make it public because you haven't put it anywhere
so necessarily publicly so yeah you can you can even start adding the license when um
when the code is still like not published anywhere when you're just working privately alone
or with someone but especially when there's a second person working on it then the ownership
becomes complicated so if you then want to add a license you need to ask everyone who has
contributed to the code unless you already have a license and then you the license tells you what
you can do so at least like add a license before you publish it add a license before a second person
works in the code. But preferably, I would just add it immediately.
And related to that, where do you add a license or how? Like, how do you tell people what's
the license of the code?
So the suggestion here is good. What I actually do is I add a single file called license.txt.
But that works as long as you only have one license in the software. If you have a mix
of licenses, you're using things from multiple different sources, then it is a good idea
to have a licenses folder in the root of your project directory, so your Git repository.
And then you add the license files there.
So it may still be just one file, or it may be a couple of files that apply to different
parts of the code.
so especially if you have code and you have data you may need or may want to use different licenses
for the code and the data for example yep okay i think we should slowly move into the break
but there is uh if you scroll down a bit a very long list of a lot of great resources on the topic
So as you noticed, it is a topic where there can be like these different opinions about things, depending on who you ask.
It can completely change something if you change one word in the sentence, like how that relates to the licenses or if it's derivative work or not.
So if you're interested in the topic, look through here and maybe you can find something that works for you.
There's also multiple tools like the JoinUp Licensing Assistant.
But yeah, for the key point, [name], what should people take from this lesson?
Well, you should have a license for your software.
I think a license late can get complicated.
It's good to have it as early as possible.
if you're unsure
I would say
do what other people do
ask your colleagues
what license should you use
and
if you actually have to make the decision
then look at the license selector
and decide
what you think is good
but yeah in general
having any of these licenses is good
yeah remember
that if you don't have a license even if you
put your code out there the default is that no one can like make copies or build onto it which is
what science is about so it's good to keep that in mind and also you might actually have an employer
who tells you which license to use for your code so you don't actually have to worry about it because
your employer might either in the contract or in some other papers tell you if you do code always
use this license so also check that out and now let's go into oh sorry oh well i'm just your
employer is also an owner of the code so you always have two owners actually and um you may
have to ask them if uh things go on for too long without a license so it's better yeah just to put
it as have a license as early as possible and have that conversation early yeah yeah okay the
conversation with everybody who's involved 10 minutes break until 11 past the hour and then
we'll get back with software citation and a little bit about sharing data and then the feedback for
today see you in 10 minutes bye see you bye
Okay we are back from the break and we have some 20 minutes left for today and with this we will
go a little bit into software citation and sharing data.
So, [name], could you switch the screen share to the software citation?
Yes. So this is the front page and we are at the software citation section.
Exactly. So as you can see here on this big picture, we are also looking at the FAIR principles.
And maybe you have heard about them already.
FAIR stands here for Findable, Accessible, Interoperable and Reusable.
And it comes across, or researchers may stumble across it a lot when talking about data.
But it also actually applies to software.
And here in the beginning, we have the question, is putting software on GitHub or GitLab actually publishing?
Does it actually help with making the code findable and accessible?
and we have mentioned it's a very good step to do that it's a very good step to
publish your code on github to have everyone be able to find it but what happens if github is not
around anymore in the future or what happens if someone decides to delete your code from there
then there is no trace of it there's nothing that you can link to and therefore it's also
important to not only put it on github but once you're done or in one of the states of done with
your code for example when you publish a paper that relates to the code also publish publish
the code and make it citable and persistent and that means for example getting a persistent
identifier such a doi which you might also know from manuscripts for your code and services like
Zenodo can give you that and there's also multiple like national services that might provide you
with a DOI for your code and then we're also if you scroll down a little bit we're also talking
about making your software citable so we already talked about that software is on a bit different
level than papers for the academic merit but if you want people to cite it you also need to make
it possible for them to cite it and one way of doing this is adding a so-called citation cff
file which we can see here an example of nowadays even github supports this so if you add a citation
cff file to your github repository it may already suggest like what kind of data should be in there
and it also if a code has a citation cff file you can download for example the bib text citation
for for that code and there's also a little bit further up sorry we're jumping around a little bit
there yeah the checklist for making a release of your software citable and release here meaning
we are in a state that this is now a done thing for now it does not have to be like everything
done but it is something that you have used to create your research outputs for example
it is in a state yeah so this is something like version 1.0 version 1.1 and so on or 0.1 or
and so on exactly when you feel comfortable it does some it does what you want it to do
in a certain way and there might be still open issues there might be still
things you want to fix but it's still it's already usable so what you can check is
we talked about license so how do you have a license assigned
um do you have some metadata for your software for example in a readme or in the citation file
format for example um do you have a clear version number like you can start with 0.1 you can start
with 1.0 um depends on what you want to say with that and it might say also there are different
things to different people? Are all the authors credited? Do you have all the contributors
mentioned somewhere? Did you get a persistent identifier from tools like from services like
Zenodo? And then also the last thing, add a recommended citation. So in this case, you also
then have a little bit of this influence on how other people may cite your software so that they
don't have to worry, oh, I found this nice code here, they have a
paper about it, they have the citation for, I don't know, the
data set they're used. But if you actually want people to cite
your software, then it's good to give them the information that
they need to do that properly. And in the very bottom of this
document there is also the information that if you cite other people what kind of
information is good to cite and there is some resources also in the blue box have you cited
any software yeah no in papers yeah um i mean again it's a part of the job so
um if i'm participating in writing a paper and then it's probably related to some software that
i wrote but um in general also before that we would cite software but there was no specific
standard and i don't think it was really counted anywhere or like it was basically a link for
people to find the software if it was online at that point. But
so yeah, this is like, this is a pretty high standard, but it is
also good. Good to have this sort of checklist and like, a
recommended right way of doing it so that
yeah, people for us. Yeah, and for us as authors, it's fairly
straightforward to write this file. If someone else would need
to find and pick already, I don't know, sometimes the
author's name might be hard to find. So like, the easier you
make it for people, the more likely it is that they actually
cite your site, your software. And yeah, I think like linking,
like you mentioned, having having a link to the web page of
a tool or something is already a good first step. But yeah, the
more you can put there also in citing other people's work, the
better, the easier it is to for those to find the right version
that you also used. For example. Okay, then, let's move on to
sharing data. And we mentioned already in the beginning that we
not go too deep into this right now this is more of a collection for you of places where you can
share data and some of them also integrate for example with github and are also used for sharing
code so you can go through the list and see what either fits you sometimes you may want to keep it
in the country that you are working in. Sometimes you may want to choose a more international forum
or sometimes there's also a domain specific forum where the likelihood of someone randomly finding
your data is higher because people that go there already are looking for something in your domain.
so this is really something where you can then decide um where you want to where you want to
publish it and a really good resource here is what's linked in the very top this re3 data
so there you can find a ginormous list of of all kinds of forums so we've just picked a few here
and put a few also national ones.
And if we have people here who know about some forums,
for example, in, what do we don't have, Germany or other places,
then please let us know so that we can add them here.
Where do you usually publish your data, Jonna?
In Zenodo, basically.
That's essentially the first option.
Of course, it does have a size limit.
So if you are in a domain where the amount of data is large, that doesn't work.
But then, yeah, I guess the more domain-specific,
so it is kind of the same as in publishing papers.
The more general use it is, the more public you want to make it,
and the more specialized it is to a field,
the more you want to find a specific place for that field.
Yeah.
And also here, it's important that you have a license attached to your data
so that everyone knows under what terms they can reuse your data.
There's also specific licenses for databases.
And then there's also some information
in the more towards the bottom of this page about licensing and ai and there might be coming an
update to this page um very soon so keep an eye on it and then also in the further reading list
we put again we mentioned it many times already the touring way oh yeah yeah but i'm at this
program okay sorry so the touring way uh there is a lot of resources there about everything that
we talked about today in both lessons and then also multiple papers and guidelines for fair
software and data as well as well as for example a software quality checklist
list. And with that, I think we can take a look at the notes. I didn't see now any questions.
No, no questions. So there is the feedback section then.
Exactly. We leave some time now for you to provide feedback about today, both sessions
or whichever session you attended?
Was it too fast, too slow, too advanced, too basic?
Do you think you will use what you learned today?
Were there things that you really liked?
Were there things that we should definitely
work on a little bit more before we do
the next iteration of this workshop?
And if you have any other feedback,
we are very happy to hear about this,
because we will continue these workshops
and we always thrive to improve
or try to improve based on your feedback.
So this is very important for us.
And you can also continue asking questions
in the very bottom with that.
So, yeah.
Yeah, I don't have anything more to bring up.
Anything else or...
I'll just keep an eye on any more questions for a few minutes.
Yeah, and now I was so worried about not having the time for the feedback
that we are now done five minutes earlier, but I guess that is okay.
Sorry for running through the software citation part,
but also that is something like check out this citation CFF file, for example,
and see how it's how it can be used especially within github and
when i guess you were also a researcher before you became a research software engineer
Were the topics of today, were they something that you have thought about in your daily life?
You mean as a researcher?
Yeah, as a researcher.
So they did come up for kind of standard reasons.
I mean, it was a while ago.
And like I mentioned, sharing the code was not normal when I started.
so there was this standard argument that if you share your code then the other people will use it
to reduce the results before you get there which is because i was also in a field that well i mean
i was doing high performance computing on really big clusters so it was like after the fact that
now that i think about it it seems like a weird argument because there were like three people in
the world who had the resources to do to um to run that experiment and they had other things to do
so it wasn't really a great argument but but you know that that was the world then
um so there were situations where either the code changed or just like the machine changed and it
didn't reproduce exactly the same result as before and due to the nature of of statistics works
sometimes um you wouldn't get quite the same headline results right so um like i was thinking
about this a few times and in the end we did start publishing the code but at that point i had
already essentially left um left the field and became a research software engineer so like i
happy to see people publish the codes that I had worked on, but it never happened while I was working on them.
I don't think software citations ever came up. We did cite software in the sense of
giving a link in the citation section of the paper, but it wasn't for credit, it was for convenience.
And so, yeah, I mean, things have changed quite a bit since then,
or at least I have the impression that they have.
Although it's been, what has it been, like eight years
since I was a proper researcher?
I say proper researcher because I have had a researcher title since then,
but I wasn't actually a researcher.
I was actually, I guess, a software engineer for the research team.
But yeah.
So, I mean, yeah, these would have prevented several issues.
and i have like i i think a few even few disagreements between research teams
would have been solved if they had published their codes like we would have known why the
results are different um because it seems like they were just doing different things
and thinking they were doing the same things so yeah stuff like that it was not just reproducibility
but just actually like interpretability of the results can depend on actually publishing the code.
I don't know, can you scroll down the notes?
Yes.
So we have people filling in there. Thank you very much. Please keep it coming.
Seems overall, we had the right speed a little bit too fast, maybe
be right level. People will use what they learned today. Licensing discussion. Oh, glad
that you also got something out from the snake make episode. Yeah, please also check all
the exercises that we have there. We try to put always the solutions there so that you
can run through them by yourself.
And then we have to bring your own code sessions
for asking more questions about these things.
And sorry to hear that sometimes the audio did not
go through very well.
And the Python, yes.
It's been difficult to follow as a non-Python user.
That's something also we're still trying to figure out.
I think it has gotten better over the years by adding, at least for self-learning, the different tabs of the different languages.
And you will see more of them also during the next days.
But Python is still our go-to example language for many things.
but it's understandable that now
that we are only demoing the examples
and that as a non-Python user,
it might take a bit longer to get behind
what's actually happening.
Sorry for that.
But yeah, we're over the time already.
So maybe we wrap up here.
We'll still leave the notes open
for you to add more feedback.
I'll say thank you, [name], for teaching today.
And we'll see everyone else tomorrow again.
What comes up tomorrow?
It is Jupiter and documentation lesson.
And I think you are part of the teaching.
Yeah, I will be there.
Tomorrow as well.
Yes.
Okay.
So bye from me for now.
I think I'll be back on Thursday afternoon.
[name] will be back.
tomorrow yeah thanks uh everyone and yeah see you tomorrow bye thank you bye