One.
Hello.
So, welcome back.
Hello, [name].
Thanks.
Good afternoon.
So, I was here yesterday, so I guess I don't need to do much of an introduction.
I just go into Jupyter Notebooks.
And also, you were here in the morning.
Yeah.
If someone is just joining us now, hello, and let's get started.
So, what are we talking about?
We're talking about Jupyter Notebooks and, well, talk a bit about various things.
So, motivations for using Jupyter Notebooks.
Then we will discuss how to launch a notebook.
We'll look at the interface, some of the shortcuts, how to basically make your life easier, at
least when working with notebooks.
And we'll have a look at the first show here, a first computational notebook, so an example
of it.
Then we will have a break.
And then after that, [name] will talk to us, tell us about how to do version control with
notebooks, which is an important thing, I would say.
So it actually matches the content of the previous week, at least.
And then talking about how to share notebooks, right?
So this is also, the sharing notebooks is also a response to one of the questions that
came up yesterday.
What do you do when all of your code is in a notebook and it's not actually
runnable as a program in that way?
Well, let's see.
I think, yeah, so writing code in proper code, like in text files or in
notebooks, well, I mean, it's a thing that we're going to discuss now, I
would say.
So what are the motivations for using Jupyter, Jupyter Notebooks?
And Notebooks in general, there's not just Jupyter, but there's many other kinds.
I think that Jupyter was one of the first widely used implementation of this paradigm called literate programming,
where you mix code with text, with explanations in prose, let's say.
And, but not only, okay, so in the case of Jupyter Notebooks, I think they are used nowadays for like data science-y workflows, I would say, and where you need to, you have some code that produces some pictures, some plots.
So, you want to show the plots, you want to show the code that has produced the plots
for context, and you want also to add some context that you can write, maybe some shows,
some equations and so on.
So, in a sense, you are documenting your code in yet another way compared to what we saw
this morning.
Right?
Yeah.
So, it's like, instead of writing just code, you'd write a lot of documentation with a
code.
so um i mean so Jupyter is also notebooks in general is also a great way of documenting
a library so you can have your documentation written as notebooks and then you have
like examples of calls to your program that produce some result that then the user can just
go and modify and see what happens yeah yeah and i think that as we mentioned you can have Jupyter
notebooks in your documentation your web uh documentation and those notebooks are runnable
so you can even validate them so it's a you can have so it's a it's a way you can basically write
a tutorial make it make sure with jupiter make sure that it runs as it should and yeah so that's
a way you can have actually automated tested documentation so stay tuned for automated
testing for tomorrow uh but yeah so that's why i actually like jupiter notebooks that's what i
the promise that they have yeah and but in general um i think the important
more general uh i think more more general use of that is when you have like a
computational narrative that you want to show so yeah you do some data analysis let's say and you
want to show uh the results with the code and so on and yeah it's uh it's it's great for that
especially if you need to communicate with other people that may not exactly know the code uh or
know maybe not even know how to code but at least they can see the plot and and
yeah and and get insight with from that yeah so there are some there please please yeah so they
The two things below, I guess, are actually pretty much examples of something that's very useful.
You can essentially reproduce or recreate your paper with a notebook and include the code to produce the plots and all of that.
So I could tell the whole story by doing the math as you go.
To connect ourselves with the topics of yesterday, so like reproducible science.
uh yeah that's that's a uh quite a quite a boost to that i would say yep so um yeah so for example
here we have some uh examples of uh some notebooks uh that uh you can uh load in in binder binder
it's a platform that allows you to run some notebooks on the web without actually having
to install anything on your on your site so we will see this later so [name] will show us
how to use binder and yeah so i will not go into into the details here but here yeah to wet your
appetite let's say we have some some different some example of the uh of jupiter notebooks
coming from different uh domains different scientific domains um yeah one about the
gravitational wave discovery nobel prize and other things uh you know so something related to
humanities i would say yes so um there are some use cases that work really well for for us uh for
for jupiter notebooks for example uh yeah so we have a really uh linear workflow okay with the
uh where you need to read data to filter it then to some statistic and plot okay and then you want
You want to experiment with new ideas, testing new libraries and maybe databases or whatever.
And they're also interactive.
So that's one of the great reasons to use it.
I mean, there are also alternatives typically with high-level languages where you can just turn on like the Python interpreter and see something.
But actually, with Jupyter, it's nicer because you can plot in the notebook.
so it's it's a bit it's a easier and more user-friendly um environment to actually do
interactive work in uh yeah and you can share explain code to colleagues for teaching for
teaching i've used jupiter jupiter notebooks a lot um yeah and keeping track of interactive
sessions like a digital lab notebook um and yeah so also yeah when you publish articles you can
actually supplement some information for that to those but there are also some pitfalls right so
these are very nice use cases but there are some some issues there so for example if you don't have
a very um very simple flow of code so if it's not linear um then it can be difficult
if you have a large code base you you may actually use jupyter notebooks as like at the top of this
code base right so you could um you may have some functions that are written in some other
in some files and in some proper source files and then you can import those uh like use those
in the in the notebook but you cannot write your whole code base in uh in jupiter i would say i
mean you can try but it's very difficult and clunky yeah i mean people often go a bit too far
with how much they include in a notebook but yeah um when you start including functions for example
then it's probably already a good idea to start moving those functions into a separate file
So anything that the viewer doesn't need to see probably should not be in the notebook is basically my recommendation, but just personally, basically.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I think that one should safeguard themselves from doing this by making, okay, so you're going to use notebooks, good.
but consider whenever you start a notebook
also to have basically a background infrastructure
where you have a properly set up project for your own language.
Then again, of course,
one thing that notebooks are really good for
is kind of fiddling around with stuff,
trying different things.
Then you might in fact have some cells that you don't run
and some cells that you run in a random order
to get things to work and so on.
So like all of these pitfalls happen for a reason
and sometimes there's a good reason for it.
So it's just that when you publish it
or when you try, when it gets big,
when you start sharing it with someone else,
it is a good idea to clean it up
and make it more presentable.
Yeah, yeah, definitely, definitely.
But yeah, the cool thing is that
they lend themselves for for rapid prototyping. And yeah, so
that's actually quite, quite good. So I would say, let's go
to, to the next episode in the lesson, I think I hope we have
made the case for Jupyter notebooks. And so we can show
the how to use them, let's say, you know, a bit. So it's a bit
the basics but just like everybody um on you know on the same page um i will now switch um to
uh switch my share to to the um to the the terminal okay for a moment okay and yeah so
So here I have a terminal, and here, what should I do here?
So I will create a director called JupyterLabDemo.
LabDemo.
Yeah, create that.
And then what should I do next?
cd JupyterLabDemo.
LabDemo.
And then I will use the conda environment that we discussed about in the previous episodes to start it.
So I first of all activate conda, the right environment, and activate code.
That's how I call that.
And then I should be able just to invoke JupyterLab.
Okay, yep, and now JupyterLab should be after this huge blurb.
So it will open it in the browser window if it finds the browser.
Or you can also, it tells you how to open it in a browser if it doesn't pop up immediately,
but it's a little bit hidden in all of that text that you just saw.
so it's the part that says
starts with HTTP and has this token
equals something
yeah I could copy that
but fortunately in my case
there's no need for that and I have this
beautiful interface
that shows me
some different things
so let me just
copy
the notes
okay
JupyterLab
so how actually does it work so you have seen that in my terminal i have actually started
jupyter lab the server of jupyter lab okay there's a web server attached to it okay
and yeah let's show here i think it's clear from the notes so this is the program i have started
in my in my terminal then in the browser i'm able to to talk to this to interact with the server
and of course there's a user here and then the notebook server
is able to interact with the
file, the notebook file, also with the file system, with everything which is in the
folder where you started the JupyterLab
server and in addition
the notebook server itself will talk to a kernel. The kernel is
not your operating system kernel
But it's like the thing that actually runs the code
that was written in the notebook.
So the kernel is actually running code.
It's interpreting the code.
So in Jupyter, the name actually comes from Julia, Python, and R.
So there's default kernels for Julia, Python, and R.
And there's different kernels.
Well, yeah, there's kernels for those three languages,
but also other languages.
so you could have multiple kernels open at the same time
but I guess we'll just have one for Python
Yeah, so for example
in my case I have a Python 3 kernel
but since I'm a bit weird I have also
a kernel for Bash
which is why I could do this
I'm not going to do this
I guess not
Yeah, so well you have
two different kernels then
And there's also for C++ for example
if some of you is interested in
having c++ developed in a in a in a notebook then you can also use c++ there why not yeah
so um other things we can let's have a look at the interface so um it's better to do this here
because it's a bit uh there's more stuff here i can show so here there's ways to actually create
a new they have a file browser you have a way to create new files uh then here on the
if you want to can actually collapse this this uh um navigation bar on the left
um then here on the right you have uh you have the notebook and you can see the notebook has
different things so you can have like two kinds of cells so the the content of a of a notebook
is organizing cells you have markdown cells which are your pros your content your comments
that contain also formulas for example then you have uh cells uh code cells here for example you
have a cursor and then uh you have also input the the output right so if you're pointing at
something with the mouse and maybe we don't or i don't see your mouse oh okay um yes unfortunately
no my mouse is not visible it's interesting um well but there is um so the gray light gray areas
are code and the um the white areas with text are markdown cells and i guess we can show how
that works yeah so wait a moment uh can i get back to that okay good yes i will show that um
there will be plenty of time to show this and uh yeah so the control here two kinds of cells so
there are markdown cells and uh yeah you have all the features of markdown there so you you can
create headings you can create links you can have um bold italics strike through and also code which
is in line can you see this um so we can if you need to type code but uh in in a in a not in its
own cell but in in the you can do that uh you can have lists with the bullet points or um yeah or
number of the lists equations and so on so these are all the things we discussed
previously we showed previously in you know when you use markdown and then you have code cells
yeah so yeah code cells um and yeah and you you create these two can do kind of things
called cells have also outputs and it goes on like that um yeah so um
so the interface has
the JupyterLab interface has
a little
some shortcuts, something we'll discuss
now about this.
Yeah, those are the kinds of things that it's better
to check when you
when you have
used it for a moment.
But don't wait too long though.
So
okay, so what should we do next?
Should we start this demonstration,
the first computational notebook?
Yes.
So here in the notes,
you have a discussion
on what are the shortcuts.
But yeah, so I'll start
a first computational notebook.
And I think I can get rid of this
so that everything fits.
But yeah, if you want to back your navigation,
you can just click on...
Yeah, so that's a file view.
So it shows the folder that you started Jupyter in.
And, well, I mean, it is very similar to a lot of other file system processes.
But, yeah.
So one thing is you created a new notebook, and the name is untitled by default.
So it's usually a good idea to change that.
Yeah.
So how do I name that?
Let's see if there's an idea in the notes.
Let's say, my first notebook, or how do I do that?
Let's call it, well, we want to call,
so the example here wants to calculate pi
using Monte Carlo method.
So what would be a good name?
Like, wait, F2, pi Monte Carlo?
Yeah, that's fine.
Good.
And now I can close this, so we have space.
Okay.
so um what do i do first of all i want to add a so i change the i want to a markdown cell here
uh so i will press m so that actually that the uh the kind of the cell turns to markdown
so i can type in header so if you don't remember the shortcut there's also this um
there's multiple layers of user interface,
but just outside the notebook,
there is a menu bar that has this save icon
and then a few other icons,
and it includes this text markdown.
So it's currently markdown
because it's showing that the current cell is markdown
and you can change it to code or raw.
Raw is just text.
So it's pure text.
It will not get changed when you run it.
so okay okay um so monte carlo method yeah and now i want to create a new cell
um so i i press usually press shift enter okay so should i maybe i mean i can draw here can you um
or not
wait
can you see
let's go back to the preview
I think you cannot really
I cannot try that
it's all black
yes
we have some weird
issues with the screen share
yeah it's weird sometimes
so do we try
maybe I'll click this again
it sometimes comes back
Do I start sharing?
Do we try resharing?
Maybe it's 25 past already.
I suggested I start sharing.
Okay, well, it's gone again.
It's back.
I suggested I start sharing.
I'll stop sharing then.
Yeah, not quite yet, I guess.
Now I'm sharing something.
Yep. Okay, so I'll stop my share then.
And now the Zoom thing is in the way. Okay, sorry about this, but stuff happens. So is
that okay? So I have activated the CodeDefiner environment and I'm going to run JupyterLab.
there we are so it started in the browser window okay now let's pretend
that I don't have this file already here I'm going to create a new file here okay
why do I have an untitled folder here let's delete that one okay so and I'll
I'll call this pi dot i pi np.
OK.
And we had already the markdown cell.
So I'll just very quickly write some title there.
This, I made a mistake now because I was going to excel.
So this is now a code cell.
And it's actually, it's a comment
because it starts with a hash.
But I want this to be a markdown cell.
So I will go here and change it into markdown.
and then press play to run it okay and the other option to run it is to play press uh control and
enter or at least that's one other option there's other shortcuts as well okay so that inserted
shift shift enter doesn't and control enter maybe create a cell okay shift enter creates a cell
below it okay so uh what do we do then so um and i'm i'm guessing we do want to actually make some
calculations well first we have a list of relevant formulas for this calculation
so that people can follow along what we're doing
I wonder if I should
just
you can reopen the cell by double clicking
you can show some formulas there
which can be useful
I'll just copy paste
so that I don't spend too much time
writing it out
but it's Markdown
which you have already used
in the notes
and in the documentation session.
Okay, so here we are.
Beautiful rendered.
We also have an image visualizing the content.
So this is kind of fun.
You can include an image either from the file system.
So I'm going to go create another Markdown cell.
But here we are actually including it from GitHub.
just the
you can navigate to the file in GitHub
and get the raw
open the raw image
and then get the link
to get something like this
okay
so that's fun
but let's get to coding
so
first we need to
import some things
And I keep pressing Shift-Enter to get a new line,
but that doesn't work.
I just keep creating new cells.
I need to get used to this again.
So import random.
We're going to need random for random numbers.
Just enter, not Shift-Enter.
Okay.
And for plotting, we're going to need matplotlib.
Iplot, actually.
From matplotlib.
um we probably shouldn't spend too much time on the code itself it's uh i mean the basic idea
yes but um like the code is in python and uh you like the language shouldn't be necessary
it shouldn't be necessary to understand the language or use python specifically there's uh
yeah so the idea is that the idea is that you compute pi because pi is going to be
close to pi divided by four is going to be the probability that a dart thrown in a square is
also in the uh in the circle circle yeah or yeah similar or equivalent multiplied by some number i
think yeah yeah yeah so we were
calculating the area of the circle by
randomly throwing randomly picking
numbers and deciding if they are inside
the circle or not so first let's pick a
number of throws
it says num points equal 1000
okay and run that and then we can write a function that
throws the dots which means picks two random numbers an x
coordinate and a y coordinate okay so
actually the function
throws a dot
right
okay
instead of okay
so
initialize well actually yeah we
throw dots because we are
we're not doing a function
we're doing a follow up at this point
yeah I was reading
incorrectly so
um here we go so we make a list of points um and we'll count how many times it hits inside the
circle so at the start this is zero then we'll do a for loop for and we don't really care about
the index but we want um
do it number of points times so this is a follow-up if you know a different language
don't worry about the syntax it is a bit weird python okay but we'll get an x coordinate and
y coordinate from random so that means if there is a random contains a function called random
we will be calling it twice
okay, to get two random numbers
and then
we need to check if they are inside
the
so how do you check if it's inside
a circle
the Pythagorean
theorem
so we'll do x squared
plus y squared
and the size of the circle
is one
so we're picking, here we're picking
from between zero and one
So the square is from 0 to 1.
I'm checking quickly if people can actually see me.
And so the square is between 0 and 1.
And so the radius of the circle is also 1.
And 1 squared is 1.
So we don't even have to square it.
So if it is inside the circle, then we say hits.
Add 1 to hits.
and in any case
we actually want to keep track of the points
so we'll append
the x y coordinate
and
we'll want to mark
whether it hit or not
so we could say
true or false here but actually
just for the plot
we want the points inside to be red
and points outside to be blue
so
So I'll go a bit fast here
and immediately mark it as red.
Because we've already stored the number of hits here.
Okay.
And then if it didn't hit,
we'll want to still add the point,
but we will make it blue.
Yeah.
I think you need another bracket there.
Yes, I do.
Yeah.
Because you are appending a tuple to the points.
Yeah, it's a tuple.
Okay.
So we have already run that.
Now, if I want to check what happened,
I could just say hits.
So hits, there were 765 hits.
I could say points, and that would be a long list.
Okay.
So...
Wow.
Yeah.
So it's nice. You can just check what the variables contain. This is why it's useful
for rapid development. But let's actually make it more of a narrative. So let's see
what the result looks like. So we'll make a plot. So we'll take the x and y coordinates and colors
and extract that from this. So this is again, don't mind syntax. It's weird.
it's though let's say what it's actually doing so extract the coordinates and
colors in this case up you're getting a it's a single list for all the X the X's
or another list for all the Y's and then at least for the colors yeah exactly
okay and then we define the figure dimension so define what the figure
looks like and this is also plots this is just how matplotlib works so
So again, I'll just skim past it.
What is important here is that you
can do this plotting thing inside JupyterLab
or inside Jupyter, and it will work out.
0 is not a good size.
I want to go with 6, I think.
OK, inches and, yeah, 6 inches.
I don't know why we use inches here, just standard.
Okay. I mean, in general, in plotting, why do people use inches?
Well, that's just the standard.
So we plot the results.
We did get this x variable here.
Axes.
Not an axe for chopping, but axes.
We'll make a scatter plot with the x coordinates and the y coordinates listed
and then C for colors.
So we need to set C equals colors here.
Okay.
And this should now, instead of this long list, produce a plot.
Let's see if it's pretty.
Okay.
There's an error.
That's a little.
Yeah.
So you called fix.
So if you go a line above, you.
There's a fix.
Okay.
So it's not a fix.
It's a figure.
Okay.
All right.
So here we have a plot.
So we have some points outside and some points inside the circle.
Okay.
Now, that's not the actual result, though.
This shows the method we used, but the actual result is the value of pi.
So that's, if you look at the equation here, it's the number of hits divided by the area,
which in this case, the area of the square is actually two times r squared.
so it's 4
and
that's
not, is that correct?
Well I mean
the area of this square is 1
so I guess this S actually means the area
of this square
and the C is the number of
the fraction of the hits
Yeah I think
this applies for the quadrant
or for the full
Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Well, I mean, we'll do it correctly here. Anyway, I'm sure if I'm reading that correctly. So the number of hits divided by the number of points is the fraction of hits. And then the pi actually is just four times the fraction, which I guess is what was written down there.
so I'm just somehow confused
fractions does not exist because
I added an extra s there
okay
you see here how errors happen right
so
how errors are displayed
yeah that's maybe I should
do that again just for a moment
yeah so I mean
the colors make it actually easier to
figure out what's going on but it's on line
two of the previous
cell 13
input cell 13, which is this one.
This is an output cell, or this is actually an error.
This is an output, this image here.
And, well, there's also markdown cells,
which I think also count as input.
Okay, well, let's get rid of the error.
So 3.06, I mean, it's three, it's close enough.
We can get some more points if we want to, and run again.
so one thing I do want to show because it was something at least I use very often if you're
making a narrative from top to bottom you probably want to run the cell from top to bottom
so here's restart the kernel and run all cells this is also useful to do before publishing
if I just make sure that if you run everything in the original or in the written down order
then it should work okay so it is running all of the cells now this is so many points uh the image
is just an image of a circle at this point and we have slightly uh a slightly better estimate of pi
here okay yeah but important here that if you change one parameter you need to i mean uh yeah
you need to run all the cells again, to be safe. You can be clever, try to be clever,
and rerun only the ones that are, but yeah. So what I could do is change this here,
run here, and then just try to go to this one, but now I get a completely incorrect result,
because I didn't change the stuff in the middle, I just changed this variable.
this didn't run and this didn't run um so if i run that one now i think i will get the correct
result but the image is not quite correct so at this point i'm confused i'm going to rerun
everything it's uh often better to rerun everything often than it is to like try to figure things out
yeah
okay
that's the example
anything else we want to
bring up here
check if there are
any questions in the notes
but it doesn't seem so
yeah but yeah I think one
comment in the notes is about
Marimo notebooks
and yeah so there's a number
of other
like jupiter alternatives that for example marimo i think it's for python but also pluto for julia
instead and these are a kind of notebook that is that compared to jupiter they have something
more so they are reactive so if you change for example in in those notebooks if you change one
cell if you change like uh num points then all the other cells that depend on that would actually
run. And this is, I think, can be useful. Of course, if you have cells that take very long
to run, you may be careful about doing that. But still, it's like a little improvement over
Jupyter from the point of view of reactivity. From other things, I think there's a lot of tooling
around Jupyter Notebooks
that we are going to briefly
skim over.
Which is...
Yeah.
Which unfortunately doesn't apply to
other kinds of notebooks.
So, yeah. But
that's why I think we teach Jupyter Notebooks.
I don't know.
Should we have a break now?
Yeah. So, I mean,
R has its own
sort of infrastructure
and R Markdown has
most of the features
so you can do
things like well I mean
it has most of the same features that we haven't
actually talked about yet and Pluto
is also kind of designed to work well
with
version control and stuff like that
but Jupiter still has
the most mature environment
because it is the oldest of
these examples
yeah the validation
tools there's a lot of stuff there
which is cool
anyway shall we have a break now
let's take a break now
so we'll do
10 minutes until
13.52
we'll write that in the notes
are you writing it down
someone is doing it
the invisible hand
thanks okay so see you at 53 past or 7 to right bye bye
Okay. Hello. Welcome back. I hope you had a good break and took some time to walk around.
so
next we'll go
into how you
share notebooks
how you include them
in your software
and just have other people
use them as well
and that starts with
version control
so
the notebooks
themselves especially
maybe I'll just show the notebook again
so this one includes an image
so it can be
it's not actually text content
and git is designed for text
so if you use it with just the default stuff
it can get a bit weird
but I mean it's not that bad
it does work
so there's a few different ways
of making it look better
so
there's the
nbdime extension for
jupiter and jupiter lab which is very
useful it allows you to
more directly compare
and merge notebooks
so
so it
is aware of the cell structure
here and it can tell you
what has actually changed in the cells
in the notebook
and doesn't
doesn't point out every change in
outputs necessarily
and so on so
that's useful
there's also other options
also for images if you have plots
then they're
saved in like a blob or text
base64 in the
notebook file and yeah
with nbdime you can actually have a nicer
yeah so we have
people show that in a moment
well maybe it's better to
just list the options from here.
So, I mean, there is also this JupyterLab Git
and JupyterLab GitHub extensions,
which are useful depending on what you use.
Here we'll show nbdime
and also show some things on GitHub.
So, yeah, so the first thing, I guess,
we'll just show what happens when things go wrong.
So here's an image I can actually open this pull request
or a comparison between two different versions
of a code in GitHub.
Let's see what it looks like.
Well, it doesn't even want to show it to me.
It's a large diff.
So we've changed some things in the notebook
and then there's this huge blob of text.
which is actually the image and the image is a bit different in some part of the image
somewhere is a bit different and it's very hard to see what's going on there's also this
text output cell here that's slightly changed so there is an option in github that you can enable
It's been a, what do they actually call them, feature preview.
I think it's been a feature preview for several years now.
But you go to the feature preview from this preferences section and enable rich Jupyter notebook diffs.
Okay.
And then if you reload the page, it should look very different.
let's see if it works okay so this line in the cell has changed this line has
changed and this image has changed so that is a lot better and well this
output has changed here you can also go back to the original source code which
is for this part it works but for the image it's not very useful okay so maybe
I will close this one okay and there is a similar well there is an interface for git in
JupyterLab itself and that is this nbdime extension it's already installed in the code
refinery environment but if you're creating a new python environment that includes Jupyter then
or well any other environment that includes Jupyter you'll have to include it for it to
work. Okay so we already I think kind of showed the the actual text that the notebook contains
maybe we should do that again. So here's the the file browser view and I think I should be able to
open it from here yeah open so this is actually a json file which is a text file that contains these
cells this is even a bit too stylized maybe the maybe i can open it with the
text editor so this is the actual text content of this file that we just wrote here
so it is text and it is something that you can handle with git but well here's the image again
um yeah and all of these outputs get uh gets changed every time you run the cell so
i mean there's just a nicer way of doing it it's not it's not that bad to start with the image
part is pretty bad but so here's the nbdime extension this is the button that gets added
when you install nbdime and there you can first of all i need to initialize the repost a repository
here because i haven't done that yet i don't have a git repository so i will initialize a
a Git repository in this. And now I have some untracked files, which is...
I don't actually know what these checkpoint files are. I assume it's because I have
JupyterLab open. But this is the actual file, pi.ipynb. And this is the example I downloaded
previously because um i wasn't planning to actually demonstrate this part so so now you stage you
stage the the yeah so i staged the pi dot ipy nb by clicking the plus button so what happens if you
change uh if you change the that file pi dot wine so if you change that because now it's staged
right so if you change that yeah i was planning to make a change so now it shows up in changed
I can view the diff. Maybe I should write this view here. So it's mostly the same.
It should show me the...
So this is the line that I changed. What is going on? Maybe it's showing me the diff to the commit.
that would be a bit annoying
leave this file
have you changed the file?
have you saved it?
I changed this and saved it
so now it's back to the original
and now it's showing some changes
I guess you need to save it
because if you don't save it
then the kit doesn't see it at all
but yeah
I think we found
an issue
with np time. I've never actually tried to do that. So if I just stage the file and commit
first and then try it, maybe that will work. Let's see. Okay. So I'll just call this an initial
commit. Traditional commit message. And then what should we change? Let's change this color
from red to orange okay now you already see that there's some change and we can go see a diff maybe
it will work this time okay so now okay a bit more space for it so you see that the line has changed
but actually um i have only changed this line i haven't changed the the actual color so let's go
and you need to rerun so now we change the image as well
and we can now again go here and see what the difference is
okay did i save it no i did not let's go and save it okay yeah
okay and
okay so it didn't show any new differences but now
that i click this button again now it shows some differences um so i had to close it and reopen
and now it's showing a difference in this image and in the outputs outputs uh let's remove that
there so um the outputs have changed because i re-ran the code and it's random so it's going
to be different every time okay so now yeah we can kind of nicely see the difference here
I haven't enabled this in the command line so if you are using git in the command line
I will need to activate whoops activate the code refinery repository
I should have thought about this before I started okay contact with code refinery all right here we
And now if I do git diff here, it's going to show me that the JSON file, so this, it's
relatively structured, relatively nice to read. I don't really care about the execution counts
for the cells or this, whatever this is. I do care about the image being different, but
this is not what I want to see. So you can also go to, well, I mean, go to the notes and
copy paste this or get it in some different way. So it's, you change the git config and
include nbdime in there. Okay, that looked weird.
i was moving to a different window um to get the terminal window back and that looked a little bit
weird on the screen share okay so now i can do a git diff again and let's see what it looks like
is it different it is a bit different so now it's um it's not really showing me the image
showing me that it's different which is better right that's like um how much can you do in a
terminal. But it is definitely better this way. Okay,
much less, much less use less information in the difficulty.
Yeah. Okay, so but we should really move on actually. I will
commit this. Okay, orange, change the orange. Oh, I will
need to first stage this one
and commit. Okay,
so let's move to
sharing notebooks now.
So we talked about
version control, and
again, there's different ways of sharing a notebook.
So there's
some
free, some commercial alternatives
where you can...
Let me back up a second.
The big thing here is
if you share
something online, just as a web
page that people can see they will not be able to run the code but there's plenty of ways to do
that so you can take this notebook and turn it into a essentially a text that includes this
website that includes the text and then includes also these code blocks and images and that's
really nice that's really good for generating documentation for example but you won't be able
to run the code from inside that website.
Then there's plenty of options
for creating a runnable shared document in some way.
And that does mean that you need a server
that actually runs the code.
So we'll show you how Binder works as a demonstration.
It's a really nice way of doing it.
And that allows people to actually run the code.
But there's other options.
And this NB viewer, this renderer, NB Sphinx, they allow you to turn the notebook into a
website. So not run the code, but otherwise great. So one option, save and export as
HTML, later markdown, all kinds of options. And then there's these platforms that allow you to
actually run it on the cloud and well and there's binder okay so first let's
ah sorry okay yes i was confused for a moment this is the next part
so uh let's go into the binder section but to do that we'll need to get the
notebook actually online so now it is only here only locally on my my laptop
up. So I think we'll actually need to create a new GitHub repository. That is actually
the first step in the exercise. So that's good. So here's a nice link, github.com slash
new, and that will create a new repository. I didn't want to actually close the website.
Okay. Yeah. All right. So we will not use a template. What should we call it? CR demo
PyCalc is written correctly. Okay, so this is a it's not actually in short
and memorable in any way but it is very descriptive of what this is and
something I will delete after sometime after this this course. So I'm going to
make it public so that everybody can access it. And importantly, I'm not going to generate a
readme file. No, I am going to generate a readme file. And then I'm going to, I guess, clone and
add the notebook. Okay, let's see where this goes. So I will add a readme file. It is a nice thing to
it's just that I already have a GitHub repository. No, I already have a Git repository, so
I'm not going to use the same one, I suppose. Okay, so let's do that. Why not? Let's also
add a license since we're at it. Make it MIT, for example. We talked about licenses yesterday.
It's good to have a license early, right? Okay, and you can make it more restrictive
later if you want to um here we are so we have a license and a readme file the readme file is
pretty much empty okay so so now you need to add your your code somehow right yeah so now i'm going
to actually just add the notebook and not push from the repository and i guess that the reason
for that is that in the first demonstration we did not make it a git repository but I did
actually make it a git repository already so well anyway let's go with the exercise as it's described
so I will go from here upload files
and I guess choose files then is good. Where is it? Okay I'm going to have
to move my windows a little bit just to see. Source, Code Refinery, Jupyter, here we go.
So, okay, there's pi.ipinb, okay.
And then now I need to give a commit message to add the notebook.
Okay, commit directly to the main branch, yes.
Okay, now there is another thing that I will need to do.
before the requirements yeah so in order for so we're going to run this on binder but in order
for it to know or to be able to run it it needs to know what what other python packages i need
so i'm going to add another file i'm going to call it requirements dot txt
and do we have a list of this if this is so if you switch to the plot lib 3.4.1
um yeah what i was going for is um so if you use python it will recognize it from this requirements
or txt file if you want r it will you will need to add a runtime runtime.txt and it will recognize
that you are using r if you have this file you can even have both at the same time
so what i'm going to do is add a requirements.txt and add matplotlib
and i'm going to use a specific version just because it is the version that i know it works with
Is it good for reproducibility?
Yeah. So in a moment, you will see that Binder actually creates a container to run this code in.
So this will work pretty well. Okay, create requirements of TXT actually is very descriptive
here. It's pretty much, I mean, I could say, describe dependencies or something, but
This is good. Okay. Now the next thing we want to do is go to mybinder.org and it opens this website.
And actually I'm going to switch over back to the repository and just copy the name of the repository.
So that's my GitHub username and then the repository's specific name. And that goes here.
Now, the name of the notebook is pi.i.pi.nb.
Okay, I'll just put that there.
pi.i.pi.nb.
Okay, so IPython notebook and from the main branch.
So this is a file that it opens to the user by default,
but you can leave it empty and then it will just open a file browser instead.
Okay so this actually constructs a web address you need to go to to launch the
launch the website. So we could click launch here but actually let's add a batch to the readme file.
So we'll have a markdown file and it has this address to this binder logo
and then the address that opens the binder as a link. So I'll just copy that.
This button is for copying and change the readme file.
Okay, so this will add an image that allows people to quickly
recognize that this repository works in Binder and that you can open it. So
Let's save that file. I should do it with the mouse. So commit changes. Add
binder button to readme. Okay and let's again commit directly to the main branch.
And there we are. So actually let's go back to the main page of the repository.
So now we can actually launch the binder page from here.
So I will go and close this one and hope that this works.
Okay.
It takes a while to build a new container.
It's actually waiting is done.
So we already have a virtual machine that we are running stuff on,
but we are now waiting for the container to finish building so that we can actually run
JupyterLab inside that container. Okay.
What else should we go through while we wait?
So I did all of these instructions I think.
Yeah, so people can now go and look at my work in the cloud.
If this finishes correctly, if it doesn't, then we'll fix it.
Yeah, well, let's go on while it's doing its thing.
So yeah, you can go even better, of course, get a DOI and launch a full version of your software.
Should we, how much time do we have and how much stuff do we have to go?
So, oh, we have plenty of time, I think.
so this exercise is about
sharing
doing it yourself
which you can definitely do
after this session
and this is about playing around
with this inequality repository
which we
we talked about in the first
section
if I was
this fast, then what did I skip over? And so if anything is
unclear, please ask questions. And if you want to do this
yourself, you can follow the steps, try to do the same steps
that I did. And feel free to ask questions then later. I mean,
yeah, a good amount of the time usually in this exercise is
waiting for binder so we can have a chat about other stuff as we wait
i have actually a remark so regarding tooling for for jupiter uh so i there's one one uh like
one python program called nb val which can be used to validate your jupyter notebook so if you
have a jupyter notebook and you want to make sure that you have run all the cells and you want to
test it for example test if the output is the same in different environments or you know even
after you have changed some underlying code that sits somewhere else you can use this tool and be
well and and get the you know just an idea whether or not anything has changed and of course in this
particular case with the calculation of pi it would always give you an error
because it's random yeah if you are comparing the value of pi to the correct value of pi then
it will not be or if you yeah or if you are correcting comparing two random values of pi
you may have a problem yeah so here possibly for reproducibility you would have to set to set the
seed of the random number generator oh right okay so if it's yeah yeah but in any case yeah so
comparing two notebooks maybe um you know maybe so you need to be careful there because there
There are some things that perhaps there can be some differences
you don't actually care about.
Some differences instead are significant
and may mean that there is a problem.
Some instead not.
So, yeah.
But I think it's a valuable tool.
Anyway, finally.
Yeah, that sounds useful.
And, I mean, tomorrow we'll...
Testing is tomorrow, right?
But finally loaded.
We'll also talk about how you compare, for example, random values.
That's one of the things.
and automated testing in general.
So, okay.
Yeah, it's loaded and it shows exactly the same.
It should be the lab interface.
Oh, except without the Git interface.
And I can run everything in here.
I can also change the numbers and run them.
So I get a different result.
Ooh, that's a problem.
Okay, let's finish running.
So yeah, with 100 points, you don't get very close.
We have a two new version of NumPy compared to Matplotlib.
So Matplotlib is trying to use something from NumPy 2.
so either I need to set a newer version of NumPy
a newer version of Matplotlib or a different version
or I need to
use a different version of NumPy
I will not have time to demonstrate that now
I'm almost sure
Is there a possibility in Binder
to set up a container and tell it
use this container
instead of just saying a requirement file?
Oh, I don't know.
I mean, I would assume so, but I don't know.
That also sounds like specialized enough that it's,
well, we can figure that out later,
and if somebody else wants to know, just ask.
There's also often when you can run some terminal commands,
bash commands, for example,
Okay, so can I do pip install upgrade matplotlib?
Oh, oh right, okay, there's a space there.
There shouldn't be a space.
Yeah, so this is one thing you can do in Jupyter.
You can try to get it to work.
And I guess I need to restart the kernel.
So is that something I can do from here?
oh actually that is this button, restart the kernel and rerun all cells.
So we'll see if the error goes away, this is just trying to fix some small thing.
Okay all right here we are, now it runs. So to fix this I would go to the repository then and
tell it to use a newer version of Matplotlib.
Okay. Next, we have the feedback section again in the notes. Let's see, where do I have the
notes open? Yeah. So let's go there. Unless you have more ideas. So I think I'm for feedback.
so yeah please fill in any feedback you have
and
ask if you have any questions
we have a few more minutes
in the schedule
so we can respond to any questions
but otherwise just
have a nice day
So, maybe there are some questions we can go back to and try to go on.
Hello.
Hey.
so i think the question about jupyter notebooks and uh uh version control uh yeah i think we
recover that i hope i hope that the person who wrote that is satisfied
um i think that sometimes uh if a jupyter notebook is too long it doesn't show on gitlab
but you may actually so it may take time but if you if you press on the button show anyway
it should show it although it could be that if if it contains images and the images are
are too large and the notebook is displayed as like literally so not as image but as a as a
json file then yeah you get very large large uh files and and there won't be any interesting
information for you to visualize there and yeah i think there's a question about reactive notebooks
and so what do people think about reactive notebooks i think we mentioned this already
uh the one thing about this uh about reactive notebooks is that they do not contain the output
so for example uh marimo and also bruto do not contain the output and they are just playing
python files so they are easier to version control but on the other hand yeah you you miss the
computational narrative there so you don't have the the outputs so it's like a very different
kind of
tool I
would say
what are
your opinions
on this
I mean
you can
with
reactive
notebooks
for example
with Pluto
you can
still export
it as
an HTML
file
export it
as a
website
and then
it will
contain the
outputs as
well
it essentially
is just
running the
notebook and
including the
outputs
but the
source code
for the
notebook
doesn't
contain the
outputs like in um the source code for a uh a jupiter notebook is well it is this change in
file that i showed and it did contain like the full image as this huge blob of text um so it
contains all of the outputs there so it's a different philosophy yeah one could take this
this note this kind of reactive notebooks and execute them and add a like a generate add those
the content of that to your documentation site or to your GitHub pages, let's say.
One could do that to make sure that content is visible somehow, so that the results are visible.
There's a question about the Git connection in JupyterLab,
is it whether it's similar to git in vs code uh yeah looks like it it looks very similar
um we saw a couple of glitches maybe that wouldn't happen in vs code but um yeah i mean
the nbdime thing is just meant for working with jupyterlab and jupyter notebooks
so the version control system
that's included in VS Code
or essentially it is a user interface for Git
it is fully general
Yeah, I think there's possibly a distinction
that if I remember correctly
the Git source control for VS Code
looks at the state of the files you have in your editor
not at the state of the files you have saved on disk so this is yet another problem so sometimes
that there can be some some issues there because git in vs code looks at uh the code you have in
your editor and it can be different from the one that you have on disk so if i understand correctly
here nbdime and the extension on in jupyter lab looks at the state of the notebook as it is saved
on disk. So then
there was that problem.
It should always look at what's saved
on disk.
Okay, I have to try that.
At least there's a way
of getting VS Code to look only
at what's saved on disk.
But yeah, it depends
on what you're used to.
What is more useful?
Yeah, just saying. This kind of
git extensions uh git integrations they they can get a little uh weird in when because of this
additional state that they have the state of the fight in the editor or and the state of the file
and this plus all the other things that that git has so all the you know the stage version and so
one so it's you know it gets better it is already uh complicated enough with the um
separate staged committed and on this version and well then you do also have the version in
your that you have currently open if you haven't saved it so yeah there's a comment for the days
lesson that it's missing hands-on activities and yeah we know of this problem so in previous years
we did like all the exercises you would see here we actually did together but since people have
different backgrounds like we have mostly them in python some in other languages but
it was basically too much and if we gave enough time for everyone to do the exercises
we basically spend all the time on the exercises so instead we can look at it like this so we have
the demos and the exercises are there for you to do later on your own time if you would like
and maybe someday we can go back to trying the exercises but with the difficulties of
installing stuff and managing everything, it hasn't worked that well.
Yeah.
I mean, if you do want to try the exercises, we do have the notes as a way of asking questions.
So if you have problems when you try them, you can always ask questions in the notes.
And yeah, you don't exactly have to follow us when we do it.
you can just go ahead and start doing them
and turn off the stream or do it now after the stream.
But the, would the, so I think for the documentation,
I see how the bring your own code sessions
would actually work because yeah, you have maybe some,
but possibly also for Jupyter Notebooks,
maybe if you're interested in this
and how to integrate Jupyter Notebooks
with your documentation or so,
So the bring your own code sessions may be useful there.
So you would apply what you've seen today,
but directly to what you're working on
instead of some artificial exercises,
which still would be nice,
but maybe you can make a longer jump
and go directly to applying these things to something new.
Because it's also nice that people are saying,
okay i will use what i learned today that's quite yeah uh that's quite a number of o's there
which is pleasant i think
yeah um and if you have anyone locally you can talk to you can basically show them exercises
exercises and say i would like to do this can you be my mentor and they can give you the starting
advice like let you know if it's the right thing to do for your own environment you do it and you
ask them for help and if you're at any of the organizations where any instructor of this
workshop has been we're around to help you unfortunately we can't help everyone in the
world because well you know we're a few people and this is an open course but
yeah i guess you know how that works
let's see
and tomorrow yes if you can scroll up a little bit there's some news for tomorrow there yeah
so tomorrow we have two lessons one is testing which is a very practical thing so it would have
some really nice exercises if we were giving you time to do them but we sort of combine the version
control the github and many other things and show you how you can use github to test your code on
every push you do and integrate that with pull requests and so on so it's really cool it's a
quite good um thing to do and i think that if you're just following along you can still get
a lot of it even without the exercises that's easy to do later and then after that is modular
code development and this used to be a sort of discussion thing now you get to see two instructors
come together and they will start with a basic idea make a code in a jupyter notebook and slowly
make it more and more modular add function split it to files and eventually end up with a program
that can be run from a command line and there's a lot of general discussion here
so to say like it's really how would you say it
it is
if you ask me it really puts everything together and shows a realistic process
from chaotic initial scientific scripts to something that's reusable
yeah okay any other news for tomorrow
or should we get going
yeah looking forward to tomorrow actually we've been in the background
yeah okay great so see you all later then please keep filling out the feedback
at all thanks so all right see you later bye see you