and welcome back
Hello. So, yeah, we have some questions in the notes to get started.
So essentially this, the modular coding session is a demonstration and essentially a pair coding demonstration.
And it's also a way of wrapping up and tying everything together.
So it should touch on most things that we have talked about during this entire workshop.
So we have a few different questions in the notes.
It would be great if you could answer at least the first three.
And then we'll get going once we have a few answers to talk through.
Well, we can already start with essentially our answers to the questions.
Yeah, why not?
So I'll start with what does modular code development mean for you?
So for me, it's if you try to structure your code such that you actually have different parts that are responsible for different things
and make clear distinctions as to okay this is something this is a logical logical pack that
belongs together and therefore it's executed in one function um this is a logical group of things
so this is one package and so on that's what module development is about for me yeah so we um
started with version control and we went essentially like we went all the way to
sharing it and putting things online collaborating with sharing code changing someone else's code and
so on um and to me the best although the most um clear definition is when you can actually
take a piece of code maybe maybe an a feature you have create a function you have written
and actually contribute it back to the original software so the original code or even even better
take it and contribute it to some other code base in a way that makes sense so then that
if you can do that then the original that the code base you're contributing to is modular
in the sense that you can put a module in and it works.
And also your starting point is modular
because there is some module that you can pick up
and put somewhere else.
It becomes usable in many different situations.
And this, of course, it happens on different levels.
It could be a function, but it could also be an entire,
well, a Python module, which means a file
or a library in
C
or C++ and so on.
This is also what you
have started writing there
essentially.
The general idea seems to be
pretty similar.
This also
has something to do with unit testing in that
a unit that you can test is
a module
if it doesn't have too many side effects.
A function you can test
is a module that you can
also then plug out
in some way.
Okay, best practices
to arrive at
a well-structured modular code
in your favorite programming
language. I don't actually know what my favorite language
is.
To me, it's
designing well
as in
if I want to have a certain
functionality uh what parts of this functionality are actually reusable what parts of these
functionality are specific to exactly what this is going to do and then separate things that are
more that i think are more generally usable and things that are well more more more specific to
this one task also potentially depending again on the project if it's large enough
thinking about how could someone else provide an alternative approach to some parts of my code
and at which point i automatically have to think okay i might need to have an interface or
something and this inter implementation of this interface that's one piece so i can define the
interface and then put in an implementation someone else could define a different implementation for
the same thing that automatically creates modular code because things can be replaced easily
essentially you surround the module with an interface so yeah if you have a defined interface
what is inside can change and so it is plug and play so one very practical thing um that i at
least when i was like writing mostly c code um in research i saw people use global values global
references so you define some something you define a thing that needs to be accessible essentially
everywhere in the code and you make it globally accessible which means it's not explicitly there
in the arguments of a function for example so like in simulation programs you often do this for
like the world the the 3d world that you are simulating so that kind of thing make means
you cannot take the function
and put it in a different code, right?
Whereas if it's explicit,
if you put the parameter directly
into the function definition,
then you can put it in anywhere
as long as they know to provide that parameter correctly.
So explicit is better than implicit in that sense.
That's, and yeah,
So basically, yeah, writing small functions with a specific task
and then making their interactions explicit.
Have everything that goes into the function be visible in the function definition
and everything that it does should also be visible
either by looking at the return value or looking at the comments.
What I also, that's partly in the answers here as well.
So try not to create a large script that you're running.
Because as soon as there is really computational functionality
in the run script that you have
that could be handled in a function,
it becomes potentially, as it's mentioned here,
difficult later on to refactor this into a function
or to refactor your code such that
this calls a function
and
the sooner you say
this is not about
the individual actions
of my script anymore
this is about
handling what I'm doing
this can normally go into
a function
so if I have something like
a script that I'm
running, this is commonly
create my target
object or whatever
and then run individual functions on that thing.
But I'm not having any,
I would say functional code in there,
in the main script.
All this is just,
essentially I can read through my main script
and know that first it's reading the data.
Second, it's pre-processing.
Third is this, fourth is this.
And just by reading through,
I essentially have one line
for all of these tasks
because it's the function call that does it
that helps me
essentially the same is also true for functions
if the function starts to be longer than
you can actually read and understand
then it's probably too long
it can be split into smaller pieces
that do simpler individual things
and then can be reused
at different places
it's kind of optimally
your code
by just reading through it
explains what it's doing
until you come to so small pieces
that they are relatively obvious
what they are doing
since I said
something about
what the code should be like
so
the reason is to
make it understandable
to make it easier so
it's not just about
style and
like
well it's not just about
telling people
what good code is in some way
this is all
practical advice right
so it makes it easier
to understand and change
and reuse
which is the point
yeah
So what do we have in C? We have, or did we actually go through the answers in B?
Mostly. This is, yeah, minimum things.
Put them in functions.
Smallest task that could be reused.
This is not directly modular code, but in general, having simple and useful comments is very, very useful in general development, regardless of modular or not.
Yeah. So I guess, yeah, maybe I already said this, essentially, the one big thing that kind of defines what modular means here is, or in general, what modular action means is, the code or each part of the code should avoid interacting with other parts of the code as much as possible.
so essentially i would say as much as sensible yeah as much as possible yeah i mean you can
always reduce interactions to zero if you just um uh if you don't care about whether it works
um yeah as much as makes sense of us yeah what you what you very often uh see in things like
style suggestions and so on
is also having not too many input arguments
for functions, which means that
there needs to be a certain balance between
what responsibilities certain functions have
and where they get their data from.
So if your function, because you want to output
it into a function, starts to have 20 input arguments,
it's likely that it's doing
either it's doing more than it should
be doing or it
might be better to have a different
logical unit than a function for this
this might be something that a class should
be doing that you initialize with
a couple of values and then provide
additional data into individual
functions
I've been talking a lot about functions
and
you can also
the data types
and data can also be
modular so you can
combine different values
that are in some way related.
So if you have data about a mesh
that you're running a simulation on,
that mesh can contain multiple different things.
It can contain objects, density, color,
all sorts of things.
And in many cases,
you would want all of those things to be stored under the same name.
So then you could create a data structure or a class or something like that
to put multiple different things in.
And then you can pass that as a single argument.
It also makes it easier to read.
So this is now a single unit of some kind of custom data.
this is the mesh that contains
all the information about
the mesh about all
points in the mesh
something like the world
let's call this a world
or an environment
it has cities, forests
and whatever and you can get those
by either functions or
other properties
yeah
okay
what do you know about programming
that you wish somebody told you earlier, Jaano?
I mean, I should have started using version control from the beginning.
It would have saved a lot of time when I broke something and
essentially had to slowly step by step undo the work until it works again.
So yeah, that's also one of the answers, essentially.
creating a copy before you start
making changes. Version control
does that for you. It's a very good
idea to do.
I would agree with the
use an IDE editor with color coding.
It depends a lot
on the languages that you're using,
but in general,
at least to me,
things like going to definitions of certain imports or something or going to definitions
of functions via an IDE is extremely helpful because this is originally more from typed
languages and pre-compiled languages but nowadays it essentially also works with Python and for
example vs code that you can just right click on a function call go to definition and you get the
function that is being called at this point and you can look into the function what does it actually
do and it helps in understanding what is happening here and um yeah it it just makes it so much more
graspable
what your code is doing
even if it's not that well
or what someone else's code might be doing
if it's not that well documented
yeah
I think actually
modularity
and unit testing
are things that would have been
very useful
to know something about earlier
I remember
at some point I hit upon the
practice of
write a test that
checks
as much of the functionality as possible.
It was essentially
running the code, running
an entire instance of the
code and checking that the values
match some expectations.
But these were all end-to-end tests.
I didn't have any unit tests.
So it would basically
only tell me that something's broken now.
Yeah. So, I think it's time to go to the demonstration. What do you think?
Yep. Let's go to our task.
Yeah.
Okay, so we have some weather data.
And what are we going to do with this data?
What we want to do is essentially, we want to plot the data over time
and make this a bit more modular.
because at the moment we have this kind of script that just plots something
yeah so i guess um
the starting point for me with this would be um i would have this piece of code in a jupiter
notebook that i wrote to do a specific task to um yeah to plot the stuff so here we are
which we essentially have here. We can define the number of measurements here,
but anytime we want to change the number of measurements, we have to modify this and then
hope that we are not forgetting to run something. At the moment, this is what we get.
We can update that, but once we do that, we essentially need to run all the
individual pieces again and we hope to not forget for example to reread the temperatures because
otherwise we get a complete mess in later stages okay so um let me add the bottom of the nodes
I will call it the modular code task,
and I'll also copy in the correct section of the materials.
Okay.
Now, the task is then to make this code better in some way.
What can we do to make it better?
So yeah, please go, if you have ideas,
write into the notes. What do you think we could do here? So one thing, I think, just
looking at the plot, I'm not really sure what is happening there. I mean, you clearly have
a plot of temperatures, but maybe it would be useful, especially if you want to take
the plot and put it in the paper to have
some axis labels.
Yep.
So how would we do that?
So
the
labels, do they
need to be defined before you start
grading the plot?
I think so.
So that's
plt.x
label
and plt.y
label. It makes sense
to put it where you define the number of measurements
this is
x label is a function
it's x label
and then it takes us
yeah yeah okay
so x is days
okay I think so
that
makes sense yeah why not
uh
the temperature
in celsius yeah
I don't find the degree sign
here on that keyboard at the moment
that's not a problem
okay
so now I guess you do need
to rerun the whole thing
okay that just running that
cell did weird things
I guess it has the plot
in memory already and it's outputting
the plot why is that happening
hmm
um because probably this the y label function i guess returns the bot
so it gets displayed yeah okay that works let's do some nope that actually didn't change anything
uh did you try rerunning from the beginning just uh um the restart and run everything
so it's the
two triangles
double run button
looks like a fast forward button
yeah
I've actually never seen
that that's weird
okay well
so this obviously
doesn't work
no I guess we can put
it where
we define the same cell as the plot
might be that this is because
it's in cells
like the original
well okay that works better
that was weird I've never seen that before
that might have been because it's in
well cells now
yeah but I think
well anyway I guess
let's not
but
But it might anyways be an idea to get this
and move it to an actual function
and then reduce what we have here in the plotting
to something that only calls those functions.
Yeah, let me first suggest a complication.
And I guess this is a step towards making it a function.
But the complication is to, instead of just making one plot,
make three different plots with different values
of the number of measurements.
So that means actually now you need to combine
basically all of these cells into a single cell.
because the follow inside the follow up if you change the number of measurements what does that
affect it affects the the part where you read the data because that already sits sets the number of
rows read and then well i guess it doesn't well maybe then you are using that the red data to set
the, yeah, the, the temperature values, okay, temperature values,
so that changes. And then the mean of course changes. And
yeah, everything changes. Okay. And then everything. Yeah. Okay,
So now we have a few different plots being created.
Start this.
So one issue that we had in the original
is not there because we have the days everywhere
because we have them not.
Oh, yeah, we are setting it inside the form.
So if we would redo it like this...
No, you're going to get an extra plot,
and none of the other plots are going to happen.
That's true.
Well, we can.
Yeah, but I mean, it looks like the plot function
is independent of the label setting functions,
but it's actually not.
The plot function, when you say plot.show...
No, actually, no, that's not what's happening here.
what is happening here is that we call plot dot clear um clf yep clear what is the f figure
clear figure okay thanks uh so so we are actually removing the labels oh and we
was forgot something uh well yes going to count that yeah so um you probably want to make it an
string yeah okay yeah so now we are uh changing the file name based on the number of measurements
okay that didn't actually work uh we
it did oh okay it just took a bit to upload update the okay fine so yeah now we actually
have the images that we can include in our um paper about the temperatures in the helsinki
airport um if it loads well well i'm hoping that the png file is actually correct can you
check the one with 25 well png should be it shouldn't depend on the number of i mean it's a
it's a pixel map okay well how seriously do we want to take the um plots being incorrect
rather though the files i don't think it's an issue at the moment
yeah let's go on and we are going to move this into the terminal at some point anyway
Okay. Well, I mean, now we do have this for loop, and we could, this also kind of nicely defines one possible way of splitting it into functions.
I guess that's not really splitting if you take the whole thing and make it a single
function.
Okay, let's, it's going to be a Python file, okay, you're moving into, moving the
whole thing into a script, that makes sense.
Okay, this is not really modular yet, but yeah, before people listening, please do make
suggestions like we are going to actually follow the suggestions that people make in
the notes.
Okay, so now we have, I guess you have to activate the environment.
So now we have a Python function.
Actually check.
Okay, let's check.
What happens?
Yeah, that works.
Okay, and it's creating the file.
It's creating the images.
Oh, it's displaying the images.
Okay, that's fine.
and I need to close them
sometimes that's what you want
sometimes not
but yeah
somehow the files are broken
actually
they are white
okay well let's
take a look at the code then
so it did display them correctly
but the figures being saved
are not
which is a bit strange
that's interesting
well what should we do um well there's definitely one thing that's sort of
functionally separate from everything else which is the plot results part right yeah um so that is
it's doing two things actually it's showing the plot well okay three things it's constructing
the plot, showing the plot,
and saving
it into an image, which for some
reason is not working.
Let's make a function out of this.
Yeah.
So do we want to continue showing the plot
since we are running from the terminal?
I don't
think so, but what we could do
is
we could return the plot.
Yeah.
Yeah, well, I mean, I was going to say, why not, but we are clearing it between each iteration.
Do we?
Because, do we actually need to do that?
I guess we do.
I think we do need to clear it, but what might work is to essentially indicate during the plot data that we want to get a plot, that we want to get some Xs or something.
Maybe that's too much.
okay well uh let's just go on and uh take the whole plotting section move it into a function
function for now yeah and uh that can be fine-tuned later but it's the straightforward
thing to do is to make a new function so now it's taking temperature number of measurements
So the number of measurements affects the file name.
So it is actually...
Does it only affect...
Yeah, it only affects the file name.
Then we might rename that because...
It could be file name.
Yeah, that makes sense.
Okay, and then we construct the file in there.
Okay, so this seems to make sense, although, well, I guess the fact that the function is
defined below, does it matter?
I think it does.
Yeah, there's a difference in how it works in inside classes and in the normal script.
classes you can reorder about the about a script test to have everything defined before it's being
called yeah okay so huh here's a question there we are why do we calculate oh did it actually
create the oh right okay so um one question why do we calculate the mean
oh because it is actually used in the plot right yes in fact somebody said that in the oh yeah
notes and i uh i just didn't understand um okay so um yes you should also include mean as a parameter
Yeah, if you want to have it in the box.
Okay.
And the reason I'm ordering it temperatures mean, because personally to me, temperatures
and mean are what this function actually needs.
And for file name, if I just want to use this once, I could actually give a default value.
Yeah, it could be an option.
That's why I...
kind of ordered in a way um by um by similar things okay
so this is what we now get
which looks yeah okay okay so now it just shows them again and again
it looks like the files are not working correctly they are not um
Okay. Well, we can come back to that at some point. It's a bit weird that we're starting
from a code that doesn't work and trying to make it better by fixing it. Yeah, I just
I don't really know what it could be.
What if we remove the show?
Does that help?
Let's see.
Yes, that helps.
Okay.
What is that?
That's a very good question.
Well, fine.
Now we have some plots.
That's good.
Might it be that show actually clears the plot?
Yeah, could be.
let's test something
okay
what happens if we do this
need to save it
so I'm getting the plots
and
I'm getting the images
so seemingly show cleans
yeah okay but well I mean
that's on one hand interesting
that's good to know
So very much like a Matplotlib-specific thing, a Python-specific thing. So yeah.
Okay, so there are for loops, functions, and so on. You can get this far,
or you can do exactly the same things in any language.
Setting the labels will, of course, be a different function depending on the library.
all of that i think what we can also um move into a function is reading the data
yes so reading the data and this is a suggestion directly from the notes so
another function for reading the data and it could be so read data is very general
and it makes sense it could also be read temperatures or something like that
Well, let's call it readData, if I know.
So the readData reads the temperatures from the CSV file, and it then also picks the column.
So it specifically is the data that we want in this case.
Okay, should we also have a...
I could...
Well, we could make this a bit more general.
well yeah yeah let's uh let's do that since i um since i already mentioned it at this point
might as well do it so you can give it a um file name argument i i would leave it at file name and
um so we are assuming that we have a certain format of the of the data and that this format
it has a column air temperature
degree Celsius.
That's the assumption
that we are putting in. We don't
necessarily know what file name
this is being saved in.
No.
We don't know the output file name.
The read data
needs the input file.
There is one good point
in the notes. There's many
good points in the notes.
One new good point
in the notes, which is that
we could read the data just once
instead of reading it many times
and then taking
the
first n rows.
That's
also an option. Then we remove
this
completely.
We'd need to then put
this
temperature
data is read data this and then we have temperatures blah there's an arrow missing
okay is um actually that is temperature data frame yeah and i'm never sure about
the the exact syntax it's a column so i think you can do a direct number indices
and then it starts with zero yeah i mean you don't have to explicitly write zero but then again why
not let's see if that works um the notes are also suggesting a command line interface is that should
Should we first think about functions a bit more?
Looks correct.
Look at side effects.
So OK, let's have a look.
Personally, I said I would wonder whether we
can return the plot data.
So something like instead of.
and have a
um
so if you are constructing
a new plot you might as well clear it
when you start
right
yeah and then leave it open that's true
Yeah, at which point we could also, in theory, do a this is PLT and then PLT.show to get our visuals back in, for example, a Jupyter Notebook.
Yep.
If you want to put this back into a Jupyter Notebook.
So this function is then usable both as a function in a program
and in a Jupyter Notebook where we want to, in the end, present this.
Yeah, that makes sense.
Okay, did you try running it, though?
Not yet.
But this seems to be correct.
Yeah, it works. Good.
I didn't test it with the PLT.show yet.
Let's see.
Yeah, I'm getting the plots.
I need to now close them again so that it finishes,
but I'm getting the plots.
Yeah.
Okay.
Well, yeah, we don't need the plot.show now.
If you prefer to keep it, then why not?
so in the in this script no we don't need them yeah if we want to put this
way we could we could actually notebook yeah go back to our notebook so what is
it that we currently need to do we essentially have this is what we are
currently doing yeah this is nice to show i mean basically so what we're showing here is um how
you import your own code into the notebook and then when it imports some functions from
no there wasn't weather prediction it was whether what was the name
it was better predictions okay
okay
so yeah importing from the
back from the file
there's an extra
ict
of predictions
predictions
yeah
okay so now we have
data
okay
so that makes sense
and there we are and now our our our script our jupiter script essentially says okay we are
reading data and then we are going over different measurements there is barely any functional code
here anymore so so what do you think about the mean calculation um it is like if you if
we're calculating more complicated statistics, it should become its own function. But it is not a
super complicated thing here, is it? To me, here's a bit of a point. For this mean, I probably
wouldn't create a function. But for the purpose of this, I would probably create something that does
build some statistics
and I would probably
because it's
not that likely that it's just the mean
that you normally need
for statistics.
If you just want
to mean, so there's a very good point
in the notes again.
Writing your own
mean function is also a bit
stupid.
It's like if you want
the standard mean
well I mean yeah the mean the average
there's multiple different averages that we could use so in that sense having a function where you can go
and change which average you want might make sense
but we could also use numpy.mean
or actually it is a pandas column so you can
call just temperatures.mean
would i think it would work i think there's a mean function just directly embedded in the
pandas column class so in in any case i mean whatever language you're using almost certainly
it already has a mean uh function in it or some pretty much like it yes yeah
so so yeah we don't actually have to write our own mean function for this one although
So, again, it would also be a good example.
It's one of the things that you might want to do,
but, well, you already wrote two functions.
So, there's actually a different question
that I would be kind of asking here.
Is the mean actually an input to the plot function or not?
Because the mean here is just used
to create a plot line at the mean level.
so and is something that is a derivative from temperatures so we don't need this as an input
yeah you could move that calculation into yeah and i think this is i don't know what do people
think is this better i think it makes sense this way it also makes sense depending on what you're
doing it might make sense to have um a line argument or x line or is it a y line whichever
it is um in the plot data that allows you to just define where the line goes and it then it doesn't
have to be a mean necessarily it could be whatever line you want um but going a bit into going a bit
um over the top of how this could be designed conceptually temperatures could be a class or
something we could have a temperature object class where you can set what kind of things you want to
have like what kind of average value you want to use and then you would essentially
say temperatures.average and temperatures.values instead of
these two
and then have it dependent on the temperature.
So people want to get to the command line.
One more thing before
we go there.
What do you think of the comments? Oh, actually
two more things. One,
what's the error message
that you get when you run this?
And
how do you figure out where the error is?
Can you run it?
Okay. So how do we figure out what the error message is? This is not the error I was expecting.
I was expecting a different one.
Maybe there is a different one. So I removed the means here. So I need to do that here.
Yeah. So I guess my main point is there's no reason to be scared of errors. They just tell
you the line that you need to change, usually, in almost any language. In some languages,
though you need to fiddle around like compile it differently to get the line numbers but still
um it's always did you mean that error to get errors yes i meant this one
so that's on line uh 11. okay yeah and this is something that a good ide would actually flag
like during the development, that this is not existent, so this can't work.
Yeah.
So two things we want to do, or at least two things, command line interface and tests.
Which do we do first?
So we have command line interface twice in the nodes.
Yeah, then let's go for command line interface.
So let's go with that.
and uh what's your favorite i think um i have started using click more and more because
i've learned it from code refinery and it's um it's convenient i'm generally fine with whatever
um i haven't personally used click that much but um you can in the worst case uh go uh
send me yeah i mean this is again something that i'm like
different languages have their different implementations of how to do command line
arguments so we'll do it again in python the example is in python but yeah you can search
the web for command line interface and the language that you're using and there will
almost certainly be a very good library for doing them in a simple way okay so
So to do this, we want to foreclick.
Yeah, you need a main function.
And then you need to define how you give those arguments in the command line.
Actually, we don't have an out file at the moment.
So our old file is currently fixed. We can change that later, maybe.
So if I see that right, then we have a definition that this is...
So this is kind of an annotation to the main function.
But yeah, this is a command.
Yeah. So now this main function is something you can run from the command line,
and then you add options so options are the command line arguments and they also
must have the same name as oh well i mean the easiest thing to do
is to give them the same name as the parameters of the main function
actually looking at this this is not the same name
this has a minus in fact yes this is well that's a peculiarity of python
yeah maybe a good number of other languages have the same issue so you cannot have a minus sign
inside the name right it would be num minus measurements it would be a math calculation
not a name so uh it has to be an underscore but click will automatically convert the
minus sign into an underscore
here.
Is the
order relevant, or is it really
name matching? The order should be the same
as in the options.
Then it's just the order that it's
using. I think I've tried.
We can try. If you change
the name, I think it will work.
We can also try changing the order.
Well, if we have time.
so these are the two values that we have and then we essentially have our functionality here
and we need to
Oh, no, we have the outfile.
Ah, we have an outfile.
Yeah, of course we have an outfile.
Well, yeah, if we are
plotting one particular number of...
No, we have an outfile.
Yeah, but we can simply replace this
by the outfile.
Yeah, yeah.
So we have an outfile.
Modular.
the modularity helps here already
we have one specific number of measurements
and then a specific name for the output file
that means we don't have the follow-up anymore
yeah, that's true
that's something I just wanted to ask
how do you set defaults in Qlik?
a good question
we don't have it in the example
But probably since this default depends on a different import, let's just have it required.
So, yeah, in this case, it would be nice to show how you add a default value.
It's just default equals something. But for the outfile,
yeah, you should not, you can say default equals none.
Yeah, but then you don't have an outfile number.
but that you mean if it's none then you use the number of measurements
but you also have to remove the required equals true
if you have default equals none i i think at least it makes sense this way
so now we check if a the alt file is not given so the default value is none that's usually easy
to check and usually not what you want so then we can use this default value
okay and otherwise we just use whatever value is in out file so um yeah that should be in file
you could also set this to false and um just have to have another default value for temperatures
of csv or something okay it depends on like how you want to use the interface
a default value for an input file can be surprising
and you generally want to avoid surprises
so now we have the out file now we don't have the for loop anymore right yes we don't have that
anymore yeah oh and yeah now we need the standard python thing if name equals underscore underscore
name if if the name equals main with lots of underscores um then we call the main function
and if you don't know python this doesn't mean anything to you and if you know python
it still doesn't mean anything to you it's just python okay um if i'm calling that correctly it's
due to forks and things, so if you have multiprocessing, only one of the things
will be called main, and therefore execute the main, and everything else will not do that.
Yeah, so essentially if you import it as a module, then main will not execute, and we can still
import it in the Jupyter code, and it will work the same way as before. But if you run it as a script,
then this main section will execute.
So it's something you see often.
If you write something incorrectly or just don't remember what the parameters are
will produce a message that tells you how to run. Okay, it didn't create a 26. Yes,
it did. Okay.
It did. It just takes time to show up.
Okay. So it works. Great. One thing I was thinking a while ago, what do you think
about the comments in this main function?
read the data from a file
this is definitely the wrong place
but readData
the function name readData is
it tells you
exactly the same thing
you don't need the comment
this comment is
more self-explanatory
this could be a
select the
requested
measurements
could
well
I would say for anyone who has
worked with Pandas a bit it's clear what this
does but might still be
useful to have
and then
plot results
so the point is the function
names explain what is happening
if someone is just looking through the
main function
we don't need to actually explain in comments
because now since we made the code modular
and we used helpful function names,
the comments are suddenly a lot less necessary.
The code explains itself, right?
Okay.
Can you also try running this from the Jupyter Notebook?
so we should see that it still works
you mean
where is my
you mean rerunning what we had here
yeah
so this is importing the two functions
and yeah
so the fact that we made this
added this command line interface
doesn't actually change anything
let's restart this
because we have an import here
and
yeah well actually yes
something can change
we no longer give the mean as a parameter
true
you see that's why restarting
was important
true
but yes
general it works
we just had a
small bug
because we changed
our
yeah
so the next thing was to
add tests
no the next thing I think would be to
to have this input
I hope that click
does something with this
yeah it works
So, yeah, this is what Qlik provides you, essentially, all this additional information,
and that you essentially have a command line interface where you can get the standard parameters
like help, some information about, okay, how does this work, and so on.
Okay, yeah, that makes sense.
So yeah, we're just telling what the default value actually is.
If you don't provide a default, I think it's a good idea to help or to give this kind of information.
Oh, and yes, it is in fact time for a break.
We have been going on for an hour.
And yes, since we are not following a schedule, I'm not keeping an eye on it.
It is definitely already, like I should have started the break a while ago, I guess.
but we can take the break now
for 10 minutes and be back
at 14.10
and then do the tests after that
yeah
okay so
yeah let's take a break
walk around a little bit and see you then
bye
see you later
and hi again
so we wanted to
get into testing
yeah so
um where would you put the tests i personally would create a tests folder
so it's not a huge project we only have one python file but let's assume it might get become
bigger at some point and even then even if you have just a single python file i would at least
create a separate file for the tests but that's just like i guess we are dealing with relatively
big projects every single time. Well, in any case, it does not hurt. So we can create a test folder,
and then there is a test weather predictions file there. And it's empty.
Yeah, there's nothing there at the moment.
do we test um we have two functions um in our package
was it retail data okay so um
these are both a little bit more complicated than it they're not just returning they're not taking
input values and returning values. Well, read data is, but it is doing something else. It's
reading from disk. And the other one is creating a file to disk. So we can still test this. And
it might actually be quite useful to show that it's not that complicated. So why don't we do
that? Okay, now there's a data folder. Because we want to essentially have our test data as
data for the tests so we create and this could be essentially anything formatted like uh the data we
are reading but in this case we have an example file already so why not use that um so yeah we've
copied the file that contains the temperatures temperatures of csv into this uh data folder
and now we can make a test read data function.
So for PyTest specifically,
the folder name should be tests.
The module that contains the tests
should be test underscore something.
And then the function also needs to be
test underscore something.
But this depends on the framework.
But yeah, so that is why the structure
that we have here exists.
Okay, so test read data.
So what do we do? We call the readData function. I don't think we need really any preample. We can
just call it, give it the file name. And I guess it's in... Is the path relative? It's always
relative to what it's called from. Yeah. And we will call it from the main, so...
Yeah. So it's test slash data slash temperatures dot csv. Okay. And now we can check some values.
Yeah. Where was it?
So it's the green. Yeah.
The values that we had. So let's-
We only take the air temperature column. That's the only column we have. So we can take
number eight. Number eight will actually be-
Number seven.
Python starts indexing from zero. So it's the index seven. Yeah. We do an asset. So one thing
is you can write a test function that doesn't have any asserts, and then the test will fail
only if there's an error. But that can happen. But yeah, so we are checking that the data is
also read correctly 16. so in a lot of cases you won't be able to have exactly the same data in
the in your tests because you don't want to push them to a public repository if you're publishing
your code um but then you can you can create just like randomly type numbers by hand into the file
and that's fine. You can probably use a different text editor than Jupyter labs
to open the CSV file and type some numbers in. And I'm putting the Aprox here also for the minus four
because the problem might be that this line is read as a floating number and we might get
something that is yeah not exactly four most like most likely it is exactly four or minus four but
yeah yeah i mean i guess one of these things where you it might be useful to show that there's an
error but then again it's also that it's specifically pandas that's reading it as
folding point it might happen it might not happen with a different library or different
language and so on so yeah let's just do it like this that this looks good looks correct
Does the read data take any other parameters?
Yes. It takes a column. So we could just...
Oh, you can try a different column name, like time. No, well...
Time might be difficult. The problem is everything else is exactly the same all the
time. So no, wait, the D is not the same. Okay. It's day.
Yeah.
temperatures. Let's see. Yeah, scroll down a good bit to say zero is one and temperatures
62 is three.
These will probably be in the church spot. Oh, you can Yeah, proxy doesn't hurt doesn't
really hurt here okay um so let's try running the test so now we run pi test
it found the test which is nice it also yeah and notice that we do not actually have this module
in the um so yeah i guess this is a bit too python specific
Yeah, this is very specific.
We just have to add a dot in front, right? Or is that relative to the tests?
Let's see. I'm never entirely sure. No, this is... I hate it.
What's the right way around this? This is the annoying thing with it. I mean, the right
way around this would be to turn the whole thing into a package.
Yep, which I'm just doing. This is a bit hacky now, but it's not really. It goes like this.
Yeah, I mean, the thing that makes it a package is that there is an init file.
Do I need an init?
I think you do, in the app folder.
bit set of txt. So there is an extra Yeah, yeah. Okay.
No, no, it didn't know module named app or
Okay.
I think so if you don't get all the package, then you have to either have it in the same
folder as the test or it needs to be a this works on different things
i know that i'm doing exactly this on other projects
anybody is no no comments in the notes so yeah i mean this is one of these things where i'm
I often get confused about what's happening.
Okay, then in this case...
But if we move the test file into the main folder,
and we also move the main file back into the main folder.
No, let's do something that I personally don't really like too much.
But in this case, I think we'll just do this.
well I mean you don't have to do
you don't have to put it in the same file
as long as
they're in the same folder it should work
okay
let's see
actually cut
because we don't want to have this twice
so
one common solution
also is to add
the
path where your
main code is
to add it to the
Python path
where it looks for packages.
Okay, now it actually ran.
PyTest is not defined.
Oh, yes, of course.
No, it's not fun because
We didn't import it here.
Oh, right. It's this PyTest.lab.rocks.
Okay, nice.
Okay, now it passed.
Right.
Good.
This is the test for
our read data.
I guess we still
have our test data
in the tests folder.
We can do read.
Let's assume that the 25 here is correct.
So let's have plot data.
So this shouldn't take too long, but we also don't have too long, so
we can take a couple of minutes to do this and then wrap up.
So this now gets a little bit more complicated because we have the problem that
need a temporary folder here because we need to write to a file for a test that should be a
temporary file but python has a package called temp file which i will use for this purpose
and this is again something that almost any language will have yeah so this gives you
a temporary file name that you can but you can create the file safely and you will not be
overwriting anything. Where that file exactly is will depend on the operating system.
I don't need anything here. And now I need, actually, is it file.name?
So let's look quickly. So you create a temporary file with tempfile.temporaryfile.
Yeah, it's .name. Okay.
And yeah, okay. You found it first. Good.
should work and then file.name and now we need to compare this with the file
that we have so do you have a standard solution there is not really a file
fileCmp. Yeah, fileCmp might make...
I assume that almost any language has a file comparison.
One way or another, worst case, you need to compare these with...
Yeah, so it's fileCmp.CMP, fileName1, fileName2. And I think we can do shallow equals true
Well, it's not going to take that long anyway.
Yes.
Slash 25.png.
Okay.
And then just an assert here.
Yeah.
Oops.
That's one too many.
Let's see if this works.
It will not work because they have a different modified time.
Can I ignore that?
So this is not the contents of the file that is comparing.
Sorry, this is, should we read in the data and read in some bytes from the data and compare
that or just i don't want to feel uh to leave it at this point but um
well but we have very limited time okay then maybe we can do file one
so open both with open file name one as file one
or this is the
as
test
is the file we wrote
not in parentheses
this is a variable name
or test output
and then with
test output okay
with
yeah this file name
as
correct output
test correct
okay
so now it's opened both files
and then you go if
test output dot read
and that's a function
parentheses
no
test underscore output
sorry
and also if doesn't have parentheses
is it has yes i'm working in typescript and javascript too much yeah no well not i mean
it's this is a peculiarity of python again so if it's equal to um isn't it correct output
you can do assert yeah
okay that should work it's actually comparing the entire contents of the files which are
it's a bit over the top but okay yes in object doesn't have an attribute right so
what are we doing so this is in line 18 let's look at line 18 we can figure it out
okay yeah plot data file name oh what is our plot data plot data takes temperatures and
text file name and attribute does what oh it's it's line 12 in plot data
maybe we um oh oh oh no no okay okay okay now um this is no this is incorrect um
I think what we need here is this okay I think this test is always the fun part it happens
very often. Okay.
Because the thing is, um, the file name just gave gave the the
integer the location of the file. Okay, this is a bit
Yeah, I remember seeing stuff like that with a file.
I'm not sure if there is... no. Okay, no.
So it's with tempfile.name temporary file as something, and then it has a something.name.
It's actually a file handler already. You can do temp. Well, I mean, this should work,
I think.
Yeah, I just need to say that. Because I'm not sure.
They need to be, so this line needs to be indented to the same level as the previous one.
Are you sure? Because I'm opening the same file again.
No, otherwise temp file is not...
Yes, that's why I just created an additional variable.
Okay, you don't have to open it. We are running out of time. But you don't have to open it. You
you can use the so this named temporary file gives you a file
handle. So it is already open in the URL. Okay, but then we have
to open it again, you can, if you go to the so you can instead
of using the test output, you can use temp file directly. So
if you remove line 10 to 21 right sorry got a slightly different idea okay um the thing is i
want this to be closed again because i have the impression we are getting a problem that um
we have an open file and we are not closing it properly afterwards uh yeah that was my idea
have to take the name into a different variable yes that's what i just did oh okay
but we do get an issue okay
so this is on line 23 um that's an assert issue uh yeah so uh i wanted to show that this is not
as complicated as it seems. But comparing the files directly seems to be more complicated than...
Might even be.
And I think we need to move on to this.
Yeah. But conceptually, you would take the files and compare them in some way
to see that they are the same.
And look at the contents. We can also just check that the file is there.
I assume it would take us another 10 to 15 minutes
to get this right now.
And I don't think it's actually worth it at the moment.
And it's an image file,
which is generally one of the easier things to check
by looking at it.
So if it was any different kind of a file,
what you would do is open the file,
read the contents,
and then compare to a known example,
which is what we're trying to do here.
So hopefully we didn't get too bogged down and lose the general context.
So the overall idea is to test what the function does.
And in this case, it's writing to the file system.
So to test that, you read the file and you compare it to what you already know it should be.
And the main thing is here, we use known test data.
so we already know what should happen
because we know what this temperatures.csv contains
and then if you were to put this online
this code, publish it
you would publish the known test data as well
and then everybody can run the tests
so
now
we could probably find a clever way
of looking at the contents of the image a little bit
and uh compare the files directly um but it's probably not worth doing today so oh well not
i think the concept hopefully got clear um and this is mainly about the concept here yeah so
one other thing to mention is that we still have everything although both the functions define the
script and everything it works well enough one thing we could have done um especially if it was a
bigger package is to
take the script and put it in a
separate file and then have things
that are imported in a different file
that would also be nice
and it would be a module you can very easily
move around but okay
let's leave it at that
there is the
feedback for day
six available and we still
have a workshop outro
in the schedule so
[name] and [name]
welcome sorry for taking your time um with the debugging the test no worries this is good to show
like this is also showing like this is sometimes what you have to do this is sometimes what you
have to think about and i think it's nice to like watch you to figure it out because that may also
like stick better like next time maybe some of the participants are in the same situation and
then maybe they remember oh yeah there was this one thing that [name] did or this one thing that
[name] suggested maybe so oh CATS is also with us great stuff not working is the most useful part
of the lesson no but it's a good a good thing I think to have it also part of the lesson if
everything would work that's not really that's not real no I mean by most useful I mean actually
most useful to see how stuff goes wrong now that was feedback from other stuff before
oh it's part of the process so don't worry
okay so the feedback is here you can give feedback not just for today but down below on