okay so the feedback is here you can give feedback not just for today but down below on
every day the whole workshop um i guess we should also save what we show now for uh what's it
we could just send this video to people who have attended and they can see the
outdoor even if they're not here right now so we're going on the schedule to the concluding
remarks here yes and it's also linked from the notes because there will be a lot of links that
we are showing here as well now so that you can just go and click them as well and by the way
hello everyone in case we haven't met yet i'm [name] i work at csc and starting may i will
be the project manager for Code Refinery. I've been here day four and day one already and will
now together with [name] go through our concluding remarks. There was a few things we promised already
in the intro that we will tell you about. So let's see that we get to that. But as the very first
thing, thank you very much to everyone. Thank you to all your participants for all your amazing
questions i've been following along a little bit on the side and there have been really good
questions and i hope they have helped you also in the in the learning process we had some team
leaders and hosts this time with us so if you joined in a team also say thank you to your team
leader and to our hosts for doing that and we hope that maybe some of you who are now participating
as a participant and are interested in helping us with this to join us next time maybe as a team
leader maybe as a host to learn with others the same is for instructors thank you all that you
are here still and thanks to also all the instructors of the rest of the week so we had
many different instructors and hopefully that was also valuable to like all the participants that we
had many different voices, many different ways of teaching so
that it did not get boring. Then we had some people working in
the behind the scenes answering the questions in the
collaborative notes. We don't know necessarily who they all
are. We know that [name] answered a lot of them. But then
we also had some people from the participants or from the helpers
answering questions, I believe. And then we have our local partners where they are already covered
with the hosts that provided a classroom for week one to learn together. And yeah, you really make
these workshops possible and enjoyable. So thank you, everyone. [name] mentioned already the
feedback so we are really really happy to read all your feedback for today as well as for the
workshop as a whole if you joined the whole workshop and there was for example a lesson
that you found completely useless let us know like that's how we that's how we get to know
if there was a lesson that you really really enjoyed also let us know because that then we
will probably keep it if we get a lot of feedback in this way and you can do that in the collaborative
notes you can do that via email to support at codefront.org or you can also join our chat and
this last option is also a very good way to stay in contact with us if you like really enjoyed what
we are doing and want to stay in contact with the instructors stay in contact with other people that
are enjoying um talking and discussing about the topics that we have in this workshop then
our chat is a really good good way of doing that and everyone can join there is no no like
restrictions requirements or anything um then you have seen a lot of different lesson materials
written by many different people and sometimes last minute updates can make things a little bit
more confusing than they have to be um and sometimes also the way we write it is not
necessarily how someone who sees it for the first time can understand it so if you had any exercise
or any materials that you were like what what are they talking about this i have no idea what to do
now uh let us know um you have learned in the first week hopefully how to work with github
all our lessons are on github so you can add an issue you can even if you are if you have a lot
of time on your hands you can send a pull request to update any of our lessons and we'll be happy to
review it and discuss there with you and we are always like using all of these to develop the
workshop materials further so it's very much appreciated and then in the future i don't yet
know when but i would guess not not any earlier than half a year from now we will also send a
well post post post post post workshop survey um to everyone who visited this and other workshops
in the past. It's about how you can, how you could make use of what you learned in the workshop. So
right now there's probably some things that you really enjoyed learning, some things that you
want to apply right away, but in half a year maybe you have a better idea of, oh this was really
useful and I'm using this and that's exactly what we would like to know. And that helps us with like
further funding and in general reporting about the project so then we have if you can scroll a little
bit down thank you please keep studying and ask for support so um you may have noticed that we
have introduced you to a lot of different topics and also in week two we didn't have time to do
exercises as part of this workshop but we would really recommend you if you are if you got
interested in any of these topics to go ahead take another hour or so sit down and do the exercises
most of them have quite detailed solutions also attached to them or step-by-step
instructions on how to go about it but if you get stuck with anything we also have
what we call a bring your own code session this is also a session where you can bring your own
question so if you have any questions or anything that you would like to screen share with an
instructor and ask about like is this correct or is this the right way to go about it then these
bring your own code sessions are the best place to come there we will have at least one probably
more instructors available and to make it most useful for you and also for us to know how many
people are interested in this we have a like a very short registration survey for this it's also
linked from the workshop event page schedule just asking I think even just your name and if you want
to you can provide already some information about the things that you would like to discuss
just so that we could invite the correct instructors for that and so far it has been
really fun to go to these sessions and hear about like how you then actually apply what you have
learned in the workshops here so it's also interesting for us um yes [name] do you want
to say something about the videos and where they are available yeah so so far i've been able to get
the videos out the same day and probably will today they're on a youtube playlist and well
there you use them for whatever you'd like i guess the main reason we make them is for
the people in the course to review what we said and the examples while you're trying to follow
along but maybe they're useful to other people yeah and share them with your friends if you want
and the same with our lesson materials so they are available where you found them so far they
will stay available before the next workshop in autumn they might change slightly but only to the
better we hope yeah um we are also working on the notes so okay we are also working on um putting
them on xenodo and we might actually make that happen now during summer for this workshop's
lesson so there you will also then have a pdf version and a like a static thing on the things
you actually learned now in this workshop but yeah the lesson materials on our web pages will
live uh will continue to live on there and you can share them you can reuse them if you
want to teach some of your colleagues about the topics you learned here please reuse the
materials they are all under cc by license so you can do that and you can even cite the lessons if
you want to so there is a citation cff file in all of the lesson repositories
with all the information you need for for citing them nowadays and then if you go a bit further
down yes so i mentioned already you can please do the exercises if you're interested in the topics
and if you cannot come for example to the bring your own code session
there is also a lot of local support available for different places here we now have only from
our partner organizations for some of our partner organizations the information about trainings
about sessions where you can come to ask for more help like at alto the garage session at cse the
weekly user support session and the training calendars but likely your own organization also
has something like this or if not your own organization then maybe your your national
high performance computing center or something like this might have help available for for these
kind of questions so please make use of them and if you really don't have anyone you can always
like reach out to us by coming to the chat or sending us an email and we can try to help you
figure these things out.
Okay, if you go a bit further down.
If you want a certificate for this workshop, if you want to get credit,
ECTS credit for this workshop, then please go on the course web page. There is on the top
middle towards right a tab for certificates there is the instructions on what you need to do and
until until when uh yeah deadline is also here 16th of april um then you can get a certificate
but you need to need to do a little bit something for that and that's described there is that
basically the learning diaries of each day and output of the exercises is it including the week
two exercises or do none of us know because someone else has written that okay i guess
someone else is taking care of that i don't know but i assume it's doing the exercises from the
second week also yeah i would assume so as well yeah you can read about it in detail actually
now that i'm seeing it here um what you need to do there open it
yeah it's a lot of text so let's not read through that now
but yeah it's a it's a learning diary and then some exercises that you all need to do and alto
has
agreed to go through that
and
provide the certificates.
Our colleague [name]
that you also know
already from day
four, I believe.
Okay.
That was certificates.
Then, yes,
code refinery.
We are a project
and we need your support please tell everyone about it as if you liked the workshop and I
already mentioned you can like come and help us for the workshops you can also teach with us in
the future if you want to if you're interested in that the best way also there is to come to
our chat and let us know about your interest and then we can figure out how we can do that in the
future. We are now in May starting our fourth phase, so we will not cease to exist at least
the next three years. But yeah, everyone who is interested in joining us is very welcome to do
that. We have social media accounts on Mastodon, Blue Sky and LinkedIn. All three of them have
usually the same content linkedin sometimes a bit longer something but in general everything the
same we try to post about workshops and other things that we are doing because besides this
workshop we are also collaborating on other workshops like for example python for scientific
computing last year we did a nice course on tools and techniques for high performance computing so
there's a lot going on and yes the rest i already mentioned you can get involved there's also a
newsletter um that we send i think twice a year the biggest the big newsletter that's usually
about like the the big workshops coming up and other possibilities and now i remember that i
forgot to put here also we also have an ambassador program so if you are interested in what we're
doing and would like to kind of get the latest news more often than half a year then we have
the ambassador program which means like people who are interested in what we're doing who want
to re-share about our events and so on but who don't necessarily themselves have the time to
get more involved to become an instructor or to host a breakout room or to host a classroom or
to help us in any other way but this like sharing the information wider and also providing us
feedback is very very valuable to us and that's why we started this ambassador program and you
can find the link on how to join that also on this newsletter page is it though let's let's check
oh it's actually linking from there okay so it's under join
and i can let's put then the link also on the notes it's under join and for individuals
and there you can find further down code refinery ambassadors that you can find the information
about that if you can put that link on the notes that would be really great okay one of the others
who are still here well someone not sharing the screen right now yes exactly okay but now to the
yeah maybe most interesting point of this outro so if you got interested in
this research software development or then there's also an association nowadays called the nordic
research software engineers or short nordic rse and [name] do you want to say something about
who is in RSE? And what do we do there? Well, we often talk, what is the meaning of a research
software engineer? But basically, it's someone that does research, but cares about the software
more than most people, and perhaps wants to be evaluated based on the quality of the code they
write and not just the publications they get. And that's basically all of us here. So we've all
studied different types of science things and then we've liked being part of research but we wanted
something a bit more long term and i found good job supporting the software and data and computing
side of things and now we're here teaching you so yes and you don't have it you don't need like the
title of research software engineer it's still something fairly new also in the nordics
so there's a lot of people who are have titles like postdoc or research assistant or
i don't know what else but many other titles like exist for that and the research software
engineering community is open for everyone who is like interested in the topic who is excited
about it learning about it maybe wants to help make it a bit more of a thing also in the nordics
so we have a community once in a while we also arrange seminars and other events we are hanging
out in the same chat as code refinery so there is a really tight connection and with our own
channel called nordic rse we have our own linkedin mastodon and blue sky same as code refinery we
post on all of those whenever there is something happening and something happening is actually
quite soon we have our second in-person conference on may 20th and 21st in Gothenburg in Sweden and
the general submission deadline is unfortunately already over but we still accept posters and you
can still also join without your own contribution so just to listen on what's going on in the nordics
with regard to research software engineering meet some people discuss your situation here
where there are maybe open positions for research software engineers or research software
engineering interested people and so on and just meet the community and see what's going on
yeah
anything else that we would like to say
at this point
I would want to just
mention
there is now a solution for the plot data
testing
in the collaborative document
awesome, yay
so it's not an unsolvable problem
no, it was
just, yeah
small details
right
okay
but then I think
we are four minutes
before
official closing time
but I guess
that's just good
yeah
thank you very much
for
for joining
for listening
for being so active
thanks to instructors
well we did this already
but thank you very much
and see you again
yeah
thanks a lot
thanks
bye
bye bye
See you.
Bye.