CodeRefinery.org
you
music
Every mistake you can think of that we will also go through today, I finally decided to go and spend some time reading about Git.
Yeah, I know the feeling. Anyway, I guess it is 10 o'clock now, so I will head off and [Name] can start with the introduction.
Will you play the jingle?
Should I?
Yeah, let's play the jingle.
Okay, see you shortly.
Let's see, how does this go?
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24,
25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31, 32, 33, 34, 35, 36, 37, 38, 39, 40, 40, 41, 42, 42, 43,
we always need volunteers and partners to continue making this also a success in the future.
And we are very happy to also welcome new institutional partners.
And then if you like this workshop, please share your experiences about it on social media
with this Code Refinery hashtag. And we are also on Mustard on Twitter and LinkedIn.
And now I've already taken a few too many minutes,
so I will give over right away to [Name] and [Name],
who will guide you to our first steps into version control.
Thanks so much, Anatole.
Let me take the screen,
and we should also tell again who we are,
the instructors, just a sec.
I have the screen share.
So hi to everybody.
It's so nice to see so many people on the document
and on stream.
We are so excited about this workshop.
My name is Sadovan and together with Gago,
we are today teaching Git from Tromso, Northern Norway.
It's snowing here.
I work with the Code Refinery Project since its start.
So this is now, I think, eight years that we do this.
In my work, I like teaching, programming,
helping researchers and students with their coding,
so research software engineering,
and also supporting people in computing.
Yes, and maybe a quick hello from my co-instructor [Name].
Yeah, hello from my side.
My name is [Name].
I'm working with the same group as [Name]
here at UIT in Tromsø, Norway.
So it's the high-performance computing group,
but also the research engineering group.
I started recently and before that,
I did a postdoc here at the same university
in plasma physics in my case.
So I've worked a few years as a researcher as well.
Yeah, looking forward to this course.
And since we both have been researchers,
we know how it feels.
We both haven't kind of officially learned coding
in our university curriculum.
We did research and learned it a bit on the side.
We know the pain.
know what is needed. Before we go into get a little bit what to expect and how to participate.
So please expect we will do an exercise soon, roughly in 1520 minutes. We will then also
do a break in half an hour. And the two things that I always have open in my browser, and
You can have that maybe open next to the next to the stream on the other half of your screen
is I have the collaborative notes.
So we will be watching these as instructors and please keep the questions coming.
The more you ask, the more you comment, the better it will be.
We are following this and the best way to do it is to ask at the bottom because we already
have so many things open here on my side and on your side.
I will be watching what comes up at the bottom.
So add your questions,
add your comments to the bottom of the page.
You will also find always here where are we at this moment.
The other place that I have as a starting point
is the workshop page.
So if you get lost and you want to find the material,
you can also find it here through the schedule.
And we have now finished the introduction section.
Thanks to [Name].
And now we will talk about Git and version control.
And I will now go into the first link, which is also in the collaborative notes.
And I want to tell you a little bit what to expect today and tomorrow and on Thursday.
There is a side panel here with lots of episodes.
We will not do all of them. There is a lot more than we chose to present.
But what we will present you is the most important parts.
The exciting thing is that we have a completely new Git lesson.
This is the first time we present it.
We have changed everything.
But hopefully to the better, because our goal was to make it possible for everybody to participate.
And you can actually choose your path, and I will tell you more about it in a moment.
I will now scroll down a little bit
just to give you an overview
and zoom in to make it more readable
so that you know what to expect today,
what to expect tomorrow.
We will now very briefly motivate why we do this.
And then the goal for today is these three episodes
to browse an existing project,
to make changes to an existing project,
and to merge changes that have been done
on different branches.
So today in day one, we learn how do we contribute
to an existing project that already exists.
And we imagine that today and tomorrow,
we want to learn Git for even if you work on your own,
even if you don't collaborate with others.
What are the most important techniques?
Tomorrow. Okay. And each of these three will have one exercise. So, so please expect 20
minutes, 25 minute exercise blocks in each of these three sessions today. And then tomorrow
we will move from, we will move the existing project and learn how do we work locally on
our computer? How do we inspect history of a project locally on our computer? And then
and super important since many of you already have a project,
you have a script, you have some code,
or you are about to start one.
How do you turn this project into a Git repository
and share it?
This is so important because we want to make it findable
and reusable.
So that's the plan.
I will now go into motivation.
Why do we do this?
So our goal is nobody leaves the workshop
without starting some form of version control.
We want to really get you excited about this.
And this will be a really short overview.
And what is Git?
And I see on the document that many of you are new to Git.
You can think of it as a tool that keeps track of changes.
And we will learn how to keep track of changes on the web.
And here's a screenshot and you can even browse
this example repository,
which I think is some of my projects.
So you can open it up in your browser and browse
and see what I was doing in 2017 and 2021.
We keep track of changes that we apply to the project.
And then whenever I want to go back
to a previous version, I can.
Some of you will also experiment with this
in your command line terminal.
Some of you will choose to do that in your editor.
So one way to think about Git would be,
it's like an undo button.
If you ever want to go back, something didn't work out,
you want to try an early version, you can do an undo,
but it can do a lot more than that.
And here are some questions that I have either heard
or I have asked, and maybe you recognize some of them.
For instance, oh, it broke.
Oof, hopefully I have a working version somewhere.
Or can you please send me the latest version?
Or where is the latest version?
Maybe you have asked, which version are you using?
Which version have the authors used
in the paper that I'm trying to reproduce?
Or you found a problem and you want to know
how long was it there?
And gets and version control is the answer to these questions.
So it can do a lot more than just rollback rollback is like an undo.
One thing we will learn already today is how to branch and merge and how to, and then on,
on Thursday, we will do collaboration.
But in order to do collaboration,
we have to understand branching.
It actually cannot go in Git.
We have to.
And what is branching?
We try to visualize it with these cute gophers.
In Git, you can work on different features
inside the same project.
And for this, you can create
these different development branches.
So on this branch, you can implement a new feature
to give this gopher sunglasses.
And on a different branch, it could be the graduation hat.
And then you can so-called merge these changes
into the main branch, recombine them.
So we don't have to wait for each other.
Also, if you want to experiment with something,
you can create this branch, experiment,
and then you can merge it or not.
Different people can work on the same code, same project,
without interfering.
And you can experiment with an idea and discard it
if it turns out it was a bad idea.
And Git is really good at that.
And finally, reproducibility.
This is really about making reproducible science,
reproducible computations and programs.
And if somebody asks you about your results
from some time ago, can you get the same results now?
And often you will want to reproduce somebody else's code
and then you are really happy if you can find
the precise version that the authors have used
in the paper you try to reproduce.
And there will be a day when you find a problem
and you will want to know
when precisely this bug got introduced.
Was it before I published a nature paper
or was it after?
I'm hoping it was after,
but at least I have a tool that tells me
when exactly it was introduced.
And we will, I will not go here to details
because we will actually practice this
in the first exercise.
You will be able to explore these tools.
You will see them in real life.
Just looking at the time,
I think we are still doing pretty okay.
Git also makes it easier for me to talk about code.
If I want to share with somebody a few lines of my project,
I can send them a link
and you can actually visit this permalink.
So if I want to tell you about this code that I wrote,
well, you can open it up in your browser
and you will see exactly what I'm talking about.
It's so much nicer than describing to you,
find a code, please go to the file, so-and-so,
search for the line that contains this text.
Oh, but please make sure that you use the version
from August, 2023.
And it's not just about software.
We can, with Git, we can version snapshots.
We can create these snapshots for software,
for scripts, documents, manuscripts, websites,
configuration files.
In the Code Refinery project,
we kind of use it for everything.
So the lesson that you see is on version control,
it's on Git.
The project website is on version control
and that will become all clear
as we show you the tools that we use
over the next two weeks.
Git is not the only tool,
but we show you a Git and GitHub
because they are the most popular versions of this.
I think I will not spend more time on the motivation.
I want to see whether there are any questions and there are not too many.
So please ask questions here.
You will make really the.
We want to keep it really interactive to see.
We don't really see you in the stream.
We hope you are doing well.
But one way.
Already a question.
There was already one question asking about why GitHub and not GitLab, for instance, so
maybe we could elaborate on that a bit.
Yes.
That's a very good question.
Why do we do that?
And when you go back to the lesson overview, we have all this blue box that answers it
because it is a really good question.
And we show you GitHub.
So we are not sponsored by GitHub.
We have no affiliation with GitHub.
we show you the service, which is owned by Microsoft,
which is proprietary,
because it is the most popular web hosting for Git.
And even if you choose other services,
like GitLab, like Bitbucket, and there are more,
and we will link to them,
it's, the probability is high that you
at least use somebody else's code that is on GitHub.
So we find it, it's probably useful for you
if you know how it works.
And all the things that we will learn with GitHub,
they also work with the other services.
And once you get the understanding of how it works,
it will be easy for you to move between those.
Good, thanks for keeping the questions coming.
Maybe just one quick comment about GitHub versus GitHub,
for instance.
My one motivation is also that most of the projects
that you will work with in the future
are most likely on GitHub
if they are publicly developed projects.
So therefore I think it makes sense
to get you familiar with the tools that GitHub provides.
There are some very small differences in how the UI looks,
like the user interface looks on the websites,
but it's nothing that stops you from using it.
And I really appreciate the comments that come in.
we might return to those.
I will now navigate to,
we are almost at the first exercise
and we will start with browsing.
So we will not make any changes yet,
but we will try to get an understanding
of an existing project.
So I will go to this episode here,
copy and browse an existing project.
And please help me pasting the link to the notes.
And we will give you a whoops, we will give you a short intro of what this is.
And then we will send you into an exercise, the exercise, you will be able to do on your
own or with a group.
And then after the exercise, we will take a break.
And then we will discuss the findings.
Here we prepared an existing project for you and the project is, it's a recipe book.
So we will not only learn how Git works, we will also have a nice recipe book of cooking
recipes which you can then use at home in your kitchen.
Our goal is to really give you an understanding of what are the building blocks.
What is really nice about this version that we present now for the very first time is
that we give you different paths, you can choose your own path.
You can spend everything we will do today, you can do on GitHub alone, if you want to.
So all you need is a GitHub account.
If you like for those who don't want to do that on GitHub, who would rather follow on
Visual Studio code, you can then choose to follow that path.
We also offer all the steps to do also on the command line.
So really you can choose.
And in future we plan to add more paths also for Jupyter, RStudio, Spyder, PyCharm, contributions
Welcome and we will start our very first step and I will demonstrate it but you can then
do it in the exercise is I will create a so-called fork and fork is a new term and think of it
as making a copy.
So I will create a copy of something called repository.
And if you want to know a little bit more about what is really a repository you can
even click on these and it will take you to, we have a quick reference and a glossary.
So it will explain you if some of the terms you never heard before, what is a fork? What
is a repository? You can read these nice descriptions. So I will show you that, but I want to tell
you that when you create this copy, you can then choose, we created this recipe book,
But we have two versions of it.
And you can choose which one you copy.
There is this one, the recipe book, and we have one which is called recipe book recorded.
Here on stream, I will only show the recorded one.
And this is just to make sure that those who don't want to, if you don't want your GitHub
account, or anything you do, ever to show up in any recording or stream, then choose
this one.
But it will help us if few people work on this repository, because then we have something
to show here on stream.
Something that you will do then in the exercise is you can open it up in a browser tab.
And assuming that you have a GitHub account that you are logged in, and here we assume
that you went through the install instructions.
The first step you will do is to forget to make a copy and I can see that three copies
already exist. And I will create the fourth one. So what the first step will be to click
on this fork, boom. And then you can copy it into your own user account. And in this
case, this is my user. Yes, I want to keep the name. There is a description. Do I want
to copy the main branch only? Yeah, it doesn't matter. I think I want to copy everything.
not. And we didn't even tell you what is a branch, we will come back to that. So here
doesn't matter so much, but I will, I want to copy everything. And once I create the
fork, I it takes a few seconds. I have my own copy of it. And you can see that this
is your own copy. If on top left, you see your own username. And you can also see that
this has been copied from forked from this place.
And the rest of the exercise will be,
you will do it in this, inside this fork.
So the exercise steps are here.
And we know that you still need to learn how to do this.
So below the exercise,
you can find solutions walkthrough screenshots,
And you can choose your journey.
So choose your path.
Is it maybe GitHub?
So if you are unsure, just take the GitHub.
If you are sure you want something else,
then choose a different path.
And what we expect from you is to get an overview,
browse the commit history.
You will then see, visually see what are commits,
what are the changes.
You will see the network graph.
Maybe let me show you that
so that you know what to look out for.
So something that you will see in this insights network,
you will see that there are these commits,
changes, versions.
You will see that there are branches,
that there are different people.
And then we have a couple of questions for you, like when was a certain recipe in this
recipe book modified last, how many changes, which recipes include a certain ingredient.
So you will learn how to search through our Git repository.
And you will also learn how to find out when a certain certain line of code was modified
last.
So somebody actually modified the guacamole recipe.
And you will find out who added the cilantro to the recipe.
And then some more questions.
Can you use this recipe yourself?
Are you allowed to share modifications?
And also you will learn how to browse issues and so called pull requests.
and you should think about like what this might be good for.
We have hints.
So in each of these steps, there is a hint
and then please go through.
So this is not a spoiler, go through the solution,
go through the walk through and try this out.
And I think we will give you 20 minutes.
And then when we get back, we will take a break.
We will take a 10 minute break after the exercise.
And then after the break, [Name] and me
will show you some of the aspects
that are the most interesting,
maybe the most problematic,
and we will also react to the questions
that you have on the collaborative notes.
Here, on the bottom of the collaborative notes, where we are, what the expectation is.
So this is our first exercise.
It will be not until 55 past, but it will be up until six minutes past and then break.
I will modify that.
Try it out, see you after the exercise,
but then we will go into break
and then we will discuss more after the break.
Let us also know how it's going
through the, during the exercise, have fun.
See you then, bye.
you
And I think that's it for this session.
I hope you enjoyed it.
I'll see you next time.
Bye-bye.
Bye.
you
All right, and we are back from the break, hopefully.
I'll just try to control the streaming settings
and it's a new thing for me.
So hopefully you're back and everything is good.
I have the screen share.
Hope you had a good break.
Now, I want to show you some of the steps
from the previous exercise
before we move on to the next episode,
because I know that there were many new things.
But it was a choice from us
because we wanted to really kind of throw you
into something existing.
And our hope is that when you see a commit,
you will get an understanding of what it is
instead of us first describing it theoretically.
The other thing that we hope is that
by providing you these different paths,
that it's a little bit like if you've seen,
there are these books which when you open it up
on one side of the page is one language
and on the other side is a different language.
And they can really help you learning a new language.
And here, the hope is that if you have
maybe already been in GitHub,
but you are curious about the command line,
you will recognize some of these things better
and vice versa.
But in a theory, let me show you some of the,
let's go through some of the steps now
before I hand over the mic to [Name].
So what was the first thing I was supposed to do?
I was supposed to fork.
Here is my fork.
I was supposed to browse the commit history.
In my repository here,
are there are 25 commits, 25 changes.
And if I click this timeline link,
I can see these 25 changes.
They all have an author.
They have a timestamp.
they have a message.
So we have a one line summary.
So it's a little bit like a logbook.
Keep keeping a logbook of changes as we program our code.
Also notice that each of these changes
has a unique identifier.
And we might, when we say commit hash,
this is what we mean.
This is a short version of it.
It's actually 40 characters.
But each of these changes is unique.
We can uniquely label them.
Okay, what was the next thing?
I was supposed to look at the network graph.
This is something I do very often, insights, network.
And in the network, we get this nice visual overview
of these are the commits.
And here the blue line and the green line
These were different branches.
So there is a main branch,
there is a little sticky note main,
but there are other branches.
And in the next exercise already,
we will learn how to create these branches.
We will also discuss what they are good for.
So here, somebody created the branch,
experimented with a vegetarian lasagna,
and then found that this was good
and wanted to have that in the main branch.
So we see that developments got merged.
This is a merge point.
And here's another one.
What else were we supposed to do?
If I go back, when was a file last modified?
You can actually see it here.
So this was last week.
You can see that we created this a week ago.
And if I want to know, how about the salads?
Yeah.
So also here last week, which recipe including green salt on GitHub, you can search for it
up here.
But some of you have noticed that it takes a little bit of time, the very first time
when you search for anything,
because it needs to create this search index.
But now it will list me all the files that contain salt.
So this can be really useful
if you look through a code project
and you are not sure in which file was it,
was this error message that I'm looking for.
Okay, now let's go to the guacamole recipe.
Where was it?
It was under sites and guacamole.
And now there is this really useful feature
which has a really unfortunate name.
Blame, so that's historical reasons.
A better name would have been to annotate.
But it's so incredibly useful because it will split
my code into two halves.
On the right side, I see the recipe.
But on the left side, I see line by line, which commit modified a specific line, the
last.
So now if I'm curious about who added this cilantro, because personally, I don't like
cilantro so much, I would consider it a bug.
And much more important than who is when.
If I want to know when was this introduced,
I can click on the commit.
And this is the change that introduced it.
So this fantasy person last week introduced
in this commit, this change.
This will be very useful for you in your,
like for reproducibility.
And I get the feedback that I was scrolling really fast
and it's hard to follow where the mouse pointer is.
So I will try to be more careful.
The good news is that everything I show now,
we have screenshots for this,
and you can find it in the solution and in the walkthrough.
Back to the overview, can I use these recipes myself?
The thing that I would look for before using anything
is the license, is there a license file?
Yes, there is one.
And GitHub even recognizes it,
that it's a so-called CC0 license.
We will learn more about licenses next week,
but if I click here on top right,
I can even get some information of,
no, I need to click on the license file itself.
On top, it will give me a summary
of what are things I can do, cannot do,
any conditions, in this case, there are no conditions.
And then there are issues and pull requests, but we will see more of issues and pull requests
on Thursday.
And some people asked, so if I go back to my fork, why don't I see any issues in my
fork?
This is something that you can enable in settings, but many projects decide to keep track of
of all the issues and bug reports in a central place.
So I will be able to find them if I go back
to the place where I forked from.
I will go back to the so-called upstream repository.
And here I see that there is an issue tab,
there is a pull requests,
we will see what they are good for.
And issues is not only for problems,
it's also for sharing an idea.
So it can, you can even share an idea for something before starting all the work.
Good.
I think I will go, how about you take the screen from me, and then we talk.
Now we will take it a step further and we will instead of just browsing a repository
created by somebody else.
we will learn how do we make changes to it on GitHub,
but also locally for those who want to.
Okay.
Yeah, thank you, [Name].
So we will now focus on the second lesson.
For those of you who want to follow the lesson yourself,
you can find it here.
It's on the top, commit changes.
And in this part now, in the next hour,
we will discuss in further detail commits,
branches, and also tags.
So you're already familiar with commits
since you've now inspected the history
of an existing repository,
but now we will discuss how to create commits.
So this is probably the Git feature
that you will use the most often,
since every time you change a file
or create a new file in your Git repository
and you want to save it,
you want to have it available in the future as well
through the, when you go back in your history,
then you can create a git commit.
Now, usually, we will start on the main branch,
so branches are different ways how to structure
or like how to have different versions of your repository.
So this is indicated here by this nice figure here,
where we have this mascot of a popular programming language.
in this case, it's Go, which is lying on the main branch.
And branches can be thought of lines of development.
So nowadays, all new Git repositories,
if you create a new repository in GitHub or some GitLab,
it will be called the main branch,
but you could name it whatever you want.
In the past, it has been called master,
but because of historical reasons,
people have now decided that main should be the new default.
And in theory, you can still name it whatever you want,
but I think it's a good idea to follow
the convention of calling it the main branch
since that's what's mostly used.
Now, if we now want a whole team work on this code
or like in this painting, let's say,
it would be very difficult if it would be a real painting
to have multiple people working on different parts
of the painting at the same time.
However, with Git, since this is typically code bases
we work with, we can create digital copies of this branch.
In this case, we create two,
One, which is here, the sunglass branch,
and the other one, which is this graduation hat branch.
And then one part of your team can then focus
on the implementation of the sunglasses.
The other one can focus on the implementation
of something different.
And then if you want later,
and you're happy with the results,
they can be merged back into the main branch.
So these branches here are sometimes also called
developer or the developing branches.
As long as they don't show any conflicts,
which means that they work on the same feature
and then try to merge it into the main branch,
will work just fine, but we will discuss this in further detail later.
Now, the last thing which is mentioned here, which you probably have not encountered yet
when you went through the history of the repository before is called tags.
And these are selected commits that you can mark as tags with a specific name,
which can be very useful if you want to have one commit that you want to be easily accessible in
the future. So in the context of this recipe book, for instance, it could be when we decide
to make a printed version of this book, then of course, you
cannot change the version, the printed version anymore. So it
will be good in the future to have committed, we can easily
find which then is the same version as the one that is
printed, even though the project on GitHub might still develop in
other directions. Or to be maybe use an example, which is more
relevant for you as researchers, if you have a manuscript or a
publication, that you submit to a journal, then it could be a
very good idea to create a tag for the version that you
you submitted. And then once you receive the review comments, and
then you change the repository, which is connected to your
publication, then you can create a new tag for every new version
that you submit, and then for the published one as well. So
this can be very useful for this as well. In my case, when I
wrote my PhD thesis three years ago, it was also very useful to
create tags whenever I wanted to have a version that I sent to my
supervisor, so he could read through it and give comments on
so that way I could work on my thesis,
which was written in LaTeX
and therefore easily storable on GitHub.
And then every time I have a version,
or like a chapter which was done,
I could then create a tag on it
and then send it to someone else to read it.
So there was no problem
with having the latest version, for instance.
Maybe just one more sentence
I should mention for the branches.
I was mentioning before that this is very useful
if you have a whole team
which is working on one code base,
but it can also be very useful if you work alone,
since you want to experiment.
So you want to, you have an idea about a new feature
or like something which you could implement
in a better way, but you don't want to touch
the main branch since that's the one
that other people might take a look at,
or also you just want to have like a main batch
which is kind of relatively clean in its history.
So you can create a new branch,
try implementing some new code,
and if you're happy with it, you can merge it,
but if it turns out that it doesn't go the way you want,
you see that you haven't pulled through
all the steps necessary, then you can just delete it
without having to do any changes to the main branch.
Of course, in theory, you could have done this also
just to the main branch,
and then kind of deleted the last couple of commits,
but I would say that this is not particularly clean.
Now, we have, again, an exercise set here,
which takes approximately 20 minutes,
where we'll now create commits,
and on top of the branch, on top of the,
sorry, on top of the repository
that you've been working with in the past,
in a new branch.
And I will now show the first two, three steps live,
and then I will leave the remaining steps to you.
And then at the end, we can then,
after the exercises,
we can go through some of the questions.
I will do this now in GitHub,
but if there is time remaining,
I will do the same thing,
or at least show some of the parts also in VS Code.
Now, I go now to the recipe book recorded repository,
which is in the Code Refinery GitHub project.
And first of all, what I will do is to create a fork.
I've already done this.
So we just create a fork now.
I copy it to my own account.
Just a question, [Name].
Should we, we should now watch or should we do something?
I will, I will, everything I'm doing now
is also shown in the in the description it's just two it's just the first two
steps I thought so that we make sure that everyone uses the right repository
and first commit yeah and the fork people have already done in the previous
exercise but here we show it it's good that we show it because just to make
sure that everybody's on the same page also if people join later yeah so this
takes now just a few seconds and now we have a copy again of this repository
and in this case, we are still on the main branch.
However, if I now want to introduce a new feature
or like a new recipe, I can now create a new branch name.
And then I click on create branch.
And this will now create,
it'll copy over all the code from the previous branch
into this new one.
And the last thing I will just quickly show
is then how to create a new commit.
So in my case, I like pasta a lot,
so I want to add a recipe here,
so I can keep an add file.
I can copy now something into
a new file into,
or like some, a new recipe.
I need to give it a name in this case
because it's a new file.
So in this case, it's a tomato dazzle.
recipe and I commit the changes.
And now this is the new part for you.
We can now create a commit message.
That's the one that the other one was showing just before.
So this would be this one line message.
And then we have also the option
to give a more extended description of this change.
Now, if you have a small project
and it might not be necessary
to have like a very detailed extended description here.
And in this case, I think it's not necessary
since it's kind of self-descripted.
But in the future, if you would work with a larger project,
then they might actually have some expectations
or like some rules on how you have to create these commits.
So there might be some template
for what to add into the extension descriptions.
But in this case, we just keep it simple.
And we now see that we have,
if you go now to the history,
we have now created a new commit
with the description that we chose before.
and also the new hash that was generated for us.
So this is the identifier of this commit.
Okay, I think this is enough for now.
I will now mute myself and in 20 minutes,
we will get back and discuss some of the problems
that some people have seen
and maybe discuss some interesting questions.
Yes, so we'll be back of 55 minutes past the hour.
And then we will do a quick summary.
before we take a longer break. And your task is now to do the steps one to nine.
Again, let us know how it's going on the collaborative notes,
ask us questions, and then we can return to the questions and discuss them here, here on stream.
See you in 20 minutes. Bye.
you
You
Okay, so we are back.
We have five minutes before the break starts.
So there were two questions which arose,
which I would like to discuss now.
And if we have some time,
I can also quickly show how to use VS Code
for creating commits.
The first thing was about comparing.
And one, in my view, simplest way
to create two different branches or commits
is by copying the URL
and just writing compare at the end.
And this will then open this interface
where we can then here choose which branches,
repositories we want to compare.
So in this case, I will now just focus on mine.
And we can have here the main branch
and we can compare it to the new recipe branch
that I created previously.
And this way, it will now show us all the differences
between the two branches.
So we assume, in this case, the only difference is
that we have the new file that I created previously,
the tomato basil spaghetti recipe in this case.
So you will see something similar
when you create pull requests,
but that's something we will discuss later in this course.
But in my view, that's the simplest way
of comparing it on GitHub itself.
So I hope this answers one of the questions.
Another question was there was some confusion
about the creating a tag.
And on GitHub, this can be some,
maybe a little bit confusing that it has a feature
which is called releases,
which is basically the same thing.
But the simplest way of creating one is then just,
let's just quickly go back.
I click here on this button,
create a new release on the right.
And I can now choose a tag.
And now I need to actually write a new name into it
before I can create a new release or tag.
So I think this is the problem that arose there
and I think it's kind of counterintuitive in GitHub.
So if I now write new release, for instance,
then I can give it a title again.
I can provide some more information, which I won't do now.
Then I can publish a release.
And [Name], can I ask, or can we take a step back?
So when do you use branches, and when do you use tags?
And so how are they similar, how are they different, and when would you use one or the
other?
It's a very good question.
So branches I would use if I have a project where I still want to develop it, or still
make changes to the project, with the idea that I would eventually merge them.
I would use tags then when I'm not planning to make any changes to this version of the project,
but I want them to be easily accessible in the future. For instance, if I want to have like this
specific version of a manuscript that I submitted to a journal, then it makes sense to have it as a
tag in my view, because branches somehow imply that I would do some changes. In fact, I have
seen a few projects where they had like an own branch for the version that they submitted to a
journal or that was uploaded to archive, for instance, which I think isn't ideal because
these branches in theory can still be changed. Now, of course, I can always go to the history.
Since I'm using Git, I can always check what was the date when I submitted it, which was the
latest branch back then. But I think a tag makes more sense. This would be my answer to this
question. Thanks.
Thanks.
Okay.
Shall I very briefly talk about VS code
or shall we do that after the break?
What do you think about the one?
Just looking at the time,
I think we should do it after the break.
I'm just looking here to whether there's any questions
that we should pick up before we go into the break.
So let me thank everybody for the questions.
Let's have many more questions.
We want to be really overwhelmed by questions.
Let's take a, we will take a one hour break.
This is lunchtime in some time zones.
We know that this is not ideal for everybody,
but in that hour, you can a little bit
process what we learned.
And we will then do a recap.
And after the break, our plan is to learn how to
merge the changes that we did.
So we learn how to browse, how to create branch,
how to create commits,
but how do we get all of these developments
back into the main branch
that we will learn after the break.
We will be back in one hour,
back here on stream.
See you then, have a good break,
and bye everybody.
you
You
music
you
Welcome back from exercise. I actually cannot hear the jingle if there was one on my side
but maybe there was one, and hopefully you all enjoy it.
Thanks to our colleague, Matthias, who created those.
My plan is now that I want to go through the exercise,
but show you the key steps,
and I want to show you how we, how Gecko and we,
how we look at pull requests when we create them
and how we look at them when we merge them.
and I also want to go through this step of deleting branches.
And then we will take a very short break.
So then only five minute break,
and then we will back for conflict resolution.
So let me go through the steps.
I'm now here, top left is my mouse.
I'm in my branch.
I will now initiate a pull request.
Let me get more space here.
Oops.
And the first thing I always verify is from where to where.
So I want to go from this repository to this one.
No, I want to go to my own one.
So I will change this to my repository.
And then I verify from which branch to which branch.
From new recipe to main.
Yes, that's what I wanted.
I will change the title because a new recipe is not very descriptive.
So we want to have a descriptive one-line title for this was so if I remember correctly
it was so idea for a tasty pineapple salad.
Here I can give more context more context for instance if if we discussed this earlier
in an issue, I can refer to it. So more context, why I did this, what I did. And then what
I personally do before clicking create pull request, I normally scroll down and I have
a look. I had two commits. Are these the one that I intended to send? Yes. If I see some
commits that I don't recognize, then I stop. I also scroll down to the bottom and I see
what is the actual change. Is this the one that I wanted to send? Yes, this is the one.
So this looks all pretty good. Note that here if I go on the little arrow I have a choice
between create pull request and create draft pull request we will this thing can be really
useful but we will come back to that on Thursday. I'm now ready to create a pull
request. Did I forget anything? Hopefully not. Let's create it. When I create a pull
request there is a new number here in the tab pull requests. Each pull request
has a number so I can refer to them. This is the pull request number one.
And before I review it and before I merge it,
I will try to reload my network graph
and it might take again a few seconds.
But what I wanted to show you is that
just by opening up a request, I didn't really,
oh, nothing merged yet.
The main branch didn't change yet.
This is still my branch.
The tasty pineapple recipe is still not on the main branch,
but now let's review it.
And when I merge a change proposal or request,
I look at the same things, the title, what is the context?
And notice that here we can even have a discussion.
You can comment on it.
You can say this is a good idea, this is a bad idea.
You can give ideas for changes.
More about that on Thursday.
I also look at what are the commits
and what has actually changed.
I often click here, files changed.
Yep, that looks pretty okay.
I want to have that in my main branch.
merge, merge, confirm
and now it's merged, so when I now look at the network and reload it
we will see a merge commit, we will see a new commit on main which combines these two
developments. And while this is loading and refreshing, I can already, if I now check
on my main branch, and I go to Salads, here I can find it. Here's the one. Has this finished
in the meantime? It hasn't. Yes, here it is. Here's the merge commit. So now I have merged
these two changes.
And this is now a little bit hard to navigate
because we have now so many collaborators
that work on a very similar repository.
But this is really what I wanted to do.
So I'm happy with this.
But now I want to go one step further.
In the exercise, we asked you to,
okay, scroll, scroll.
We asked you to delete a branch.
And what I will show you is that when I delete a branch,
I will only delete this sticky note.
I will not delete the commits.
The commits will still remain there
because the commits are now part of another branch.
So what we wanted you to see that deleting branches
doesn't necessarily delete commits.
And we also wanted to show you
how can you safely remove branches.
One way is I can click on the button and then it's gone because here Git knows that GitHub
knows that this has been merged.
It is safe to delete the branch.
It is safe to delete the sticky note.
But what if I forget?
I forgot.
I navigated back.
How can you find out which branches are safe to delete?
You can also leave them there.
I mean, they don't cost anything.
No problem to have them there.
But after a while, maybe you will have, I have now five branches.
After a while, you might have 50 branches and you want to do some cleanup.
So what I sometimes do is I navigate here to the branches, top left.
And this is a little bit tiny font, but this symbol here tells me that this branch has
been merged.
This one has been merged, the new recipe.
It is absolutely safe to delete it, your trashcan.
And now it's deleted.
And if I now reload this page, I would have to wait a few seconds. The commit will still
be here. But this sticky note would be gone. That's all we did with deleting branches.
Super
And my suggestion is that we will take a five minute break
and then [Name] and me will return to step number seven
and we will do a pull request.
We will show you a pull request across repositories.
And at the same time, we will try to create a conflict,
but it will be a conflict
between two different code versions.
So it will be very friendly and the humans will help the programs to resolve the conflict.
Sounds good.
Just catching up here with any questions.
Yeah, so let's take a break until the full hour.
So until...
I need to make that visible.
here, break until the full hour.
And then we show you some conflict resolution
in Git directly on GitHub.
See you in five minutes.
Bye.
you
And welcome back for the last half an hour of today.
Here we will continue on the idea of creating these change proposals pull requests on GitHub.
But now we want to take it a step further.
Because what I will try to do is I will try to create a pull request between my repository
and towards the one that I forked from.
At the same time, we will, with Kaggle,
we will try to change the same recipe
in two different ways, and we will see what happens
and how do we deal with it.
Because that can happen in real life,
that you work with somebody
and you modify the same portion of the file
in two different ways.
Let's see how Git deals with this.
Also note that when I'm now on my fork,
it informs me that this branch, which is the main branch,
seems to be four commits ahead of the one that I forked from.
That's interesting because that also shows me
that the fork and the so-called upstream,
they don't automatically synchronize somehow magically.
I have to, we can synchronize it, but we have to do it actively.
So until I do it, they are really separate repositories with their separate histories.
Why four commits?
What are the four commits?
I did two commits on the new recipe branch.
I did a different commit on the main branch.
So three.
Where is the fourth one?
The fourth one was the merge commit.
It was the one where I combined new recipe with main.
So my branch is four commits ahead.
But now I will try to create a new change, and let's see what we do.
I will create a new branch, and I will call it another recipe.
It's not a great name.
It's also good if the branches are,
if the branch name is descriptive.
Let me take a descriptive branch name.
I personally like to call my branches with my name
because then I can find them again
and what I'm doing on the branch.
So in this case, I will do,
I will make a change to modify guacamole.
So now everybody, please watch.
So now no more exercise, you don't have to,
you don't have to do the same thing.
Now, please watch and let's see if I,
if I make some mistakes
and please continue asking the questions.
So I'm seeing the questions coming in.
I create this branch.
What do I need to do now?
Oh yeah, here, create branch.
Yes.
And here it is, so I'm on the new branch.
And guess what?
I will now modify the guacamole, which happens to be here, sides, guacamole.
And I can modify it directly here, the pen button on top right, edit.
What should we do with it?
So I personally am not a big fan of cilantro.
What I will do is I will reduce the cilantro amount to 0.5 tablespoons.
Something I like to do when I do this on GitHub is I switch on the preview so that I can see
what did I actually change.
showed it here I removed one I added 0.5 that looks good and now I want to commit change
on the branch
this is not a good commit message because it's it tells me what file I change but it
it doesn't really summarize what I did.
A much better commit message would be
reduce the cilantro amount.
And why did I change it?
Well, because I'm not a fan.
Does this look okay?
Yes.
Do the Guacamole branch commit changes.
If I now go back to my repository on top, there is this yellow field that also some
people were wondering about.
What is that?
This is because GitHub now recognized that I have a new branch.
I modified it recently.
I maybe want to create a pull request.
Yes.
Thank you.
I want to.
So this can be helpful sometimes.
If you don't want to create a pull request, just ignore it.
But I really want to.
And this time,
I want to create the pull request,
not inside the same repository.
I really want to send it to Code Refinery recipe book.
So this looks good.
From my branch, from my repository,
towards the main branch, Code Refinery recipe book.
Let's summarize it in a title.
reduce cilantro amount
more description if needed again i scroll down what is the change
here is the change now how come i see all these other things
which i didn't modify now this is because
my main branch was four commits ahead
and I created this new,
I created this, what was it called?
The other one modified guacamole from main,
which was four commits ahead.
So what I see here is not only the cilantro change,
but also all my other local changes.
This is fine, but maybe this is a bit misleading.
So it's not only the cilantro amount,
it's also plus new salad recipe.
So here I bake together a couple of unrelated changes
into the same pull request.
Not the best practice, but happens.
And now I will open the pull request.
Oh, there are already 18 pull requests, wonderful.
We will review them later.
We will maybe not have time now, but thanks to everybody else who sent pull requests.
This is really cool because we can now build together a recipe book.
But I suggest that now we switch the screen to [Name] and [Name] makes a pull request,
which will also modify the guacamole recipe, but in a different way.
and let's see what happens then.
And [Name], you're muted.
Thanks for telling me.
So I'm now on my fork of the recipe book recorded repository
and I will now change the same recipe
that [Name] has changed before.
In fact, in the previous exercise,
I changed the amount already,
but I will now increase it to two tablespoons of cilantro.
Oh, go for three.
I'll go for three, okay.
So I will now make a commit.
So I will now say, increase amount of cilantro.
Again, I could provide some more extended description,
is, I don't know, I really like
cilantro, for instance,
and of course provide some more explanations.
But for now, that should be enough.
I will now commit the changes.
So I have created now a new commit.
So if I go back to my repository,
I will see now again, if I click on commits,
Oh, sorry, that's the wrong branch, my bad.
So I go now to the change cilantro branch.
And I take a look at the commits, it should appear now.
And it does.
So increase amount of cilantro, that's fine.
And now I compare pull requests.
Create a pull request.
So I go and choose the repository I want to
merge my changes to.
So this would then be co-definery recipe book recorded.
That's fine.
I enter the main branch
and I do it from my local branch here,
which is in my namespace
and I use the change cilantro branch.
So I can now say, again,
I should also provide a title which is more descriptive.
So increase cilantro in,
Oh, remind me of the way, it's okay.
Guacamole recipe.
Then I quickly check the changes.
In this case, I have two commits.
One in the first, which was in the previous exercise,
where I reduced it, now I increased it.
And here, down here again, I see the changes
actually in the files directly.
So this is what I want to merge.
And I can see here that I increased the amount
Cilantro by free. So I will now create the pull request and then I will give the
screen back to another one.
All righty, I will take the screen and let's see how it looks on my side.
Just a sec.
Here I have it.
And I'm now looking at the, that's not my fork,
that's the central repository.
And I clicked on the pull requests map.
There are 21 open, 22 now.
Thanks to all of you,
we will look through them and merge them.
Maybe some of you tried to merge these
and now you realize that you cannot.
And this is a bit by design,
but now because now only the code refinery team
has the permissions to merge and modify this repository.
But don't worry, we will on Thursday
when we really practice collaboration,
we will create exercise repositories
where you also have permissions to review
and merge and modify those.
So then you will also practice being the person
who is reviewing these changes.
So now I want to focus on two changes.
One is the one that I created,
and the other one is the one that [Name] created.
And now I will do something which is not super nice.
I shouldn't really review my own changes,
but now for the sake of time,
I don't want to switch too much back and forth.
I will review my own change.
And of course it's excellent,
but I will still double check here.
Is this what I really wanted?
what's happening here, lots of changes,
but that looks pretty okay.
Overall, I will merge it into main branch.
And now it is, is it safe to delete?
Yes, it's safe to delete.
Now it is on the main branch in the central repository.
And that worked.
But let's see what happens when I now try to merge [Name]'s change.
This one, the pull request number 39.
Here we go.
Something is different here and it's this one.
It doesn't let me merge, I can't really click here because there are conflicts.
And why are there conflicts?
Because on two different branches, we have changed the same portion in two different
ways.
The Git now doesn't know which one do we want to keep, like, do we want to keep the one
that is now on main?
Or do I want to keep the one that the change that comes in from this other branch, and
we have to help get deciding.
It's really good that it stops here, because it doesn't, it will not just accidentally
let Gago override my changes. So it stops here. It, it needs some human advice. So let's try
it together. And you can, you can do it in many different ways, but we will try it here
directly on GitHub and Gago will help me. So I click first on resolve conflicts just
just to see what is the conflict.
And it doesn't now show me all the, if you remember, I have changed a couple of files.
It was, I changed guacamole, but there was also some pineapple salad and there was some
other change.
But we only conflict in this one file, and we only conflict in this one portion.
These that I see here, these symbols are so-called conflict markers, they tell me where
is the conflict.
And the conflict is between main and between the main branch, and the change cylinder branch.
On the main branch, I reduced it to 0.5.
On the ChangeCylinder branch, it was changed from 1 to 3.
And we need to decide now.
And I will now not take my own version, but I will take this version.
And the way to resolve a conflict is, and whether you are on GitHub or whether you are
and your editor, that's to decide which version.
And then don't forget to remove these markers also.
They should not stay there.
So I will, I decide to keep three, remove these markers.
And once we are happy, mark it as resolved.
And now what we don't see because I'm zoomed in is that on the top right there is a button
commit merge.
I also this resolution needs to be committed to be a new commit that decides between the
two versions.
the merge. So these were, [Name] did in fact two commits, one was this one, one was this.
Where does this come from? This was my resolution commit. The conflict resolution created a
new commit because it merges between [Name]'s branch and the main branch.
Now, before I merge it, I want to review
what did we get at the end.
Files changed.
At the end, it's changed from 0.5 to three.
Are we happy?
We are happy.
Let's merge.
This was a relatively easy conflict.
Sometimes, the conflict will require that you actually talk to the other person and
discuss with them on, maybe you schedule a video call, but at least now you know technically
on how to tell Git which version you like better.
Back to the lesson, I will now scroll down to the summary.
What did we learn?
And what did we learn in this lesson?
What did we learn today?
We learned how to browse a project,
how to create commits and branches.
And in this episode, we learned how to merge them,
how to merge two branches together.
This is the basis of collaboration.
We will use this a lot on Thursday.
And it's really useful also for your own work.
If you want to put something unfinished
finished or something that you aren't sure about
on a side branch and not on main.
But when you are new to Git, it's also fine really
to start just with one branch, create commits.
Better to many commits than to few commits.
They don't have to be beautiful.
And same with pull requests.
If I may quickly mention this one question
which came up in the documents,
what to do if I have like a pull request
and I only want to merge half of it.
I think the best strategy
is to create many small pull requests
if you're able to separate it
so that this situation doesn't arise.
So in the ideal case,
you have one pull request for one encapsulated feature
or one change instead of one huge one.
Exactly.
So at the beginning, start using these features.
then later what is a good practice
is to not put unrelated things into a commit
because it is hard to separate unrelated things.
Also don't put too much into a pull request.
Not unrelated things into a pull request
is something I've done here.
So what if the guacamole recipe change was good
but my pineapple salad wasn't good?
So then suddenly it becomes a little bit difficult
to separate the one from the other.
So what would it be nicer is to create
two separate pull requests, which create nice little units.
A small pull request is easier to review
than a gigantic one.
Nobody wants to look through 20,000 lines of code,
but at the beginning, it's good to use them
and make it nicer later.
So don't let the beautiful commits
and the beautiful pull requests be the enemy
of just good enough.
Looking at other questions, we have nine minutes left.
We want to use it now.
We can do a little bit more discussion,
but one thing we should not forget is to,
we would like to hear feedback from you.
Maybe somebody can paste our feedback form
into these documents.
So what we would like to hear from you
is what went well today
then what should we improve today?
So what should we remove, change, do differently?
This is very important for us
because we look at the feedback, we use it.
If there is something we can improve already
until tomorrow, we will do.
And I hear that there is cut visible on the screen
on the stream and even audible, but I don't hear that.
So that's too bad for us instructors, [Name],
but apparently there are some cut sightings on stream.
So please, now that I share it, please give us feedback.
Was it, how did it go?
Was it too fast, too slow?
Tell us one good thing about today.
This feedback is anonymous.
What was good about today?
Tell us one thing that we should improve for next time.
And next time is maybe already tomorrow.
Any other feedback will come.
And while the feedback is coming in, I want to look at,
is there any other question?
Maybe the one about how exactly are conflicts happening?
For example, what if we change lines?
What if the change lines are moved?
Could be considered different lines
and therefore different entries,
even if they are changing the same thing.
That's an excellent question.
And Git is really smart about this.
it doesn't look at blind numbers.
It uses some really smart algorithms to decide
which parts are the same thing,
even as the code evolves,
even across file renames.
So it is really smart.
It is often not a problem.
You will probably not see it when working just on your own.
You might see it when collaborating.
When it happens, it's not a big deal.
You now know how to resolve it technically.
We will also on Thursday, when we do collaboration,
we will discuss on what are good strategies
so that we can avoid conflicts from even happening.
And in one sentence, the strategy would be
keep branches small, keep commits small,
don't do too many things at the same time,
then the likelihood that there will be conflicts is smaller.
We are doing amazing with time, five minutes left, yes.
Did you comment on how we do very similar things tomorrow,
but with VS code and command line and locally?
That's a great prompt here.
There was a question comment about that.
That's a great.
So let's, with everything we did today,
how will that connect to tomorrow?
Tomorrow we will learn how to clone a repository
and work locally.
Some of you have done it already.
Tomorrow we will take this recipe,
make a copy onto our computer
and learn committing, branching, merging locally.
Locally, we will, this is possible either in VS code or command line.
But even if you don't, if the command line doesn't work for you, you don't want to install
VS code, please still come tomorrow.
Because the other episode tomorrow will not.
You can do them only on GitHub if you want to.
So the second episode will be we will do some of the repository browsing and history inspection
but a little bit more in depth than today.
We will study a repository that we don't know.
It's written by somebody else but we will try to figure a few things out about it.
This is a very typical situation.
And then tomorrow the finale will be to turn your own project and it doesn't have to be
a real project where you don't have to share your project
that you have on a computer,
but we will create your own example project,
but learn how to turn it, make it a Git repository
and how to share it on GitHub or GitLab.
And what would be the next steps
if you want to make your project citable.
So these are the goal for tomorrow.
We will then tomorrow also talk a bit more about the balance.
what is a good balance when you start using it, of where to start, how to progress,
and what are typical things, typical problems that you want to avoid?
Of course, you're already welcome to browse these, and then tomorrow come with lots of questions.
questions. So, if someone has tried the VS code track today. Are there is tomorrow something
different than today. Do you learn new things. Yes, there will be. So, if you have done this
already today then the first episode, there will be some repetition but I think it doesn't
harm, to get it a little bit more into our muscle memory, there will be something new
and that is, we will take a closer look at what is the difference between a local branch
and a remote branch. And we got a few questions about it today, we didn't really talk about
it by design, but tomorrow we will hopefully give an understanding that you see the difference
between what is a local branch and remote branch. This is something that confused me
a lot when I started using it. So that will be different already in episode one.
Yes. Okay. And if someone starts from tomorrow and hasn't been here today, I guess that works
fine. Also, that's fine. No problem. Invite your friends and so on.
Exactly. So even if, or even if you were here today and everything failed, and I don't know
you don't find the repositories again, please come tomorrow. You don't need to have the things
from today for the tomorrow's exercises. We invite your friends. It's really fine and welcome to
join just for a day or just for an episode.
And thanks a lot for the feedback. One thing that was really good and one thing to improve.
Yeah, and we should thank [Name] for this latest lesson redesigned.
And [Name].
Well, yeah, but I was gone on the weekend when [Name] was working on it.
But anyway, it was a great effort to rewrite it this new way that introduces it with GitHub as the main flow, main path, and the other things there.
there.
So we're really looking forward to see
how this goes for future days.
And you can all help us contributing.
We know that there are some rough edges.
If you go into the Git history of the lesson,
you will see that there has been some weekend work
and late changes.
So this will evolve as we go.
But now, I mean, in this workshop,
we learn how to contribute to other people's projects
and your contributions and issues and ideas are really what makes this go.
Yeah, so I guess there's no new questions. So, you can expect videos to be processed
by later this evening.
If you want to be more involved, consider joining the Code Refinery chat and asking
what you can do.
We've got different stuff that people can look at.
Anyway, yeah, anything else or?
Yeah, we need more cats tomorrow.
So that's a clear takeaway here from the feedback.
But I think I'm happy.
I don't know, Gego, did we forget something?
No, I think we went through most of the important things that we were planning to go for anyway.
We can go through the documents today in the afternoon and see whether we missed anything
and maybe, if there is time, we can discuss it tomorrow.
Thanks so much, [Name].
I'm looking forward to teach with you again then on Thursday.
Tomorrow we will be with [name].
Really looking forward to it.
Thanks everybody.
to all the people answering questions, working in local rooms. Thanks to [Name] for the
intro. There are lots of people who make this happen. Have a nice afternoon. See you all
tomorrow.
OK, thanks so much.
Bye.
See you next time.