CodeRefinery.org
you
You
♪
one and two, so be prepared to also look back
into the Git intro lesson if there is concepts
that you maybe need to look up again.
But if you are joining us for the first time today
and you know the basic concepts of Git,
then you will also be very well prepared
to follow the exercises and also the lesson materials.
For the hands-on exercises,
you need to make sure that your authentication to GitHub is working so you can check this in
the installation instructions and that is when you are working on your own computer.
But many of the things you can also do just from the GitHub web interface.
And today it really all comes together so everything that we learned in day one and two
You will be present in today's exercises.
This also means that it might be harder to follow if you really just learned about version
control, but please don't give up.
If it's going too fast, if there is too many new concepts popping up here and there, then
just take a step back, try to follow as you can, and remember that you can always come
back and review as necessary.
are joining today for the first time just briefly how this workshop works. So everyone watches the
live stream, the thing you're watching now on Twitch. We will have exercises that you can do
either in your own teams that you have that you are maybe in right now or if you don't have a
team then you can also do them on your own. And we will have a minimum of 10 minutes break on every
hour. For communication from you with the instructors but also the instructors to you,
we use a collaborative document and if you registered you got the link in the email
that you got after registering and that looks something like this.
And here you can see all the important links that you need for this workshop,
the agenda with the links also for example to the material I just showed behind this short
welcome and practicalities. And then we have an icebreaker and the way we can answer that icebreaker
is we find this little pen symbol which might be up here or somewhere up to the right with some edit.
You can click that, that changes you into edit mode. Then we can scroll down here and answer
for example, the question what you had for breakfast, I had some bread with some cheese.
And you can also do that now, just add another line here and put in what you had. And then
what has been the most collaborative project so far? As mentioned before already, mine
is code refinery materials. Mostly I'm working on my own. And then we have here the question
and answer section. So whenever during the day you have a question, you can put it here
in the collaborative document and the instructors will have a look at it. And then we also have
a whole team behind the scenes which will answer your questions here.
And the lesson materials are available, will stay available and are linked from the
workshop web page and then the recordings will be available on Twitch for some days still and then
will go on the Code Refinery YouTube channel. We have also updated our instructions for the
certificates, which is also linked from the Code Refinery Workshop page. If you go on that one,
you can find the link to certificates up here and find the instructions there.
And then one small reminder that on March 26th and April 2nd, we have Bring Your Own Code session,
where you can really bring your own code or bring your own project and get some help from
our experts in implementing the concepts that you learn here in the course. Also,
or the version control, for example,
if you have some bigger, more in-depth question about it.
And now I will give over to our instructors for today,
which are [Name] and [Name].
Thanks, [Name].
Let me take a screen,
and then we will start by saying hi and who we are.
Just a second.
Here we go.
I'll keep the collaborative notes open.
Hello, everybody. Good morning. Day three of the workshop today. We will take Git and version
control to the next level. My name is [Name] and what I like to do, I like to help
researchers with their coding and programming and computation. I come from computational
chemistry and these days spend time with code refinery, with high-performance computing,
and teaching. And I will be together with lots of people that you see or don't see.
I will take you through the lesson today, but my co-instructor today is [Name].
Good morning. My name is [Name]. I'm also part of the high performance computing group
here at UIT in Tromsø, Norway. And in my case, I have a background in computational
physics. So I was doing a postdoc here at UIT before I switched over to the HPC group.
So both [Name] and I can relate to the struggles and challenges that you as researchers might face
for anything coding related. Looking forward to this seminar.
And first of all, I took a lot of notes on my paper that I want to go through, some housekeeping.
So, on the bottom of the collaborative notes, you find the link to the lesson that we will
go through today.
And that's the page that is on the upper part of my screen.
And what I recommend you to do, if you had the tab open, maybe you were curious about
it yesterday, one thing I recommend you to do, reload the page.
So F5, reload it.
Make sure you get the fresh version.
We have been making changes to it until late night yesterday.
So it's like, it's like, you know, when you take a cake out of the oven, it's still warm.
It's amazing.
Hopefully, it's not undercooked, and hopefully, we don't get stomach ache.
But I think we have a really nice lesson for you.
We will have three exercise sessions.
they will all be even,
there will be longer exercise sessions
than the previous days.
I think we will need probably at least half an hour
for each exercise, maybe longer.
So today it will be really important
that you communicate back to us how it is going.
And we thought about all the possibilities
how people can participate.
So in groups or on your own.
So all of this will be possible.
Or expect chaos.
We expect chaos.
This is one of the most fun parts of the workshop
because we will all start in collaborating
a hundred people together, anything can happen.
So it will be chaotic.
This is what we expect.
This will be a lot of fun.
Once we start collaborating,
please remember code of conduct.
I mean, we are collaborating on a repository
that will be public.
Let's make sure that we are all comfortable.
let's not commit or send pull requests with any weird things.
So I wanted to say that.
Then I wanted to say that everything today
is possible to do on GitHub alone.
If you don't have any editor,
if your command line doesn't work,
if your authentication to GitHub doesn't really work,
it's not a problem, don't give up.
you can do all the exercises today on GitHub alone,
if you choose to.
We will build on the knowledge that we got
in day one and day two.
But even if you joined only today,
there will be links and you will have time to read up.
The exercises will need some time to set up.
We will give exercise leads time for that.
I will also show you some behind the scenes
of what we need to do to make this workshop,
to make these exercises possible for everybody.
So I will show you that in a moment.
And I will now go into these, the concepts.
Okay.
Before we go, so someone said that [Name]'s voice
was a little bit low.
Can you do another audio test?
Or [Name], can you say something?
Or increase your volume?
Am I still too low?
If I speak like this?
I can increase the input volume if that's necessary.
I guess it probably needs to be increased some.
Even if it gets metallic.
I hope it's better now.
Sounds good to my side.
Not too metallic.
Sorry about that.
I guess...
Well, it's...
Well, okay.
Okay, they say it's better and keep commenting if it needs to be adjusted more later.
Okay.
Yeah.
So it's good that this was pointed out and sounds good, no problem at all.
I will now navigate into concepts and this is a connection to the previous days.
We will not go here through all the details again.
What we want to do today is use all the building blocks,
creating branches, creating commits,
creating pull requests and put them all together.
And now we will be able to collaborate.
We will really learn how to propose changes
to repositories of other people.
And we will be able to review changes
contributed by others.
And some concepts that we heard mentioned in the last days.
And here you can browse these read up,
like what is a repository?
What is a commit?
What is a branch?
What is a tag?
The one thing I want to show now here with [Name],
we have pictures on it,
like what is the difference between cloning and forking?
This is a question that came up a few times.
And I will scroll across the text and go straight to the pictures.
So those of you who will, who prefer to do the changes on your computer, in an editor
or on the command line, at some point, there will be a cloning step today.
And a clone creates a full copy.
And here we have this picture of a cloud because this repository is on a cloud service.
It's somewhere on the internet, and it contains branches and commits.
It contains also a tag.
And when you clone it, you copy everything.
And something that we have seen in one of the exercises yesterday, is that when we clone
All the branches are still there, but the branches get renamed.
So there is origin slash something, and origin is the place where we clone from.
It's a placeholder.
And it will typically create one local branch for us to work on, which is the default branch,
which will be the main branch.
So one thing that is missing here in this picture is that it will also create a local
branch called main from the default branch on the cloud service. So that is cloning.
And how does it differ from forking? Technically, it's very similar. So technically, clone and
fork are implemented in a very similar way. But if I scroll down here to the other picture,
a fork is also a copy. This is something we have done on Tuesday. And this is something
we will do today again. And that is making a full copy, but it stays in the on the internet.
And it it is a copy from somewhere to my own user space. And it could be from a place where
I cannot write cannot where I'm not allowed to create new commits to a place where I'm
allowed to make new commits.
This is often a starting point to make modifications
and it's a starting point for collaboration.
And in principle on my fork, I can do anything I like,
but I should always have a look at the license
because the license will tell me what are the things
that I'm allowed to do, expected to do.
But if the license allows me to do things,
I can do whatever I want on my fork.
I'm just here taking a pause because I see questions, which is awesome.
They are down here and I also see them on a different screen.
Does a commit does a fork inherit the commit history and branches of the so called upstream
repository as it does all the branches and all the commits.
But after I created the fork, it will not.
So if the left repository here then gets new commits and new branches, they don't automatically
go into my fork.
If I don't, if I create a fork and never touch it again, it will stay frozen in time.
And at the time when I copied it.
But today we will learn how do you update your fork and we will see that this used to
be more difficult.
It became two mouse clicks.
But we will practice that today.
We will see in an exercise how our fork gets out of date and we will learn how to update
it.
And one more mechanism that we will see today and we will use it to, we used it to create
exercise repositories. And the groups will use it to create their exercise repositories
is generating from a template. So you can take a git repository on the left side with
commits and branches. And you can make it a so called template. And from it, you can
generate new repositories. And if we stay in the cooking and baking analogy, it's like
a cookie cutter, like when you when you make, if you bake cookies, maybe you have like this
metallic cookie cutter, and you can then cut equally looking cookies with it. So then the
the cookie cutter will be my template
and I can generate repositories that look the same.
What happens when you generate a repository
is that all the history is flattened.
So it will flatten all the history into one commit.
So when you, when later, when we practice,
you will recognize that, oh, that's again,
with this repository book, sorry, the recipe book,
but there is only one commit
because all the history will get flattened into one commit.
But that's fine because this will be a starting point today
for us, and then we do all the collaboration
and the branches on top of that.
I will not talk about this part about importing.
So there are even more ways to get a repository,
to copy a repository,
But the point I want to make, and we will experience it.
So we can fork and we can clone.
But after we have done that, these repositories don't automatically talk to each other.
We need to actively tell them to.
And we do that either by pulling changes or by pushing changes.
And this, so then on the command line,
you will type git pull or git push.
And then if you work on VS code,
you will click on icon that says publish branch,
but under the hood, it will then push your branch.
So we need to actively synchronize changes.
And all the other operations that we do
when you work on a computer,
like creating commits, creating branches,
They are all local.
They don't need network.
Only push, pull,
and clone need travel over the network cable.
Okay, another look at the questions.
One question was about this flattening that I mentioned.
Is it the same thing like squashing?
Yeah, you could think of it.
So all the commits are squashed into one.
So technically it's the same thing.
So we don't need to really understand this today.
It's only that if you wonder why is,
why does the exercise only contain one single commit?
That's because we generate it from a template.
Did I forget anything important before we move on
and prepare you for the exercise?
Hopefully not.
So I will scroll up and go to the next episode.
And I want to prepare you for the exercise.
We will give you a lot of exercise time here, sorry here collaborating within the same repository.
Here is now we want to do collaboration.
There is some exercise preparation to be done.
And depending on whether you are a team or whether you are following on your own, different
steps are needed.
And we, you can do that in the exercise time.
So this will take a couple of minutes and that's okay.
So the first part of your exercise might be to really set up this exercise repository
and what your team leader will do.
And if you don't have one yet in your team, then designate one of you to be the team leader.
One of you will generate this exercise from the template.
And if you are following on your own, we have done that already for you.
But then we ask you to please tell us if you want to participate, because we need to add
you as a collaborator.
So here we need to be collaborators.
Once you get added as a collaborator, you will get an invitation from GitHub.
You need to accept it.
And then the other thing we recommend to do is once you get added to an exercise repository
is to unwatch it.
There is a screenshot here, but I want to show you how that looks.
So I will go into some of the, this will be the exercise that we will do with the stream
participants who are not part of a group.
And there is this button called watch and unwatch.
And here you will be able to select what kind of notifications do you want to get.
And by default, it might be that by default you have this one.
And then you get emails about all new issues and all new pull requests within the same
repository.
And maybe you don't want all these emails.
So what I do and what I recommend you to do is to switch to the participating and mentions.
It will only, you will only get up email updates about the issues that you have opened and
the pull request that you have opened,
or if somebody mentions you.
So this is what we mean by unwatching.
So there is this preparation time to be done,
but let me give you an overview
of what is part of this exercise.
And we have tried to make it clear
of what is possibly familiar,
like cloning a repository.
This is, we have done it before.
creating a branch we have done before,
committing a change to a new branch
and opening a pull request.
Now I know that not everybody maybe was here
and we don't expect that you remember everything.
So if you are unsure about this,
you can then always jump to the previous lesson
and have a look, how was that again?
How did I open a pull request?
And then we try to crystallize here.
What is the new thing?
What will be the new part in this exercise?
We will see what is a protected branch.
I will show you that in a second.
We will learn how to cross reference issues and pull requests.
And we will practice to review a pull request.
And even open draft pull requests.
So these will be the new things.
And for everything that is new, you will find screenshots and explanations below.
So use these hints, use these solutions.
And then here are the exercise tasks
that you can do with either within a group or on your own.
Okay, and I wanted to show you a little bit
about the behind the scenes
because one thing I need to do here
before everybody starts with this exercise.
And that you get an idea of what is,
I will look into this one,
centralized workflow exercise recorded.
So you don't have to do this.
I only want to show you what are the things
we need to prepare here.
There is a settings tab where I can control.
control. So now the team leaders will need to add collaborators. And the collaborator
in this case are the individual stream participants. And now I will change the role from read to
write. So from now on, actually, people can change the exercise. But please try to go
step by step. So I will change that to write permissions. The other thing I wanted to show
you is that we are using protected branches. And I do that up here branches. The main branch
is protected. What does it mean? Edit. It means that hopefully, unless I forgot something,
nobody can commit directly to the main branch or push directly to the main branch. And all
All changes to the main branch need to go through a pull request.
So that could be an interesting setting also for your exercise repository.
And I will do the same.
I need to give write permissions also on the unrecorded one.
Also here I will give you write permissions so that you can soon start with the exercise
settings collaborators and teams and now everybody can write to it.
So these kind of steps will be the beginning of the exercise hopefully it is all clear
here it's really important that you let us know how the exercise is going.
So during the exercise session, please give us feedback.
We need to give you, well, at least half an hour.
So I would say that we will do the exercise
until the full hour, at least.
We will then take a break.
We might need more exercise time later.
Here, let's collaborate.
The goal is open a branch, create a branch,
create commits, open a pull request,
and then review somebody else's pull request.
And let's practice to give this kind constructive feedback.
And then if you have time,
try to create a draft for request.
And below you find screenshots and also discussions,
how can that be useful and how to do these steps.
And I will practice here with the stream participants
and I will also practice with [Name].
So we will then, after the exercise, after the break,
we will look at some of these steps here on stream.
I'm checking my checklist,
but I forgot to say something essential.
Will we meet on Twitch before the break?
Yes, but just to hear the nice jingle
and just to remind everybody to really take a break,
to not let the exercise not consume the break.
So we'll be back, but only very briefly.
If yes, then let the exercises commence. Half an hour, but half an hour might not be enough.
Don't worry, we will give you more time later. Let us know how it's going. And we will reconvene
on stream in half an hour for just to announce the break.
Good, let's try it out.
Let's see what happens.
I'm really excited about this.
See you in half an hour,
but see you on the notes before that, bye.
you
And we are back from the exercise block.
And we know that not everybody finished, not a problem.
Let's first take a break.
We will take a 10 minute break, but then we will go through these steps together with
Gago.
And also in the second exercise, we stay in this repository.
So don't worry about it. If, if you didn't finish so far, everybody take a break from
your screen and I will see you again in 10 minutes. See you then.
you
Back from the break, after a nice jingle, welcome back everybody.
So what I see here on top of my screen is, this was the exercise that with the stream
participants we can see that there is activity, there are many branches, lots of commits,
there are also some merges already.
So some of these changes have emerged, so that's very nice.
I can imagine that it was possibly not enough time
before the break.
And here I'm looking at the feedback from exercise.
It would be really helpful if you can indicate here
whether you are done or whether you are still in halfway.
So I'm not sure how representative it is,
but I'm looking at there.
This is in the notes.
So modan, is each of these O's, does it stand for like 10 people or 20 people?
Or did really only five, six people indicate?
It's not a problem if you got stuck, because we will, with [Name] here, we will demonstrate
the important steps.
And in the second exercise session, you will stay in the same exercise repository.
So it took a while to set up, but you can then either continue.
We will do a very similar thing, but we will focus more now on the review part and the
modifying part.
Thanks.
So now a few more people answered.
So maybe it was okay time.
I suggest that let's have some fun now.
You can all watch.
You will have enough time then in the next exercise
and [Name] and me will try this.
We will open an issue, open a pull request
and review it together.
[Name], how about you take the screen share from me
and you create a pull request.
And then I take it back and I will be the reviewer
and we will together review the changes.
Sounds good, yeah.
So we're moving now to the second lesson,
but as Radwan already mentioned,
it's a smooth transition since it's basically
the same thing, just that we will now focus
a little bit more on the reviews.
But I will just quickly go through the steps again
that we also did in the previous lesson.
So I'm now on the centralized workbox
as recorded repository,
and I will now start by creating an issue.
So I want to add a recipe,
So I say, add my tomato spaghetti recipe.
And why is it called issue?
Because it was, I think it was invented
to keep track of problems.
But here we don't use it to,
for a problem we use it to communicate an idea.
We communicate what we intend to do before we do it
because it gives us a chance to collect feedback.
Exactly, yeah.
One thing I can do here is to assign someone
for this issue.
And in this case, it's already assigned me automatically,
but in theory, I could assign anyone.
So I could also send another one if I would want.
I will just assign myself here.
And how do you also...
Can I just ask, how do you use this assigning in your work?
So I can tell that what I find sometimes useful
is that by assigning,
I communicate to other people that I'm working on it.
Yes, it's very helpful if you're working a team
where there's multiple people working on the project
and you want to indicate that you already decided
that you will work on this and have already thought
maybe about the problem,
so that other people don't duplicate this work,
so that they don't waste any time.
And sometimes, if you know that another person
is an expert in a certain part that you want to fix
of the code, for instance, then it might be a good idea
to assign this person as well as it.
maybe for the issue, but especially for a review,
that would be helpful.
I can do a similar thing with labels.
So I can say this is gonna be an enhancement,
but if it's like, if there's a mistake in the code,
if it's a bug, then I can indicate that here.
So this can also be very helpful for others.
In this case, I just choose the enhancement
and I will submit this now as an issue.
Oh, one question that we just got on the notes is,
do we always have to open an issue before we do a change?
you don't but it can be good practice but it's strictly speaking it's not
necessary and for smaller things it might be not necessary at all in my view
yeah so here we want to show you the technique it's more useful for bigger
changes so that when the big change is ready it doesn't come as a surprise to
everybody and also what you want to avoid is that after spending few weeks
developing something then you don't want to hear no thank you
this doesn't fit at all. What would have been nicer is that you first communicate what you
intend to do, you collect feedback, and then you code. So it's about avoiding surprises,
but for very small changes, not needed. Yeah, but that's a good point. You always
want to communicate before you spend a lot of time on the problem.
I will now create a pull request. So I will go back to my main branch. And it's already
showing me here that I already created a new branch. I will just quickly go to my new branch.
where I added the recipe that I mentioned in the issue.
And I now deliberately misspelled something.
So I misspelled the recipe the same way
as I, as a German native speaker,
would have done it in primary school.
But this is not the only problem in this new recipe.
There's also one major mistake in the ingredients
which would ruin the whole recipe.
So let's see whether that one will be able to spot it.
Yes.
So here we go a little bit step ahead
because we already show you
what people will do in the second exercise,
but that's great.
And in the commit message,
so the commit message here was
add tomato basil spaghetti recipe.
And in the commit message, you did not reference the issue.
It's not a problem.
So it can be done either,
it can be done in the commit message,
but it can also be done in the pull request,
which I think you plan to do.
Yes, I created this before I raised the issue,
so therefore that's possible.
But I will now go back and it will already show me,
it will have this pop-up here where it's suggested
I could now compare the differences in the code
and create a pull request, so I will do this now.
I'll just quickly check, okay, I'm going from this branch,
from my new tomato spaghetti branch into the main branch,
that's what I want to do, I want to add this recipe.
And now I can assign a reviewer.
Let's say I choose [Name] in this case.
I can, again, I can choose some labels if I want.
In this case, I think enhancement makes the most sense.
And I could provide some more information if I wanted to,
but in this case, I think it's not strictly necessary.
If I scroll down, it will also show me the added file
or the differences.
In this case, I only add some lines.
I didn't delete any,
but otherwise that would be shown here as well.
And let's not forget to reference the issue number
before you open it.
Ah, yes, thank you.
So I can reference it here, fix.
Like there's a number of keywords I can use.
And we have them in the material.
So it's fix or fixes, close, closes, resolve, resolves.
Yeah, and it shows me now which issues
I could reference it to.
And I have here issue number 19.
So that was the one that I erased before.
So I will now create a pull request
and I will give the screen then to [Name]
and then we can discuss good practices for code reviews.
Yeah, so open it up.
Sorry, I forgot to mention one thing, sorry.
Okay, I just quickly mentioned this one thing.
It's good practice for when you create pull requests
to make it a lot easier for a reviewer as well
to try to have short chunks of code
that you want to be reviewed
since the attention of the reviewer is limited
And maybe for some complicated bugs that you want to fix,
it is necessary to have several hundreds of lines of code.
But if possible, always keep it short
because you want to, and you can also add
some additional comments if you want here
to some of the lines of your pull request
if you want to communicate even more information
than there is already.
So this can be always a good idea
because since we don't speak person to person
or face to face to another person, to the reviewer,
Sometimes if you work with someone in a different time zone
or in a different university,
it's always good to over communicate
and not provide too little information.
But I will now create this pull request.
Sorry about the one, and I'll give the word to you.
Oh no, nothing to apologize.
This was great.
We have enough time and it's really good
that we do that here step-by-step.
Okay, keep the screen.
I will now take it from you in a second.
And then we do the reviewing together.
Good, now I first need to find your pull request.
So I go in pull requests and now I will review,
this is yours.
So each pull request and each issue has a number
and your pull request is the number 21
and I will now review it.
So let's discuss what are the things that we should look at
and how do you review a pull request?
I have been assigned, so okay,
go request it for me, so that will also,
somewhere I got an email about it.
So if I was somewhere else, I at least know.
And then the thing that I look at,
oh, this is about tomato basil spaghetti.
First thing I look at is the title.
I might also look at which branch is it going to,
typically the default branch, it's going to main.
This is the goal here.
And the next thing I would look at this file changed.
Is this also what you do Gecko anomaly?
Yes, I spend most of the time on the files changed.
So let's look at what is in there, files changed.
I would now browse it.
I mean, overall, it looks pretty okay.
There are some problems.
One problem is up here.
And I could ask Ego to fix that, so the spelling.
I will show you that there is actually a better way.
And that will be part of your second exercise.
So let's come back to that in a moment.
There is also another problem.
Can somebody spot it?
It looks like it has an unhealthy amount of salt here.
So this will,
this is something I'm,
so how do I get feedback?
Well, one way to give feedback,
if you go back to conversation,
we can have a discussion here,
so I could give feedback here.
And it's nice to be kind, thanks so much.
Really nice recipe.
But how about that salt amount?
The salt amount, shouldn't we reduce it?
And now if I comment, it's here, it's recorded.
So we have a context here, we have a discussion thread.
If I need to, and now we, us two are part of this discussion
Sometimes I need to involve an expert, so I don't know,
but I can ask somebody else for an opinion.
You can then mention people.
I will now not mention somebody else,
but let's imagine you want to ask me for,
somebody wants to ask me for an opinion.
You could mention, what do you think?
So if you start this ad,
and if this doesn't make more sense
because I'm asking myself,
but then I will get an email
and you can involve other people into a conversation
if you need their opinion.
So I'll remove that.
So that's one way to comment.
The other way that might be maybe more useful
is to, if I go back to fast changed,
you can comment directly here.
For instance, I can say here that by clicking on the plus,
I can give a leave a comment.
Not sure about the salt amount, add a single comment.
And but on the other hand, Parmesan cheese, nice.
I really like this, add a single comment.
Because then, when I go back to the conversation,
it's the submitter will see what line am I referring to.
They don't have to guess.
Imagine there are 10,000 lines.
And here I refer to this line.
You can even refer to entire code blocks.
So this can be useful.
And there is, you can even go a step further.
Because I could add a comment here that spelling is not correct. Can you please fix that? But
I know how to fix this. There is this plus minus symbol here, add a suggestion. So I
can add an actual suggestion. So if I click on the plus minus, I can edit the code directly.
So it should be tomato, basil, spaghetti.
Hopefully that's correct.
And if I now add a single comment with a suggestion,
which can be on one line or it can be on multiple lines.
Well, let's see how that will look
when we go back to the conversation.
When we go back to the conversation, there is a suggestion for a change.
And now [Name] doesn't have to do anything except accept it or not.
And I mean, I will not give the screen back to [Name], but formally, it should not be
me committing my own suggestions. But now, if Gago reads this, can accept this by zoom
out here by clicking. Why is this not in my screen? And guess what this is? This is a
commit message, fix spelling mistake.
So we can do all of this without going back to my editor,
going back to my command line, commit.
And now this has been fixed here, there's a new commit.
And now if I look at the files changed,
there is no spelling mistake anymore.
And what would now, but now I'm a little bit too lazy to fix the two kilo salt, I don't know how much it should be.
I leave it to Gecko. What would be the mechanism now for Gecko to make an improvement to the pull request?
Some people, what they do is that if they see that, oh, there's something wrong,
what they will do is that they will close the pull request and open a new one.
But that's not very good because that will fragment discussions and it will fragment the context
because then it will be a new pull request and we will
then we need to remember that we had also the pull request 21.
So a much nicer mechanism to
to improve pull requests, and you will practice that
in your second exercise
is to
recognize that pull requests, they are always from a branch
towards another branch. And if you want to make changes to a pull request, all you need to do
is to add new commits to the source branch. So if [Name] adds new commits to the branch,
they will get added to the pull request. And this is the way to modify a pull request until
until we are all happy here.
And once we are happy,
we have resolved all the conversations,
then we will merge it.
And this is what we will practice.
So in the second part,
and let me go to the second part here.
It's very similar.
We are still in the same exercise repository.
You don't need to set up anything new.
The new thing now is we will focus more on the reviewing.
and you will you will practice the things that feature showed you and what you can try to do is
maybe try to open a new pull request where you
maybe there's a typo that is easy to fix and there is also a larger mistake and then
then look at other people's pull requests in the same exercise
try to make suggestions to their pull requests, try to do what I did with this typo fix,
and then learn how to make amendments to your pull requests by adding new commits to it.
We can maybe give some general advice for how to do reviews. One thing is spend time on things
that humans are good at, by which I mean don't spend time at things which you can automate.
For instance, if one typical thing which is very often done by so-called linters or code
formatters is things like code formatting.
If you say, okay, you don't like the bracket here, you would want to split this into two
lines and stuff like this.
This is not something which we should focus on during the code review because we have
automation tools for that.
However, what we should try to do together is to get the code which is there to an acceptable
stage and then get it merged as soon as possible so that a lot of people profit from it.
It's really not the case that the reviewer is there to show how smart the reviewer is
or to show how he or she would have implemented or they would have implemented stuff.
It's really kind of a collaborative effort.
And in this case, it was me as kind of the new kind of employee in the group, the new
member of the group who now creates the pull requests and then the senior person, the very
experienced person, the other one who did the review.
But there is no reason why it couldn't be the other way around.
Because the purpose of a pull request is not just getting the code to an acceptable stage,
but also to transfer knowledge.
So in my experience, one is learning a lot from reading code from other people and the
pull requests are a wonderful opportunity for that.
And also, maybe one last comment, another one is a very experienced developer might
understand whatever gets submitted quite quickly.
But one quality of code or like one side of a good
code is also readability and how easy it is to understand for
someone who is not an expert in whatever the proper language might be.
So also the perspective of someone who is new to the team can be very valuable
to improve the code itself.
These were such great points. So is this really a diversity that makes codes
better great points that it's about learning it's about the reviewer doesn't have to be
the senior person it can be the the new colleague in your in your team this was really such
great points and also try to so it's like try to like it's code review but that doesn't
mean that you are not allowed to give any positive comments or like say to point out
things that you like. I mean, there's nothing worse for someone who spent weeks on fixing a
very difficult bug, submitting the pull request, and then the only suggestions he gets are like
some tiny comments about some semantics, which really don't kind of have a large impact on the
overall code. And then the pull request doesn't get accepted that way. So I mean,
for the person who spent a large amount of time on fixing this bug, this can be really discouraging.
So I think it's really important to communicate things well and also to focus on the positive
things as well.
Because, I mean, as always in the internet, it's easy to kind of point out or like to
communicate things in a natural way that you would never communicate face-to-face.
And for somebody who joined the project or just imagine how you would feel if it's your
first pull request to a project.
it's so important, your first experience
on how they respond to you.
And if the response is very negative
and if the experience is negative,
I mean, you will never come back to the project again.
So especially this first contact is so important.
And then it's not so, the code doesn't have to be perfect,
but to really bring them into the project
and give them a good experience.
So let's practice that.
Let's practice the technique.
in this exercise and what we will do,
we will give you 25 minutes.
We're basically until the hour
and then we can take a long one hour break
and here focus on suggesting changes,
how to apply changes, what we just showed you.
And we try to summarize this in this,
so the tasks are very similar.
We try to hear this still again, what are the new things in this exercise?
And you stay in this centralized exercise repository.
It's only later after the longer break where we will move to a different repository.
Just looking here at notes, whether anything unclear there.
I saw a good question.
It was something about, is this what we do for every project or something like that?
And I think it's worth mentioning.
So day two, so most projects would be somewhere between day two and day three.
So day two was simple, you push directly, you don't worry too much.
Day three, we're going through the really formal process of collaborating on something
bigger.
So not every project is day three, maybe not many projects are day two, many are probably
in between there.
Yes.
So here we can imagine, this is a project for, you can imagine we are three people,
four people in a research group.
One person is the principal investigator, but it's not the person who will review everything.
we agree that we all help out with reviewing.
Nobody, everybody is, nobody is more equal.
So the model that we are trying right now
could be a good fit for that scenario.
Three to, three to 20 people, or three to 50 people.
Once it gets much bigger,
maybe we want to do the thing that we will do
after the longer break.
Good.
Thanks a lot for pasting.
we will then be, the exercise will be until the full hour.
So until zero, zero, but then there will be a,
should we then announce the break?
Yes, we will announce the break,
just that people don't forget it.
So we'll be back in 25 minutes for the jingle,
and then we will announce on one hour break afterwards.
Good luck, everybody.
We will also help here,
all the co-organizers and co-instructors will help
with the reviewing for the requests in this,
for the individual stream participants.
Have fun.
Let's all, let's suggest and improve
and let's be really positive.
See you later.
Bye.
.
you
Welcome back from exercise everybody.
And the little jingle was reminding us that we should take a long one hour break.
So step away from the monitor.
we will be back on stream in one hour.
And I realized I don't share the screen.
Whoops.
Here.
We'll be back in one hour.
And it's so nice to see all this activity
that happened in the meantime.
We will discuss it then when we are back
and we will then introduce some more really fun things
that are possible with code review and pull requests.
See you all in one hour.
Bye, and I need to click on the right thing here.
See you then.
you
Welcome back.
We are back from a longer break, back on stream.
I hope the exercise went well.
I'm really happy here with the progress we've done
on our exercise repositories.
We will now move on to the third episode of today.
And I also wanted to say something
about these exercise repositories.
Because in the third episode, we will use a different one.
And you don't have to be worried that your recipe suggestions stay here forever.
We will keep these exercise repositories for one more week.
But after the workshop, we will delete them.
So everything we did here will be gone.
You don't have to worry about that.
Also I learned that today is the Pi Day, March 14.
Hopefully this has influenced some of the recipe choices.
For the third episode, we will use a different exercise repository.
We will now practice a forking workflow.
So I will already navigate to it.
You will set it up in your exercise session later.
There will be less to set up because this time you will not have to add any collaborators,
you don't have to communicate your GitHub accounts.
The whole point of the next exercise is that we learn how to modify somebody else's repository.
And somebody else's repository could, for instance, be all the Code Refinery lessons,
which are all repositories.
So now you know, you will learn how to suggest changes
to the lesson.
And some of you have already done that.
So thanks so much for that.
We didn't have yet time to review everything.
So I will now navigate to the episode called,
oh, this one, that belong to others.
How to contribute changes to repositories
that belong to others.
So there's a little bit of setup, but it will be easier.
Make sure that you don't stay in the same exercise repository as from earlier today.
Can someone add the link to the notes?
My hands are a bit full here.
Oh yeah, the cat is there.
Okay, so everybody focus on the cat.
I will paste.
We are now here.
We are here, and this is maybe not in the nicest format,
but at the bottom of the document,
this is where we are.
And a lot in the next exercise will be familiar.
Again, a new branch, again, a pull request.
This time, the pull request goes to a different repository,
not the same repository.
you don't have to add collaborators,
you don't have write permissions in the exercise repository
and you can still suggest changes.
That is really cool.
And there will be a few things that are new.
So every time we try to sneak in some fun new aspects
and one will be automated testing.
testing, we will show that in a minute with [Name].
And then we will also show you that
after the changes are merged, you will see that your fork.
So when you start the exercise,
you will fork the exercise repository.
You will see that at some point the fork is out of date
and we will practice how to update it.
And then at the bottom of the page, there is,
There are some thoughts about how to approach
other people's repositories with ideas, changes, requests.
And then hopefully we managed to have
for the last 20 minutes, 30 minutes of discussion session
where all of you can ask us about Git and GitHub
and best practices.
So that's the plan, but we will first start.
So you can first just watch.
we will show you the two key steps in the next exercise.
And for this,
Gago and me will go into this forking workflow
exercise recorded.
And the first exercise step will be to create a fork from it
to create your own copy.
Should I give the screen to you, [Name]?
Okay.
So as another one mentioned we are now on the forking workflow exercises or
exercise recorded repository and I've already created an issue. Again it's
pretty much the same as before. I'm just going to add the recipe again and I'm
to create a fork, which you do by clicking on this button. So I've done that just now,
a few minutes ago. So I now went to the four seconds.
So you have now, you are now in your copy. Yes.
Something that will, some people will ask about this. Where are, where are the issues here?
Because now I don't see them here. And we need to remember that issues typically stay on
on the central, the upstream repository.
So when you created the fork, you copied everything,
but you didn't copy the issues.
And up there, there is no issue tab.
One could enable it, but it is customary
to track all issues and ideas and problems
in one central place.
Good.
Yeah, very good point.
But we will see afterwards how to link pull requests
to issues in the original repository.
So I'll now create a new branch,
which I've already done as well,
and I just copied the same recipe
from before into this branch.
So it's the same as before, with the corrected title.
So the two issues that [Name] has pointed out
in the last review, they are not an issue here,
but we will see whether there's anything else.
So I now go back to the repository,
and I create a pull request.
So I can see here, there's this pop-up,
it shows me this branch is one commit ahead
of the original branch.
And I can now create a pull request
by clicking on contribute.
Then it suggests open a pull request.
So I can double check now again,
whether I'm creating this pull request
between the right branches.
So I'm here on my local fork.
And the branch that I'm using here is a feature branch.
So the one that I just created now,
and I want to merge this code into the main branch
of the original repository.
So I see that's correct.
I can add a title.
In this case, it takes the last commit message.
And this time in the commit message,
I've already referenced that this code
is supposed to be fixing an issue.
So in this case, I've wrote fix hashtag one,
because the issue that I'm trying to fix
is the first one that has been created to this repository.
Also, if I would write it here, just to quickly show it,
it will now show me all the issues
that are listed there in the original repository,
and I could choose this one again,
but I've already done it here in the title,
so I don't need to do that here again.
But it shows me here with all the issues,
or it would show me here all the issues
that are existing for, that are open at the moment
in this original repository.
Now it's the same thing as last time.
I can again choose [Name] as a reviewer.
If I want to specify someone, I can add a label if I want.
And then we create, we click on create pull request.
And we will now see how this automated tests
can be extremely helpful.
So [Name], should I give the screen back to you
or should I quickly point out what is happening here?
Yeah, you can explain that and then it will go,
then I will take it over and merge it on my side.
Yeah, so now something interesting happens.
In this repository,
we added some so-called GitHub workflows,
which is a way of implementing automated tests
or automated checks for every code
that is submitted in a pull request.
Okay, click here on details.
We'll show you afterwards how this is set up and then I get here all the steps
that are done in this test and it shows me here that one test is failing so in
this case there's only one test that is done otherwise there would be multiple
jobs listed here on the left side and it tells me here that in the file that I
submitted the test checks whether I have ingredients as a section and it tells me
that I don't have any.
Now let's take a look at the code again,
which I can do here at clicking at files changed.
And it already shows me that there is something wrong.
And it tells me here that ingredients is not in,
let me just scroll to like show you full message here.
It's saying that this section is missing ingredients.
And if I take a closer look,
I see I actually misspelled ingredients,
therefore test catches a mistake.
And I did this kind of on purpose
because in the previous lesson,
this mistake was already there
and [Name] and I were not able to spot it.
And now the automated test was able to spot the mistake.
Now this of course is kind of a artificial kind of test,
like usually in a code project,
which would be more relevant would be to add tests
that check the functions of the new implementations
in your code.
So whenever you submit something that changes something
in the code base, you can automatically test
whether it breaks anything
of the previously existing functionalities.
Or I can use this also very frequently,
but it's not very often to check
whether the code formatting is correct.
So these two things are usually done
in these GitHub actions.
But again, like in this case, which is really nice,
it showed us like there is a mistake here
which we, which slipped under our radar
when we were doing the code review manually.
Okay, another one, should I give the screen to you or?
Yes, give me a second.
I will take the screen and let me review it.
Let's now take the perspective of the person reviewing.
I will just refresh my page.
Um pull request one is open and one issue is open that's the one
and I will make the font larger.
So even without even before I click on the pull request itself I can see that
that, so the new thing this time is this,
is this, so there's a new symbol here.
And if I could, if I would click here,
I would see the same detail that,
ooh, no, I clicked on the wrong thing.
If I click on the X or on the details,
I would see the same what [Name] has just seen.
And now I know what the problem is,
and I also know how to fix it.
So let me first fix it and then I want to show you
how do we do this testing?
How does it work?
And then what does it make possible?
And it will only be a preview
because then next week we have a whole lesson
on automated testing and then we can go really in depth.
But let me first fix this.
we know how to review changes no i can go i can do it directly here no this one
it was the plus minus symbol in in not ingredients it's ingredients
and i will now
Well, I can keep the screen, but [Name] can't commit it, so just that I don't commit and
upload my own suggestions.
So maybe, maybe you can click on it, but we stay with my screen.
I don't even know whether something will change here automatically or I need to reload.
see. Yeah, actually, it did update. Yeah, I just updated it. And now the tests are running
again. If you scroll further down, you can see that the tests are running again. Oh,
they have passed. Yeah. Green checkmark all checks have passed and I can verify by going
to the details. And now everything is happy here. Zero errors. So something was happening
run Python checks recipes.py. Where does that come from? Well, first, let me merge it. Let
Let me first merge it and then let's talk about the testing.
Merge.
Just thinking whether this will do anything
with our exercise.
No, it's fine to merge.
Now we have it on the main branch.
How did the testing work?
We edit,
And now there is a symbol it's running again because the testing now runs not only we defined
it to run not only on each pull request but also on each modification of the main branch.
So there's this check recipes which is a little Python script that will check whether our
recipes contain ingredients and instructions.
It doesn't have to be Python and in real life it would verify something else.
So we don't have to go into this file really.
Of course, if you are curious,
you can click and see what is inside.
The really key thing here is this folder,
.github.com slash workflows.
And inside there, we can add scripts
and we can tell them that they should run automatically
every time we push or create a pull request
or create a release.
So I will go in there and see.
We have one recipe in there.
Well maybe recipes are confusing word.
We have one script.
And we gave it a name check recipes.
You could have several scripts here.
I will open it up.
And this here we define on each on each modification of the main branch on each pull request towards
the main branch, do a series of steps and run it on a Linux-like container.
You could here add, you could run tests on a macOS system or a Windows system.
I think you could even run them on your own custom container.
And the series of steps here, it's up to you to define what it is.
So what are typical things that we will want to do at a pull request?
One thing that we will see next week is, well, run a series of automated tests to make sure
that the functionality is still working.
Then another thing you might want to do automatically is to build the documentation.
We will learn how to do that next week.
Spell checking.
If I go back to our lesson and I zoom out,
if you want to browse our lesson in PDF format,
well, that PDF is generated automatically
as part of a workflow at every pull request.
So there are a lot, many things are possible.
You could automatically package your code.
You could even automatically upload your code
to services like Zenodo and get a digital object identifier.
I don't know what else we could do, lots of things.
So we will come back to that next week.
So this is just a preview.
So then when you practice in the next exercise
and the test is failing, I mean, don't feel bad.
This is a silly test that checks for certain sections.
We only want to show you what is possible.
Next week we will show you how to create these workflow files for your own projects.
Good.
There will be a second interesting thing that you will see in your exercise is that
the change that [Name] sent and that I merged, which was a new pasta recipe, pasta this one,
it is now on the main branch in this exercise repository.
But if we, maybe we can again switch perspective
and Gago takes the screen from me.
And if we go back to his view on his fork,
we will see the change is not there on the main branch.
Exactly, so I'm now on my fork.
And if I take a look at the commits,
I will only see the initial commit.
So whatever has been committed to the main branch now
of the original repository is not appearing here.
Yeah.
If I take, we'll take a look at that
and I would see there's already four commits
and these come from the pull request.
Yes. So two of them were one,
when one was your pull request,
the second one was where we fixed the spelling mistake.
And then the last one, which is the merge,
it's a merge commit.
So that's why we have four.
And then going back to your fork and there is,
we can actually see that it's behind
because it tells us there,
this branch is three commits behind
the upstream repository.
And now there is a two-click way of updating it
and you will do that in the exercise.
That is this.
Click on sync fork.
Exactly.
If you want, you can compare,
but I mean, we already know what the difference is.
it will be, it's just this one document.
So I can click on update branch.
And now it's identical again.
So if I now take a look at the full commits,
it will be the same as in the upstream branch.
So that will be an exercise step.
And this was easy because we have been careful
of not really modifying the main branch.
It can be useful to,
okay, I'll just capture the screen.
It can be useful to consider the main branch
or the default branch as read-only.
For every new pull request, we create a new branch.
And then it will be easy.
Our main branch in the fork will always be either up-to-date
or a little bit behind, but we'll never be ahead.
And then updating will be without any mistakes
and any problems.
You could just for fun,
try to actually modify your own main branch
and see what happens then if you try to update your fork,
whether this will work and what will happen.
So that can be an interesting thing to try.
And now looking at the time, timing is really good.
So we will soon start the exercise session and we have an exercise block here and it
will be we will give you half an hour which might be too much time but it's also then
nice to try some of these fun things out and or maybe catch up with what didn't work well
earlier.
A couple of things are already familiar and what is really new is listed here.
And again, at the bottom of the page,
we have screenshots of how does it look, where to click.
And then if you finish with the exercise
before half an hour,
have a look at the last section
where there are some thoughts,
and this can then form a basis for a discussion.
So the last half an hour of today
will be a Q&A session where we really open this up.
So I suggest that we will be back at 55 past.
We will be back here with a jingle.
I will say a few words.
We will then go into a short break
and then we will come back for a Q&A session.
So prepare many cues, many questions.
Have fun at the exercise.
Hope that works well.
Again, it will really help us if you let us know
Whether this worked well or where you are in the exercise step.
Good luck.
I just need to find the right button in my remote control.
See you in half an hour.
you