CodeRefinery.org
you
Test, can anyone out there hear us?
Yes, Test.
Good morning.
Good morning, everyone.
So someone says audio is good.
Should we do the standard audio check?
Let's do it.
Me, [name], and [name].
One.
Two.
Three.
Okay, let's see what they say.
Anyway, good morning, and welcome to week two.
Good morning, good morning.
I'm less loud than the other two, but it's always, I don't remember who said that people
always start with, so, so, let's get this started.
Exactly.
I'm sharing this collaborative notes document
that most likely you are familiar with.
And there you will find a couple of icebreakers.
Should I start asking [name] about the first icebreaker?
Works on my computer.
Like, I guess you heard this sentence.
You know, what does it mean in practice that you
trying to, I guess the context here is that you're not able to get something work on your computer
and you ask me and I'd say, well, it works on my computer. Has this happened to you or?
Oh yes, it has happened. And we have solved it in many different ways. Sometimes we just say,
okay, I don't need to run it. You can run it. It works on your computer. Please do the work now.
In other cases, restarting, like it says here also, has also helped to solve the magic of
these computer problems and more recently, like in, let's say, in recent years after
visiting the CodeRefinery workshop many years ago, also stuff like containers have helped
and I guess we're going to discuss that today.
How about you?
Yeah, no, I was just thinking that in general, this is such a common problem that, you know,
you might be trying to help your grandparents with their phone and you look at their phone
and it behaves in a different way than, you know, even though you have the same model
and same everything, it's, it's, it's quite amazing that, you know, that technology in
general tends to not be that, how can I say, reproducible or, you know, stable, robust.
But usually, yeah, restarting it or when it comes to software, reinstalling it sometimes
fixes magically.
I mean, isn't it actually pretty amazing when something does work across other computers?
I mean, like, just imagine if I write something and it works on three different operating
systems of computers and three different operating systems of phones, or two phones, and who
knows however many other things.
Yeah.
That's a big deal.
It's certainly still a feeling of magic when that actually works, like, first try.
And you send some code or try to run it on a different computer, and it just works.
And you're like, wow, I tried it.
So what are the reasons why something usually doesn't work then?
Good question.
Exactly, there's so many reasons.
Like even this part, this thing of the restarting, you know, I was trying to explain to my child
that your phone went to a state that it's not the usual anymore, so you need to restart
it too.
Yeah.
So wait, what's a good metaphor, a non-technological metaphor, where you have to restart it?
Yeah, that's a very difficult one.
I'm thinking of cooking, because cooking is our usual one.
I guess that you know that if you messed it up, yeah, you have to restart in a sense that
you have to throw away everything and re-remake your, I don't know, or...
What about one of these forever stews where there's a pod and you keep adding stuff to
it and taking it away, and it keeps going for, well, days or weeks, but sometime it
gets messed up and it's too spicy or too whatever.
or poisoned or something, and you have to throw it all out and start from the beginning.
Because many other things, I mean, when you're cooking, normal cooking, you restart on every
new recipe.
Of course you can get the master chef who is able to fix if it's too spicy or too bland.
But we still have a couple of minutes and the second icebreaker is about what do you
know now about programming and scripting and software, which you wish somebody told you
when you started?
This is the kind of question that we have always been asking each other and always been
asking to whoever comes across that.
It's not truly or strictly related to this day, but in general, you know, some kind of
advice for your younger self or future self?
For me, what it says there, how to organize folders and code is definitely one big one,
and how much it matters. Because maybe you have heard about that before and you're like,
ah, yeah, but I'm just trying something out now. I don't have to worry about this. And then
it grows and grows and it's more messy and messy and at some point someone asks you hey can you
share this and then you have to like either put some order in your mess or write like
super long documentation where to find the different files and where to find the different
data so how much also this organization actually matters for your future self and how much time it
it can save you would also be my answer here about you.
Yeah, I mean, I feel in a way related to this kind of about the physical
geography of the systems we use, because I feel that sometimes,
especially the the new generation might be growing with iPads or other devices.
They don't know the kind of, you know, geography of the file system,
that there are folders, that there are processes.
And so, and then when people start working with, you know, super computers or HPC clusters,
then suddenly, is it now on my computer, am I, you know, where am I in the network of
computers?
So, this actually helped me a lot, understanding where am I, what is connected to the place
where I am now, to kind of, you know, then understand, okay, I can't do this, what I
would normally do in my laptop, because I'm not on my laptop
anymore.
I'm somewhere else on the internet.
But it's 10 o'clock, so will we have a small jingle?
I guess we can.
Okay, we're back.
So hello everyone, welcome to week number two, day one of week two or day four of the
Code Refinery Workshop Spring 2024.
I'm [Name].
I'm a staff scientist at Aalto University.
And with me today is [Name].
Do you wanna say something about yourself, [name]?
Yeah, hi, I'm [name].
I'm an application specialist at CSC in Finland.
So we continue from last week part.
And for those who were joining us last week,
You should already be familiar with this collaborative document
that we've been using.
We can use this document.
Basically, you can use it to interact with us,
to ask any sort of question, or write comments, or share links.
For those who are just joining today,
basically, after registration, you get access to this document.
And then by clicking the pencil here on the top bar,
it switches to this kind of code markdown mode.
And there you are, as you can see,
people are answering to the icebreakers.
And at the bottom, you can add new questions.
And when you don't need to edit anymore,
you can click back on this eye,
so that it feels less sluggy
and it's more efficient to read it.
So, the material for the lessons of today, they're linked here in this collaborative
document.
But, however, if you start from the workshop page, you can scroll to day number four.
And the first part, the first two hours is going to be [name] and I covering this topic
of reproducible research.
So if you click on the link, you end up on this page, I can briefly talk about the learning
outcomes for this page. So the idea and what we will cover on this first two hours kind
of builds up from where we started with the first week. Ideally by the end of this lesson
you should be able to follow good practices, good enough practices to keep your directories
and your projects well organized. It's important that you understand that code and software
in general, have basically dependencies
that can be related to the system, where you are,
or to other libraries and other piece of codes
that are written by others.
And so it's important to also document this.
Then, hopefully, you will be able to document
the computational steps and have an idea when this
can be helpful and useful.
And then we will briefly introduce you
to the world of containers.
we will just, you know, scratch the surface there.
We will not go deeper into that,
but it's an important topic to basically consider.
And [name], do you wanna say something else
here related to the learning outcomes or?
No, but maybe let's talk a little bit
about how it all connects in the next page.
So for those of you that have joined already last week,
you might be familiar with this wonderful little image here
by [name].
And this time it looks a little bit different
in a sense that we have added
all the Code Refinery lesson titles to this figure
because the Code Refinery workshop itself
could also be called like a workshop
on reproducible research.
Like everything that we do here
like leads to you being better prepared
for doing reproducible research with your code.
And we have these six helpful steps here.
And for example, the get your files and folders in order
is already, will be covered today
in the reproducible research session.
Then we have the good file names for,
on folder names, which is covered in tomorrow's lesson
about documentation, and then on day six,
modular code development.
We talk a little bit about like how already naming
can help you in starting your documentation, for example.
Then in general, documenting code,
writing read-me's, code comments,
and how that can help you help others
and you understand your code later better.
Then we had the version control,
basically whole last week, or not just basically,
the whole last week was all about version control,
introduction to version control,
and then also collaborative distributed version control.
If you have missed that,
you can always go back and watch the videos
to learn about that there.
And then this week, we talk basically on every day,
something about destabilizing your computing environment
and the software we will start today
with, for example, the containers idea, then Jupyter Notebooks tomorrow, automated testing
on day six, and also modular code development, we'll talk about how you can do this stabilization.
And then in the end, you will probably want to publish your research outputs, which means
your code, your data, your documents, and topics related to that will be discussed today
afternoon in the social coding and open software lesson. And that's basically how it all connects
and these two hours that we have now here on reproducible research are like a small glimpse
into the world of the tools and the concepts that can help you with making your research code more
reproducible. So do you want to continue [name] with the motivation for this lesson?
We can go to the motivation.
I like to what when you were explaining this to me,
when we were discussing, that one
can look at this in the sense of timescales
that the Git version control are basically
focusing on your day-to-day work or the weekly timescale.
But then sometimes you don't need to control
or you don't need to version control anymore.
The daily changes, you want to start
version in the whole project, which might last for months.
And so what we will cover here is
like moving away from the day-to-day timescale
to the controlling at the project level,
so at the month or year level.
Or it can even be bigger.
As you heard in week number one that we were time
traveling through Git, here we will do even more time
traveling, meaning going back to very old versions of operating
systems and and things like that so that you know the future the future selves and the future
other people who want to rework with what we did are able to to travel back in time
so it's good to start with some motivation let me briefly check if there's anything on the
HackMD that is worth mentioning all right there's nothing specific so
Basically, the motivation when it comes to this episode on reproducible research, one
could even argue that the whole Code Refinery workshop should be called reproducible computational
research workshop, because as you just heard from what [name] has described, everything
is kind of connected together with the goal of having a project in the specific case,
a research project that is able to be run many times over and over and with the goal
that you know that the same output is when you have the same input and the same code
you are able to reobtain the same output. So in this funny cartoon here this is funny
I don't know if it's that funny because it's actually a trouble not funny at all thing
for the doctoral researcher who is in this situation, and maybe many of you, if you've
been to this type of situation, please let us know in the collaborative notes. But here
you see the senior professor saying, don't worry, you know, you don't have to start your
code from scratch, because maybe some postdoc has written all the pipeline for the lab,
but the postdoc most likely has left to another lab. And the professor continues, you can
reuse the software that the previous person on the project wrote several years ago.
And then the doctor researches like, are there instructions for how to use it? I doubt it.
Is the code commented? Not likely. Where are the files? Who knows? But this is going to
be painful, isn't it? It's just a scratch. So I don't know about you, [name], but at
At least I have experienced this at the very beginning of when I started with the research
work.
And of course, here the context of course is academic research, scientific research,
but the same issue could also be applied in companies.
You wouldn't like to deliver a tool, a software tool, where one day you are able to make it
work and another day it's just giving completely different results.
So here are some more scary, funny, but not funny anecdotes in this box here.
So for example, a group of researchers obtain great results and submit their work to high
profile journals.
And then usually after six months, if not even more, depending on the field, the reviewers
finally tell you what's wrong and they ask for tiny changes to the figures or another
analysis.
And then when the people start working on the revisions, they sometimes realize they're
not even able to regenerate the same figures of the submitted version of the paper or then
maybe some data got lost, some code they used to work suddenly doesn't work anymore and
no one can figure out which part of the system stopped working. Why aren't we able to rerun,
know the same code that we did before submitting this paper and this of course lost everything
and in some cases even you know the manuscript actually stays there in the in the file drawer
as this ever happened to you [name] that in this kind of situation
oh yes especially when the when the reviewing process is very long and you basically already
forgot what you what you did like half a year a year ago and then you should fix just a tiny little
thing that the reviewer didn't like or that you maybe noticed even after submission and
can be very painful but it's a hard way of learning also. And you pointed out really well that
it's something that you did which is something that also came out in the first week that
the main collaborator that you have is yourself, and specifically yourself in the future.
So you know that if you document well the software pipeline, if you really write down today
how you created that figure in six months or in one year, your future self most likely will be very
happy that you wrote down these notes, that you made your research reproducible, because this is
is what we're talking about here. And so that, you know, you will not have to restart from
scratch like in this, like in this cartoon here. So most likely you heard about reproducible
research and again, I highly encourage to use our notes, shared notes document where
you can write your experiences on reproducibility in research. And even if you, there's many
nice talks and papers, so if you have a favourite talk or a favourite paper on the topic, please
link it in the collaborative notes.
But in general, kind of this so-called reproducibility crisis started maybe sometimes in 2010.
It kind of started with the field of experimental psychology, where they clearly noticed that
biases, which can be intentional biases or unconscious biases in the research process,
they were making the findings highly, how can I say, variable, basically irreproducible.
So then what you see here in this figure without going deeply into the details is from a survey
that the Nature Journal did in 2016. And so here they asked various scientists in various
fields, how they felt, you know, if they feel that they were struggling in reproducing an
experiment, could be their own experiment, could be some experiment that you read from
a study that you try to reproduce locally. And the sentiment in general across all fields
is that, you know, more than half of the respondents, they were saying that, yes, there is a crisis.
It's impossible to reproduce the top papers in my field. I'm struggling to reproduce
what I did six months ago and so on. So these levels of reproducibility this is something
that is important to understand because often in science what we see is just the tip of
this pyramid. What we see sometimes is just the article and within the article there might
be a description of methods and they might be mentioning although it's very rare if they
they use certain libraries or certain software tools.
But often the kind of this methodological details
down to the kind of to the code or to the computation
they're kind of left to the reader as an exercise.
And unfortunately, that's what makes it really difficult
that sometimes just by reading an article
it's just impossible to replicate what these people did.
So, hopefully an article comes with some documentation, meaning that, you know, the method section
in the article sometimes needs to be expanded so that it can start adding details on which
methods were used, what type of computational, I don't know, solutions were adopted, and
maybe a description, you know, if they are not able to share the data, they could at
least describe how they collected the data, how they measured the phenomena.
But you can already understand that sometimes without code and without data, it's still
impossible to reproduce the article that you're reading.
Some articles, it's a minority, but it's getting more and more popular.
They actually come with code and with the data.
In general, recently in the publication process, many journals are asking for this data availability
statement and code software availability statement exactly for this reason.
if there is a chance that the data can be reused and if it's possible to, you know,
look at the code that was used for the paper. This gives a great, you know, chances that
the whole, that the main results from the article actually reproducible because running
the same data with the same code should hopefully produce the same results. In practice, however,
It's not as simple as that because code on its own tends to depend on multiple libraries,
multiple versions of softwares that one might be using.
And then we have this layer of the environment.
So with the environment here, we don't mean our nature and nurture, but we mean kind of
the computational environment where the code is running, where the data are stored.
So that if one could truly reproduce the same computational environment, bring the same code
and the same data, most likely, if not very often, you are able to obtain the same results.
So this kind of gives the context of the reproducibility and why it's really important in research.
we have a little bit of a discussion item for our collaborative document and so
yeah it is already there and people are already answering so
you can show it a little bit yeah maybe i switch to
so
What are your experiences with re-running or adjusting a script or a figure you created
a few months ago? I really like the figure because I don't know about you [name] but
for me at the beginning at least like I was kind of I'm not saying that I was editing
my figures with Photoshop but for example the arrows they look so I didn't like the
arrows of whatever program I was using in those days and so I was always manually fixing
some arrows or the fonts in the arrows. Have you ever done that? Have you committed this?
This crime, yes. I've also done that. Because also when you're new to using
things like matplotlib in Python or something like this and you don't quite
easily know how to do it, but in some other software it is really just a few clicks to
add an arrow to highlight something, it's a natural step to go. But then it will come to
haunt you at some point, very unlikely. Yeah, I mean, there's not even anything
wrong per se. The issue is that often people don't write down that, after I generated the figure with
with Marble Plate, I open it with Inkscape and I change all the fonts to whatever fancy
font I wanted to use. If people would already document this, then there would already be
a one layer of reproducibility added in this process of the figure. But of course, in general,
I mean, it's clear that if one could create the figure all with the script, then you don't
need to write down whatever manual steps you need to do with Photoshop or Inkscape.
And it's super easy to forget those steps, these manual steps afterwards, because running
the script is easy, but then opening it again in another software is like one more thing
to think about always.
That's in general a big issue with this graphical user interface tools, that of course you can
document all the clicks and buttons that you need to do for re-obtaining the same output,
the same outcome.
sometimes it's difficult and then the interface changes and suddenly you can't, the buttons
are not there where they used to be and you can't do that anymore.
So here people are still writing. Have you continued working from a previous students?
I guess yeah this at least I found it quite common not just in my experience but with
the people that I help in my in my daily work.
It's nice that someone is talking about preregistrations and register report.
I'm one of the strong, strong supporter of this, of this way of doing science.
But maybe the clock is ticking and it's 1021 in Finland.
So if there's nothing else specifically to be mentioning here we could continue with
the next.
So organizing your projects.
Basically this is something that everyone came across that you start your it can be
your doctoral studies, master's thesis, or it can even be that you just joined a new
company and you're working on some software. It all starts with the project organization.
And so of course complex projects might have very complex structures and dependencies and
multiple locations with data and code. But most likely you are starting with your own
project where you are the project manager and the main responsible on the organization
of the project. There's of course hundreds of ways of storing data and organizing your
file system but here in this page we try to kind of give you the basics that are useful
for organizing your project so what you see here this is like a so-called tree view of
a file system where you would have a folder called project name and then inside that folder
there are some subfolders data process data manuscript result and this as SRC which is
like source, source for the code and doc for the documentation.
So of course this is not the only way to structure a project but you understand that let's say
that you win the lottery and you then decide to stop doing research work and you move to
a nice island in the Pacific Ocean and live there happily.
least the next person who will need to you know resume your project kind of gets a clear
idea if already sees the same structure that we see here it's a structure that is familiar
to the new person and then most likely you know there are some notes written on this
readme document that would explain what's in different folders and what is the status
of things and then it's easier for your collaborator basically to continue where the project was
left very different from the situation that we saw in that PhD comic where the poor doctoral
researcher had no idea about even where the files were stored.
So in general, this tracking that we've been covering in the first week, the tracking of
the changes of the code, it starts to now scale in this time scale that we said earlier
is now becoming also tracking of the data,
tracking of the results that, you know,
you might be producing.
And so, basically, I mean, this all fits into the kind of,
into what we were mentioning earlier
that it's not just about the tiny changes,
documenting the tiny changes with the Git version control,
tiny changes to the code,
but also depending on the project,
might also need to version control the data and there are tools for that or version control the
results because you would have more iterations of the same figure and then in the end you want to
keep whatever is the final version of the figure and so on. So when it comes to tools and templates
but maybe before talking about tools and templates we could also ask these couple of questions to
to the people who are watching us.
So how do you collaborate?
They're already being answered.
Okay, that's excellent.
You are so efficient this morning, everyone.
And so the first question that we wrote
in the collaborative notes is,
are you using virtual control for academic papers?
And this is of course very interesting
because now it's not about tracking the changes in the code.
One is actually about tracking, you know,
about changes in the manuscript.
And then the second question is how do you handle collaborative issues, for example conflicting changes.
Maybe before switching to the collaborative notes, I'm going to ask [name], are you using or have you been using some sort of version control for academic papers with your supervisor?
Yeah, like many others also already wrote here, we are currently using mainly Overleaf
for collaboration on academic papers. It's nice because it has the integration with Git
and you can look back in history and all these kind of things. And how we are fixing these
collaborative issues there, like conflicting changes is that, well, everyone sees at all
times like what the others are already working on so there is never that situation that some
change comes out of nowhere but then we also try to first comment like I would like to add this
here and then we all say okay and then we let that person work on on a section for example.
How about you? Yeah I mean I've been working with seniors in my in my in my previous research I
I was doing lots of basically neuroscience and some of the seniors I've been working with that
might not be at the level of technology that they could use, you know, get virtual control
or a system like Overleaf. However, even tools like Microsoft Word or Google Docs,
they also have embedded so-called version tracking or virtual control. So even with graphical tools
like Microsoft Word, you know, it's not the best tool for doing virtual control,
but it's still possible to travel back in time,
see what has changed in the document
and comment on each other
and then work with this type of conflicting changes.
But it's nice that people here are writing their experiences
and also maybe this is a trend that I've noticed
with the new generation of younger PIs and supervisors
that they're more moving towards this type of overleaf
or distributed documents,
distributed tools for for collaborative writing.
So we still a few minutes and there are some very nice links
here that [name] added to this page.
This is something nice that came out last week because last week
we talked about how you can have a repository that is a template
So, that by cloning or forking the template, you can basically work on the folder structure
or existing structure from the template.
And so, here there's a nice collection of templates that by basically by forking them
or by creating a new repository from the template, you are able to get a folder structure that
is similar to the one here.
So, this is good practice that if you're starting a new project, you can actually immediately
start it as a repository as a git repository and for example we can have briefly a look at the
touring way template where you see this type of similar structure there's more subfolders but
you know it doesn't really matter it we clearly see that it's a similar to the structure that
that we were proposing.
More recently, there's also this type
of reproducible publications.
And so Overleaf, the tool that [name] already mentioned,
is an important one, but it's not the only one.
And in general, this is also something
that journals are kind of catching up,
trying to also publish something
that is a little bit more dynamic,
in a sense that now there are publishing platforms
that allow basically to run the code
while you are reading the manuscript.
And so, for example, Jupyter is now
able to be in some publication platform.
They're using it.
I can mention a couple in the neuroscience,
at least in the notes document.
However, it's 10.29, which is exactly one minute
before our planned schedule.
So [name], what are we going to do next?
We actually had five minutes more for the collaborative document, but I think we looked
at it already and there's at least no new questions that need to be answered.
They have already some answer here.
So I think we can go on and then after the next section, we will have a little bit longer
break also to collect our thoughts.
So I will take the screen share from you, built-in display, just move the Zoom stuff
out of the way and show you the next section.
So please continue answering in our collaborative documents the question that we already have
there.
collection to look through also after the workshop of what kind of experiences have
different people made and how they solved it. Our next section will be about recording
computational steps. So we probably all have been in that situation that we have some steps that
we need to do in order to do our works. Like [name] mentioned before, the plotting can be
one of these steps. Before that we probably need to process our data in some way that already makes
two steps and there is probably many different ways of how we can record these kind of steps
that we need to run one after another and in which order and how they are connected.
And one way of doing this are workflow tools and that is what this next section will be about.
And that is one way of how these steps can be recorded also in a reproducible manner.
And for that section, just find my mouse, we will take a look at an example project
that we have in our code refinery space. It's called WordCount.
You can see here it has like a lightweight structure that [name] discussed before.
Here also we have some code data, some other folders and then some more files.
And we'll look into those a little bit more in a bit.
So first this repository provides us with some code that takes in some data.
And the data is also part of the repository, which are book texts.
And then it provides us with some code.
Maybe we can take a brief look here.
So in the data section, we have four texts that contain the text of a book.
And then when we go into the code section, we have two scripts.
Those are small Python scripts.
And no worries if you don't use Python in your work.
You don't have to understand what's happening here.
Basically, the name already tells a little bit
about this story.
So we have a count script, which counts
the number of times each word appears in a file.
And in this case, we want to know
how many times each word appears in each of these books.
And that gives us then the word and the count.
And then the second step in this workflow
that we'll be working with today is
plotting this frequency of the 10 most used words
in these books.
So a pretty simple workflow.
First, we analyze the data, then we plot the data.
And there can be many more, of course,
but this now just simplified to look at it.
There is also mentioned in this readme here
that there is dependencies,
and this is something that we will look at
a little bit later in this lesson.
So for now, we can maybe ignore it
because I will demo this now here.
If you want to run this on your own computer later,
then you can have a look at this environment file
and see what to do with it.
And you will learn that in the later lesson.
And so in our case, we have kind of a given structure
of how we run these things,
because we first have to count the words
and store that somehow.
And then we need to use that data to plot
the frequency of each words.
And one way of how we can do that,
and which is maybe the first thing that comes to our mind
is to just run one Python code after another
with the inputs and the outputs.
So let's do that.
I will move this aside.
The link to this repository is in the collaborative document
so you can follow there.
I hope you now see my, yes, you see my command line.
So I have my terminal here.
I've cleaned it up a little bit and then I also have down here,
for example, what if I type something here,
you can see the command I typed in the bottom
just so that you can follow along a little bit better.
Let's now first do what we learned last week.
First, we get the code to our computer by using git clone.
I'll get the link from outside of your screen, I'm sorry.
Hit clone, paste the link, okay, and then we go into the word count directory.
Okay, so now we can take a look that all this information is really here.
We have the code, the data directories, we have some other files.
Everything is here.
If we now want to run,
for example, our Python code on one book,
we can copy the line for
the Python code from the readme file,
which was something like this here.
We call Python, we call the script that we have.
We want to run it on the book called IELTS.txt,
And we want to store that those results in the statistics
out of the data.
OK, that didn't take long.
And now we can, for example, look with any kind of tool
what we have in statistics out of the data.
So there we now see the is 3,822 times in that book.
then the next one is off, and so on.
This will probably look quite similar for the different books,
but we still want to get these names.
What we can do now is we can also plot the whole thing in similar way.
Luckily, the readme already provided us with these code lines,
so we can copy them from there.
Here, it looks a little bit different,
So we call Python on the plot.py script.
We have an input data file,
which is our statistics.data,
and then a plot file where we want to store the plot.
So we can run that as well.
Yep.
And then we can take a look with this program,
for example, to show the plot.
And let me just check that you can see this.
Yes.
So this is one of the plots, what we want to have.
In our case, we now have four books.
So it seems easy enough that we just run
these Python scripts one after another for these different books.
Then we could make ourselves a note,
we ran Python script 1, 2,
3, or we can even write them down.
We could even collect them in a bash script or some other kind of script.
It could be a Python script or something else where we just
record running one script after another.
We also have that actually in this repository.
It's called runall.sh.
So there you can see now we have multiple rows of the same stuff.
So we have Python, code count i,
and then one book after another, we run through.
Then the same for the plot lines,
we plot one after another.
So that would be one way of recording these computational steps.
One shorter way, because you maybe are looking at this and you're saying,
okay, we could also do this a little bit shorter.
Yes, we can. We can, for example,
loop through the different files that we have in our data directory,
and then apply each script on each book file automatically.
That would then look something like this, a little bit shorter.
Don't worry about the bash.
we just have here a for loop and we loop through all these four books and then we apply these
count.py and then plot.py on our files. So [name] what do you say this is now more reproducible?
Are we there? Can we stop here? I mean already this is quite an advanced project in a sense that
that I can see from what you've been describing that we're trying to remove the human from
running the script, from the interaction with the data, because often when I inherit some
code from some project, and even me, myself, I'm responsible of that, instead of having
a generic plot.py, I have been having plot underscore book1.py, and there inside I would
have hardcoded the name of book1, and then it would be silly that I need to create many
plot underscore book two plot underscore book three so this project is already excellent that
this plot and count they're like functions modular that then depending on the input they can be they
can be rerun but they should that maybe i would criticize on the reproducibility what if the books
would be 1000 that you know sometimes these four loops with this bash terminal scripting you know
maybe something dies with one of these 1000 books, is there a better way for, you know,
scaling kind of in a more reproducible way? Yeah, good that you're asking. Of course,
we also have a better way or a way that helps with some of the issues that you have mentioned here.
and so now we are going from basically saying do this and then that so in this
case we said first count the words how often they occur in the
text and then plot it. We describe the dependencies between those plots because
Here we can see that the second one requires the first one to be run because we need the
output of the first script to be produced before we can even run the plot.py file.
Workflow tools are one set of tools that can help with that so that you don't have to worry
to make clear, run this and that, but you state, okay, this plot requires count to be run,
so the workflow tool figures out how it can do that and how it can connect these different steps
that you have in your workflow. And one example workflow tool that we will be looking at
that today is SnakeMake.
It's one of many tools to create
this reproducible and scalable data analysis workflows.
In the case of SnakeMake,
we can already take a peek here in the repository.
We scroll up.
There's something called a snake file ready for us.
It describes the workflow in a human readable way,
but that also the machine can deal with.
This is a Python-based language,
but you can run all kinds of script with it.
In our example, we run a Python script,
but you can run also R scripts or
any other language that you might be working with.
One nice thing about this SnakeMake workflows is that they can
scale rather seamlessly from your own laptop to
high-performance computing cluster or the Cloud without the need
to modify this SnakeMake file.
While when you are running some other kind of script,
you might have to modify things there to be able to run it like in a different environment.
There was one question in the collaborative document,
what's a script?
The answer is pretty good.
So we collect all the commands that we want to run
into one file and have a series of instructions there,
similar to like a cooking recipe, for example, where it's described like what you need to do
and step by step. Okay, then the snake make file. So, you can see it here. Maybe I
make it a little bit bigger still. So, we can find already some things that we have seen before.
For example, we have our Python script mentioned here,
the countered pi, the plot.pi,
we have our data files mentioned here.
The way this is set up,
so this is already set up for us for
the workflow that we just showed.
The first thing here is that we define variable data with
snakeMakeSpecific function that finds us all the book titles
in our data directory that end with the extension text.
Then we only want the title of that book in this data variable.
Then we have a so-called rule-based system here.
So in general, every rule within SnakeMake has an input,
which is according to what we also were calling it.
There's some questions about what is SnakeMake,
like didn't understand that, and reasons
for computational steps.
So could you?
Sorry.
Oh, wait.
It's like the last two questions.
our SnakeMaker is used for.
It's for recording the computational steps in a different manner.
Maybe this becomes clear now when we go through it a little bit better.
What is the main reason for recording computational steps?
That we can reproduce our computational workflow also later.
So if we would now just run.
Let me just show this again if we or if we
would just run our one Python script after another.
Then we would.
Maybe forget like what did we actually run and in
what order did we run those?
So we try to write it down somewhere and one
way is to put those calls into a script that
we then store.
For example, alongside our data.
or in our repository.
I hope that answers.
But at least the snake make what it's used for.
I hope that will become clear during this section.
If not, please move the question to the bottom again,
and we'll try to explain it in more detail.
So the snake file contains of rules.
And every rule, as a minimum, needs an input.
Or every rule has an input, an output, and a shell command,
every normal rule.
So we define what kind of things does this rule need to run.
And in this case, we need this Python script.
And then we need the book file defined.
So now there's some questions like snake make
versus a script that runs stuff in a loop.
We will also get back to that a little bit after this demo.
OK, yeah, so we'll see.
Good.
What are the differences?
and it might also be like this is one example of a workflow tool and it might help you in some ways
but it's not the solution to everything like if you only have a few steps in your workflow and
little input files and are very sure that you will never have to like run it on many many more files
for example then probably SnakeMake or any other workflow tool is overkill and like you can just
run it by using a script instead of like kind of adding this another layer of complexity
that you do with the workflow tool. Okay I'll get back to the other questions
afterwards but yeah please keep them coming. So we have our rule that we call count words
where we have our Python script for counting our input file.
We define what is the output file.
In this case, it's collected in this statistics folder
with the same name as the input file and the data extension.
And then here we define this very same call
that we also had in our script before.
And we use these wildcards for that.
So we don't need to write out this here,
but it will be filled in
when SnakeMake is running automatically.
And then we have a second rule here for making a plot,
which takes in also the script again, a book.
This time it is the output of the previous script here.
This is the important part for Snake Make to figure out how to
run these scripts and how to deal with the data that you give it.
Then we have output file,
which is the plot, and again,
the Python call in this case.
Here you can see that it's not like Python specific,
but you could have any other shell commands here.
Then we have this overarching rule here called all,
which is basically that collects
everything that is to be done in this workflow.
It waits for inputs to be there that are the statistics,
the data file, this book.data file,
and the plot figure.
Let's get back to that in a moment.
Let's first maybe run this once.
SnakeMake can be run with the command SnakeMake,
and then we have to give it how many cores to use for this run.
Then right now, because I have already processed one of the files manually,
we first delete all output.
I have forgotten that I need to go into my Konda environment,
and [name] will tell you what that is after the break.
I have to first Konda activate
Code Refinery environment to make my SnakeMake available.
Now I can run the delete all outputs command.
It tells me something about building DAG of jobs.
We'll get to that in a moment.
Then it deletes all the outputs of
previous runs that are also part of the repository.
So we want to now see what SnakeMake does when we run it.
So we have this snake file in the base repository.
So we can run SnakeMake like this.
And then it tells us a lot of things.
And for some reason, this is not updating.
I'm sorry for that.
I hope it's slow enough to follow along
if you want to do that later.
So I'm scrolling up to what SnakeMake actually told me.
So here, it's, again, building this DAG of jobs.
And that is how SnakeMake figures things out how to run.
So it will first go and look at the all rule.
what are the expected inputs for this very last rule.
And then it will go further up or look at the other rules.
Where do these files actually come from?
Where is this plot produced?
And then it will run, try to run that rule.
And then it will notice that, okay, for creating the plot,
we actually need the data first.
So we need to have counted the frequencies of the word first.
So then it will find the rule
where that is the output and run that.
And it summarizes this all here.
So we have the name of the rules,
all it found out that it needs to run it once
to collect all the outputs.
Then we have the count word rule,
that it figured out because there is four books.
It needs to run it four times
and the same for the make plot.
And then it tells us why it ran each step that it ran.
So it figured out statistics IELTS.data
is not existing at the moment.
So it finds out what it needs to run
to bring it into existence.
And that is then step one out of nine, and then it checks further what to execute and goes on and on.
And one thing to note here is that there is different job IDs that are not necessarily in order,
So it will figure out that for each book it first needs to run the statistics file and then the plot file.
But it does not necessarily run first the statistics file and then the plot file for each book.
But it may mix it up a little bit so that it runs first two books, the statistics file and then one of these plots and then another of the statistics and another one of these plots.
and that it all gets to know through this snake file.
Now I see that I'm already very short on time,
basically already over,
so I will check what I wanted to show here still.
We could now go and check that all the files are there.
Maybe for right now you can trust me that it
created all the plots and all the statistics files.
And now the power of SnakeMake comes really from this
that if we now had a script that would run all these steps,
and we now added a new file, for example.
Let's do this briefly.
There's a question, the last one.
Yeah.
Maybe useful to go now I don't understand this code how come it runs for multiple books the files only run once
Oh
Um, which code is maybe like in the snake file
I assume maybe it was talking about the snake file or something. Like how does the snake file run for all the separate codes?
Okay, this is figured out in the snake file by using these wildcards.
So in this step here, it figures out what all text files are available in this data
directory.
So it knows that there is four right now.
And in the command line, it showed us, like, for each of the books that it ran it, like,
for Sierra was one book, last something was some book.
So we can see that it actually ran it for all the files.
So if we now, this same thing we can do with a script.
But if we now have a new data file, for example,
this, don't worry about the editor.
It is now just an editor.
And there is some text in here, is some text in here,
which I would like my script to count and plot.
And I save that.
In the script case, I now would need to run my script again,
or I would need to run the steps separately again.
In the SnakeMake case, if I now run SnakeMake again,
you could maybe see it was very fast,
that it now was a little bit faster.
And we can see in the job statistics
here that it figured out that it only
need to run one file and that is,
you can find it here probably,
the new.txt, so it found there's
one new file that it has not processed all the way,
so it processed only the new file.
The same thing happens also if there would now be,
for example, a change in one of the scripts.
Let's say in the plot script,
We don't want to plot the script,
the bars in blue,
but want to put them in red, for example.
We would go into the script and change it.
If we then tell SnakeMake to run again,
it will figure out which files are affected by this change.
It will figure out that it will not have to run
all the statistics again, but only the plotting.
And that is, unfortunately, the time over for this topic.
If you're interested in this, I would highly recommend to go on the lesson page.
is also the example and some discussions around it and all the steps that I had planned to do now
and that I didn't get through are mentioned also here and also some more explanations of each
of the rules and then also take a look at the solution how to do it. You can also visualize
this workflow, this DAG directed acyclic graph, what SnakeMake is using in the background.
And we are using SnakeMake here because compared to many other workflow tools, it has a rather
gentle learning curve. I understand that this was probably a little bit confusing. Sorry
for that. But if you take a look and try to apply it yourself, I think you will better
understand how things are connected and why this could be a benefit for also your workflow.
You can use it on many different platforms. SnakeMake is also very smart in a way that
it can figure out if there is independent steps that it can run those in parallel.
You can also run it with the next two topics of this lesson, the isolated environments and
also containers. It's very much used in bioinformatics, but as you can see, we can
use it for counting words as well, so it's not specific to bioinformatics, so you can run all
kinds of workflows with it and they have a super extensive documentation with lots of videos and
lots of tutorials going on and there is lots of similar tools that you can also find here
that you can use for that. So we can collect these computational steps in many many ways
and workflow tools may be able to help with doing this and I will still go
through the questions and look at it but I think now we should take a break, right?
Yes, thanks [name]. I think now we can have a break, 10 minutes break, so we can be back
on the stream at 11. What is that? Finnish time 11.14. And I can write this in the notes.
Thank you.
you
You
Hello, and welcome back.
So hopefully you're all still well motivated
to make your work more reproducible.
So it's really nice that there's many questions on this topic
that we've been covering so far.
And compared to previous rounds of the Code Refinery Workshop,
I think this is great that we decided
to focus more on giving you demos and showing you the tools,
because then the questions are actually more you know at the general level that rather than trying
to you know rerun the same scripts that [name] was running for example and focusing on specific
errors that are not related to this topic and in general we will have time to answer all these
questions with more details during the longer break and all the answers of course will be
archive so hopefully this is a great resource for your for your future learning goals.
All right so we kind of if we go back to this time scales of tracking changes and making things that
you can rerun what you did six months ago or a year ago after tracking the tiny changes
with the version control from week one then we look at kind of recording the steps because
Because in some cases, maybe, you know, there's just a single script that you need to run.
There's just a single data file that you need to load.
And maybe that is the single step of your research.
But in many cases, one needs to, like we saw with the books, run through 1,000 books or
1,000 parameters, hyperparameters, 1,000 whatever training input files in machine learning.
So then the computational steps and all the steps
that one needs to record, they start to scale up,
that it starts to become impossible to manually remember
that you still need to run whatever permutation, 1,555.
But then in general, if we keep on increasing the time scale,
so what we're trying to document and what
are trying to record, then we go at the time scale of the system of the project. So in
this funny XKCD figure here, this is not just about actually scientific research. This is
in practice when it comes about any modern digital infrastructure can be popular social
media that you use or, I don't know, your email service provider. So people, companies
and scientists and researchers they build on top of other people's work and sometimes
you know there might be a tiny little element that is literally keeping all the infrastructure
together and when it comes to scientific research and scientific code of course you want to
document if you truly depend on that little you know project that some random person in
Nebraska has been maintaining since 2003. In the Internet, actually, there's one tool
very useful in the Internet, which is called Curl. And for many years, the Curl command
has been basically maintained by a single person for free, even though it's one of
those core elements that is inside any software that uses the Internet, basically.
So continue with kind of the kitchen analogy because we always like to talk about cooking.
So this also came up in the collaborative notes that if the software, if the code is
like the recipe, so they're like the steps that you need to run to cook whatever you're
planning to cook and if the data are like the ingredients that you need to mix together
to obtain what you want to cook then we have the so-called libraries or modules or whatever
you want to call them that they're like the cooking books because most likely you don't
want to write your own cooking book you don't want to write your recipe you want to reuse
an existing recipe and libraries maybe many of you are familiar with the Python programming
language most likely you're using libraries like NumPy or pandas or matplotlib so that you don't
need to write in pure python you know how to take care of big matrices or how to work with
tabular data but you can easily reuse existing libraries so that you can focus on the actual
you know enjoyment of the final cook cooked product rather than you know focusing or rewriting
something that already exists so with this specific page here with this
specific lesson we're trying to understand that there needs to be a way
when we want to document all our process all our steps there also needs to be a
way to document how we depend on other libraries because maybe today there's a
certain version of NumPy and it might be that in one year or in five years from
now that version will have drastic changes to the current version that is right now and then
your code will not be able to run anymore because it was depending on these external libraries.
So to understand this in a more practical way and here I'm asking the help of [name]
to do this exercise together. So let's consider this so-called WebRotier time capsule of
of dependencies. So that could be that. All right. You inherit some code from the previous
postdoc of the research lab that you're joining and all you see in the code that there's a
couple of imports of some libraries. So that's it. You don't really know which libraries
the codes need but you just see maybe like in the Python case would be you see some import
NumPy. Then you have another a little better case maybe or is it better where with the
code there's also a readme file which basically writes down you know you really need NumPy
for this for this project. But it doesn't mention which NumPy do I need the NumPy from
2011. Did it even exist or you know a NumPy from 2024. Then you might find you might be
more lucky and with the project that you inherit you might find that there's also some sort
of a structure file this specific file format is this is just a text file but it's called
YML yet another markup language and the YAML file is just a way to basically write in a
in a way that is machine readable something that also a human can understand and this specific
case we don't need I'm not going to tell you right now what this means but at least you see that
here we explicitly say that we have our code depends on having NumPy and
and SciPy and SumPy and other Python projects and here interesting actually they even have
references to some git projects. So in this case, [name], would this mean that
this dependency file is also referring to a specific branch in a specific project, isn't it?
Yeah, to the master branch in the GitHub repository of some user called some project.
Okay, so then if I inherit this file with all the other files of the project, then I would know that
i also need to figure out how to basically git clone this branch from this project and
make sure that it's visible with the rest of the libraries but we have more cases in this
challenge in this case this is a similar file than the one before but i see some differences
there's more added numbers so [name] do you think or at least i guess that these are the
numbers is more like trying to fix the version what I was saying earlier that maybe one really
needs to have version 1.16 but what about this this thing that you see at the end of the git url
yeah because if you don't have the versions then you usually get like the latest possible the
latest that is available and that of course might change between years or even already weeks and
And then for Git, now we are not referring to a branch anymore,
but we are referring to a specific commit.
And we have learned about commits and also tags
last week.
So it's way more specific than referring to, especially
the master branch, which also is something
like the tool might have developed over time.
So the master branch might not be the same
as it was a week ago, a month ago, a year ago.
But the commit stays or the tag stays.
So that basically we are literally
traveling to the exact time point
where the project, some project, had a specific tag
or specific time point.
And then the last case, if you see what I see,
that now this some project and this another project,
now they have their own version.
So most likely here, the person who
were working with this project, they also made a release
and they gave it a tag name that is, in this case,
the number of the release.
So that it can be made more clear in this dependency.
So now we have these five scenarios.
And in your opinion, [name], which version
do you expect would be the easiest to rerun and why?
I would choose version E, because there you have actually all packages, so also the things
that were in version D and the previous one were on GitHub only and linked to there, and
linking to some cryptic commit hash or something now have versions, so they have been packaged,
it's like a much nicer way of referring to them. But already D is very good, I think, in terms of
reproducibility because you have the version. So even if you run this one year from now,
that old version will hopefully still be available somewhere so you can still use it.
Whereas when you don't specify the version and rely on the latest and greatest, then that might
be have more features or have like good stuff coming with it as well but it might also have
deprecated so some functionality just doesn't exist anymore or has been replaced with a different
function call or something like this so there can be issues coming from that as well. How about you?
Yeah I mean I kind of naively thought that the C would be the way to go because I get the latest
of whatever the latest NumPy, the latest Python and the latest, you know, but if I, and I've
been working with this type of, you know, get the latest of everything, but then suddenly
things don't work when you get the latest of everything, then you need to go and track
in this some project that actually they clearly specify it stopped working after NumPy went
to whatever version.
So long story short what we're trying to motivate you here and I can tell you this is so important
if that's one of the things you need to remember from today and if you want to learn one thing
from today learn this. This is absolutely one of the most asked questions that we get
in our support work at Aalto and in anywhere and it's the versioning of the dependencies.
So there's one tool there's various tools for doing that and some tools are specific
of some programming language here for the purpose of focusing on a single one we will
talk about Conda.
And so Conda is this type of tool that can be used with Python but not only with Python
Conda can also be used with R for example it's one tool that is able to track this type
of dependencies.
So what you saw here in this YAML file,
these are actually machine-readable files
so that the Conda program is able to read these
and, for example, create a so-called Conda environment
with the specific version.
Now, what maybe some people struggle
at the beginning to understand what
are Conda environments or Python virtual environments,
I usually give this example that in one operating system,
you might have one installation of Python.
and that has a specific Python version
and it has some library with it.
By adding more environments,
it's like that you're reinstalling Python.
You are installing a new version of Python
without a set of libraries.
And with this type of virtual environments,
you can have multiple versions of Python,
for example, installed in your computer.
And it's actually a great thing.
One could argue that, is it that I'm wasting disk space?
Sure, maybe, you know, you are wasting some disk space,
but we're still talking about small files, small library.
The price of wasting some disk space
and having multiple versions of Python
storing your system is that actually you can have
for different project their own specific
Conda environment, their own specific Python installation.
And so you're sure that, you know, for that project
you can work with a specific Python version.
Here we see 3.10 and some specific, you know,
NumPy, or whatever libraries you need to use.
And the second advantage of using virtual environment
is also, of course, the portability,
because I might now start a new project today
with this type of dependency.
I don't really need to fix NumPy and Pandas,
because I'm happy with whatever I'm starting today,
the new project, so just give me the latest.
But then I might want to move this project to another system,
or I might want to share this project with a colleague.
And so it's possible to so-called
freeze the environment, meaning that with some commands
after activating the environment or after going
inside this other installation of Python,
then I can also tell, ask the program,
give me all the libraries that have been installed so far.
So how are we doing with the timings?
I guess, do we have time that I will give a quick demo of this?
Or?
Go ahead, a quick one.
OK.
So let me get the right windows.
So in this white window, you see where I'm going to type.
And in the bottom window, you see the comments
that I've been typing.
So here I have this file that you saw there, myenv.yaml, and now what I'm able to do is that
with the command that you see here I'm able to actually create this environment. Specifically
now instead of typing the same command that you see there, conda env create, so start a new
environment, I will actually use a program called Mamba and we listed it there. It's basically like
conda but it's again one of those tools that you should learn about it's a it's a conda that is
being rewritten in c so that it's much faster than the conda otherwise i timed it yesterday it
would take 20 minutes for conda to to resolve this environment with mamba it takes maybe less than a
a minute. So mambaenv create and then I specify this file. So now what happens is that it's
basically first seeing what type of request, what type of libraries I'm requesting. But of course
you understand that even though I'm requesting only Python and NumPy, Pandas and Seaborn, so very
basic stuff. These tools themselves, they might depend on other, many other libraries because,
I don't know, Seaborn needs to depend on Matplotlib plus some other opening some specific
file formats, figure formats or writing in different figure formats. So in the end, actually,
this Mamba is now installing 72 packages. So there's actually 72 libraries that are needed
for this specific environment for this specific project and now it's downloading and extracting
all the packages and now the environment is ready so right now i'm not in that specific
environment so as you see here at the end i need to activate the the environment so i activate it
And in the name of the environment, it's called myenv.
So now the prompt has changed.
If you have worked with Python and specifically from the terminal, you might be familiar with
this, but if you have not, this is something that is worth investing some time and learning
about the Conda environments.
And now it's like I connected to a new system with a new Python installation, and specifically
the new Python installation that I asked with all the dependencies and now here I'm able let's say
that I have to pass this environment to [name] so I'm able to type this command conda m export
and this will show all the files all these 72 packages that were installed and you see that
there's quite many of them and now it even has so-called resolved down to the tiny version
out even to, you know, to some specific hash of which version of CBOR am I going here. So with
the syntax that you see here in the learning materials conda m export and this greater than
it means dump the content that you see here on a file environment.yml. There's an easter egg here
that one can also one can also export from history and this is again important to look
at this so let me try running also this command
and now the difference from this command is that actually this kind of is able to give
me back the original environment that I used. So with conda-envexport I got a fine-grained
detailed version down to the tiny hashtag hashes of all the 72 packages. With conda-envexport
from history maybe this is useful for the next project that I can start. I hope this
This was, you know, motivational enough for people to get started using Conda, but this
is, again, I repeat, the most frequently asked question every day.
We even have a joke in our support room that how many days have been going on without Conda
being mentioned, and usually it's zero.
But if we scale down even more, so now we're trying to look at the dependencies of the code,
dependency of all the libraries. What if we scale even bigger, [name]?
I can keep the screen share if you just tell me when to scroll or do you want to take over?
No, you can keep it. You can scroll down a little bit. So yeah, so now we have been talking about
how to record the computational steps, how to record our dependencies of the tools that we are
already using in our workflow,
but what if it's still not enough?
What if we want everything in one file?
What if we want an entire operating system
together with the dependencies,
with the code, maybe even with the data?
That's where containers come in.
Now, we also get back to the icebreaker
before, like this topic of it works on my machine.
And these containers are like one of the answers to that.
And there's many different like tools
for building using containers.
One of them is Docker.
That's where this meme here comes from.
And if you scroll a little bit down,
we can again think back to our kitchen analogy
that we have our codes and scripts,
which are basically our cooking recipes.
They tell us what goes into our dish and how to prepare it.
Then we talk in the world of containers,
we talk about container definition files,
or in the Docker case,
it would be called a Docker file.
They are like a blueprint,
how to build a kitchen with everything in it,
that you have everything ready to prepare the dish that
is described that you have in your cooking recipe.
So the container definition file is the blueprint.
It shows us how to create this kitchen.
Then container images are
then example kitchens that are built from this blueprint.
Now you scrolled away from there, sorry.
Then we have the containers themselves,
which are built from the images,
from the example kitchens,
that are really the kitchens
where you can prepare these cooking recipes.
And you can go through here, these images
and have a guess which of the images
represents which operating system.
Containers can come to you in many different forms
and in many different occasions,
you may have come across them.
And that's why we also ask this question
in the very bottom of the collaborative document.
if you ever have been in contact with containers and how you came across them,
because that can be very different for people.
Please go and answer that question if you have come across containers,
because that might also help others to see where are
the use cases for this kind of systems.
The benefit is that you have really everything in one file,
not just the dependencies, but really,
like you can have a whole different operating system.
Like if your laptop is running on Windows, for example,
and you find a tool on the internet
where you only can find installation instructions
or prepared software for Linux system, for example,
that might be one case where then a container
can be very helpful to like have this operating system
that you need to then install your software
inside of there and run it via that.
These definition files that already mentioned what
we related to the blueprints,
they are usually text files,
and a little bit further down,
we have an example of that,
and [name] will show it also in a little bit.
They instruct you how to build this environment.
What do you need?
What kind of operating system do you use?
What kind of software do you want to have installed in that environment?
And then when you build an image from that definition file,
from this container recipe, that is then basically like a piece of paper
where you have the operating system and these base tools installed on it.
And then whatever you do then on your command line or on your computer
within that container,
then you're adding a layer of transparency.
Maybe you have seen it when you want to
update your house or something like this.
You have the blueprint of the house in the bottom,
and then you add a transparent layer where you draw
all your ideas that you want to add to your house,
that you want to add a staircase in the middle of
your living room just to try how it looks.
Then at some point, you're like,
oh no, that's not the idea.
I throw that away.
That is also then why the image,
the container image, it always stays the same.
These transparency layers, they are then thrown away after you
close the connection to that container that you're running.
Other use cases for containers are exactly this.
If you have your code and that runs in a certain environment
and you want to make sure that everyone is using the same environment,
you can provide them with an image of this container
or you can provide them with this definition file,
like the instructions on how to build that image
and how to run that in a container.
Here is now the example of a definition file.
This is now from Singularity.
I mentioned already Docker and then there's
also Obtainer and Portman and probably even more than that.
But these are, I think, the most famous ones maybe.
This you may come across also when you're
working on clusters, for example.
It's very much used there.
And here you can see that this definition file is a text file
similar to what we have seen with Conda.
We are defining like the operating system first.
Here we are using a Docker image
that is somewhere on the Docker hub.
I think it's called of Ubuntu,
which is a Linux operating system.
So if [name] would, for example, have a Windows laptop
and would want to run an Ubuntu on that laptop,
you could use this file to build a container to run Ubuntu in.
Then you can provide a few more things that you want to add there,
so you can define environment variables,
you can install stuff which is done here in this post section,
And then you can also add scripts that should be run when the container is executed.
And is that now maybe where we go into the demo?
Maybe we can come back to the pros and cons of containers when we start wrapping things up.
So I think that this demo is a funny one.
So, in this specific container recipe that you see here, basically the user wants to
run the command, the Linux command cow say, which is a funny command that it displays
some ASCII, ASCII art, ASCII cow that can say whatever you tell the cow to say.
However, if I would be working on my own computer, I would have all the rights to install this
specific Kause command and I wouldn't need to, you know, start containers, install containers,
create the containers. But often when I need to scale because my laptop is old and it doesn't
have enough RAM or enough CPUs, I'm most likely going to work on some remote machine.
It can be one HPC cluster, it can be the Lumi supercomputer, it can be various things.
So let's now go to this remote machine where I am right now. I could even call that deactivate.
OK. Let's see where I am. I have a subfolder called the pen sorry environments because now this is the stage where we're really recording the whole environment operating system.
So if I try to run the command, which is called Kausei,
hello world.
All right, the command is not installed in this remote
machine.
I could now open a ticket with the administrator
of this remote cluster and ask them,
can you please install Kausei?
Of course, maybe I feel a bit silly
because it's a silly command.
Maybe I don't want to ask the administrators to install
this type of thing.
But it could also well be that the administrator actually
not supporting installations because they get too many requests and what the administrator
could tell you, you know, create yourself a container so that you can run this command.
So given this recipe that I've written here in this kaose.dev, so this is the same recipe
that you see there and it's again another one of those machine readable format,
machine readable and also human readable that the human understand that we want to use Ubuntu
get and it's like really that I'm installing a new Linux machine and make sure that I run
this type of installation script. So let's build it. So the software that I'm going to
use now all the steps that I'm talking about the year they're listed in this exercise
two in the in the page. So the tool I'm going to use is called Obtainer. Let's see that I have it.
Yes, I have Obtainer 1.2. And so Obtainer is one of those tools that kind of emerged from
the Singularity project. Obtainer became more like the branch dedicated to scientific computing
while Singularity CE is more supporting enterprises.
I left this here because these are something
that often is problematic because Obtainer
to create the images and it's to download,
you really need to imagine that you are downloading
a full operating system.
So it can require lots of disk space,
but I already set this step here.
So I can look at the environment variables
in my in my and I already have set this temporary folder and and a cache folder and now I can
finally build. So now it's like I'm installing this new computer. So obtainer build the name
of the image that I'm going to create is this CIF and then the definition file is cow say
all right so now what is happening it's really like that i'm connecting to a
new laptop and i'm installing the operating system
so first it needs to download the image of the operating system
it's now installing everything that is needed for ubuntu
in this operating system it's installed it's really so fast
it's installing all the kaos and everything else
it's making sure that you know the file system of this computer of this virtual
virtual computer is you know has everything that is needed installing some other dependencies and
hopefully in the very next few seconds it will say that this is done and I can now basically
like connect to this computer it's funny that I'm still in the same computer so now it's actually
creating this this file so now this CIF file becomes like a new computer that I can log in
into. And when I'm inside this new computer, even though it's a virtual computer, it's not a physical
computer, I'm able to finally run the cowsay command. So I remind you that we are where I am
when I type cowsay, command not found, but now I can actually enter this computer, this virtual
machine, this container, obtainer shell, and the name of the image that I created.
it. And now I'm inside. You see the prompt change. It says obtainer. Now I'm in a new
computer and now I can test the command. Let's see if it works. Yes. And we got our cow that
can say whatever we want to say. So suddenly without any administrator rights without any
special permissions I was able to install a new program and run it. You can understand
and how powerful this is if you depend on specific,
especially in machine learning,
people need to work with some specific version
of libraries PyTorch,
which might depend on specific version
of so-called CUDA GPU card drivers.
And with this system,
you can specifically go down to the drivers,
down to the libraries for your research work.
So it's 11.49.
We still have good 10 minutes for wrapping up.
So [name], what about the pros and the cons of containers?
Yeah, one nice thing here is now also
that even if something goes wrong, because it still might,
there is so many levels where these things can go wrong.
Because everything is now in one file,
it is very easy to remove, rather than if you think about
if you install something on your computer,
you might have to go into different places
to find all the files that were actually
involved in the installations you're working on at the moment.
Then also, many of us are nowadays working with huge datasets,
and sometimes these datasets are getting too large to transfer.
So containers are also one way
of sending the computer to the data, so to say.
So we don't have to download the data,
but there's probably some Cloud service that is set up,
where you can then like run your container very close to the data and don't have to worry about
this transfer. And then if it's like if you have a lot of dependencies in your in your work
you can take away some of these challenges to deal with these dependencies because they might
be on different levels. It might not just be like within Python that you can solve with Conda but
already like on operating system level there might be some libraries that you need that you need to
install in some certain way to make it work. So this is also one way of like recording on how
this can be done and also then with the image you can actually provide a working machine so to say.
So it also can solve this works on my machine situation. And then [name] could now send this
this C file that he just created to me and I could probably run it here on my computer
and also like happily look at the cow saying different things even though I don't have
it installed on my computer. But then of course with this same thing you can also like solve
your installation problems by hiding them behind this kind of container solution,
which may discourage good software development practices.
Of course, we hope it doesn't,
but it may result in that.
It can, of course, then also change that.
Now, we don't have this works on my machine problem anymore,
but we have this,
okay, it works only in this container.
and then if you have a colleague who for some reason
cannot install this container software
on their laptop or something,
how do they then deal with this?
But it still helps with this works on my machine problem.
They can sometimes be difficult to modify.
So if you, for example, go on Docker Hub
and find some image that does almost what you wanna do,
do but not quite there's something missing it can be sometimes difficult to modify those
and there's many different ways on how you can go about this by for example just adding another
layer on top of that image that already exists if that works for your use case and then
In the similar as with Conda environments, also container images can become very large.
They may take up a lot of space on your laptop.
So it's always good with all these tools to, as one of the first things that you find out,
find out how to clean up unused images, unused containers, not running containers, things
that you don't need anymore, how to clean the cache so that you don't run out of disk
space because you need to try 10 different operating systems with your software.
And then good little red box, do you have anything to say about the danger, [name]?
Well, I mean, that in general, it's like when you install software, you might only want
to make sure that you're using official and trusted images,
that you never know what you might be installing
if you use an untrusted source for, let's say,
Ubuntu operating system.
So this is, as usual, it's good to trust those trusted images.
And if you are not sure, talk with your local helper
or colleague.
In the same page, there are also some other demos
that you can try yourself.
For example, if you install Docker on your machine,
here, there's a nice demo where you
can travel back in time to a specific version of RStudio.
And here, we've done a conda, with conda,
basically, that you can install a specific version.
But maybe it's time to wrap up.
So where do we go from here?
I checked the notes document.
I don't see there are many nice questions, interesting
questions, but we will answer them there.
I think it's now too important, though,
to understand that now we discover
and we uncovered all these timescales
of the documentation of the project
from the tiny changes of the Git
down to the large changes of operating system
and libraries that are in a specific version
of our OpenStreetMap system.
So in general, the take-home message for you
is that this is important for every project,
but the second important take-home message here
is that you don't need to feel anxious or stressful
or stressed about all this, you know,
knowledge and all these tools.
It might well be that some of the tools
that we show here today,
you don't see an immediate use right now.
It's more than it becomes you,
like it starts to become a personal choice
that maybe you understand that workflow tools are important
and you understand that there will be some learning curve,
some time that you need to spend to get it running,
but then this will make maybe benefit you in the future
if you know that you will be running,
you know, many workflows, many pipelines,
or you will be building pipelines in your future career.
But for sure, it's important to worry about dependencies.
Again, maybe you're just, you know, playing with code
and you're just happy with one local Python installation
and after a few months by installing random packages,
you see that it's all a mess
and then you will just reinstall everything
and start from scratch.
But sometimes when it's not about working alone anymore,
when you need especially to show to other people
your work that you've been doing, the dependencies,
so the conda environments,
and even writing down the steps,
it becomes kind of part of your work.
So at the end of the day, it's not just sharing your code
to show what you did in your research,
but also sharing kind of how for other people,
how other scientists can rerun your code.
And then last comment, when it comes to the containers,
again, you got a nice overview on the pros and cons.
You might wonder, do I have a use for them?
It might well be that right now you don't need
to learn Singularity, Obtainer, Docker, and so on.
But then you start facing the issue
that you need to use a remote supercomputer
and suddenly you can't install the tools that you need.
Or more in general, you did such, such an important work
that you really need to document it,
that this work, this result should really need
to be reproduced in 10 years from the future.
So again, with the higher requirements of your project,
you might start thinking, you know, maybe I really need to use containers for this case.
Hopefully the overview that we gave is kind of useful for everyone from the most
beginner to the most advanced users. Is there anything else to cover, [name]? Anything to
mention from the collaborative notes? No, there's very many questions and it's
Really really great thank you and we will still go through these and answer a bit more and also
please ask follow-up questions if the explanation you got there is not sufficient or doesn't solve
your question. Yeah I mean thank you for listening everyone as usual we wrote in the
collaborative notes this feedback part because we are continuously improving our
our lessons, workshop after workshop. And so if there's something that could have more
clarity or that would require more justifications, just write it there. All comments, all feedback
are welcome. So [name], will you now go and start using Singularity after this?
I did start actually using after a CodeRefiner workshop
many years ago.
And I hope, well, yeah, that everyone got an impression
what these tools can be useful for.
And as mentioned before, like the easiest way to get into it
to start using them and then ask from your local IT support
if you run into issues with them.
And I think now we have a one hour break before we go into the next lesson, which if I remember
correctly is social coding for the afternoon. Is that correct?
Yeah. Excellent. Thank you, [name], for being here with me again. It was nice to teach
together. It's 12 o'clock in Finland, 11 o'clock in Central Europe. So it's time for a lunch
or branch, depending on the taste. See you in one hour and thank you. Bye.
you
Hello, and welcome back.
You hopefully can hear us now.
Let's see, I'm adjusting something here.
So, yeah, hopefully you had a good lunch break.
So what do we have now?
Well, first off, we should tell you if the things from the previous lesson were a bit
difficult.
We have these things called bring your own code sessions, where you can basically bring
your work and we can look at it and provide a little bit more
hands-on support in using these tools for your own work.
So there's not much we can do.
We can't help everyone, but we can at least get you started.
If you do have more questions and you have collaborators
or support people locally, try talking to them.
And you can show them the Code Refinery lesson saying,
Oh, I saw this, I would like to use it, can you help me?
And they can probably help quite a bit.
So what we have next, the lesson, is called Social Coding and Software Licensing.
This used to be called Software Licensing and was about, well, the permissions of reusing
software.
But it's been changed so it's much more broad now.
So in the previous lesson, we talked about ways to make it where your code could be used
by other people.
But do they have permission?
And do they have permission to contribute back to your code and make this whole cycle
of all the different things going together?
Yeah, so, is there any other introduction or should I send it straight to you all?
You can send it to us, we should maybe say briefly who we are and give it over to you.
So yeah, who are our instructors for this lesson?
We have [name], who I think is new here.
Yeah.
Hello, I'm [name], I work at Aalto University as a research software engineer and well,
I suppose that's enough.
Yeah.
And [name], I think you know from last week.
Yes, University of Tromso, Norway, research software engineering and support for computing
software development, high performance computing.
And I'm really looking forward to this lesson.
It's a really important topic.
It's something that we all need to think about.
And I like how it nicely connects to the earlier session from today.
is about, it's again about reuse,
but less on the technical level, more on the social level.
And what I will try to do is I will be here,
be Yano's sidekick.
I will be watching the notes
and hopefully we get lots of questions.
I will try to keep a really lively discussion.
So for everybody, the best way to participate
is that you watch and listen what we do.
there will there will not be any exercises here we will have some we will try to involve you through
the document we will ask you some questions through the document we hope to get many answers
and i will try to lift some questions also here into the discussion
so this is more of a discussion session than a um well than an exercise or a demonstration
but we'll still try to spend a good amount of time in actual discussion.
Should we get to it?
I will also have questions for [name], because he's actually the expert here.
But I'll also try to keep this on track.
Yeah, I'm not sure about the expert part, but I'm also sure that I will have questions to you too.
So let's keep it really...
We'll see.
Let's see.
Yeah. So yeah, social coding and open software. So
yeah, this is a relatively broad section. It's about how you
some things you need to think about when publishing your software and how to get credit
and allow people to reuse it and in general how to interact with people around your published code.
So let's get down to it.
This is the plan for the course, for this section.
So we'll first talk about social coding, general topic.
Some about licensing and then how to get people to or how to enable people to cite your software.
And what to consider when sharing data.
data. So it's more about laying out things that you need to, or
that are good to think about when you are publishing your
work. And kind of prodding a bit at your brains and getting
getting some ideas out so that they come to mind when you are
actually working on this. So let's get directly to the
or actually i can click through here social coding section and here we have our first
exercise discussion topic so maybe i should copy this to the notes
yeah i'm working on it so i can i'm testing okay thanks it's it's in there now okay so yeah so
So there's a few things about,
initial thoughts about social coding.
So why would you want to share your code?
Of course, talked about this already.
Hopefully there's some ideas out there.
So can you click to the collaborative notes?
Yes.
So here, what we would like is,
we would like you all to add your votes.
you can vote by adding these little O's
and you can choose many in question one.
Yeah, so we'll get a little paragraph
and feel free to add something
if you see something missing.
Yeah, and here we want to hear from you.
Yeah, what are your motivations to share code?
What are your concerns?
So have a look at also the other questions,
question one, two, three, four,
And then together now with [name], as we discuss,
we will then return to your answers.
And we are really curious to see
which ones are the most motivating, most concerning.
So why would you not share your software, basically?
Well, why share your software?
Why would you not?
Yeah, how is software different from papers?
There's a lot to talk about there, we'll come back to.
So how about, how is it for you, [name], when, when question one, what are for you?
Why share them?
Out of these, which ones are the most, which one?
Yeah, I guess.
I mean, as a research software engineer, we mainly work for, with open software.
So it also comes from there, but just thinking of my own projects, which are not all research
projects.
One big thing is to just have it out there so that I don't lose it.
That's a really actually important motivation for sharing.
So you never lose access to it yourself.
That's a good one.
Also for me.
Jay, answer is important to me.
How about the good for your CV, is that important for you?
I mean, to an extent, I'm not looking for a job, or I'm not expecting to be looking
for a job very soon, but yeah, it is an important point, especially after working as a software
engineer for a while, if you don't have any code out there that people can see, that would
be a bit concerning, but as a researcher, yeah, as well.
And yeah, I mean, it is good to keep accumulating your portfolio as you go.
But yeah, I mean, actually one of the main reasons though is that I want feedback on
what I'm doing.
I want to see if people are actually interested, and if they're not, then I will work on something
else.
So yeah, that is the main thing.
I want people to actually see it, read it and I want to know if it's if other people
think it's interesting because if I'm doing some research that nobody cares about then
I should work on something else.
What's the most concerning thing for you when sharing or and maybe what what used to be
and what is it now? Yeah, like 10 years ago when starting my career, I was afraid that the code
looked bad and people would just think it looks bad basically. I don't know what the downside of
that actually would be, what would be the problem with people thinking my code looks ugly, but
But that was a real concern.
And right now, I think the main thing is,
there's a definite thing on my mind.
It's mainly that if something better already
if I haven't actually noticed it and I'm somehow taking some eyes off the better version of it.
How about you? What is your main reason for sharing and also for not?
It's the, so that ideally I can reuse it in future. So I share it with everybody else
but I also don't share it with my future self.
So the answer, J.
And the CV part is important,
and the job search doesn't have to be this year, next year,
but how about in five years, what, in 10 years?
I would like to be able to show what I worked on,
which means that if I have the choice
between working on a project that is open
and where my contribution will be visible
and one which is completely closed
and I cannot show it to anybody,
I will probably choose the more open one.
So it works also, it can also work the other way
in attracting collaborators.
So a project that is open will,
is more likely to attract me to work on it
because then I can show my work inside there.
And how about the worries?
Also, I used to think a lot about
that somebody will like go in and, I don't know,
steal the idea.
I'm not worried about it because,
I mean, I have a hard time understanding my own code.
I don't think anybody else will figure it out before I do.
And an ugly code.
And I think if we look at the answers,
so the answer B, it will expose my in quotes ugly code.
It's the answer that wins today.
And it's the answer that wins every single time.
And hopefully it is nice for all of us to see
that we all think that way.
And it actually doesn't matter and nobody will judge
and the code is never finished and it's okay.
And when you go and find somebody else's code and it's useful and it does what you want it to do, you are happy about it.
I mean, you don't think, well, this is ugly.
So I find it really comforting to see.
On the positive side, there is the more general, I mean, not just the CV, but the reputation you get.
it's a social reward you get for publishing something that is maybe more important than
the professional side of it. It is natural to think that if your code looks ugly then
maybe that would kind of go in the wrong direction, maybe people don't like it,
but in practice it's more important that there's something out there that kind of works and people
will always be happy to find anything and I mean of course if it if it's nice and if it's ready
and if it's usable that's good but it's still better to find something than nothing
okay should we look at the other questions
so
So software is different from papers, which is true.
So yeah, in my mind, the analogy is between software and papers.
Papers are often usually mainly about the results, about the scientific results.
A software publication is kind of like a publication that describes your methodology,
your experimental setup. So if you're running an experiment or especially if you're building
a device to run the experiment then it's also important to describe the entire process in
detail so that people can repeat your and reproduce your study. So yeah, publishing the
software is kind of analogous to publishing the blueprints for your experimental device or
publishing the entire methodology of your study. And here I can say that there are
journals that specialize on where you can publish, you can describe the software part.
But it's not so much about publishing the research results used with the software, but
where you can focus on the software part.
And hopefully, towards the end of this session, we will have time to mention those and discuss
those.
Yeah.
Question four is essentially, well, it's a large part of what we'll come back to.
I don't know actually if there's a huge difference in software for question 3.
There's about publishing rights, so I'm assuming who can publish what and what is considered plagiarism.
I don't know that there is a huge difference there.
Software licensing works differently because software is something you can run, you can use to do something.
a paper is mainly the it is the text that you just read
um so software can be used in different ways
in more different ways than papers but in general i i think the publication
rights work almost completely the same way
good point and i think we will return to that to that aspect also question four
here we wanted to hear from you but we will discuss that also in a little
moment, I believe, or should we go there now in question for,
um, well, I mean, we can do that.
I don't mind.
Um, so what do you look at?
Um, should we answer this ourselves first?
What's the first thing you look at when you find a, um, software written by
someone else that you could use in your project?
So this is about, you want to do something,
you search for it, has anybody done it?
And now you see that, aha, there is a repository on GitHub.
And it's very similar to what I wanted.
Can I just reuse it and change it?
And the things that I would look at is license.
Yeah.
So can I even change it?
and am I allowed to change it?
And especially, as we will see in a moment,
I can do almost anything
if I just keep it on my own computer.
But the important question is, am I allowed to change it
and then publish the result?
Because that's what I really want to do.
So can I change it and share it?
Because publishing and sharing is often related.
So that's one thing I would look at,
but there are many other good answers there.
Yes. So how is the project still alive? How recent are the most recent commits? Are there
open issues or pull requests? So yeah, is it being developed? And if it's old enough,
it might not run or you might need to do a lot of work to get it to work.
Yeah.
It's of course also nice if it stays up to date and people can use it later.
yeah and i do look at that when was the last change um will it be hard to install yeah but
then if you see a project that hasn't been touched in three years i think it's it's nice if we are
also uh it's i mean i also understand the other side i mean i have many projects that i started
i worked on them and then i stopped working on them because if i if i would support every
every single project that I ever started,
at some point, I would not be able to start anything new.
So it's a normal process that many projects,
most projects at some point stop.
And it's nice if we are constructive about it
and nice about it.
So you could also be the person
who then finds a project that has stopped
and takes it up and revives it.
So sometimes I feel bad when I get,
I see comments on my own projects,
this is this this is a dead project nobody has the issues are not followed up the pull requests
are not merged yeah well uh yeah maybe somebody else can do that this is open source and at some
point i need to move on to other projects yeah it's always better to have it out there than
not so even if you cannot actually continually develop it you just need it for your current
thing and then it's done it's still better to have it out there
of course it is also good to communicate clearly that you are no longer developing it so that
other people feel free to pick it up and yeah continue working on great question on
line 247 so what exactly is software if i write a python code
a script that does an analysis to get the result of a paper.
So is that part of software?
Is this what we're talking about here?
Should we then, do we need to think about licenses?
And it's a rhetorical question.
So yes, yes, it is software.
It can even be, it can be a short script.
And then we don't have to do much.
We can add a license file or on top of the script,
we can write that this script is shared under the,
MIT license or GPL, and we will see what they mean
in a moment, so it can be, that can be enough.
But basically anything to reproduce the results,
data, software, we need to think about license.
Because I made a little script that
maybe it takes me 20 minutes to write.
Maybe it will save somebody else days.
somebody else will be really grateful if they don't have to write it and can reuse it.
Yeah, or even if it takes 20 minutes that's still time saved.
So especially it is important if this is actually something you've used to
produce a figure or a result in your paper to actually publish it in such a way that it can
actually someone else can use it to reproduce the results in your paper and then go from there to
add on to it. Yeah, it is important to publish that. And it is software, so it needs a software
license and all of that.
So I'm watching as questions will go on, and I might trace them, but maybe, yeah, maybe
you can move on and follow up.
Yes, let's go on to. Yeah, so, well, comparing, sharing papers and sharing code is exactly
what we were just talking about.
Something we didn't really go into is academic credit, which all researchers roughly know
how it works.
You use an idea from another paper, you're not directly using any text from the paper,
you just read the paper and then you are continuing to work.
you cite the paper in your own publications. And that is kind of the currency of academia in a way
that shows that people are actually interested in your work and
you are building or you are adding something important to a field of science.
So yeah, the thing you want to do as a scientist is put papers out there, have people cite them
and you never want to put any restrictions on them or anything like that
yeah good point and often there are restrictions but they come from maybe from the journalists but
not from the researchers you want maximum visibility for your papers
yeah of course I mean yeah if you publish in a journal then it might not be openly available
hopefully there is an openly available version somewhere
Okay, so software or code can or works a bit differently, so you can kind of mix and match
and well, I mean, you can mix and match research trials in a way you create some understanding
of a topic and then you cite them.
But here you can actually take blocks off or copies of lines of code from something
or you can use a library that someone else has written. So you can mix and match in a more
complicated way and build on top of other people's work. So one quick question is,
should you cite software that you use? When should you cite it? Should you cite
the Linux operating system? How far do you go? I guess we will come back to that.
that question at some point. But yeah, with software the situation gets more complicated.
So there's the dependencies on which you build your software and then there is
the algorithms, the scientific methodology that is kind of implied by the software.
So there's a lot more considerations there.
Okay, so I mean a lot of journals require you to share that share your code much should
we go in there we spend a good amount of time looking at the questions but this didn't actually
come up
We can just summarize that yeah today we and in future we might not have the choice whether
we like want to share it or don't want to share it and it's a good thing I think there
is a yeah so it seems that in future we will be required to personally I find it a good
development but it also means for us now that we we have to start thinking about it so whatever
I use now I have to be ready so that if I then share it in five years when the project
is done and we are publishing then I need to be able to share it yeah yeah so when from
From the start, you need to think about this licensing and these sorts of things so that
you can actually share the code when the time comes.
Yeah.
Okay.
We got a couple of great questions, so maybe we have time, I just want to raise them.
So what was the biggest thing that raised your awareness of this, like the biggest event
and led you to adopt better practices?
Was it seeing other people using these practices?
Is it that conferences I think in my original field where I was most of my work most of
my time as a researcher where I was developing the code there wasn't really a tradition of
sharing or publishing openly, anything. It took quite a while. I think I was actually
a research software engineer by the time I properly started sharing my own research codes.
I think the main thing was actually seeing it done in other fields, but also I was often
frustrated when two groups came up with different results for what is essentially the same question
and there was no clear way of checking, even checking that their code produces that result
because you didn't have access to their code.
So yeah, that was quite frustrating and of course then you see people just publishing
their code that is the obvious solution to the problem of course it's still good to have both
codes that produce those different results so that you can actually figure out what's going on but
yeah not publishing it is the original problem there is one more question that but it's more
general i wonder do we have time now for one more question or should i postpone it it's not
it can also wait well i think we should have time the questions that are now on the screen
are actually something we already talked about.
Yeah, one thing that I wanted to discuss a little bit
is this, whether we can give examples
of repositories we've worked on.
And I'm paraphrasing here.
So the person says that,
I'm working on one project over many years.
And is the project too big
or am I just really inefficient?
And I just wanted to say, no, I mean, probably not.
It's normal.
I would say that's the normal thing
that I think many researchers will work years,
maybe even decades on one coding project.
And there's nothing wrong with it.
Because then you really know it well.
You know all the ins and outs, you know what it can do.
You can implement new ideas in it quickly
because you know it so well.
We as research software engineers
would typically help researchers.
So we often jump from project to project
because at least in my case,
I'm now often, I'm not driving the project.
is somebody else and I help out. So then I do more jumping from project to project. But
I just wanted to say that there's nothing wrong with it. I think that's the normal
situation. I think it's a good sign if you end up spending a lot of time on a single
coding project. I have some that were kind of one and done, wrote down an algorithm and
and publish the paper on it.
And then I have a few where the project evolved
for years and years and years
and someone else is now working on it.
And those second ones are of course the ones
where other people are actually interested in the results.
The first ones are the ones
where the paper didn't really get cited
and I moved on to something else.
That is why I didn't continue developing them.
Yeah, great.
Okay, let's move on to licenses.
Should we talk about licenses the next episode?
Yes, we did we talk about reusability yet?
Well, that is actually something we will talk about
in the next section as well.
What from here do we need to bring up before we go on?
The thing that I would bring up here
is also contribution guide.
It can be nice to see in a project how to contribute.
Yeah.
How to get started?
What is the decision process?
Especially in a bigger project,
it can be a bit daunting to just see a huge bunch of files
where you have no idea how everything interacts
with everything else.
It is important to have a good style guide
and contribution guide so that you know how to get started.
And yeah, mostly everything else we have already talked about.
So let's move on
and talk about licenses. Okay so this is obviously a very important topic when it comes to publishing
your code without a license no one can really do much with your code you're just kind of putting it
out there for people to read but with the license you state what people can actually do
with with the code that you publish so we'll need to talk about derivative work
what actually is derivative work so when you take someone else's project or actually well
I'll just finish the sentence so when you take somebody else's project and make some changes to
it when does it count as derivative work and when not when can you just share it and when do you need
to follow the license and I guess the answer to that the way I just said it is kind of obvious
because if you're actually working on someone else's code that is the route to work but it
can be even more than that. And then we'll talk about available licenses and what do they mean
and give some practical advice. So what you should take away from here is basically
when do you need to think about licenses and where to go and check what my license means what.
And we will try to keep it really practical so we will not go through all the different licenses and
discuss the pros and cons but we want to give you practical advice of where to start,
where to look for, how to compare and what to do in your repository to be ready for this.
So there's a few things around this general concept of copyright.
We'll mainly talk about copyright specifically, but there's trademarks.
So the trademark is a name for something.
It could be, of course, the name of your software,
but in general, it's just a name that is public,
the sort of public face of a product or a thing.
A patent is a technical invention, that's novel and non-obvious, but the basic idea
is that it is a technical invention rather than a product or a thing you can just kind
of look at or it's not an object, it's not a file.
And then copyright applies to almost everything else.
So it applies to creative expressions, something you spend time on creating.
So it could be software, writing, graphics, photos, books, movies, and yeah, copyright.
you have right to the things that you create for basically forever from your point of view.
So lifetime of the author plus 70 years. I don't know what jurisdiction that is but it's
roughly correct in almost any jurisdiction. Yeah, of course, try to reproduce it and 70
years later. So let's see what is the running but the yeah. So the important takeaway is
we we create creative work so we are creative people when we write code and scripts it falls
under copyright and then [name] you mentioned that you have copyright so the question is who is you
it could be the person it could be your employer so that sometimes it depends
it depends on the country depends on the employer yeah depends on your contract
so this is also something to think about and practically speaking that can be complicated
even if like people try to make it sometimes as clear as possible so maybe it's that the
company always owns everything or maybe it's the idea is that you or the person who writes it the
employer owns like if you're working in a university you might own the copyright to
everything but it can still get complicated so it is just easier to make sure you handle the
copyright situation immediately so that it doesn't get into so that you don't get into
a complicated situation which means deciding on a license and publishing under a license
and a great question on on the notes is that now that we have generative AI and we have AI
artificial intelligence assisted coding. Yeah. It opens a whole new set of questions
about licenses, about copyright, about ethics of it.
And we, I guess we may have a section on it, but most of these services, all of these services
as far as I know right now, they do give the user the copyright, they give it away or you
buy it from them. But even if they do that, you only have copyright if it's not derivative
work or if it's not a direct copy of something that already exists, which is something you
just have to check yourself. You cannot trust that the system will take care of that for
you.
Yeah, but it's also hard to check. It's hard to know where this code comes from. And a
completely different question,
which is really hard to answer is,
the original creators, do they get credit?
Are they credited?
Are they, did they agree to it?
And was their license respected?
So that's a completely different set of questions.
Yeah.
Yeah, there, if you are thinking
that there might be an original author,
then the simplest case would be that,
oh, the best way out of it would be
to just assume that they have copyright and respect it
because then you will not get in trouble.
Yeah.
So [name], what is derivative work
and why is it so important for us
when we write and change software?
Yeah.
So derivative works, the name says,
basically means you have taken something
and made changes to it.
It may be even completely re-implemented it,
but it is somehow derived from someone else's
copyrighted work.
So it's derived from something
where someone else has copyright.
And it could be sampling.
We have some nice images of historical images
of actual resampling going on.
Yes.
It works on many levels there.
I think we have a clip for people.
I will copy it to the notes.
You can, you can,
Yeah.
You can vote on it.
So there's some examples
and the question is if they are derivative work or not.
So I don't know if I should,
well, I'll give the quick guide to how to answer it.
But when you are,
yeah, like I said, when you're taking something
and changing it, that's kind of clearly derivative work,
but often it's also derivative work
if you are taking an idea from something,
but not like you're using someone else's code,
for example, to write it in a different language
just rewrite it, that might still be derivative work. As long as it's derived from a copyrighted
work, it is derivative work. It depends on the field. If you are taking ideas from a painting
and creating your own painting, usually we don't consider that derivative work.
If you are translating a Python library into R, even if you are completely rewriting it,
it's still considered derivative working well usually so I hope I didn't give out the answer
to a direct question maybe I did but that's kind of the general guideline so it can be quite expensive
and so we have to we have to think about it both when we if I find some code on the internet
then I change it I have to think about derivative work let's go and we have to think the other way
to think about derivative work is do you want to make it easy or difficult for other people to
change things and that you can also then steer a little bit with the choice of license
yeah so yeah the license can give you can give it people the right to create derivative work
as much as they want or it can restrict it a lot okay um should we start going through this
i guess so yeah so a couple of them are maybe not so surprising the thing that was surprising
to me many years ago is that when even changing the whole language nothing is left from the old
code not not a single character everything has completely changed i i was surprised that
that is that is derivative work yeah so nobody has voted for linking to libraries
But, in fact, if a library is published under the traditional, standard GNU public license,
for example, and you statically link to it, that can still be considered, that is still
considered derivative work.
So for some licenses, it depends how we link to it.
I think maybe that's a little bit technical, we will not go into too much details.
So for plugins and libraries, typically it's not derivative work, but it can be depending
how it is included, linked into your project.
And maybe it's a bit arcane because this is mainly talking about compiled languages and
like old engine stuff like C and C++, but I mean, people are actually still of course
using them.
And the reason I bring it up is because I was using this when I found out about this
and I was kind of surprised and had to change some things.
But answers, so questions H and I, they, so when we, when you, so H means clean room design,
it means that you don't see, you never see the code, but somebody explains you what the
code does, how it works, you can think of explains you the algorithm, and then you write
the code.
So that is typically not derivative work.
Also, if you read the paper, read the algorithm and write the code based on the algorithm,
typically not derivative work so an algorithm is typically not something that can be copyrighted
yeah yeah so if you're implementing an algorithm that's not derivative work
if somebody describes you what the code does um on a more detailed level and you just write down
what they're telling you telling to go to do then that actually probably is derivative work
so yeah i mean clean room design means you know the algorithm but you don't know the actual code
Okay. So containers. Okay. So yeah, recipes are like source code. Containers are like
a program. But we didn't actually talk about specifically the licenses yet. Okay. Let's
go there. Because this is an important topic. It's about choosing which license to use
use and also what it means when a code has been published under a specific license.
So there's, well, there's proprietary licenses, which generally mean you have sold a piece
of software and you have rather restrictive, you sell a rather restrictive license that
they can, only this person can use it for this purpose.
Yeah, that's because you're actually selling it and getting money from it.
But mainly talk about open source licenses.
So they range from strong copyleft, which means derivative work has to be published
also under a strong copyleft license.
You can think of it as the license kind of infects everything it touches.
So everything that uses a strongly copyleft piece of code also will be strongly copyleft
or at least copyleft.
So I guess that the main difference here
between strong copyleft and copyleft is that
copyleft is the less strong version is usually designed
so that you can actually link against it or use it,
use the products, use the library
without having to publish your code as copyleft.
Whereas strong copyleft is kind of,
it just tries to make everything copyleft
as much as possible.
And I think it's useful to not think in too much in terms of using because the using could
be linking plugin.
Maybe let's think in terms of remixing.
You take a couple of codes from different places and you remix them with your own work
and this is your code.
So remixing and then what is interesting are the little arrows.
So in the in the image that Tiano is sharing there are these fields and the arrows between
they actually show the compatibility.
What license can you combine with another license?
The one on top, so the so-called strong copy left,
the arrow goes only one way.
Then if we go a little bit lower towards the dark green,
we have the permissive licenses,
and they are called permissive
because they can be combined with almost anything,
even with proprietary licenses.
but you can see that the arrow there goes only one way.
So you can take a code that has been licensed MIT
and if you want, you can make it proprietary.
You can sell it, you can close it.
So all of this is possible.
Right.
Yeah, and yeah.
So a copy left software cannot be used in a,
software cannot be used in in a well yeah there's there's often a separate proprietary
license for a copyleft library but that license cannot be directly used in a proprietary thing
oh it cannot be it cannot be distributed together with a proprietary thing and um
which means that now now let's think in two different perspectives one is that
that I just want to use the code. That's one perspective. But the other perspective is
we develop the code. And now you can decide what do you want with your code to happen?
Do you want it to be used in as many places as possible, proprietary, not proprietary,
then you would prefer probably a permissive license. If you want to make it as easy as
possible for everybody else. On the other hand, if you want to make sure that your code
is not distributed with another proprietary code,
then you probably want to move up on that green pyramid
and choose a more so-called copyleft license.
Right, yes, this is mainly about distributing, not running.
If you're just running on your own machine
or even making changes on your own machine,
that's usually not something we think about.
So the license doesn't really restrict you from just running or even changing it on
like locally and never showing it to anyone. Although it's kind of hard to
never show something to anyone, but in principle that's allowed.
So it is mainly about distributing. Somebody's asking, what is the
difference between MIT and Creative Commons? Because here they are on the same image.
Yes. MIT and BSD are traditionally software licenses and Apache. The differences between
them are small. Creative Commons is traditionally more for data and for both artistic things
like books, like lecture materials, and not so much for software that's intended to run
and produce a result, for example. So there are differences in the way it's written. And
I would basically just use software licenses for software and creative commons for other
things. What if you have both earlier in the session,
we had on we had a repository example repository, there was data and there were scripts and
read me's and maybe a manuscript. So what can you do if you have data and code in the
same place. And I can answer it myself. You can, you can put, you can then put both licenses.
You can say that, well, all the data, all the slides are licensed creative commons attribution
and all the code is licensed MIT. And that's what we do in, in our code refinery lessons.
So that's how we license our material. Yeah. So yeah, nothing forces you to just use one
license for an entire repository, you can have different licenses per folder or per file.
The only thing to take into account there is that you have to then, well you have to look at those
arrows there, you are distributing them at the same time if they are in the same repository.
So there might be some compatibility issues. Also even there you can have the data be
creative commons and have a gpl strong copy left license for the software that will not be a
problem the software is not so directly linked with the data that that would be a problem
but still you you in that case you do need to take those arrows into account
okay um well well something we didn't really mention is this lowest level here which is
It's so permissive that there's not really even a license there.
It's just published as public domain and anyone can do anything they want with it.
Often these lower levels here might require at least attribution.
You need to tell where you got the code or the data.
So yeah, there's a great resource here for this join up licensing assistant is very useful
when you're trying to actually figure out what license to use.
Should we, it's 10 to two, I should say.
I think what I would like to do before, we will take a break soon.
I would say maybe in five minutes, what we could try to do in before the break into five
minutes is that we, there were some good questions that I want to bring up later when we discuss
But one question that we could talk about now is what should we do practically?
So we have this overview, let's say we choose a specific license, but what should I do then
practically with my repository?
And so one thing that we advise you to do, and I think this is so in the material people
you can find it a little bit below that scheme,
is add a license file to your,
it can be either a file called license,
or it can be, if you need multiple licenses,
you can create a directory called licenses,
and add the license text into the repository.
The other practical advice is to do it
early in the project.
because when there is nothing there, when the project is small, it's only one person,
it's easy to change it. When the project already exists for 15 years and there are 20 people there
from five different institutions, then it's more difficult to change the license.
Unfortunately, a common problematic situation which we did run into with those
long existing codes in the field of science where stuff wasn't really published when I was there.
Several of those software were published later and somebody did actually figure out where I was working at
and write an email to my work address and ask if they can publish the changes I made to the code under a specific license.
So, you have to do that with every author that has made changes to your projects.
And when it's just you or just your team, it's really easy.
So yeah, do it then.
And when somebody has left and gone through five different postdoc positions and is now
working as a research software engineer in, well, you have no idea where, it's really
hard.
Yeah.
Because then you need to possibly reach out to all of them and get their agreement.
So, do it early.
For most projects, a license file is enough.
On top of your code, you can add that this code is licensed under this and that.
It's not strictly necessary.
So you don't have to add the copyright header for it to have the copyright.
And then another thing that we recommend is to have this discussion with your group.
So if maybe have a discussion with your supervisor, or if you are the supervisor, have a discussion
with your students at the beginning of a project.
Discuss, it's a little bit like a data,
what is it called?
Data management plan.
Like, what is your plan?
What is our plan to do now,
three years later when the code is done?
How do we want to share it?
What is the license strategy?
This is, discuss it with your colleagues,
with your project.
Discuss the ownership.
Yes.
And the copyright matters, ownership matters, because only those who have the copyright
can change the license, and it may be your employer.
Yeah, and it is also, so a lot of these bigger projects, for example, will have this contribution
guide or contribution agreement that essentially states that you are giving away copyright
or you're publishing it under this license.
So if it's an MIT license, for example,
then it's enough that you publish under that license.
But they might actually ask you to give away your copyright
to that change that you're making to a big project
because then they don't have to chase you up
if they want to change the license.
So that's also something good to talk about
already in the beginning with your team.
If somebody leaves the team,
then do they give away the copyright?
do you does your team have permission to do whatever with the code which I mean usually
it should it is good to have so how about we take a 10 minute break then we can think about
more questions hopefully we will see more questions and then in the last half an hour
we will talk about software citations data and hopefully we get lots of questions that
that we can hear discuss.
Does this sound like a good idea?
If yes, then let's be back five minutes after the hour.
So a 10 minute break.
Okay.
Yes, let's take a break, walk around.
See you.
Bye.
you
Hello. We are back. Hopefully you can hear us. And I hope you had a good break. Stretch
your legs a little bit will be another talky section but we'll have some well we'll have
a lot of interaction with the notes like in the previous section hopefully.
So you wanted to bring up a question which I'm conveniently already have visible here.
Yes.
Yeah.
So I wanted to say thanks to all the really good questions.
Please keep them coming also for the remaining 20 minutes.
This is the best way of creating the session.
And one thing that we thought would be good to discuss
is the question that,
so the one,
so what happens if somebody actually uses a code
without permission?
Is that the one?
Yes.
Yeah.
How can you show that they used it?
And what can you do?
I mean, there's the legal side of this, and then there's how things work in academia.
Because universities or researchers don't want to be fighting each other in court, especially
when they are in different countries and different jurisdictions anyway.
But I mean, legally speaking, it is actually breaking the law.
doing something illegal and there are systems to handle this. It might be too minor to really
get a lot of attention and like I said, you probably don't want to go to court with it.
But that is at least for big companies or universities that might be something
that they think about. And more practically speaking though, if somebody publishes a
paper using your code and doesn't credit you or does it breaks the license when they do it,
does it against the license text, that is academic misconduct. That's like if they publish the paper
then the journal would probably take it into account and maybe retract the paper.
It's also true that academia works a lot through reputation.
So, um, basically just talking about it is, um, is part of the solution to the problem.
Yeah.
And it can be another motivation also to, to open up our own code and put it on Git,
because at least if somebody steals my code, at least I can show it because I can show
the git history and i can show that well that's weird the code that they published looks exactly
like the one that i put on github 2014 how come so at least you have a you have a basis
for an argument so this can maybe help us to motivate to share our own codes
Another thing we didn't mention about licenses at the end of the previous section.
So at the end of the licenses section there is a part about choosing a license in case what you're publishing is not derivative work, you're starting from scratch and you actually have to choose a license.
There's a lot of practical tips here, it's a useful read when you're actually choosing
a license, it's good to come back to this.
But one important thing is it's just practically not a good idea to invent your own license.
So these standards exist for a reason, they've been written by lawyers and you don't really
want to try to do the work of the lawyers.
plenty of standard license texts available and importantly this this is
tools around that people use that recognize standard licenses so if your
license is not standard people will not know what to do with it the lawyers will
probably say just don't use it I don't know what to do and if you if you can
Let's scroll up a little bit to that image again.
It's, what's the scenario here?
It's really about the compatibility.
So these are the arrows between licenses.
And if you invent your own,
it will not be clear what it is compatible with.
So that's really the problem.
So don't invent your own license
or take one of the standard ones.
And [name], which, what is your most favorite license?
Which one do you typically take for your projects when you have to choose?
When I'm starting and there's no reason to choose any specific license, then I would
probably go with MIT.
And why?
Just by default.
It's the most permissive license that allows people to do anything they want with it, but
still requires that they acknowledge you. I don't want it to be completely in public domain because
I still want people to acknowledge that I've done some of the work, maybe slightly selfishly, but
it's not very selfish though to put it under MIT. I want it to be as widely used as possible,
but i also want to be recognized um yeah what's your favorite
it's either so mit for the things that i just want to share and i don't really mind so much
what happens to that code yeah sometimes i i want to make sure that when people make changes
changes to the code that they are obliged to share the changes.
And then I go for the share alike, the reciprocal.
So here it's on this image is called reciprocal licenses.
For instance, the MPL, the Mozilla public license or the EUPL, the European public license.
So often I go for those if I want to make sure that whatever people come up with all
improvements i can remix them into my own projects also so it goes both ways so when i want to insist
on the both ways i go for the reciprocal licenses but they are a little bit more restrictive
if i don't care yeah or if it's such a like a little project and
probably nobody will do anything with it anyway than mit
Yeah. At some point, I think I've maybe done it once. I could move from MIT to a reciprocal
license, but I would generally start with MIT just by default. When there's no other
file in the project, except the license file, then it's MIT.
That's how early I think it's good to start thinking about licenses.
Shall we talk more about the credit part and the technology of it?
So how to cite, how does it work, software citation and software publication?
And this is also about academic citation.
So the MIT license requires acknowledgment,
but that's not quite the same thing as a citation
as researchers think about it.
So this enables also citing software
as an academic publication.
Well, that's one thing we'll talk about.
So a couple of questions there that we'll try to answer.
If you put your code on GitHub, GitLab and so on,
is that publishing?
We already talked about licenses.
So assume you also put a license there.
Is that publishing?
Where do you publish software?
How can it be cited?
How do you make it cited?
How do you make the software citable?
Yeah, so let's get into it.
So just putting your software on GitHub and GitLab,
that is a good part of publishing.
We've mentioned these FAIR principles, I think last week at least.
It's a collection of four words to think about when it comes to publishing and doing
reproducible science in general, so not just software.
It comes from findable, accessible, reusable and interoperable.
So, if you put something on GitHub or GitLab, it's accessible.
If people can find it, it's accessible.
It's also pretty findable.
GitHub is good at indexing things and GitLab, if GitLab here means the official GitLab.org
interface, then it's pretty good at indexing things so that search engines can find it.
doesn't make it reusable necessarily depends on the license and how on the
coding practices and it does not make it interoperable interoperable would mean
that it runs on different system and it plugs into or it can be used in in
different different kinds of situations with different types of data and so on
and there can be also problem with which of the findable there is a very simple
simple trick on how I can make my code not findable anymore. And that is by what if I
delete the repository? What if I delete my account? So it's a good first step, but it's
it's not enough to make it really findable for the next, I don't know, five years, 10
years. Yeah. I don't know what the horizon is that we want to make things findable. So
we want to go a step further. And one way is to really make it citable and persistent.
Yeah. Okay, so we'll talk about making it, well, first citable and then persistent.
Okay, Katz is here. Hello. So, of course, we also already talked about reproducible and
how to make it work after five years. That is also a big deal. But yeah, so let's talk about
that a little bit. So what do you actually need to cite something? And I guess one
pretty important, very important question is what software do you actually cite? So
if you use, I mentioned the Linux operating system, I guess that's an obvious thing.
If you use the Linux operating system, you probably don't cite it. But if you use a
a specifically scientific software library that someone else published with their paper,
then you probably do need to cite it. But there is some balance there. Different fields have
different conventions about what you cite, even when it comes to papers. We never cite
Einstein, for example, in physics these days. No, I mean,
that was about those I said in the wrong way around, I was
about to say we don't cite Newton and not even Einstein,
but I kind of said it the wrong way around. But anyway, so if
something is really fundamental enough, and it has its, it has
intrinsic value already, then it's known enough, you don't
need to cite it. But that, yeah, that depends a lot on the
field and the same applies to software but earlier today we talked about dependencies
so in the other session and so are dependencies fundamental like if i if i want to cite a code
but the code is using five other dependencies and each of them uses five other dependencies
do i need to cite all of those yeah that is a good question and i think my answer would be that
But we don't have to.
So you don't have to cite all the different dependencies.
You cite the libraries that you use, that your code is using.
And then you are hoping that the libraries in turn, when they publish their papers, they
are citing all the other libraries they are using.
So for a lot of things, just having it as a dependency might be enough.
Like if it's a really commonly used library, you might not cite it in a paper.
I would actually, I would maybe follow a citation trail kind of.
So if you are citing a piece of software and that piece of software is citing another piece
of software, then you should consider whether to cite it or not.
But if that other piece of software just has it as a dependency, it's not citing it, then
it's also probably the case that you don't cite it, although it depends on the situation,
depends on how much.
So citations are about the giving credit for the science.
So it and dependency is about being able to run the software.
So you use them for those, for different things.
And one thing that will help so much when citing is in your code, write down how you
want to be cited.
Already this relatively simple thing.
If I can find it easily, how do I will cite you?
I will cite you that way make it easy for me to find out how you want to be cited.
So for that I mean there are things you need to know how to for citing a piece of software
or a piece of paper or a paper or anything and I mean here's a complete list or maybe
an almost complete list but you can make life easier for other people by creating these
citation.cff file and it is a structured way of writing it down in a machine readable way
and it contains all of the information that's needed to cite your software.
So this is a message that's displayed or it says essentially just this is how you cite my software
but yeah this title, version, maybe a digital object identifier or it is actually very good
to have one, we'll come back to that, and then the names of the authors and maybe identifiers for
them. So that's the same information you would look for in a paper to cite it and you just
provide it here in a format that makes it easy to find. Now github for example will read this file
and process it to different standard citation formats so that you can put them into whatever
software you use to write your paper and cite other software. Okay so that's a good thing to
add it's a really these days it became a standard and many services understand this file so if this
file is in your repository, then many services will use it. So have such a file, get a digital
object identifier on services like Zenodo, where you can make your code really persistent. So then
even if I delete my GitHub repository, people can still find the code thanks to the DOI.
Zenodo is nice in that it integrates with GitHub so that whenever you create a new release
on GitHub, if you have enabled Zenodo, then it will create a new release also on Zenodo,
make a new copy so that you don't really have to do much to keep it up to date.
Here's some examples of how to cite software following standard formats.
There's also some journals that allow you to publish software papers. That's another way
of making your software citable. There's a good list of those here.
I think that's all you need to know how to make it citable.
Is this another section?
Yes.
No.
So the last section is about sharing data.
Yes.
So we have a few minutes, so you should probably go there.
But yeah, for getting the DOI, that is a separate section.
Okay, is there anything in the notes about citations?
Yeah, there is this question about citations in the CFF file.
And I think it's a good question because it's very general.
It's about which particular version should people cite when they use the code.
Because one thing you can do on services like Zenodo is that for each version of your code
you can get a different DOI.
Yeah.
And then you can, you can recommend people to, to cite.
So I would probably, my recommendation would be
that people should cite the version
that they've actually used.
But then you are maybe interested in knowing
what is the combined number of citations
that my software has.
Yeah.
And that you can also get this information.
So you would be more interested
in the sum of all of the versions.
but it might be also interesting
to see the evolution of versions.
So Zenodo actually creates this sort of sub-DOIs.
So a DOI that essentially ends with the version number
or a numeric identifier for the version.
And that allows you to,
so you can cite the specific version using that identifier
and it will still count the citation,
all the citations to your software together
when you want to.
So, yeah, I mean, digital object identifiers
actually support versioning directly.
So that's something you can do.
The service will also create one
which will always resolve to the latest version
if you find it practical.
So maybe that's the one that you can have in your readme.
Yeah.
Okay, so.
About sharing data is at the bottom, by the way, if anyone needs to really.
Yeah.
Oh, yeah.
Please do fill in the feedback.
We have five minutes so we can quickly look at sharing data, which is not that different.
But there's a few more considerations you need to take into account.
But also data.
You don't need a software license for data, essentially.
essentially. So it's also a bit simpler in some ways. I think the main thing though with data is
that it tends to be bigger than software. It tends to take more space. So there's some registries
that specialize in publishing data and they can go up to, I mean they have a limit of how much
data you can actually publish there but Zenodo goes up to 50 gigabytes per researcher and
there's a bunch of other options that may have more or may have less. Zenodo is run by CERN
so it's something you can kind of expect to stick around for a really long time
but all of these are good options.
Then there's local options in almost every country
that you can usually use to publish larger datasets.
So giving everyone internationally access to save a lot of huge datasets is hard,
but you can usually have a local service that allows,
allows, for example, all the Finnish researchers can publish
in these places and can publish a much bigger data set
than is possible on Zenodo.
But this is something essentially
that when you get to that problem,
you need to read up on a bit.
So, one practical thing can be that what you really want to do, at some point you want
to have a paper that is citable, that is a DOI, at some point you want to have a software
that has a DOI, and maybe you have also data.
And sometimes they go to three different places, so the paper goes to the journal, the software
goes to, I don't know, Zenodo, and the data goes to one of these services.
And it can be really useful if each of these three sides the other two, so that you Yeah,
somebody who finds the data can find a paper and can find a software and vice versa.
Data is a little bit different than software in terms of sort of licenses are similar but
different in data, we are less concerned about changing, we are more concerned about reusing
in the software, we are very concerned about changing because we want to change software,
we want to create derivative work.
Data, it's more about how is it used?
How is it combined?
With data, it's much more depends on your community.
So different academic communities
have different preferred platforms.
It depends on the country.
But the principles are the same.
You want it to be findable
and you want to connect the software, the data,
and the paper because they belong together.
they all tell a story.
Yeah, so probably the biggest difference
is that data tends to be,
it data doesn't tend to change.
Once you publish a data set, it usually stays the same
or you get a few updates, but not very often.
And software changes a lot.
Okay, just one more quick thing about AI.
There's, you, well, you can take the existence of AI
into account in different ways with data and with software.
But yeah, so essentially, most licenses allow, for example,
well, they allow data mining.
And so they kind of also allow your data
your software to be used for training AIs. But this is an evolving field. The laws are
not setting stone in any way when it comes to training AIs. So the current state of affairs
is we have a bunch of links here but if something is public it's likely okay to train AI on it.
But yeah, I mean, it's not necessarily very useful to go into much detail because the
situation is changing so quickly.
And can we maybe show now that we are out of time on a collaborative document, just
a feedback form.
It would be really nice to hear one thing that was good that we should keep and one
thing that we should change, improve for next time.
Of course, any other feedback welcome.
So this is what we would like to hear.
Also can we prepare news for the day?
So we are essentially done with the material, we would appreciate feedback, but if you need
to leave now is the time when we've covered everything.
So let's see.
we covered the things mentioned in the schedule. It was more, how do we say,
more discussion, demonstration. It's a different style. You see from the
feedback that we see that some things are too advanced. We still believe
that it will be really useful. Tomorrow we will look more on documentation. How
How can we document code differently approaches?
Yeah.
If anyone is watching just a conclusion
or reading this later,
there's many good questions during the day,
which are in the notes document,
which will be archived on the website.
So tomorrow will be,
well, tomorrow and Thursday for that matter
will be like today.
So it will be lots of demos and discussions and time for questions and answers.
So you don't need to prepare, but if you want to, you can try to follow along.
There will be things that you can possibly do, but we'll be running it as demo.
What did he think of this format? So, less exercises and more showing things. I think
it worked really well because instead of lots of questions about small technical problems
and things breaking, we had a lot more high-level questions about why things are used. And thus,
That allows us to focus on, well, the interesting part.
And then you can review the other things later.
But it can also feel, I can imagine that for some it can feel many things went too fast.
But then let's remember that we don't need to remember how we did it.
We can look it up.
And the how is not even the main point.
more the why and what is possible again what is possible why do we do things we know that
it exists we try to now show many different aspects and focus more on the why so like the
main takeaway probably yeah the main takeaway from the social coding section would for example
be that you recognize when you need a license for your software and you remember that the
material has a lot about it that you can check out when you actually are deciding what license to put
to use. So it's not something you do as an exercise right now because it's actually pretty trivial to
just click add license file and choose which license to add. It is much more important to know
what the differences are and remember that that information is on the course website that you can
check and the same kind of also goes for the for the first section so it's more important to know
that the tools are there and to recognize when you need them than it is to actually have used them
in an example yeah and i mean yeah yeah like it's there's lots of things saying today was too
advanced. I mean, yes, we know what we're doing is sort of advanced stuff using SnakeMake,
Conda Environments, or Containers. Any one of these things could become its own whole workshop.
So, don't feel that you're left behind or left out. Feel that you know what you...
feel that feel inspired to learn something in the future so it is so it
is true that doing an exercise forces you to be more concentrated and allows
you to learn something more deeply so if there's a topic that you think you need
to learn better, you can always repeat the demonstrations
or do some of the exercises in the notes.
And well, at least I don't think
it's any problem to ask questions
about those in the notes.
We might not be as actively there outside the workshop
time, but it could still work.
So tomorrow we cover, is it Jupyter and documentation?
or documentation in Jupyter.
Yes.
So documentation is about how we can use Git repositories to make
basically websites which are useful for documentation.
Basically, it shows how we make these lessons themselves.
We use these same practices.
Jupyter shows many Jupyter tips and
tricks for reproducibility that you might not know.
Then day three is really cool.
really wraps everything up. There's automated testing, which sort of puts everything together.
And then modular code development, which is an exciting demo of starting with some small code
and making it better and better incrementally, hearing the analysis of all of these steps.
So, anything else? Any other comments to address here?
Just a big thanks to everybody involved, and we'll be looking forward to tomorrow.
More time for discussion in a collaborative document. That would be... I guess we can
try to do that.
Yeah, OK.
Well, thanks a lot.
See you next time, I guess.
See you then.
OK, bye.
Bye.
you