CodeRefinery.org
you
Test 1, 2. Can anyone hear us?
Test, test. Hello. Good morning.
Good morning, everyone.
So, yeah, like usual, we have 10 minutes before the main thing starts, but let's do the initial icebreaker stuff.
First off is our audio good.
At least for me, the levels seem good.
Should we do the standard sound check?
So, the order on my screen, me, [name], [name], [name].
One.
Two.
Three.
Okay, let us know if our audio is or isn't balanced and who needs to adjust.
So, as usual, we have some icebreakers here, some interesting questions to think about.
And today we've got, how would you explain your current job to someone from the year
1700, which is something I saw on some sort of social media in the last few days.
So I guess if many of us do computer things, this will be hard, but let's see how well
we can abstract ourselves back down.
is what's the best documented project you've seen? And do you prefer reading short social
media posts or long blog posts? So, of the people here, how would you explain what you
do to someone from...
I mean, I like the first one, actually.
Yeah. I mean, that's what I wrote, so...
Oh, okay.
Yeah.
Some would guess that that was one of us in some way.
I mean, it's at least clear it's a research software engineer or, yeah, a support person.
I mean, I guess that is sort of general.
Like, there's complicated machines or other tools.
People need to use them, but aren't the specialist in there.
And people exist to help with that.
I think one of the problems that I see was explaining it to someone from the 1700s.
I see my work at least very much as helping people to allow them to keep their specialization
and not, well, having to worry about anything else or having to worry about nitty-gritty
things.
While in the 1700s I think there was not that much really specialization in science at least.
I mean not necessarily in science, but in 1700s we are already in the industrial revolution, right?
Yeah, I mean very, very, very beginning.
Yeah, I mean the first industrial revolution is sort of going on or done, the second hasn't started.
So you have people whose job it is to operate a big machine like a windmill or a certain part of a boat, I think.
Yeah.
At least mills.
It's like applied research and science and so on.
Or, you know, something like that.
What do you think the, well, the second job, reading letters and writing letters,
is that a scientist making journal articles? Maybe? Maybe.
That's what a scholar does. Yeah. Organizing assemblies of
people to discuss that conference organizer or something.
email and chat. So, okay, so it could be any job, but you're so busy writing emails that
you can't do your main job, which is a lot of manager, I guess. I guess that's also partly
me. Mathematically rephrasing what people have already invented in 1700. What is that
job. Could it be some sort of programmer or other researcher that's using math that's
already been known then but doing it faster in computers now?
A lot of math, actual math research is rephrasing, I can't speak right now, rephrasing stuff
that people have already invented, but making it easier to use and clearer.
And, well, even making it usable, because there was just not the computational power
before now. There's quite a lot of stuff that, well, in theory would work, it just
took too long, and now computers are fast enough to, yep, now you can actually do this.
So if you're just joining now, we have an interesting icebreaker there.
If you registered, you should have the notes link, and well, you can read the questions
as well as I can read them, so let's play this game.
But so today, well, [name] will have some interlater.
How do you think the workshop's going overall, everyone here?
Have you all been happy?
I think it has been going well, like the week one redesign was very successful, like looking
at the questions that we got, more into towards how researchers actually encounter version
control and GitHub on their journey.
And week two, I'm still a bit unsure about the no exercise sessions
because they have always been very nice.
And I've gotten people into looking at these things themselves
and trying to figure them out versus us showing it on stream.
It probably depends a lot on how people learn best.
Yeah.
What is more beneficial?
Very true.
What do you think?
This is definitely helping us cover more ground and not feel as busy and not feel like we're
always running out of time.
I do hope that this also moves more to the direction where we can then support people
after the workshop and make this more of a mentor thing.
I suppose that means people joining our Zulip chat and asking questions there when they have questions.
Because, of course, during the workshop, we have the collaborative document, the notes, which we will not be actively checking after the workshop.
Yeah.
I mean, yeah, my ideal would be for the second week, imagine if we could do the workshop like
we've been doing now, but then in the afternoons we could arrange some sort of like, well, like
the bring your own code sessions, which we actually have for Code Refinery, but we should be doing as
part of our own individual or institutions also. We could tell people, okay, next week come to
our garage with any of the questions from Code Refinery about how to do it and we'll help you
set it up and or you know help you do the exercises test it out whatever it may be
and that would be good but it's almost time to get going um if you're joining now please write your
job. So you can see the icebreakers here. How would you explain your job to someone from year 1700?
And if you can't figure it out, write down what you do and we'll work together.
So I propose some sort of workshop for other teachers or people that run workshops
that will discuss how we do this very kind of streaming workshop. So basically, I would help
train people, train other people to do it. If this is interesting to you, look at the most recent
Code Refinery blog post and see what it says. We can announce that at the end. I guess it is time.
So, [name], I think you have an intro for us. Yes. Do you want to play the jingle, the short
one. So, welcome! [name], I believe you have our first intro. Yes, are you sharing
my screen to the stream? There you go. Okay, very welcome to day five of this Code Refinery
workshop. We're almost at the end already. Very sad about that. Soon it's over. But we still have
two days ahead of us. So week one of this workshop was all about version control from really the
basics of Git to collaborative use using GitHub. And then yesterday we started week two with an
overview around the reproducible research. We discussed how to record computational steps with
SnakeMake as an example tool, dependencies with Konda as an example tool and environments
with containers. And in the afternoon we then took a peek into the FAIR research software
development practices, licenses and what you need to know about these kind of things.
related to your research code. So today we're going to look into different ways of documenting
your research software, meaning from comments to readme files that we now have been looking
a little bit at already, and then to actually doing really nicely rendered web pages similar to
the Code Refinery materials pages and how you can do that like with a few small commands yourself.
And then in the afternoon we will take a look into the world of Jupyter notebooks and that you maybe
have already come in contact with during computing classes or while like working by yourself.
And here we're going to focus on things that can make your research also more reproducible
using Jupyter, for example.
So even if you know it already, I think there will still be something new in that lesson
as well.
And then for newcomers today, this workshop is fully live streamed.
So you will all watch the sessions via Twitch.
And if you know the workshop from before this year,
we don't have any dedicated team exercises in this second week.
But we have a lot of time for interaction
with our collaborative document, which
I will be showing in a moment.
And then we plan to have a minimum of 10 minute
breaks every hour plus a one-hour break over, well, in Finland,
midday lunchtime.
So our collaborative document, you should have,
or you have gotten the link after you
registered to this workshop.
It looks something like this.
And depending on how wide and how zoomed in you have this,
you will find a little pen symbol up top.
me it's now up here to the right for you it might be somewhere here up to the left where you can
switch to the edit mode if you want to add something here. Here we have all the links
also to this welcome session and then to the materials and the archive of previous questions
and let's switch to edit mode for a moment then we can scroll down we have our icebreaker question
here. Today we have three questions that you can answer. How would you explain your current job to
someone in the year 1700? Quite tricky one. For me I think the first one fits best. We have really
big complicated machines and I help people use them. So I try to help people use supercomputers
and maybe I can add a plus one here or a little dot. What's the best documented
project you have seen? Since we're going to talk about documentation we can pick
up on that later. For me I think it's also the scikit-learn documentation that
is really really great if you haven't seen it. Take a look and do you prefer
reading short social media posts or long blogs. And this is now a voting system, so like I added
my little O here, I basically added that me too. And here I also prefer
maybe often more longer blogs and also in the code, well more often the longer source code to
have everything at once. And then if you go down here, then here you can actually edit your
questions that you have about the upcoming session. So you can see some people already wrote some
here, so you can always ask that during the workshop and instructors will pick it up.
workshop. All the materials are linked from the workshop page and you can like come back
to it and look at them and you can also reuse them if you want to for your own workshops.
And we also record this whole workshop. So for some days the recordings will still be
available on Twitch and then after that you can find them on YouTube. There's usually
playlist and then you can look through the lessons and to jump to the lessons that you're interested
in. If you need a certificate for this course for university you can find instructions for that on
our web page and as mentioned before this session already we have this bring your own code session
so if there was a tool during this workshop that you would like to start using in your own work
You can come to these sessions and can take a look at these things with our experts or if you have a question related to tools like SnickMake or whatever.
They will happen next weekend, the week after Tuesday.
And now I will give over to [name] and [name] for the documentation lesson.
The floor is yours.
Thanks. I will take over the screen share.
Oops, where did the window go?
We have already put into a question or three questions about motivation and what our kind of wish list or what we think or what you essentially you think about documentation, what should be in there?
So, I think it's kind of expected that the best documented projects people have seen
are really big projects.
So they are things where you don't want to go through the source code and try to understand
what it's doing because it's so big.
Also, they are aimed at an audience who doesn't necessarily need to know all the details of the
thing that the package is doing. You just need one small piece. In Scikit-learn, you usually
don't use everything that Scikit-learn has because it has a lot of things.
things. So PyTorch is really big. Scikit-learn is really big. There's NumPy, SciPy. Pandas,
okay, yeah, Pandas is a bit – I often have to go and actually find stuff in the documentation
to use Pandas, and it often helps. But that's true. I think Pandas can be a bit complicated.
I'm not actually sure about FlutterDust.
Do you know that?
No.
And then, yeah, Tidyverse is really good.
Yeah, sorry?
Tidyverse is good at enforcing good documentation.
In my experience, it's not necessarily
that big project means good documentation, actually.
It's more active use by a lot of people,
which are activated by a lot of interested people who then also re-contribute a bit,
doesn't necessarily make all big projects having a good documentation.
Yeah, that's a good point.
Especially for details.
So, if you've ever actually, so that there is a built-in documentation thing for the new
operating system. All of these things you can run in Linux, for example, the commands like ls and
cd and so on. It's kind of a running joke that those are almost unreadable,
but they do have all the details. Being a really big project doesn't guarantee that
the documentation is especially good. Although it kind of does guarantee that there's a lot of it
available. So someone might write a tutorial who's not even involved in writing the code.
I guess my point is small things used by a small number of people don't necessarily need
so much documentation and you kind of have to decide what level of documentation is appropriate.
It depends on who's going to use it and it depends on how much time you have
and a lot of other factors. Well at the same time a small project that has
little documentation can still be well documented. Yeah I mean it's a small project it doesn't need
it doesn't have as much the document because it's also not that complex it's easier to just grasp
what it's actually doing okay but yeah i don't know what flutter does but if you wrote down
something that you think has really good documentation then there's the question
what actually makes the documentation useful what makes it good so that's the second question here
of course, what makes it important? Well, actually not a huge number of answers. Can
we think of some more? Well, okay. It's important for at least anything that's more complex
than a few simple functions to be actually useful to someone else. If you don't have
any documentation and everyone needs to read through your code to understand what it actually
does, then it's very likely that people just won't use it. They will have a look at, okay,
there's some code, I don't care. I have no idea what it does. I don't have the time to go through
the whole source code. And this applies to you yourself in the future. So yeah, if the future
is important, yes, that's a good answer. So if you go back to your code, even if it's a really
short simple code that has only three functions or three main functions. When you
come back to it in three years you're not going to remember what those function names are and
it's much nicer if they're mentioned in the documentation somewhere you can quickly see
so rather than you have to go digging through the code to figure out what you need to do or
how do you need to call the functions so it is also useful for yourself
okay so what is good documentation how would you describe useful documentation
um it helps you understand the code it gives you examples on how the code is being used
so that and yeah yeah okay so a really good point so it helps someone else use the code in without
them having to ask the creator. So if it's code that you wrote, then people don't have to always
come and ask you. You can offload some of that work to the documentation. Of course, you can
never write perfect documentation, so there will always be some questions and some things will
just not be correct. But it's much better than having to always show people exactly how to use
it for everything. That second point to me is, well, clear engaging not too long. Not too long
is a very relative thing, but I think that mostly applies to the initial readme, which is only
some part of the documentation. Yes, you shouldn't put useless information or repetitive
information into your documentation, but I'm not sure if I would agree with the not too long
in general. Well, too long is always... You can always make something too long.
Yeah, that's a good question. Can you add information that's actually relevant
and make it too long? I think it's possible. At some point, it's easier to just read the code.
So, at some point, it's no longer useful.
But also, it is important to structure it so that there is this, like, the first page
you see something relatively short that tells you what the software does.
Something like a README.
And then there are tutorials that tell you how to do the things that the software is
designed to do.
And then for each user-facing function, each function that a user could need, there's some
description of how to use it and what it does.
I would rephrase that, for every function that you intend to use it to use.
Right, yes.
It's also good if you want to, if you have the time, it's very good to have documentation
for all the functions that you never expect any user to use because of course someone will be
developing the code. Might be you in three years or might be someone else.
So it is good to document everything at least a little bit.
I think the third point is also quite good with having examples that actually help you to get
started. So, yeah, which is the tutorials that you mentioned is and the points here generally are
good. Yeah, I think. And yeah, the last edit point is actually something
easy to navigate. Yes, easy way to find what you're actually looking for, which is really
difficult. That's probably one of the most difficult bits in my opinion because a good
structure is not easily found. And if your code is growing then it's very likely to get messy
structure-wise at some point. So how do you motivate your colleagues to contribute to the
documentation. I mean, the first point is they explicitly say it's meant as a joke,
but I'm going to take it seriously because the best way to motivate someone, especially like
if you're developing something as a job, if it's part of your job to develop software for research,
actually paying people for spending time on it would be a good idea. It's not
something we always do very well, but it is actually a very good way of motivating people.
actually pay them for their time. But yeah, there are other ways as well.
So, yeah, explaining why it is important, explaining why it helps them in the future
and helps get their work cited, so it helps other people use the code. And for researchers,
citations are the kind of important so if other people can use your code then they can also
contribute to your field and help you in your career as well. And what I think is important
both in an academic or non-academic setting if you have undocumented code it takes a lot more
more time for someone else to get into that code.
Yeah.
And might even be impossible.
So just documenting saves money, if you want it like that.
Or in the academic instance, heaps knowledge.
It saves you time, and it saves your research group
time in the future.
There are so many non-doc, there's
so much non-documented code around
that is essentially, okay, well, this was done by a PhD master student, whatever, last year,
and he's gone. If you're lucky, he answers to emails. If you're unlucky, he doesn't,
at which point it's, I have no idea how this works, and I can't understand the code, so this
is dead upon the person leaving the group and might even have been dead before.
That last point being added is true, very important.
So we have talked about how to cite software and how to make sure that the correct people
get credit for software.
Documentation is part of the software.
It is an important part of the job of actually doing the research and getting to a result
and publishing the software and publishing the paper and all of that.
So the person, someone contributing to the documentation really should be looked
at, someone who's actually spending time contributing to the research project.
At least if we are at the point where we can actually talk about citing software,
then definitely someone who writes
documentation should be included in the authors for that software.
Okay, I think that is quite a good piece of information and let's head to what should
documentation actually contain.
So we basically covered everything in the first section, but I just want to quickly
show what we're going to do in this lesson.
So in the first half, essentially,
will be discussions about documentation
and then how to write good README files.
And then in the second half, we'll
go through a demonstration with a slightly more
complicated documentation than README files
and how to get that viewable online,
how to deploy it on a website.
So let's go to the motivation section and feel free to answer of course in the notes
even though I'm not sharing them right now. So why documenting code is essentially done.
Yeah so let's talk about that. So yeah what should a good documentation contain?
Should we, let's wait for a moment before we start throwing around ideas, give people
some time to talk.
We can already collect what we had further up, which is how would you describe a useful
documentation?
Sure.
Yeah, so there are some points that go to that section, so okay, so the arrangement
should be boring.
So yeah, it should contain the things
that you expect it to contain,
which is installation instructions,
some quick start, and how to,
so these are tutorials on how to do a specific thing
the code is intended to do,
and a reference, which means,
I guess we'll get back to it,
but some documentation for almost everything in the code,
but in a structured way,
so that you can find what you're looking for.
.
where to report bugs, where to report issues or where to report or where to discuss about
features that you would like to add or would like someone to add to the software
and then in general how contributions work.
okay so here's our checklist it's mostly the same things so you would want to have in the
documentation you would want to mention the authors of the software the license purpose
is something already mentioned how it should be cited it's useful to have that's also in
the citations file of course and then some examples where you can or tutorials how to get started
dependencies um installation instructions is important
the reference documentation is already mentioned um yeah and how do you want people to contact you
and some frequently asked questions section this is roughly almost everything was was there in the
answers so that's a good thinking we've roughly have the same ideas okay um we do have um in the
next step kind of a list of popular tools and solutions let's go there um we will go over
some of them in more detail and I think the only things we really want to mention here for these
tools and solutions are the formats that we commonly use to create documentation or
which is mainly markdown and restructured text. Okay right so yeah okay we have a whole section
on in-code documentation, which basically means the documentation that is embedded in the code
itself. And then I think in the next section we'll have readme files, so we'll talk more about that.
So yeah, Markdown you already know because the collaborative document is in Markdown. I was
I was going to just open it and show, but it's, you can,
if you're looking at it, you can see it.
So this is Markdown.
Yeah, and the restructured text is another option.
So can you, do you want to say more about
why use either one of them?
Well, the one biggest reason is that
it's a relatively simple format.
It's all text-based.
So you, well, yeah, it's all text-based.
So you can easily put it into version control
and see differences.
So it's not a binary format
where you get a big binary dump of the data,
but you can actually follow what changes were made.
It has most features that you need
for having a nice looking, at least online document.
So I guess, I mean, they look a bit different, but they have roughly the same features, and
I guess restructured text, because it is what Sphinx uses, and Sphinx is very commonly
used to build documentation, it might have some features more, some features are there
more by default, whereas in Markdown, you might need some expansion plugin, something like that.
One thing is that Markdown is maybe a bit simpler. It's maybe a bit faster to learn,
but it's not a big difference. It's a very small difference. There's many flavors of Markdown,
unfortunately so some syntax that you use on say github readme files might not work in a different
place so yeah there's um and there's multiple flavors that implement for example equations
So they might do it slightly differently, unfortunately.
But the standard, the text formatting things generally work the same way.
Yeah.
yeah so we'll in our example in the next second well not the next section but the
the next hour we'll use a mist flavored markdown in Sphinx but yeah you can you can use
essentially whatever you want in Sphinx and of course Sphinx is not the only thing out there.
And there is a list of other static html site generators on this page as well so
feel free to have a look at that. But really the main thing the main reason to use markdown or
restructured text is that it is text so you can version control it and you can use it with your
source code very easily. So yeah we will use Sphinx and one reason is that it is actually
what we use to build this course website. It's very commonly used in Python projects but not
limited, of course, to Python. It is itself, it runs in Python. There's plenty of other options
and a lot of these use Markdown. I guess that's probably enough, probably all we want to say
about this. Sphinx is a built-in thing for API documentation as well.
Okay, let's head on to Encode documentation.
Well, I mean, wikis are another popular option, but they don't exist as text in your repository.
The advantage is that it's pretty easy to start editing it.
You don't even really need to learn any new language, even though Markdown is an easy
language to learn.
But yeah, it is not connected to your repository, which is the main big downside.
Leite is very common and that produces PDFs. The advantage is that it's very popular and
people in certain fields know how to use it. The disadvantage is the PDF format.
It has some restrictions on how you can use it. It is not easy to turn Leite into a website,
although it is possible and it's not easy to automate building it although it is possible
so it gets a bit more complex.
Doxygen is well you can use it for it's very popular for C++ you can use it again for API
documentation so it's kind of like Sphinx it's just another option and here's some other tools
and they kind of seem to go with certain languages but in principle you don't need
to pick a specific one based on what language you use. It just depends on the community.
Okay, so in code documentation. So anything that's inside a source code file is in code
documentation and it's probably the first thing you do maybe after the readme file.
So when you start writing code it's good to already start including some documentation
in the code itself.
So let's take a look at these two comments, I wonder how much should we go back to the
notes even, well let's say, let's paste something into the notes and, okay, let's
Okay, it's already there, so yeah, which one is better, what is useful about either option?
Let's just do a vote, you can write down some comments below, but yeah, vote for option
A or B. So what makes comment B so obviously better? Maybe this was too obvious a question.
This is a pretty obvious question. Well, comment A only says what's plainly written there already.
no additional additional information obtainable from comment a is comment b wrong on purpose
you record temperatures below minus 50 as measurement errors and this checks
if it's larger yes if it's larger than it i don't actually know if it's i don't think it was on
purpose but um yeah you're right now we check if so this one actually doesn't if you just have this
And then this line of code, it doesn't actually
tell you that it's wrong.
But here, you say why you want to check
if it's bigger than minus 50.
And that's a measurement error.
So yeah, now you know that the code is actually
wrong when you just know what it's doing.
It could well be on purpose, actually.
So the comment definitely is useful,
because you just spotted the bug.
Yeah, is there anything here that we didn't mention? Not really? No. Yeah.
Okay, yeah, and there's some situations where people often use
comments where having version control is actually a better option. So sometimes you see people
comment out a piece of code and, you know, for testing that's fine. You comment it out, you run
it once and you see if what you're doing is working. But it's then not a good idea to just
keep it lying around in the code because when you remove a piece of code and you commit it to version
control, commit it to Git, the code exists. Before removing it, if you have committed it to Git,
the code exists in Git and you can get it back. So there's no reason to keep it also commented
out in the code. It just makes the code harder to read.
And this is not even the worst thing. So if it's at least commented out,
it's not looking as if it were a normal code, but I've also seen things like if zero.
Okay. Yeah.
Or if to comment stuff out.
Yeah. I'm guilty of that, but it's usually to force. So for example, if it checks for a file
and then creates one if it doesn't exist. I might force it to delete the existing file and overwrite
it by doing that when developing. But yeah, just keeping that around in the code is not a good
idea. It makes it harder to read. Another one is emulating version control.
So a comment that tells people why you changed a piece of code is not really that useful or that's
what version controllers is meant to do. That's why you write a comment for each comment that
you make in Git. You tell people why you're making the change. So it's not necessary to
make those in the code as well or in comments. I think what's important with these kind of
of in-code comments is that they explain things.
They don't state what's happening,
but they explain why things are happening.
Why are you doing these kind of things, and so on.
And that's where these kind of inline comments become useful.
Yeah.
And then there's a second type of ENCODE documentation.
Yes, so this is more about the API documentation.
There was already a question a little bit further on and
further up in the collaborative document about it.
Ah, right.
And this is, I think, the answer to that question.
What should be in a doc string?
In general, yeah, what's going into the function, what's coming out of the function, what does
the function do so that whatever kind of API documentation generator you would be using
can pass this and create a nice looking documentation out of it.
the better structured for whatever parser you use it is the more the better it
the better it is for the for usability in the end.
Yeah so it is actually very common to see the comments take more space than the actual code
Even though this is a relatively constructed example, it's also relatively realistic.
So it is useful to tell how you're converting between Fahrenheit and Celsius in this function.
And what is the expected input and output.
And it is actually just having this line of code inside your code is less descriptive
than calling this function.
So yeah, this is a good example.
This is how you do it in R, just occasionally change from Python for variety.
Okay, so, yeah, so docstrings can,
they do more than just comments
because you can pass them out into this documentation.
And so you can automatically generate
this API documentation part of your documentation,
which is very useful.
And what that really means is
that your API documentation lives with the code.
It exists in the same place as the code.
and you, well, that makes it more likely
that you will remember to change it
when you change the function.
So there is no separate file
where you have all of your API documentation.
It is in the same file as the code, which is very useful.
Okay, so a good docstring will describe
what the function does.
What are the input variables and what are the outputs?
Format as they are the input variables, so what types?
So essentially, how to use the function and what is it doing.
Oh, and one very good point is that the name of the function
is also important for documentation.
So here, the function name tells you exactly what it's doing.
And that is important.
So then finally to README files, let's go over this section and then have a break.
So README files are kind of the first, well I said that you might want to first start when you're
starting to write the code, you might want to start with in code documentation of some kind,
but then README files are the first thing that a user would see and that anyone you share the
code with. When they get your code the first thing they look at is a readme file and if it's
on GitHub, GitLab, something like that, then it's a nicely formatted section on the front
page of your code. So it is the first thing people see and I think it is very important
to have. So you should always have some kind of a readme file. It might also be enough
in a small enough project to put everything in the readme file.
I would agree.
In general, I think the readme is kind of your way to advertise your code.
Yeah.
So we have a few fun exercises for readme files and I think we should take a little
bit of time to so we have already talked a lot about what is required but we should spend a
little bit of time playing around with it so let's do the exercise one as a demonstration
but for that we need a readme on github so in the next section we'll use this
this documentation example, but I will also use it in this readme example.
And if we open the readme file here, we'll see that it's written in Markdown.
GitHub nicely renders Markdown automatically.
So what are these things?
some more information about what kinds of formatting you can use here. But let's try
make a note. So if I copy the whole thing, maybe it doesn't copy these ticks. Let's see.
So what is each of these things? No, it does copy the ticks. Oh, because the ticks are
part of the Markdown language. Right. Okay. So the first thing is a note.
It will do some fancy formatting. The second is important. And one thing you can do if you're
editing it on GitHub is you can preview. So let's see what it looks like. Okay. So there is a blue
information thing. There is a slightly more red and well I guess yellowish but
more visible version of it. Okay so that's a fun thing you can do. What is this
details and summary? I guess this is some kind of card section. So let's try this.
so if you add this details tag and it has a summary on top, short summary.
Oh okay so details is something that's hidden by default but it has a title
and then when you click on it it expands. So this is useful for making the readme more
readable but still you can include some additional information that people might need.
Okay and then there's some batches. So a lot of projects have these automatically updating
batches that fetch some information like is the documentation up to date and building correctly
or do the tests currently pass in this branch and so on. So this format creates some sort of a batch
This is from image.shields.io, so it builds you this image with the text that you put in.
Which is essentially the address that you use converted into text.
Yeah, so this is also a link that goes to example.org in this case.
this case. But there would be a lot more realistic cases for using this. So you can use a batch,
for example, to show, well, like I said, that the documentation is correctly compiling.
Which would probably come from a different source because that commonly comes from some kind of
of continuous integration or a system that tells you okay it actually builds properly and so on.
Okay so we should go on a break soon. Let's take an example readme quickly
so we can find something on github. Do you have an example in mind that has some batches and
what other useful features we would want to see.
Let's look at
NumPy
is the one that always comes to my mind when I think of a Python project.
Go for NumPy, I think that's fine.
Okay, so NumPy is a huge
project. You have to scroll down a bit to get to the
to the readme file. So the batches are on top. There's a DOI that links to the digital object
identifier of the software. There's a stack overflow page for NumPy where you can ask questions
and it shows how many downloads per month they've had.
And an open SSF. I'm not actually sure what this is, some sort of score. So you might have
something like the coverage of tests and or whether the tests are passing is one I mentioned
all sorts of useful Ataclans information in there and then they have everything
you need to know about NumPy right on top
code of conduct and how to contribute or call for contributions in this case
and yeah, so these are the most important things. In the documentation itself, actually this one,
this readme already tells you how to install it. Does it tell you how to install it? Well,
it has a pypy tag, but it doesn't really tell you how to install it. Okay, fine,
it tells you how to test something, test that it runs correctly.
So here's the documentation page though and let's go to the web version.
So there's a getting started section, there's a user guide, there's the API reference
and how to contribute. So the most important parts are quickly there,
there's installation instructions and links to important things like issue tracker is where you
report bugs for example and support QnA.
Okay so maybe I should still quickly show what an API reference looks like
like so this is I want to function well let's just do infinity so somewhere in the code
they define this numpy.infinity which represents an infinite number and there they have a doc
string that's essentially converted into this section of the documentation okay so I think
that's enough of that example and let's take a break before we go to the next section so
I would say at least until five past then we'll we should have plenty of time all right
so see you at five past bye
you
Hello, we are back, um, hope you had a good break.
There was a question about the repository that I showed. I didn't actually save the
changes but that's actually the template, that's the repository that we're going to
use in this next demonstration anyway. So I will show it in a moment. Sorry, we don't
use it in this one. We use it in the next one. So let me just quickly hop over to that
just to answer the question that I started to answer.
So there is this documentation example repository
that allows you to generate an example that we
will be using today.
And what I showed was actually generated
from this documentation example.
So it's something that I will delete in
after this course is over.
but you can also generate an example from here.
It will be more important later what the contents are,
but of course, for the thing that I showed,
it was mainly that it has a README file.
Okay, so Sphinx and Markdown.
So yeah, we mentioned that Sphinx is the thing
we use to generate these course materials,
and they are large part written in Markdown.
And you can also use RichText in
RichText with Sphinx, that is probably the default
but it's also easy to use Markdown
and since you're all used to Markdown by now
because all the nodes are in Markdown, we will use that.
Okay, so this is mainly a demonstration
so I will soon move into the
Visual Studio window
But you can also try to do this probably better to just follow along for now but you can also
try to do this in a project of your own or just following these steps.
So I will just expand this window a bit.
Okay, so the instructions start with some checks that everything is working as expected.
So Sphinx runs in Python, so we need to have Python.
We do have Python.
I will just quickly run through this, just that we don't run into problems while doing
the demonstration.
So we need Sphinx build. Whoops, I clicked on Sphinx build, and now I'm no longer copied.
I have no longer copied what I was expecting. So, okay, Sphinx quick start is a descriptive
tool we'll use. It has the correct version. Everything's fine. And one important thing
that you need to install separately is this mist parser. So for this to work, you need
both Python, Sphinx, and Mist parser.
So Mist is the kind of markdown we will be using.
Okay, so let's get started.
So right now we are in an empty folder.
So there's nothing in here.
I will make a new directory.
I'll actually use the file view for that.
new folder
doc example
and then in there we okay we need to go in that folder and then run
Sphinx quick start in that folder so let's go there to documentation example
and then run Sphinx quick start right here
Okay, maybe I need a bit more space for this. Okay, so it asks you a few questions.
Let's say I don't want to separate the directories now. It's usually best to just
stick with the standard, with the defaults. Project name is something we of course need.
need. This is only a test project. Let's call it that. Or should we have a funny name for
it? I'm not great with funny names. I will not start because then I will not be able
to continue. Okay. Author's names, that's my name. Project release, so that's the version
number, let's say. So it's 0.0.1. And language, let's do English. So it will support English.
English and no other languages by default.
Okay. So now we have a bunch of new files here.
So quickstart created
all the files that Sphinx needs to run in this folder.
There's this conf.py,
which has all the configuration for this project.
there's all the project name, copyright statement, all those name,
version number and then we have some extensions that you can add
and we will in fact add one since we are here why not do it now. So we want to add this
mist parser extension here. Okay and that's probably the only thing we want to change in this
in this file. Let's look at the other files. So okay, conf.py has the configuration options
for Sphinx. Then we have an index.rst, which is the main file for this documentation. It's a
rich text file. Oh, sorry, [name], did you say something?
No, I wouldn't call it the main, it's the root file.
Okay, yeah, the root file. So, in this case, it has a title and then it has a talk tree,
so a table of contents, yes. And then you can define some indices in here that it will
use to generate the documentation pages.
Okay, the makefile and make.bat are something you use to actually build the documentation,
so they're workflow files.
We don't need to go into the details of what's in there because it will look pretty complicated.
And it's essentially like you never modify.
Yeah.
Okay.
So there's an empty build directory, an empty static directory, an empty templates directory.
So the build directory, it's where Sphinx puts things that it creates.
So you generally don't put anything in there.
is for your own HTML templates, you will not be creating any of those in this example.
And static is for static files for the HTML site like images or CSS for styles and so on.
So mainly images are the ones you will run into first, those will go into the static folder.
Okay, so let's look at the index.
So we will not use this indices and tables section, so we can remove it.
And then, okay, so this section here is a comment in rich text, so this will not be
displayed on the website. Let me show the whole thing. It states that it's the master file created
by Sphinx Quickstart. Then we have this table of contents, max depth of the table. If a file
contains sections, like how deep do you want to go in those sections? And then in here,
we can add our own pages. Sorry, let me
disable that because it is definitely going to make things
weird for what we want to do here. Okay, so I should actually probably have logged out of
everything. Okay, so here we go. We can add a page into a documentation, so somefeature.markdown.
This is a file name and that file doesn't exist yet, so we need to add it, but
once we add it, it will be in the table of contents. Okay, so let's add that file.
Let's call it somefeature.md and then we can start adding things here.
So this is now marked down so it should look relatively familiar by this point.
It has a title, it has a subsection title, some normal text and a list and some nested
items in that list.
And I need to also save this one.
And now going back to the terminal, I could probably run something in VS Code as well
to run this. But, well, let's just run it in the terminal, follow the instructions to
the letter. So, what we run is Sphinx build. Then we give it the directory that we want
to where the input files are in,
which is this current directory, so dot,
and then where do we want to put all the build files?
And that's the underscore build directory.
Okay, there's a warning, non-existent.
It didn't find some feature.
Okay, so did I do something wrong?
Yes, some-
There's a typo.
Oh no, wait.
somefeature.md. Yes this is somefeature.md. So then the right folder. Okay it should be.
No. No it's not. True. This isn't right. So I originally opened
the folder one above this one and then created this folder. Okay so it was in the wrong folder.
It's a slightly unintended. Okay, let's try again. So I'll go to the terminal and run the
same command again by pressing up arrow. There we go. And there it was.
Am I sharing the entire terminal window now? I think there are many.
Might be cutting off a little bit of the bottom.
Yeah, it's actually complete.
OK.
It just looks odd because it's line breaking.
No, I mean, I think the last thing I'm seeing in the stream
is this line here.
Yeah, sorry.
OK, I've updated it.
Yeah.
So the command I just ran is this things build dot
and then underscore build.
OK, so mostly it was visible just
when it reads the end of the last line, then you maybe didn't see it. Okay, but here we are.
It's a little bit wider as well.
Okay, so now we should have the files. It didn't complain about anything.
And now in this build directory, this is what we had previously. And now we have
Well, we have some HTML files, importantly, an index.html.
So we can open that in a web browser and see what's inside.
So there's different ways of doing that from the terminal.
I think in this case, we can try to do this in VS Code.
We can go live, on the live server.
The problem is that it will open the folder that's in the bottom of the, but while it
will open the folder that's currently open in VS Code.
So this font is really small, okay, now it's really big.
So yeah, that's the build directory and finally, okay, so now it opened the actual documentation
page.
So this is what the default looks like, it's a table of contents, there's some feature
and a subsection and then there's this navigation area.
Okay, so let's go to some feature and this is now the page we wrote in Markdown for this
some feature section.
Okay, so how are we doing?
are actually we haven't spent all that much time here yet so let's do a bit more
so we can go and edit the somefeature.markdown and try some
try some more fancy features of the mist markdown.
Okay, so maybe not as that fancy,
but there's different levels of titles,
which we are already seeing.
So just level one,
level two.
so this will look slightly different once we run oops that's still level two with three of these
hashes it will be level three and with four hashes it will be level
four okay so this will look slightly different actually why not
why not just keep recompiling and show as we go
Okay so this is what the different levels of titles look like.
There's a useful feature here so there is a permalink
to each of these heading each of these sections so when you say
hash then the section title it will take you directly to that section in the documentation.
Okay, so what else can you do? You can do numbered lists, so let's do three items,
but now we don't actually have to keep numbering the items correctly. You can make edits and
sometimes the numbers come out or sometimes you forget to change the numbers, but
but the Markdown Renderer takes care of that for you, so the numbers will come up correctly
in this case, yeah, that's expected. Okay, then some other things you can do and you can
also test this in the notes. Maybe don't add too large tables into the notes, but okay,
This is what a table looks like.
So you need to have a header and a line below the header and then the renderer will realize
that this is supposed to be a table.
Okay so this is a table of whether each number is prime.
I'm always a bit confused about why one is not a prime,
but fine.
Two is a prime.
Maybe one is a prime.
What do you think?
Let's also add a bit of spacing there just to,
so one useful thing, of course, in Markdown is that
the texts written into,
The text document itself usually looks good enough on its own, so you don't even need
to render it to be able to read it properly.
But this creates a table, so 4 is not a prime, which is good to know.
And then, well, you can have, importantly in software documentation, you can have code.
So this is Python code.
So we'll start with three ticks and then the language name.
So Python.
So let's just do a quick function.
hello world or just hello and this function prints
hello world okay so that's an example of how to include code in
in markdown and i will language yeah in a certain language so i will quick
also just copy paste in an example from that's written in C so that you see there's multiple
languages I just didn't write to write all of this C code into the markdown file okay
because there's a lot of a lot more you need to do in C to get the same result okay
OK, you can also include a file directly.
So this is literal include directive.
So it's the same three ticks, and then literal include,
and the name of the file.
That was the question, if you can give a bit more
explanation of what you can configure and what you can do.
and I think going through the conf.py a bit would be useful. Okay yeah.
Let's see so there's one more thing so we don't have an example.py so this will not actually
work so let's get rid of this section but one more thing before that so you can
also write math equations which is important in many fields
So this is a math section and this is something that the specifically missed flavored markdown does for you.
I think that's also for the literal include, that's also missed.
Oh yeah, okay, that is true.
We do need to do something in the conf.py to get this to work, so we'll be there in a second.
So we'll just write this very interesting equation with a green theorem.
Okay, and you can also do an inline equation.
So again, math is, it's not square brackets, what are these called?
Curly brackets.
Curly brackets, okay.
Okay. So that's an inline equation. Okay. And so, okay, this will actually not work.
No, let's see. I'm quite surprised.
Well, it mentions that in some older versions of Sphinx, you needed to include it.
Okay, yes, so this Sphinx is, so now this is included in Sphinx or with the Mist
parser extension directly. We don't need to change the config file for this to work.
Let's change the config file anyway.
So here's the config file. So there's not that much here actually.
That's where to look for HTML templates and what files to not include.
And we could change the HTML theme.
Yeah, we can do that. I don't know what the defaults are.
Well, you could use the Sphinx RTD. I think that should be part of the Codefinery environment.
Okay, let's do that. So is it Sphinx RTD?
I think read the docs RTD. Yes. Let's see if this works. No. Okay. So we don't have
that one. So that failed. It's things RTD underscore RTD underscore theme. Sphinx read
Orthodox theme with underscores.
Okay.
Okay, that works.
So yeah, this looks a lot nicer, doesn't it?
This looks pretty much like our course documentation,
which is built on this as well.
Okay.
It's half past, so yeah, okay, we are doing good time.
time. So I mean in principle there's a lot you can change but a lot of it is not in the default
configuration options here. So you have HTML templates so you can write any HTML file you
want and include the contents in that Sphinx creates into that. There's also a number of
these themes that you can use and you can install third-party themes as Python packages.
So there is a lot you can do.
But yeah, so I don't know if there's anything we can easily demonstrate here in the time we have.
I think the theming is probably the easiest that we have done that.
Yeah.
Okay.
We could build this example.py file to show how it actually works and just add a example.py.
this literal include section it also specifies the language and we are putting emphasis on
lines two and three here so we don't know what those lines are yet because we didn't
create the file yet lines two and three that means if I'm importing
something, it will probably be those lines.
So those are the lines we're emphasizing and then we do something.
I think that's already sufficient.
Yeah.
Okay.
So that's some Python code.
And let's demo.
And your example of Py is again in the wrong folder.
True.
Let's move it to the right folder.
Okay.
Good.
Thanks for noticing that.
Okay.
So now it's including the example code directly,
and it's added some emphasis on these two lines.
And that's pretty convenient, especially in our case,
where we sometimes have examples that build on one another,
and we just want to highlight what changed
in between the previous and this piece of code.
So that's something that's quite useful there.
yeah and of course this is a way of including the same example in multiple different places
for example okay so we did the math we did the so we we did not add one thing we didn't add
is api documentation and we have talked a good bit about that so maybe we should do that one
as well before moving on to the next part. One thing I want to mention is that this is
also a nice way to, in general, present examples and keep the examples as actual runnable files.
So I think you can do literal includes that only include certain lines and don't
not just highlight but just include the specific lines that you want to show.
but you essentially have the example files as whole scripts or whatever,
which makes it more usable in the end.
Yeah, that's a good point.
Because often you write a tutorial with some code examples,
but it's hard to write that in such a way
that the code examples actually work and actually run.
run. It is hard to test those code examples but if you instead include certain lines from a script
you can always run the script and see that it actually works. Okay so I've deleted the
script-like part that I added but instead now I'm adding this multiply function and importantly this
function has in code documentation, it has an API reference. So this is now our code for this
project and we want to have an API reference added to our documentation. We don't currently have one.
So how do we do that? First we need to go back to this index.rst file
and we will be documenting the example module example.py here. So let's just call it the
subsection example. Let's actually add a whole main section API reference.
I assume the example will work but this looks a lot like
Markdown and RST are getting mixed together so we'll see. It looks suspicious.
Okay, so this is another of these tree tick sections, we'll call this eval RST.
I am very much starting to think that I'm doing something wrong here.
No, I think that's perfectly fine.
This is already RST, so why don't I just have an RST section directly, like this.
Ah, yeah, but then you can't use the hashtags for the titles, the API reference.
Yes.
Well, this title is already in RST.
This title is already in rich text, so why not do it this way?
Okay.
So let's have an example of how to do titles in rich text instead.
So this is a big title and this is a small one, I think level one and level two.
So this will be auto module example.
So module in this case is a Python module, it's this example module here.
And then some magic words members so we include all of the members everything that's in example.py.
Okay and now we do need to go and change the configuration file conf.py.
We need to add an extension autodoc extension we need to make some other changes as well.
So, there is an auto-doc extension that generates this API documentation.
The rest of this stuff, I think, maybe goes on top, but below this first comment, maybe.
Yeah, on top.
So we need to import some things.
What we essentially need to do is we need to inform Sphinx on where this can be found.
And that's what we're doing here.
From OS, we are getting the path we are currently on.
And this allows us to set the path Python
is looking for code in.
So if you are not familiar with Python,
you can think of this as a magic expression.
But then you put whatever your source path is in here.
So our source path is the current directory,
so we just use dot.
OK.
Should it run now?
I think it should run.
I think it should.
In a normal Python project, you would probably
have something like source in here and not dot.
Yeah, or the Python package name.
You know what I did incorrectly here?
I've just added this section directly to the index.rst,
and not as a separate file.
That's why I got confused.
It doesn't hurt too much.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay, so it should build.
Build the example, build import module, example.
No module named my project.
Okay, so what is happening?
Right. I still have these lines that don't work in my code.
Yeah.
I should be importing something else. Okay. So yeah, now it should work as long as I have
NumPy available.
Which I think you have.
And let's do some proper formatting there. Okay. Now it works. Okay. So now let's go
back to the main page and here we have the API documentation directly in the main page which is
not the best thing. Not optimal.
Okay. Normally you would do this. Yeah normally it would be a separate section here
in a separate file. Okay but it's, we have a limited amount of time it would not be that
complicated to fix this, but it works already, so let's keep it as it is.
Okay, so that was the Sphinx and Markdown example. There's a lot of stuff there you can play around
with. You can try doing this yourself either with the example or with your own project.
Are people confused about Mist and Markdown and restructured text?
Not a huge number of questions in the notes, so I guess we're fine.
Well, there's a bit more information here.
Write them in the document. We can come to them later or they can be answered in the document as well.
One useful thing to mention that often saves me and often I forget to do and therefore get into trouble is there is a way of checking links in this generated documentation.
So, at least if the links just don't work at all, this will help you.
If they lead you to the wrong place, it might not save you, but it's a very common issue
to add wrong or incorrect links, so this is useful.
Okay, let's then head on to the next section.
GitHub pages and how to deploy Sphinx documentation to GitHub pages. This is again using GitHub
and GitHub is not the only option, but it is a common and easy option. Since basically
everything we have is on GitHub, we will demonstrate using GitHub.
GitHub. So we will be using two things, GitHub pages, which is a way of including websites
essentially in your repository and showing them as HTML as websites instead of the source
code. And GitHub actions, which are things that run automatically when you push something
to your repository so this is a really useful thing in general we'll see an example of.
Okay so yeah this is pulling a lot of stuff from the past two weeks and putting it all together
so we'll just go into it and see how it goes. Okay so there is this documentation example
repository and I already made my own version of this documentation example, so it's generated
from this template as it says here and at this point I should have the instructions
available for me. Okay, just a small moment. Here we are.
So this is a repository that contains,
it's already on GitHub,
but it contains essentially what we just did.
So there's a documentation folder in this repository.
It has a conf.py for Sphinx
and all of this other status,
some feature.markdown that we just created.
It is very familiar looking.
and then there's a source folder for our actual software. It's actually an empty folder
just as a readme file that says this is where your code would go. So yeah, this is an example.
Okay, so
we could clone this locally and do what we just did to build the documentation,
but instead we're going to do it with a workflow file so we will add a new file
is the um is the text too small
that may be slightly better okay so let's create a new file
and this needs to go into dot github slash workflows
And now we can choose whatever name we want for the workflow, so let's call it documentation
and it's a YML file, a YAML file.
So this is something I would rarely type out, basically never, I just always get an example
from somewhere and change the parts that need changing.
But the syntax is not that complicated.
So a workflow has a name, documentation.
When do we want to run it?
So we run on a push, a pull request.
So if somebody makes a pull request,
we want to run this documentation builder.
And then workflow dispatch.
This means that we can manually ask this workflow to run.
which is useful for an example. Okay permissions so it needs so the idea is that it work this
workflow will build our documentation and then put it in our repository in a branch
and then that branch is our website so it needs the permission to write into our repository.
Let's give it write permissions to the contents of the repository.
Okay and then we'll define a job for this workflow to run.
So there's a job step called docs.
This will run on so you need to tell it what operating system you want your job to run on.
Ubuntu. That's the simplest option for me. And then we define some steps to run.
Okay. So at this point, maybe I will quickly tell you what each step does,
but I will not write out the details. So first we need to check out or clone our repository.
and then we need to install Python because Sphinx runs in Python. Then we need to install
some dependencies and that is a piece of code we write ourselves. So this step install
dependencies runs a piece of code which is pip install and the dependencies we need.
Okay. Am I now on the same level as the name? Yes. Okay. Then we want to build the documentation.
So it also runs a command. It runs the Sphinx build command. The source for the documentation
is the doc folder and the build folder is where the documentation goes.
Now, importantly, the build folder will not appear in our repository. It's not modifying
our repository at this point. It's just running on some random machine in the cloud and creating
a build folder. So, we need to copy it somewhere where other people can see it. So, deploy
to GitHub pages. Now, what does this do? This runs a workflow
someone else wrote for us that actually does the deployment but we need to give it some parameters
and well okay before we give it the parameters we only want it to run if the push is to the main
if something gets pushed to the main branch so this looks a bit complicated it is a bit
complicated but what it does it it prevents this from publishing documentation that's
in the wrong branch. That's in a pull request, for example. So, only documentation in the main
branch gets updated to the actual documentation. Okay. And then some parameters. Publish it to
a branch called GitHub Pages. It needs a secret token to actually modify the repository.
and well that's where it should find the build documentation.
Okay, so a good number of steps here but each of them in principle is hopefully something that's
familiar to you by now. So we are cloning a repository, installing Python, installing
dependencies, building the documentation,
and the last thing is new.
We are pushing it to a new branch
in our existing repository.
OK.
Now I have a new file.
I want to commit this to GitHub.
Actually, this is a pretty good commit message.
to build and publish documentation. Okay. And I'll just push directly to the main branch
in this case. I'm the only one working on this project. Okay.
Here we go. Now we have a new workflow file. Okay. Well, did anything happen? Not really.
Yes, there did.
it is something did happen. It is already running. So the workflows are already set to run
in this repository. They are automatically set to run. As soon as you have any workflows being
set up, they will run. Okay, that's nice. There's a workflow that hasn't completed yet,
but we can look at the details from here. So this is all the steps we just defined.
And now it is done.
Now it is done.
Okay.
So it prints some output at each step.
It's installed Python, Sphinx build and so on.
Okay.
So what did it do?
It created a new branch.
Oh, that's still yellow.
Maybe I need to just refresh the page.
Now it's, yeah, it's a nice green tick.
So everything's working.
created a new branch called GitHub pages which is here and now this has this index.html and
everything that's needed for the website. That's essentially a copy of the build directory
as we specified in our. Okay I would assume that it's not working as a page yet though
I need to go to settings. Yeah at least it's not deployed as a page yet. So if I go to settings
there's a pages section here and here I can select deploy from a branch
and the branch I want to deploy from is github pages
gh pages okay and the root of that branch save the settings
Okay, and now if I go to, so the URL is slightly different from this repository URL, but it's
related.
So I need to go to myusername.github.io and then the name of the repository.
Okay and here we are. So now my documentation is online. Anyone can go to this address and
see it. Actually one very useful thing to do after this would be to take this URL and
edit the readme file and add some sort of link to it in here. I will do the simplest
possible job of adding the link here but you might want to format it slightly better.
Add a link to documentation in readme.
Okay, so now we have, I guess, I made a mistake in Markdown syntax here.
Okay, so now we have a link to the documentation in our README and it will get updated automatically.
So now I did a new push, it's rebuilding the documentation, although even though there
wasn't any change to the documentation.
It's always when I change anything in this repository,
it will rebuild and publish again.
You can also, which people very often do,
put it into the About.
Yes, so the About section is not visible now
if I make it a bit smaller.
So here is an About section.
So if you click on that cogwheel in the top right corner,
there's the website URL.
OK.
Or use your GitHub pages website,
which will point to the correct one,
even if you change the name of the repository.
You can also add a description here.
Example of building documentation.
OK, now that's updated.
So now there's a link to the documentation
right here in the sidebar for anyone who's
looking at the Adjurable story.
After this is the lunch break, right?
So we have five more minutes.
We definitely don't want to start on the next section, which is
how to publish your own website in GitHub Pages.
It is quite similar
to this one, and you can check it out on your own.
I guess the biggest difference is that we're not automatically building
the documentation. We're not automatically building
the website. We are only publishing it on GitHub Pages.
Yeah. Well, I did mention there are alternatives. There's GitLab. CI GitLab is a common alternative
to GitHub. And GitLab Pages, Read2Docs is commonly used. And well, those are the alternatives
we mentioned here, I guess. There's essentially all the places where you can host your report
stories. Almost all of them also have a way of hosting a static website because it is
actually just HTML code.
Which you could also on whatever other server, web server you have that you in some way control
and just point it to, okay, this is the static website.
Yeah.
True.
GitHub Pages or GitLab Pages is just a very simple way to have a web host for you, that
you don't have to explicitly pay.
So we will skip over the hosting websites and homepages on GitHub and go to the summary.
And probably the best way of doing this would be to ask everyone, if you have any questions
questions, please ask them in the notes and see if there's anything interesting there
or anything very important to bring up.
I think the first point in the summary is actually quite important. There is not the
one right way to do things in documentation. And I would add to that, it's in general more
important to have some documentation than to have a perfect documentation yeah yeah this is a typical
case of better have something incomplete than not having anything at all well now if you feel
this went too fast or you just want to learn this better to actually use this on your own
repository. The instructions are on the course website or on the website for this section.
So I essentially followed this deploying Sphinx documentation to GitHub almost exactly. So
just take a look there and the Sphinx and Markdown section where you can set up your
documentation first.
But yeah, so there's always a balance you need to find with how much time you spend
writing documentation versus how much time you spend coding and how much time you spend
doing research and other things in your life.
So for smaller projects, a README file can easily contain everything you need, especially
you have in code documentation as well. Something that takes that in code documentation and turns it
into an API reference is nice and you can do that very quickly with Sphinx even if you don't write
any other documentation in there. But that's a small step further and then in a bigger project
you will have a full-fledged website with lots of examples and so on. So it depends on
practically speaking how much time you have to spend on this and you want of course to spend
time actually writing your code as well and not just documentation so there is a balance there.
In most projects, just a README is enough, because most projects are small.
And you can essentially put all the examples also just in the README if it's a really small project.
Even kind of API definitions you can put in the README
in a small project and you don't need to set up a whole Sphinx environment for it.
Okay but it is time to go for lunch break. After the lunch break we will have a section
on Jupyter notebooks. Anyone who is around do you want to do a quick outro or a quick teaser
of what's after the lunch break? Jupyter notebooks are a really useful tool for research so
Yeah, I mean, I guess many people know Jupyter in general.
Here we go over just a little bit of the basics in case anyone doesn't know.
But more important than that, we talk about how to make them a little bit more reproducible,
like some ways of sharing them, which perhaps you didn't know about.
of diffing and merging them using them with version control and so on. So
basically it will help you go from using them and a big mess to using them and a
little bit more organized and closer to regular code. So with that should we go
to lunch yep so okay we will see you later then enjoy your lunch okay thanks
bye bye
you
You
♪
file, where the code is really nice. Yeah, that's really reproducibility right here.
It's this can be a nice, really nice way of sharing supporting information that should
go along with the manuscript. So the manuscript has the has the summary. But then if I want
to verify it or to understand it, or I want to reuse it, I have all the steps here available.
a wonderful solution to share. So instead of just putting graphics, I mean images and
tables into the manuscript, it can be a nice way to put images and tables into the manuscript,
but then put all the steps into a notebook. And here we show you Jupyter notebook but maybe
if you are developing R, maybe you're using R Markdown. And that's a similar idea. So
So here's more about the idea than again, than really, it's more about the why than
the how.
Yeah.
So basically, in our studio, can you do the similar thing in our markdown?
I have never used it, but I think it's possible.
Yes.
Sorry.
I was just, I will answer one question in the, in the notes, but it's the same idea
that you can interleave code and markdown text in the same document.
And please, all the comments and questions, as usual, in the collaborative document, especially
[name] is now checking out them and can raise something out loud if we find something that
we particularly want to share in the stream also.
Scrolling onwards to the lesson material,
there's use cases and pitfalls.
So as with any tool, Jupyter is good for something,
but then not so good for some occasions.
And here we try to have some overall view
of the good stuff and then the not so good stuff.
stuff. So, the basic use case is this kind of linear workflow. And how I understand the
linear workflow is that it starts from a point and goes forward from there, not doing any
branches and so on. So, do you agree, [name]?
Exactly. It's really an excellent fit for when you have this step-by-step workflow and
at the end comes a figure, an image.
Yeah, you mentioned data analysis. So you start from reading a data in and then some
data manipulations cleaning up and then doing the plots and there you go. So that kind of
I think Jupyter is really good.
And as mentioned also, if you want to experiment and test,
it's really easy to experiment
because you can have the different versions there
next to each other and run them as you like.
And there's many, yeah.
So the service that [name] shown,
and we will later demonstrate,
it allows people to run the codes
without like installing anything, they can run it in the browser. So we will come back
to that. Yeah. And maybe if we have time, if you if it's easy for you to open up the
notes, we are getting a couple of really good questions. Yeah. And I want to encourage more.
So at the bottom, there are two that we can briefly discuss now one is how does it work
with privacy and sensitive data. And what we what we will later show is that it can
be a good idea to put your notebook onto GitHub and make it runnable for everybody and make
that part of your paper. But now how about privacy and sensitive data? So what can you
do there? I mean, you don't want to put the actual sensitive data then on GitHub and make
it publicly visible.
Yeah, never a good idea to put sensitive data in GitHub. But like, I would like to start
from the fact that Jupyter runs, if you want to do locally, you can run Jupyter locally
on your computer, so you don't have to share anything anywhere if you don't want to.
And then considering GitHub and sharing and reusability, you can share your code, but
But not the data.
And I think that's the case, regardless of the tool that you are using to write the code.
But it's still nice to share some data so that people can actually run it.
But then you don't have to share the actual sensitive data.
You can show you can share an example data set with John Doe, Jane Doe, example person.
And so that people can still verify this is working, they can still replace it by the
actual data.
But then the sensitive data can be then protected on a dedicated server.
So that can be a good solution.
Similar solution is if your data is big, gigantic, but if you have terabytes of data and it's
difficult for you to share it, it can still be nice to share a small example data set
so then people can still run your notebook, but then replace it by the real gigantic data.
How about kit and notebooks?
I just want to say that we will come back to that.
Yeah.
In before, in the next half an hour, we will show you what are some of the challenges when
working with Git.
Because we still want to work with Git, we still didn't forget what we thought last week.
We want to use Git.
But there are some challenges, but we will show you that there are really nice solutions
to to use all the tools from last week to in combination with notebooks.
So we will get there.
And keep the questions coming.
This is wonderful.
Yeah.
And there's an upcoming question about the privacy in Google Colab.
So I think in there, it's the question of Google's privacy and should refer to the privacy
statement of the Google Colab service.
Yes.
And if I would run them the notebook with sensitive data, I would run it on the infrastructure
made for it.
And maybe that's my own computer.
Yeah.
You can run also JupyterLab in many HPC clusters, so then the data can be in your cluster, but
you can still use Jupyter if that's what you like for your workflow.
Some of the pitfalls in Jupyter, especially when there's this non-linear code flow.
Would you like to elaborate on that a little bit right away.
So if it starts to, if you have, if you write a program that has lots of modules, and it's
not first we do this, then we do this, then we do that, then we do the other thing.
But sometimes you have a code that maybe we go in here into this module, or maybe not
maybe into the other module, then it, it doesn't really fit into a notebook.
Your notebook is really like a recipe of do these series of steps.
If it doesn't fit into a series of steps, then maybe notebook is not the right thing.
But you can use modules also in Jupyter.
You can so the and we will get back to that tomorrow, we will actually show how to do it.
So you can if you have reusable code blocks, and you realize that while I'm using the same
code block in all of my notebooks, and I'm tired of copy pasting it.
You can put these into module and you can include modules in a notebook, but it should
be this series of steps.
If it's a series of steps, then yes, yeah.
And mention some good practices, Jupyter, the basic Jupyter usually renames that you
use is the default naming of untitled.
So when you start a new notebook, it's a good idea to always have your own name so that
you later know what the notebook is about.
And also run all cells before saving.
I think that's something that we can show in the example later.
Yeah, let's demonstrate the good practices.
Yes.
So the notebook interface and how to actually start the whole JupyterLab.
So I will go into a terminal here and get it started.
Let's see where I am.
And typically, so we everybody else than Matias, we should watch and ask, but I just wanted
to comment here that typically we want to start the notebook, you are often inside some
environment.
So now we are in inside a software environment.
And often you have a specific environment for each of your projects.
This is something that we have recommended yesterday.
And in there, we will now start up a notebook and the notebook will then open up.
we start it, but then we, we interact with it through the browser.
Yes. So as mentioned in the material, I create a new folder and I go there and then it says
I have to launch the JupyterLab. But first I need the Codefinery Conda environment, right?
Yes, so here you activate your programming environment that we have set up with all the
dependencies that we need.
For this example, if people later want to try it on their own, like you can, you can
create an environment that is looks exactly like ours.
And in this you can run this around the JupyterLab.
Is it the JupyterLab with minus in or is it JupyterSpaceLab?
work actually, with or without the minus.
And I wanted to mention that you actually can, if you don't want to mess up with Code
Refinery and Conda environment stuff, you might be unsure how the Conda works or something.
We encourage you to try and ask for help if needed, but if you don't want to, there is
also a version of JupyterLab as a desktop app. I'm not sure which platforms
it supports but that exists at least. So here now I'm launching the JupyterLab
in the terminal. I'm using this no browser option because I want to
decide where in which browser I open it. There's a lot of text coming up but we
We don't want, we don't need to care about that.
Only thing we do is we copy paste this URL in the end.
So if you would, if you would have left out this no browser, it would open up your default
browser somewhere.
But if you want to have more control of which browser it is, I also do the same thing as
you.
I take it into my browser, then I decide where this is opened.
So I copy-paste this to a browser into URL field and it opens.
So now the...
Actually let's go to see how this Jupyter is structured.
So in the core there's this kernel and notebook server and they are now running in the terminal
here.
And then the browser is what shows you the user interface, and then you can happily use
it.
So now we have the user interface in the browser, and now we should go to see what's around
the Jupyter interface, right?
So in the material there's this screenshot that you can refer to whenever you want to
if you forget something.
Is it easy for you to zoom in a little bit?
Yes, I think so.
Yeah, great, thanks.
So we have this toolbar containing some tabs.
Then there's some buttons, some menus and the file view in the right side.
So the toolbar contains the file explorer and open kernels and the git integration and
this works if you have used the CodeRefinery Conda environment because this is an extension
and it's there installed.
why we recommend trying the CodeRefinery Conda environment and other extensions in here.
But we focus on the file browser and later on in the Git extension.
So now what we do, we create a new Jupyter Notebook and the launcher in here is the place
to go.
The first option is Notebook.
There are other options.
You can open a terminal or text file or markdown file here if you want to.
But as we are in Jupyter, let's go with the Notebook option.
I'm going to zoom out just a little bit.
And as I mentioned, it creates a new file and it's untitled.
So what I do first is rename the file, right?
Is there questions or something?
Should I just go on?
All is good.
Yep, great.
So now in the Jupyter notebook file, there are different types of cells.
I can create more cells and I can delete cells.
I can reorganize cells and this is obviously some keyboards or how it looks very fast.
Yes.
And I can say that the way I do it often is that I click on these symbols.
Also, if you move the mouse over the cell,
there is a symbol like I want one more cell above or below.
Yes.
Just quickly mentioned that I'm gonna explain
from the material, I'm gonna explain these cells,
but afterwards there is the list of keyboard shortcuts.
And as with any tool,
if you want to use a tool quickly and effectively,
I really recommend to learn the shortcuts it applies to any any tool basically
Everything is of course like credible mentioned it's it's all here you can
Yeah I meant the symbols in the cell like if you yeah this you know the third cell from
the top and then the symbols to the right there I use those
Yeah, so you can reorder.
You can add cells below, above and delete cells.
Yeah, I use the keyboard shortcuts.
There's a A for,
actually it shows the keyboard shortcuts in here.
So you can hover your mouse and start to learn.
Nice, I didn't know, okay.
That's right, that's a handy one.
So they are different.
Now, these are all code cells.
I'm gonna remove all but two.
And what would be the first cell
if you start a new notebook?
Would you start with the code cell?
In reality, yes, but later,
I would like to have a title there,
but maybe I will come up with the title later,
but let's start with the title.
Yeah.
So here's a small menu that you can open and see all the different types of cells that
you can have.
Usually I use Markdown and of course Code4Code, but then there are certain cases you might
want to use raw, that means it shows you the raw text, nothing fancy there.
But we want the fancy thing, so let's go with Markdown.
And the point there is that it renders nicely, so it looks fancier than just the plain text.
How did I get it to render?
I use this run command, and it tells you that shift enter is the shortcut there.
This is now the start of my cool coding project, and then I can start the coding stuff.
What should I import there?
Sounds good. Yeah. Right. So there are markdown cells and there's code cells. What else you
can put in the markdown cells than just text?
I'm wondering whether we should follow the example that we have there, just that people
can recreate it step by step or? I just found and copied the Markdown cell from
that lesson material and now if I run this one we can see different options so
there's headings, there's links, there's different formatting for the text and
even equations and images. So this is really nice and the equations work as
everything that's in between these dollar signs is an equation and the
syntax is the LaTeX syntax.
Okay, so some of the shortcuts and navigation.
If you double click the cell you go to the edit mode
or you can go with Enter and Esc keys to the edit mode and back.
you can with arrow keys like from here from the edit mode I run or click ESC
and then I can with arrow keys navigate the cells back and forth.
And let's not forget to save.
Okay. I think we go forward. Is there any questions?
All is good. So just to summarize, we, you, you have often two, two ways to create cells.
It can be a code for it, for example, Python, and it can be a markdown cell and markdown.
we have discussed earlier today markdown is what we see in the in the notes document and
then you can do more you can do equations and images and then we will build up notebooks
by putting code and documentation and try to tell a story so what's the example that
we will show next. Yes. Go next. And there's the first computational notebook example.
And you mentioned the magic word story. So one of the benefits is there that you can
have this narrative around the code. And that makes it easier to understand for people that
are new to your code.
So in this example, we are creating this code that calculates pi, the value of pi with this
statistical method.
And scrolling onward, we first launch the JupyterLab.
That's what we have here already.
I'm going to hide those first cells that I can get a clean slate.
We can also start a new notebook even inside, isn't it?
Yeah, that's even better.
So here's this plus button and we get the launcher back and new notebook.
And again, it's untitled.
rename it. And here again we are, this is demo only, [name] will type and we will
check that there are no typos. Yes. And everybody please ask questions. So if you
don't remember anymore how I did open the Jupyter in a browser that I wanted
it. Here's the command in this demo.
And I think now your goal will be to scroll down to the first point and we will build
up an example notebook by following these points 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8. And if people
later want to try it out on their own, you can, you find everything here.
So first I copy-paste, it says that add it to a markdown cell, so I copy this line here,
go to my JupyterLab and I'm using the shortcut M to create this, to change this cell to be
a markdown cell.
Of course I can use the option menu here as well.
I click into the cell and Command V, I'm using Mac, so Command V or Control V to paste.
Then we go to see what else is there.
So all the cells that are needed to create this demo, they are included in here.
So what you basically can do is to copy paste the cells.
be careful that you use the appropriate cell types. So what happens if I use a code cell for this?
At first it looks not so great. And if I try to run it, it does not run because that's not
a code syntax. So that's why... Yeah, it's not Python. It will try to interpret
that's this with Python and Python is then confused.
Yes, and then it's again Markdown cell.
Oh, there's a cool picture.
So this is now a conceptual explanation
on the method that we're gonna use on this Pi calculation.
Again, now this, I took this one, so fourth one.
Now this is the first code cell, which is there.
So it imports the modules that we need.
That's why we don't see an output for this code cell
because there's no output.
It just imports the libraries that we want to.
I will continue copy pasting the cells.
The point here is not to understand this code or the Python syntax,
but to figure out why this Jupyter Notebook is
then a nice way of structuring the code or
a nice tool to use for this kind of code exercise.
So now these are the all the cells if I didn't miss any in between and we got
these plots and they are visualized in here like right after the code cell and
then there's also the final result here outputted so oh well it's quite close to
the actual pi value.
Yeah, and the big picture here,
like don't worry if all the steps are not clear.
This is, it's a certain approximate way
to compute the number pi.
Here, the big picture, what is really important
for all of us is that we have documentation and code
and images in a notebook and the computation,
it's a series of computations.
So something that we will try later is,
what if we run them in the wrong order?
And what does it mean for us?
What does it mean for our like good practices
of how we should use notebooks?
Yes, and an example of this documentation in between,
I could add here, for example,
a subtitle that start plotting,
I'll start and more explanations, of course, if I have any.
So going onward from the lesson material, it mentions that there's possibility to use
other languages.
So there's R Markdown for R and Pluto for Julia.
So the workflow there is similar to the JupyterLab.
So we hope that even if you want to use R,
you still get the idea of this workflow from this lesson.
Did we show how to run things in the wrong order?
I was just a little bit distracted
here answering questions.
Right.
So what I... I can do it now. So what I do is, let's say I want to start over the whole
calculation. Now the values of all the variables and everything, the code has run,
the variables are there. So what I do first, I want to demonstrate what if I want to start over.
I go here and restart the kernel and it says that all variables will be lost
which is okay because I want to start over and now I will go and run the
cells one by one with this shift enter but let's say let's say I forget this
one I grab a cup of coffee and I forget this cell and I continue running from
here now I get some error message and what should I get from this error
message yeah now the notebook doesn't know the variable points has never been
defined it doesn't know what the value is because we never ran the cell so two
two cells up, three cells up.
We sort of sell them before.
All right.
What's next?
Actually now, just a new question.
Is there a search function in here?
What if I don't find this name points in anywhere?
Can I do some searching?
I normally, so maybe there's a clever way.
What I do is I use the browser search.
Yeah, okay.
for these kinds of situations.
Actually, now that I press command F,
it actually opens the search inside here.
So maybe there is, let's see, points.
Okay.
Now I can see that this matches to the one in error message.
So I run this one.
Now I run the erroneous cell again.
Now it works.
So if I run the cells,
So often when we develop it try things out and then improve and you develop you
often you when developing you don't run everything every single time you run the
cell until it works and you go somewhere else you try something else but
what can then happen is that we can get into a situation where you think
everything is working but then you give it to the next person or you come to it
in a week and suddenly it doesn't work anymore because what what the next
person will do the first thing that the next person will do is they will run
everything from top to bottom. And so the good practice and the good recommendation is to run
everything from top to bottom before you save it and before you share it with other people
to make sure that this is working because this is the first thing they will do.
Yeah. And in addition, I would also restart kernel and run all cells because then you might
have saved some variable value somewhere in different sections and it remembers the last
saved value. So if you restart, you kind of make sure that your code works from top to the bottom.
Yeah. Should we talk about Git or version control and notebooks?
Definitely. Before we go into the break. Yeah. Going to the next part in the lesson. Notebooks
and version control. And this is still a demo demonstration. And let me know if there's any
questions in or such questions that you should address here.
So there are tools to do version control on this Jupyter files.
Underlying format there with the Jupyter files is this JSON.
So if you only use the basic git diff tool, it may look much more complex than your original
code and then your face goes like.
So there are tools to make that easier and which one of these we have in this conda environment
here?
JupyterLab, Git and mbdime.
Checking.
Yeah.
So the mbdime we definitely have.
We have, I think you have some of the Git extensions.
I'm just verifying here.
Yeah.
We have, we have JupyterLab Git.
We have mbdime in there.
I think the GitHub web interface nowadays
can also render the Jupyter.
Yeah, and maybe this is something we can show,
but this is something you need to enable.
So there are these three steps there.
Okay, so let's first go in JupyterLab interface.
So yeah, this is what it would look like
without those tools.
This is a difference of an image that has been edited.
It's pretty horrible,
unless you like the underlying format of a PNG picture.
But going forward and using these RichDiff tools,
we can actually see how the picture was previously
and how it's in the new edited version.
So let's see if we can do it in here.
What I need to do first is to initialize the repository.
So we are in the folder that I have this Jupyter Notebook
files.
And I can create a Git repository out of that folder
without leaving this Jupyter Notebook, which is kind of cool.
So I click Initialize Repository.
So now this folder is a git repository.
It shows that there's untracked files.
So why there's four files untracked,
although I have only two files in here?
And what should I do with this?
Let's see.
And these look like the original two notebooks that I created.
And these are some checkpoint files.
So what should I do with the checkpoint files?
So the checkpoints, I think they are directories, maybe checkpoint files, but these are often
things that I ignore.
I get ignore.
I add them to my git ignore, because they are, I see them as temporary local files that
I don't want to have in my git repository.
Okay.
So I right click and ignore that file.
And it tells me that git ignore does not exist,
but actually it just creates one.
And then I can track all the files
and make my first commit.
And now this is only going to the local folder.
So, I run the JupyterLab in a local folder, I created the git repository that's again
in a local folder.
Later on, I can upload the folder in GitHub if I want to.
Now there's the first initial commit done, so there's the snapshot of these notebooks
as they are now.
Now let's change something.
Okay, let's then verify what we will see.
For instance, you can change the size of the figure.
So somewhere there is this figure set size inches,
because maybe make it larger, smaller.
I'm scrolling to the lowest cell with the, yeah.
Or change the colors or something like that.
Yeah, I would love to change the colors,
but I don't remember how it's done.
Let's start with the size.
Yeah, let's go with the size.
Now it's smaller, this one.
So basically, it still renders the output
as a regular size, but I think this went bigger
so it's actually, the actual image is smaller.
So now if I would print out or save it to a file it would be smaller in size.
Now I save and let's see.
Now the Git extension shows, yeah there's some changes.
So before I commit the changes I want to show what has been edited.
So I click this small icon that says Diff and now this is how this Git, Jupyter Git tool
shows the difference.
So here's the code that I changed, the lines and the output.
So this is the old one and here's the new one.
everything with red is the old one everything is with green is the new one and that's that's good
and this works because we use this nbdime extension which is notebook diff and merge
and which helps us to really easily see what was before what was after if we used if you
try this with a notebook or with a jupyter lab without this extension we might see a difference
in the underlying source code.
Can we, so long story short, we recommend to use this extension.
And also on GitHub, we recommend to enable that extension so that you can see nice differences.
What is your question?
Yes.
I mean, I just click the show source button and this is the horror lying in inside.
Yeah, I really prefer the nice render here.
Yeah.
Great.
And if you want to try it out on GitHub, we have done on our lesson, we have, we have some
steps on what you need to do.
So it's a, you need to go on preview features, enable this rich Jupiter preview, I forgot
the name.
So I now wait, but I'm on GitHub, and then some settings.
So on yours, yes, on your picture there, and then you go on feature preview.
Nice.
Yes. And then on the left side, there is rich Jupyter Notebook diffs. I think you have it
enabled.
Yes, I have it enabled. So this is basically the same similar looking feature exists in
GitHub, which is really nice.
And then if you go back to the lesson, we have an example. So if you click on scroll a little
bit up, up, yes, there is this sentence that will be down. So on the bottom of your screen,
You can click on that link.
It's actually a diff.
It's a comparison between two versions.
And you can all try to open it up.
If you don't have that enable extension enabled, it will look not very understandable.
But with that extension enabled, we can see what was before what came after.
Okay, great.
I guess now we are up to a break, right?
Yes, we got a couple of interesting questions, but I, I will take the questions.
Let's take them after the break.
So after the break, what we should discuss, like, what are the advantages of notebook
versus script, or script versus VS code VS code versus notebook.
So that's for after the break.
I will add here.
So info box.
So when should we be back?
Is it sharp?
Let's be precise here.
Zero one.
Okay, great.
Thank you.
And then we'll do more Jupyter.
See you soon.
See you.
you
Welcome
Welcome back from the break. We continue with the Jupyter notebooks and a big topic for
the last half hour or so is the sharing notebooks. But how about if you share the notebook to
someone who does not use JupyterLab but instead wants to use Visual Studio Code. And for that
I wanted to show you how it looks like.
This is the same folder that we used in the previous examples,
and there we created the Jupyter Notebooks in the JupyterLab.
Now, the same folder opened in Visual Studio Code.
I can see that here's actually
the same notebook that I created as an example there's the same plots and
everything showing up oh this is smaller because we created it smaller so they
open up just nicely did you have to install anything other than VS code I'm
gonna check my extensions. So yes, there is a Jupyter extension installed in, but it's,
you can find it in the Visual Studio code and extensions and search for Jupyter. Yeah.
And you personally, if you like write a notebook, do you write it in VS code or do you write
it in a browser? I really like the JupyterLab interface and the looks. I don't know why,
but I prefer this one. How about you? Yeah, me too. I use the browser for notebooks. Yeah.
I use Visual Studio Code for a bunch of other stuff, but yeah, both work, which is nice.
So then to the sharing of the notebooks, there's many different ways to share and actually
too many.
Which one of these you have actually used?
I mean, they obviously both are all useful, but which one you have used?
So one, one thing that I'm even sure we listed this one step is to put it on places like
GitHub.
Yeah, so there's one way one way to share it and somebody else can view it there.
It's static because it will it actually you can only see the image of it, you cannot go
in and change it.
But we will also show you a way where you can share it in a way that people can really
run it and change it.
So which one I've used GitHub, I have used binder. I have also experimented a little
bit with Jupyter light. I have not tried the other ones. Yeah, I think further further
down we have also some alternatives that are there are some companies behind it. So I have
Yes, I've tried to co-calc. Sorry, no, the, is that the one? No, I'm, what I meant is
the Google collab. Yeah. I have tried. Yeah, some of those. Yeah. And well, if static is
enough for you, then in JupyterLab, there's this file menu and there's this export options,
options but some of these might need some extra installation so just so that you know but this
is of course the probably the easiest way to just share the file but let's go with the
use case where the people that you want to share the file with want to also
So experiment on your notebook.
So this is a demo about that.
And the use cases you want, you want people to be able to run it without even installing
any software environment or Jupyter or JupyterLab or anything.
All they will need is a browser.
Okay.
So it says that I should create a new GitHub repository.
So let's do that.
I'm going to GitHub and this is a Jupyter Binder demo, and I will, what I will do is
I will then, once you create it, I will share the link with everybody else so that people
you can see what we did there.
So do you want to link to this repository?
Yes, but I will add it to the document.
So it's public, just a second, I need to find it.
It is this one.
So the next step for me is to add a new file.
It took me some time to find this button because now it's zoomed in so much that it's in here
but it's next to this code button, create new file.
I want to upload a new file right yep because I yes I have the notebook that I
just created in the previous example and commit message yes we always have to
write something here it's a difficult to come up with useful ones though don't
worry we are totally not judging the commit message. Yeah and committing
directly to the main branch because I know that there's can't be no one else
doing any editing yet because this is so new thing so new repository I mean. Okay
now it's there with the readme nice what would be the next step?
Next step, I need to also navigate to the right place.
There's this requirements.txt, right?
Yeah, that's a nice connection to yesterday.
This is a file.
So we need to describe the software environment that we need.
It can be either a requirements.txt file.
It can also be an environment.yaml file.
Both were mentioned yesterday in the reproducibility lesson.
And here we can list what are the libraries that we need.
And in this case, we will need the matplotlib,
which is a Python library used for plotting.
And we-
So if, how do I know that which libraries,
which things I need to list in the requirements txt?
Well, that's a good question.
If sometimes it's a bit trial and error.
So it depends a bit how you installed the dependencies
that you use in the notebook.
I like to, personally, when I install dependencies, I put them into a file like requirements.txt.
And then I install from the file, because then I don't have to remember it, I can look
into the file.
But if you don't have the file, and maybe you installed this half a year ago, and you
don't remember anymore, then I go into my notebook, and I see, I look at all the imports.
And now, yeah, this is at least a starting point here.
Yeah.
And with with some Python knowledge, you would know that random is actually not.
It's a standard library, it's part of Python.
And but botlib is an external library.
But this is now about this Python knowledge.
Right, so we don't need to take this random now, but we have to take sorry, I'm navigating
back to the GitHub, we have to mention matplotlib and the version.
If we don't, if we leave out the version, we will get the latest one, okay, which will
still work today.
But the question is, will the notebook then still run in five years.
So depending on what your use case is, you might want to put the version there or not.
If we forget to put something into the requirements of text, we will notice it.
Because this is now this will run as an isolated thing.
And if there are dependencies missing, we will notice.
So sometimes I do like I add something, I run it, something missing, okay, I add something
more until it works.
Yeah.
So the next step shown in the lesson material is to go to my binder.org.
And this is just a web page, right?
How does this help our cause?
Here it will help that once we have the repository, there is this GitHub field where you can put
a GitHub repository address.
And if people want to try it out later, you can notice that it doesn't have to be GitHub.
The notebook can be on other places.
Let's see.
GitLab or it can be on Zenodo or some other places where you can deposit a notebook and
even get a digital object identifier for a notebook.
So that would be even better than putting it only on GitHub.
But here we want to show how to do it when your notebook is on GitHub.
So you take the address.
So can I just use the URL the URL from the URL field
without the tree without the main yeah like this so that will hopefully work
notice that on the left side it says head it will take the
it will actually take the main sorry the main branch the default branch you could point
it to another branch or attack if you have that.
Yeah. Do I need this path to notebook file? And it says optional. So I guess no.
And you don't even have to launch it. You can. What we can do is there is this one.
What you can do is just below the line below there is the launch partner batch and right
of it is the little arrow, click on that little arrow. And now there is a markdown version
and RSD version. What you can do is you can copy that markdown badge. Yeah, because that
will form a nice link to documentation lesson and let's put it into our readme. Okay, so
I copy this one and go to my repository and to the readme file. And I want to edit it
it now. And maybe you can zoom in a little bit. Let me see. Yeah. So I copy pasted this
markdown tag in here. So it's an address to a web server and this web server, which is
which will be running on my binder.org.
It will be generated on the fly.
On the fly, it will create, hopefully, let's see.
It will create a container for us.
It will install the dependencies into it,
the dependencies which we have described
in requirements.txt.
And in this container, it will run the notebook, hopefully.
Yeah, so now I have this party started.
And now it's a cool looking tag in my readme and it didn't cost anything.
So I click the tag and now it took me here.
So it's loading up and while it's loading up it's showing me this static version of
files. Can I actually click here? Okay, click on it, but it only gives you a static preview
because now, yeah, now it's installing the dependencies and why it's installing. If we
are impatient, it will, it at least wants to give us like the preview of how it will
look. Yeah, it's nice to see at least like, is this what I'm looking for? I mean, if I
realize here that no this is not that this is not the droids we are looking for no the
tributor lab that we are looking for then maybe I go away but now I see that this is
exactly what I want to see so I shall be waiting for the actual binder container to start yeah
and it's the first time we do that it can take seconds minutes once it is has been set
up it's faster to to run and this is normally not not a problem because this is really for
now we imagine that we are the person reading the publication and now we want to reproduce
the steps and I don't mind waiting waiting three minutes for this thing to start for
me yeah in the meantime what we can do while this is spinning up we can have a look at
the questions and discuss some of them.
Yes.
Let's open up the notes.
There are some more detailed question,
like one more bigger picture question was,
of what is the advantage of like,
when should I use a notebook?
When should I use VS code?
When should I use Python scripts?
And it one answer that we gave is that it's also a bit personal preference.
It's we show you different tools and you can choose the one that feels more comfortable
for you and for the use case.
There's a question.
Oh, yeah.
Okay.
Here's answers as well.
some funny rendering here, just comparing JupyterLab and VS Code. I think VS Code can
do about the same things. There's also the Git integration right in there, so I guess
that's all in all easier to start in VS Code. The Git is there already, I think, and you
you can add the Jupyter extension.
So maybe there's less overall installation thing,
maybe less hustling in the terminal
if you want to avoid that for some reason, like me.
So it's a question of what people prefer.
It's also a question of who do you collaborate with?
Yeah.
Is there something else?
So there are interesting questions at the bottom but I need to look it up.
So one question is that it is definitely possible that you have different environments in different
directories.
So you could imagine that if you just move out of a project and move into a different
project that it automatically switches environment.
I need to look up the details.
I know it's possible.
something called .env, .env,
but there's just one solution to this,
which will change your environment
if you go into a directory
and it will change it to something else
if you move out of it, but I need to look it up.
Yeah.
Then there is another question
which connects more to what was discussed yesterday,
like what is the best tool for managing dependencies?
I think that's hard to answer
because there are so many tools.
Maybe the two most popular ones are Conda or virtual environment, but there are really
many and, and again, it depends a bit on what you prefer, what your, what your collaborators
prefer.
Often these tools can, but the idea of isolating environments to have isolated environments
per project that's a good idea and any of these tools allow it and often you
can convert one to the other yeah like for me for example I think I've used
conda and virtual and but more more in the way that if I have instructions I
I know how to launch the virtual environment
and then I can navigate myself around the code
or run the code.
So to all those people who might be wondering
that, oh, this is all too much,
start, if you have the collaboration case,
so there's someone who created the environment,
start from trying to run the code
and launch the virtual environment and run the code,
that's already enables you to start the collaboration there.
So don't worry, although it might feel overwhelming
discussing all those different virtual environments
and tools for that.
Okay.
So in the context of Binder, it's often a requirements.txt or environment.yaml.
How are we doing there?
Is it still in the process of?
So if you, if you go to that link again from your readme, does it resolve?
I think I've lost my...
Did we not commit it?
Because I can also, you have committed it, what people can do, I can also start it on
my side.
No, I mean, I just lost my tabs.
Yeah.
But lucky you put this in in there.
Oh, yeah.
So you can start it from there.
And I started it on my side, people can try to but let's not, let's see whether it's overwhelms
binder.
So on my on my computer, it started up.
So it will also soon do it on yours here is now we see the planets orbiting.
So the moons are orbiting Jupiter and there it is.
So this is now not running on Matias computer.
It's on somewhere in the cloud accessible through the browser, you can try to visit
it too.
And you can try to run the notebook that we just created.
And you can even go in and change it.
So what if I change it? Does it save and where?
No it's so if you change it and then leave it at some point this this container will vaporize.
So I can basically I can mess up everything here in this environment if I want to and
so you can original is there. Yeah.
If you wanted to change it and keep the changes you would have to save them so you can you
you can take the notebook and save it onto your computer. So that will be the way to
preserve them. But here we can all experiment. I mean, go in and try to modify some numbers,
try to run it. And we have a we have a dynamic notebook. And if we know we could go one step
further and get a do I for it, and which we will not do but but then we are sure that
this thing will be available the next 10 years.
And if we are careful about dependencies
and about documenting dependencies with versions,
we can be reasonably sure
that this thing will still run in 10 years.
Pretty cool.
Right, so I made some edits. I wanted to see how close this statistic result was, so I
compared that result to the actual Pi provided by NumPy library and well it's in two decimals.
Quite okay.
Yeah, this is very cool. Binder is a wonderful service. It is non-profit. There are different
services that do similar things some of them are non-profit some of them are
for-profit here we wanted to show you a really nice service that is there's a
lot of good for community and is a non-profit one yeah there are some
optional exercises about tracking the dependencies which we also discussed a
a little bit what to put in the requirements and TXT
and how to find them.
And then there's an optional exercise
about sharing an interactive notebook.
So what does the interactive mean in this case?
This means, and it will connect to somebody ask a question
of how can you have interactive images?
I mean, interactive graphics in a notebook.
And this is one way of doing that or doing it.
So you can have a slider for instance,
that you can slide from left to right
and then you can make it change values
and then you can define it
so that images automatically adapt to it.
There are many ways to implement this,
but here we show you one.
Yeah, so I really encourage you to go to see the,
like optional exercises that there's a quite a lot of nice material also some
new things for me also I guess one that I actually would like to advertise here
now is this shell commands magic and widgets so there are some extra features
in Jupyter, you can ask it for help about some object, so if you don't know what this
np.sum() does, you can add a question mark there and apparently it will tell you.
Scrolling a little bit down, you can run shell or terminal commands in Jupyter by adding
this exclamation mark. That can be really nice for example in a case that you want to
know in which folder you are in. Now this is probably going to look curious because
it's in the binder container, but anyhow.
And then, oh, there's some magic.
I think I have never tried this.
And then the widgets that we mentioned that you can add more interactive elements in the
JupyterLab. Yeah, do we go to the summary?
Let's do that. And also, a reminder to everybody else, on the bottom of the notes, I have pasted
requests for feedback. Please let us know how today went. There are also some questions
that we can discuss in voice, but I don't know if you wanted to share some summary slide
or say a few words, [name].
Yeah, in the lesson material,
there's this nice summary, more links
and blog posts and articles.
And then also, again, mentioned these other tools
for other languages than Python.
And like a reminder on the thing
that we already also mentioned
that when you start with the JupyterLab or Jupyter notebook,
you start experimenting and develop more and more.
At some point you have a really long notebook,
but then it starts to grow.
So the one good practice was to,
every time before you save and share,
restart kernel, run all cells
to see that your notebook actually runs in order and there's no errors and then
also try to organize it and use the subtitles or headlines headings to keep
the notebook in order so that it's easy also for you after one year to
get back to it.
Yeah.
You mentioned some questions.
Is there still something that you would like to raise?
So we can, that was commented.
Tomorrow we will connect to this.
We will, when we discuss modular code development,
we will actually tomorrow start in a notebook
and we will then experience a moment
when maybe it feels like, you know, uncomfortable
and it feels like we want to move out of notebook.
So we will see that, we will see a situation
and the situation will be once we start adding tests,
that, so we will start in notebook
and maybe move out into scripts.
We will also tomorrow talk about automated testing.
So two really exciting lessons coming up.
We hope to see you all tomorrow again.
And thanks a lot for giving feedback below.
Tell us one thing that you liked about today.
Tell us also one thing that we should change or remove.
Yeah, I think we've been changing at least something in in every time we have this workshop,
right?
Yes, because this the topics they are evolving, so we need to evolve with them.
And this is this goes more about the content but it also goes it's also about the forum
and how we present it.
Yeah.
So thank you for this lesson.
Thank you for following and thank you for the feedback.
Keep it coming.
And thank you for having me here.
Yeah.
Thanks, [name].
Always pleasure.
of music. Sure.
you