CodeRefinery.org
you
Test one, two, can anyone hear us out there?
I probably need to be louder.
someone else say something good morning everyone okay morning yeah I guess maybe
we're sort of balanced
okay so hello everyone it's our last day is anyone else excited
Sad that it's over.
I will be happy to get my days back.
But I mean, yeah, also sad that it's over.
So anyway.
It has been a nice constant, being here every morning, but before 10.
So we need to do an audio test, and when processing the videos for yesterday, I realized the audio
wasn't quite as balanced as I would have liked.
So how should we do audio tests better?
Someone once said we should say something more in-depth than 1-1-1-2-2-2-3-3-3.
So any ideas?
And someone has reminded me, today is not completely the last day of Code Refinery.
It's the last day of streaming, but the teaching continues with the Bring Your Own Code sessions,
where you can, well, bring your stuff and you ask us questions and we look live at things
and give advice.
So from these icebreakers, what's the worst bug you've seen or experienced?
So anyone want to go first?
The ones that are resolved by restarting your computer.
The ones that you cannot pinpoint why they happen.
They just happen and then they are not there anymore.
And then you're like, okay, is this fine?
So I wrote down my answer, but it was a memory issue in the C code, which is always.
very hard to figure out.
But also at that time, I was not using either version control or tests, so just I was working
on something for a day and something else broke and I have no idea what's going on.
At least with C, I think that's a relatively common experience.
I had something similar once, and the only way I fixed it was by running the code in
a loop a thousand times, which would some sort of reliably cause an error message when
quitting, and then commenting out half my code until I could narrow it down to one
line.
I'm sure there's better ways, but that was what I knew how to do at the time.
Yeah, unfortunately, this was a problem where the code runs from the beginning to the end
and produces incorrect results, but also in a statistical way.
So you have to run it a bunch of times before you can notice that it's slightly off.
It really was the worst kind of problem.
Yeah.
So my worst bugs, or you could say maybe what's been worst to solve, has been things like
I'm editing some code, but that code isn't even running because the bug is somewhere
else.
Like once I made a, was it debugging or testing tutorial or something, and I had the same
code in my same code was in the file twice the same function was defined twice and people were
editing the first one and towards the second definition took precedence and it wasn't even
running and yeah there's another one um that i think is kind of a good lead-in
for today's topics. So this was that I wrote a measurement for a high-performance computing
program that we were spending millions of hours to run, like hundreds of thousands of euros worth
of computing time. And I wrote a measurement that calculates A, B, and C, and then it should
add A, B, and C together and print the result. I added B and C together and printed the result
instead and never printed A anywhere in the program. That wasted some time.
It's also one of those things that no matter how well you test A, it's not going to help.
Properly testing the program before starting to run it would have been
and very helpful.
Yeah.
So, how do you make sure your code continues to work
when collaborating with others?
Like, if it works one day, how does it work tomorrow?
Have you ever had these kind of bugs where something worked, it was nicely tested, but then it got changed and broke, and then everything...
I guess that memory issue in C is one of these things, you can easily break something in
a completely different place of the code.
also just manually running it and printing some variables values brings me quite far.
And I guess that's quite often the starting point of testing,
manually looking at prints. I guess as a spoiler alert, we're going to talk about exactly this
kind of stuff today, and you'll see what we tend to do these days because it's best practice.
So I didn't see a good suggestion for what to say. Someone suggested
Sally Scripps' sleek software solution swiftly, but we need something quick and easy to say,
not that we're gonna trip us up. What if we say fair software? So me, [name], [name],
I'll repeat fair software. Fair software. Fair software. Fair software. Fair software. Fair
software. Fair software. Okay, is it balanced? To me, [name] might have been a little bit louder
than [name].
But I'm only here for a very short time, so it's better that you are balanced.
But it's 10.
Should we start with Jingle?
Yeah.
Okay.
Let's go.
Hello.
Welcome.
Hello. Welcome. And we have [name] for the introduction.
Already here. Okay. Yeah. Hello. And very welcome to this last day of streaming of the Code Refinery workshop.
So we are in the last day of the teaching sessions of this workshop,
and yesterday we looked at documentation and Jupyter and saw some demos.
Today, this goes on and it basically wraps everything up.
So everything comes together again in today's sessions.
Now in the morning, we have a session about automated testing.
So really putting all the Git and GitHub things together,
and implement tests that can check
your code when you are collaborating with others or working by yourself.
Then in the afternoon,
we will have a session on modular code development,
which is a live coding session where we take a code that is right now
in Jupyter and plot something,
and then show live how to make this more modular
so that it can be more easily reused
by you and others in the future.
And this is highly interactive,
so we are kind of dependent a little bit on you there
to give us hints in what to do with the codes
in the collaborative document,
and I'll show in a moment how to do that.
But also, please stay until the end because we will tell you a little bit about what can
come after this Code Refinery workshop and also talk a little bit more about our Bring
Your Own Code sessions, which you might have seen in the schedule already for next week
and the week after, Tuesday afternoon.
So if you're new here, if you're joining us today for the first time, this is a live-streamed
workshop so everyone will watch the live stream here on Twitch and then you can interact with
the instructors and with some people behind the scenes also via our collaborative document.
For that you need to register to this workshop via the Code Refinery web page and then you will
get the link to this document which looks something like this. So here we have some
information for you where you can find all the questions and answers, the workshop web page,
the schedule and the link to the lesson materials and then we also have some icebreaker question
for this morning and the way you can add your answers there is to find this little pen symbol
which might be here or somewhere to the right depending on how you're looking at this page.
So you click the pen symbol,
you switch into edit mode,
and then you can scroll down here to the questions,
what's the worst bug you have seen or experienced,
and then find these little three dot lines
here and add your own answer to the question,
and the same for the next ones that we have here.
And then we will have titles here about each section and underneath here you can ask your question.
Is this the place to ask questions? And then hopefully someone will answer. Yes, there's someone answering.
And we will provide these documents after the course. You can find them on the course web page.
course webpage so you can go back and see what have others asked, what may help
your understanding. We'll also have breaks about 10 minutes every hour and
all the lesson materials that you might see during this day are available and
linked from the workshop page and they will also be available afterwards and
And you can also reuse them to do your own workshops, for example.
The recordings will stay online on Twitch for some days, and then they will also be
available approximately tomorrow or today on the YouTube channel.
If you're interested in certificates, you can find instructions on that also on the
workshop page.
Maybe I can show that briefly.
there's up here this certificates tab where you can find this and all the materials are linked here
behind the schedule. And then yeah the bring your own code sessions we'll talk about
a little bit about this more in the end of today. And now over to our instructors for today
[name] and [name]. Great, thanks [name].
Okay, I will take over the screen share.
I'm also showing the same document. Okay.
Okay, here we go.
Okay, good. And does that look correct? It does.
Yes. Good. Okay, so let's get back. So we already
talked a bit with the icebreakers and people can read those but yeah so where do we start so we
are first lesson is automated testing yeah so um yeah let's get down to it so um or first uh
before you learned automated testing. Can we share the lesson? Yes, we can. So,
the link is in the notes and also in the schedule, and here we go.
Yeah, and I guess this title show is exactly what our icebreakers were asking,
preventing yourself and others from breaking functional code.
So, yeah, so what's the way you do this, like, without automated testing?
What were you doing before you learned and what are people probably doing before learning
about this?
Yeah.
Can we go to motivation, maybe?
I guess.
The first motivation lesson has some...
So yeah, and this first point, if you've ever been an experimental scientist, you probably
know that calibrating your instruments is an important thing you do.
So you have to get there, and anytime you have some microscope or measurement thing,
You run it with a known sample to see if it gives the value you expect.
And we see a quote here that says the same thing should apply to software.
If you haven't done some sort of test to see if it works, then are you really doing science
Or are you just making some hopes or whatever?
So this would be something like checking
that you can reproduce known results.
And essentially, every time you change something,
move the thing around, or just come
into the lab in the morning doing some basic checks
that everything is OK.
So let's give an example, if we scroll down.
So when you're programming, you might have some function.
So here, can the font be made a little bit larger?
Yes.
Okay, that's hopefully good, yeah.
So what do we see here?
Yeah.
So this is Python, there's other examples here, but yeah.
that converts from fahrenheit to celsius which is pretty easy yeah and we can look at it and we
think it works but how would you actually test it in real life like if you're making this function
and you didn't know automatic testing yeah would you so i guess i would run it with some number i
know the result for. I would run it with temperature in Fahrenheit being zero, because I know it
should return 32. Not exactly, because that's the wrong way around. I would give it 32 and
then expect zero, I guess.
Yeah. So you give it the known obvious values.
Yeah.
And since you can probably know your function is linear, if you can test two values, then
it's probably good.
this case that would be enough. But are you sure? I mean I guess it's worth
testing a few more if it's easy and also some special cases like negative
Kelvin does that give you something or null values and so on. Yeah. Integer and
floating-point inputs. But anyway so this is what we're going to see during this
lesson. And this is at the smallest most micro scale testing a single function
but you can also test much more than this. So for example down below we see a
test of a whole program. Not like that far down but just a little. Oh you mean
I mean, we don't see what it actually is, but it shows it looks like it runs with some
sample data and says this is what the output should be.
So it is telling us that it's correct, which is good.
So what else can the test help us do?
I mean, I guess in addition to telling whether it's wrong or right, it would be useful to
know where the problem is or how the test figured out that there's a problem.
Like, this just tells you that it's correct, which I guess is fine as long as it's correct.
But it would be nice to know what it checked, more nice to be reminded what was the check,
what passed.
And if it fails, where did it fail and how?
Can we scroll down a bit to see what else is in, what else it says?
So preserve functionality.
Okay, so that means if it works, it keeps working.
Help users.
So basically, actually this happens often on our computer cluster.
We install some software for a user and we wonder, did the installation work correctly?
If we, the admins, can run a test suite and it says it works, then we have some reasonable
confidence that we didn't completely break the installation.
Help other developers modify it.
What does that mean?
Well, if you're changing something, you can be confident that you didn't break anything.
It also kind of helps with documentation.
It tells you what should work and how it should behave.
Yeah, like for example, if I'm modifying someone else's code and there's tests, then I can run
those tests, and if they pass, then, like, if it's someone else's code, I usually don't
know how the whole thing works. But I might know enough to change just a little bit of
it. But I don't know how my section relates to all the other sections of the code.
So having these tests is really useful, because I can be reasonably sure that I haven't broken
something unexpected. And same for the other developer. If I say, oh, would you like this
change, then they can see if the test still works and not have to read my changes so much.
They can just look locally.
And this complexity is also a good one.
I've written some things before that are really hard to test, and eventually they become hard
to modify and maintain.
And that's just not great.
There's a good question.
Is this about testing code?
What about other things, Python?
This is a really good point.
And for example, the thing that we'll show later on,
GitHub Actions, has exact ways to do this.
You can basically install, like test installing and running
your code your package on different operating systems on different versions of the operating
system and so on yeah yeah that that's really helpful um yeah and if you want to test that
it's installed correctly in your system then hopefully you can also run the tests included
in the package. Yeah. So when's it okay to not add tests? The next section here.
Oh, we should be... I will also add this as a question to the notes. So you can ask is everything
that we do test it? And the answer is probably no. And to me it depends on how important
it is. If it's a small script that I will also always be, there will always be a human
in the loop watching it and verifying it worked, then whatever. But as soon as it gets big
enough, I'll try to have some at least sample data to show.
So often the time when it's really time to start adding tests is when you're going from
a single script or a Jupyter notebook to having some functions and having multiple files and
so on, at least for me. But of course if you have a big untested block of code in a notebook
or a script, then that's maybe not as trustworthy as it could be. And maybe that's fine.
So, what are some examples of things that are easy and hard to test in your own opinion?
Okay, let's move that also to the notes and see what people come up with.
What's hard to test is interactive things.
Something that requires a human in the loop to properly work.
Like, you can simulate a human by some predefined answers, but it's not quite the same thing.
There are also things like testing frameworks, which basically, like for web browsers and so on,
that can go and virtually click on things on a website and see if it works. But
since our audience is probably scientists and researchers, that might be getting a bit deep,
but you can bet for sure that big companies making websites and so on have these kinds of things because
Well, it's better to do it once then need a human to do it all the time
Okay, should we go
On um
There's some other advice here, but I think you'll probably see the types of tests well
You can read that yourself later, we don't really need to go.
I guess the main point there is you can test at different levels.
Like above we saw a test of a single function.
But maybe for your case it's better to get some sample data and test the whole thing.
Like an end-to-end test.
Or whatever.
Often times it's some combination.
I would try some end-to-end test, and then
test of individual functions where it's easy and the risk of breakage is high.
So, where do we start?
Yes, so let's go to the next section, but at this point I think I will move on to my empty
example folder and we can start because the next section is a demonstration.
Yes, so we are at the section testing locally.
Maybe, well, is there anything we need to show from the web browser window?
Maybe I'll show on my screen quickly.
locally. So here we are on testing locally. The link is in the notes. And we will be using
PyTest. So we'll start with some simple code, which Wiz provided to us. And we will slowly
add it to files and make some tests. And this is a really reasonable thing to do. So pytest is what,
at least my default package for testing Python code. It's really common, it's relatively easy to
use. So, yeah, it's a good start.
I actually, I cannot say that I've seen any other framework being used to test Python.
There are other frameworks and people use them, but in Python, it's essentially the only one.
I'll create a new Python file, example.py, and put some code there.
So we start with example.py.
Did you make a new directory to store this stuff?
Yes.
This should be an empty directory, but I did try running pytest to check that it exists.
So there is a pytest cache.
So we're adding example.py.
And it has, and so this is supposed to be a demo.
So you can try to follow along, but we're not giving you time and we're not going slow
enough that we think it's easy to follow.
Okay, so I have this extremely complicated mathematical function and I want to test it.
So what should I do?
So the way PyTest works is it automatically looks for functions that start with test underscore.
It also looks for modules that start with test underscore, but we don't do that yet.
So let's define a function called test add, test underscore add.
So the important thing is that it starts with test underscore, and then I guess I will write
in the function name what I'm testing, so I'm testing the add function.
Let's close the side panel.
Okay, so what does assert mean? I went a bit ahead of my house, sorry.
Assert, what does that do?
Is it self-descriptive? It might be if you speak enough English.
So assert is a Python statement which runs whatever is after it. And if it doesn't evaluate
to true, it prints an error. So PyTest uses this. It uses standard Python statements.
But if there was an assertion error, it would capture that error and then print some extra
debugging information beyond what Python would do.
So what if there's a different kind of an error?
What do you mean by different kind?
Well, I don't know. I gave some parameters that you cannot add together.
Well, I think Python would probably, or PyTest would also capture that and print it well.
Okay, so any error will, PyTest will capture any error essentially,
but assert is a nice way of producing errors when things don't work.
Okay, well let's, should we add something that evaluates to true? So if we add two and three,
that should be equal to five. No, five. Okay, what else? What else would work?
So, what else in Python should be added?
Well, there's this, we see it adds two strings together.
So, yeah, let's try that.
So, the way strings work is if you try to add with the plus operator, two words, space
and ship, and that should return space ship, so it just puts the strings together, concatenates
the strings.
Okay.
So now we have our test function, and notice the test function takes no arguments, so PyTest automatically finds it and runs it.
It has all the test data directly embedded in here, as you can see, and will print any errors it finds.
Open a terminal window.
I will need to activate the code refinery environment.
Can we split the window so we can see?
Yes.
So whoops, looking at the tests and the...
There's not a huge amount of space.
Can you split the window so it's on the bottom?
Right, that's a good idea. It should be possible. Okay.
Okay, yeah, so there's a question in the chat. What are we trying to do here?
So we have some pretend code, which is add A and B. We pretend this is our highly advanced
scientific code, and we want to demonstrate a test for it. So we run this thing called
test add. So we've made a function test add and PyTest will automatically run this for us
with some nice extra stuff. So the simplest way to run this function would be to run
PyTest and that's it. Yeah so we do PyTest. I think we need to tell it example.py.
That's true, because example.py doesn't start with test underscore.
We need to give it the file name.
But let's also add a verbose flag so that it will tell us what it's doing, give some
more information.
Okay.
So we see test session starts, whatever.
So it ran test add and said that it passed.
Yes.
It did tell us that it, yeah, it ran the test add function.
Yeah.
Okay.
So yeah, all it did is run this function and it didn't encounter any errors.
So it passed.
So if we had a hundred times more code here and 20 different test functions, we could run
them all automatically, all at once.
And yes, and in this case the testing function is doing nothing more than running the function
with some real life values.
Of course you can get more advanced, but that's essentially what testing is.
Running stuff with sample values and seeing if it comes out right.
So what happens if something's broken?
Should we do a test and see?
Okay.
Let's make a break the function.
So now it's clearly not adding.
So I will not run it from here.
I will run it from here in the terminal.
So pytest.
Okay.
Okay, so now it gives a lot more information.
Yeah, and we see a really nice error message.
It says, failures test add, def test add,
assert add two, three equals five.
It says that assert minus one equals five
or minus one equals add two comma three.
So if we had a hundred different test functions here,
we could go and know exactly which function failed
and with which arguments.
OK, so that's the basic idea.
And there was some comment in the notes
about how someone was using unit test.
And it seemed really hard and in a lot of boilerplate.
And you notice here, this is really easy.
Yeah, there's not that much boilerplate in here.
Just fixing the code to make the test pass again.
Okay.
Yeah.
These are all one-line tests.
Of course, the function is very simple, so writing one-line tests is easy, but still.
So the next part here is a test in the episode is a test that considers numerical tolerance.
So can we add as a test add 0.1 and 0.2.
So we assert something.
We want 0.1 and 0.2 equal to 0.3.
I'm actually curious if this will work or not.
No, it did not work.
So it does this work?
Yeah.
Adding 0.1 and 0.2 produces 0.300000000000004 because it's a floating point number.
So it goes in powers of 2.
Floating point numbers are never quite exact.
Yeah. So what's the solution here?
What do we do?
Yeah, good question.
I guess we could check that the difference between the result
and 0.3 is small enough.
So basically we would test with numerical tolerance somehow.
Yes.
So should we try that?
Yeah.
Like, is the difference small enough?
So we take the difference.
but now we want the absolute value of the difference because also if it's
negative that is not good but this is some number and it should be smaller
than some arbitrary number let's say
in the notes it's the power of seven is this seven so basically yeah okay does
it pass now? Now it passes. Okay, great. Let's go to the notes. We have some really good
questions there. I'll switch here locally. So towards the bottom. So yeah, so there's
lots of questions about how this works with more advanced code.
So this is simple.
So whenever I'm doing things, okay, there's the classic case.
You have some simple functions, but you're writing code not because you know the answer,
but because you don't know the answer.
So what do you do?
So several things I would do. I'd break down the big complicated code I don't know the
answer to into small pieces and make sure each individual piece is tested and correct.
So that way, known things are simple, but the complicated thing, hopefully it's correct
with the known parts.
Can you get any really simple sample data? So, for example, you make a test function
that processes millions of records from somewhere,
you give it a list of two records
and see, can it average this correctly?
So basically, in your mind,
there's all different ways you can think
and try to simplify things down to a smaller example.
And actually, after the break,
we go to a test design episode
where we'll talk about this a lot more.
So maybe save some of these questions, and let's discuss more there. There'll be lots of time.
Yeah, this is...
Yeah, so many of these test design functions, let's get to in the test design episode and not
now. Do you see a question, can you test a particular test function without running
through all the functions in the file so you can tell pytest run only this particular test
function and so on do you remember the syntax for that or is it something we should just
i think it's dash k someone should check you can look it up as easy as we can look it up yeah um
And we always have a test in the file that we're wishing to test.
Not necessarily.
You can split them into a separate file, and that's something people do often, or even
a separate folder.
Yeah, I guess for big enough projects I usually see the test in separate, yeah, separate files.
Okay, there's a mention of this benefit, this approach versus plain code that can be automated.
I'm not quite sure what that means, but I'll answer what I think it means.
So what do I think it means?
So you could have a separate script, basically a separate Python program that imports this
module and then runs some stuff and says, is it correct or not?
But that's not that different from what we have here.
And PyTest provides some extra, like all these extra debugging error messages that deselect
certain things if you want to test only that.
It will print output if you want to or don't want to.
But that being said, quite often I do basically have a test function that, you know, is just
a plain Python code.
It loads stuff, does an analysis, and prints, is it correct.
So there's times they start that way or have that in addition.
The point isn't to use OmniPyTest.
The point is to see that you actually can make these tests.
And maybe next let's go to automated test and leave more of these questions for the break
and final discussion, because I think a lot might become clear later.
So with that being said, let's see, first I'll come to my screen.
So automated testing.
So we did this ourselves.
So what if you forget to run PyTest?
So the part we did ourselves, well, we did write the tests, but we run PyTest manually,
I guess is what you mean.
If I forget to run it, the tests don't run, and then I can easily make changes that break
something.
Yeah.
The tests don't really do much if they don't run, I guess.
So it is nice to set it up so that they run automatically.
Yeah.
And that's what we're going to see.
So we're going to see how GitHub, on every push and pull request, is able to run all
of the tests that we have defined.
So let's go back to [name]'s screen, if you're ready.
Yes.
Okay.
So what should we do next?
I guess we want to publish this.
So we will take the same exercise repository, or is it the same one?
Well, no, it says make a new one.
Okay, fine.
I guess we can use the same directory though,
because it's pretty simple.
So we do need to make a new repository
because this is not the repository.
This is not using Git.
Okay, yeah.
So I need to go and initialize.
I could directly publish to GitHub as we go.
Yeah.
So let's try that,
because we are going to need to do this at some point.
Yeah.
Right?
Yes.
see us use everything we've learned during the past two weeks. So we will see
using Git from day one. You will see making GitHub repositories from
days two and three. You will see us setting up a GitHub actions like in day
5. And how this can be made social in day 4. So this might be fast, but we'll tell you
and we'll slow down in the important parts.
Okay so and yeah my the user interface here vs code does a good number of steps in one go
when I click here. Okay so yeah what do I want to include not the pytest cache not pycache just
example.py. Okay and there we go.
Open GitHub.
Where should I go next?
Should I keep showing the code or should I go to the new GitHub page?
Maybe let's show what we would really do in real life.
So would you be using VS Code for?
Well, okay, what do I want to do next? What's the next step?
So, what I want to achieve is I want these tests to run automatically
whenever I make a change, or at least often enough that I don't forget.
So, how would you do that?
So, wait, let's back up here.
we're doing the example under automated testing and it gives us some sample code to add to a
repository, a functions.py file. Okay, let's do that. I guess [name] will go and copy
the functions. Yes, so we'll create a functions.py file
This is quite similar, actually, to the example.py in that it has this add function.
But now we also have a subtract function.
It has this comment because I copied it directly from the notes.
But you can also see that comment, so fine.
It has a multiply function.
And we will also have this one I missed, Fahrenheit to Celsius, or convert Fahrenheit to Celsius,
which uses these other functions.
Okay.
So, this code is provided in the exercise, and we will commit it and push it to GitHub
now.
Okay.
So, add it.
And [name] is quickly here doing all the git committing stuff.
We're not explaining it again.
Yes.
Commit message and then push the changes to GitHub.
Okay, there we are.
But now we don't have any tests for this functions module.
But we add that later.
Okay.
Or do we add it later?
Yes, we do add it now.
Yeah, that is, I guess, the next step.
Yes.
Or at least it's a necessary step on the way.
So, what am I doing here?
I should explain as I go.
We add a file test underscore functions.py.
So, as you said, PyTest will also check for files or modules with the name test underscore something.
and now we actually don't directly have access to these functions so we we need to import them
so let's say from functions import add should you copy and paste from the
This is Python and it's also hopefully clear enough.
So I will rename the convert Fahrenheit to Celsius function as I import it into F2C,
but otherwise I'm directly importing the ones we have.
And this first test is what we already saw.
two and three equals five and add space and ship equals spaceship should i include the other test
as well yes copy everything we will uncomment it later okay so we'll keep them commented for now
and i suppose um i feel like i'm done with something so i will add and commit
So, and now [name] is doing the committing, which we pushed for.
Okay, so step two in our exercise, or demo, is to run the test locally.
Okay. So, we did that already. Let's try it. So, now we can just run PyTest and it will
find the test underscore file. This test underscore functions. And it will find one
test and it passed.
Yes.
So, collected one item means there was one test.
Okay.
Okay. So, seems good.
So, next up in our demo is to enable automated testing.
So, now we switch to the GitHub view.
Okay. So, let's go there.
And this is the GitHub repository.
It opened in my browser window when I clicked open.
And it is this PyTest example.
So, it has an example.py.
Um, I need to refresh and it should have more files.
Yes.
Okay.
Functions and test functions.
Good.
Yes.
So we can, now we do, this is the main part, the main point of what we're doing
here, so we will tell GitHub that every time there's a push run pytest on test
functions.py and we do that via GitHub actions, which if you look at the top of
the tab bar. There's actions. So click there. OK. And I don't have any actions yet, so it's
suggesting a number of things I can run. Yes. And one of them is Python application. Yes.
OK. So go there. And it even nicely says create and test a Python application. Yeah. And it
It gives us a bunch of boilerplate.
So this basically is what you need here.
But I think there's some edits that we'll do.
Okay.
What do we need to change?
So it says to modify the highlighted lines.
So we need to say jobs pull requests have write access.
I'd probably copy from the notes.
So it needs write access to pull requests.
Oh, right, to post comments to the pull requests.
And we'll see what these things do later.
is basically lots of different configuration. Yeah okay so let's add um under install dependencies
we need to tell it to install flake 8 pytest and pytest-cov. So this is something called
test coverage which we will talk about later. And then down here below instead of just running
to test, which would work and run the tests, we will also use this coverage report then. Yes,
and let's see, does this match? So, before we leave this window, let's slow down and take a
look at what it does. This is called YAML, and it's a configuration, well, it's a simple markup
language. It defines data. So we see on line 15 there's jobs. There's a job with the name build.
It gives some permissions and steps. And this uses, it says first checkout. It sets up Python.
It installs some things. And if you look at lines 31 to 33, this doesn't look, this is basically
the same kind of stuff you can run in a terminal. So this is basically creating a virtual machine
of some sort and letting you run Python stuff inside. There's lint with flake 8.
Line 42. We see it runs pytest with this extra option coverage report. So
So these options are new to us, but PyTest is not new.
So it's running the same thing we've run before, but automatically.
And if PyTest detects any errors, it will exit with a failure, and then GitHub Actions
will detect PyTest failed, and then give us a warning.
And that's the main point here.
Yeah, so when will it run? It will run whenever we push to the main branch or whenever there's
a pull request to the main branch, which is often enough for me.
Yeah, okay.
Okay.
So, yes, so it says commit changes.
Okay, let's do that.
And testing workflow. And commit. Okay. Did something happen?
Yeah. Can we go back to the code view? Yeah. There's this yellow thing that we saw previously.
So what have we done now?
So we have made some code locally.
We set up PyTest.
And now we've told GitHub to run the test we've made on every push and pull.
And yes, there's been a lot of different code and stuff we've pasted here and there.
you can you don't like we have gone fast you haven't had time to read everything
we've been pasted the point is that now
github is running it as we see from this yellow dot can you click on the yellow
dot yeah so it is actually done okay we can still go take a look what it's done
And here is the section where it runs test.
So it has completed the test.
Yes.
So.
Okay.
Sorry.
I out of habit moved back, but is there something else you want to point out there?
Yeah.
Can we go back?
Let's give people time to take a look and see.
So now here, GitHub has run all of the different rules we've defined.
It checked out the repository, set up Python, run PyTest, and PyTest worked.
So it will run it on every commit.
So let's continue.
So we've done this verification that it's run.
So let's add a test that reveals a problem.
So I guess [name] can go back to VS Code.
Yes.
Just move the window here.
So I believe that is this next step.
Test subtract.
Yes.
So first, can you do git pull to get all the updates?
that happens by clicking here and now we can see that we have added this workflow here so now
github has the file we added on github is now present in our local repository
so since we're up to date we can do some new things okay
Okay, so let's uncomment this function and save.
And now, given that you said we were uncovering a problem,
I assume this test will fail if we run it.
So should we try it locally or just push
and see what happens?
Commit and push.
Okay.
test subtract so we added a new test for the subtract function and push it to github and
i will show the github view again go to the main view and now it's again running the tests
Okay let's go to the action view instead so it shows the previous one that worked and now there's
a new push that's well the tests for that new push are running let's see it usually doesn't
take very long but we'll see oh you can actually see how far it's progressed
So by clicking on it, it's done.
We see it fixed.
Yes.
OK.
Now I think it's the time I take over the screen share
as your partner and make the fix.
So I will click here.
So can someone, or actually, I can
paste this repository in the notes.
So here I am, I'm logged in.
Why don't I see the dot that shows the failure?
If I click on Action,
I see a test failure.
So what do I do?
So first I'll make an issue about it. So I click on the issues tab, click on new
issue. I'll be quick about it.
So, this issue says there's a bug in test subscrap outwork on it, so basically someone
knows that it's there and it's being fixed.
Of course, if someone was working on your own project, you would just fix it.
But here we're showing if something was bigger, took more time, and we wanted to synchronize
better.
So how do I fix it now?
Well, we go back to day three, and I would make a pull request.
And I guess I will do that through the GitHub web interface.
So I click on code, and we know from, ah, now there's the red X.
So we know from GitHub that I can edit directly here.
So I click on Functions.
And I've identified the problem.
I know that I can click on Edit in GitHub and make the change.
So if this was a big enough project,
I'd be fixing it on my own computer.
But for a demo, this is good.
I need to fork the repository, and notice that [name] hasn't given me any permissions
here.
So for any other code online, I could be doing the same things.
So I fixed the subtract function with one line.
I will commit changes.
So this is all happening quickly, but it's day three kinds of things.
commit message will be, and then the extended descriptions.
So, I'm giving some notes about what it was, and I will propose changes.
So, here we go.
So, again, this is day 3 kind of stuff.
So there's my head repository of RkDarst, and I'm sending it to the other repository.
There I see the changes, I will create pull request, and it's the same things here.
I should include in the description fixes number one, so the issue number, so the issue
will be automatically linked and closed and created.
And now, here's the cool part.
So it says that I cannot update it.
And also, I have a feeling that it's not running the tests because now GitHub doesn't run tests
from new contributors.
So let's switch back to [name]'s screen, if you're ready.
Yes.
I'm ready.
Okay.
So if you go to the pull request view.
Yeah.
I noticed I have a new issue and a new pull request.
So if I go to the new pull request, fix the subtract function. Nice.
Yeah, the test hasn't started running because I haven't approved that [name] can run tests
in my repository or can run workflows. So I will approve it.
Okay.
And now they're running.
It's running.
And we just wait a second for it to turn green.
And we will see, does it work?
Okay.
that's happening. It says it fixes, changed plus to one, plus to minus.
Oh, it failed. I wonder why. I was going to go here to see,
so the plus has been changed to minus. That seems fine. Okay, let's take a look at the,
I guess the fastest way is to go through the pull request. Yeah, let's click on details.
What happened?
Ah, the coverage report path failed. So the tests passed, but
something failed here. Resource not accessible by integration.
Well, okay. This is something, well,
no, this is something we added. Yeah. I guess we'll leave it be.
I guess this is what we call the demo effect, so
something in github has changed but okay well the test did pass so i'm fine with merging the pull
request yeah confirm merge here we go and the pull request is automatically closed and the issue is
also automatically closed yes okay now since the main branch has been updated it's actually
again running the test here i'm kind of interested in it whether it will actually work here or not
but we'll see i guess this is because it couldn't write to the pull request or something
or save the data yes now it did work okay um
so actually creating the coverage thing doesn't work from a pull request now yeah
yeah well um we can fix that later but um and we also noticed the issue is closed
Yes. So I guess I will switch back to my screen and let's wrap up and go to the
break. Yeah. Okay. So this was relatively fast work here. We used PyTest. We made
same example. We committed to GitHub. We added a test in GitHub which can run PyTest on every
single commit, whether [name] makes it or whether someone makes the commit in a pull request.
test. And this can really remove the friction in contributing to projects. So I make a project,
I add some tests. Once people start contributing, I'll make sure that the GitHub tests are set
up. So that way, when someone said something, I can see really quickly, has it worked? And
the person submitting can see before and see, okay, like, have I done everything I need before the
original author should take their time to look at it? And this helps a lot.
It works for both the centralized and forking workflows for one repository or multiple
repositories. And GitHub Actions can run on Windows, Mac, Linux operating systems. It has
this marketplace to run different kinds of things easily. Basically it's this thing that automatically
adds things to you. It's completely free for public projects in line with GitHub's normal
philosophy. But this is not only a GitHub thing. So GitLab has a CI kind of thing. There's other
services, some of which provide free time and builds for open source projects. So I propose
now that we go to our break, and we can keep taking questions then. And the next episode,
we will go into test design. And there, a lot of the question people have been asking,
like, how does this apply to a big, complicated project that's not these really simple functions?
we will start discussing them then. So start adding your questions. Anything else for now?
No, I think that's fine. Okay, get to the hard questions in the next section.
So let's go to the break and see you in 10 minutes at 13 past hour. Bye.
Bye.
you
We are back, I hope.
And I see some messages from the streaming software, I hope that's not bad.
So
Well, is everything okay with people in the stream?
Yeah.
And now we go to test design.
And people have been asking previously, how does this work whenever I have some really
complicated code?
I can't make a two-line function that tests it.
Should I really have a lot of small test functions for everything?
And now is the time to ask those questions.
We probably can't answer everything, but write it in the notes.
And this is really the core here.
It's really easy to give these demos and show usePyTest on a one-line function.
Whenever you're testing a software that uses random numbers and has thousands of lines
and has no one fixed result, how do you even test it?
How do you make sure it's correct?
I mean, you have to have something, right?
Because if you don't even know what the right answer would be, how do you know that it's
it's giving what it should.
So yeah, and for a lot of it, there's a first question that's been asked, do you have a
practical way to test load-level functions that interact with external hardware?
So once I was reading something, and it was like, here's a way you could run the Linux
kernel on custom hardware and it has some network interface which is used for running tests so
when you have questions like this if you say to me okay this is hard to test
do some web searches and i bet someone has figured out how to do it before
just because well yeah yeah i assume this is a common problem i've dealt with it a couple of
times. I guess in practice it ended up being quite similar. It's not exact, so you need
some tolerance. You check that an absolute value is smaller than a number. And of course
the tests run slower because a physical thing needs to move from place to place while it's
running.
And maybe we don't see it here, but a lot of test design is structuring the code so
that it can be tested.
So if you have one 1000 line function, that's really hard to test.
But can you break it down into 800 line functions, which are complicated but can be tested, but
the unknown part is just contained in a very few parts, so what you can't test you can audit
separately. So anyway, this episode we're about to cover is normally an
exercise and we would give you a lot of time to basically...
Well, I'll scroll down quickly here.
You would see there's a lot of different sample functions, and we would challenge you to test
them.
But we're going to do that ourselves.
Do we have time to do all of them, or should we focus on a few?
Or should we just discuss some of them?
do you think? Well I think probably not all of them. We probably don't have time to do
all of them. I guess so if when things come up in the notes it's probably worth discussing
and otherwise we could pick some of these and actually write the tests. So maybe let's
start at the beginning and but depending on what people request we'll jump to
those so I will switch to [name]'s screen. Okay and I'll be doing actual coding
yes so I'll show the VS Code window. So do you make a new file to put these in?
or that would make sense how would we so let's do this what's the first example
the first factorial example the first example is this factorial function so
this factorial dot pi since the solution is basically the same as what we've done
already should we actually do it or should we discuss I'd say let's discuss
yeah maybe it's enough to discuss. So maybe I'll switch back to my screen then.
Okay. So we see here the proposed solution is basically what we've already
already done. It adds, it tests some values. How do we test really big values? Can it even
be tested in this case?
There is a limit to how large a normal integer can be. Is there in modern Python, so there
There is a way you can handle really big integers, but is that built-in in modern Python?
I'm not actually sure.
I think so.
I think Python by default will go to big int.
So I guess in theory this works for anything big.
Are you happy with these tests here?
Do you think this is enough?
What else would you test?
I would like to see some, to test some larger numbers,
because these could easily be hard-coded into the function.
So a larger integer.
So I guess at least one example case
that would go to the big integer realm.
Yeah, that would be nice.
Okay.
And to check that that's correct,
I think you would first compute it somehow by hand
or in a different way.
Another thing is what if you give it an incorrect thing, like something that's not a number or something that's a negative number or a non-integer number.
So, in PyTest, we can actually test if it will raise an exception when you tell it to
do a negative number.
Should we do an example of that, or should we move on to more interesting things?
I think time's ticking, maybe we should go on.
But anyway, the point is, if you search PyTest test raises exception, you'll find an example
and it will tell you how you can check does it actually give value error here.
Okay.
What's the next one?
a function which receives two strings and returns a number.
Okay. Is there any challenge here beyond what we've already done?
I mean, yeah, it is. I could easily come up with a few examples and
and compare them to the correct result that it does not seem like there's a lot of complication
here.
Yeah.
This again, like maybe it's not a string, maybe, maybe it's something different.
But then I think it would raise an error.
Okay, so let's look at the solution quickly and I guess this last one here,
word occurrence. So it tests, does it detect substrings? Which is actually a
very interesting point. So triple a is contained within five a's?
That's true.
So I'm not sure if that test actually...
That is not the result I would expect from a function called word occurrence.
Yeah. So is the test wrong or is the function wrong?
I mean maybe this is the intended result, but then it needs to be documented. I'm a bit surprised.
So the point here is that by making the test, we considered the corner case and realized maybe we need to update our function also.
Which is good.
good. Okay. A function which reads a file and returns a number. Is this worth doing
for real? Or?
There's a lot of places in code where you need to read a file and do something, or where
have a function that reads a file and does something with the contents. You could always
split that into one function that reads the file, another one that only does the work on the contents
and then test the second one separately. But still, yeah, I think occasionally testing,
reading a file is worth the trouble. It's maybe not complicated enough that we want to go through
it in detail. Yeah. The solution, I guess, should I just give the solution? Yeah, I guess.
What I would do is make an example file and the test would be reading that example file
or a number of example files. Yeah, so if you ask me, this is where my opinion would be
this function is doing too many things. The function is both reading the file
and doing some analysis. So doing the analysis is worth testing. Reading the
file is difficult to test. So why doesn't this file... why aren't there two functions?
One which reads the file and returns maybe the file object or the raw data,
and another function which does the counting. And then the one that does the
counting is easy to test because I give it some arguments and it gives the
results out. And the one that reads the file maybe I wouldn't test yet because
it's so simple and not worth my time to do this boilerplate code where I make a
contemporary file, I open the file, I save the data, and then I run it on the file.
Yeah, the file opening function is a built-in Python thing, so it doesn't need to be tested
necessarily.
Yeah.
I mean, if this was a really big program that had thousands of users, then yeah, maybe testing
opening the files would be worth it, but for most of what I do, I don't care that much.
And this is a case where making it easier to test improves the function itself. So,
for example, whenever I was working with someone once, they had a lot of really great
analysis functions and a lot of really great analysis functions but the
functions read a file and then did the analysis instead of doing so instead of
having it separate so that whenever they wanted to apply this to a new case like a
new kind of project, they had to arrange all of their data into exact same format, which didn't
make sense anymore. So making it easier to test makes it more modular, which incidentally we'll
talk about later, and would make the code better overall. Okay. What's next? Something with an
external dependency. Is this worth testing?
I mean a lot of functions will have external dependencies.
It is worth testing unless you are just testing the dependency.
But I mean hopefully the dependency will have its own tests.
I'm not sure about this one though. So what's the point here? There's
It's from reactor import max temperature.
So this seems like it's really testing whether the reactor itself is working correctly.
Although you could also think of it as testing whether you understand the reactor interface
correctly or whether it's working the way you are assuming it should be working for
your code.
So it might be worth testing, but it's an edge case, I probably wouldn't.
So yeah, this is what you said, is it testing if maxTemperature is set correctly, or if
changing maxTemperature changes the function as you expect?
But let's look at the solution and see.
So here, this monkey patch is something from PyTest.
And you might look at this and say, where is the value of monkey patch coming from?
How does PyTest find this?
So the answer is this is PyTest magic.
So if you give it the name of some standard argument, it will pass in something to the
functions and let you do things like this.
So this means monkeypatchoh, do you know the definition of monkeypatch?
How would you describe it?
I think monkey patch is a coding term, one module like this test function is changing
the value of something on another module reactor when it's really not designed to be changed
this way.
So in plain language, this code means when this runs on reactor, it will set max temperature
to 100, so it's a known value. Then the test can run. And then when the function is over,
it will restore it to the previous value. So this allows us to make sure that maxTemperature
is something known, so we're testing only this function and not the external dependency
of what is max temperature.
Have you ever done things like this?
I can't think of an example, but I, well, yes, in some case, not often.
So essentially replacing something in a library because, for example, I don't have access
to certain hardware that's required to run the library, you just replace a function in
that library with a function of your own and run that instead.
So yeah, it is a useful thing to do.
In most of my cases, the maxTemperature would be a constant, so I would just test the function.
And if the function fails, I have to see, did the maxTemperature change or did the function
break?
And that's a bit unfortunate, but there.
But in a case where maxTemperature is really defined somewhere else in dynamic, you have
to do something like this.
Or maybe the original function could be defined to take two arguments.
It's up to you.
Okay, should we continue?
Yeah.
Should we do this as the talk about this and then test-driven development, then do that
as a demo.
Sorry, so first talk about this and then do test room development as a demo.
Yeah.
Yeah, that makes sense.
So we have a class here, a Python class.
If you haven't seen this before, then don't worry, but we won't explain it now.
We see it sets, it models a pet.
The pet can be initialized with a name and hunger level.
And when we call this go for a walk function, then hunger gets incremented.
So how would we test this function?
What do we have?
What's the steps you would have to do?
Yeah, you would definitely have to create the object.
We have to create the object.
And then if this is something you wrote yourself, you know that it starts with hunger equals
zero.
Mm-hmm.
So I know one thing you can test is whether the  you can test the init function immediately.
Okay.
Yeah.
And then I suppose you would run go for a walk a few times with different starting values
and check that it increments by one.
So by starting value, do you mean we would set hunger to a certain value, then run go
for a walk, and then check the final hunger value?
Yes.
Okay, yeah.
At least that's one thing.
Makes sense.
Yeah.
Should we check the solution?
Yeah, let's see.
So, pet Fido.
Yes, so we check that it's initialized to the value we expect, zero.
We walk, and then we test isHunger greater now.
Okay, that should always work.
And then we set hunger to minus one, if that makes any sense.
We run go for a walk, and then we check isHunger zero.
And I guess what's the lesson here, that whenever we have something that changes state, we have
to set the state, check or run it, and then check the state after.
And this is pretty normal to do.
There was also a couple of questions about, for example, a stochastic thing or a thing
where you cannot necessarily predict the result, and we did talk about that a bit, but
I'm just saying it would be good to get there, have time for that as well.
Should we go straight to testing randomness next?
Yeah.
Let's do that. Okay, should we go back to your screen?
Okay.
Are you ready?
So I will get a...
Actually, first let's look over the thing here.
So, we want to test randomness. We can try fixed random seeds, so this is where basically
you pre-know what the value is, or we know what the random number generator would make.
We can see, does it follow the expected distribution, or we can look at it by eye and think, what's
the i thing we're looking at, yeah.
And there are often some hard parameters
you can test even in a completely random case
without setting the seed.
You can test that the value is not outside some boundary.
Yeah.
That it makes sense for what it is.
Yeah, like if I was testing randomness,
first I would test, well, I can make a test
and not even look at the value.
does the function run without errors?
Yeah.
Is the answer of a dice rule, if I run it 100 times,
is it always between 1 and 6 inclusive?
And if I trust my random number generator,
then that's better than nothing.
And we get better from there.
So if we're testing Yahtzee, do you know how Yahtzee even works?
Roughly, I mean, you throw dice and then you check if the dice match certain predefined
sets.
Yeah.
I guess we can look at the code in more detail.
Should I just copy paste the entire code to my file?
So in yatsi.py, okay, so what do we have here?
Can you explain?
We have a rollDice function, which it seems, oh, it rolls number of dice.
So it returns a list of a random choice between one and six inclusive integers and yeah, in
the parameters, you can set the number of dice you want to roll.
Okay.
Yeah.
And then Yahtzee.
And then Yahtzee itself, play with five six-sided dice and three draws.
Okay.
So first, you roll some dice and you check.
I'm not exactly sure how this will end up playing Yahtzee, but let's see.
What's the most common number visible in the dice, I suppose.
That's the most common side.
And then how many of those do you have?
So if you have like three fours, this would be four and this would be three.
Yeah, I would expect the most common side is called the target side.
Number of same sides is how often.
So how many of those you have.
If it's equal to five, you return five.
Okay.
I guess you get five points from that.
If you get five of the same, then that matches something.
you can try again. Okay. Throw a second and a third time and do the same thing again.
Okay. And then it returns the number of same. So this is counting how in tree throws how
many of the same number you can get. And if you're rolling five dice, right? Yes. Okay.
So if you get five of the same, then you don't need to roll again. That's the best result
you can have. So then you just immediately return that.
Can we try running and see what it says?
Okay.
But to be honest, looking at all this stuff, it doesn't quite make sense, but we can use
it as a code.
It's not a standard Yahtzee game.
It's a much simpler version of Yahtzee.
This is running a number of games and then printing how many times you got five.
Okay, so back to the terminal.
So let's run the code.
It did not do anything.
If name equals main, why doesn't it print something?
Did you save the file?
Good question.
Okay.
I did not.
That makes more sense.
Okay.
So six guys.
So it ran 100 games, and on six of those games, we got five dice showing the same number.
which is called a Yahtzee, I guess.
So, what are the different levels we could test it at?
Should we test just the dice roll first?
Yes, that makes sense. It's not a completely trivial function, so it makes sense to test it.
In practice, we always throw five dice,
but I guess since it's general enough,
you can test it in different ways.
Should I just write test directly into this?
Yeah, I'd say just throw it right in there.
Maybe just directly after the function I'm testing.
Yeah, let's do that.
So in the solution,
says test roll dice with no arguments and the solution suggests we set the
random number generator seed to zero and then we test the actual value. So this
function random dot seed it's so in random number generators there's
something called a seed and if you start with the same seed the generator will
always give the same values out. So that by giving the seed, we should be able to predict
what comes out. So we can assert RollDice5 equals the list, and from the solution the
values are 44135. So what's the problem here? Or what could be a problem here?
What if Python's random number generator has changed since we last did this workshop?
Yeah, well, then the numbers would be different. And I guess this test doesn't really tell you
whether the rollDice function has broken or whether the random has just changed in some way.
Yeah, should we try running it and let's see if this works?
Yeah.
So pytest.yatsi.py.
It didn't find a test because I didn't save it.
Okay.
Okay, trying again and it passed.
Okay, so it didn't change.
So this actually works pretty well for testing this function, I guess, so what's the disadvantage though?
If the function changes, these outputs would change, so it will verify it's always giving the same output,
but it doesn't give you any flexibility for changing how the dice are rolled, because then it would give something different.
Should we go to next? So there's test Yahtzee. So maybe this one you should copy from the
notes okay so basically in this test it will play Yahtzee 1 million times and
we'll check did we win approximately 4.6 percent of these million games okay this
also sets a random seed. Yeah, so this time we don't have the problem that if random changes
then the result will change because actually with any seed it should be roughly the same,
approximately the same result. If you're running it enough times it should work. Yeah, okay.
Okay.
The downside is that it takes a while.
Yeah.
Okay.
It's done.
And now it says two tests passed.
Good.
So it was the correct number of wins.
Yes.
So I guess this is in the category of testing distributions.
We check that the, we set up a specific version of whatever random process is running and
And it needs to, given some correct number, plus, minus, whatever random error.
Yeah.
Okay, let's go back to my screen and see what is next.
So we did this testing randomness with Yahtzee.
Designing an end-to-end test. Maybe we should go to discussion now and let's see what people
say. So please start asking your hard testing questions.
So we'll get something. Designing an end-to-end test.
So this is basically... This is a bit hard to read quickly.
So it's basically some shell function, the unique command, and how would you test that?
And basically you give it some input data, and you check is the output what you expect.
And this is also a pretty reasonable way to test some things.
So, instead of each individual function, just run the whole thing on some known data.
Do you have any comments here?
Well, I mean, this is something that's very common with my projects.
So, they include some test data and you run some full process of, you take some actual
processing steps and it should always produce the same expected result.
As long as there's no randomness involved, this is a very useful test, very useful type
of test.
The downside is that it doesn't give you a lot of detail.
If it fails, you only know that your process fails.
So hopefully you also have a unit test failing at that point.
But if not, you kind of need to go digging and figure out what's going on.
Yeah.
I mean, my philosophy would be if the end-to-end test failed, at least I know and I'm in the
same place I would be otherwise, which is go down and debug it.
And maybe I would use the opportunity to guess where it is and make some unit tests now that
I know how it can't fail, or what's likely.
Let's go on.
More end-to-end testing, create an actual end-to-end test.
I think we don't have time for this.
Let's go to the notes and see what good questions people have.
So down to test design, there was this good question, do you have a practical way to test
low-level functions that interact with external hardware?
I think that's probably answered there well enough.
think we talked about something like that. Yeah, yeah. How to design a test without running a
whole solver whenever it's very complex like this? Hmm. I guess, yeah, can you break it down to
several small subroutines. Can you give it a, what's the simplest problem that has a known
non-trivial value? So this is not exactly answering this question, but some of the tests
that I was most proud of, it was during my postdoc, I was had to generate random graphs
according to some particular algorithm. And the algorithm was in fact the thing that
the research was about. So I had nothing to compare to. So how would I test this kind of thing?
Well of course I ran it and looked at it by eye, but is there some glaring bug here?
So here's what I did. My algorithm took some parameters. Basically the problem,
their probability of making links in certain forms. So I set this probability to zero,
and then I should get an empty graph out of it. And then I did it again, and I set the probability
to one, and I should get a complete graph. And since there were two or three different
parameters going in, I could do different combinations of these parameters,
0, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 0, with different probabilities that are 1 and 0, and C is the
graph that comes out what I expect, which is usually either a complete graph or an incomplete
graph or some known number of edges in there. And this actually let me define some bugs
in my code that I couldn't see by eye. And I was really happy with figuring this out.
think that's a good example of end-to-end. Is it end-to-end or is it integration? I'm not sure
what kind of test it is, but in the end the name doesn't matter. The point is it worked.
I guess that's an end-to-end test. It's not checking whether multiple libraries work together.
Okay, a good workflow in Python. What's this question? If I do a test, it will apply to
a version of the code. I need to add a test to a new function. Do I new test? This is
a really good point. So, test-driven design. This is something we skipped in the previous
lesson. You can, in fact, write a test before you write the function itself. So, this is,
is it extreme programming or something like that, test-driven development? Anyway, once I saw it
written this way, you want to add some new functionality. You make the test for it, and
then you run the test code and you see it fails because the function isn't defined. Good. Now,
you write code until that test passes. So this ensures that everything you do has a test
and you think about how you want to use the function before you write it.
So this is basically defining what the functionality should be
before you start writing it and first writing down what the function should do.
and only then writing the function, which makes sense.
But it really depends on how you want to do things.
So I've used all kinds of strategies, and I don't think I've ever done anything that's pure test-driven development.
I guess test-driven development does  it requires that you can define what the end
result is, that you know what the end result is before you start working on it.
And that works in small steps, but it usually almost never works for an entire new feature
or a new code base, especially in a new research software.
are unlikely to stay, the requirements are unlikely to stay the same.
This next question, some kind of research test which determines how successful the proposed
approach is. If you can define an overall success as a test then I would definitely do that
and probably start with that. It's relatively easy and probably high
impact because you can quickly run it to see where your errors are.
Yeah.
Yeah, again it relies on you knowing what the result should be. So you can probably
know some features of it like a range or errors or how fast it should be, but often not exactly
what the number is at the end because if you knew that then probably you wouldn't write the code.
This next question.
I have no tests working with images.
This idea of getting some test images with easy cases manually annotating and comparing,
I mean, yeah, that sounds exactly like what I would do.
Of course it can be difficult to make the initial images, but if you don't have some
test data for something like this, you're going to be looking at some images to see
if it's correct anyway.
So why not make an image that doesn't have any confidential data and is small, add it
to your repository and then it saves you a lot of looking separately every time
you make a change. Do you consider...should we look at this screenshot here?
Example of how a research test is formulated, can we comment? Um, question
Ideally, parameters shouldn't be hard-coded but uploaded over a file.
I mean, if it's easy to hard-code, then why not start with that?
So, is it a test?
If it's a test, then hard-coding parameters often make sense.
You will change them much less often than in when you're running an actual code.
So hard coding is much less of a problem.
Yeah.
So it looks like so, yeah, so there's different use cases depending on the parameter.
it will either run the first use case or the second use case.
And then it will see, does it give the right output?
This is better than the check.
Where's the check?
Or is it checking if it runs?
Is this a check here?
Oh, it's an equal sign.
Would that be a comparison?
Or maybe the test is below, lower, and we don't see it.
Yeah.
But I mean, as a starting point, I would start here.
And if there get to be so many test cases,
I can't keep track of them, then I'd probably
start splitting them out.
So one small thing here is that which test cases run
is hardcoded here.
So I guess what I would do is turn this into a function
and then run it with two different input parameters, either use case equals one or
first use case equals zero and then use case equals one. Of course, then you could instead of
use case as only single parameter, you could include all of those numbers,
all of those parameters into the function parameters.
It makes sense.
Then you could easily run both cases, post-test cases, in a single script.
Yeah.
Okay.
If a test fails, how does it fail?
Will it be printed, or what?
So it depends on the frame...
Wait.
Ah, this is commenting on that.
I think there's a lot there.
So let's go to the last question before lunch break.
Does a big project include test codes in source code
or C only final?
So for every good open source project I know of,
the test code is included in with the actual code itself.
There's little reason not to.
And it really improves confidence of things
if you want people to be modifying it and improving it and if not well
i mean yeah i guess someone could release the code without the test code but then don't expect
other people to be able to contribute to it that well
um yeah if um if the tests are not included then you cannot check that you installed it correctly
or at least it's not easy to check that you installed it correctly so
So also for that reason, it's good to include the tests.
So did we miss anything?
I'm not seeing many chat messages or other questions,
hopefully.
So should we?
Well, what's the overall summary here?
So, we've seen different ways to write code which ensures other code works.
And by making it automatic, you can run it much more often than you could otherwise.
And it will hopefully make your code more correct.
But more importantly, it makes your development easier.
Like, the few times that I've started with tests really early for some research code
where I didn't even know what the answer should be, I've been really happy because I run this,
I can see all my really simple syntax errors and debugging syntax errors and so on much
faster than I could otherwise.
then I could use my brain, do manual effort for tests
and checks, which are not easy to automate
and actually are difficult. So with that said,
do you have any other final wrap ups?
Well, having to test run automatically
is super helpful because you will forget to run them
otherwise. So we've seen how to do it. But yeah, it's just automating it, making it as easy as
possible is an important thing. And it's also useful for others because, of course, it's much
easier to get everyone else to run the tests when they don't actually even need to run them.
They will just run automatically.
I guess we should go now. At least I need to get or go out quickly.
So thank you and see you in about an hour.
Have a good lunch break.
Okay, thank you.
Bye.
you
Hello, hello, can you hear us?
So should I go to [name]'s screen, I guess?
Yes, let's do that.
OK, so this next section is a type-along or something,
not a type-along, but a demo, but something
between us doing things in the stream and an exercise.
So it works best when there's a lot of active participation
the notes document. So this is about modular code development and just to get
started in the document we have a few questions so please go and take a look
at those and answer those.
Yes, we see them here.
Yeah, so there's also some answers given away in this image that is linked from the materials.
So we'll quickly show that, but we're also already getting some answers, which is good.
So to you, what does modular code development mean?
What does modular even mean?
Yeah, what is modular?
The first thing that comes to my mind when I think of what is modular is the International
space station, because I think I learned the word from there, but it consists of this kind
of a central structure, but that's also kind of a module of its own.
The main thing is different groups have made these sections to the station and you can
plug them together.
They're like Legos.
You can take one piece and plug it into another piece, and the idea is that all the wiring
should work and that there's some sort of interface between the two that helps all the
parts work in all of these sections.
So basically you can ship up one new module and connect it and that works.
Like you can add and remove things, you can understand each part separately.
Yeah and someone can design one part of a bigger whole and then as long as the interface makes
sense you can plug it into a bigger thing and out of those smaller modules then make something even
something bigger and more complicated and it's still kind of it remains understandable and
manageable. Yeah so why do we have a lesson on modular code development? Like what's the
big point here. Well yeah, so a software project can get really big and it can get and in fact it
does get so big that or software gets so big that it's hard to understand. Like if you have
the whole thing written down in one section it is very hard to continue developing it.
it. Plus, when you make something modular, it's not just easier to understand the modules
and then understand the whole that the modules make up, it's also easier to split up the
work. So you can split the different sections, the different modules between different developers,
different people in your team, and someone from the outside can come and write a module
for the thing you designed.
So it makes development easier, it makes testing easier,
and it makes it easier to share your work.
It kind of pulls together a lot of what we've done
in the past two weeks.
So at least in Python,
the things you import are called modules.
Does modular code development have to be about these modules
or is that what this is about?
It's not exactly.
Modular code development is also about functions.
Small functions that do individual things that you can pluck out of a code,
then move into another code and will still work.
So making your, first of all, writing functions,
but then also writing functions that are in themselves modular,
They are independent of the whole project in some way.
But it is also organizing those then into modules, so organizing them into separate
files that could be depending on the language, could be Python modules, could be libraries,
could be shared objects and so on, depending on packages.
different languages or different programming languages have different words for these but
the structure is roughly the same.
What about this last question? Would you prefer your code to be two times slower if it was easier
to read and understand? That depends a lot on the situation. Yeah, if it's a high performance
computing thing, then the main code of course should be as fast as you can make it.
But in most cases, the code should be first understandable and then maybe also efficient
if that's necessary.
But first you should have a code that works and then you can try to make it faster.
But that's actually something I didn't mention in testing, but one very useful idea is to
write two implementations of something.
So you have a slower algorithm, and then you also write a faster algorithm.
And if those produce the same results, then probably both of them work.
The more different they are, the better.
Yeah.
I did that once to, like, verify something.
I've done a lot of high performance computing work
and that's a very useful approach.
Because things you write for the main thing need to be really fast.
But then they are not readable. So you also
write a slower version.
So does modularity always make it slower?
or no I don't actually it's an interesting question because I can't actually think why
it would make anything slower okay that's good principle I mean code that's easier to
understand is unlikely to be really fast just because it's a different you're optimizing
for a different thing. So they don't have a lot of overlap. And I guess making something
more modular might also make it slower just because you are optimizing for a different
thing when you're writing it.
So I guess this question F, would you prefer your code to be twice, two times slower if
it's easier to read and understand? That's not exactly the trade-off we're making here
then.
Yeah, not exactly, but I mean that it's still a good question to think about and it is kind
of related to this lesson because modular code development is ultimately about making
it understandable and manageable.
Taking a really big complex system and making it manageable is, I guess, mainly what we're
talking about.
Well, understandability and being able to reuse it is definitely things I want.
So what do we do next?
I'll pop back to your screen.
Yes.
So yeah, here is one answer or some answers that you could have copied from if you were
looking at the notes.
But this is a link from the notes.
Okay.
So yeah, there's a lot of things that do go wrong with research software development, like
long functions and overcomplicated design that's kind of a maze of problems in the code that you
have to get through. So is this sort of like if you have bad code design non-modular code
maybe it works in the short term but in the long term you're going to have a major problem?
Yeah, that's the idea. So it becomes complex and something that is complex is hard to maintain
and hard to take care of in the long run. Gets to the point where you don't understand
the code you wrote a week ago very easily.
That's good.
Okay, so here are the questions we already talked about. Just skipping through that section.
I will not go through the learning examples in a lot of detail either because we partly
already talked about that, but this is taking a lot from the past two weeks, maybe slightly
different point of view than in the testing lesson where we took a lot of this social coding and
sharing things aspect of it, but now we're mostly working locally by trying to make
a local code better. So let's just get to the task itself.
Okay, so what do we do? So here's an example task and now this is much closer to real scientific code
than the add function in the testing lesson. So it's hopefully somewhat readable if you go
go through it, you can see what's happening. But it could be made a lot more modular, a
lot better. So let's just start by copying this into a Jupyter notebook. And can you
switch to your screen if you have the notebook ready?
There is my screen. Let's adjust the size of stuff. I've made a new directory for this
I will start a Python 3 kernel.
Should I just copy and paste from?
Yeah, let's just start by copying and pasting here so that
we can all see the code in the same way.
Okay.
Then we'll see what it does.
Should I run it?
Yeah, why not? Can you make
this screen either wider or show the entire lines?
Or what do you call it? Wrap the lines?
Okay, so now it's visible.
Okay.
We need the temperatures file.
So you need to download some files.
So should we actually just go through, like, how did we know that?
Yeah.
What is happening here?
What do we see?
So it says read CSV temperatures dot CSV.
if I scroll down, no such file or directory.
And it gives the file name, hopefully.
So we are missing a file.
And if we start looking at the code,
if we had started looking at the code before running it,
we would have realized that it's reading a file.
So why don't we just download the file?
Do you have the link?
Should I do it from Jupyter?
Yeah, why not?
Let's see if it works.
I know on my computer I have a program called wgit installed that will download a file and
save it in the current directory.
So I will run this.
And it says temperatures.csv saved.
Okay, so now we should have the file.
And I will delete this row.
Yeah.
Okay.
So now we should have the file.
Yeah.
Okay.
Let's do what we were thinking of doing.
what it does first. It's taking a while to run. Well, at the meantime, we can look at the line.
It is importing pandas and matplotlib. Matplotlib is a plotting library and pandas is for data
processing. Then we define the number of measurements is 25, whatever that means,
and we read in some data from a CSV file.
We do have this in the notes.
It's data provided by the Finnish Meteorological Institute
about observations of air temperature at the Helsinki-Vantaa airport in 2022.
Okay, so there's another error somewhere.
Well, let's see.
Key error, air temperature.
Well, let's walk through the code and hopefully it will be-
Yeah. Should we look at the file,
like open it and see?
Okay. So what we're doing here is we're reading this data from
the CSV file and taking this number of measurements,
number of rows, so we're taking
25 measurements from this data file, and then the temperatures should be a column from this
CSV file with this name. So, yeah, I guess it doesn't have a column with that name. It's
probably the structure of the data has changed between the Code Refinery workshop, so maybe
we should take a look at what the CSV file contains.
Should I open it through the file browser?
Yeah, I mean, oh, you mean the one in Jupyter, that makes sense.
So it seems a bit broken.
It did not download.
It links, it doesn't link to the raw data.
So this is, okay, it should be raw data from GitHub, there's a mistake in the link.
Okay.
So I can send you the correct link.
I have the correct link here.
OK.
So now I'm again using Jupyter to remove the temperatures.csv
file.
And now I will paste raw data, raw.githubusercontent.
So this should be raw.
Yeah.
And now it says it's saved.
Should we try again?
Yeah. Let's see what happens.
Okay. That looks better.
Okay.
Okay. So we're reading 25 rows of the data and plotting something, but it's calculating some statistics here.
So it's calculating the mean of the temperature measurements.
and then it's plotting the temperatures oh and it's adding this dashed line for the mean
of those temperatures okay and i guess this is the first 25 days of the year so we're talking
january so the temperatures range from minus 2 to minus 12 or so yeah so it makes sense it
actually looks okay. Okay, so what could we do to make this better or specifically more modular?
How is it not modular now? I mean, I can see some immediate problems.
This notebook has to have a file with one certain name, one certain output, and runs everything at
once. So please go to the notes and add any suggestions on what should we do, what we can
do to make this code more modular specifically or just better in some way. And yeah, we can
spot a few problems here immediately. Yeah. We do have a couple of goals in mind though
So, as we start working on this, we want to be able to create a plot, create several different
plots.
We want a plot with 25 measurements, but we also want a plot with 100 measurements and
with 500 measurements.
And I guess, so then just, well, let's start with that.
We have some suggestions here. Don't load the data when creating the plot,
load it separately. Separate the plotting and loading to data. That's a good idea.
Separate to read data from file and compute statistics and plot results into different
functions. Yes, that is a very good idea. Three different functions.
okay so three functions yeah let's let's do that and should they be in three
separate cells in Jupiter I mean yeah that that works I don't have a
preference on whether to split functions into cells or not so what
should I do can you okay well the situation now is related into three
different cells. So let's make a cell for a read data from file function. Okay. And
copy split the cell there. Yeah. Should I split the measurement cell? Yeah. So the number
of measurements needs to be set here, so yeah, split it out.
Okay.
But now I make these functions, so can you give me some advice?
Yeah.
Well, okay, so to make the, so how to split it into functions, yes.
Okay, so the suggestion was to make a read data from file, so I guess that would be running
this pandas.readcsv, but we probably also want to keep the temperatures equals something
because we don't want to write a function that is just the pandas read from csv function.
We wanted to do a little bit more. So, let's do read these two lines, readcsv and then
temperatures equals column. Okay. So, yeah, define a function and it could be just read
temperatures or get temperatures is fine yeah okay and then we need to call that in the original
cell right right good idea return temperatures that's right i almost forgot that yeah and then
we need to call that in the original cell to get the temperatures uh variable set so temperatures
equals. Now, actually, the read data from file comment has become unnecessary.
Yeah. Or has it?
Does get temperatures tell you that it's from file?
You can make it a doc string.
It could also be the function name directly could be something like read temperatures from file or
what would be read data.
Sorry can you say that again? Something like read data or read data
from or read temperatures from file. If that's the function name then it's
clear what it's doing. Yeah.
Get temperatures
like this. Yeah that that works. Okay yeah. Then we want two other functions
So, should we give this function arguments?
Well, do we do that later? Yeah, so that has not been suggested yet, although I'm not sure if they
thought about it. Okay. They didn't write it down in the suggestion. That's another thing that's
important, of course, in modularity, modular code development. But let's do it as it,
let's stick to this now. So then the other one would be for compute statistics.
Okay, so maybe I'll split here.
Wait. Okay.
Okay, so this returns the mean. Well, it should return the mean. It currently doesn't.
It's missing the return. Okay, so it returns the mean temperature value.
you. Should we get temperatures inside that function? I guess it's fine. I also don't
want to make too many suggestions that are not yet in the discussion. Okay. So let's
keep it as it is. But we need to no, we actually we do need to keep the temperatures. We need
temperatures to be defined in the main part of the code.
Okay. Yeah.
we we need to do mean temperatures equals get temperatures in the main code so i copied this
to here but then we do need we need to pass the temperatures variable to compute statistics
okay so mean so i guess we need to do mean equals compute statistics and then yeah pass the
temperatures there okay okay um there was one more suggested function was plot results
would that would be i guess um everything below this mean equals would go into computer plot
results. Yeah, and I guess I should make the cell above this. Yeah, so I will copy and paste it here.
Okay. Okay, that doesn't need to return anything, but we do need to call it.
and we need to pass temperatures to it it's a not defined inside the function
otherwise so the temperatures and the mean also I guess yes true it need
unless we call well like let's not call compute statistics inside plot and the
plot results. It's probably this way and then we need to give it this argument.
Okay. Okay. Now what else? So I mentioned that in the long run we want to create three different
plots with three different numbers of measurements.
So, what could we do about that? Right now, we are actually, so we have hard-coded a good number
of parameters directly into these functions. And I think the, well, the number of measurements
actually is kind of semi-hard-coded into all of them.
Right. That's just-
So we define the number of measurements there.
So we should make it a parameter in
some one way or another of all of these functions.
Okay.
So yeah, let's start with getTemperature from file.
That should get just
numMeasurements directly as a parameter.
And I can delete the cell then?
Yeah.
Because it's not hard-coded anymore.
Then we can just call it with 25.
Compute statistics.
Should compute statistics get num measurements?
It can.
The other option is to use the length of the temperatures column.
So doing len temperatures works directly.
And because it's actually a pandas data frame,
it doesn't even take any time to calculate.
It's already calculated, so we can just use it directly.
Yeah.
I guess, since this is pandas in a more real project, we would just use the mean, but this
is pretending that some big pandas could do a mean for us.
But anyway, okay.
Yeah, that's true.
Good.
And actually, I mean, that is a good suggestion.
Using pandas functions directly is better than writing your own.
But yeah, let's stick to this for now.
And then in the plot results, we have a few options.
I don't know, there's nothing in the notes right now about this, but how should we do
this?
Well, actually, there is.
Pass the file name as input is a suggestion.
So should it be the first or last argument?
I would make it the last one, because it could, in principle, be optional.
Should we make it possible to do it without a filename?
So you wouldn't save the figure then, I guess.
That would make sense.
So basically, we can plot it only in Jupyter, or we can plot it and save it?
On that note, later we'll want to move this into a script and there we will not have,
we will not be able to show it in Jupyter.
So that could also be an option maybe.
So but I'm not exactly sure what would be the best way of doing that.
I don't know if people have suggestions.
So let's just leave that for now.
We do need to fix all of these function calls now.
Yeah, so getTemperatures needs a number of measurements.
So that was 25.
Compute statistics actually doesn't.
It doesn't?
Okay, yeah.
And then plotResults needs a file name, which previously was 25.png.
Okay.
Okay, so let's see that it runs.
getTemperatures.
Ah, so yeah, I have to run everything in the notebook.
Yeah.
I will do restart and run all.
I wish it would just automatically rerun everything with the click run.
Get temperatures.
Did I misspell it?
No, we renamed it.
Oh, right.
Get temperatures.
File.
There we go.
So one suggestion is we could add some styling arguments to plot results.
That's true.
Okay.
I think it's a bit out of the scope here.
So, do you mean we would add them here?
Okay, let's do a couple of things.
Okay.
So, first of all, there's this hard-coded arguments.
There's this R minus and color equals B, blue.
So, there's red.
What this R minus means is red and connected line.
And the B is for blue, color is blue.
And then the line style with two dashes is, well, a dashed line.
So those could all be optional arguments for this function.
Yeah. So should we do that?
Let's do that.
One thing to think about here though is how much reuse does this function have?
And if this is for just producing plots for your paper, how much options do you want to add?
But optional parameters are generally always fine.
You don't need to give those parameters.
So we can say, yeah, OK, good, temp color is R.
And I guess mean color, maybe.
OK, so what's the benefit of doing it this way?
Well, it makes it easier to go and change the colors in your,
when we have a script that plots all of these,
that creates all of these plots for our paper,
it's easier to go and change a,
the color of say all of the temperature plots.
And I guess if we wanted to plot some with different colors, depending on,
like what it was.
So the one thing I mentioned that we want to do in the long run is to plot at
these three different ways.
Let's do that.
The easiest way to do it here is with a for loop.
So let's start with that.
Should I do it here?
Yeah, let's do it here. So let's do a for loop
of four n measurements in,
and we want the 25, 50, and 100.
Okay and we need to indent these things so what else needs to be changed this
should be end measurements. Yeah and then we probably also want to change the
file name. Should this be, we used a Python F string thing. Yeah F string for a format
of formatted strings. All right useful way of doing that. All right okay nice
looking way. So one suggestion is, should the color and font markers be global variables?
What do you think? I mean, that would make it less modular in the sense that the function
would depend on things that are defined outside it. So it would make it harder to take out
of this specific notebook and use somewhere else.
But the upside also is if you want to enforce a uniform style across your paper with of
course users, some function calls could also use this current optional parameters to change
them.
could do that with global parameters. Although even then I would suggest making it a Python module
and then using this space, the global space in quotation marks inside that Python module.
So yeah, it depends on the situation. There's upsides and downsides. But we want to make
things as modular as possible here because, well, this is the modular code development lesson.
So let's try to reduce global variables as much as possible.
Do we actually have any global variables left? I guess not.
No. Okay.
That's fine.
So everything's controllable here.
And now I think we also, so one thing we haven't, we've been talking about,
we haven't mentioned the word or the expression is side effects so previously these functions
did have some side effects and that means they changed things in a global scope
so some global variables depended on whether these functions were run or not and now
Now we pretty much don't have side effects anymore.
The plotting thing might be changing default axis, but otherwise, yeah.
Should we run it?
Yeah, let's run the whole thing.
I'm curious to see.
And now let's see what people say.
Is there something we can do to improve these plots?
it look different? I guess, yes. So, it's... Yeah, it has a bit more data. But why does
the first one have... Oh, sorry. There is a 25 there as well. Okay. Yeah. So, it's very
hard from... So, okay. We don't have access labels. So, it's a bit hard to tell these
plots apart from each other if you just see one of them. And if we put them in a paper,
should have access labels yeah so where should we do that
in the plot function or in here
is the cell function only going to be used for temperatures and means in the
future or multiple things i would think so
it takes a temperatures and means mean argument
in making it too general might not be a good idea because then
we kind of end up just coding in the parameters instead of coding in the code.
But also we want to make it somewhat general.
So of course, in order to avoid side effects, the label should be set in the plot function
but also we can we can make the labels in the parameters oh one good suggestion
is to set the a global y-axis I'll set the same y-axis to each of these plots
so that we can directly compare them okay
So now we are how do I the X label needs a closing quotation mark okay how do you
actually so it's Y limit right is it PLD dot Y limit or do you need to get the
axis from the plot. ylim or set ylim let's see do we have a okay yes someone
says this so do I call it with zero and the upper limit yeah and first a lower
limit and the upper limit should I have a hard-coded upper limit or as an
argument it I think it should be an argument because it would depend on the
data but then we probably so we need to pass it as an argument okay we can do
that
should there be a default value yeah we're not something like 20 degrees or
oh wait this is yes okay mm-hmm but that means the lower value should be lower
yeah okay the lower value definitely shouldn't be zero because we're actually
always below zero yeah so what would you reckon well it should probably be
variable. I guess this also should be a variable. Minus 15 probably is a good default value here.
Okay, this is not maximation. This is max temperature.
Okay, so we have 20 minutes, so I think it would be good to move to the part where we
make this a script. Let's just try running it first, though.
Okay.
Yeah, okay, well.
Well, okay, now I'm a bit unsatisfied by the fact that the lower limit is not a parameter,
but the higher limit is.
Yeah.
They should both be parameters.
Should I reparse, pass them together as a...
Yeah, okay, like temperature range or Wylim I guess is good enough.
What was the lower one? Minus 20, minus 15.
It was minus 15, but minus... I mean, given what we know about the range actually, you can just pass the, yeah, you can just pass the tuple directly.
like you're just wilding oh well that also works uh like this it works yeah yeah okay i'll try it
yes okay okay and um for measurements from january i guess we probably don't need to go as far as plus
15 but um yeah i find it interesting that i know that this is a higher average temperature
Okay, but yeah, so we got it
Yeah, so okay. It works now. It does what we want. Um
Why would we want to move it to a script?
Well, I mean, I guess we'll have different input files
And yeah in jupyter I have to go actually edit it every time I change the value
Yeah, and
With the script, I can somehow, like, basically, we can make another script that will run this
with different parameters automatically.
Yeah.
And you can, so we can add parameters to the script that you can then from the command
line, you can pass parameters to the script and different temperature, different Y ranges
or different numbers of measurements and so on.
Okay, so to do that, do you want to move the command line or, well, yeah, should I, whatever
text editor you want to open, that's a.
Should I create a new Python file from Jupyter so I can make a text file and we can call
this.
I should give these names.
Temp analysis.py Descriptive name is good.
So one thing that happened when we were moving things in the functions is that we essentially
removed the comments and the function names became the comments and the same goes for
file names.
So a good file name is in itself a comment.
Makes sense.
So the first thing to do to make it a script is to copy everything that runs all the Python
code into the script and in the correct order.
Actually should I export it as something?
Yeah.
Okay, let's try that.
Is there an...
Save and export notebook as executable script.
Okay.
Okay, well, it downloaded it.
I'll go to the command line now, if that's okay.
Yeah.
New Terminal.
Let's see, can I move this down? Yes.
I saw it was called untitled one. So I'm using Linux command line commands here
to copy a file from the default download location to the current place and
and replacing the temp analysis script. I guess I should open it again.
Yes, I guess it didn't.
Yeah. Okay, here we go. Okay, so now there's some extra comments. The good thing is that there's a
comment in the beginning that actually is a useful thing to have. So that tells most
operating systems that this is a Python script so you could run it directly
without calling Python script name but yeah it's not 100% necessary but I mean
it's a nice thing to have, nice thing to know. Should I show that? Yeah, why not.
So we need to make it an executable so we need to change the permissions.
So this is a Linux command.
It says make this like chmod, change mode, and now I can run like this.
It doesn't work.
Does the graphical plotting even work?
I actually don't know.
It probably is actually stuck in the show statement.
So let's go to the plotting.
OK, it did open.
It popped it up.
OK.
And if I close it, it does another one.
And then another one.
So yeah, for the script, we probably
want to remove the plot.show line.
OK.
Or at least make it optional.
Let's make it a parameter so we can
add a parameter that says show plot or something like that.
and then if show plot, plot.show.
Maybe default it to false.
Yeah, yeah, default to false.
Okay.
One very good question.
How about version control?
We are pretty far with our code
and we haven't started using version control.
Should I start with that?
Yeah, let's start version control.
So git init and then I guess we'll commit the script
the script and why not the why not the notebook as well should I give the
notebook a better name first yeah really what should it be called why not temp
analysis temp analysis.ipy and b okay yeah
okay so there is a very good suggestion to include tests but since the previous lesson was tests
i think we will prioritize adding a command line interface
Another suggestion is to add a command line interface using ArcParse.
Do you remember off the top of your head how to do that?
Because if not, I suggest we use Qlik instead of ArcParse.
So, I can do it with ArcParse.
I think I could do that off the top of my head.
but I'm new to Qlik, so maybe we should do that
and you can teach me something.
Okay, let's use Qlik.
So Qlik is built into Python 3,
at least most latest versions.
So you probably don't need to install anything.
You can just import Qlik at the top of the script.
We probably should remove the cell name comments as well.
That's not useful information.
So, yeah, click as it sounds.
And then at the bottom where we have this main section, we make that into a function.
Okay.
Should I call it main?
Yeah.
That makes sense.
usually the thing you run as a script in a Python script is often called main.
Now, to keep this as a script, though, we should add the standard Python boilerplate of
if __name__. That's without the...
On the left side, it's without quotation marks on the right side with. Okay. Then run main.
Okay, what does this do?
Okay, so if you are running this as a script, then the name will be main, otherwise it will
be the file name.
So if you're running this as a script, it will run the main function.
If you are just importing it, it will not run the main function, it will just define
all the functions that are in this file.
So this is useful if you think you might ever want to import the functions we have defined
here.
It's something you usually just do when you write a Python script, at least at some point.
So now we need to change the main function a little bit.
So what parameters should we add?
Let's do at least the number of measurements.
So the first thing we add though is we add a decorator above main that's at click.command
and parenthesis open and close.
And then below that at click.option.
And in the parenthesis, we need to first add the name of the option, the command and argument.
So it would be minus minus measurements or dash dash measurements or num measurements
maybe.
And then let's make it a required parameter.
So comma space required equals true.
Let's say type.
So another argument type equals int and at a help text.
So another parameter help equals
number of measurements to plot.
This though, this is not a list.
Now we're just plotting one number of measurements.
So remove the for loop.
Yeah, remove the for loop.
And now we need to add an argument to the main function
called num underscore measurements.
So the dash becomes an underscore.
Okay, that looks good.
So now it gets num measurements as a,
this function gets num measurements as an argument.
Oh, yeah, good catch.
Yeah. We can also add an input file. Oh, this is something we didn't do yet. So let's add
an input file parameter.
Okay. Could it be before or after numMeasurements?
Well, it should be after, but the order only needs to be the same as the order of arguments
in the function.
So let's call this in file of minus minus in file.
And then the required is true.
And the help text is something like file name or file
name for reading data.
OK, that makes sense.
OK, and we're going to remind people it's CSV.
But now, and now we need to add it as an argument.
So may needs to take in the file argument.
Before or after?
It should be after the number of measurements.
OK.
But now, we are not actually using this in getTemperature.
So let's pass it to getTemperatures.
Maybe the file name should be before,
or well, I guess it doesn't matter that much, but.
To my brain, before makes the most sense,
like most important.
Yeah, it's the, yeah, the most important
for first modifiers later.
Okay.
Okay, so then we go up,
look up to the get temperatures function
and add file name parameter.
And this has a different file name
or different name of the argument,
but I guess that doesn't matter.
Yeah, that doesn't matter.
Okay.
Should we add an output file argument as well?
And then try running it.
Okay, so I will save.
And actually we haven't run it yet.
Python.
Okay, now we have two required arguments.
So let's just see what happens
when we run without the required arguments.
So it tells you that number of measurements is missing,
and it also tells you that you can get
more information by writing dash-dash help.
Should I do dash-dash help?
Yeah. Let's do dash-dash help.
So that will print each possible argument
and the help text we have added to these arguments.
So we need to add a number of measurements,
which is an integer,
and we need to add an input file.
So how many measurements should we do?
Not 25. 25 is standard when we started.
And in file is...
What was the file name?
temperatures.csv
temperatures.csv, okay.
And it saves it to the standard 25.png still, right?
yes yes so we didn't add an output file argument so the output file is numberofmeasurements.png
which works for now but we could also make it an optional argument okay yeah so let's run this
and it should have created the plot file we have created them a number of times so well
six seconds ago. Okay, the other ones are older. So, yeah, it clearly worked. Yeah. Okay,
let's do an optional argument and give it a default value. So, it's almost the same
as the infile. Sorry. Does infile need the two dashes here? Can we make it a positional argument?
If it's always there.
I am not actually sure how you can or whether you can do that with click.
But I mean, there is usually a way of making using.
Yeah.
Creating positional arguments.
Let's try it and see.
So what's the other option?
We need to add a file.
Maybe this could be optional, equals, it's optional, right?
Yeah.
Required is false by default, you don't have to give it the required, but you can give
it the default value.
So it's not required, you probably should give it the default value.
But in this case, I guess the default should be none.
And then we can construct the filename from the number of measurements.
Okay.
Yeah.
Non-output filename default, or no, default, how do you do?
So then we need to check if outfile needs to be a parameter of the main function.
It should be the last parameter of the main function.
Do I need to set a default to none?
I don't think so.
I don't think it makes a difference.
Yeah.
OK.
So
should I try something here?
If.
If outfile is none, outfile
equals.
This thing based on the number of measurements.
Yeah.
and then we can use that out file and I guess I could do more complicated things
here like also include the input file name as one of the options and so on
yeah but well I mean I guess this is good enough yeah okay
save it and give it a try yeah let's do that okay so I come back to my
terminal. And now, if this works as I hope, since there's not the dashes here,
so there's two kinds of arguments. There's optional arguments that have dashes,
and traditionally they can be in any order. And there's positional arguments like this,
which have to be in a certain order, but you don't need to give the name of them.
So, oftentimes, the important arguments that are always required become positional, and
you give them by order, and optional ones, well, they're like that.
Should I try running?
Yeah, let's see.
Let's see if it works.
Default none.
Ah.
Okay.
Default equals none.
Syntax error.
There's a comma missing.
Yes.
No options name.
Okay, so I guess it has to be.
Dash dash file.
So it should be possible to have an option or maybe it's an argument then.
Could it be argument?
Well, let's see. Yes, it needs to be an argument.
So, it's a click.argument and then just a name for the argument, and it can be required.
Oh.
making an argument instead of option has probably failed somehow.
It might be that it needs to be before the options. I'm not sure.
Okay. Well, let's go back to option.
Yeah.
So we have to give it the infile. Let's see. What else?
So yeah, someone asks if the click.option lines need to match the order
in the function arguments. And yeah, that is how click works.
So it doesn't go by name.
They always need to be the same order. No, yeah, it doesn't go by name.
Okay.
Yeah, there we go. So it worked. I guess we don't need to look at the plot again.
But can we try saving to a different file name?
Yeah, let's try that.
And then I think it's time for a break.
Yes.
Because we have a couple of good questions and a few other things to do after the break.
How many can we plot?
Can we plot 500?
I don't know how many measurements there are in the file.
There are not 500 days in a year.
might fail well let's do 200 okay I'm gonna do it now I push enter and it
worked okay so there should be a new file with a name called 200 plot 200 and
yep it worked yeah it's probably not one measurement per day because otherwise
stay number 175 you wouldn't expect to go below minus 15.
Right, yeah, yeah.
So it would make sense to add more arguments and make the script more general, like adding
the option of giving three different numbers of measurements if we actually want these three
different plots in our paper, or just write another script that does that instead.
Yeah.
Okay.
But otherwise...
Yeah.
Let's go to the break end, I guess.
So there's a correction that says click is not in the Python default library.
I'm actually not 100% sure about this.
Maybe it's not.
I have the impression that it is in some of the latest versions of Python.
At least I generally don't install it, but maybe I just have it somewhere.
But it is good to include it as a dependency anyway.
So yeah.
Okay.
It's not a part of the standard library.
So yeah, it needs to be a dependency, which we'll do after the break.
Yes.
So see you at 12 past.
Sounds good. Bye.
you
Hello, we're back.
Hello.
Or so we hope.
So where were we now? We had just done this command line.
So, [name], for this command line thing, how is it better than making a notebook I can rerun?
Yeah, so one thing is that it could be a utility that you share to many people,
that people just install and can run without knowing any Python. But really for a lot of
people also a notebook is something that's easier to run than a command from the command line.
So that's actually a bit hard to say which one is better. So I added a question in the notes
actually. So please vote and give your opinions on what's actually better. Which one would you
rather get if someone's sharing a project with you. But the big upside in a command line interface
is that you can then use it to script an entire workflow from downloading the files
to producing the plots and maybe producing tables for your paper, plots for your paper.
Like you can go from raw data to a finished paper in a single command once you write the script.
Yeah. And I guess for the computing clusters and so on, that's very relevant, isn't it?
Yeah. Yeah, it is. Usually you don't get an interactive environment for command,
so you don't get a Jupyter notebook or a computing cluster.
This actually happens pretty often when people come to us. They have a Jupyter notebook and says,
says, I need to run this on the cluster for 10,000 different values.
And well, if it's a loop in a Jupyter notebook, you can only run it on one processor.
But once it is as a command line, it's really easy to write another interface, like whether
it's using state make or your own script or whatever that will go and run it 10,000 separate
times on 10,000 different computer processors and then combine them later.
Okay, so we have some time rather limited I think.
One thing we probably should do is move a bit closer to a package and also this is something
that also helps answer this question. So what I'm thinking of is taking the functions from
this file that could be used in a different project and turning them into a module that
you could share with other people. So one question is, do you think the plotting function
is too specific, or should we just include all of these three functions?
Should we pretend the plotting function is too specific and the other ones are the general
code?
So let's say the plotting function is something we wrote to have a uniform plotting thing
for a single project or for a paper, and the other two are something that could easily
be used in other projects as well. So let's take the first two functions and create a
new file or a new Python module.
Okay. So to the browser, new, new text file.
So this could be something like temperature utilities, that's pi.
And then we need to paste these functions here.
So these two get moved.
Yeah.
Does this need any other dependencies?
it does depend on no it's not doing any plotting does it it depends on only on
pandas I guess okay so that we need to import pandas is panda still needed here
I don't think so.
I will move it.
Okay.
And now what do I have to do?
Okay, so now we need to import the functions
from this temputils.
One way to do it without having to change any of the code below is to import
from TempUtils, but then this maybe depends a bit more on,
oh, sorry, this makes it a bit less readable
because now if you import specific functions
and then you're looking at the code below,
nothing about that function name
tells you that it came from TempUtils
and not from Pandas, for example, or Matplotlib.
So yeah.
So maybe import temputils.
And you can give it a shorter name if you want to.
But it's fine as it is.
And then when we call the functions,
it needs to be temputils dot something.
And compute statistics also.
OK.
Now it should work again.
And then for distributing this code,
one very important thing that we haven't done yet
is keeping track of dependencies.
So in our original notebook, we didn't really
have any way of doing that.
I mean, you can always create a requirements.txt file
and have a list.
So, okay, so how would you, let's think if this is a bigger project, let's imagine that
you have more than two files in the project that import things.
How would you figure out what the dependencies are?
Well, what I usually do.
What I usually do.
Yeah, what would you do?
You don't actually have to do it to show it, but what would you do?
So I'd make a new virtual environment with nothing installed in it.
I would try running my things.
I would see what fails with import errors.
I would add that to requirements.txt in the virtual environment and then repeat until
it's done.
That would be basically exactly my answer as well.
We would create an empty environment and then install packages until it works and put all
of those package names into requirements.txt.
But now we do know what we want, so we can just write a requirements.txt file for this
project.
Another way of doing it, of course, is you start a requirements.txt when you still can
track all the dependencies in your head when they are just in a couple of files and then
you write them down and when the project grows you keep adding stuff to the requirements.
Because it just pandas and click that's required. And matplotlib.plotlib.
How do you make sure that we got this correct and that it hasn't become
doesn't go off after a time.
Well, I mean, basically the same trick.
You create an empty environment, you install the stuff in requirements.txt, and then you
see if it runs.
But actually, since we just set up tests in the previous session, what our test workflow
on GitHub did is install all the requirements and then run the tests.
So if the tests succeed, clearly the requirements were sufficient.
So that means not only when we have the test, it's validating our code, it validates all
the requirements.
So if someone else wants to use the code, we can be reasonably sure that it has all
they need and there's not something obvious being left out of it.
Yeah, exactly.
So that's a great thing about these test workflows, because they don't run on your machine.
If the test succeeds, then it runs on at least two different machines.
It runs on your machine, but it also runs on this cloud system that's just installed
from scratch with only the dependencies you specified.
So that's a lot better than just running on one machine.
Yeah.
Okay.
So requirements.
I guess we already have the Conda environment, so there's  well, and we shouldn't be
too specific about how things are done in Python. We have another course for that, actually.
Yeah, so that's fine. So yeah, now we have specified the requirements and should be
installable by anyone. I mean, we don't really have a lot of time. We could just move to wrap up.
One option would be to add tests to
to all the functions we defined, but how complicated would that get? Yeah, compute statistics is
easier to test, we can just test that one.
One more thing that we touched on, but we didn't, I guess, quite finish. What do you
think about the function name compute statistics that's a bit general for what
it does yeah but it computes one specific statistic it it just computes
the mean yeah so maybe we should change it to compute mean yeah should I do it
or yeah yeah let's do that but that's that's these I was about to say last
step, that's the second to last step, then we commit the changes to git and give it a
nice name, or give it a nice commit message.
compute statistics, compute mean.
Now we probably did too many changes between commits, so we're going to have a big commit
that changes a lot of things.
Yeah.
Should I try running it to verify it works?
Yeah, yeah, let's do.
Okay. And you could also run PyTest on test and you need the name of the file.
So it's temputils.
Name error compute.
Ah, of course.
Yes.
So I forgot to rename it.
Compute.
I typed the name wrong.
Assert to, I did the test wrong.
Hey, it worked finally.
Great.
Okay.
Now, there were a bunch of things wrong with the test.
Now that it works,
are we sure that it's correct?
You shouldn't stop thinking if the test is right,
just because you get the correct result.
Yeah.
But yeah, I think the mean of 1, 2, and 3 is, in fact, 2.
That's correct.
So from the command line, I will git add temp analysis,
temp utils, requirements.
From before, we have learned git status to see what's missing.
We have the plots that are generated.
Should we make a gitignore file?
Maybe we can...
That kind of, well, that would eat up the time
of the, well, the wrap up and discussion.
But it's a useful thing to remind people of though.
Yeah.
Should we go to notes then?
Okay, yeah, let's go to notes.
And yeah, just please continue to have a conversation about it.
How could we still make this better?
What else would you do to in this project?
Did you think it was useful?
I thought of another benefit of the command line.
So let's say we send this analysis,
and it's some reasonably complicated thing, to someone,
and they want to run it on their own data.
It's easier for them to have this defined interface
that says, here's how you give the input file
and how you configure it,
than to have to go figure out your code,
modify it, and whatever.
If we run several different analysis, so let's say we have a different input file that we are testing,
then we don't have to modify our main code for every individual task,
and have to remember how to go back to the tasks we had before.
How similar is this to what you would do in your own work?
It depends a bit. Often I don't start from Jupyter.
I often start from scripts, but if there's a lot of plotting involved then I would start from Jupyter.
And then it would pretty much follow this workflow.
Yeah.
I think at some point, certain parts get complicated enough that they make more sense as a separate
utility module.
And then that might become a package of its own.
That's just the dependency of the script.
And yeah, if the end result is something other than displaying plots in Jupyter, then it
would become a script at some point or a command line interface.
But Jupyter is pretty good at displaying plots and running a relatively simple Python script.
So one option here would have been kind of to go back to Jupyter.
If you want to give this analysis to someone who finds Jupyter more comfortable than the
command line, then you could import this utility functions into Jupyter, import all the functions
needed into Jupyter, then just call them in the Jupyter notebook in a single cell, basically.
So we might have the Jupyter notebook that's used for development and testing and exploring
new data, in addition to the command line which runs known analysis on existing data.
Yeah.
Okay.
Um.
Hmm.
Okay.
Well, this is our time limit.
Yeah.
Um, so people are already filling in the feedback form.
But yeah, please do.
We'd like to get feedback for today.
So we do have a little bit more, so don't leave yet.
We have an outro session.
And also, we plan on talking.
There are some requests to talk a little bit about AI code
generation and things like that.
that. Should we talk about the AI code stuff first? So what are the specific
questions? Maybe we can add a section? Yeah.
Let's see, what do people think here?
What should we talk about, if anything?
So who uses AI to make code?
I must say that I do not right now.
I have now started using it all the time, since my employer is providing the license,
and then why not?
So yeah, GitHub Copilot.
So how does it work?
It essentially makes suggestions based on the code you have right now.
There is a chat interface as well, so you can ask it to write some code that does X.
But the interface that works better actually is usually the code completions.
It's mainly like there's always been this code completion systems that try to guess
the kind of code you would want to add and allow you to, for example, write in languages
that have more boilerplate code, create a class, like write all the boilerplate code
for a class with a couple of, typing a couple of keystrokes, and Copilot is doing a lot
of that for me. I see. It's like all the standard ARC parse stuff that I'd always be making. Yeah.
Yeah. Okay. But it goes a little bit beyond, but it cannot do anything
really new or really complicated. So it's just this basic, relatively basic things.
It will usually have a suggestion for even more complicated things, but it's more often than not
not that you just have to go and change a lot of things. It's only the basic structure
that's correct. But it's still doing a lot of work, though. I don't know, how would
I evaluate? How much time is it saving? 50% or a bit more of actual coding time?
Yeah. What's the license of the generated code?
For Copilot it's essentially they just give you the copyright as long as you know
as the usual warning is it might in some I think relatively rare cases output code that is an exact
copy of something that already is out there. In fact, it will do that very often if you
take something really simple, but that's just like you would type it out by hand in exactly
the same way anyway. So that code is very structured. So there's a lot of exact copies
out there. But yeah, I mean, at some point when it gets complicated enough, you have to
You have to know yourself that it's not a copy of something.
And that's a big caveat.
But yeah, otherwise, usually they just give you the copyright,
because otherwise the service model wouldn't really make a lot of sense.
So, I heard that we should do the outro before this discussion, too, before people leave.
So, okay, mix that up.
So, [name], would you like to grab the screen and summarize everything for us and tell us what we should do next?
Yes, hello.
Okay.
Hello, hello. Can you hear me all right?
Yes.
and can you see my screen? Yes I can see it's now also on the stream. Okay thank
you very much [name] and [name] for this very interesting session. So this was now
the very last session of our workshop but it's not the very last thing
that you can join for this course. So stay with me for a moment to tell you
more about that. So this was the Code Refinery workshop for this spring. We would like to
thank you, the participants, very much for participating, putting so many questions and
so good feedback after each day in our collaborative document and discussing the questions and like
being very active there. We'd also like to thank our team leaders and hosts that have
made this possible to spread to even more people and provide more personal support to some of our
participants here. Then also a very big thank you to all of our instructors of this workshop. It was
a quite big group this time. I think it went all in all very well. Then we also had some
Some people working in the background that have so far never appeared on stream that
were answering the questions in the collaborative document in addition to the instructors.
And then we also had some local partners that hosted the rooms there and answered questions.
So you all make these workshops possible and so enjoyable.
Thank you very much.
[name] and [name] have already told you about the feedback section, so if you go to the
collaborative document and in the very bottom we have our feedback, a little bit about today
and then you can also let us know what you thought overall about this workshop, no matter
if you joined all the days or just a few of them, like let us know how you like this workshop,
you like this format, things that we can do better, things that you really much like
that we should not get rid of, and all these kind of things.
And if you come up with something later, you can also send us an email to support.coderefinery.org.
Or you can also, and you are all very welcome to, also without feedback, join our chat.
It's on Zulip.
So you can find this behind the link.
Actually, is this document linked from the collaborative document?
If not, I would like to ask one of my colleagues here to link that so that you can click those
links also.
Then if you have struggled with some of the exercise instructions or found some broken
links or have some update suggestions for our lesson material, now during the first
week of this course, you have learned how to do issues, pull requests, so you can practice
that on our lesson material and we are very happy to get also like feedback that way and we are
always at least trying to develop this workshop materials further latest before the next workshop
so we are really relying on your feedback here and also we will take a look at the
questions that you ask and see if we can improve the material to make these things more clear.
At some point in the future you will likely receive a post-workshop survey that is then about how your work in the long run has been affected by visiting this workshop.
So we know that there is like a lot of topics here and it's a lot of things to take in at such a short time.
But maybe after like a few weeks, you may get back to some of the topics and you may get an understanding to where these topics can help you in your work.
So that's why it will take some time before you will get this workshop, but it will come.
And if you get it, then please answer it. That helps us a lot to continue the work that we are doing.
Yeah, because it has been a lot of material, a lot of possibly new concepts for you.
This is just a starting point and there is so much more to learn and dig into.
You may have noticed in this week too that we tried to show some of the exercises on
stream, but there were also in many lessons, many more exercises that we did not go through.
So you can go back to the material, look through them, try to do them yourself.
And if you do that within the next two weeks and you have some trouble with this, you can
also come to our bring your own code sessions.
And this is also if you have some more questions like we had this morning, for example, for
the automated testing, many people were asking something about like how to do this, how to
apply this to your own code.
If you have questions like this, then this bring your own code sessions are a very good
place to come.
Many of our instructors will be there, and we will try to help you further with the topics
discussed in this workshop.
So it's the next Tuesdays, 1, 2, 3, and the link will be sent to all registered participants.
As mentioned many times already, our materials are publicly available.
are all open source and will continue to be updated. You can also reuse them for your
own workshops and this link leads you to the main overview of all the lessons. So there's not just
the lessons that we went through here in this workshop, but there's also a few more there.
So you can go and take a look. The videos will stay on YouTube, you can always like re-watch
them. They also have these little nice section tags that you can jump around to the topics that
are of interest to you. And then we have a lot of local partners that provide support
with the topics around this workshop. And you can find the list of the partners here
for Finland, Sweden, Norway and Denmark. Many also with their link to the training calendar
where there is like further training going more into high performance computing or
I don't know what we other have, scientific computing with Python and these kind of things.
So you can check them out and some of them are also not necessarily only for the group for example
at Aalto University in Finland, but some of these trainings are also open for all.
So even if you are not in these areas, I would recommend to check out the training calendars of
these institutions. And then again, a reminder about the certificates. If you want one,
check out the course web page, you can do that briefly. Up top you can find this tab to
certificates, if you click that there's instructions on what you can do to get a certificate for this
course. And then how you can support us, so we are a project and it always helps to like tell
everyone about us, tell your friends if you like this course, tell them about our materials,
our webpage, use our social media handles. We have been trying to post a little bit about this
workshop too, so use those to re-share your experience about it. We are also eagerly reading
these posts, so please make use of that. And we will probably have more workshops of this type
further developed in some way, so you can always come back as a team leader, for example,
so you can bring your colleagues, sit together in a room and watch the stream together and then do
the exercises together, for example, like some of you have already done. And then you can also
become part of the Code Refinery team. In general, the project lives currently still from
in-kind contributions by the organizations, meaning that our organizations sponsor our time
for the project. So if that is something that sounds interesting to you and especially your
organization, please get in touch. As mentioned, we live in the chat, so that's where really
everything goes, where we also have a nice help channel where you can add your questions that you
have for example surrounding this workshop or also later when you implement these things you can
go and ask for help there's a lot of so-called research software engineers especially around that
really enjoy helping people with their computational research challenges and then we also have a
newsletter about once or twice a year where we update about upcoming workshops or this we recently
switched our newsletter provider, so let's hope this goes well. You can find the link
on our webpage behind the newsletter. And then I mentioned already this research software
engineers, so many of our instructors are actually research software engineers and we
also have an association, the Nordic Research Software Engineers, where you can find the
link behind this one here. I think it's just nordic-rse.org. Let's see. And so the research
software engineers, they are like these people that are between the researchers and the software
developers that combine this experience of both of these worlds. And basically, the code refinery
workshop could be also called like a introduction to research software engineering. So if you liked
what you learned here and would like to go further in that, then the Nordic RSE community is a very
nice place to be in. Basically we live also in the same chat as Code Refinery
in the Nordic RSE channel. We sometimes have some like seminar series and upcoming now also
So a conference in Espoo in Finland in the end of May that you can still submit contributions
to that you can still come and join us for.
And we are also on Twitter X, sorry.
And that was it with the wrap up.
Do my fellow colleagues here on call still have to add something to this?
other upcoming courses do we have? Someone commented on that in the feedback.
Yes, I guess the next one that is by some of the code refinery community is the
tools and techniques, Tuesday's tools and techniques for HPC, but we don't have a
event page for that yet. It will come up in April and you can probably find these
information soon on the Aalto training page, I would guess.
So, the other courses of the similar form, in the beginning of June, we have a live stream
kickstart course, mainly hosted by Aalto University, but each year some others join.
And it's about scaling your work from your local things to a computer cluster.
And, ah, okay, I'm under attack.
So okay, well at least you get some entertainment
Yeah, and then in the autumn, we have a yearly Python for Scientific Computing course,
which is quite similar to what we're doing here. And who knows, maybe more in the future.
Through Code Refinery, sometimes we advertise other courses by partners,
which should be of similar quality.
Should we go back to the notes? Yes. What other? So one of the biggest changes we've had is we
made the second week more demo-based rather than exercise-based, and we'd like your comments on
that. So part of the reason was that we didn't have as many exercises the second week anyway,
So when people came prepared for exercises, then there were not enough
and helpers, the people who were prepared to help with the exercises, didn't have
enough to do. So, yeah.
Yeah.
Any other comments?
Do any other instructors want to join here and give general questions and answers?
Yeah. Should we? Oh, [name] is here. Do you have any thoughts on AI coding?
Yeah, first of all, thanks for today. I was watching it and I was typing. Really enjoyed
the many questions. I had to really type a lot. It was really cool today. Yeah, I mean,
AI coding exists, it's an important tool.
Do you use AI coding much?
Yes, I do.
Okay.
I do, so AI-assisted coding.
Sometimes I write comments and then it tries to code,
or I write a code and it tries the comments for me,
or I ask it to write a test,
or I write the test first and ask it to write the code
that matches the test.
It saves a lot of time.
There were a few questions and points about translating.
And that's kind of one way of thinking about what these AI models are really good at.
It's essentially, well, I guess there's two big things.
And one is translating from one format to another.
So that would include also taking a code
and writing tests for it,
or taking a test and writing code that fulfills that test.
And like sort of trying to go from one type
of information to another,
or just going from one language to another.
Yeah, and that works really well.
So I, for instance, I'm now learning R.
So I'm a beginner in R.
So what I've tried a few times
is that I have a Python code and I ask it to translate it
to R and then I have a really good starting point.
So it can help me actually learn the language.
I can see like, okay, this is something that works
and I can study it and I can improve it
and maybe it's not perfect,
but I believe that it can also help beginners
to get started and learn coding.
So the other big thing that it's really good at
is just remembering stuff.
So it's like, in principle, Google also is useful
for finding any, or any web search is good
for finding all of the same information
but this is more integrated to the actual coding workflow.
So it can not just find the documentation for some library
but actually suggest how to use it in your code.
Although the information does tend to be old pretty quickly.
So you have to take that into account.
Yeah.
So from the whole workshop, what are your main takeaway messages that you'd like people
to carry with them.
Anyone? Version control is super useful. It makes everything possible. Yeah.
Everything runs on top of version control and publishing your code as early as possible
is relatively, it's easy and it enables a lot of useful things.
What do you mean by publishing as soon as possible?
You mean putting on, like making it available by GitHub or similar?
Yeah, or at least putting it online somewhere, and preferably with a license.
Yeah, because GitHub and many of these platforms, they provide free stuff to public projects, usually.
So the sooner you go public, the sooner you can start using these.
Okay, does anyone else have any other comments in the notes?
Or should we wrap it up?
I see a question from earlier, where to find more resources and examples on modular development
in testing for research?
What would you say there?
It's a great question.
I'm not sure there is this like one resource for it.
Yeah.
I would study.
Have a look at the code that you are using.
And how do they do testing?
How do they structure their code?
But it can be a little bit too big.
So maybe look at the smaller projects.
Have a look at other projects, how they do it.
I'm not aware of one book that will discuss this in one place.
Are you aware of any other things that cover these topics specifically for research in
this much or more detail?
Did most researchers sort of figure this out themselves, or how does it go?
I mean, I really don't know.
I learned this sort of by following other projects and having to figure it out myself.
So that's why I like this course so much, because it can save other people that effort.
I have a feeling that still a lot of it is figuring it out yourself, but at least you
see the vision and, well, if our audience is researchers, then you're good at figuring
out new things.
So as long as you know what to look for, you can find and adapt.
There are a couple of papers that are nice, which is this Ten Simple Rules to etc. etc.
Ten Simple Rules to Make Your Code More.
Oh, they are nice.
They are good summaries.
Yeah.
And I guess it would be nice if we made a collection and listed all of them.
There's a link to a book called The Turing Way, which I know about.
it cover the details of coding? I see chapters on code testing, code review, and so on. So
I guess that would be a good thing to look at that goes into some good depth.
Yeah, okay, should we call it good then?
We're almost at the hour now.
So thanks to everyone who attended.
Yeah, I can just say we will send an email to everybody with some summary. We don't forget
that in a week. So next Tuesday, the Tuesday after, you can show up at the sessions, bring
your code, bring your questions, it will be on zoom, it will not be recorded, not streamed.
We will email you the connection details. And I hope people show up and that we can
and show up with questions.
Yes.
Okay.
Well.
Should I hang it up then?
Thanks a lot and good luck in your future research.
Thanks everybody.
See you soon.
Thank you.
Bye.
you