still have some 10 minutes [name] are you there? I'm here there was a short network
error but I think we have recovered. Okay was it on my side or on your side? It
It might be on my side.
OK.
So maybe I'll ask you.
Did we say how people can write questions in the notes
at any time?
True.
So that's the same notes document
that you already were using for these icebreakers.
You can use it for writing questions there.
And so anything that comes to your mind,
please write it there.
And then we can give answers.
It also gets all the links to whatever
we're looking at and any notes we're sending to you.
And everyone you don't see on the stream
is there watching that and answering your questions.
So go for it.
Okay, that's all.
Yes, we have a big network of helpers already.
So if I ask you, Suza, what is scientific computing?
How would you answer that?
Basically, I would answer that scientific computing
is, at the baseline, every part of computing that helps science, that helps researchers.
And then, obviously, you would want to ask, what is computing? And, well, computing is
using computers instead of pen and paper to solve your problems. So solving problems with
help of computer to help research is what scientific computing is.
Yes, I totally agree. There's this funny xkcd. Someone said that there's always an xkcd for
anything related to computing or computers. And you know, is this your machine learning system?
So you know, it's like a pile of stuff. And sometimes we have this maybe approach to computing
that we might not understand all the bits that are happening inside the pile. So we kind of maybe
have a kind of some sort of black box experience with the computing that some data comes in and
something comes out. So this very short introduction is actually trying to, you know, open this black
box. And I think it's still important to get the basic. So like [name] was saying, a common site,
if you're computing flowchart would be that you know that you have some data,
whether it's collected data or simulations, and then there is some processing happening,
and then you generate some outputs that can be statistical tables,
AI model, machine learning models, whatever is the output, and then you know you write papers,
posters, figures, and publish, and become successful, and you know be a famous scientist.
But then what actually happens in practice, and I think this is very important because
we were chatting with others that sometimes this jargon of the basically hardware that
is needed for doing scientific computing is just assumed that everybody knows about everything,
but maybe it is not like that.
And I also think that it's important once someone knows how the components are connected
with each other.
And if they're actually physically close to each other
or physically far away from each other,
then it can also affect, you know,
is it going to be fast?
Because yes, the memory that I'm using
is really few millimeters away
from the computing that is happening.
Or is it that the data that I'm loading
is far away in some remote server in the cloud,
as they say.
So what do you see here in this type of stacked
picture is basically that we, you right now,
even with your laptop or with your desktop computer
that you're watching this stream,
or even with the phone, because the thing is similar.
We have the hardware level and inside the hardware,
the physical box, there are CPUs, GPUs,
RAM, SSD, and the network.
So these elements, there are the definitions here
and we will not go through the definitions.
Maybe this is familiar to all of you,
But already, if you feel that you don't know
what are all these elements,
then you already might be kind of missing
in the moment where you later you will see
that you request some computing resources
from an HPC cluster.
You are going to be asked, do you need CPUs?
How many do you need?
How much RAM do you need?
Do you need GPUs?
Do you need to use the local disk,
which is this SST here?
Or will you use some network disk
that is not physically inside the hardware that you use.
So these type of things are actually things
that you will need to think about daily
when you work with high-performance computing systems,
but they're basically things that sometimes you,
how can I say, forget that they are always there
whenever you are working.
On top of the hardware level,
there's the operating system
that basically is basically interacting with the hardware
and then enabling the fact that on top
of the operating system,
you can run your Python or MATLAB or R.
There's a nice little box here about containers.
We will not cover those today,
but basically it's like bringing another operating system
with the software on top of the operating system
and the hardware.
So without going through this definition
that maybe some of you have,
I just want to show that we have a great video series
on understanding computing through the kitchen metaphor.
So I will not show the video right now,
but it's linked in the page.
And in the video, there's gonna be [name] with a cat.
Actually, they are going to basically explain
how all these elements, the CPU, the GPU,
the RAM, and so on, are kind of connected to each other
and what it actually means in practice
for your day-to-day work.
There's also a set of slides
with this metaphor of the parallel computing in the kitchen.
And so the metaphor kind of goes,
if I can cover it just briefly,
we have still a couple of minutes,
that each burner of a stove is like a core,
it's like one of this CPU.
and then the whole store stove is like the processor.
Then, you have the memory, which is the counter space
where you can leave some of your ingredients that you need,
that you need to move inside these pots
on top of the burners.
And then of course, if the kitchen counter
have the ingredients that are ready easily to access,
you might have more ingredient
that are a little bit more far away in the fridge,
for example, or in some other cupboards.
And then you have the instructions, which is the program.
So the recipe that takes all these ingredients
and on top of one core or maybe more core,
if you need to cook multiple things in parallel,
can basically process the ingredients
and generate the output, which is the food.
We don't have time to go through this metaphor
and everything, but I really like this picture
that, for example, what if you don't have enough CPU
or enough memory.
This, I don't know if this has ever happened to you
in your kitchen, probably not.
But you know, you have these cases
where the kitchen counter is too small.
You just can't fit all the ingredients there.
You don't have enough burners to cook everything.
And so this is also when things might start slowing down
or maybe where your process might actually die
because you don't have enough memory and it gets killed.
Another last thing that I want to mention,
that sometimes people have expectations about clusters.
Working in a cluster doesn't necessarily means
that it's gonna be faster.
And here there's a nice example
that the laptop processing unit
might actually have more power than the stove
that has to share all the power
with the multiple processing units.
So often your laptop as a single processing unit
is much faster than let's say that the same processing unit
in a cluster, in a server.
But of course, it's also kind of the compromise
that on the laptop you have only one
or a handful of processing unit.
In the cluster, you can actually run thousands,
tens of thousands of processing unit in parallel.
But then again, what you need to understand
is that is your code written in a way
that can actually use the tens of thousands
of processing unit?
Or is it that when you move it to the cluster,
it will just use one processing unit,
which is actually slower than the one
that you have in your laptop.
So all of these will be covered later
with the example during the morning.
And just the final picture, the GPU.
I find it very funny.
So where GPUs are like the burners,
but in parallel, you can cook multiple,
in this case, you know, chickens.
So it's a large system that at the same time
can do the same operation multiple times.
So hopefully this was, how can I say,
inspiring enough and motivating enough
and maybe you all knew about these things.
We don't really have time to cover this
but you can read this page
and there's even a video related to this page.
But basically this is what I was just saying
that sometimes moving the stuff to the cluster
doesn't automatically make things faster.
So, I'm basically ready to switch to pass the ...
Or do you want to add anything, Suza,
that might be good for clarifying?
No, I think you covered most things.
Excellent. So, I would also switch the screen
to [name] and [name],
but do you want me first to explain a bit
of the geography of the cluster or will you go through, you know, what is the login node then?
I think it's probably good if you would explain that.
All right, so basically one thing, like you're all familiar with your own laptop or desktop, you
log in with your username and password and basically this is where you would be, you know,
that you have a desktop or you have a laptop it can be in the Alto network that you see here because
it's in a it's in a it's in a office at Alto or maybe you're at home in the internet with your
with your laptop so then we Alto uses this virtual private network and the idea is not to make your
life more difficult the idea is that once you know that your laptop your personal laptop or
or your computer that are part of the network,
then other bits that are inside the network
also becomes accessible.
The reason, of course, is kind of confidentiality
of the information that might be moving
between these different elements.
And in general, it also makes it easier
to prevent external attacks.
So using the VPN in the end is useful,
but of course there are also ways to connect to this system
without necessarily being in the VPN.
But for simplicity, let's say that now
you're in the Alto VPN.
So now you actually have access
to all these different elements that you see here.
There are the department workstation,
maybe you have one, or maybe that you're given a laptop.
We also have this type of external interface,
vdi.alto.fi, where you can basically get a virtual desktop.
That's the VD, virtual desktop interface,
so that you know you are, I don't know,
out for a conference, but you don't have
your Alto laptop with you and you need to access something,
you can always go to this vdi.alto.fi
and see the file system,
the same thing that you will still see in the department.
And then there's the Triton cluster.
So the idea of the cluster
is that there is another network inside the network.
And this network between these hundreds of computers
is actually very, very fast, extremely fast.
It's called InfiniBand,
and it's a type of connectivity
between all these multiple computers that we have there
that it allows really quick exchange of information.
Instead, if something from the Triton cluster
would need to talk, let's say,
with the department or station
or with the storage that is outside of the Triton network,
things would already feel slower.
The thing is that to enter the Triton cluster network,
you need to go through the so-called login node,
which is triton.data.fi.
Now I put this sign there,
which is, for those who have a driving license,
it means that you should not stop there,
even if you wanna stop the car for a few seconds,
it's not good, you need to move on.
And the idea is that the login node
is good for connecting to the cluster,
running simple things,
but then what you wanna do is getting a dedicated node
that is just for you with the resources that you need.
Do you need a CPU, one CPU, many CPUs,
a little RAM, lots of RAM, and so on.
This will come clearer with the examples
that are given in the morning
and also later in the afternoon with the exercises.
Then Triton has its own storage system.
And the reason is exactly is this speed reason
that if Triton would try to access the storage system
that you have in other Alto computers,
it would take the Alto network down
because all the IO that is going on between the nodes
and the external storage will be too much.
So this is why we have a dedicated
so-called scratch storage system.
The disadvantage of that,
the good thing is that Scratch is huge.
We have five petabytes of Scratch space,
and it's also very fast to read and write,
but the problem with Scratch is that it's not backed up,
and it's kind of the price to pay
for having a huge and fast file system.
So you understand that it's,
this is the similar kind of architecture
is also in other computing cluster like CSC.
So you understand that it's every time you kind of feel
that your analysis is ready,
it's time to move it out of the scratch file system.
Last thing that I want to mention is that we also have
a kind of virtual desktop interface to the Triton cluster
in this ondemand.triton.aalto.fi.
So if, again, you are not with your computer
or you need to visualize the files that you have generated
or the picture or it runs on Jupyter Notebook,
then this is the website that you want to visit.
And I think I covered everything.
How do you actually get, if you want to move something out from scratch, how do you get it out?
Yeah, this will be my understanding some of the examples in the morning, but basically there are different ways.
One way actually would be exactly this with this on demand, for example, that you can see the file system and get something out.
But of course, there are all these other,
in our documentation, we have, for example,
you can actually, how can I say,
make this file system visible in your operating system.
So let's say that you have, I don't know,
out the windows, you can actually make a scratch
so that you see it with all the other letters
of the disks that you have there.
And then from there, you can basically copy some files out.
So there's multiple different ways
of getting data in and out of the Scratch file system.
And we will show a bit of those.
But yes, that's a very, very important question
that we often get.
All right, so is there something to lift up
from the notes document
or do you wanna take the screen share?
There is some stuff there.
I guess I can switch to the notes.
Do you have the notes open on your computer
or should I switch there?
I should have them here.
Okay.
In the kitchen metaphor,
what are the notes we define for Slurm?
Yeah, this is a good question.
Maybe Slurm can be seen as the chef manager that coordinates
all the other little chefs in the multiple kitchens that
are in this department, or in this apartment building.
And I don't know if that's a good metaphor,
but I see that people are answering, so that's good.
Is there a smart way to move data between Triton, Scratch,
and department?
Yeah, this will be covered.
And it's partly covered.
All right, I don't think there's anything to mention.
So maybe we can now switch to you, [name] and [name].
Yes.