There.
Now it works.
Okay.
Yes.
We're getting the sharing set up properly.
Now we've had this nice demo, and I think, well, if I was learning here.
the things I would have understood hopefully and well now I know from own experience I've
learned it now I've heard this all this and I think I understand it but in a week or so
I will realize I forgot half of it and I actually didn't really understand the details of this
suspect. So where do I go? What can I do? I can answer to this question with our beautiful help
page. So in our web pages that hopefully are already familiar to you, we have a section all
dedicated to help. We even have a video actually there a few years ago in a similar workshop like
this one we had a guest [name] from Code Refinery Norway he gave a nice short video on how
to ask for help because often sometimes the problem you have it might not be exactly you know
the actual problem that you might be having and so if you know that you might have a problem or even
if you don't know what type of problem there are multiple ways of getting help from us maybe the
The one out of the many ways, the one that I can mention is the so-called Garage, which
is a daily Zoom session that we are hosting at 1 p.m.
And the barrier is extremely low.
You might not even know what is your question or what is your problem.
And it's not even limited to Triton or to parallel processing or things like that.
We get people that they might just need basic IT help, or we even get people with questions
related to privacy, ethics, security, you know, even though we are not maybe the best
persons at Aalto to answer this question, but we most likely know someone who is the
best person.
So the barrier is extremely low, just come there every day at 1pm.
And then of course, when things get a little bit more complicated, they start to become
more like a consultation.
And so for that, we have the issue tracker, where you can basically paste a bit of your
code and you know something that cannot be solved quickly in within the one hour of the garage
session and of course that's the documentation that we have here in in general also we try to
also host some focus days in the in the garage so now I opened the garage space and so sometimes
we get guests from some departments as key so the IT services from from those departments
And sometimes, for example, we have this special day.
So recently we've been running the COMSOL
Multiphysics Focus Day every Wednesday.
So if you know that you're gonna use COMSOL
and you're not sure if your setup is optimal with Triton,
then that is the place to come for with.
So yeah, basically this is how to get help.
Maybe we still have a few minutes.
I could talk about kind of where to go from here.
In this page, which is the same page
where there's the upcoming courses
that we are hosting slash co-hosting.
If you scroll to the bottom,
there's also this nice picture
that [name] draw a few years ago,
which is kind of the skills map
when it comes to computing in general,
scientific computing.
So most of you here, for example,
have the type of basic skills that I even briefly cover
in the morning, understanding the hardware and the software
that you might be using.
And then, of course, sometimes you
need something a little bit more specific to your field,
whether it's simulations or whatever
is the kind of more science-related skills.
And then we start going that, before going
to the cluster and HPC, and the more advanced uses or tools
that we can use along with our coding
and scientific computing.
It's important to, you know, learn the Linux shell
and sometimes not just type in a few commands,
but as you already saw today,
sometimes you need to write a script.
So those scripts that you saw today,
they were so-called LRM scripts,
but in practice they are shell scripts.
And then on top of that, this is where we are here today
in learning our cluster and HPC are working.
When it comes to scientific coding,
there are more courses that we offer and in this i'm gonna mention that exactly one month from
today we have the next round of the code refinery workshop you can already register at this link
the code refinery workshop is a half six half days that are basically covering the basics of
of where is the schedule?
I don't see it here.
No, this is actually the lessons, but oh yeah,
it was here above, sorry.
Yes, Code Refinery March 25.
So the first three days, the first week of Code Refinery
covers everything about Git version control.
And we also cover kind of how to use GitHub
and the features that GitHub provides
so that you can create issues, pull requests and so on.
So it's very useful for this type of collaborative coding.
And then the second half focuses on reproducibility,
specifically the so-called computational reproducibility
and kind of there's a little bit more kind of,
how could I say, best practices
when it comes to scientific computing.
So automated testing and this type of continuous integration
and modular code development and so on.
So, basically, the last thing that I want to mention before we go for lunch break is
also that we have been running many of these courses in the past, and almost everything
is available in our YouTube channel, so you can kind of retake a past course.
But if you feel that it would be nice that we do a rerun of a past course, or maybe if
if you feel that something is missing in your curriculum
and you would really need something new
that we've never been running,
we have this form where people,
where you can basically request reruns of older courses
or a run of new courses.
And so here you see a long list of GitHub, Python, Julia.
This is the one where we are right now,
introduction to HPC and so on.
So, I think this is all cover for today.
Maybe I mentioned now for the exercises,
the exercises will happen in Zoom.
And the reason is that we will not be recording
what happens in the exercises room.
So you are free to use your microphone,
show your screen if you're having an error
that you want us to look at.
We will split in multiple rooms,
depending on what you wanna test
or what do you wanna learn.
In room number one,
we will basically go through all the exercises
on the Triton tutorials one by one
from connection to the login node
up to running this array jobs and other parallel things.
So this is highly recommended
if you recently got a Triton account
but basically never really use Triton.
Room 2 is more for helps if you have issues with connecting to Triton or other issues that could
be related to account, Triton account. And room 3 will be a little bit more advanced where for
those users who already are maybe familiar with connecting to Triton and running some
sbatch SLURM jobs but maybe you your needs are you know you might be needing CPUs, GPUs, or more
advanced parallelization and then we have one room dedicated to how to use large language models
and on Triton we actually store already some popular open source language models and we have
even a little bit of examples on how to run those local models so this is you know kind of a hands-on
way for testing that and finally room number five is the speech-to-text which is a tool that's been
used a lot by Aalto. Aalto doctoral researchers where, for example, the need of this tool
is that you might be collecting an interview, so in the form of speech, and this is a tool
that transcribes the interview into text. And for security and for confidentiality,
this all runs on Triton, so you don't need to, you know, upload your sensitive interview
outside of the Aalto network. And so for those who are interested in that, you can try speech
the text with the demo in room number five. It's 12 o'clock. I think we are done. Is there anything
to bring up from the notes? I would say that please give us feedback at the end of the notes.
At the end of the notes, there's this quick polling and you can give us also feedback
at the end. So please give us feedback on how did you find the course.
Because this is the first time we have done this kind of like a one-day quick kickstart
and it's good to get feedback on how it went in your mind.
So please leave us good and negative feedback, both welcome, because that will make the course
better.
Yeah.
All right.
So have a good rest of the day.
So hopefully some of you will join us for the exercises in Zoom and yeah, great.
Thanks a lot.
See you later.
Bye.