Uh, there you go.
So see you later.
So the page that I'm showing right now,
the webpage that I'm showing is the same
that you have received in the email if you register.
And if you have access also to this notes document
that you've been using for writing your answers,
it's also at the very top.
And this is basically kind of the collection of links
that we will use throughout the day.
So if I scroll down to the schedule,
we are basically here.
And very briefly, I give you a little start
or a little intro of what is happening right now
and what is this.
So I guess you already heard who we are.
We are the people from other scientific computing,
kind of our part of the School of Science.
We help everyone at Aalto basically,
we support large performance, high performance computing.
And as [name] just said, all sorts of requests
that can be related to software,
but not only software, also data,
open science and many other things.
We are well integrated with all the other
research services network and IT services networks.
So we're all in working together
to support people at Aalto University.
On top of that, we also collaborate a lot
with other universities in Finland and with CSC,
which is the main partner for computational resources
for basically all the Finnish researchers.
And we also belong to the Code Refinery Network,
which is a network that spans across all the Nordic countries
where we organize this type of workshop.
The course for today, normally we have this course
and we will have this course as a three days course,
so much longer and much slower.
We have it in the first week of June,
and we do it because that's the week
when the summer workers are joining at the university.
So usually the scale there is much bigger.
We have 300 participants,
and then we basically,
instead of having just a single day like we have today,
we have multiple days where we can cover
in detail all the topics.
So if you wish to have a more in-depth,
like deeper overview of everything.
I recommend joining the June version,
the longer version of this course.
But now here, most of you already have a Triton account,
already have maybe even submitted jobs
and work with Triton.
So this is more like a compressed two hours
of what can you do with HPC and specifically with Triton.
And then in the afternoon, we can actually spend time.
We have three hours together where we can do
whether you want to do the basic exercises that we have,
or maybe you want to learn how to run large language models
like local large language models on Triton,
or maybe you have more advanced needs,
whether you need to use GPUs
or some other more advanced parallel programming.
So the afternoon part, if you want to join,
that will happen in Zoom,
and it would be much more interactive.
I don't basically need to go through all the practicalities,
but maybe what you're already feeling right now
that instead of being in a Zoom room,
right now we're using Twitch TV,
which is basically like a TV streaming.
And the main advantage is that with Twitch TV,
as soon as the streaming stops,
the recording will be immediately available
so that you can re-watch it later today
or whenever you want.
And on top of that, we don't have the issue that,
you know, sometimes in Zoom,
there might be some participants that might appear
on the screen or maybe a microphone that are not unmuted.
So we don't have this type of issues.
Basically, what else can I say
that we use this type of vertical screen sharing?
And the reason is that for those who have only one screen,
so kind of laptop users,
they can have within the same screen space,
basically a space for the Twitch stream,
where they can watch the streaming
and in the other, in the rest of the screen,
they can keep the web browser open and so on.
Of course, if you have multiple screens,
you don't have this issue,
but with this approach, we are able,
you should be able to always have the window,
the streaming window visible.
Maybe I don't need to go through everything,
but if something goes wrong, it can happen, stay in tune and, you know, if the streaming
disappears or something like that, we will try to get it back and if there's larger technical
issues, we have already a plan B for everything. Just a last reminder that, you know, we follow
the Alto Code of Conduct and so we hope that this is a great experience for everyone and if you
feel that something is wrong just get in touch with one of the organizers so we
still have some 10 minutes [name] are you there? I'm here there was a short network