Okay.
Okay, so now we're in the pre-live or pre-main course icebreaker time, where we'll talk to
you a little bit and get ready to go.
So what you see shared here is the, what we call the notes document, or just notes.
It is a place where everyone can edit, so you can't see it on this share.
if you go up here you can switch to an edit mode and then you can write stuff here so it's marked
down the exact format doesn't matter that much but the important thing is if you take it up and the
only people that have it are people that have registered so you should have just gotten a
reminder email that also has this inside of it is that true okay yes and if you scroll down to the
bottom you see icebreakers here. So the purpose of this is you can come and you
can switch to edit mode and answer these questions and we'll discuss. So for
example I just put an "o" right here to show that I'm very familiar with command
line in Shell. So it's sort of like a bar graph we're making collaboratively. So
Everyone go open this up, vote for whichever one there is, and we can get an idea of how
we should be presenting stuff.
So the questions are, how familiar are you with command line shell?
Have you used version control before?
types of computers have used for work before? What types of programming you do? And then just
a free-form question and answer. What kinds of scientific work do you do or think you do? Like,
whether it's machine learning stuff or physics or chemistry, whatever it may be.
Okay, let's talk about what our answers for these would be. So, first off, I'm [name]
[name]. I work at Aalto University in the Aalto Scientific Computing team, and our job is
basically to help you with scientific computing kind of work. I guess you probably know that
because that's why we're here giving this course.
So of these topics here, I'd say I'm probably
very familiar with command line shell.
I use it all the time and script in it.
I've done plenty of version control before.
I've used mostly own laptops, desktops, group servers,
and high performance clusters.
And my main programming is in Python and shell scripting.
[name], would you like to introduce yourself?
Yeah, so hi everybody.
My name is [name].
I'm a research software engineer
in the autoscientific computing.
So on the topics, yeah, I would say that I'm very familiar
with the command line nowadays.
I've worked in these topics for years, years now.
Have I used version control? Yes.
In fact, just yesterday we were talking about anecdotes
on how, where we learned some of these skills.
And in my first summer job in Aalto University,
my supervisor wanted me to learn how to use version control
and that has definitely paid off.
Like that was years and years ago.
What type of computers have I used before?
Mainly, I do my work from my own laptop
and connecting from that to various other machines
like HPC clusters and a remote desktop and such.
So the laptop is the connection that I use
to the wider computing world.
But I would say that all of those are basically
what I've used so far.
My programming background is on the physics side, but nowadays Python, I would say, is the one glue
that glues most of the coding together. I would say Python is my main language, and then I would
say maybe C or shell scripting, I wouldn't know really. But yeah, basically whatever works for
the specific case at hand. Yeah, great. And [name], would you like to introduce yourself some?
Yeah, okay. Hi, so I'm [name]. I'm, I think, the newest member still of the
research software engineering team. Regarding the icebreaker questions, well, I'm familiar with
the command line. I've used it for a long time now, but I wouldn't say that I'm very familiar
with it. There's certainly areas I could still learn something about it. I've been using version
control for a fair bit as well. Still sort of a myth that I didn't use version control for my
PhD studies, but that's what it was back then. And well, I worked on my own computers,
as laptops and desktop.
I've worked remotely,
and I've also worked on the cluster.
Nowadays, that's just like similar.
I mostly do Python programming-wise,
but I've done a fair bit of other things.
I've done Matlab, I've done R, I've done C.
I've done SDCC, if anyone knows about that, it stands for Small Devices C Compiler, it's
for very close to hardware programming, and that's basically what there is to tell about
me in terms of computing, I think.
Okay, cool.
[name], would you like to introduce yourself?
Yes.
Hello everybody.
couple of minutes before kind of the official start and before mentioning something about myself I'm
checking the answers that you've been writing for those who join now you should have received
this notes document at notes.coderefinery.org and there you can basically edit the document
it's like a google doc but everyone can edit but it's just text based and when it comes to me
I work with the same team as [name], [name], and [name], and yes, I'm very familiar with the
command line. I started in, I think it was 1983 with the Commodore 64, and the only interface
was the command line. 1983? Yeah, I think that's when I got my first computer. I mean,
The commands that I was tapping was more like load and then name of the game.
I don't remember now the basic commands, but you know, that was my first interface
interaction with the computer.
Even though I was ex-sport, because my dad with this job, he also has access to one of
these computers with punch cards.
So I've seen also those back in the days, but more, you know, back to nowadays, yes,
the command line is maybe the most powerful tool.
I will share a link actually, there's a nice nature paper
that they show how important it is to learn the command line
or all type of science.
Virtual control, it's actually all the pages,
the web pages that you see that we in our documentation
or even the websites that we share sometimes,
they're all actually based using,
they're all written and shared through Git and GitHub.
So even though it's not just for, you know,
keeping track of your code,
it can also be very useful for publishing.
And in general, I mean, a bit of Python, a bit of R,
MATLAB, I used a lot of MATLAB in the past
because with neuroscience, which is my background,
we have lots of those tools.
But great to see that many people are connected.
There's 41 people in this HedgeDoc notes document.
So if you feel that it's getting a bit slow,
you can switch to the view mode.
And what were you saying, [name]?
Yeah, and I guess we're about to start.
If we look at the icebreaker answers here,
people are basically answering what we'd expect.
So the audience as a whole seems to be
at the right level for this course.
So we are not talking about the prerequisites
of most of these kinds of things.
important tools you'll use but not the main topic of the course. Our main topic is this section
right here. Although our team doesn't just support the cluster, we support everything that you see
on this list. So as you'll learn later on, we have different help sessions where you can come
and we're around to help with all of these things because we completely understand that computers are
complex. There's just so many different things that people have to know and learn in order to
do stuff. And that's why our team's funded. So you can focus on your work and we focus on
the other stuff. With that being said, I guess it's time to start. So I believe it's
[name] and [name] with the intro. So I'll hide myself and switch to [name]'s screen.