Because of the commands they sometimes provide quite long outputs. So what we've done also,
I have another one terminal over here which will automatically output what I'm typing here.
So if I'm typing the command like echo test it will appear over here. You will find it useful
later when the screen will go off and the will be polluted already by the output of the different
and then I will clear the screen somehow of my terminal.
And so you can still look at these commands over here.
That's not it.
I have also done this,
my demo space in my home directory on my local computer
as part of my university page.
So I have on my university page,
directory called shell.
If you go to this HTTPS,
user's auto.fi, my username and shell.
So you should have this link actually over here
on the code refinery.
So you don't need to type it on your own,
just click it over there.
So here you will get first,
here we'll get all the scripts that we will be preparing.
They will be automatically added over here to the webpage.
And then also you will hear the whole,
you will hear, see the whole bash history.
It's easy to take it out from here
and copy-paste it to your own terminal.
Okay, by saying that,
I think I'm pretty much done with it.
So this is a hands-on tutorial.
So my target over here is to be more or less 50-50.
If I'm saying something like for 10 minutes,
then I expect that we will spend 10 minutes
on actually doing something.
So there will be lots of doing over here.
And so it does really make sense
that you have your terminal open
and you have all the setup ready to go.
I think this is pretty much what I had to say
about the initial part.
If any question is left,
then please go and type it over here.
I'm not alone on this course.
I'm the speaking kind of head,
but there will be several of our team guys
helping you and me to answer these questions.
So if you type the question,
be sure there will be someone to reply you
pretty much immediately.
So there will be work done in the background.
But let's get back to the material.
So this Linux shell basics has been given,
as I told you already, in autumn.
So now we will be working on the Linux shell scripting.
The material is quite comprehensive.
This is the one which is online.
I will not read you from the slides.
I don't have actually any slide over here.
I will use its material and everything
what I will be saying, it's more or less somewhere here,
but I don't really follow directly the material itself.
And the exercises which are part of this material
and actually written fully by our team,
they will appear over here.
So I have an example of first exercise
and so that you, when we will come to this,
you will see how it will go for.
Okay, so the first icebreaker and the starter.
So you're told already, if you haven't answered yet
the question, please try to do it also over here.
So that will give us some picture of what we are doing
and who is taking the course.
and let's get your hands dirty. So my first touch will be actually writing the script.
So that's what we are here all together. So my first script will be
let it be the hello bash. But before we go actually for writing the script we have to decide
or you have to decide which editor you will use to write your scripts. So you have a number of
options over here. There is a very popular like Emacs. If you are familiar with the Emacs, go with
it. There is very popular another one EIM. It's also the text editor which is used by many people
on Linux, but both of them and Emacs, let me put it this way, so it's the Emacs and
VIM, they are quite complicated and they require some kind of passion and
experience. So when you are becoming the experienced users of Linux shell, you
will definitely, you will pick up one of them. For less experienced people, we
suggest nano. Let me run it and let me show how it works. I would suggest if you are not really
experienced with any kind of text editor on the Linux shell, then use that one. It will
be the most intuitive, I would say. So when you type here something,
type something and then you want to exit the code then you just press ctrl x it will ask you do you
want to save it yes and then it will ask you where you want to save it and for instance i want to save
it to the hello bash. Okay, and I'm now in my demo space and I've got this hello bash dot shell.
So that's the first script I have created. It's not really a script. I have demonstrated how to
use nano. It's up to you which one do you prefer. I prefer vim and during this course I will use
mostly vim simply because it have it has really good highlightings it has and i'm just way more
experienced with this one so let's try to i will delete this line and then let's try to write your
first script your first script ever will come with this cryptic line what it stands for it's called
the shebang. Shebang is nothing else than what it says to the program which runs it,
which interpreter is supposed to be used. So binbash is the path to the binary
which will run the code which comes after. And this number sign and exclamation mark
is a special two special characters which are widely used on linux especially for the
which are used on linux for the shebang mark so in the same way when you'll be writing some python
script you will be putting this shebang with the usr being python if you will be writing some tcl
or some other something which is just normal text so that will come into use as well in the next
let's actually output something which is the hello bash
let it be even correct way so now I'm done I'm also able to put here
some comment so
let me say that it prints hello bash that's that much you're supposed to know
so then another one about syntax so this is the command this is the shebang
that's the command which comes and which outputs the hello bash and then
Then you can continue the string, for instance,
to another line.
So just put the backslash like this one.
If the line is pretty long and you want to make it
more or less compact and readable, you can use it.
We don't need it right now,
but just this part of the syntax.
And then also the indentation.
If you are a Python user,
so that you know that you need to,
all these strings, especially,
all these blocks, they're supposed to be indented,
but in case of bash, it doesn't really matter.
So you can put another one command over here,
like this, hello bash again.
Okay, type in hello bash again.
and that will be completely okay. You can do it even more compact, you can do it with the
delimiter, it will be also okay. You can do it this way, it will be also okay from the bash syntax
point of view. So bash will not tell you anything about your syntax, about all these lines. So the
empty lines that will not be that will be just omitted as usually
and this is pretty much everything else this pretty much it that you should supposed to know
about the syntax so we will come later to the blocks we will come later to the if statements
and this for loops etc and the other stuff and you will see that the actually i will use
use indentation over there, but it's only for the sake of readability.
So let's try to run the script.
If I do it like this, first command not found.
Okay, so what happens over here?
You can see that actually, from the Linux perspective, you can check out what kind of
permissions this script has.
even if it's the already something with the .shell
actually the .shell is nothing else than just the
extension so extension can be any bash script is not supposed to use .shell
i'm just using .shell because i want to make sure i want to make sure for
myself that i know that that's the shell script and it's written by myself
so but only because it's text it's supposed to be executable this execution bit over here
it's missing so there should be x you remember from the previous course there should be it's
readable it's writable but it's not executable so what first i need to do is i need to change mode
and say that my script is going to be executable hello bash plus X so now you
see I've got this plus X fine it's already executable if I still try to do
it like this hello bash nothing is found
Why? It's because the bash is actually to not pick up your local files by default, so it expects
that your binaries, even including the scripts, they are somewhere in the
directory, so you have to call them explicitly. And calling explicitly saying that I need to put
the path. In my case it's just enough if I put dot and the slash. That means that in current directory
take the hello bash and execute this. So now it has happened. Well, this is our first step.
And now what's next? Next I would like to use the good practice
and create a directory where I will be putting all my stuff
and I'm not only will be keeping all my stuff in there,
I will also make it this way that bash will actually look
at my directory when I want to execute something
and will be executed, the script will be executed
without this dot slash.
So how to do that?
I suggest that you run make dir in your directory
where you have been. We will come to this during the exercise. So I have already
been directory so but when you will need to run it just like this. So I have
already been directory. I have even a couple of scripts over there which
we will be later used. No, just one. But then let me move that bash. No, hello bash
only hello bash over here. So now I have it in bin
and it's not yet enough. So what next I need to do? I need to modify
the environment variable called path. So if you look at the echo path
there should be some directories where your bash will be looking at
to find the binary that you are trying to run. So even the bash itself
it's somewhere in the directory. So in our case it's bin-bash.
But you see that this bin-bash has been already added by default.
so it's already part of the default, so it's bash user, bin bash etc, so it's part of the default
and it's always there, but our local bin has never been added to the path. Path is modifiable,
so you can edit this and let me do it this way, so I can use the command export,
so now don't go deeply into this just type just you will just use it as is when we are
we'll be doing the exercise export and I will say that export my path and do the changes
so add to my path something which is called demo space
pin. What will happen after? Let's see. If I take a look at the bash at the path once again you will
see that actually my directory where I have my scripts has been added to that path and now it's
executable. Now if I run something like hello bash it will immediately be executed as next
and I can tell you even more this command type minus a this the utility within the Linux which
can always ready to tell you which binary will be run when you type with with no absolute path
so in this case it tells me exactly that hello bash is like this
Okay, then what else I was about to tell you.
So the execution summary, kind of executive summary is that you create the file, you make
sure that shebang is there, then you don't really care much about syntax, that's a takeaway
message then if case that should be enough already to get you running but
then in case if you want to be efficient and productive so you will organize your
own pin directory and you will add it and export later to the path variable so
that information should be pretty much enough to go for the exercise to go for
exercise
let it be first exercise because you are still will be playing with the
editor so let us say that it's going to be 10 minutes
yeah and now it's 12 22 so that we will go till
till till till where was the exercise down
we will go the first exercise to 32 of your local time so i put here xx because i'm
expected some people are not from finland so some people are from somewhere else so it's not
uh no sorry the vice versa 30 or let it be three so now it's your time you try it
you may succeed, you may not, not a big trouble, just ask your question online
and when you are done please put something like this over here or if you
see that it's come, time is coming, so press it over here like this or if you
still don't really care, you're just listening, write it over here. Okay, so not
10 minutes is yours and let's go
I'll mute myself for a second
you
If anyone still needs time, just mark it.
I think we can, we are still adapting this.
be I think 10 or even 15 minutes is just fine. It's just we need to see that what's the level of the
and how fast we are. We are flexible, no trouble with the extra five minutes at all.
And also I forgot to tell about the breaks. Thanks for reminding me is that we're going
to have the breaks every hour, something like 10 minutes, so no worries about that too
Even though I speak a lot and I'm trying to do it intensive, so it's kind of still intermediate
Okay, I guess most of the people. I will continue. Can you hear me?
Hopefully yes. I mean if you can't hear me
then just tell me. Okay, so the first exercise has been already done, has been already over,
so your hands are already dirty, which is good for me and good for you. So welcome to the world
of the bash, even though that some of you have already written some scripts.
Actually, even this hello world is not so practical, but let me write another script.
Let me go back to the prompt. So if you are a Python user, for instance, then you may think,
okay, I'm writing Python and I have a kind of sandbox where you can test it easily with just
write in the command and then for instance you do something
like that and you just quite yeah that's fairly easy and you can think about how to do that with
the bash well you're already actually there so this command line that you have it is already the
the kind of ready-to-go prompt for you.
You don't need to put bash,
you don't need to put anything else.
You just put your comments and everything what you want
you can put over here.
So in this way,
bash is adapted for the interactive usage.
So scripting is just the kind of fancy addition
and the kind of value added to the bash,
but bash itself is mostly about prompt.
and most of the commands you can run as is
just from the prompt.
And this is what we will use also over here.
So some of the statements, some of the expressions,
I will just test it from the command line
before actually adding them to the script.
So scripts are made mostly for a sake of automation.
Scripts are made mostly for a sake of
if you have a long list of commands,
you don't remember all these parameters
and you want to make out of this complex construct
of some utilities, you want to make out of them
some kind of one single command.
So this is what for you are using the scripts.
Again, and see that for instance,
one example that I will show you.
So for instance, I will be doing this archive
in time to time of my demo space
and saying that I want to compress it
and my file name, which I want to my archive name
will be like demo space tarc.gz.
So it's the quite common in Linux,
tarc utility and the gz compression.
And then I'm saying that actually my directory,
I want to compress, that's the demo space. So I can just put one single dot, but for the sake of
readability, let me put it this way, demo space. So I'm doing the compression. So these are warnings,
the edges, you can skip them. So now you see that I have got the file over here. I'm not exactly kind
kind of, I'm not exactly,
it's my colleague over here.
So I'm not exactly, maybe wants to do it time to time.
So what I want to make over here,
that I want to put it to the bin
and make it one single command,
shorter one and easier to one,
and which will serve us for the whole course.
So we will do the modification to that.
So let me call it tar me, for instance.
My shell script will be starting once again
with the bin bash, with the shebang.
And then I'm putting here my command over here.
And as a good practice,
remember to have some kind of comments
and some kind of revision history.
so what you've done and when you have done.
So I'm saying yet nothing you about the Git over here,
but I'm encouraging you in your entire life after all,
use Git for a kind of versioning.
Here, we'll just skip this part
and make it kind of more simple,
and the Git part will be covered already
the code refinery when you will be there so but here
archive my directory so that's the easy way
and then let's try once again change mode plus
x and what's good about this because the
If you put tar.me.shell, you will see that actually it's immediately found from
my Bean directory because my Bean directory has been already added to the
path and I don't need to do anything else if I decide to go and make another
archive. I just run tar.me and that's it. We will use this further to develop a
bigger script. So, this will be part of our exercises, it will be part of our
demonstrations overall. So, this is why I did this right over here.
Variables. So, definitely what you want to know about when you start
programming something, how to use the variables within your code. So, the
Variables is nothing really specific.
So let me start doing this in the prompt
and then we will move these variables to the file.
So variables, it can be any.
It can be just the letters and digits
and then minus, it could be hash.
So there is quite a number of the,
There is some special characters,
if you go to the variables section of this material,
so you will see there were somewhere
a list of special characters.
Yeah, sure, it's here, it's coordinate substitution.
So these characters cannot be really used in the variables
because they are part of the other syntax,
but then everything else can be used as a variable.
so let's see what else so variables
for instance assigning the variables you just put the equal sign and say my first
bash variable it will be like this it's already there so in order to call that variable it's
enough if you put the dollar sign in the front of the name and so you can see echo will give
give you the output of that variable.
In the same way, you can use this dollar sign variable name
within any commands or within any part of your script.
It's just will be a colon
and it will be returning you the value of that variable.
Variable, there is no kind of definition.
There is no points.
There is no strings, booleans, integers, et cetera.
So all the variables inside of the bash,
will be used as is. If you are doing this up as a string, that will be interpreted as a string.
If you are doing something else, it will be. If you make an integer summation within the
integer expressions, then it will be interpreted as an integer, etc. So bash is really flexible
in terms of variables. So even if you are not defined it, but you still call it, it will just
return you the empty variable and not the error so be careful about this and this is actually quite
common error is that you are misprinting or mistyping the variable and you call it later
and then you are surprised that okay nothing comes out actually bash doesn't really take care about
it it relies on your and it still thinks that you are making your scripts pretty much robust
in checking whether the variable is empty or does it exist at all. So here it comes the place where
the quotation also matters. Let me open once again the hello script
and I will use it as a sandbox for this kind of situation. So for instance I want to assign a
variable and let it be some text
and then if I go to the echo and want to output that variable that should be enough but then if
if my syntax, or if my sentence is more or less complex.
So if I want to say that var is,
okay, I have to use already,
well, not exactly have to use with echo,
but let's assume that we have to also with echo.
So I have to use the quotations.
And here where comes the difference between the quotes.
So the echo with the single quotes
will produce you exactly the sentence you have it within the single quotes
it will not open for you the variables but the double quote quotation will do it for you
so here take a note quotation matters so then there are a few other things for instance
less complicated cases
so let's try it out so now we will actually we can use it
we can comment this once just we don't need it
and use it as a sandbox so it has been already added to the bin it's executable by default
so and now you can see the difference the first line has been using the single quotes and the
second line was using the double quotes so yes take it take it into account along with the variables
which you kind of create yourself and define yourself. There is a bunch of other variables
which have been already created for you by the environments, by the bash itself and by Linux
itself. You will be surprised if you type this printenv, you will see a long list of all kind of
of predefined variables. Some of them read-only, some of them are changeable, but most of them
you don't really need to touch, except with something which is kind of, I don't know,
well I don't know even the exact example when you need to change the variables. Well, sometimes
you end up changing this, for instance, I've been doing this for the script which is
over here, but anyway
Anyway, so, and a few examples that you may find useful. The first one was already
mentioned, that's the path, that gives you the list of the directories where Bash will be looking
for the binaries when you type it without the absolute path. Then home, it's exactly your home
directory. Then for instance shell, that's exactly your bash shell which is defined for you. So I
said nothing about the other shells but that's probably the good point to do that. So bash is
just one of the shells. We were talking about this on the first part of the course.
and there are other ones which are perfectly fine to use like a Z-shell or something else like
corn shell it's up to you but this course is focused on the bash mainly because bash is the
most popular nowadays so and this is also the shell number one for us because we are running
the big cluster installation triton and so on triton we expect everyone used to bash so this
is one, and because I'm part of the team so we push people to use bash and the whole course is
about bash. How to change your shell? It's the change shell command. If you want to do it on
your local desktop it's easy to do. You do the change shell and you just put the bin bash and
your next session will be started with the bin bash. Okay, said that I think we can now jump to the
exercise number two. So I call it variables and I will give you another 10 minutes to do
what. First you need to adapt your Hello Bash shell and assign the Hello Bash to a variable
and print the variable to the output. So I've done it already for you during the demo.
so now try to use your memory don't look yet at my hello bash but try to use your memory and
try it out then the next one which haven't been done yet but now you have to implement it on your
own so your script which will be placed also in the bin and call it whatever you want i call it
here print vars which will print for us the home shell and path one per line so now time is yours
and we are 48 so let's say that already 49 so that let's go this way we will have both
and the how to call it break let's call it joint break and exercise sessions so
we will come back to the screen at 1309 but so 10 minutes for the break 10
minutes for the exercise and you decide how you use in which order I mute myself
and I will add it to the.
you
If need, if there is a need for more time on this, just, just mark yourself yet need
time and
So it's kind of time already, so only some people marked the lag done.
Do we still need time, or should we wait for everyone?
Or if there is any kind of trouble, just ask.
But definitely we will cover all the questions.
There was the question about the bin bash,
but this shebang was in the wrong order.
Okay, let's get back to the material.
my next stop was actually tell you even more about the variables. This is something which
is very specific to the bash. This is what you probably will not see in most of the languages.
So when you can do something with the variables on the fly, the constructions looks like
this curly brackets column and then some kind of cryptic syntax which will do something to the
variable as a string so what can be done with the string so you can make it for instance
all capital, all small.
You can replace some part of the variable value.
Then you can, for instance,
check whether this variable exists or not.
You can redesign it,
redefine it with some default value.
So there are quite a number of things that can be done.
can be done.
So I'm not really put everything to this material.
So, but the selected of them are over here.
So you can check them out.
And then on top of that,
you can also actually forgot to sale.
So if you're ever thinking about syntax,
if you're ever thinking about some particular commands,
which have been used within this bash scripting.
So all the internal logic is written in the bash manual.
If you go to the, for the man bash,
you will see the very long,
I mean, it's at least 100 pages
if you will print it out in a normal font size,
but you will see all the details about what else
and what kind of, what kind of options,
what kind of arguments are given by every single command,
which I use internally,
and then what all these magics, all these extensions,
all these practical aspects of the bash programming.
So, the magic I was thinking about is that, for instance, I know that the echo var already
exists because I have it designed.
Actually, let me tell you one thing, you can unset the variable.
So if you don't really want this variable to exist anymore, it will exist as long as
your session is there.
So but if you don't want to exist it anymore, you just can do it with the unset var.
now if you see that I'm trying to address var, it doesn't exist anymore. Bash is not complaining
anything about calling the undefined variable, but it just returned the empty line, which is fine.
Which is not an error, that's just a feature. So let me say that I want still to define it somehow
and for instance it's still undefined but I want to check it out so my approach would be here
checking out for instance
this one is pretty simple for the sake of checking out the existence of this variable
so you see what will happen so echo or bash on behind of echo it will check
that variable exists or not and then give this error message which comes
after the question mark so here I'm saying that bash var not defined so if
you use it within the script or within your function it's perfectly enough to
make your script more or less robust there is another one option if you
instead of exclamation mark you put something like equal that would check that variable
and if it does not exist it will assign some special value some default value it could be
anything then just put default value oh it's up to you what do you decide to do this but then
if you see from now on
echo var even as it has been defined undefined over here you see you remember
that now it's already the has the value and
the thing to remember with all these major
constructions with all these curly brackets
this do column and the equal sign is the only operator
which actually does something to the variable. It changes it. It assigns the default value or
another value which you just put it over here. All the rest which are listed here as
selected operators, they do really nothing to the variable. They just simply extract it or they
modify it on the fly and put it to the online, give it to the output, print it to the output,
but then they actually do nothing with the variable itself. So a variable stays as is.
Let me do the example. For instance, here I'm grabbing the fpath. So I'm saying that that's my
path to the file and I'm naming that variable accordingly. So if you take a
look at the path it's pretty much like that. So what I want to say that
I want to first get the path
for instance here this cryptic says that okay return me everything what is
before the last slash. Oh, actually everything except
what is after the last slash. So now I'm getting the name of the file actually. So you see that
I've got rid of this one while the file itself, I mean the fpath, has not been modified.
It's only the modification which has happened on the fly and it has been outputted to the script.
In order to make it modified, actually, you have to reassign it to another variable.
So if I assign it to another variable and say, let's call it fpath2,
now it's going to be already something which will be
remember it, which will be saved to the memory and which will be part of your global space.
So you see.
And then, for instance, another example.
If I want to keep running this fpath thing and want to return only the path.
So that's another approach.
So I'm not going any more deeply into this.
I want you actually to go this deeper into this thing so learn this section and let's try it
let's say that we go for another 10 minutes playing with this variable magics so what I
want you to try I wanted to try in this construct where you have the variable name and then the
curly brackets and then something after the variable name late on your own or
or actually, if you will be ready,
here is my,
or did I put it over here already?
So here is my suggestion for you.
So you pick up, once again, your Hello Bash
and you change it in such a way
this variable HelloBash will be printed in capitals. That's the first. And the
second one is that you will wrap once again that fpath variable in the way
you want to, but I mean you just copy paste from the course material and make
your script to return file name only without the full path and extension. So
the hint over here is that I've said you previously over here is that you will
not be able to do it with one single iteration you will have to do it with
two iterations and for that you will have to save one variable to another so
let's see how you will manage this to do you will have now 10 maybe even 15
minutes because it's gonna be quite quite a challenge for you especially for
the first time but then let's go so we will finish when at 1325
you
sorry i also forgot to mention so here i will put the
the answers, both of them.
That's the answers for the previous exercise I'll do the same for the exercise after all
you
You
Okay, we're gonna keep going.
So let me demonstrate you a few techniques over here.
So the first, I will also put it to the,
the answers to this, both exercises,
to both tasks of this exercise will be on the notes,
but then first let me go with demo.
So quick demo for the first one, echo,
and then we were expecting some modifications to the var.
So we need the curly brackets,
and then we need to say what we want so we put two hats over here that should be enough let's see
what we get out of this so yeah so you can see that actually the first one was the
from the previous version of the script and the second one was already the first
they say the other one so regarding the fpath plane so there was a request to do the
get the only the archive that was somewhat complicated and complex and I do hope that
that place some of you have got already some of this so let me grab this one and say that I
go to the bin and I will create my new script. I will call it some kind of fpath
and I will play with that and I will say that it's gonna be bash once again
and let's see what can be done. So I actually can use pretty much the variables
modifications this magic from the
from the
learning material, but here what I'm getting, I would get it only on the fly
I don't really want it on the fly, I want it to be
another variable, but here I don't really care about the original fpath
I can simply reassign it in order to make the
modification not on the fly but save them to the variable
I can simply assign it this way and you will see later that actually
so let's say that I want to put the fpath
and I can say here that's the phase one
it's going to be the fpath
part which will be I will take off everything which is behind this one
this slash so the only thing which will be left to me
that's this one okay and now that's the
moment where I can already if I don't care
about what's the final result of fpath
this is where the moment
where I can't put something like this
but modify it a little bit so let's say that here
I put the comments
just to simply here we get
archive with the extensions. Okay, you can check it out from the command line. I know that it's
going to be like this already because I already checked so I just put it to the to my script
already directly. So now, so this block is over here. Now the next step
getArchive out of
so now we have to get rid of this
too so how to do that is that we can say that okay we don't need dots
and we don't need anything out of these dots
now the tricky thing because of this syntax so this will allow me to get rid of the only the last one
content of which comes after the dot but what i want i want the everything after the after the
after the dot so in this case i will have to use the two percentages so that was the complication
over here and that was kind of thing that you had to had to find it out from the
from the manual page or just to try it to fit with that
okay now let's see what's going on change mode let it be okay okay it should be plus x
and now I'm ready to run fpath and so in the phase one we've got archived argz and after the second
one we got the archive so take a look once again it's nowadays looking like this so let me put it
to the
solution part
where am I
15 minutes functions
that's going to be the next one here is the
so here is for everyone who wants to
take a look at this later on
Okay, now we can, if any question please ask
if something is yet unclear, so I can take rid of this one and we just have
actually the part which we need. So saying that, I think I'm done with the
variables and you know already pretty much a lot so you know already how to
use the variables you know how to find them how to call them you should know by
now know that the variable can be undefined and then you also know this
matrix of this bash variables which you can do with the curly brackets and do
some modifications on the fly in case you want to do this so if you want to
substitute this modified variable and put it to the command line. So that's the way to do
with the curly brackets. So now the next one I wanted to try is functions. Functions
are everywhere. It's just a piece of code which you can use repeatedly. Usually, I mean, if you
know that within the same code you will use the same snippets, so you can just put them somewhere
else to the function and then use them all the time within the code. This is quite normal,
this is quite usual, and this is not an exclusion in terms of bash. Functions are there. The only
difference is that the functionality of the functions is nothing really extraordinary.
it's just a piece of the code which will work in the normal global space.
So, basically, you will have access to all the variables that you use within the script.
You will have access to all the variables, the global space, that would mean that you have
access to all the variables that you have assigned within the script itself. And then on top of that,
every single modification of that variable that you do within the function will be seen
to the end of the script. So just remember this. And this differs this function's functionality
from the other languages. On top of that, functions do not really return the result
of the modification of this variable with the return command. It does have a return command,
but return command does nothing except returning the exit code. The exit code
this is something which is I already mentioned it once and so every time
every time when you run some command for instance if I run something like echo test
you can expect that this command has returned some exit code. The exit code is saved in the
variable called $ and then the question mark. And in case of bash, if it's zero that means
that the action has succeeded. And if it's non-zero, one, two, three, any other digit.
so it means that the action actually has failed. So this thing to remember and to take a note if
you are doing so. Now let me get back to the functions. What I suggest to do is that I suggest
to organize the file which I would call functions. Surprise, surprise! You don't need to put .shell
or anything like this, it can be just functions. Another one surprise that within these functions
those the file where you want to define it you don't really need to push the put the shebang
i will tell you i will show you how to call the functions later on but just for now it's enough
if you just do do it without it so my first example will be for you is the usage of your space
So let me first get out of this and copy-paste the command from the material. You can do it
on the same way. So what the command does, it shows you the files in this current directory
and sort them out by their size. So in my situation, I'm trying to look at all the
files including the hidden ones. So the hidden ones, as you remember from the
previous course material, that's the one which start with a dot. So by default if
If you don't address them specifically, no one of the commands, neither ALS nor other
commands will see them.
So this is why they are called hidden, even if they are not really hidden in such a way.
But you must say explicitly, and this is the expression how to address all the hidden files
in the current directory.
So because no one of the hidden files is found, disk usage gives me the warning that nothing
can be accessed.
It's completely okay, it can be ignored.
the other files are over here so I have tested this command and now I want to make a space
usage out of this one so let me write a function
or did I have a functions okay I probably haven't functions
I haven't yeah that was empty so now let me go into that function and put the body of my function
and then puts the actually name etc around so the way you write the function you open the curly
brackets so you put the name of the function it should have this brackets round brackets
parentheses and then you put the curly brackets and then you put actually the name of the
the name of the uh the command itself so now it has been defined now it's in the file
and the function file does not need even the execution bit so if you look at the ls
minus l functions you will see that it's nothing else than just normal text file how to source it
so you can go to you can just grab that file functions and type source
and you will have these functions part of your environment how to check it again you can use
type minus a and see that what kind of function is behind the space usage and you will get the list
so there are two signs here first space usage is part of your environment by now and second sign
that you can see that actually it's supposed to work right away so by now
because it's your part of your environment you can run it pretty much like any other binary.
So now you can see that after running space usage there will be this kind of list exactly that I
would have get out of this command but this command is now has a kind of a nickname space usage.
the name you come with is just up to you and actually bash doesn't really care except that
you are if you are not trying to rename some real some real binaries and even for that there is
medicine i don't tell you yet anything about this but for this there is medicine as well so let me
say that I'm pretty happy with this already one, but there is something else that can be used with
the functions. Functions can accept the input parameters. And input parameters, so if let me say
that if I call space usage like this, and then if I say some argument number one, argument number two,
argument number three and so on, they will immediately be within my
function, they will immediately recognize as $1, $2, $3, etc. And we can use it.
Okay, so let's say that we're expecting some input arguments, input parameters. And let's say that my
space function will be actually expecting a directory, so that I don't
really go and check the current one, but I can check any one.
Now what to do? Now I know that my directory is going to be like this.
And so what kind of thing I can implement over here? So I can say
that everything within this directory like this or even more I can say that
everything within this directory will be checked it's already a good progress so
we've got already something to solve but in case in case I want to make sure that
actually this directory is provided how to check it and here where we can use our magic variables
and so we can implement it in a way that okay I keep it like this but I put my curly brackets
and I use this operator which will say if it's equal if this one is not defined
then let it be my current directory current directory in the bash notations
is dot so in the same way I can do it over here if one is not defined then I
I want to say that let it be dot.
Now we are good enough to go with the new space usage.
So now we already have created pretty robust code.
Let me check it once again.
Was it the minus or was it the...
Yeah.
Ah, okay.
So here I'm doing one thing.
So I don't want to reassign it, but I want to return it.
So I'm using the minus operator.
You see what's the difference?
With the equal, I would reassign it.
So I don't really want to change,
and I will not be able to change this special variable $1.
But with the minus, I will be able to return the dot
without changing the variable itself.
That's the difference.
Okay, now we are pretty much robust,
and now we can even put again,
return the space usage,
well, return the space usage
with disk usage command.
Now let's try.
Now we need to source it once again,
functions.
Now let's try type once again.
Now you see that my script function,
which is now part of my environment has been modified.
And now let's see how it works.
First, I will use it with some variable.
So I wanna, for instance, check the,
my demo space.
Okay, let's see, it works.
So once again, this warning is just about the dot files.
you can simply ignore this and then if I put no parameter what it do for me
okay now I can see that actually it's trying to do it the same way
like this so which is pretty much what I have expected out of this function
say it again
now you have written the first function which can be used then within the code
so how to do that
let's say that i want to
i will demonstrate it for the sake of demonstration over here
so now let me do the kind of dummy file
let me copy functions to some
space, whatever, space.shell. So, I do it only for the sake of demonstration how to
call the function within the code. So, I'm now looking at the space.
Here, I already need this shebang, because I'm doing the actual scripting
and snow again in the previous file which was called functions i was only defining the function
was not executing them in this situation i want to define it first and execute it after so and
that's the way to space usage and then even if i put some arguments i can put the argument right
away space, usage, and then, for instance, let it be my home. Yeah, like that.
Let's see what it gives us. Oh, I can do it with the more readable format, so I can give it
with the home. So let's see what we will get. Again, we will have to add the execution bit
and then because we are already in the bin we don't need anything else
space shell so yeah pretty much works. Okay so now you've got also the idea how
to call the function within the script and again if you are kind of lost and
and you you still can go to the bin and you can check it from here and see what's going on
so I don't really steal all this this of course from you so you have access to them
so what else I wanted to tell you about the
There are also options how to use these pairs within these functions, how to use them
with the local variables. We don't really want to check it out.
One thing that I wanted to introduce you, another one
beneficial part of the syntax which is called the command substitution.
So, let me say that I want to define a function. I want to call this function
me. Okay.
So, what I'm doing right here, while defining this function, I'm actually putting to the command line
not the command itself, but the outputs of this command into one single line. So,
command line substitution means that you actually want to substitute the output of that command
into some part of the code, into some part of the other command that you are typing. It's quite
useful. You will see it in the further examples that we will run. And now just one single
to show you how it works. So I have created it so I have it added to the functions and now I can
once again with the type minus a see that my function has been added and if I run it you can
now see okay host name is not found i didn't check it host name
minus s
strange well whatever so
ah okay actually i know the i know the problem over here
so it's good that we've got this error message so what has happened just now again this construction
where you have the round brackets and the sign dollar sign at the very beginning it gives you
the output of the command and it just prints it to the prompt so for instance i want to check id
yeah and I want to check ID with the UN so I'm just checking my username
basically if I do it like this it's completely fine it will return me the
the the actual output of the command but if I will try to do it like that without
substitution it to the code without substitution it to the prompt so I'm
I'm getting the error message.
Why?
Because bash in the ground,
it will execute this command substitution.
It will put the output of the command substitution
to the prompt and it will expect
that it's going to be a name of the command,
which is not correct.
And so this is why you are getting the error.
Let me fix that functions
and say that actually what I'm looking for is the echo.
So what I need, I need to put them all together and then output it to the screen.
So let's see what will happen. I have to source it once again.
Now I expect that it has been fixed. Yes.
Now you see that I've got the perfect information about myself.
Who am I? What's my group number? What's my group?
And then also what's my machine name?
cool so once again now you have at least two functions defined you know how to do
it you know how to call it you know how to call it function both from the prompt
and from the from within the script and then on top of that you also got some
impression how to use the command line substitutions
oh i think we are
we are done but not yet fully i still wanted to add you
something with the script because i touched the
command substitution and so what i wanted to do
I have to, I wanted to demonstrate you some other commands. So let me introduce you some practical
usage. Well, me function was also practical, but this is even more practical than it is. So
you remember that tar command which I used just with the explicit, saying explicitly what's the
name of the archive is going to be and then send explicitly which exactly directory I wanted to
archive. So here what I'm doing in this command, let me explain that. So let me make it more readable.
Here what I'm doing, I'm using the command substitution
for a good. So first of all I'm using date. Let me say that I save this command
for you without executing right away so I know what date will provide to me. This
format of the date will give me year, month and the day. Okay that's what I
want. Then what I want else I want the current directory but I want to have a
current directory only the actual name one so you remember we've done it with the variables
now i introduce you another one way to do that you can use the built-in utility called
base name or maybe it's not built-in maybe external but anyway it's part of the system
So now you see that I'm getting the bean. So out of this one, out of this nested command substitution,
so first of all the command substitution can be nested and Bash understands this kind of syntax.
It's quite clever. So you will get bean, here you will get date, and the rest will be just as normal.
Okay, let's try it and let's see what will happen.
That's correct.
So we have created some files inside the directory
that we are archiving, so tar was given this warning.
And now you can see that actually we've got the tar archive,
which is named bin, and then the date,
which is dynamically perfectly generated name,
which can be used for the scripts.
So my suggestion that we will use it right away,
and actually we will go to this,
was tar something tarmi and we will use it actually not as a function but we will use it
as a command okay so so
pretty good we're already on the functions and i think we are ready yet for another 10 minutes
exercise. So let me see, it's there. Or maybe even 15 minutes, simply because it
may take you 15 minutes. So now what I want you, this is the simple one, you can
copy-paste it as is, just create the bin functions and make sure that space usage
in me both are there. And then on top of that what I want you to ask is add yet another one
function to that function's files and test it. So let it be called fast find function
just the ff and what it's supposed to be you provide with the fast find any search word any
and it must return all the files and directories in the current folder which name contains this word
and I suggest let it be case insensitive so in case of find you just put this minus i name
so basically just use this one put the search word the word I mean if you are not familiar
with the find you still have some time to try man find or you can take a look at the
course material from the reverse part so you can find some examples of find usage over here and
yeah let's say that we get 15 minutes because this is i expected that you back to the
functions and you will write something maybe more and then you'll write your
first function and make it to work. So 15 minutes so that means that we are back
to the at 14.22
I guess Enrique is adding it to the bottom but I mean if you are up for this so the text
is already over here
Thank you.
Bye-bye.
you
Ah, one addition, let's also have the break.
so we set 22 so let it be till 32 so we are including this 10 minutes break
sorry that's important just go and stretch your legs
or whatever you want to stretch
you
so we have left now already less than 30 minutes to go
it's almost 32 so i see that less and less people are actually
in time with doing the exercises so we will have a short also questionnaire at the end
don't run away we will ask how complicated was the material so you will actually your
opinion will have an impact. So if you think that we are pretty decent for the intermediate level
your replies are warmly welcome. If you think that it's too complicated or too intensive or etc
your replies are even more welcome. So I will try to adapt by tomorrow the
material if I decide to do so. So let's get back to the functions. So the space usage and me
actually the easiest probably was just to go to this demo space which I have
posted on my web page copy it from there and there you would get the ready to go
functions so please do it if you haven't done yet so or if you were typing on
your own, then just consult these functions that this syntax is correct. So one question was
why that was returning the error message that the command does not exist. So this was explained in a
way that command substitution will print to the prompt the result of the executed command
and that result will be already interpreted as a command.
And so if you just put your login name on the prompt,
then of course there is no command with that name.
And so basically you will get the error message
that the command doesn't exist.
Just a second, I close the room.
Oops. Back online. The other one. Fast found. So what I was trying to, what I was trying to
make it to do. So find function. Where was it? Find name. So that should be already
good enough to get started
the only thing that you need to substitute is search word
like for instance if i would like to be some kind of word
i don't know let's say that i
what kind of stuff i have here do we need store bin
okay let me find for instance the bash history
so now I want to iname and then I want to find something which has bash in name
that wouldn't be enough because it will be looking explicitly for something which is named bash
but we are looking for something which has bash in the name so we need to put this
stars just to make sure that actually we are looking for something which has bash
now that should be good enough and we found already bash history which is in
the current directory and we also have found the hello bash which is somewhere
down there okay now we need to create a function we have already ready to go
command we have it tested from the prompt and we are ready to put it to the
functions. So let me call it
fastfound. I open this this way and I close it this way and I put my name over here. So I also
was told that this should pick up any search word, not only bash. Okay, so we can
and remove it from here,
and then we need to specify what we want.
The good practice,
if we actually use some specific variable over here,
even if you can use this $1,
and you expect that the variable exists,
we usually, and the best practice I usually suggest,
well, I'm not sure about we,
I usually suggest that you use the,
you reassign this $1 to some other variable it's made in the way that you do not occasionally
actually would try to edit this or modify and otherwise you would get the error message
so in this case that should work perfectly yeah i guess so but let me see
The only error over here is that I don't want to use the quotes, single quotes, I need to use this
double quotes. Why? Because I did the explanation at the very beginning of this session, double quotes
make the bash to actually open the variables and substitute the variables. Single quotes will just
take the word as is with the dollar sign and nothing would happen. So this is already something.
and let's say that I want to source it once again and I want to see that
type minus AFA and see it's there and if I want to try this again with a bash see
whether it works it works if I want to try without bash does it work it does
work because find will find you everything even if you provide empty string so basically
it's just we're using this star to tell you that it has lots of file inside
okay we don't really want this kind of situation so it really wants to make sure that actually
this word is not empty what to do in this case we can use once again a logic
a magic of this variable exchange and then what we do here is that we are supposed to actually
give out either the variable itself or the error message and so that we can say here that
what was a directory or search word so sorry we are search word is missing
does it work for us yeah I'm pretty sure this would be already good enough for us
but one thing to remember we still don't want that this find will be executed how
to do that and this where we come with another one thing which i didn't tell you yet but i will tell
you on the next session but i will already use it over here just to make this kind of function
complete so let's say that i will execute it like this and let's see what's going on so source
and then if I run ff search word is missing so it's already completely correct and so we have
just exited the bash so we don't really need anything over there but then if you want to be
completely sure what's going on actually let's don't go that far and let's go to the next session
and then I will do the explanation and do the modification to this code already right away
so to have to have it on the line and go in line with the traditional thing I can
put it as a replace
okay here you go
brush
so here you go and let's make it more compact
like this
good so let's get back to the material so my next step was actually touch a little bit the
redirections. So I'm not going to the conditionals yet, so I wanted to tell you something about
redirections because I want to touch a few other things within these subjects. Redirections have
been actually pretty much covered, I think, due to command line utilities. I think they have been,
yeah, redirections have been covered pretty much in the same, in the previous ones. And then also
we have it's quite a lot of things covered also within this material so that's a kind of advanced
one but let me say a few words because it's important even if you know this it's still
important so every time every time when you are running some kind of any command when you are
running any script whatever program a lot of happens actually under the hood and one of the
thing which has happened is that you are getting along with your running file several file descriptors
open for you. Some of them are reserved and even enumerated so that's the 0, 1 and 2
and they stand for the standard input, standard output and standard error output
and all of those guys there actually can be controlled. So you can control where
by default if you type something like echo or if you type any commands and hit
output something it goes to your standard output and the standard output
is the screen the terminal of your terminal so you just see it on your
on your display basically but you can control where it goes and one thing to
do is to actually do the redirection and you can redefine actually all of them
but let's say that I want to do the redirection of something which I don't
want to see I can use as an example pink command so pink one of the Google DNS
servers what it tells me that if pink goes through that means i am online so i don't want this to be
interactive i want to just one single one single packet which will be sent and then exited but i
still don't want this one go to the screen. I want only the exit code. And we were talking with you
already, the exit code, even if you don't get any output of the command, you can always take a look
at what kind of exit code was given by that command. And if it's succeeded, then the exit code
will be zero if it's not succeeded it will be something else than zero one usually one or it
could be two it could be in two five six six so that's kind of exit code so i think uh maximum is
256 that's the maximum but uh can be wrong so not really sure usually from the programmer
perspective you can by the number of this output you can say what exactly has happened and what
went wrong. Okay, but in this case what I am saying here, I've used the redirection sign.
This says me that I want to redirect the standard output to some other place. So, you can do it
and redirect it to a file and that would be part of the exercise. But you can also do something else
and you can use the special device called null. On Linux that means that everything what goes to
the dev null will disappear it will not be seen anywhere so let's see what will happen over here
pink is okay and then if you see that i can actually check the
status which has been returned it's zero so it's correct
let's emulate somehow the situation that we didn't reach the pink so i will not be
disconnected myself from here but let me just come with something which does not exist and
which will generate the error message so in this situation ping actually has returned the error
message it still came to the screen and you see that actually the status the exit code of this
command was something which is not zero which is already from the point of view if you want to for
instance run some kind of if or conditional statement so this will be already good enough
to say that okay it's if it's not succeeded then do that and that okay but we still have one other
problem if there is an error it's still on the screen so what we do by default this redirection
pipe, this redirection sign will redirect everything which goes to the standard output.
But we also want to redirect everything which will go to the standard error output. So how to do that?
And we can say explicitly here that please redirect the file descriptor number two
and here we put the redirection sign to the one. So what will happen over here?
Okay, so from the bash point of view,
both standard output and standard error output
will be joined together and redirected
to the standard output,
which means they will go directly to def null.
What will happen here is that no error message
will appear on the screen.
And this exit status is the only one we get
because we are just requesting it explicitly.
it's correct, but in the modern version of, so this is the most common syntax for this kind of
notation, but in the modern version of the bash you can also use the compact way
so you can do it the same, but
but probably the other way around
Ah, yeah, that was the problem, not this one
Yeah, so here you go
So, here you actually, you get the output, only the exit output.
And what else I wanted to introduce you, but actually not the introduction, but the kind
of remembering from the previous course, is that this exit status can be used with the
logical operands. There are two operands in the bash syntax. That's the logical end and
logical or. So basically end says that if the exit code of the previous command was
not zero, was zero, so if it succeeded, then do next. And we can say that echo, we are
online like this yeah
let's put the quotes just to be more readable
essentially we are not uh i mean we are getting the error message
we are not getting the error message we are online and in the same way
that if something went wrong we can always say that
echo
we are down
okay at the moment we are online but then if something went wrong
whatever so we will be getting the message that we are down so this is my
touch on the redirections and then these logical or logical and and logical or
You can use it within the script easily, you can use it from the command line and
this is the most often used, how it's most often used on the command line, but
nothing stops you from using this on the screen. Then another one thing which I
was about to tell you is that actually usage of the pipe. Pipe, this is something
which stands for this one.
So basically, output of this command
will be redirected from the standard output
of one command to the standard input of another command.
And so let's see how it works.
So we have had kind of a couple of examples,
like for instance,
actually we have had already this disk usage.
So let's try it once again.
Okay, what I did, so what's happening over here is that we are redirecting everything
what we've got from the disk usage command to the sort and the tricky thing that if you
want to redirect also the error from the from the command number first you will
also do it this way okay
maybe it's the other way around so I was yeah that's the other way around but
actually if I want to get rid of if I want to get rid of for instance this
message you can do it from this exactly situation so I don't really want to get everything what
comes as an error I only want to get something which comes to the standard output and so you
can see that our output is way more clear even if it's harmless it's still if you want to make your
code robust, you can do it this way. And also I have demonstrated you how to do
that the other way around. And I think we're pretty much
what I was thinking about. So we have eight minutes left, but if you're up for
the yet another one exercise i was actually planning to finish right on this exercise so
we can try to do it right now and then we will come back to this on on wednesday tomorrow at
12 i'll do the explanation so let's say that the rest of the time you spent playing with the
the redirection and piping this exercise.
Do as much as you want, as much as you can.
I'll be here probably for the next 15 minutes at least.
And we will continue otherwise tomorrow at 12.
And [name], if you want to get something
like how complicated material is,
that's also a good chance to do it right now.
but otherwise let's say that our last exercise for today is this one
redirection and piping so try to do it that should be fairly easy but except
the last one last one will probably take you some time to get to the point but
it's also doable there should be no something
not much of the troubles
okay let's try to do this and then i will
get back to the screen we will be about three minutes late
running today but let's hope that's okay
you
You