It can be started as well.
Yeah, I'm muting my phone as well.
So now recording is on.
Let's get the executive summary of the previous ones.
previous ones, so we went over the previous days,
or the day yesterday, there was the loops and conditionals.
That was already done.
And we went pretty much, lots of details and technical,
nicely, things like matching operators,
like working with the different,
we went through the arithmetics,
we went through the how to do the loops
with the for loop and with the while loop.
now the next step is to proceed through the several practical parts so my thought was that
this day we should be able to cover how to work properly with the input and then how to make the
traps what's the here docs and here stream operators then I was thinking about tell you
and show you several techniques well at least one technique how to make this script run in parallel
in bash even though it's not the real parallelization but at least that's kind of
emulation of the parallelization and then if we have left time we will cover also how to use the
arrays let's see how far we will pass this time so working with the input it's actually an
executive summary because we have already touched this subject several times you know somehow how
to use with the arguments then we use already the read command so you know how to get the output
from the prompt from the command line and then additional to that will be how to read from the
standard input. Let me start it to do it one by one. So, I have prepared several things.
I'm in my bin directory once again and I have prepared the several things for the
input things. So, input parameters. You remember already that everything what comes to the input
parameter as the argument is available to the script for several variables. One of these
variables as this dollar sign and the number sign it will give you the amount of the line arguments
then if you want to just list all of them you will have to address this dollar sign and the
at so that's the whole list of the arguments which are given to you as options to your script
and then, in case you want to just address them one by one, you're working
with the arguments like
$1, $2, $3, etc. So this you already know, this you already
remember and here I'm making you one single file which makes a summary of
these arguments given to your script. The first one is using the
arithmetic expression to check out the number of the line arguments. Then I do the counter. I go
through every single element and output it on the line. And here I just increment the counter.
and this is my demo so if you see amount of arguments is zero list of commands is
empty which is correct but let me see that I can do something better and I
give some arguments and here you see that I am listening so now these are
these are just the some methods how to get those arguments and how to get
started with them and how to use them. At the end of this slot I will also mention you some
advanced techniques how to use it but before that let's go back to something which is
which is more simple. So read command. Read command is actually pretty straightforward
you can use it within your file, you can use it from the command line as well
pretty much like that. We have had already one example with that and so here I have my
read variable, so these are which the variable name can be any, the point is that we just assign it
my text whatever it is and so if I wanna have access to that variable I have access to that
variable that way so we have had already one example and one exercise so you remember how to
use that but let me surprise you actually the read command which we are using right here and which
which we are using to give the input from the command line.
The original hangar is designed
not to read from the command line,
but to read from the standard output.
And so what happens with the read command?
What happens if you, for instance, do some piping?
So essential example.
So if I want to count,
you remember the amount of files and directories
my current directory. So this is what I do. I re-address the output of one command to another
with the piping. So what happens over here in between those commands is that the standard
output of this first command goes as a standard input to the second command. So that's being said
how to do next so if I want for instance execute some command and pass it to my
script what will happen how to make sure that script will be capable of actually
doing something with that input that comes out so let me show you several
approaches and I will start with the read command so by default if I just say
read all that's what happened read by default will grab everything what comes
to the standard input of my script and put it to the all variable so to proof
of concept let me do it this way I put read all and echo all so everything else
was commented for the for the future explanation but this one is just two
commands so let's see what will happen if I produce if I give no input then
essentially it will be waiting for the input but then
nothing happens but if I keep if I give some kind of
some input okay and you will see that actually
exactly what I gave to that command to my script
will be has been read by a read command and it's now part of the all variable another way to give
so piping is just one thing to redirect something to the pipe then you can also do it like this
so if you have a file for instance you can redirect as a file or if you don't have a file
but you have some some text yeah so I never told you about the process substitution so it's probably
the right moment to tell you right now so what's the process substitution is it's a bit
it's a bit advanced technique but in case I have a command and result of the command
is not saved in any file it's just dynamically generated but I still want
to use it as a standard input okay so what can be done over here and I will
tell you then later then why it's in some situation the must-to-go method
even though most of the kind of things you can do it with the pipe but sometimes
you can't really do it with the pipe so what I expect here for instance if I'm
doing something like echo some input what will happen over here echo will generate some inputs
and this construct the redirection sign and then the uh and then the brackets around what they
will give me they will generate a dummy file descriptor and this file descriptor will be
be forwarded to my script.
And so now let's see what will happen.
So we will get exactly the standard input.
In the same way, if you have a file, for instance,
I have a file like students remember
from the previous sessions.
So I can just redirect the file if I have it.
If I don't have a file, I can use the process substitution.
So just to take away message that process substitution
will generate a dummy file on your behalf
and it will be deleted right after the command is executed.
So you don't need to do all the savings all the time.
Okay, now you know this, you can put it on your demo.
So there was also some additional information
in the material if you want to.
But here I just, I show you what will happen
if I forward this student CSV.
What has happened over here is that my read command, which I did over there,
actually has read only the very first line
of the file, which is correct behavior. So it has read the very first and then it has been
assigned to a variable that's it okay but let me see I will come back to this just in a second
but I still want to continue with the read command in general so if I want actually to put something
into a number of the variables or even into the array I will tell you later about arrays
if you will have if you will up to this but now let's just look at this with
them several variables so if I put to read and after the read I will put a
number of variables what will happen read will use the default IFS
telemeter so by default it's just the space on your line so what will happen
over here, every single set of characters delimited by the space will be assigned
to the first variable, second to the second, third to the
third, etc. And then, for instance, if there is not enough variables, then the rest of
the line will be assigned to the very last variable. But if variables are too
much, then those remaining variables will just stay empty.
So let's see what will happen here.
So for instance, if I want to do the proper check,
yeah, I want to put it like this,
just to see that if we got anything empty.
okay so now let's see I'm getting back to my input parameter so by default if I run it as is
everything is empty actually I can even do the timing so that you know that it's the time out
so if nothing is given for say for four seconds then just just die or it can be even one second
because I am expecting the pipe it's not the interactive mode so in this case it will be
just like that okay if I provide some input and let it be a a b b c c for instance these are
three five variables or three five kind of different input snippets of the
of the string so you can see that actually what has happened
it has been interpreted as one single one because it's in characters
no no because pipe is missing here because my pipe is missing my bad
so here you go oh this input.s13.sh has got this line as the standard input and what it read has
done for me so it has assigned the variable f1 as aa it has assigned a variable f2 as bb
f3 as cc and since there is no other variables except the rest so the rest has got the value
of the rest of that line okay so far so good but let's see another thing that if variables is not
enough then actually the rest will remain just empty it still will be assigned but it will be
empty so that's the way input is being given to the file and read by the read command
okay but now we were working with one single string in most part of the situation you are
not working with the strings you're working with the whole bunch of text the blocks then how to do
the blocks. I comment out this part and I go next one. And here where it comes into use the while
loop and the approach that we already tried last session. And now I will go in the same way but I
just read line by line. So what's happening here? Read is again in action. Read is trying to read
everything what comes to the standard input by default and so what I'm saying here minus r is
just the it can be basically omitted as well but it's good to have it's just to avoid this
all kind of special characters and make sure that the all the lines not in one so we're making sure
that ifs is empty so because we are we want really the line by line so line in this case
will be the variable it's of your choice it can be any and just remember that exactly the same
variable you will be using over here and for a sake of proof of concept I could do whatever I
want with the line but I'm just do the numeration so I put the counter over here and increment this
counter every single iteration so let's see what will happen now it will expect some bunch of text
some bunch of text and so here this is where I can use already my file you can
use your own but here is the one which I have already in the ready to go ready to
play with and see that actually proof of concept so I went through all these
files and they have been numerated so that the kind of proof to you that
actually every single line was taken separately. It's not a kind of just taking the whole bunch,
the whole block of the information and output it to the back to the standard output. No,
it's actually working one by line. And in the same way you remember already from the previous
session when we were trying to make the summation of the total number of students,
so there were also possibility that you can split them into the variables
and actually work with every single line separately and with every single field of that line separately
so that's the standard input but that's not yet it
so I can come back to this once again
there is another methodology quite commonly in use
is that when you are checking when you're using the minus p operator so you remember that this
double square brackets they have had all this minus d if you want to check that
directories x minus f if you want to check that the file exists etc minus n minus zeta
so it has also another one operator which is stands for the minus p and you can check whether
standard input pipe is existing so what happens when you run a script when you run a script
this and bash will automatically it's actually not actually the bash but the linux in general
automatically detect whether something comes to the standard input and if something comes
to the standard input this standard input blocks pipe will be assigned okay now what we can do
we can easily check it and use it. So one way to use it, it could be as well while,
like here, it could be read, like here, or it could be just normal cat. So many of commands,
not all of them, but many of the commands that you use normally, they are actually expecting
some kind of standard input and if within the within the script you run some command without
any argument and the one which is expecting standard input it will grab the one which comes to the
script itself okay so in this case I can of course say def std it's for a sake of clarity so this way
we get kind of clear notation that we are getting the standard input that comes to my script.
This is unique, I mean it's this kind of virtual device, so this is unique for every single
program. But in general you can simply omit this and just use it without.
So let's see what's happening when we use this kind of approach. So if I'm taking
if I do nothing it will check that actually no pipe is existing and so nothing will happen
and now if I am giving something to the standard input
so in my case it's gonna be actually like that echo so it's the it will go through the pipe so
this this technique so this technique is expecting pipe so the previously while one was the kind of
free direction of the file, but this one is expecting the pipe. So
you can see that actually some standard output has been generated. In the same way we can do
something else, something huge, I don't know, ls output, so that will be also going as a standard input.
Okay, saying that, I must admit that I am pretty much done with the input parameters.
Now I want to go and make a demo for you.
Make a demo which will give you some impression.
Actually, I can make this bigger demo later on.
but now we can go to the first exercise so it's already time for the exercise
so my very first exercise would be this handler inputs and my idea of this
exercise was that you pick up the function which has been early added to
this our function commands file and I want you to actually you know here we grab the dollar sign
dollar sign one which means that the first argument which is given to the uh to the function
given from the command line but now I want you to do something that
some kind of piping would work as well. So try to use that minus P and then
std and try to do that in the same way but with a pipe. So I think 15
minutes should be good enough because subjects is interesting even if the task
is only one but I mean it's a little bit more complex than simple running simple ls etc so
that's a bit of programming so we will come back at 30 not at 40 30 no 30 39
so now it's your time time for the exercise
if any question as usual we just ask
You
you
I will be ready to go.
So let me take a look at the append path. So I will just copy paste the ready to go solution.
So there were probably you may have it implemented in some other way. So the way you want it.
But here is the one of the example of working implementation. Let me copy paste it over here
to the right place. So it's over here. So take a look at. So what I'm doing here. So I'm checking
that the pipe is existing. So now even if it's a function it's not anymore in the kind of compact
way. It's just the kind of if else etc. So more readability. So I'm checking that out. Then I'm
I'm reading it into the path.
So that's the way to read the stdin to the variable.
And then I need to also to check whether this path
has been already added previously.
This is from the original script.
And this is from the original script too.
And then it's just the checking if nothing is missing
then we put the error message.
So the whole thing was over here, here and here.
so now you should be ready to go if you want to play with that so you can already actually put
both parts together and see what comes from the standard input and see also what comes from the
command line okay this is being set so now I want you to actually
do some real stuff with me. So I have spent my evening developing the start.id further.
So what has happened over here? You remember we were playing with the
loops. You remember we were playing already with all these if conditionals and from now on we were
also looking at the standard input and all these parts together. So now my parts together would say
that I want to be able to tar not only current directory or not only a single directory that
I provide to the tar.it but I should be able to make a list of directories and make the archive
of multiple directories. I mean, separate one by one, but still multiple within one run.
And then my target over here was also, okay, I can also get the names of the directories from the
standard input. Essential example over here would be that if I run find and I find some
directories within and I just need to pass this list of these directories to my new script
everything is here it's pretty much implemented I've got the working version of that
but now I have done several kind of mistakes over here so and my next exam for you
and we will spend on this another 15 minutes from now. Now you should be able
to read this code, now you should be able to analyze this code and now you, I
expect that you should be able to find several syntax errors and several
logical errors in the code and fix them and get this code to work. So now another
one 15 minutes is yours we can give you even more just because this is very interesting
so this is once again so you grab my RIT the one which I have in my on my home page and this is all
so this is this one and try to work with this
so let's say that you have another 15 minutes to go
i hope it's enough if not enough we can quit doing all because I think that's actually quite
an important topic. So the floor is yours. I can give you several hints over here.
For the sake of a simple syntax check you can use
bash minus n and then the script name. And for the sake of logical one
I can give you another one hint. There is one way to see how the script is being implemented
line by line. It's the bash-x.
So go ahead and check out what's going on and why some things do not work as they supposed to work.
so I'm muting myself and now the floor is black yours for the next 15 minutes
and we will be back to the back online at 13 and actually let us join it with
the break so let us see 15 minutes for the exercise 10 minutes for the break
and then we are back on 13.10. I'll put it over here.
Muting myself and stopping the video.
you
Yeah, back online.
Hopefully you still can hear me.
So, and I do hope
you have had fun.
So, it's actually, I hate
debugging someone's code.
I'm not sure about you, but on the other
hand, that's the
perfect way to
learn the things.
So, analyzing the code.
That was actually quite complicated.
I'm pretty sure you are not
done most of you, but I'm pretty sure you have spent at least those time with
having fun. So I need to find the errors. So probably I should have told you how
many errors. I think I have done about four or five, but no more. But these are
we will find them out. So my first touch would be let's see the syntax error. So
because the logical errors, they are somehow somewhat...
Logical errors, they are somehow less intuitive,
but at least the syntax error, they can be found right away.
So the first error that I have found, that's on line 21.
Let's see what's there. Something with the then.
21 then yeah essentially that's the one of the errors which is quite often being done so when
you are forgetting this semicolon and when you put in the if operator and then operator on the same
stream on the same row so let's go and see next are we done yeah the syntax errors are there but
I'm pretty sure there are some others, so let me see what's going on.
What's happening when I execute the code? So I can try to execute it just like that.
So this, remember my expectation from the code analysis, if I run it without anything,
I should get the copy of my current directory, archived copy of my current directory.
Okay, so command not found on the line 13, so one more error to catch.
So let's see what's there on the line 13.
On the line 13, we have this construct, and
what I would say is wrong here is that this dollar sign.
Let me explain why.
So this is the arithmetic expression.
And as I've told you previously,
arithmetic expression if you use just like this just the round brackets it will return you only
the exit code and this is what you need so you only need the exit code because after that comes the
logical end so it expects nothing else no other output with the dollar sign over here you actually
you're producing the output so what you are doing here what what this code is doing here so it's
actually producing putting here just the number of the number of the arguments in this case that
was empty there was zero so that's still not considered to be a right output for the command
line so that's the one and then let's see further what's happening
does not exist skipping pvd blah blah blah does not exist there is no line anymore okay
so my next step is that I will try to bash minus x so I want to see the execution of the code line
by line so I will have better impression what's going on and at which point this pvd does not
exist skipping okay echo pvd does not exist and here at some point is checking the pvd
which is ridiculous so that should be the directory name let's get back to the code
and see that directory name so the only pvd we are using is this line
and you can see the error is here the quotes so the quotation is wrong and it
does matter as I already stressed you on the very first lecture so if you are
using the single quotes you will get the content of this what is behind what is
in between those quotes without any substitution but what we expect here we
expect here a substituted command so and actually vim is also was able to make
your highlights properly this way so we've got already how many free errors I
think fixed yes so let's think the next one so what's going on
rgz exists, skipping. This is already correct.
Something looks like... No, it actually doesn't exist,
but it's still skipping.
So what's going on? Let's try bash
minus x once again, at which point we are skipping.
so we are skipping it at the point where we already generate the archive name
and we are checking that the archive name exists and it thinks at some point it exists
why it doesn't okay let's take a look at the logic of this this is already not anymore a syntax error
but that's the logical error and the logical error says here that minus f operator actually returns
success. So it returns success if the archive exists. So what we actually need
here the negation. So we want to check that if archive does not exist. So the
exclamation mark over here tells us that this archive should not exist and only
after that we should proceed. Or we also can just swap else and if over here but
But in this case, this fix is way faster.
So now let's try the next one.
All right, so now these are just the errors that come from the tar, they're harmless.
And now we should got, we actually got the beam.
So at least this part is fixed.
But now let's check me.
So I remove it to clean it up.
I go up and I want to make several directories. So let me do it just from the command line.
So my bin and my store. Okay, let's see how it works. Can it take two directories at once?
Okay, bin store does not exist, skipping. Well, at least this part does not work. One
directory works the current one but when it comes to the when it comes to the
a list of the directories it already stops over here so let's see at which step we are so we are
minus d bin store so at some point when we are checking the existence of the directory we are
checking the not the one directory at once but both directories so this is definitely a mistake
okay and now I can see mistakes right from here but let me show you where it's here
it's also a common thing oh so that's the thing
it's a common thing when you're working with
the for loops people keep putting this list of items in quotes I do it time to
time also so it's not surprisingly actually here there should be just the
list with the with the separator so separator is usually space so it can be
any, but usually it's space. If you put something like quotes around, so that means that it's one
single item with all these spaces included into it. So that's another one error. It's actually
both syntax and logical. And then if you use the other ones, it's already correct. So variable in
case of conditionals that should be quoted but for the loop list that should not be quoted either
so exception over here if you have a list of some items which are which have special characters
and then you have to put into quotes every single item but anyway so between the items there should
be a concrete separator so there should be space from now on let's try are we good
okay something already exists
archiving bean archiving what's what's why this dot is there so let me see what we've got
we've got bean story okay it's not exactly what we expect we're expecting two of them
so let's see what's going on bash minus x echo exists skipping so somehow the archive name was
not generated properly so somehow the archive name was just that dot and without really
anything else so let's see what's going on over here so this is already over here
for dir in dirs so we don't know yet the directories so we expected that something comes
would come from here yeah we expected that this one should go to this one
dir dir and archive and this one was missing so what I suggest I suggest that we actually put
one echo command over here to see that what's the status of that variable so there is no
good debugging tool for the bash scripts you are not in the stage where you're programming
on C or Fortran not even the Python one so you cannot really trace the variables one by one
so your tracing is just to put in this print in echoes and so let's see what's going on further
so my dir is store is correct okay but store somehow is not giving correctly over here
Okay, I see the problem. So, the problem is my,
the problem is my construct over here. So, I was trying to use this magical,
magic of these variables, and was trying to use this curly brackets operator
to remove everything which comes before the slash okay uh so what that says to me that actually i
was planning to remove the path only but I have actually removed the whole name why because I was
giving the by default directory name with the slash so my script does not accept this one
and if I remove it see what's going on okay now it's much better now you should have got already
two directories archived bin and store both are there and then if I try it once again
what will happen I should get that they're existing okay and now let me do one thing
I want to make sure that it also works when I
provide in through the pipe. So let's say that I will provide bin from the pipe and store
from the command line. Let's see
Okay, so surprisingly this one works too right away, so I haven't done more errors in this code.
So okay, so now we can remove both, but now we have one trouble over here that we have found,
but let's see if that's going to be a feature. So we need to get rid of, when we get these arguments,
we need to get rid of these leading trails and at some point we will do this but let it be the
exercise for the next one. For now we've got pretty much working tar.it
and so you can copy and use it as an example or the other
the other script writes.
So now I'll drop myself to a new thing.
So if you still have questions or comments,
don't hesitate yet to ask.
I don't know, is there any way of going anything?
So, but just put them online if you want to.
Then my next subject, my next subject,
well, what's the time?
So my next subject would be Herodox and the placeholders.
So what I was about to tell you
is that Herodox paradigm is pretty,
it's not even Bash, it's Linux in general.
So it's in all the other,
in all the other,
this concept exists in all the other shells as well.
So it's not kind of new, nothing surprising.
but the thing is that you can actually redirect
the output of whole block to a command.
So why it can be useful,
for instance, if within the script,
you need to generate an email
or just a pretty long message
to the, and output it to the screen.
You can, of course, do the echo
and just shift the lines from one to another
and use this trailing slash,
but you can also use this here doc.
So let me show how to do that.
So I have prepared you one file,
one script which actually generates this exactly
what we are doing.
So a couple of dummy input requests,
so asking something from the command line.
And now what I'm doing, I'm doing here the here docs.
So these are two back redirect signs.
I call them back redirects, back directs or by redirects.
So you can of course call them less than,
greater than, et cetera,
but I prefer to call them redirect
the back redirect signs so it's just my attitude so what we are doing here when we are redirecting
a block of information we are putting just the command and we are putting the
back redirect signs over here these two web operators and then we are putting the magic word
magic word is a kind of stop word so from now on bash knows that everything what comes from this
stop word to the end of this stop word will be piped to that command the benefit over here is
that actually on the fly everything which will be piped it will be examined and then the variables
common substitutions and whatever you guess here to come they will be placed over here
so let me see let me show you how this particular example will work so if I run it
it will ask me for my name [name] and then here the new generated text based on
that template which was there so you have see now at least three replacements so both variables have
been replaced with the existing ones and then also the date substitution command substitution
has been replaced take a look once again at this one so if you need any email if you need
any latch text if you need to redirect this text to the let's say to the file you will work with
pretty much the same thing so let me show you now the example once again here document some name
some so name whatever it's called and now we've got the file with exactly the same thing
so you can use it as a template okay so I don't need that one but let me get back to this one
once again so there is one particular feature is that if you don't really care about all the
substitutions you can avoid them you can tell to bash that please do not don't don't make any
substitution. So whatever those variables will be, whatever the dollar signs or any special
character will come into the text, they will not be touched. So trying again, some name,
whatever it is, it doesn't really matter. So now because we expected that there will be no
substitution, there are no substitution. It's not a surprise. So probably not what you want,
but sometimes it's useful. Another one thing that's maybe useful and how you may think to use it
is to make the comments. Usual comments they go like this
this number sign number sign and there is not any special syntax in bash where you can make
the long commands, but there is this workaround that you can use with the here doc. So now I'm
introducing your... well this stop word it can be any, I'm just putting the comment here. I'm
introducing you one thing which is called no operation command so this
column column operation it does nothing it's literally does nothing so and if
you output something to that operator so nothing happens and you can use that to
use this as a comment so now what will happen this read read will not be
executed. Here you go. So that was just skipped. And then if you ever want some command to run
but do nothing, just do it like that. In bash it's perfectly fine. So it's part of the shell.
Okay, I think that's what I have to say about this much. What I wanted you to do, I wanted you to
play a little bit with the here doc so that something would have left in your memory and say that let's
put some
something to do ah yeah just another one addition to that one
another one in addition to that one so
there is also along with the here doc along with this
double back redirect there is the triple redirect
that stands for the return stream so it will be sending the stream
so for instance if you I don't know if you want to see the how the
variable is looking like one particular example ifs you can redirect like this so that's uh
i don't well I haven't found too much usage of this kind of operator except that for ifs or some
other variables but somehow for instance in many cases you can use pipe so you can use ifs but for
For instance, in this case, IFS is not really printed properly.
Never actually bothered to find why it's this way, what's the echo is doing wrong.
But at least here, if you want to avoid anything else,
and you want to put the string as a raw standard input-output for the command,
that's the way to go with the free ones.
I think I will not go any deeper with these ones, so now I have them mentioned
and now let's give you 10 minutes just to play with that and just to see that how
how these kind of things are being done. So if you are, whatever you are done with this one
but and if you still have some time and I want to play so at the end of the material
there is example how to use the templates play with that too that's interesting so this is
something where you can use as a template and then if you will be later implementing
some kind of script which will be working for you as a template this also possible to be done okay
Okay, so now let's say that we have 10 minutes to do that,
and that means that we are back at 44.
you
now we're ready to go
and I guess so let's continue so the here docs was already there hopefully
you also had another part of your fun playing with
that so let me show what I was expecting from
you so let me say yelp or just
end or whatever you call it and
forward it to a file and then let's see what happens if I do it
from the command line from the command line bash will continue
this uh uh this continue asking me what I'm
what I want to and so my point was here that
i type some text type some text okay then type more text and then I need to finish it at some
point and finishing it I need to use this magic stop word so now the
cat should have generate this file for me which is there another one thing so if I want to
play with
variables for instance
so and I want to say that variables like home
like shell should be here what else was requested
uh common substitution like pwd pwd and then is that it okay and
ah okay I was trying to do it in the wrong way somehow I have duplicated those commands
twice. So now let's try it again
home
shell and the command substitution pvd and then that's the end
so that should be correct file name and here you see that all this
information that I have expected okay that was there that was the task
for you to play with. My next is traps
Nowadays it's quite often that you will start running something
well nowadays the hardware is so powerful so that
and the codes are so well optimized
quoted of course and then but sometimes you have to just try to
kill the existing script. So in our particular case we were playing with the tar.it
and the tar.it was making the archives and then at some point you realize that actually you're
archiving the wrong directory or you are realizing that actually you're archiving
the right directory but it is too big and it takes too long or it's taking too much of the
IOs of your computer and you wanna kill it. What will happen after? So killing the process in
Linux in general, the concept is very simple. You are sending the signals and then the program's
supposed to actually react somehow on the signals. A bunch of the signals which come from the
operating system or from the user, they are catchable and so the
the command and the script can catch the signal
and can react this and can do something.
There is one signal, maybe more,
I don't know exactly, I don't remember,
but at least one signal is not catchable at all,
so it doesn't make sense to try to react to this.
I mean, if Linux is trying to kill it
with the signal number nine,
the process will be simply killed.
But all the other cases, command cases,
they can be still uh cached and somehow reacted so let me show how to do the reaction
so I don't have any script ready but I can come up with the trap.sh and see
bin bash as usually so we always start all the scripts with this one then some comment
trap testing and then actually let's do this so what trap wants trap wants some command to be
executed echo for instance say we are we are interrupted okay and then the signal which is
expect it when we are when we are kind of killed. So the signal in our case I would say it could be
one. So this hub when session is disconnected then two for instance it's just the interruptions
which when you're trying to kill something with the control c that's exactly what you send
and let it be the just termination signal. So that's the first signal when you are trying to
kill something, your program will get this signal number 15. And then if you try to kill something
concretely, you send the signal number 9. Okay, so let's try this out and let's see what will happen
with the script. We also need some kind of body. So trap is a trap, but we need to be some kind of
body which we'll be executing so I introduce you the command called sleep so what the sleep is doing
sleep is sleeping essentially so when you are sleeping this so that means that you can say
that how many seconds you want to be sleep so let it be that we can sleep for 20 seconds just
that's good enough for us and so that should be enough just to play with that and see what's
happening so let me change mode plus x and let's see what's
going on. So we are sleeping. If I press ctrl C, you see what has happened. After ctrl C,
this trap has been executed. Okay, it's already something for us. But best practice would be
actually not to have a command over here but to define some kind of function. So I can define a
function which I called whatever I want. So let it be end or let it be even interrupted.
And within this function I can already start doing something and then I will put it over here.
and so that would make my code way easier to read, I understand, and so that I know that every time
once happens something, when my program is getting one of these signals, this function will be
executed. So once again, it could be some text,
it could be if you are in the middle of something you can for instance remove some
temporary files and directories
okay it could be that you kill some other processes
because you know that you have to clean up after yourself for instance you know that you are running
several processes which are dependable on this one and you want to say to those of them okay
something is going on please kill yourself or just clean up after yourself then what else can be done
here these are at least something which is very usual so when you need to clean up some temporary
files and then you need to kill some other processes which are dependent on you over here but
but this is one of the best practices
how to work with the traps
and how to make your code even more robust.
So let me say it once again, trap,
if I kill it, so interrupted command not found.
Well, let's see what's going on.
Okay, it's the,
It's the misprint interrupted.
Yes, yeah, now that should work.
And now what's the bash is doing?
Even if there is this kind of issues,
it will never tell you before it actually comes
to that point, after that it will generate the error.
So that's a little bit tricky, some text.
So at the moment, we are just killing it
and so, and getting the text and nothing else.
Practical example.
Practical example would be our tar.it.
So let's say that we copy our tar.it.
So the, what was the latest version we have developed?
That was version three.
We are copying it to version four
and all of them are for the sake of clarity, named like that, so that you would know,
would see the development of the stuff that has been done. And now I can try to
do it more. So let's say that I will be developing this version number five and I
need to define the trap. Trap is usually being defined at the very beginning of
the code so that the code would know that exists. And so I define the function and over here
over here so my function is looking like so what I want to do here for instance I'm in the middle
of archiving something and tar what is doing when it starts to archive something it will create the
file and starts to fill it up and if it has been interrupted this semi or even just some partially
filled archive file will just remain there so this is definitely what I don't want to
so I want to keep everything what has been done but what is ongoing I want to
kill and so what I'm doing here is I'm saying precisely we have been interrupted
okay and then I'm saying that echo
cleaning up the ongoing
archive so here I have to put the double quotes just to make sure that archive
little bit and then I actually do the cleaning
I can also check if it exists so I mean just in case if it's in the process
and make it even more robust than it is
and then just simple cleanup archive after myself
And then I would say that our code is becoming more and more clean and robust. So I'm not really
going to check it because there is no any huge directory. Or actually let me check it with...
Should I try to play with my home?
Okay, I can try it. So first of all let me check the syntax without running bash
so the syntax is correct and let me say that I want to go with my home or I can
do it even this way so it will definitely take some time so it will
try to create some directory over here you can see removing blah blah blah
archiving over here I don't want this I decided that I went wrong so I keep
control c and what has happened it has been interrupted and cleaning up the ongoing stuff
and so there is nothing over here essentially yes robust yes easy to implement of course yes
so now you know one technique how to make how to surprise and impress your
future employee when you keep doing these things. So my thing I was I was
actually thinking to give you this slip stuff to do but I happens that I have it
done it already myself
let me let me catch for you and slightly do the slightly difference
so now the traps so catch signals let's put it this way I create a file
create a file any you can use touch something it can touch will do you some empty file
you decide what you want file name
and then catch any of those signals
1, 2, 5, 1, 2, 15. Withdraw and remove the filename.
Also put some text when interrupted. Okay, so now you have, I don't think you even need 10 minutes,
but let's say that we have 15 minutes altogether the break and the playing
with the traps and so you share your time up to you how you do this but just
to make sure that we are in time and so we will have still two sections to go
okay so now Dex 15 minutes again yours and now we are coming back to 14 to 15
so let me copy not sure if
Okay, and Rick is doing already or not, or he's not yet.
So I'm muting myself.
So 15 over, we will come back.
So it's the exercise and the break all together.
you
Yep, back online, should be ready to go, hopefully the trap was okay.
And I don't think I need to demonstrate anything, it just simply should be ready to go as is
with this slip command.
Or let me...
Instead of this slip, what I was expecting from you is that you touch a file, we can
even make it a more professional way. File name, file name
let's be kind of less professional, my file and then I touch file name then I
don't need this, I'll let it be sleep over there so that it takes some time before
we actually do something and then I wanted to remove that filename
remove that filename okay so I guess that would be looking like this
interrupted yeah with the u not a that should work out I will copy paste it to the to the notes as
well
okay now we go with the chop analysis another chop
And now my next step will be
debugging profile. Let's say that we have somewhat covered it already with the
code analysis when they did this, but I don't really think there is any sense to tell you more about
what can be done except this bash minus X etc so the profiling really sucks and
the debugging really sucks with the bash so it's it's where these programming
abilities actually ends pretty much or at least I have not heard about any
kind of good good debugging tools maybe already exists or because I'm I'm an old
school guy need to check it out but at least nothing that I would have heard
about essentially. So what I wanted to tell you and show one technique is how to proceed with the
parallelization. I'm not talking about any parallelization that you would think from the HPC
point of view. It's not the HPC way, so it's not the MPI, it's nothing to do with the shared memory
models, if you know what I'm talking about. But it's rather how to make the command executed
within one script. So consider this script just normal one, whatever. So let's even get the star
id back to the screen. So consider the script that every single command is executed serially.
so it waits for the result of the previous command and then will be executed one by one
one by one for most part of the code it's completely okay but then when it comes to the
body for instance here you decided okay we are running the archive archiving procedure and so
So the archive number two will run after archive number one has ended.
Sometimes it's okay, sometimes when you don't really care about the amount of time it's
spending or maybe it's the amount of time it spends on to execute this thing is so negligible
so that you don't really care about this.
sometimes you do actually care and in this case you have an option to send your command
to the background what that means so the bash has a concept of foreground and background processes
everything what is in your screen right now running right now for instance I'm running vim
vim is taking my foreground it's taking my terminal so this is why this is what I am interact with
and vim is now the process which is running in the foreground but there is a bunch of and huge
list of the programs which are running in the background and you can add to them everything
what you want. So I can send the vim to the background, I can send whatever I want to the
background. You probably already know about this or if you don't then I just send you to this
section from the first part of the course which is called processes where this concept has been
introduced foreground and background processes. You can go through it on your own, but then I
come back to the parallelization technique. So what will happen to my tar-it script
if I will send every single tar command to the background? Well, it happens exactly this.
this command will go to the background and the script will continue with the new one
and this way all the programs all the tar instances they will be running in parallel
in the background and the script will be just waiting for them all to end and
when they all they have done so the script will end as well so this is kind of emulation of the
parallelization so we are basically we in this situation we are using the multi-processing
of the ability of the operating system before I actually do any change to the tar.it
let me demonstrate you with the sleep command so I think
I think I can call it parallel, I would put quads around but bash doesn't really like it
so let me see that it's over here, so I still need to put my shebang
brush once again fingers a bit faster than tools trap is optional you don't need it but I just
for the best practice I kill doing this I will explain what I'm doing here
so you see if I go if I do the loop over a number of iterations so I'm using here just the seconds
one, three, five, three items as a second.
So every time I run a command,
so I'm using here the grouping, curly brackets
in this situation, they are used as a group.
I mean, I group the commands such a way that ampersand,
so ampersand at the very end of the command
is sending this command to the background.
That's the rule.
And so in order to sense the whole bunch of this command
to the background, I need to group them.
And so I'm here having this curly brackets
and grouping this command inside the for loop.
So what happens over here?
Sleep, then one of these seconds is substituted.
It will be one process,
which will be sleeping for one second,
another process, which will be sleeping for three seconds,
then another one which sleeping for five seconds let me first see what will happen if I do not
send them to the background I will need to I will need to take a time let's see what's going on if i
don't send anything to the background so my parallel code change mode plus x and I do the parallel
shell and see how long it takes. There is this utility, we have used it already with the
gaussian implementation. Let's use it once more. So time will tell me the
total time of execution. So you can see that it's executed one by one serially. Altogether it took us
9 seconds. So it's okay, 1 plus 3 plus 5 is 9. That's what we expected. But then
let's see what will happen if we will send it every single process to the
background. Let's see the execution time. Once again time parallel. And now you can
see that actually they will be sending to the background all the time. So
So basically what we are getting, the execution time went down to the 5 seconds.
What that means, that's the longest chain in this for loop.
So basically 1, 3 and 5 were executed in parallel.
This has ended early, this has ended after, but this was the last one.
But again, still the whole cycle took me only 5 seconds, which is more or less in some situation
maybe the lifesaver. So if your code really is taking a lot. And one key thing over here
is that by default if you just send the stuff to the background,
it will be sent to the background and from the bash perspective that would mean that the
command came to the end and that means that okay it came to the end and it will be just ended as is
so what's happening right now what we really want to we really want to tell to the bash please
you have something in the background and check it out and try to wait till they are done
and only when these kind of background processes which this script has
generated so they will be kind of the child processes of this script only of
one only when your child processes are done only at that stage please and the
whole thing and so this is exactly what wait command is doing over here so we
need this so just remember when you will start applying this concept of the
foreground and background jobs, you will have to use the wait as well. And then
another one approach which I think is reasonable over here is to kill all. So
basically what I'm saying here that find me everything with this command. This
command jobs minus p will return me everything which has been created by
this script if by some reason by some reason I want to interrupt this script without waiting
for the end and if some reason this one of the command is just taking so long or one of the
command processes hanging became zombie or something well it's became something that's
other difference it's just hanging it just doesn't do anything I want to make sure that I clean up
after myself and so that's this jobs what is doing so it will join you a list of the processes which
has been created by this script and with the command kill all will kill them all
okay and so I'm saying that every time it's the when the signal exit is
giving so please do this for me. So that's that easy and now we can also see
RIT what can be done over here. So if I would like to implement this within the TAR archive
so let me see that I actually copy this one to the
it's already version five okay and now I'm doing these changes once again and I'm saying that
the most time-consuming part of the script should be executed in parallel
so I put the ampersand over here so every time when my script comes to this point it will
submit the tar to the background okay and then I need to make the same thing that I would have
done it properly so I make to wait it wait till and so I put the comment wait till all our
tasks
are done okay
so we can also put the comment over here just to know
yeah we put it into the background we can try to execute it and then yes I would say that this
this trap also makes sense to put it over there
so the traps can be many that's another one thing for you so here I catch these signals but here I
can catch some other signals so the trap commands can be many it's not a big deal over here I can
just copy paste it or you can just incorporate it into this one so it's just up to you how you feel
it
check my
syntax and run it for the for a good
okay it's correct so again those ones are harmless
it's just the simply because I am creating the file and putting the file
into the same directory so the tar complains that something has happened in
this directory but this is completely fine so
rm bin and now I'm a bit because this story etc they're actually
they're actually quite small but just trust me that yes we are running a number of the stars
in the background so if I do it like for instance I want to have store yeah I
want to have been and I want to have my home home will take time so let's see
what's going on store have been home run it so now we are
archiving store, parallel bean,
and then when parallel also archiving my home directory,
which is what I wanted.
I send it to the background, the whole thing.
And now, let me see, with the command jobs,
I can actually see what's going on.
So I have several processes running over here.
So tar-it, tar-it,
and then actually they have been stopped
because I killed them and sent to the background
the original file and there was a trap which was...
Okay, but now I just wanna get it back.
Well, again, I don't really want to interrupt you much
with that because that's a concept
which has been already very well explained
in the first part.
So if you are curious what's that,
just go to the host part and take a look at the material over there
okay so this part I didn't come up with any good
example how to do that so this is why I was thinking to the why I had that I better demonstrate
it on myself because it's somewhat complicated and not really covered by this course but hopefully
you have found something useful out of this. What I want so well I can clean up it first for myself
being this can be killed then this another one which has been created
occasional as well and file name I don't need it either so now it's more more or less clear
so now the time to ask the questions otherwise I've after last section if you
need some specific and you want to yet ask me then please do because that's the
last half an hour that we are running the course otherwise I will just jump to
the arrays and seems that I have enough time to go through there from this part
and we even have time for the exercise, or at least this exercise will be with you as a homework.
So, arrays. Arrays, this is something within the bash which has been introduced not recently, but
I think many people don't know that arrays are existing in bash. So most of the people are
working with the variables. I've seen even the quite advanced users which were really surprised
when they heard for the first time about the arrays in the bash. Not that often used, but if
you know how to use this, you can definitely make use of them. So array is nothing else than a list
of items which are under the same name. So there are two types of arrays in bash. One is known to
you is that normal indexed array and then another one which is less known but to those who is
running for instance python or php codes they may have heard about the
dictionaries and the in case of php that's the associative arrays so this is what is implemented
also in bash in bash it's called as well as in php associative arrays so they are one-dimensional
both and in case of indexed array so it's where every single item has an index and you can address
it by index sorry somebody knocking the door but don't really open so in this case you just open the
In this case, what you have to do is that you have to really make a list of elements of this array
So for instance, in my case, let me clear first the screen just to not really overwrite with this one
So you do the array and you put the list within these rounded brackets over here
and every single element of this one will be the will be the index, okay?
So let me see what exactly is going on. So the easiest part...
oh okay there is something is yet running
it's there let me check that is there some jobs still running
nope
okay no I mean back to the back to the arrays so now I have once again I have defined this one
and now for instance if I want to address some elements of the array what do I do?
So here where comes the curly brackets back to use once again. So my array elements there just
go now name of array within the curly brackets and then the number of the index.
So you do echo array
and the index element. So in my case, r, you remember, this one was looking like
this. So my first element, it's actually marked as 0, so the indexing starts with
the 0, it's this one. So my second one
is this one. And my, for instance, I don't know, my fourth one
there's no fourth okay strange my third one okay yeah of course it's starting from the zero so
basically these are elements like that so if I want to assign the new element so assigning new
element is pretty much in the same way you can do this r for instance and now I know that the
element number four is missing so I'm assigning it like this so new
now this element has got also the element number new so the easiest way to declare the easiest way
to print it out there's a dirty way there's a command declare which we will use just in a second
you can declare and say, print me the archive.
Archive, sorry, too much of the tarring.
Print me the array.
So here you can get kind of very rough overview
what elements of the array are existing.
Okay, and then
the next one is that,
For instance, the arrays, these functionalities are pretty much limited.
You can assign a lot of stuff, but it's nothing to do with the real languages.
So, all these kind of libraries to work with the arrays,
like what you have in the different
real programming languages,
like sorting the arrays, finding the smallest element,
or going through the,
finding kind of all possible combinations, et cetera.
So, everything what you think about
is not implemented by default,
and it's not part of the really bash.
So you will, if you even want to sort,
make the sort of the array,
so you will have to Google
and you will have to find out
how to do that properly with the sort command.
So it's not even built in functionality,
it's the external function or external command
that can be used.
But again, something is still can be done over here.
So now this is the indexed array,
has been created you can change every single you can change for instance every single element so
i can put it new too yeah and so that you can see that actually this became that
this became this has got a new value you can assign some values which are somewhere not
on the list and you can see that actually all the other values in between
4 and 12 are missing but 12 is here so basically you can do pretty much the
same things with area elements as you would do with the variables but they
just get the index so a couple of things how to address them properly here is the
simple construct, which I can explain to you.
Let me put it to the bin as well.
Okay, I'm missing my exponential mark. So what's happening over here?
I'm printing it out. So what I'm saying here that I'm saying here that please
pick up this array and go through the indexes. So the indexes, these curly
brackets in this case, it's the mark for the explanation mark. So that says that
actually where I'm going through the indexes and not through the values
itself. Otherwise that will give you the values of the array. And so what I'm
saying here that every index has this value. So this is the way to print the array nicely.
But the only thing that I have to, what I have forgotten to say here, so I have forgotten to
define it. So let me just copy paste some dummy example from here. The address of the
university I'm working at
okay and then let it be even more
like this
so let's see
the only thing that I have to change mode once again
oh here you go so my small for loop just went through every single element of that array and
kept it over here
most probably cases where you end up using this it's the assigning of the area elements
from some command output. That's the way it's being done. So again you put the list and then
inside of the list you just expect some command substitution and then that means that you expect
actually some list of some items over here. So they will be automatically assigned to one,
one, two, three, et cetera.
If you need to append elements,
so this arithmetic stuff will work also
for the array elements.
If you want to kill them somehow,
so for instance, you want just empty,
that's enough if you just assign the empty list
to the array, or if you want to unset it completely.
So in the same way as you would do it with the variable,
you can do it with the name of array.
So that should be just there.
And then, if you want to unset, for instance,
just one particular element that's over here,
do you remember I told you that how to make the sorting?
It's not straightforward at all.
So you have to be really, so you are using,
this is where you are using our key string operator.
And so you are using also the, in general,
sort command and then the command substitution so it's not it's not that cool at all
same to say if the normal array indexed array what I'm saying about
let me check it something
something is all going on
but I don't really I didn't kill one of the process
let me see which one I didn't kill and why it's still trying to do something
no there should be nothing strange okay i'll take care about this later
just to be sure okay so let me get back to this so as I told you the index array doesn't need
any declaration. So whenever we have this r equals something, that's enough. But if we're
thinking about associative array, what it looks like? Associative array, it's supposed to be when
instead of index, numerical index, you actually have some real name and the key is a real name.
So this is why sometimes they're called dictionaries like in Python. So basically you're
saying here okay my e is university but the value of this element is the name of the university
so it's kind of meta information and then the subject itself and this is what is called in
the IT world the associative arrays and this what is in the bash world that needs to be declared
so you need to say I mean if I will try to do this right from the command line and do this
associative array right away it will be the error message so what I have to do I have to
put the capital A and say that associative array will be this one now bash knows that I should
be able to assign the array items this way okay syntax broken is address something is broken
okay it's probably
my light has gone off so the system thinks that I am out of this
uh I'm pretty sure it's about the
what
no it's actually all is correct okay so let me
back so now if I want to read it declare minus P in the same way as you would do
it previously so now I have it on the S bar interesting why so let's try to get
it back again syntax error and expression error token is address
um that's becoming interesting
it's probably some misprint somewhere which I don't really see
street address error in expression error token is address
There should be somewhere a misprint which I don't see
Well, anyway
Let me delete at least this part, it has already been...
Yeah, it probably didn't like that part at all
Well, there is only one element, S4
Why?
now I'm in doubt what's going on so that should be pretty much correct so that has been declared
as the associative array ah okay no it hasn't been declared as associative array so I did it in the
wrong way so the name for the which has been declared is this one and the name that I've
been using to assign it is this one so what I'm doing right here so that I will declare the right one
okay it's even doing the converting random fly then I do the assignment
proper one so you see that actually misprints uh-huh once again
as declare ah it says me it cannot convert okay I want to kill it first
like that I want to declare it once again clearly it's okay and now I want to put it like that and
now I should be able to print it as array okay now everything is perfect so you see that sometimes
mistype and lead you to these kind of unpleasant surprises. But anyway, here you go.
And the way you work with them is pretty much the same. So let me demonstrate you on exactly the same
beam beam array and so if I do the assignment we're here that way yeah
and I do the declaration right away and now I do the commenting so you can see
that actually I do the declaration and then assigning of this stuff on the same
line which is correct it can be done as well this way and now I should be able to print associative
array in the same way as I would do it with the index but instead of index I would use keys so
let's see how it goes so it goes perfectly as expected so you can see that the
element the key is here and the element is here and so the only thing that I've lost somehow on
the way this treating the address which is not what I want so this is probably
it could be something like this or it could be better something like this
i think that was there why we didn't get it properly street is addresses why they are missing
Okay, this is a demo effect. I didn't try, I didn't test this script, so
we'll not go deeply into that. Let me spend my last seven minutes better saying you something
more useful. So this is one of the examples which I wanted to tell you, and this is copy-pasted just
from my own bin directory. So this is one of the things which I'm doing more or less
automation for my backups. And in a sense, in parallel, that's a demonstration how to use
the associative arrays. So look at this. So I do the declaration of the associative array called
dirs and then I define for every several items for every single directory which I want to
make a backup I define it like this you can define it some other way I'm just for the sake
of readability do it this way but you can put it everything in one line and that will be also
pretty much working solution now I do something with my rsync so I defined what I want to do with
the where I want to put what kind of options will be given to the rsync and now what I'm
happening over here so that I go through all the indexes in that array all the keys sorry
from that array and syncing them in a way that I just substitute the value of that one
and then everything what comes from here that's that very simple but yet working
solution so nothing would stop you from making a single list but as soon as you
learn how to use arrays I'm pretty sure you will not use the lists anymore you
will start using the arrays so that's kind of advanced techniques and let's
leave those normal lists to newbies and unadvanced users of Bash. So I have five
minutes left, actually four and fifty, so my task was that we would have
done already one more exercise, but I think it's just doesn't make sense to
keep being in a rush, I put the exercise over here. I can say this will remain as a homework
if you want to, if you're really keen on trying something. And if you have any trouble,
please send me an email, I can help you with the code. Then what I would definitely ask you to do
is to go at the very end of this document and give us some feedback so please
I will leave you four minutes of your valuable time to write a couple of words for us which
are important in the sense that we are adapting the material all the time we're adapting the
course the length of the course and the type of the material which we are going which we
you are getting hands-on tutorial etc so otherwise I thank you for the
participation of this course and then also I already mentioned to [name] if
you're up for the credit if you want to go for the credit then just let me know
or let [name] know we have some special assignments really to know these are
quite complicated but I can still provide you and if you are really want
spend more time so you I can make sure that you will spend at least more at least one week doing
some other work for the bash programming and learning some stuff and then I can also promise
for myself that I can help with the special assignment if there will be a need but anyway
that's an option thank you from my side and I'm done so [name] if you want to say something that's
the time. I'm muting myself. Otherwise, when you're done with the feedback, that's it.