CodeRefinery.org
you
Hello, can anyone hear us out there?
Hello, hello.
So yes, someone says hi.
Okay.
Should we do our audio balance check?
Yes.
So the order can be me, [name], [name], and [name].
One.
[name]?
Two.
One.
No.
Three.
Two.
No.
Three.
Okay.
Four.
Five.
Six.
Seven.
Eight.
Okay.
It sounds pretty balanced to me.
Yeah.
Okay.
This was already an example of multiprocessing with message passing.
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay, so now we're in the pre-live or pre-main course icebreaker time, where we'll talk to
you a little bit and get ready to go.
So what you see shared here is the, what we call the notes document, or just notes.
It is a place where everyone can edit, so you can't see it on this share.
if you go up here you can switch to an edit mode and then you can write stuff here so it's marked
down the exact format doesn't matter that much but the important thing is if you take it up and the
only people that have it are people that have registered so you should have just gotten a
reminder email that also has this inside of it is that true okay yes and if you scroll down to the
bottom you see icebreakers here. So the purpose of this is you can come and you
can switch to edit mode and answer these questions and we'll discuss. So for
example I just put an "o" right here to show that I'm very familiar with command
line in Shell. So it's sort of like a bar graph we're making collaboratively. So
Everyone go open this up, vote for whichever one there is, and we can get an idea of how
we should be presenting stuff.
So the questions are, how familiar are you with command line shell?
Have you used version control before?
types of computers have used for work before? What types of programming you do? And then just
a free-form question and answer. What kinds of scientific work do you do or think you do? Like,
whether it's machine learning stuff or physics or chemistry, whatever it may be.
Okay, let's talk about what our answers for these would be. So, first off, I'm [name]
[name]. I work at Aalto University in the Aalto Scientific Computing team, and our job is
basically to help you with scientific computing kind of work. I guess you probably know that
because that's why we're here giving this course.
So of these topics here, I'd say I'm probably
very familiar with command line shell.
I use it all the time and script in it.
I've done plenty of version control before.
I've used mostly own laptops, desktops, group servers,
and high performance clusters.
And my main programming is in Python and shell scripting.
[name], would you like to introduce yourself?
Yeah, so hi everybody.
My name is [name].
I'm a research software engineer
in the autoscientific computing.
So on the topics, yeah, I would say that I'm very familiar
with the command line nowadays.
I've worked in these topics for years, years now.
Have I used version control? Yes.
In fact, just yesterday we were talking about anecdotes
on how, where we learned some of these skills.
And in my first summer job in Aalto University,
my supervisor wanted me to learn how to use version control
and that has definitely paid off.
Like that was years and years ago.
What type of computers have I used before?
Mainly, I do my work from my own laptop
and connecting from that to various other machines
like HPC clusters and a remote desktop and such.
So the laptop is the connection that I use
to the wider computing world.
But I would say that all of those are basically
what I've used so far.
My programming background is on the physics side, but nowadays Python, I would say, is the one glue
that glues most of the coding together. I would say Python is my main language, and then I would
say maybe C or shell scripting, I wouldn't know really. But yeah, basically whatever works for
the specific case at hand. Yeah, great. And [name], would you like to introduce yourself some?
Yeah, okay. Hi, so I'm [name]. I'm, I think, the newest member still of the
research software engineering team. Regarding the icebreaker questions, well, I'm familiar with
the command line. I've used it for a long time now, but I wouldn't say that I'm very familiar
with it. There's certainly areas I could still learn something about it. I've been using version
control for a fair bit as well. Still sort of a myth that I didn't use version control for my
PhD studies, but that's what it was back then. And well, I worked on my own computers,
as laptops and desktop.
I've worked remotely,
and I've also worked on the cluster.
Nowadays, that's just like similar.
I mostly do Python programming-wise,
but I've done a fair bit of other things.
I've done Matlab, I've done R, I've done C.
I've done SDCC, if anyone knows about that, it stands for Small Devices C Compiler, it's
for very close to hardware programming, and that's basically what there is to tell about
me in terms of computing, I think.
Okay, cool.
[name], would you like to introduce yourself?
Yes.
Hello everybody.
couple of minutes before kind of the official start and before mentioning something about myself I'm
checking the answers that you've been writing for those who join now you should have received
this notes document at notes.coderefinery.org and there you can basically edit the document
it's like a google doc but everyone can edit but it's just text based and when it comes to me
I work with the same team as [name], [name], and [name], and yes, I'm very familiar with the
command line. I started in, I think it was 1983 with the Commodore 64, and the only interface
was the command line. 1983? Yeah, I think that's when I got my first computer. I mean,
The commands that I was tapping was more like load and then name of the game.
I don't remember now the basic commands, but you know, that was my first interface
interaction with the computer.
Even though I was ex-sport, because my dad with this job, he also has access to one of
these computers with punch cards.
So I've seen also those back in the days, but more, you know, back to nowadays, yes,
the command line is maybe the most powerful tool.
I will share a link actually, there's a nice nature paper
that they show how important it is to learn the command line
or all type of science.
Virtual control, it's actually all the pages,
the web pages that you see that we in our documentation
or even the websites that we share sometimes,
they're all actually based using,
they're all written and shared through Git and GitHub.
So even though it's not just for, you know,
keeping track of your code,
it can also be very useful for publishing.
And in general, I mean, a bit of Python, a bit of R,
MATLAB, I used a lot of MATLAB in the past
because with neuroscience, which is my background,
we have lots of those tools.
But great to see that many people are connected.
There's 41 people in this HedgeDoc notes document.
So if you feel that it's getting a bit slow,
you can switch to the view mode.
And what were you saying, [name]?
Yeah, and I guess we're about to start.
If we look at the icebreaker answers here,
people are basically answering what we'd expect.
So the audience as a whole seems to be
at the right level for this course.
So we are not talking about the prerequisites
of most of these kinds of things.
important tools you'll use but not the main topic of the course. Our main topic is this section
right here. Although our team doesn't just support the cluster, we support everything that you see
on this list. So as you'll learn later on, we have different help sessions where you can come
and we're around to help with all of these things because we completely understand that computers are
complex. There's just so many different things that people have to know and learn in order to
do stuff. And that's why our team's funded. So you can focus on your work and we focus on
the other stuff. With that being said, I guess it's time to start. So I believe it's
[name] and [name] with the intro. So I'll hide myself and switch to [name]'s screen.
Uh, there you go.
So see you later.
So the page that I'm showing right now,
the webpage that I'm showing is the same
that you have received in the email if you register.
And if you have access also to this notes document
that you've been using for writing your answers,
it's also at the very top.
And this is basically kind of the collection of links
that we will use throughout the day.
So if I scroll down to the schedule,
we are basically here.
And very briefly, I give you a little start
or a little intro of what is happening right now
and what is this.
So I guess you already heard who we are.
We are the people from other scientific computing,
kind of our part of the School of Science.
We help everyone at Aalto basically,
we support large performance, high performance computing.
And as [name] just said, all sorts of requests
that can be related to software,
but not only software, also data,
open science and many other things.
We are well integrated with all the other
research services network and IT services networks.
So we're all in working together
to support people at Aalto University.
On top of that, we also collaborate a lot
with other universities in Finland and with CSC,
which is the main partner for computational resources
for basically all the Finnish researchers.
And we also belong to the Code Refinery Network,
which is a network that spans across all the Nordic countries
where we organize this type of workshop.
The course for today, normally we have this course
and we will have this course as a three days course,
so much longer and much slower.
We have it in the first week of June,
and we do it because that's the week
when the summer workers are joining at the university.
So usually the scale there is much bigger.
We have 300 participants,
and then we basically,
instead of having just a single day like we have today,
we have multiple days where we can cover
in detail all the topics.
So if you wish to have a more in-depth,
like deeper overview of everything.
I recommend joining the June version,
the longer version of this course.
But now here, most of you already have a Triton account,
already have maybe even submitted jobs
and work with Triton.
So this is more like a compressed two hours
of what can you do with HPC and specifically with Triton.
And then in the afternoon, we can actually spend time.
We have three hours together where we can do
whether you want to do the basic exercises that we have,
or maybe you want to learn how to run large language models
like local large language models on Triton,
or maybe you have more advanced needs,
whether you need to use GPUs
or some other more advanced parallel programming.
So the afternoon part, if you want to join,
that will happen in Zoom,
and it would be much more interactive.
I don't basically need to go through all the practicalities,
but maybe what you're already feeling right now
that instead of being in a Zoom room,
right now we're using Twitch TV,
which is basically like a TV streaming.
And the main advantage is that with Twitch TV,
as soon as the streaming stops,
the recording will be immediately available
so that you can re-watch it later today
or whenever you want.
And on top of that, we don't have the issue that,
you know, sometimes in Zoom,
there might be some participants that might appear
on the screen or maybe a microphone that are not unmuted.
So we don't have this type of issues.
Basically, what else can I say
that we use this type of vertical screen sharing?
And the reason is that for those who have only one screen,
so kind of laptop users,
they can have within the same screen space,
basically a space for the Twitch stream,
where they can watch the streaming
and in the other, in the rest of the screen,
they can keep the web browser open and so on.
Of course, if you have multiple screens,
you don't have this issue,
but with this approach, we are able,
you should be able to always have the window,
the streaming window visible.
Maybe I don't need to go through everything,
but if something goes wrong, it can happen, stay in tune and, you know, if the streaming
disappears or something like that, we will try to get it back and if there's larger technical
issues, we have already a plan B for everything. Just a last reminder that, you know, we follow
the Alto Code of Conduct and so we hope that this is a great experience for everyone and if you
feel that something is wrong just get in touch with one of the organizers so we
still have some 10 minutes [name] are you there? I'm here there was a short network
error but I think we have recovered. Okay was it on my side or on your side? It
It might be on my side.
OK.
So maybe I'll ask you.
Did we say how people can write questions in the notes
at any time?
True.
So that's the same notes document
that you already were using for these icebreakers.
You can use it for writing questions there.
And so anything that comes to your mind,
please write it there.
And then we can give answers.
It also gets all the links to whatever
we're looking at and any notes we're sending to you.
And everyone you don't see on the stream
is there watching that and answering your questions.
So go for it.
Okay, that's all.
Yes, we have a big network of helpers already.
So if I ask you, Suza, what is scientific computing?
How would you answer that?
Basically, I would answer that scientific computing
is, at the baseline, every part of computing that helps science, that helps researchers.
And then, obviously, you would want to ask, what is computing? And, well, computing is
using computers instead of pen and paper to solve your problems. So solving problems with
help of computer to help research is what scientific computing is.
Yes, I totally agree. There's this funny xkcd. Someone said that there's always an xkcd for
anything related to computing or computers. And you know, is this your machine learning system?
So you know, it's like a pile of stuff. And sometimes we have this maybe approach to computing
that we might not understand all the bits that are happening inside the pile. So we kind of maybe
have a kind of some sort of black box experience with the computing that some data comes in and
something comes out. So this very short introduction is actually trying to, you know, open this black
box. And I think it's still important to get the basic. So like [name] was saying, a common site,
if you're computing flowchart would be that you know that you have some data,
whether it's collected data or simulations, and then there is some processing happening,
and then you generate some outputs that can be statistical tables,
AI model, machine learning models, whatever is the output, and then you know you write papers,
posters, figures, and publish, and become successful, and you know be a famous scientist.
But then what actually happens in practice, and I think this is very important because
we were chatting with others that sometimes this jargon of the basically hardware that
is needed for doing scientific computing is just assumed that everybody knows about everything,
but maybe it is not like that.
And I also think that it's important once someone knows how the components are connected
with each other.
And if they're actually physically close to each other
or physically far away from each other,
then it can also affect, you know,
is it going to be fast?
Because yes, the memory that I'm using
is really few millimeters away
from the computing that is happening.
Or is it that the data that I'm loading
is far away in some remote server in the cloud,
as they say.
So what do you see here in this type of stacked
picture is basically that we, you right now,
even with your laptop or with your desktop computer
that you're watching this stream,
or even with the phone, because the thing is similar.
We have the hardware level and inside the hardware,
the physical box, there are CPUs, GPUs,
RAM, SSD, and the network.
So these elements, there are the definitions here
and we will not go through the definitions.
Maybe this is familiar to all of you,
But already, if you feel that you don't know
what are all these elements,
then you already might be kind of missing
in the moment where you later you will see
that you request some computing resources
from an HPC cluster.
You are going to be asked, do you need CPUs?
How many do you need?
How much RAM do you need?
Do you need GPUs?
Do you need to use the local disk,
which is this SST here?
Or will you use some network disk
that is not physically inside the hardware that you use.
So these type of things are actually things
that you will need to think about daily
when you work with high-performance computing systems,
but they're basically things that sometimes you,
how can I say, forget that they are always there
whenever you are working.
On top of the hardware level,
there's the operating system
that basically is basically interacting with the hardware
and then enabling the fact that on top
of the operating system,
you can run your Python or MATLAB or R.
There's a nice little box here about containers.
We will not cover those today,
but basically it's like bringing another operating system
with the software on top of the operating system
and the hardware.
So without going through this definition
that maybe some of you have,
I just want to show that we have a great video series
on understanding computing through the kitchen metaphor.
So I will not show the video right now,
but it's linked in the page.
And in the video, there's gonna be [name] with a cat.
Actually, they are going to basically explain
how all these elements, the CPU, the GPU,
the RAM, and so on, are kind of connected to each other
and what it actually means in practice
for your day-to-day work.
There's also a set of slides
with this metaphor of the parallel computing in the kitchen.
And so the metaphor kind of goes,
if I can cover it just briefly,
we have still a couple of minutes,
that each burner of a stove is like a core,
it's like one of this CPU.
and then the whole store stove is like the processor.
Then, you have the memory, which is the counter space
where you can leave some of your ingredients that you need,
that you need to move inside these pots
on top of the burners.
And then of course, if the kitchen counter
have the ingredients that are ready easily to access,
you might have more ingredient
that are a little bit more far away in the fridge,
for example, or in some other cupboards.
And then you have the instructions, which is the program.
So the recipe that takes all these ingredients
and on top of one core or maybe more core,
if you need to cook multiple things in parallel,
can basically process the ingredients
and generate the output, which is the food.
We don't have time to go through this metaphor
and everything, but I really like this picture
that, for example, what if you don't have enough CPU
or enough memory.
This, I don't know if this has ever happened to you
in your kitchen, probably not.
But you know, you have these cases
where the kitchen counter is too small.
You just can't fit all the ingredients there.
You don't have enough burners to cook everything.
And so this is also when things might start slowing down
or maybe where your process might actually die
because you don't have enough memory and it gets killed.
Another last thing that I want to mention,
that sometimes people have expectations about clusters.
Working in a cluster doesn't necessarily means
that it's gonna be faster.
And here there's a nice example
that the laptop processing unit
might actually have more power than the stove
that has to share all the power
with the multiple processing units.
So often your laptop as a single processing unit
is much faster than let's say that the same processing unit
in a cluster, in a server.
But of course, it's also kind of the compromise
that on the laptop you have only one
or a handful of processing unit.
In the cluster, you can actually run thousands,
tens of thousands of processing unit in parallel.
But then again, what you need to understand
is that is your code written in a way
that can actually use the tens of thousands
of processing unit?
Or is it that when you move it to the cluster,
it will just use one processing unit,
which is actually slower than the one
that you have in your laptop.
So all of these will be covered later
with the example during the morning.
And just the final picture, the GPU.
I find it very funny.
So where GPUs are like the burners,
but in parallel, you can cook multiple,
in this case, you know, chickens.
So it's a large system that at the same time
can do the same operation multiple times.
So hopefully this was, how can I say,
inspiring enough and motivating enough
and maybe you all knew about these things.
We don't really have time to cover this
but you can read this page
and there's even a video related to this page.
But basically this is what I was just saying
that sometimes moving the stuff to the cluster
doesn't automatically make things faster.
So, I'm basically ready to switch to pass the ...
Or do you want to add anything, Suza,
that might be good for clarifying?
No, I think you covered most things.
Excellent. So, I would also switch the screen
to [name] and [name],
but do you want me first to explain a bit
of the geography of the cluster or will you go through, you know, what is the login node then?
I think it's probably good if you would explain that.
All right, so basically one thing, like you're all familiar with your own laptop or desktop, you
log in with your username and password and basically this is where you would be, you know,
that you have a desktop or you have a laptop it can be in the Alto network that you see here because
it's in a it's in a it's in a office at Alto or maybe you're at home in the internet with your
with your laptop so then we Alto uses this virtual private network and the idea is not to make your
life more difficult the idea is that once you know that your laptop your personal laptop or
or your computer that are part of the network,
then other bits that are inside the network
also becomes accessible.
The reason, of course, is kind of confidentiality
of the information that might be moving
between these different elements.
And in general, it also makes it easier
to prevent external attacks.
So using the VPN in the end is useful,
but of course there are also ways to connect to this system
without necessarily being in the VPN.
But for simplicity, let's say that now
you're in the Alto VPN.
So now you actually have access
to all these different elements that you see here.
There are the department workstation,
maybe you have one, or maybe that you're given a laptop.
We also have this type of external interface,
vdi.alto.fi, where you can basically get a virtual desktop.
That's the VD, virtual desktop interface,
so that you know you are, I don't know,
out for a conference, but you don't have
your Alto laptop with you and you need to access something,
you can always go to this vdi.alto.fi
and see the file system,
the same thing that you will still see in the department.
And then there's the Triton cluster.
So the idea of the cluster
is that there is another network inside the network.
And this network between these hundreds of computers
is actually very, very fast, extremely fast.
It's called InfiniBand,
and it's a type of connectivity
between all these multiple computers that we have there
that it allows really quick exchange of information.
Instead, if something from the Triton cluster
would need to talk, let's say,
with the department or station
or with the storage that is outside of the Triton network,
things would already feel slower.
The thing is that to enter the Triton cluster network,
you need to go through the so-called login node,
which is triton.data.fi.
Now I put this sign there,
which is, for those who have a driving license,
it means that you should not stop there,
even if you wanna stop the car for a few seconds,
it's not good, you need to move on.
And the idea is that the login node
is good for connecting to the cluster,
running simple things,
but then what you wanna do is getting a dedicated node
that is just for you with the resources that you need.
Do you need a CPU, one CPU, many CPUs,
a little RAM, lots of RAM, and so on.
This will come clearer with the examples
that are given in the morning
and also later in the afternoon with the exercises.
Then Triton has its own storage system.
And the reason is exactly is this speed reason
that if Triton would try to access the storage system
that you have in other Alto computers,
it would take the Alto network down
because all the IO that is going on between the nodes
and the external storage will be too much.
So this is why we have a dedicated
so-called scratch storage system.
The disadvantage of that,
the good thing is that Scratch is huge.
We have five petabytes of Scratch space,
and it's also very fast to read and write,
but the problem with Scratch is that it's not backed up,
and it's kind of the price to pay
for having a huge and fast file system.
So you understand that it's,
this is the similar kind of architecture
is also in other computing cluster like CSC.
So you understand that it's every time you kind of feel
that your analysis is ready,
it's time to move it out of the scratch file system.
Last thing that I want to mention is that we also have
a kind of virtual desktop interface to the Triton cluster
in this ondemand.triton.aalto.fi.
So if, again, you are not with your computer
or you need to visualize the files that you have generated
or the picture or it runs on Jupyter Notebook,
then this is the website that you want to visit.
And I think I covered everything.
How do you actually get, if you want to move something out from scratch, how do you get it out?
Yeah, this will be my understanding some of the examples in the morning, but basically there are different ways.
One way actually would be exactly this with this on demand, for example, that you can see the file system and get something out.
But of course, there are all these other,
in our documentation, we have, for example,
you can actually, how can I say,
make this file system visible in your operating system.
So let's say that you have, I don't know,
out the windows, you can actually make a scratch
so that you see it with all the other letters
of the disks that you have there.
And then from there, you can basically copy some files out.
So there's multiple different ways
of getting data in and out of the Scratch file system.
And we will show a bit of those.
But yes, that's a very, very important question
that we often get.
All right, so is there something to lift up
from the notes document
or do you wanna take the screen share?
There is some stuff there.
I guess I can switch to the notes.
Do you have the notes open on your computer
or should I switch there?
I should have them here.
Okay.
In the kitchen metaphor,
what are the notes we define for Slurm?
Yeah, this is a good question.
Maybe Slurm can be seen as the chef manager that coordinates
all the other little chefs in the multiple kitchens that
are in this department, or in this apartment building.
And I don't know if that's a good metaphor,
but I see that people are answering, so that's good.
Is there a smart way to move data between Triton, Scratch,
and department?
Yeah, this will be covered.
And it's partly covered.
All right, I don't think there's anything to mention.
So maybe we can now switch to you, [name] and [name].
Yes.
Yeah, thanks for that intro.
That puts us on the right path now.
So yeah, as a reminder, keep asking questions.
We'll be talking now, but there's other people
who will be answering.
Let's see.
Yeah, so what do we do now?
Now we've got an example where we go through exercises.
Well, not really exercises. It's a demo. So we're going to go, we have this model problem
where we analyze a bunch of public domain books from Project Gutenberg. We'll go through all
the steps that someone might go through. So we will go through downloading data,
copying to the cluster, getting our project set up, running things in different ways.
And this example that we are going to be giving, it's not like, I wouldn't recommend trying to
follow it, like type along it. It's better to watch it and try to see what is the usual
like workflow that you might do when you're running stuff in the cluster. So what we're
trying to show is a simple example that this is how a typical workflow might go through.
Of course, the case here is very small, but we'll try to show a typical thing that people
do when they're doing the cluster. And in the afternoon, we have a lot more time to actually
replicate the same thing if you want to try it out yourself.
Yeah, so normally we'd have this course over several days, over three days, where the first day
is a broad intro and the second two days for four hours per day are doing exercises together.
And now we're trying to do a similar amount of stuff in an hour and a half.
So it really is an impossible situation we've got here that we're trying to do. But that's okay.
Yes. So what's our example? So if you look down here in the notes, I've added a link to
the series of things we'll be doing, but don't, this isn't something you can
really follow because we'll be saying a lot of things that aren't in here, but
this is sort of like the big picture thing. So our general plan is we do the
demos now and then in the afternoon there's time you can come and work on it
yourself by reading the material and trying to follow along in a more
structured manner. I'm trying to give a link to the tutorials here. Okay I'm
adding it to the notes. I think it's already used.
Okay, yeah, so what is the example we want to do then?
So our previous example was calculating pi, where basically we would, it's like a stochastic
method of calculating pi.
You pick a random point within a square and see does the point fall in a circle, and if
do this enough, you can rearrange the fraction to be pi. But this is a more data example.
So in this example, what we will do, we take Project Gutenberg is a project which takes
public domain books and makes them available. So we found a data set of several thousands
or tens of thousands of fiction books from Project Gutenberg. All of these books
are taken, and we compute engrams in them. An engram is basically a sequence of words
or characters that you see together. For example, th are often next to each other,
or the words the is right before some other word and so on. So we have some simple code which can
analyze all of these books and then compute the distribution of all n-grams within them.
And yeah so if you want to you can take this and use it to predict the next words that might come
up in a sequence. But we probably won't go that far. So is this an appropriate problem for a
cluster? What would you say, [name]? Yeah, so I think this would be like, of course, if the problem
becomes bigger, like if we are dealing with the whole Gutenberg dataset or something, like
suddenly we have a huge amount of books, it immediately can go from like something that
is feasible to do on your laptop to something that is only possible to do on a class.
So this case is a good example of a case where you might want to split up the job
among like books, like you maybe want to analyze some books with one computer and some other books
with another computer so that you can do it faster, like you can easily split it up among
the data. So it's very easy to get it rolling in the cluster. So it's very like a data-centric
situation. And this can happen quite a lot. Often we are doing the same thing over and over again.
And in this case, we are analyzing different books, but we could run different parameters
and stuff like that. These kinds of cases are very good for the cluster because your laptop
doesn't have to do all of those calculations itself.
Yeah. There was this question earlier on how do you know if a problem will be well-suited
for a cluster. In this case, like [name] said, since the data can be divided and each book can
can be analyzed separately, then yes, this
will probably be distributed pretty well among the cluster.
We don't have any communication we need here.
So we're already thinking that way.
So of course, the data is a little bit
too small to need the cluster.
But well, it's an example, so that's OK.
[name], should I switch to your screen?
Yeah, sure.
OK, let's see.
Yeah, so you see here the series of exercises we'll do. We'll roughly be typing the things
from here, although we won't be doing some of the earlier cluster from the command line
exercises.
Should we start with getting the data into Triton? The first thing usually what happens
is that you have something you want to do and you need to get it to the cluster. So, in this case,
what I would now do is download data to my own laptop.
Yeah. So, quite often what we would have people do is try to transfer the data directly to the
cluster and not downloading to your computer and then uploading to the cluster if the data is big.
But we want to demonstrate how you would transfer data to a cluster because that's something that's
really a common thing. It's something we haven't usually demonstrated.
So, [name], you've downloaded a zip file. Yes, I see the zip file here.
So, there's multiple ways you can do that transfer, but this time I will be using the
ondemand that [name] brought up previously. So yeah, [name], if you explain what I'm doing.
Okay, so ondemand is a web interface for the cluster. So you can go there with the web browser
and then you can, so [name]'s already logged in here, you can browse different storage locations,
you can get the shell access this way, you can run Jupyter or you can even get a graphical
desktop here. This is nice because it's easy to use and can be used from any web browser.
It's not the most powerful thing, but sometimes convenience is more important,
and for this transferring data, that's the case.
When we are talking about transferring data, where are we actually transferring the data?
Yeah, that's a good question. Before we transfer the data, we need to stop and think,
or do we want to put it? So, it often happens that people begin working, they throw data somewhere,
and then it becomes a giant mess, and that's not good.
So, this is a project. Will it be a personal project or a group project?
Well, in this case, I would say it's a personal project.
Let's say.
So, we can put it in your personal Scratch directory, your personal work directory.
So, even for personal projects, we would generally recommend that people create a shared directory
for their group so you can share later when it comes up. But for something small, we can
start here. So, I see [name] can browse to the work directory. It also shows the path of the cluster.
Yeah. And because I have, of course, a lot of projects, I have a lot of
directory is already here, so I'm going to jump into a subdirectory here so that we can keep it
a bit clearer. For your case, your work directory might be completely empty, so you don't have to
necessarily go into a subfolder. But it's usually a good idea to have some sort of mental separation
between the projects and folder structure to represent that separation in the work directory
so you can find whatever you have stored there. Yeah. Did you talk about the path here? So,
we see it's slash scratch /work/[name]'s-username/teaching/winter-kickstart-2025/.
Yeah. So, the main thing here is that the scratch directory, it doesn't mean that it's
going to be scratched, like thrown away immediately. It means that it comes from the fast
network file system, the Lustre file system that the cluster has. So Scratch is the place
where that file system resides in the cluster. So whenever you go to Triton, to the login node,
or to the on-demand, or to the compute nodes, the slash Scratch is the fast file system.
There is also a home file system, which is mainly for storing authentication secrets and
that sort of stuff. But it's not good for computing because it's small and it's not fast.
And this is large, and it is fast.
And underneath there, we have lots of project folders.
Like if you have a research group and you want to collaborate among the research group,
we can create you a project folder there.
It's easy to get one, and you should get one if you want to do a collaborative project.
Otherwise, you can put stuff into your own work directory,
which is under /scratch/work/ and your username.
Yeah. Yes. So, okay. Should we upload the data now? Yeah. I'll create a new directory called
data so we can keep it clear and let's upload it into the data folder.
Okay. And we can do it from the web here, which is nice.
Let's see. Is this how you would normally transfer? Oh, nice.
Yeah. Cool. So is this how you would normally transfer data to the cluster yourself?
Well, I would probably use command line tools like rsync and stuff like that because, well,
I'm familiar with those. But in the case of small files or individual files, it's very easy to
transfer. But if you're transferring lots of files and you want to verify that they are transferred
correctly, you might use other tools as well. Or you might mount the file system into your laptop
so that you can straight up copy files from your laptop there.
Yeah.
OK.
So now we've got our data on the cluster.
So we also need some code there.
And the code's all already made.
And it's in a Git repository called hpc-examples.
So this repository has a bunch of small sample programs
useful for stuff.
And so again, we're not going to talk about the way version control works in details.
But since we have it there, we can run a command git clone and then copy it all onto the cluster.
Yeah. So to get to the place where we previously were, in order to now run that command,
I need to first connect to Triton. So I will use an SSH client. You could use from the
on demand, you could open this in a terminal in the web browser as well, but because I'm more used
to running stuff through the SSH, so I'm taking a remote connection to the cluster and taking an
SSH, so now I'm, the name changes here, so now I'm in the login node of the cluster, and then I'm
going to go to the folder where I previously put the data. Yeah, and it's really important to be
able to match up the place you put data from the different interfaces.
If you upload data by on-demand but don't know where it is in the command line, then
you've got a bit of a problem. Okay, so here we can see that
I use the command called `cd` to go to the folder, like change directory, and then I'm using command
called `ls` to list the files. I can notice that the files are now there.
Yes, so we verified it there and git clone.
Okay, so now we got the code. [name], what should I do next?
So let's see. Let's look at our thing. We've cloned it and you've listed it. Yes. So I
guess first let's verify that the code works at all. So we are going to run Python on the
relevant code, which is n-grams, so ./ngrams/count.py.
And now we're at the point we have
to know how the code even works.
So this is the code that we wrote ourselves so you know.
If you wrote your own code, you would know how it works.
And for other code, well, you need to read about it and see.
OK, so yeah.
Usually codes like this have this kind of documentation inside of it.
So there's a few conventions, such as dash dash help will usually provide output.
So [name] has written a nice help output here that will describe how the code works.
This applies to other commands in the Linux system, like for example, `ls` or `cd` as well.
You can run the `--help` to view the manual for those ones as well.
Yeah. But okay, so the way this works is we give Python, so the program that's running the code,
the name of the Python file, and it should be `python3 ngrams/count.py`, and then we
give a path to the data we're analyzing, which would be `../`, which means go up to the parent
directory and then to the data directory and then to the zip file (`../data/Gutenberg-Fiction-first100.zip`). So this code will automatically
decompress the zip file and find the text files inside of it without us needing to decompress it
ourselves, which is a nice feature. And this what we're about to see is really significant here. So
notice that we can run the same code on different data files without modifying the code. This is a
command line interface that's been added to this code. So, when something's really small,
maybe it's not important, but it really is convenient if you start adding these to your own
code. It can let you be a lot more flexible. Yeah, often these are called arguments for the
script. So, this is called, for example, the `ngrams/count.py` is an argument to the Python command,
and then the `../data/Gutenberg-Fiction-first100.zip` thing is an argument for ngrams.py. So by giving these arguments,
we can change what data we want to analyze and we can also give other things as well.
So this is often called scripting and Code Refinery has a great course or Code Refinery
will have in its course very useful teaching on how do you start scripting your own code
into this sort of format. Because if everybody follows the format, everybody gets stuff done
faster. So, I highly recommend joining that course that's coming in the spring to learn
more about this. So, let's try it out, right? Yeah. Let's push enter.
So it's telling us a little bit about what it's doing.
So where this is running right now is on the login node. So yes, it's on the Triton cluster,
but it's not really using the Triton resources. It's using just one place that everyone has
access to. So this is okay because it only lasted 20 seconds and we're just verifying
things are working, but sometimes people log in and run all their code here, and then they're
not actually using the resources and are slowing things down for everyone. But yeah, let's see what
does the output say. What do we get from this? So it seems that we got the n-grams that are
size one, so basically like letter frequencies in this case. Yeah. So there's a lot of spaces
Space is the most common character, and then E and T and A. Yeah, I mean, that looks about
what I'd expect from English character frequencies. There's different Unicode characters in there,
so there's some other languages. But yeah, so it worked. So we've transferred our data.
gotten the code working, barely, and now we're ready for the next parts. Did we get all our
explanations? We explained help, the actions. So, should we now modify what we previously
run so that we can run it in the queue? So, what sort of modifications do we need to do
for the command line call in order to run it in a queue?
Yeah, so I guess whenever I run something in the queue, so in the queue basically means
we prepare our order, our request for computing. It gets added to a queue with all the other
requests on there and then gets run on some cluster node somewhere and then those results
will come back to us. So when we say running in the queue, that's what we mean. So in practice,
since we haven't been running much on the cluster lately, we will have first priority. So the queue
sort of looks at how much people have run and the people that have run less have higher priority,
and so on. So it won't look like a queue, but in reality, there is one under the hood here.
and to test things out I'll usually do things interactively first. So that means we run it
in the queue but we see the outputs right here. So for this we add the command `srun` to the start
of our command. So `srun` means like "slurm run". So slurm is requesting resources and then we'll run it
right away. We add this `--pty` option, which basically means make it interactive. So
it will show the output as soon as it's created and not buffer it up. Do we need to request some
resources here? Like how much resources? So I see there's... Yeah, so all of the jobs that we are
requesting from the queue, they need to have some resource specifications of like how much
does this job need so that the queue manager can fit them to a correct place in the, well,
among the resources and among the other jobs. So the first ones we usually want to do is `--time`
and we know that it doesn't take long time so I will just say 10 minutes over here (`--time 00:10:00`).
Yeah, seems reasonable.
And some memory amount.
So we know from R, actually, we can look from here.
So in the previous code, it says max RSS,
which means resident set size or state size.
Anyway, it basically is how much memory it's used.
So it says it's using 44 megabytes,
so we can give it 500 MD (`--mem=500M`).
Yeah, I mean, anything less than a gigabyte
is so small that it basically doesn't matter.
Yeah, usually when you are requesting these,
you want them to match what your code is running.
And in this case, it's close to the ballpark.
We just give it a bit of a leeway,
like it has a bit more time headroom and then
a bit more memory headroom for the code.
OK, should we try to run this, or do we need more options?
By default, the job gets one CPU, so I think this is good enough, so I don't think we need
anything else.
So what do we see now on the outputs here?
Yes, there's this new thing, slurm job ID, something queued and waiting for allocated
resources.
So we see some sign that it's got added to the queue and is waiting for resources and
it got those resources.
And I guess we're waiting the same 20 seconds for it to run.
And yeah, there we go.
It looks pretty similar, maybe a little bit slower.
But well, it had to start up and read the data and stuff
like that.
This is good enough.
Should we create a JavaScript out of this
and then have a small break after that?
Yeah, sure.
OK, so now we've run things the most basic way right now.
This is interactive.
But with this, we can only run a few things at a time
because our own brain has to be sitting here
and waiting for the output to come out.
But instead, what we can do is we can basically
write up our orders and then submit it to the queue,
let it go process overnight or however long
and come back later.
So it's like walking to a restaurant and saying,
I would like this takeaway order.
And instead of sitting there and watching them cook,
they prepare it while you go walk around
and do some other shopping or whatever.
And then you come back and your order is ready.
So for that, we go to the realm of editing files.
So `nano` is a simple command line based text editor.
And there's an [script] file here called `run-ngrams.sh`.
And this will be what we call our batch script that
has the order of stuff.
Yeah, the name `.sh` means that it's
it's a shell script, so usually the ending means whatever what the script type is. In this case,
it's shell script, so some instructions for the command, like basically terminal commands that
should be executed whenever the job is running on the actual machine.
Yeah. So the other things [name] are writing here are basically the magic words to make
the shell script work. So we know this by heart because we've been doing this so many years,
but in practice what you'll do is you'll find one of the examples and grab it and then copy and
paste it. So don't worry. The first line says this is a shell script that should be run by Bash.
the second and third lines, this `#SBATCH`. The hash is a comment character.
And then `--time`. These are like the same options we gave to Slurm. So Slurm automatically
finds them from these comments. Yeah, well, when we give this to the queue system,
the queue system will look through the script and it will search for these kinds of statements. And
then it will determine what are the resources needed for the job. And then when we submitted it,
it will go to the queue and then once the job is in the queue, once it gets a suitable compute
resource, it will use this executable, in this case the terminal itself, to run all of these
commands. So it will basically type for us in that computer once it gets the resources needed.
Over here, I've added a few extra options to the call that we previously had.
So maybe [name], you can explain what these options mean.
Yeah.
So in the code, if you looked at the help text, the `-n 2`, means now we're taking 2-grams.
So instead of simple character frequencies, we'll have all the frequencies of pairs of
characters.
`-o`, is output file.
So it will be saving the output to `ngrams-2.out` (`-o ngrams-2.out`).
And then we have the same data file as before.
So we can save and exit.
So in Nano, it's Control-X, and then Y and Enter or something
like that to save.
So can you run `ls`?
And let's see.
Yeah.
Now we have a new script here.
and new script run ngrams.
And to submit this to the queue, we
use the command `sbatch`, which means like "slurm batch" submission (`sbatch run-ngrams.sh`).
And once [name] pushes this, it will be added to a queue,
and it will probably run very fast.
So [name] will very quickly try to run the command `slurm queue` to see it's still running.
OK.
Yes, so there we see.
saw the submitted batch job stuff. So the command slurmq says there's job 5819061 running.
Yeah, it says state equals running on node pe71. Yeah, so when we submitted it with the sbatch,
we can see the queue status with the `slurm queue`. And because this is such a small job, it will basically
go immediately to the queue. But with the Slurm queue, we can check how long does it take for
our job to get running. And once it runs, what do we get? I'll type `ls` now in this folder here.
Yeah, so it's done and we see two new files. One is `slurm-(somenumber).out` and that's the output
from the script itself. The other one is `ngrams-2.out` and that's the output of the code.
And let's look at it. So we can use this program called list which is a pager to view the file.
So just to view the contents of the file. So I will first view the slurm output.
Yeah. So, this is just the management stuff. We see it took 25 seconds. About the same amount
of memory. Yeah. Okay. Looks good. Yeah. And I can quit. I'm still in the program,
because it's an interactive program. I can use letter q to quit here. So, now I'm back in the
command line. So, what Slurm did for us, even though we said to the program that,
hey, put the output into this file, and it wrote the output to that file, Slurm also will capture
whatever output the code would say to the terminal, basically. If we would run the code,
and we would see some output in the terminal, Slurm will always capture that, and it will
provide it into this output file. We can change the output file name by giving an sbatch command,
but that's a different thing. But it will always capture that. So, you can always, like,
see what is the output. So, it's, like, compared to the interactive running, it's not that
different. We just, like, we tell it what to run, and we can always see the output.
So, and let's look at the ngrams output now.
Okay, this looks more interesting. ["e", space], ["t", space] ["t", "h"], ["h", "e"]. So,
"the" is definitely the most common word there. Who would have thought?
And then empty space and an "a" article is quite or "n" article is quite common as well.
Yeah. Okay. So, yeah, there we ran our batch script. Anything else before we go to the
break? Should we look at the timings?
Yes.
And the history?
So, when we have run something in the queue, we can run slurm history. So, the slurm is
this command that has various features that you can use. It's like an easier way of accessing
the Slurm output and we can see like let's say Slurm history from one hour. I have run
some other jobs previously so they might be here as well. We can see actually we don't
see any other jobs. So we see here that's just the two. Yeah so here's the interactive
one, and here's the non-interactive one, the batch job run script.
Yeah, and we see the requested memory, the amount of memory it thinks it used, CPU time. Can we see
the efficiency of the job? So, how much processor and memory it actually used? So, if we copy this
Each job gets a job ID that specifies, well, it's a unique identifier that you can then
look stuff up with.
And we can use this command called `seff` to check the efficiency of a job.
So if we run `seff` and then the job ID, we will see what was the efficiency.
And we can notice here, for example, that the CPU efficiency was very good, 100%.
memory efficiency not so much. But this was such a small job that it probably didn't even capture
that because these are sampled values that are sampled every so often. And the job is so fast
that it probably didn't even capture them correctly. Okay, great. So should we quickly
look at the notes and then go to a break. I'm switching to the notes on my screen.
So there's some good questions here. Most of them have been answered or we can talk later.
Someone asked about the priority. So how is the priority calculated? Is this something we should
answer now? Because it's actually pretty complicated, but maybe [name] has a quick explanation.
So the priority is basically calculated based on your past history and the sizes of your jobs that
you previously submitted. And the size of the job is calculated based on the number of CPUs you have
requested or the number of memory you have requested or the GPU resources you have requested.
so everything has basically like a price. And the size of the job, so memory request,
CPU request, GPU request, times the time gives like, I'm going to say it's like a block,
volume of the job basically in the cluster. So that is used to calculate your usage.
and your priority is basically like it has a half-life of like for every job it just has a
half-life of two weeks where like the priority goes down so basically it means it's just like
tries to make it so that everybody has a fair share of the resources so if somebody runs
a lot of big jobs they get less of them in the future so that other people have the chance to
do it. So the best thing usually is to just run what you want to do and keep the resource
requests close to what your jobs need. And there was a question of how do you choose these ones.
So usually the good answer is to measure what your job needs and check with, for example, `seff`
what the job needs. There's a full documentation in the SciComp documentation on how do you measure
these. But usually you want to measure what your job actually uses so that you can choose the
appropriate resources. So you run an example job and then you check how much it used and then you
lower the resources closer to the actual resource needs, giving it some leeway so that if there's a
memory spike or something like that, it doesn't go over the memory limit or if you give it a
bit more leeway in the time department so that you know that it finishes in time.
Yeah. The other question that I might answer now, how do you estimate the memory and time
needed for a task? And this is a really good one. And basically, I guess I'd say experience
and knowing the problem. I mean, there's no one magic answer here other than just run it and see
what it actually uses. So for example, if it runs on my own computer, I know it won't need more
memory than exists on my computer. And start with a few CPUs. So usually I'll start and I'll request
more memory than it needs and see how much it uses and then decrease to the amount that's used.
If you don't request enough, you'll get an out of memory error and then you know you need more.
And for CPUs, we'll talk about how to scale up the number of CPUs you use to see what the proper amount there.
I highly recommend looking at the guide posted also to the notes on what sort of measuring sticks you can use to measure the program size.
Also, there was a question of is time requested or time used, the one that is calculated using
the priority.
And it's kind of both, because when the job is in the queue, your estimate of how much
time it will use is used to calculate how big the job is.
If you say that I want the whole cluster for one month, the job is huge and you won't
get it ever, because it's such a big job, like it's impossible to get that much resources
at one time.
And if you like, so then the like the perceived time usage is like, or the requested time
usage is used to calculate the priority.
But once the job has finished, the time usage that it actually took is the one that is used
to calculate your like past priority.
But in any case, it's best to just try to match the request as close to the actual early
users as possible and to do some simple measurements to get to the right ballpark.
So if you know that the job finishes on your laptop in 15 minutes or maybe an hour, you
don't need to request a full day's time in the cluster,
because it's way overboard, because it
takes an hour on your laptop.
So might as well put an hour in the cluster as well.
But maybe we should go to a break.
Yeah.
So I guess we come back at 16 minutes past the hour
in whatever time zone you're in, unless you're
in a weird country, which is fine.
Yeah, you can keep answering or asking questions.
We'll keep answering and when we come back,
it's parallel stuff.
So see you later.
Bye.
you
Hello.
So looking through the notes, I don't see any new questions
we haven't answered.
So I guess let's continue with our task.
But maybe first, we're going to do parallel now.
So what does that mean, parallel?
and how are we approaching this?
Yeah, so this is, I would say, it's way too complex
a thing to have everything said in this small session,
but it basically means using more than one processor.
And there are multiple ways we can do this and
the most important one, I would say, that we are going to be focusing on this
session is this kind of embarrassingly parallel
where we just run the same thing with different inputs multiple times. Basically, we would
start the same program multiple times, and that is the easiest way. But there's other
paradigms as well. There's multiprocessing, there's a message-passing interface parallelism,
MPI parallelism. But it basically means that we use more than one processor. So you know that
Your laptop probably has eight to maybe four to eight CPUs already.
Yeah. You know, while I was making the kitchen videos, I had to very carefully research what
is parallelism. And I think the answer I got is that there's more than one point of execution at
the same time. So we have multiple processors. One processor is executing our analysis on
one book and another processor is on a different book. And this is what I guess we'd call data
parallelism. And in particular, we will use first array jobs, which is embarrassingly parallel.
So basically, instead of running one program that does multiple things,
we run 10 copies of the same program. And then these 10 different copies will all process 10
different books within the 100 books we have. And they'll all write out separate files,
which we can then combine later and hopefully see the same output.
Yes. So these kind of problems arise all the time. So if you have different data sets you
want to process, if you have different parameters you want to process, you want to do different
different options, different random number seeds or whatever, there's multiple different
ways that you encounter the situation where you do the same thing, but with a small difference.
And in these cases, the embarrassingly parallelization is your friend. And even though it's called
embarrassingly parallel, it just means that it's easy to parallelize. And in this case,
[name] said, the book analysis is very easy to parallelize. So, maybe we should look into it.
Yeah. So, I'm switching to your screen. There we are. So, we're back where we were.
So, we already have a working batch script, the run ngrams. So, I guess we can make a copy of
this with the `cp` command and call it `run-ngrams-array.sh`. Oops first argument first so first
what are we copying and then the other one yeah my mistake yeah no okay and now we can open the
new file the array running file so we need to tell this program that it should run as an array so we
add a new slurm option here. So the sbatch comment, and now we give `--array=0-9`.
And that means the same file will run 10 times, and each time there'll be one different variable
inside. And that variable would be set to 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9. And how do we use that
variable. So, the program `count.py` has built in support for this. So, there's this extra argument
we can add in `--step=10`. So, step means it will run every 10th book. And `--start` will
be tell it what book to start on. And here we use the magic word $SLURM_ARRAY_TASK_ID [so `--start=$SLURM_ARRAY_TASK_ID`]. And this is
something you would just look up from the array examples. There's no way you would know this
by yourself automatically. So yeah, so now 10 times,
they run on 10 different books. So the first one runs book 0, 10, 20. The next one, book 1, 11,
21 and so on. Do we need to have them save the output to different file names?
Yes, so I added here to the output also the task ID because otherwise they would
like they would all try to write it. Can you make it newer? Yeah, yeah, let's scroll.
Yes, okay, so unfortunately this wraps this code [lines are scrolling off the screen] but yeah on the output (`-o`) one I added
this $SLURM_ARRAY_TASK_ID there as well. Because otherwise all of them would write to
the same file. So when we are submitting this job with the array structure, we are telling the queue
that, hey, I want actually 10 of these. I want 10 of these and just give me a different number
for each one of them. And based on what number we're getting, we do something. And there's
various things you can do to map this number to parameters or whatever. There's multiple examples
in the documentation, but this is like a simple example where we can straight up use the number
over here. So, should we try that? Yeah, okay. So, now we submit it with sbatch again.
And I'll try to be, again, fast to get the queue status.
Yeah, so queue.
OK, so we see here now there's 10 different things running.
0, 1, 2, 3, 9.
We see there's the underscore ("_") and number,
which is the different array tasks.
They're all running.
On the last column, we see under node list,
many of them are running on a node named pe32,
but there's a few that are running on other ones.
Basically, we've managed to run on different nodes here.
It's important to note here that all of
these jobs are completely independent of each other,
so they don't understand.
If you have a program that needs to
somehow communicate among the different things,
this is not an average job.
you need other algorithms to run that sort of program.
Of course, you can then run that with an ArrayJob if you want to run multiple of those kinds of
programs. But here, all of the programs that are running, all of the scripts that are running,
are completely independent of each other. So they do independent stuff independently and then they
give the output at the end. Should we look at the outputs?
Yeah.
So now we see there's output ngrams to array 0, 1, 2.
Do you want to look at one of these and see?
Yes.
Let's take, for example, these.
Yeah, I mean, it looks like the normal thing,
but about 1/10th as much data there.
And if we look at any of the outputs here,
we can notice that, well, it looks similar as well.
But again, the number of n-grams
is 1/10th of the overall amount.
Yeah.
OK.
So there's also a script included in the HPC examples
will combine all the output, because presumably we don't want 10 separate output files, but we want
one. So it's, I think, called `combine-counts.py`? Yeah. So it takes a series of input arguments,
which is the inputs. So we can use this glob syntax. So the asterisk ("*") means fill anything that
matches this pattern. And we can use the `-o`-argument to write it out to another place.
So this is often called like a map-reduce kind of a thing, where you do something over multiple
things. You do this mapping and then you reduce the information together. So this is quite common
in like data heavy stuff. You want to do stuff independently and then combine the outputs
together. Yeah, so now we see the new output file. Do you think it's the same as the original one?
So it should be sorted by amount. Should we look at the first 10 lines and see if they're the same?
Yeah, let's do that. So let's look at the original one first.
Yeah, what does the program `head` do?
So it prints out the first lines of a file.
By default, it prints 10 lines.
I don't remember, but we can give it a number, what we want.
But you can look at the start of the file, like if you want to check what the data looks
like or something.
Yeah, so if you look at the first 10 lines there, and combined.
So the moment of truth, is it exactly the same?
And those counts look pretty much the same to me.
Yeah, so it worked.
Yeah, so we didn't have to do any modifications to the code itself, like it was the same exact
code that we run. Of course, the combination, there had to be some sort of way of combining
the results after the fact. But there wasn't any major modifications to the code itself.
We could run it separately. Of course, you need to have some way of mapping the
$SLURM_ARRAY_TASK_ID to the task what you want the code to do. But once you have figured that out,
it's usually plain smooth sailing to get an easy way of getting lots of parallelism in the cluster.
And this is very good for jobs that you need to do something a lot of times.
Yeah. And this is your own brain power that you'll need to spend to figure out how to
distribute things and split it up like this. And this is what it means to be a scientific
computing person. But okay, there's other options. So there's also a mode of this which tries to use
multiple processors within the same program, something called multiprocessing, which is a
Python module. And would you like to give that a quick try? Yeah, let's try it out. So if we
So, if we first try running the previous single core version, let's try out that and let's
just verify what we have.
So, I copied from the history, so here I'm running the code.
only change here is that this time we are checking for words, like instead of letters,
we're checking for words for the n-grams. So it takes a bit more for the job to run.
And we see it used more memory, 500 megabytes now, about the same amount of time.
Okay, so we've done it with one processor with a code that isn't written to use multiprocessing.
But if we are starting to use multiprocessing, the first thing you must check is that does your code support it?
Is your code written so that it understands multiprocessing?
In this case, this program isn't, but [name] has written a version that does support multiprocessing,
right?
And this is called `count-multi.py`.
Yeah.
So now it basically works the same, except we will tell it it should use more processors.
So first we have to request the extra processor from Slurm.
Yeah.
So within the srun areas of the arguments, will request CPUs per task equals how many?
Four. Let's put a bit more memory because there's going to be overhead because all of
the processors are going to be needing memory. But we have now a requested. So in the slurm,
So if you look at this block of text before the Python command, so where we have the S run and
we tell the Slurm requests, we have now used CPUs per task equals four to request more CPUs.
You don't have to worry about the task. It's a different thing for MPI stuff. But CPUs per task
basically asks for four CPUs. But the code yet doesn't... Software updates. Nice. The code yet
doesn't know how to use those processes unless we tell it that, okay, you should use four
processors. So different programs have different ways, and it depends on the program. But usually,
if you have multi-process, like code that can utilize multiple processors, there's a way of
telling it how many processors it should use. And in this case, I think it's threads.
It's not right, [name].
Yeah, OK.
So I think now this has everything it needs.
So we're saving to the same output file.
That's fine.
Should we try running it and see what happens?
Yeah, let's put threads or let's put to a different file.
Let's see if the head is like the output.
OK.
So it's running.
It says it's using four processes.
And so while we're waiting here, do you
think this will be faster or slower?
Well, it's probably going to be a bit faster,
but not that much because the program probably cannot.
Yeah, there's multiple things that can happen there.
But this kind of example test case
probably won't parallelize that well
because there's lots of overhead and that sort of stuff.
So this is really interesting.
So it ran.
So let's look at these numbers carefully.
So first, there's the wall time.
So wall time means the clock on the wall, so the real time
that's passed.
So we've requested four times as many resources.
And it's run, what, 20%, 25% faster, something like that.
So basically, most of our extra resources
appear to have been wasted.
Ideally, it would run in 1/4th of the time.
But really, it ran in 3/4ths of the time,
or 4/5th of the time, something like that.
So this code really didn't work well with multiprocessing.
Let's look at user time.
So user time, and this is the amount of time
that the processors actually spent doing work.
It went up from 21 seconds to 29 seconds.
So this is OK.
You'd expect it to run a little bit slower.
It has to spend more time communicating
between the different parts.
But yeah, combining this with the wall time
not really going down.
it shows that our parallelization really hasn't worked. And that goes to a question which is in
the notes. Should we do the changes? Should someone do the changes to make their code
support multiprocessing? So it really depends what the code is. Is it going to be efficient?
[name]'s running `seff` here. Yeah, let's run quickly like `seff` and the job IDs of the jobs. So it'd be
take the job ideas from the output over here and look at them, you can see that the first one had
a CPU efficiency of 90% and the second one had a CPU efficiency of 40%. And like [name] said,
it depends on the case that you're running. If you're running a physics code or something,
the parallelism might be needed. Otherwise, you might not get the results in a reasonable time.
if you're running a data-hungry process that tries to run, for example, in here we are trying to go
through multiple files, there might be a lot of overhead with the file reading and writing
and that sort of stuff that doesn't really help. And in actuality, running the array job would be
faster. So sometimes running serial but more of them is faster than running something parallel
because there's these overheads that are needed to make certain that the communications work and that sort of stuff.
So, multiprocessing really depends on the case, and if it's low-level codes, it's usually better.
If it's this kind of run through something like data, it doesn't necessarily help.
but it's usually best to test. It's usually best to test and see how it works. But usually,
if you have an existing code trying to get the results done, there's a question of,
do you want the results done or do you want them to be done faster? If you want them to be done
faster, you might benefit from multi-processing because the wall time goes down, the time it
takes to run them. But if you want the results done, let's say you need to run a thousand
simulations or something, it doesn't necessarily make sense to parallelize them because there's
thousands of them and the overhead starts to accumulate. Instead, it might be just better to
run a thousand individual simulations and not parallelize them at all. Because that way,
you reduce the overhead time and you just get them done. So, aggregate jobs are quite often
the fastest way of getting bulk stuff done. But if you want something like you are waiting there
in the queue, waiting for it, waiting for the results to come by, then the multiprocessing
might make it faster to do that specific simulation. But it's like a question of
do you really want to go through the hassle. If your code already supports it, it might be good
to check if the code has support for multiprocessing and then test it out whether the
multiprocessing version is faster. As an example, when I was making these codes, I maybe spent
15 or 30 minutes getting a first version of the single core code working. It was pretty fast.
And then I spent many hours working on the multiprocessing version. I could make something
that initially worked quickly, but then understanding why it was slow and trying to
make it slightly better took a long time. So this might also be what you'll experience for
your own stuff. But should we talk about some of the speed considerations and why it's so slow?
There's a good question about why is the multi-processing slower? Or is there something
else to talk about first? Yeah, I would say that in this case there's a few considerations.
First off, it needs to load the data for all of those different multiple processes. So it needs
to open the file four times. Each one of them needs to load the file in order to get the data
in. So there's data slowing down. And I can say from my experience in making this,
the program is a little bit faster when it reads the data directly from the zip file
compared to uncompressing the zip file and running it on all the files separately,
open them independently. It really depends on the format the data is stored in and all that.
I could have repackaged it into a format that optimized for reading, and it would be even faster.
But this is a real thing that you can experience with this example if you want to give it a try.
And also, if you think about the word counts, it's calculating the word counts. It has to,
like each process that is analyzing a different file, it needs to store those words into memory,
into the counts, like how many counts has this word appeared or this ngram has appeared.
So each one of them has to house its own copy of this kind of word dictionary. And that, of course,
means that there's four times the memory usage. We see also the memory usage grow because of the
extra CPUs. So there's these overheads that happen when the individual processes have to
do the same stuff that the one process would do as well. And then that makes it slower.
And these kinds of considerations happen. In some problems, there might be a situation where
like you get benefit, but you only get benefit once you get over the overhead, like basically
like let's say we would have a thousand books or 10,000 books, then like the overhead is
smaller because now we can reuse the same processes most likely and do the calculation
like the word counts. But it depends on many factors. And yeah, like there's no one simple
reason why it might be faster or slower. There is the point, this moving data between processes
in multi-processing, that's a big thing here. So Python multi-processing isn't actually shared
memory. There's actual different processes. So it has to use inter-process communication to
share the data. And in practice, the way the program stores the data is relatively inefficient,
so it apparently takes a long time to do this sharing of the computed enneagrams between things.
But again, the question, when you're encountering these sort of
situations, it's usually a good idea to measure your program, profile your program,
and ask us, maybe, is it worth the effort of trying to parallelize something before you start
just putting more hardware to the problem? Because sometimes the correct solution might
be to look at the problem from a different point of view, instead of looking at it from the point
of view of, okay, what do I actually want to accomplish, instead of, okay, I just want to use
a fancy word for doing that. Yeah. So there's one final thing I'd like to say, and that is the input
and output, like someone mentioned there. So I noticed when saving this, you notice it's a plain
text output format, which is good for most purposes, but it has to create every line individually.
And every line has a JSON serialization, where it puts the words and letters into the
brackets and stuff like that. And I found that in practice, that's slow. It can spend a lot of the
time just writing this output. And when you're trying to use the data, spend a lot of time
reading the data in, especially when the number of books starts getting larger. So basically,
the processor itself for doing this kind of analysis is so fast that the format the data
is stored in becomes the bottleneck here. And since it has to write it all once and it writes it,
it's not writing it in parallel, it's writing it in serial. So that becomes a bottleneck
and slows things down.
So all of these considerations, so the data thing especially,
when you're doing things like machine learning training,
GPUs and so on are so fast that oftentimes the speed
of getting data to the GPU is the bottleneck here.
If you don't use the good data loaders that
operate in other threads, if your data is not
stored in a preprocessed format, you
end up taking more time with that.
And that's a really nice thing about this example,
because we can actually see the slowdowns because
of the data, IO, and so on.
Yeah, it's usually a good idea to remember
that when it comes to computers, let's
say accessing memory register is a few seconds.
Let's say the scale is something like it's actually
like nanoseconds, but let's say it would be a few seconds, then accessing the RAM memory
would be a few hours or something.
And then accessing a hard drive or a network drive or whatever, that would be years.
So it's like the scales are, because we're talking about milliseconds at that point,
so the scales are wacky when it comes to computing, so it's usually a good idea to measure stuff
when you're doing stuff, and think about, okay, is it worth to create more complex code
just to get basically nothing out of the exercise?
But of course, sometimes you have to do it.
You have to test it out to see if it happens.
But it's good to remember that normal, everyday life experiences don't necessarily translate
one-to-one to computing environments.
might encounter that like it's suddenly, yeah, suddenly something behaves differently.
But also I would say that existing codes, like nowadays, most of, a lot of existing
codes, scientific codes especially, are written to support multiprocessing straight out of
the box.
So multiprocessing is not bad if it's written correctly.
In many cases, like if you're using R or NumPy or any machine learning framework or whatever,
they support multiprocessing by default. So it's a good idea to check the documentation
of your specific case. Does it support multiple processors? And if it does,
then utilize them if they make your problem go faster.
Yeah. Do you want to show how we can use OnDemand to look at the outputs of the things to wrap up?
Yes. So I have here the folder so I can see it over here. But if I want to look at it in a more
graphical way, I could also go to the start place on the on-demand and start,
let's say, Triton Desktop. So, let's start one. So, this is basically like a virtual desktop that
is running on one of the compute nodes in the cluster. So, it's a pretty bare-bones experience,
but it's very good if you want to, let's say, view a plot or something and you don't want to
to transfer stuff to and fro from Triton.
So it's now running.
And I can launch this over here.
So you notice that I now have a place here.
And this is running on the Triton file system on Triton.
So can we go and access Scratch, for example?
Yeah.
However, we navigate to it with the browser.
Yeah, I'm typing Control-L to get this.
/scratch/work/[my username]/teaching/ ... to kickstart.
Let's go here.
Yeah, OK.
And I could even use the editor here to edit it.
But there's alternative editors that you can use as well.
But let's say you want to view one of these outputs.
So I can just open it up with an editor and see it up there.
So if you want to view a plot or something you can,
or you want to do some simple edits,
this is also a nice way of doing some interactive uses.
Yeah.
OK.
Maybe I'll switch back to the notes here.
And we can see what unanswered questions there are.
The other instructors can join us for the outro.
But yeah, this was a general, yes, OK.
So in the notes, now there's a feedback for the morning part.
So you can answer the poll here, tell us what you think.
So too fast, too slow, whatever, a good thing about today,
something to improve, any other feedback and so on.
In the meantime, what's our plan?
So we have a lunch break coming up
and then we'll go to Zoom.
And in Zoom, we will be able to answer more questions
and basically do all of these different examples
and exercises together.
So you have the time that you can work on it yourself.
Ask more questions.
We can look at your individual problems, and so on.
There'll be different breakout rooms there
focused on different topics.
Yeah.
Do you want to give the outro, and then we
can look at the notes questions and keep answering questions
until it's the end?
OK.
Are you placed to switch to my screen?
Yeah, exactly.
So can you stop sharing?
Because yes, I'm still sharing.
Yeah.
No.
Should I restart my sharing?
There.
Now it works.
Okay.
Yes.
We're getting the sharing set up properly.
Now we've had this nice demo, and I think, well, if I was learning here.
the things I would have understood hopefully and well now I know from own experience I've
learned it now I've heard this all this and I think I understand it but in a week or so
I will realize I forgot half of it and I actually didn't really understand the details of this
suspect. So where do I go? What can I do? I can answer to this question with our beautiful help
page. So in our web pages that hopefully are already familiar to you, we have a section all
dedicated to help. We even have a video actually there a few years ago in a similar workshop like
this one we had a guest [name] from Code Refinery Norway he gave a nice short video on how
to ask for help because often sometimes the problem you have it might not be exactly you know
the actual problem that you might be having and so if you know that you might have a problem or even
if you don't know what type of problem there are multiple ways of getting help from us maybe the
The one out of the many ways, the one that I can mention is the so-called Garage, which
is a daily Zoom session that we are hosting at 1 p.m.
And the barrier is extremely low.
You might not even know what is your question or what is your problem.
And it's not even limited to Triton or to parallel processing or things like that.
We get people that they might just need basic IT help, or we even get people with questions
related to privacy, ethics, security, you know, even though we are not maybe the best
persons at Aalto to answer this question, but we most likely know someone who is the
best person.
So the barrier is extremely low, just come there every day at 1pm.
And then of course, when things get a little bit more complicated, they start to become
more like a consultation.
And so for that, we have the issue tracker, where you can basically paste a bit of your
code and you know something that cannot be solved quickly in within the one hour of the garage
session and of course that's the documentation that we have here in in general also we try to
also host some focus days in the in the garage so now I opened the garage space and so sometimes
we get guests from some departments as key so the IT services from from those departments
And sometimes, for example, we have this special day.
So recently we've been running the COMSOL
Multiphysics Focus Day every Wednesday.
So if you know that you're gonna use COMSOL
and you're not sure if your setup is optimal with Triton,
then that is the place to come for with.
So yeah, basically this is how to get help.
Maybe we still have a few minutes.
I could talk about kind of where to go from here.
In this page, which is the same page
where there's the upcoming courses
that we are hosting slash co-hosting.
If you scroll to the bottom,
there's also this nice picture
that [name] draw a few years ago,
which is kind of the skills map
when it comes to computing in general,
scientific computing.
So most of you here, for example,
have the type of basic skills that I even briefly cover
in the morning, understanding the hardware and the software
that you might be using.
And then, of course, sometimes you
need something a little bit more specific to your field,
whether it's simulations or whatever
is the kind of more science-related skills.
And then we start going that, before going
to the cluster and HPC, and the more advanced uses or tools
that we can use along with our coding
and scientific computing.
It's important to, you know, learn the Linux shell
and sometimes not just type in a few commands,
but as you already saw today,
sometimes you need to write a script.
So those scripts that you saw today,
they were so-called LRM scripts,
but in practice they are shell scripts.
And then on top of that, this is where we are here today
in learning our cluster and HPC are working.
When it comes to scientific coding,
there are more courses that we offer and in this i'm gonna mention that exactly one month from
today we have the next round of the code refinery workshop you can already register at this link
the code refinery workshop is a half six half days that are basically covering the basics of
of where is the schedule?
I don't see it here.
No, this is actually the lessons, but oh yeah,
it was here above, sorry.
Yes, Code Refinery March 25.
So the first three days, the first week of Code Refinery
covers everything about Git version control.
And we also cover kind of how to use GitHub
and the features that GitHub provides
so that you can create issues, pull requests and so on.
So it's very useful for this type of collaborative coding.
And then the second half focuses on reproducibility,
specifically the so-called computational reproducibility
and kind of there's a little bit more kind of,
how could I say, best practices
when it comes to scientific computing.
So automated testing and this type of continuous integration
and modular code development and so on.
So, basically, the last thing that I want to mention before we go for lunch break is
also that we have been running many of these courses in the past, and almost everything
is available in our YouTube channel, so you can kind of retake a past course.
But if you feel that it would be nice that we do a rerun of a past course, or maybe if
if you feel that something is missing in your curriculum
and you would really need something new
that we've never been running,
we have this form where people,
where you can basically request reruns of older courses
or a run of new courses.
And so here you see a long list of GitHub, Python, Julia.
This is the one where we are right now,
introduction to HPC and so on.
So, I think this is all cover for today.
Maybe I mentioned now for the exercises,
the exercises will happen in Zoom.
And the reason is that we will not be recording
what happens in the exercises room.
So you are free to use your microphone,
show your screen if you're having an error
that you want us to look at.
We will split in multiple rooms,
depending on what you wanna test
or what do you wanna learn.
In room number one,
we will basically go through all the exercises
on the Triton tutorials one by one
from connection to the login node
up to running this array jobs and other parallel things.
So this is highly recommended
if you recently got a Triton account
but basically never really use Triton.
Room 2 is more for helps if you have issues with connecting to Triton or other issues that could
be related to account, Triton account. And room 3 will be a little bit more advanced where for
those users who already are maybe familiar with connecting to Triton and running some
sbatch SLURM jobs but maybe you your needs are you know you might be needing CPUs, GPUs, or more
advanced parallelization and then we have one room dedicated to how to use large language models
and on Triton we actually store already some popular open source language models and we have
even a little bit of examples on how to run those local models so this is you know kind of a hands-on
way for testing that and finally room number five is the speech-to-text which is a tool that's been
used a lot by Aalto. Aalto doctoral researchers where, for example, the need of this tool
is that you might be collecting an interview, so in the form of speech, and this is a tool
that transcribes the interview into text. And for security and for confidentiality,
this all runs on Triton, so you don't need to, you know, upload your sensitive interview
outside of the Aalto network. And so for those who are interested in that, you can try speech
the text with the demo in room number five. It's 12 o'clock. I think we are done. Is there anything
to bring up from the notes? I would say that please give us feedback at the end of the notes.
At the end of the notes, there's this quick polling and you can give us also feedback
at the end. So please give us feedback on how did you find the course.
Because this is the first time we have done this kind of like a one-day quick kickstart
and it's good to get feedback on how it went in your mind.
So please leave us good and negative feedback, both welcome, because that will make the course
better.
Yeah.
All right.
So have a good rest of the day.
So hopefully some of you will join us for the exercises in Zoom and yeah, great.
Thanks a lot.
See you later.
Bye.
you