the nine o'clock and so i think we can start
Hello everyone and welcome to
yet another Code Refinery
workshop, September-October 2025.
We have a format that
is slightly different when it
comes to the schedule compared
to previous workshops, so if this
is not the first Code Refinery workshop
that you follow, you will
find some interesting changes,
more exercises basically.
what I'm showing right now
on the twitch.tv stream is
the main workshop web page which
is our kind of communication channel
so that here you can
follow the schedule you get all
the links to the materials and
you will also get access to
the questions and answer document
that we will soon introduce
so right now we are at
day one i'm scrolling down to day one
and i'm gonna talk about this welcome
and introduction to the workshop
so when i click the link
that is there it will actually
go to the presentation material
that we will use
so we will not use
any powerpoints here they're all materials
and they're all hosted in github
so that if you find a
typo you will learn how to
submit an amendment all right but
we are glad that you are
here briefly about code refinery
so code refinery is an ordi
project focused on teaching
scientific computing tools
But Code Refinery is especially
a large community of
research software engineers, researchers
who need to work with computers
and code and data and
in general enthusiasts about
research software and anything that
is related to that.
But Code Refinery is also
this workshop where we are.
here right now and lots of lessons
and open learning materials that
some of them are covered in this workshop
but we also have other
learning materials that go beyond
for more advanced topic
there's many founders and
organizations that are involved
in code refinery
The main funder is
the Nordic E-Infrastructure Collaboration
and the partners are
Aalto University, where I'm from,
CSC, IT Centre for Science, also in Finland.
Then we have from Denmark the Centre
for Humanities Computing and
the Danish E-Infrastructure Cooperation.
Sweden is there with the EuroCC, ENCCS
and also the National
Academic Infrastructure for Supercomputing.
And then we have Norway
with the University of Oslo, where
one of our first instructors is from.
And then RIS Sigma 2
and University of Iceland, where
our second instructor of the day is also from.
So I'm already going to say hi.
You might see their faces here to [name].
Hi, hello.
Good morning.
Yeah, hi.
I will introduce you properly, don't worry.
So with all your expertise and titles.
But briefly to motivate a little bit,
there's this nice image by
[name] that kind of tries
to give you the
what are the six useful steps
or helpful steps for
making reproducible research.
I'm not now going to
start talking about
reproducibility, reproducibility crisis
because I don't want to spoil the fun.
That is for next week and
you will hear all about
reproducibility issues in science.
But in general, all the bits
that you will learn throughout
the workshop are related to what you see here.
So getting your project folders
and files in order, making sure
that you can travel in
time, specifically that you can
travel back in time.
Travel in the future, it's still not there.
and in general so make your research
that is transparent in a
way that other people can look
at your code maybe look at your data
if possible and look at
your documentation so that you
are able to open your software
or open your data and follow the best practices
Sometimes we don't really like
the term best practices.
It's much more inclusive to
say good enough practices,
because sometimes the good enough
practices is truly what really matters.
So how does this workshop works?
Well, the format, as you
are seeing, it happens on Twitch TV.
And the reason is, well,
you know, most likely you've been
to some Zoom teaching with
hundreds of people there.
It's not very...
It can be stressful to
keep people microphone off and so on.
Here it's more like a TV show.
We are here in a small studio
and we are broadcasting to
anyone in the planet who wants
to hear about reproducible research.
And by doing this also, it's
easier to take care of the recordings,
that the recordings will
be immediately available on Twitch TV.
And later, after we basically
cut them and subtitle them, they
will be also on YouTube.
The attendance is kind of
choose your own adventure.
There are the first part,
which is happened this week.
It's all about version control
and Git with GitHub.
but then after that we
have different episodes happening
multiple weeks and come join the topics
that you find more useful
could it be reproducible research
could it be software licenses
could it be whatever you need
or follow them all we
don't really track attendance and
you can watch them live or
you can watch them later
materials are always available
they are linked in the workshop schedule
as I showed earlier and when
it comes to the actual schedule
we try to have at least a
10 minutes break every hour and
for this first part in the
first week we will have a one
hour break in the middle
so in when it comes to time zones
because we try to fit
multiple time zones this will
be a convenient break for maybe
people in UK and Iceland and
for the Oslo and Finland it would
be more like a afternoon coffee break
then i briefly mentioned
about this collaborative notes document
that i was showing earlier and
the idea of the collaborative
notes document is that it's
somewhat like a google docs
so that everyone can edit at the same time
and this is much more
convenient than using a chat
for example the zoom chat that
i was mentioning earlier
because here the questions
are basically forming a nice
documented set of questions and answers.
What is really interesting
that sometimes it's not just
the experts or the helpers that
are going to answer.
Sometimes you might know the answer.
You might have experienced the same bug,
the same issue with some
operating system and you can
share your experience.
So it's truly a
collaborative document where we can
all edit at the same time.
To edit the document, if you
open the page that you received
in your email, there is a
pencil in the top right corner.
So if you click on the
pencil, the view mode will change
from view to edit.
So I will briefly show it.
Now I have another window
here with the notes document.
I scroll up I see this
pencil I click the pencil and
now I'm in this edit mode and
I can see here there's
already 93 people watching this
page maybe editing this page and
many of you everything here
where you're from is it sunny
is it not sunny it's a
nice data set of locations and weather
and this is how we
run sometimes polls where basically
you can add in this case an
O to say you know if you wished to get them
and here you can already
start asking questions and you see
we use with this indentation
we have nice colors and different questions
Maybe the only thing that
it's important that you always write
on top of the last line so
that it's easier to know when is
the end of the document.
And if you feel that
the document is getting very
slow, then it's good to, you
know, we have a good server
that hosts this document.
But sometimes if I would say
if the number goes above
150 simultaneous edits, it starts
to get difficult.
So then it's good to click
on this eye icon.
in the very top part of
the screen and so that it goes
back to this view mode.
All right, back to the introduction.
Try to please don't put
personal data or passwords into
this share not documents.
At the end of the day,
we will archive it so that
after the whole workshop, we have
a nice set of question.
very briefly about the practical setup
so you might have noticed
that this screen share streaming
that we are doing right now
is not the usual landscape whole
screen type of setup but we
have this vertical stream and the
idea of the vertical stream share
is that it really helps those
who have a single monitor
for example laptop users
because then you can keep
the twitch tv open in let's
say like you show here on the
left hand side of the screen
and then you have all the
right hand side free where you can put
for example the web browser
with the with the lessons with the materials
or your terminal if you
are learning it with the terminal
or vs code or any other
window that you might need
so this is very useful if
you have a single screen of course those
who have multiple screens they
can arrange the windows as they prefer
All right, I'm soon done
with all these intros.
I promise you I will.
This is the only day where
we do this long intro, but
I'm just very happy that there's
so many people involved in this workshop.
Again, we have now here it says 370,
which was the number from a few days ago,
but this morning it was
426 people registered from really
all over the world.
and behind the scenes
there's 15 coordinators and
helpers, instructors, facilitators.
It's a big work but we
hope that there is value in
all this energy that we put into this.
briefly on the workshop etiquette
as usual we try to be
nice to each other and you
have to understand that we
are very different some people
might be experienced coders who
have coded all their life
some people might have just started
or maybe not even will
never code they're just here to
learn the tools that their
coding colleagues are using so
let's just respect everybody else's
space and differences let's try
to be helpful in the collaborative document
And if something is not right,
if you feel that something is wrong,
we have a code of conduct
and you can get in touch
with the workshop organizer, Samantha
and I, or with the
general support at coderefinery.org address.
final notes well most of
you are registered if you register
you will get more emails from me reminders
and links and anything helpful
but of course you can also
just watch the the twitch tv stream
and and don't worry about it for those
who need certificates there's
a clear instructions there if
they're not clear please ask
in the notes document
And finally, Code Refinery is
an open project.
Anyone can join us.
If you follow the link
here, there are multiple ways to join us,
whether you like to receive emails
once in a while, not too
many, don't worry, or maybe
you want to actively join us.
For example, we host a Zulip channel
where many, many, many researchers
and software engineers and HPC admins,
they're all there and
answering each other's questions, sharing.
interesting links and sometimes
also funny memes.
But I think I've talked enough.
So maybe I'm going to ask [name].
Hello, [name].
[name] is here with us today
and he will be with us for
many days as the broadcasting
expert or broadcaster.
Is that broadcaster?
Broadcaster is good.
Expert is saying so much.
Well, as I was explaining earlier,
if you look at the distribution
of all the broadcasters in the
world, you are falling in
a quite high percentile.
But I'm asking you if you
can switch to the notes document
so that we can have a
look if there's already any.
This is the wrong one.
So sorry.
Okay.
Yes, this is.
Yes.
Okay.
so that we can have a look at
if there's anything relevant
in the questions and in the
meantime our first speaker or
our instructor can set up their screen share.
[name], there is one question.
Someone says that they are
not going through the
installation session because we see
that some people are very new.
That's a good question.
In our installation pages, there
is this minimum required installation,
which is just the fact if
you have a GitHub account, that's enough.
You can do the exercises
only using the GitHub web pages and
so you know you don't need
to worry i would say that
the more heavier part of the installation
which is the setting up
of a conda environment it's more needed
for from next week so for the part two
but for today and for the
next days having a github account
is all you need if you want
to of course not just use
the github website to work with
git because you want to do
vs code or the terminal
then you know if you didn't
have time to do it today you
can do it later in the afternoon and
if you need help we can set
up some ad hoc installations
sessions all right so I guess