Hello everyone and welcome to
day two of the Code
Refinery workshop, September-October 2025.
I'm [name] here, your
workshop organizer for this time
along with [name].
And with me today we
have [name] from CSC
Finland and [name] also
from Aalto University Finland.
And [name] also from
our team is the broadcaster for today.
so a bit of reminder if
you were not with us yesterday
it's totally fine you can
still understand everything and
do everything that will be done today
and if you want to re-watch
what was done yesterday on twitch
tv on the same link that
you watch in this stream you
can also watch yesterday's videos
later for example if you want to catch up
but in general today you
are good to understand what's been doing
and also be able to do
the exercises along with the
instructors in the workshop web page
that I'm showing right now
you find the materials for today and
so now I'm scrolling down to
day two and today we will
continue with this git version
control and I'm gonna briefly give
you a mini intro
so yesterday we learned about
all this terminology around
git version control so you
heard all these terms like forking
and pull requests and commits
and it's okay if not
everything is fully clear because
these terms will be repeated
today and also tomorrow
But the goal, what was important is
that you understood the motivation,
why it is so important to
work with virtual control as a
time machine to go back in
time in a previous version of
your code or whatever project
that you are version controlling.
today for day two we'll move
to local work so if yesterday
we were using this github.com
web browser web server meaning
that the files were stored
somewhere in the cloud in
actually microsoft cloud because
github is microsoft today
now it's good that we have github.com
as a remote repository but
it's also good to work locally so
and this is what will happen today
so the files instead of
being just in github.com will
come to your computer you will
be able to edit them do changes and
when you're happy you can push
them back to the cloud
github.com servers or you know i
don't want to spoil the fun
you will see today what we will do
In the links that you have
received in your email there is
also this notes document and
just a reminder although I
was just chatting about it when
you visit this notes document
it looks like this and you
can use this to basically
interactively ask questions to
our instructors and our helpers
by clicking in the very top
there is a pencil which will
switch the notes from this view
mode to this editor mode
and it's basically a simple text editor
so that many hundreds of people
can edit at the same time.
I think it's like a Google Doc
but a bit more reliable
because Google Doc has
limitations of simultaneous editing
and also simplified.
I can already see some questions there
and our helpers are already answering
so keep the questions coming
and I don't want to steal
any other precious time to our
I believe now it's a good
moment to switch to [name]'s screen.
I guess you're going to be
the first one, right, [name]?
Yes, I'm going to share.
Excellent.
I'm sharing [name]'s screen.
All right.
Right.
So the floor is yours.
I will move out from the
scene and have a great workshop, everyone.