Hello everyone, we are starting
day three of the Code
Refinery workshop, September, October 2025.
I'm [name], I'm at Aalto University
and right now you might
already be seeing our instructors
of the day, [name] De Cristoforo.
Hello [name].
Hello.
and [name].
Did I pronounce it well?
Yes, you did.
Yes.
Hello, [name].
Hello.
But [name] and [name], they are
both in the UIT, University
of the Arctic of Norway.
So up there in Tromsø.
They're part of the
Research Software Engineering Group
and they work with HPC and this type of stuff.
So lots of HPC experts
as instructors this year.
And you might also see [name].
Hello, [name].
Hello.
who is controlling the streaming
and the broadcasting for today right
so a couple of reminders
before we actually dive into the
best day well i mean i don't
want to say it's not maybe i don't know
if it's the best day but
one of the most amazing days
of the code refinery workshop
today it's day three and i'm
scrolling down to the schedule for
today and i click on this day three intro
and here we are so for day one
and two it was like
an introduction to version control
in day one you got all
the terms and you managed even
just using the github web
interface to do commits and things like
that for day two we kind
of moved on the local computer
which is very important because
then you already start feeling kind of the
the power of such tool that
you can work locally and when you're happy,
you can push on a remote place, GitHub,
GitLab, your server, whatever,
and collaborate with other people
who can then pull locally the
changes that you did and so on.
Today, which is day three,
everything comes together and we
show exactly this power of
the collaborative distributed version control.
so the concepts that are
introduced today they build on top of
what has been shown already in day one
and day two and so here
it's not necessary that you
do things locally you can also
use the GitHub web interface to
do this type of collaboration with others
But I really like I was saying
that this is the best day because
what you learn today is
something that even can go
beyond software engineering or code.
Because with this tool, with
what you will learn today, you can go out
and fix typos in documentation
of your favorite packages, software packages.
You can make web pages, help other people,
web pages and truly, you
know, unleash the power of
open source development.
What else?
Some practicalities.
I scroll up, I switch window
to this notes document, which
you should all have received via
email in the reminder that I
sent a minutes ago.
if you were not with us
in the previous days so in
this notes document on the
very top right corner which now
is hidden by our webcams but
it's okay you should see a pencil
I can turn it off for a moment
yeah so you see my mouse
is moving there on top of the pencil
when I click the pencil it
will switch to like an editor edit mode
and here I'm scrolling down
and there's already some questions
and some of our helpers
have already answered and this
will be the main interface so
that everyone can ask and answer
at the same time you can
answer some of these questions
give your comments and feedback and and so on
but I don't want to steal precious time
so I switch back I click on
the eye it is also good
because then in this rendered
mode it's lighter for the server
so we can get the webcams back
and I think we could switch to
I think [name] is starting with
the screen share and enjoy
day three of Collaborative Git
Code Refinery workshop thank you
Yeah, thank you, Nico.
And welcome from our side.
I always consider this day to
be the most fun, since we
kind of build upon what we've
learned in the last two days.
And we now work together with
others on the same code base.
Expect today to be
slightly chaotic, because multiple
people will now work together
on pull requests, on code reviews.
We'll merge into one GitHub repository.
So not everything will work
according to plan, but that's fine.
That's part of the fun.
[name] already mentioned almost
everything in terms of bookkeeping
that was to be said.
Maybe just a few things on
my side that I want to add.
First of all, we will
have today three exercises and
you will have roughly 30
minutes for every exercise.
So it's a bit more time
than you did have in the last two days.
Um, so please keep an eye
on the Mata documents that
has mentioned, because we need to see that.
What do you, at what stage
you are doing the exercises.
So please let us know
whether you're done or not,
whether you have any questions, this
will be a central part now for
us to the way how we communicate to each other.
Also, please do remember the
code of conduct.
So please don't put anything
weird into the pull requests or
the reviews and so on.
Um, but otherwise, um, I think
we are ready to go.
As [name] already mentioned, so I
and [name], we both work at UIT
and we're a research soft
engineering group and we've both
worked as researchers before.
So in my case, it
was fusion plasma physics.
In the case of [name],
you have a background in
bioinformatics and computer science,
if I remember correctly.
Yes.
So what I'm trying to say
is we've been researchers, so we
have been in your shoes.
We know what kind of struggles
and challenges you have in
your everyday life when you work
with code as a researcher.
And hopefully we can
We can help you with most
of these topics now today during the seminar.
Okay.
I think that's all there is
to be said before we start with the lecture.
So I think we are ready to go ahead.
So the first thing we will
mention today is just a quick
reminder of the concepts that
we've discussed in the last few days.
So that's what is a repository?
What is a commit?
What is a branch?
And so on.
You will have time during
the exercises to read up
on these concepts again, if
you feel slightly unsure about some of them.
You have 30 minutes, so
there's plenty of time to read
up on old topics and then build up on them.
But there is two specific things
that I want to pinpoint,
which we should emphasize now,
and that's cloning and forking the repository.
So I think that we
should start with discussing that
in a little bit more detail.
And a very easy way to
do that is by pointing out
this figure, which is shown here.
So what you can see here
now is a repository, which is
here indicated to be on GitHub.
So this cloud here refers
to a server, cloud server somewhere.
In this case, it's on GitHub.
And this repository here
contains multiple branches that you
can see here indicated in
these different colors.
So we have the blue main branch.
We have a green experimental branch.
We have this red ideas branch.
Every branch has multiple commits.
So each square here refers to a commit.
And we also have a tag here in this case.
So then the version 1.0 came out.
And then we can either clone
or fork this repository.
And you will do both
things today during the exercises.
So what you're already familiar
with is cloning.
So that means that you
copy the whole repository as one
piece to your laptop or
your workstation, wherever you work locally.
So you can see this then a copy,
which then changes here the
names of the branches, but
otherwise it stays exactly the same.
And then there's a second option,
which we will work in
the third exercise today, and that's forking.
And forking means that we
copy the repository inside of GitHub.
So we copy it from the
original place to another one,
usually your own GitHub account.
So then if this is,
for instance, the recipe book from
the code you found in the
repository, you would copy it
over to your personal GitHub repository.
And it stays exactly the same.
So conceptually, it's very much the same,
but we will see that in
exercise two and three what
the major differences are.
Now, maybe one of the first questions
that arise then is when
would you actually want to fork
and when would you want to clone?
So [name], may I ask you,
what do you usually do in
your everyday life when you
work with code repositories?
In which case do you prefer
to clone and when do you fork?
Well, the main thing that decides
what you do is generally
whether you have right access
to the repository.
If you do, then you can
just clone and push your changes back.
In many cases, if you want to work on
or modify software that is managed
and maintained by someone else
at a different university or
wherever, it is easier to just make a fork
and then you can work on
it and modify it without
having to always request that
your changes be accepted.
Um, and so that's, that's
one main reason to fork as
instead of just cloning.
And often that's the case
when you work with repositories,
which are much bigger and
where multiple people are working in it.
So if it's just inside
of your own organization, if you only have two,
three people working on
one repository, then probably
cloning is enough.
But if you then want to contribute to,
let's say a large project, like NumPy,
for instance, for those of you
who work in Python, they
might recognize that immediately.
That's one of the most popular libraries.
then you cannot just clone that.
You would have to fork it
first and then work on the code.
So it's also correlated with
the size of the repository.
And one other reason that
people will fork is if they
want to take the particular code base
or software in a
completely different direction and
make changes that they have
either couldn't get accepted or
have no intention of trying to
merge back in with the original project.
Yes, that's also an option.
And also always keep in mind
what kind of license the
repositories use, right?
So if the license gives you
the rights to make changes to it and use it,
or if it's a restrictive
license, that's also something you
should keep in mind.
We will also learn today
how to synchronize the
changes between different repositories,
or like between fork repositories
and cloud repositories.
In the past, it has
been quite cumbersome on GitHub,
but they made it really easy now
in the UI, so it's just a few mouse clicks.
We will go through that later on as well.
And
We should also mention
generating repositories from templates.
That's relevant for those of you
who are now exercise class leaders,
so those of you who
will clone their repository for
your local group.
In this case, we can
use templates for that.
And the difference between a template
and a normal repository is
simply that a template will
flatten the history.
So it's like a Git squash,
if you remember from the previous days.
basically all the history
from this repository that you
cloned has been flattened so that
we start with an initial commit
and start from a kind of new state.
So we don't have all the
history from the creation of the template.
So for those of you who will work on
or will lead an exercise
class, this will be important.
Okay, I think we have motivated
what we are working on today enough.
And I think we can
then start with introducing the first exercise.
Was there anything I have forgotten?
And I think that's everything.
Okay, so let's go to the next chapter.
And that's now collaborating
within the same repository.
So imagine you work together
with your research group on a package
that you develop, which is
at the moment only relevant
for two different people in
your research group, then you
probably would want to
start with collaborating inside
of one repository.
And that's what we will
practice now in this first round.
In this exercise, you will
be asked to create a pull request.
So what is a pull request?
Maybe we should give like
an explanation of the concept.
So if you haven't heard that before,
if the idea is to make
some changes to the code base, it
could be a new implementation.
It could be something completely new.
It could also be just a
change to existing code or a
fix of a mistake of a bug in the code and you
make this change as a proposal,
you put it out as a
proposal, so that other people can look at it,
give their opinion, say
whether they're happy with the
changes or not, and then get it merged.
So instead of merging it
directly into the main branch,
you have like this additional
sets of controls that the changes
have to go through before you merge them.
In this exercise, we will now start with
the repository that is outlined here.
I'll just quickly give
some information about how the
team leaders would have to work with this.
And then I go to those of you
who are not in the team,
but will work directly with
the repository together with us.
So if you are part of a
team or an exercise room, please
go to this repository and book it.
And then you would have
to send invitations to all these people who are
parts of this group.
So I'll just quickly open
that in an additional tab.
So go to the tab now.
So you can hear, use this template.
And if you do that, then
you, I will just now show
the exercise that we will work on.
You can go to the settings
here, go to collaborators and
teams, and then you can invite people.
So in this case, let me
just make it a little bit
larger so that everyone can see.
You have different roles, and
in this case it's important.
Okay, unfortunately I have to
scroll down to the right.
Let me see.
This is slightly difficult to see.
Let's just go back to the general one.
You will have to set it to read.
In this case, let's see, so
the, ah, here it is, sorry.
So we go to the team section.
Sorry, here it is.
OK.
I'm just not used to have
such large in the GitHub repository.
Here you have different roles,
so it will be important that
you set this to write, because
by default it might be read, which means
that those of you that
you invite to participate in this,
to work on this repository, will
not have the option to create,
yeah, to merge as pull requests.
So in this case, please set it to write.
Also, one thing that we can do,
which we should, which I want to mention,
is if you go to branches,
we can set additional rules for these branches.
And in this case, I've set up here a rule
for the main branch that
you have worked with already in
the last couple of days in
the code refinery workshop, we
can here add this additional
rule, which says that we require
a pull request before merging.
And I would recommend doing that
for repositories where multiple
people work on it, since that means
that no one can just change
the code in the main branch
without anyone else approving the changes.
So this is something that
you should enable, otherwise people
might just by accident
merge into the main byte, which
is not what we want to achieve today.
Okay, so let's go back to the material.
That was all the information
which is important for those of
you who manage a group of participants.
But those of you who
will work with decentralized
repositories, you will work together
with us, so with [name] and
also [name] and [name].
In this case, you have
two different options for this exercise.
You have the first one that
we will not share,
in the stream, and then there
is one which we will show.
So this is the one that we
will show on the stream.
If you don't wish that
your username will be shown during the stream,
you will work on the
centralized workflow exercise repository.
And if you don't mind,
then please choose the recorded one.
It will be fun to see
a few people trying out this one as well,
so that we can see a
lot of different recipes that will be added.
Okay.
If you haven't already sent us
a request to be added to
the repository, please do so now.
You find all the instructions here.
We will then send you an invitation
and then which you need to
accept and then you can
participate in this repository.
And also one additional thing, by default,
you might have the setting
here to all activity, which is not
what you want since that would mean
that whenever someone creates
a pull request or an issue
in this repository, you will
be spammed by emails
So set it to participants and mentions.
That's a good idea.
Or you can also set it to ignore
so that you don't get
any notifications by email
whenever something happens in the repository.
OK.
So much about the whole UI stuff in GitHub.
But let's go to the lesson itself.
So we will work now
with this recipe cookbook.
So it's basically a collection
of different recipes in this repository.
Let me open that repository once again.
So if you go now to the
code, I'm now in this repository
that those of you will work
with who choose to work individually with us.
We are in the centralized
workflow exercise repository.
And you can see here, we
have here multiple directories,
which all contain different recipes.
So if I let's go to salads, for instance,
and I will just now open
a random document, let's say the
fruit salad in this case.
And you can see, we have here this file,
which contains an ingredient section
and also instructions, which are
in this case, relatively detailed.
Now, we don't ask you to spend
that much time on creating
a very sophisticated recipe.
It can be something super simple.
The idea is just that
you contribute or make a pull
request to a new recipe.
Now, some of the steps
you're already familiar with.
So you will have to
first clone a repository, then create a branch,
then commit the changes to
a new branch, and then submit a pull request.
So that's what you've done so far already.
But then the new concepts here
will be how to push to this remote repository.
creates an issue, cross-reference
the issue in the pull request,
and then break the pull request.
The instructions are here, and
then you also find the solutions down here.
And checking the solutions is not cheating,
so please just have a look
at the solutions and follow them
in order to contribute.
Is there anything else we
should mention, or should we just
go into the exercises?
[name], did I forget anything?
Not that I'm aware.
That should be good.
Okay, so in this case, we
will then start the exercises.
It's now 20 past, so we
give you roughly half an hour.
So it's 10 to 12 in
Central European time, whatever that
is in your time area.
We will then get back to
you on the screen and then
start the break for 10 minutes.
So please use that break and
then we will go for this exercise ourselves.
So [name] will then contribute
a new recipe to the repository
and then we will go for the exercise together.
Okay, then I'll leave you
to the exercises and see you in half an hour.
Bye.
Hey, welcome back from the exercises.
You can see that there is
already a lot of nice
contributions to the recipe book.
So thank you all for contributing.
So you can see here in
this repository, the central aspect
for exercises recorded repository,
there's a bunch of issues, a
lot of them have already been closed as well.
There's a lot of pull
requests, many of them have
also been already matched.
So thank you all for contributing.
That looks really good.
Before we go into the break
in 30 seconds, let me just
quickly show you the graph.
So we can go here on insights
and the repository, and you can
go to the network.
And that gives us a very
good overview of the different
branches and who's working on what.
So we can see here the main branch,
and then we see here
already some merged branches.
This is the other one, for
instance, and we have some
branches here, which are open.
So we can see there's
a lot of contributions already made.
Okay.
So let's go into the break.
for 10 minutes and afterwards,
[name] will create his own pull
request and we will discuss
the whole exercise in detail.
See you then, bye.
Okay, welcome back, everyone.
I see that a lot of
you have already submitted very nice recipes.
Thank you all for that.
And I have seen that there
was a couple of questions
about these automated tests.
So if you know, look here
at the repository again.
So I'm here to centralize
that exercise is recorded one.
You can see that some of
these recipes have like this
green checkmark and some of them
have this red X, which
we haven't discussed yet.
So let's, let's have a look.
Let's let's click on it
and see what's happening.
So we have here this
really nice biryani recipe that has been added.
And if you scroll down, aha, okay.
It tells us that there
have been some checks.
We'll discuss them in a minute.
And if you look at them,
it gives us an error message.
Okay.
Looks like the instructions are missing.
Okay, so what is this test here?
That's something that we'll discuss
in more detail later on.
And also there will be
a whole section about this in
a later stage of this workshop, so not today.
But just to give you a hint already,
so on GitHub, we can
create additional tests, which are
here in this .github workflow directory.
So let's click on that.
And here we have a file,
which is called check-recipes.yaml.
So let's open that.
And this now contains the tests
that we run every time you
create a pull request and if
you push towards the repository.
So at the beginning, it gives
us a name of this check.
In this case, it's just basic recipe check.
We can specify which branches
we want to run these checks on,
on main in this case.
And then down here, we can
then specify on what kind of
server this is running.
So this is something that GitHub provides.
So in this case, we just
use a standard Linux server.
And then at the very end,
this is the relevant part.
We run a file, which is
called Python check recipes.
And if you go back to
the repository, you can see that
there is this file.
Now, if you don't know
Python syntax, that's perfectly fine.
You don't have to understand
what's going on here.
So let me just tell you
the only thing that this file does
is it checks whether there
is an ingredients and an
instruction section in the recipe.
That's all it does.
And then if there is one,
it gives a green check.
And then if there isn't one,
then it gives this red cross.
Now, this is of course
a somehow silly example, like
you would use this later on, for instance,
if you have tests written for your code
and you want to make sure
that every time there's a
new contribution to your code,
that this doesn't break any
of the existing functionalities of
your code base.
But in this particular case,
we can now have a look
why this exactly happened.
So let's go to the changes.
We can click on file changed.
And we see, okay, the problem
is that this user outsmarted us.
Like the check is really stupid
and just checks whether there's
a hashtag, hashtag ingredients
and instruction section.
What we haven't thought of is
that you might use Unicode characters here,
which look really nice,
but unfortunately our tests have
not been prepared for.
So one could change that
by suggesting to, there's a refresh button.
Let's click that.
Someone has made changes to it right now.
Okay, these things have not been changed,
but what we could do now
is to suggest to make the
changes here, to remove this
Unicode character here, and then
the tests would pass.
So this was just a
quick kind of introduction to tests.
We'll discuss it in further
detail later on,
Okay.
I think it's time that we
now discuss the whole exercise
in further detail.
So [name], can I give you
the mic and you would focus for the exercise?
Sure.
Okay.
And I guess we can switch
to my screen share.
Oh, sorry.
Let's unpause that, resume.
Okay, there we go.
All right, so we're working
our way through the exercise tasks.
We begin with opening an issue.
And so let's find a
particular issue that we have
that needs modifying.
So here I'm looking at
the guacamole recipe.
And I happen to think that
it needs some garlic to give
it a little more kick.
So let's go ahead and do that.
So we'll create an issue here.
And let me just resize this
so we can see that.
Here's our new issue.
And we'll call it guacamole
needs more garlic or it needs garlic.
Okay, guacamole tastes better if
it has garlic.
So we should include it as an ingredient.
Okay, so there's our issue
that we can reference and we'll
go ahead and click on create there.
All right, now heading back
over to the code.
So here we're not working
locally, so we're going to skip step two.
If you are working locally,
then you need to clone using the URL here.
And that's covered elsewhere, so
I'm not going to go over that right now.
But we need to create our
new branch that's going to contain our changes.
So here we can just type
in, and I'm all for descriptive naming.
So guacamole, add garlic.
Okay, and so we can say
create that branch from Maine.
And so there we go.
So now we're working in
this branch rather than main.
You can see that it doesn't say main here.
It says guacamole, add garlic.
And so now we're going to
go ahead and make this modification.
If you're working locally, this
would be where you would
edit the file directly, but we're
going to do that in GitHub.
So here's the guacamole recipe
here, and we can go and edit it.
And there's the edit this file.
And so we can go down
here and add two cloves of garlic.
And then additionally in
the instructions, mince garlic.
Okay, so there we go.
And we can then go back up
here and go to commit changes.
And so then when our
commit message add garlic, and we
can add an extended description,
but I think it's pretty simple.
Here, we can add garlic
as an ingredient and include.
instruction item.
OK.
So we can then commit that.
There is also an option.
We could have skipped the
branch creation previously and just
done that right here and given it a new one.
And that's fine if you're just doing one
one change, but in this case,
you often may want to
have multiple files change and
so it's easier to use a
dedicated branch that you've already created.
Okay, so then we'll commit changes.
Okay, and so then we can see that
that is now added there and
we have the instruction there.
Okay, and then going back
We can see that it says
now that this branch is one commit ahead.
And because of that, we
have the option here to
contribute our changes back to the main branch.
And so let's see, looking
at the instructions here, we've
created a change on the new branch.
Oh, we forgot to commit
the cross-reference to the issue.
So let's go back and do that real quick.
First of all, the issue is number 23.
We can see that here.
Then let's come back over and
go to this commit.
Okay.
Well, I think we'll just
reference that in the pull request.
So here we have the option
then to create the pull request.
As you can see, we can
create it from the commit itself,
or we also have the option to,
if we're in that particular branch,
to use the contribute option here.
So let's do that open pull request.
Let's make sure.
Yeah, open pull request towards
the main branch, step six.
open pull request.
Okay, so here we have the description.
This solves the issue number 23,
and it automatically knows where
that is for us.
And then we can do this.
Okay, so we now can then
create the pull request.
Okay, so now it is telling
us that we have a review required.
And it is also, as we
can see right here, that it
is performing the basic recipe checks.
And since the ingredients heading
and the instructions headings were
both there properly, then
that particular pass check passes.
[name], do you want to switch
to your share and do the review?
We can.
First, what you could do is
to assign me as a reviewer.
That's something we could share.
Sure, yeah.
OK.
Yes, now this we have this
window is very narrow, so
that assignment is shows up in the bottom.
If we were to actually have
a normal sized window that's going
to show up on the right hand
side here so we can see here reviewers.
And so then it makes a
suggestion here and we can request that.
We also click here and search
for or choose a user that way.
So we'll go ahead and click on
[name] there.
And so he is now listed
as a reviewer and will
hopefully approve our changes.
So over to you, [name].
Okay, thank you.
So we'll now wait until
I'm sharing the screen again.
Okay, here we go.
Nice, so I'm now still
in the same repository.
And I see in the issues, I see
that [name] has created this issue
where he says that the
guacamole recipe needs more garlic,
which is quite nice.
I can already see that there
is a pull request here linked to it.
So that's because [name] has
now linked the pull request
to this issue number.
So that's what shows up already here.
So I could now click on that directly.
But of course, I could also
find the same thing if I
click on pull request here, it
will also show up.
So I will now open this file.
Okay, so let's have a look.
So what are the first things
you should do when you look
at a pull request as a reviewer?
So first of all, of course,
let's look at the title.
Does this seem to make sense?
Yeah, that sounds reasonable.
That's something we can work on.
It's not some kind of
spam or something which has
no relevance for the project.
Now, if you scroll down, what
do we see here?
We see the initial message
that [name] has written.
I can click here to see the commits.
So in this case, it's one simple commit.
So this would then show
me the commit message, which
you remember from the previous days.
Now, since we have a check,
it also shows me whether
the checks have passed.
In this case, they have.
So everything seems to be fine.
And now the most important tab
is this one called Files Changed.
because that actually shows me
the changes in the code.
So I will click on that now.
Okay.
So in this tab, it shows
me which documents or which
files have been changed in this pull request.
In this case, it's only one.
It's in the site directory
and it's the guacamole.md, so
this markdown document.
If this pull request would
contain multiple files that
have contained changes, then they
would be listed down here.
So we could scroll down
and then multiple files would be listed here.
In this case, there was
only two lines which are added.
So if this pull request
would delete some lines or
rename them, they would also appear as red.
So you've probably already seen it.
If you have reviewed some
other pull requests, otherwise you
will see probably later.
So if like [name] would have said, okay,
I don't want any onions in my recipe,
then this would have been
shown as missing now in this pull request.
Okay.
So what should we do now as a reviewer?
First of all, we have a
look whether the changes in the
code make any sense.
So in this case, we see
that the only changes that happened
is that two cloves of garlic have been added.
And in the instructions, we
see that the garlic needs to be minced.
So that's very simple.
There's not many things going on here.
So in this case, I can
then click on review.
And since it's just very small changes,
I will just approve them
right away and write a nice message.
something like that.
And I can submit a review
and say that I approve this request.
Now, I think it's always
very important to be very polite
since in this case, it didn't
take [name] a lot of time to make this change,
but let's assume this is now
a very large code base and
[name] has spent weeks on working
on a specific feature that
he contributed to this project.
And if you then kind of
submit like after weeks of
work, it's pull request.
And then the only feedback you
get from a reviewer is like,
here's a spelling mistake.
And here is like something
which is not really relevant.
Then this can be quite discouraging.
So I think it's always very important
that the first time an
external person collaborates with
a new project that it gets
welcomed and gets a good impression.
Because otherwise, if you would
be now very nitpicky and
mean, then [name] would probably
think twice whether he would
want to contribute to that project again.
Okay.
And in this case, I
think everything seems fine.
So we can go ahead and
merge the pull request.
And guess what this merge is?
It's another commit, right?
So we can here create a commit message.
In this case, it already
has this proposal here, which
is simply merge pull request
number 24 from this branch
into the main branch.
So in this case, now we
click on that merge.
And now what I can do
is to delete the branch.
And that is safe to do,
because now the changes from
this particular branch are already
in the main branch, so all
the checks have been stored.
So I can now delete this one.
It's often good practice to
delete unused branches, stale
branches, so that you keep a good overview.
If you would now go to the code
and have a look here at
the history of our repository, then
we see here that
The latest commit now refers
to the launch pull request.
One thing we haven't mentioned
yet are draft pull requests.
I really quickly want to
mention them since that was one
point of the exercise.
Sure.
Certainly, there are times
when it's important that you
keep your collaborators informed
of your progress, that they can review it
and catch if you're heading
off in the wrong direction as
far as the approach that you're taking.
Or if you need feedback on
what you've done so far, it
can be useful to have draft pull requests
that are works in progress so
that you can get that
feedback and people can look and
see what you have so far.
And that can be very useful.
And the other issue is that, of course,
it's important not to commit
half working code into your tree, obviously.
Yeah, it's always important
to communicate with the maintainers
and the other people in the project
because the last thing you want
to do is to write 5,000 lines of codes
and then realize that no
one else is interested or no
one else actually wants that feature
or has a different plan.
So if the reviewer says, okay,
I want this repository to go
in a different direction, I'm
not interested in your
particular implementation, then it's
much better to ask in advance
instead of like working on
it without telling anyone else.
Also by communicating that way
you make sure that no one
else is duplicating your work.
So you save time as a, as a whole group.
Yeah.
- it's that's sorry
I just that's also why we
started out this with the creation
of an issue, so that if even before you begin.
- Writing your 5000
lines of code, you can get feedback
and not really opening an issue
to say this is a problem and then going off
and working to solve it, but
opening it up and including
a statement that you're
planning on approaching.
The solution
in a particular way, so you
can get feedback as soon as possible.
Exactly yeah.
[name], what do you think?
How large should pull requests
be on average?
They can be any size.
They should be cohesive, one unit.
You don't want to make a
set of changes that make
changes in three different places
in the file and commit
those all three separately if
they don't actually function collectively
as a unit.
For larger code base, yeah.
Ideally, your commits should
always leave the branch or in working state.
It's not always possible, but
it certainly is an ideal
that you should strive for.
Yeah, so you should have,
the better thing is to have
many small pull requests if that's possible.
Of course, sometimes it's just impossible.
If you have a very large change
that needs to be done to the code base,
but in principle, it's always
better to have many small
ones, since it's less work for
the reviewer to go through 50
or 100 lines of code and
understand what's going on than
going through a major rewrite of
the whole code base.
Also,
As you said, we should always
keep the pull requests cohesive in
a sense of like it's one particular feature
and then it doesn't matter
whether it's spread over three
or four different files or
whether it's just one.
That's much better to have
like one coherent feature in
one pull request than having
like three completely unrelated things
in one pull request.
So it's better to keep it that way
so that you have a, that
you also make it easier for
the review of what's going on.
Like if there are two
completely separate things from each
other in a pull request,
then it's not good practice.
There were a few other things
that I wanted to mention
about good practice for pull requests.
And one thing we've already
seen are these automated tests.
So what you should focus on
as a reviewer is doing things
that humans are good at and
not things that can be easily automated.
So if you, for instance,
have a particular way how you
want the code style to look like,
then you can use something called linters,
which is a tool that
checks whether the code formatting
is the way you want it to.
This will be mentioned in
further detail at a later
stage, but I'm mentioning this
in order to pinpoint like you
as a code reviewer should really
focus on the things that only
you as a human could do
that no automation tool can do for you.
You should also probably merge
as soon as possible since
you want the other collaborators,
so everyone in your team have
access to the latest changes.
So you don't want to keep
that away from everyone for a few months
and then only merge it once
it's a hundred percent perfect.
Like things are never fully perfect.
It's better to merge as soon as possible
so that like everyone can
benefit from the changes that you make.
And also it doesn't really matter
whether the review is done by someone
who is more experienced or not,
because code review is not
just there to make sure that
the changes that you do don't
screw up anything in the code.
They're also there to communicate.
So if [name] now, for instance,
as a very senior
engineer has a brilliant idea
what to implement, then he
can create a pull request, and
me, let's say I'm a junior member of the team,
I'm not as experienced yet,
I still would learn a lot
from doing the code review, since
that's a very easy or very
good way of transferring
information and transferring knowledge.
Also, the perspective of someone
who is not as experienced can
also be very important, since
one quality of code, it's not
just what it works well,
I mean, of course it should
do what it's supposed to do.
It should be hopefully performant
and so on, but readability is
also a major criteria for good code.
So if I, as someone who let's
say is new to this
programming language that [name] is using,
and completely unable to
understand what's happening, then
maybe that's on one hand the side
that I'm not particularly experienced
and I should learn more, but
it could also be a sign that
maybe the code is written in such a way
that it's very overcomplicated
and it could be written in
an easier way, which is
then better for everyone who
works with the code and also for new users.
So the perspective of like
a diverse team of different
people with different levels of
experience can be very valuable.
So there's no reason to assume
that code reviews can only
be done by senior people
who are very experienced.
Is there anything else, [name],
that we should mention before we
go back to the material?
I think that's most of it.
Okay.
So in that case, let's go
now to the next section.
So I'm here, the material of the lesson.
So I just scroll to the bottom.
We have discussed protected
branches already.
And then we have here a quick summary.
Let's just quickly have a look
whether there are any questions
in the markdown document that
we could answer now, which
are still connected to this topic.
Let's see.
I'm just going here to the
end of this document.
I see that there are already
a lot of answers there.
Any recommendations of using Copilot?
Okay, that's a good question.
[name], do you want to
share your thoughts on this?
I will pass to you.
Okay.
So personally, that's not
my personal opinion.
So take that with a pinch of salt.
I think it can be very
useful to use Copilot if you're familiar with,
if you can decipher what
the code that Copilot spits out does.
So if you're already experienced
in your programming language,
and you can understand everything
that Copilot does, then I
think it's a great tool that
can make you much more productive.
However, you should always remember
that you still have the
responsibility for the code.
Copilot doesn't take this
responsibility away.
So if you are unsure
whether what Copilot does makes
sense, then that's maybe a
sign that you shouldn't fully rely on it.
And you should always
check yourself whether
What are the changes that
couplet suggests make sense?
I mean, that's the case for
any AI tool, really.
So I would encourage you to
use it, but always don't become too complacent.
Always try to always understand
what couplet does, whether that
makes any sense for your quick base.
Yeah.
I was just going to say
that it's very important to
understand the code, not rely on
does it give me an error when I run it.
If it doesn't give me
an error, that doesn't mean
the code is correct.
So you have to be very careful about,
particularly with more extensive
amounts of code being provided.
it's very critical because particularly
if you're working with anything
that has the potential for
resulting in erroneous results
or potential for security
implications, those are all things
where it's particularly important
to be very careful in
reviewing AI generated code.
Okay.
Yes, so someone has posted a question
probably a very good resource
that you can read up on.
Let's see, there's another question.
In the exercise, we created a branch.
Does modifying a file work the
same way of pull requests?
Yeah, so if you remember from the lecture,
pull requests, they're always
from one branch to another branch.
So if you would contribute
directly, let's say if you
push something directly from your
main branch locally to the main branch,
on GitHub, or if you
just change something directly on
GitHub, it is not a pull request.
Pull requests always work from
one branch to another branch.
So let's see, does that
answer the question, does modifying
a file work the same way for pull requests?
Yeah, so if you then change
the file in one pull request, then, sorry,
in one branch that is connected
by a pull request, then it
will update the pull request automatically.
So that's maybe something
we haven't explicitly mentioned,
but how would we deal
with a situation where we are,
I'm happy with some changes, right?
So I'll open the repository again.
And I will now use
again this adding Periani recipe.
We can see here that's a
pull request from Bergen to Maine.
And we saw that particular
pull request had the issue that
the tests failed because there
was this Unicode character which
our automated tested capsule
were unprepared for.
So what we did here was
to change the file in this branch.
I suggested here, let us show the change.
What I suggested here is
to remove this character so
that we have ingredients here
written only like that without
a Unicode character.
And this was then committed.
So if you see here, I
made a commit, which is, you can
have a look at this commit.
So I changed here this line.
I removed just this character.
And this now updates the branch.
And by updating the branch,
which is connected by a
pull request, it automatically updates
the pull request as well.
And then the tests will run again.
And in this case, they passed.
So in theory, now we see
that all checks have passed.
And we see that someone
had, okay, we actually didn't
do a formal review.
So let's do it quickly.
Let's go up.
And it already has this pop
up here asking me to do a review.
So I'm going to click on it.
Okay.
I'll have one last look.
That looks all good.
Ah.
Okay.
So I can give some additional
comments if I want to, I can say.
I don't know.
Let me make sure I don't
make any spelling mistakes.
Let's just start to review.
Okay.
Let's see if there's anything
else that needs special attention.
It looks all good.
Even tips.
That's very helpful.
quickly add review comment, okay?
Okay, so let's go up and
we can finish your review.
We can click on it and
I can approve it now.
So I'm gonna now submit the review.
And we can merge it.
Okay, let's see, are there
any other questions in the document?
I hope that this question
is answered, number 20.
So let's go back to the material.
I'll just bring it up again.
We now go to the next
page, and we now start with the next exercise.
So this will be the last
thing we do before we go into the lunch break.
We will now basically focus
on the code review process.
So a lot of it is repetition.
Just to focus this time is
now on the creating the
pull request and suggesting changes to it.
So we've already shown most
of these steps here during the stream,
but I will ask you
now to create additional, let's
see how many pull requests we have.
If we don't have enough, we
might need to make a few more pull requests.
Let me just take this down.
No, sorry, how do I?
Okay, let's go to the number
of issues and pull requests
Okay.
So for this exercise, we'll
ask you to create a pull request again,
and now then go through
the review process here, which is mentioned.
So I just screwed up my
screen share a little bit.
Let's open the other window.
Okay.
Okay, so all the, what you
need to do is describe here exercise number two.
As I said, focus on the review button,
on the review function, use
this plus minus button to suggest changes, and
Otherwise, I think it's mainly
the same thing.
So now you can practice doing code reviews.
And I think we give you roughly 25 minutes.
So we would then finish
at Central European time, that would be 12.58.
I will then just quickly say
a few words before we then
go into the lunch break.
So with that said, good
luck with the exercise and see
you in 25 minutes.
Bye.
Okay, welcome back from
exercise number two.
We are almost at the lunch break,
but let me just use the
remaining time to quickly discuss
one question which appeared here
in the collaborative document.
And that is here, one
participant has a hard time to
find a plus and minus symbol.
So let me quickly show where
you can find that by creating
a pull request or doing a readme.
So I'm now again at the
same repository as before.
And now let me just pick
one of the pull requests here.
I go again to files changed to see
what the code actually looks
like that has been changed.
And now, in this case, I
can click on this blue plus sign.
And let's see.
That's interesting.
It doesn't show it to me right now.
That's strange.
Let me try a different one.
That should not be the case.
It's changed.
I click on the sign.
Ah, and here it is.
Actually, I don't know why
it didn't show previously.
Does anyone else know who's in the call?
I guess that's a no.
But what we need is this
Add a Suggestion tab.
So I click on it.
And now it displays this one line.
And then here's suggestions.
So if I make changes here, let's say
Okay, what is that actually?
That's 500,000 avocados might
be slightly too many.
So let's reduce it to 50,000.
I believe that's enough.
Then I can do up a single comment.
Now, if I go to
conversation, I scroll down.
And now it just suggests a change,
but also it does it twice
for some reason, I guess I misclicked.
But if I now click to
commit suggestion, I can make
this commit automatically.
So now I create an
additional commit without the person
having to actually do it themselves.
So that way we can suggest
changes to the code automatically
as a reviewer, and we can also merge it
if the person who creates
the pull request enables that, which
is done by default.
So this makes it much
faster to suggest changes to
the code than doing it back and forth.
If you're telling the person
who created the progress what to
do, then that person has to do it.
You can just create it right
away with this plus minus sign.
I am a bit surprised that
I didn't see it the first time I clicked on it.
So I'm not entirely sure
whether that's because I'm zoomed
in so far again.
[name], have you encountered this before?
I don't remember ever not seeing this.
Okay.
So this is strange, but
thank you for noticing.
We just, I'll try another one
just to see whether this
is a reoccurring theme.
So we see here different pull requests.
I click on fast changed
500 gram of chicken.
Okay, let's say we want to
make a change here.
And I say we want to have
700 grams, add a single comment.
And now it appears here.
So I can commit it directly here
if I want to create a
commit by add these changes to the,
request.
Or I can also do it in conversation.
It appears in both places.
And yeah, I can then commit if I want.
But I'll leave that now for
the person who created the pull request.
I hope that answers the question.
There are some other questions.
Yes, so pull requests, this
feature is also available on GitLab.
So for those of you who
are not familiar with GitLab,
GitLab is basically an alternative
platform to GitHub.
It is not owned by Microsoft,
but you can host your
own GitLab instance if you want.
So it's a kind of a free version.
But some of the functionalities
that GitHub provides are
not automatically enabled in GitLab.
But you can think of it
just as a different option instead of GitHub.
The strange or funny thing is
that GitLab calls pull
requests, merge requests, but
they're exactly the same thing.
They just have a different name.
So all the concepts that
you've learned today in the last two days,
they are also applicable if
you use a slightly different
stack in the future.
So like there's maybe the
names change, but in principle,
it's the same idea.
Okay.
I see we have two minutes over time.
So, um,
Let's go into the lunch break.
So here in central Europe,
that would be from right now
until 2 o'clock, so 14.00.
If you are in other parts of Europe
or somewhere else in the
world, then you can, I
guess, easily calculate when we are back.
So we are back in 57 minutes.
And we will then go for
the last part of the material today,
where we then go for
the third exercise that we'll focus on.
creating pull requests from
forked repositories.
So have a nice lunch break
and see you then in 57 minutes.
Bye.
Okay, welcome back, everyone.
I hope you have a nice lunch break.
We are now in the last
section of today's workshop.
So we will now discuss how
to work with repositories where
you don't have access to them
or write access to them.
But we will now show how
you can work with them.
You can even contribute to them,
even if you're not part
of the original organization that
created the repository.
It can be a complete outsider
and still pay for requests.
And we'll show you how to do that now.
And before we go to the last bit, however,
let me just quickly kind of show at
what stage we have now
the repository from the previous exercise.
So you can see there have been
a lot of new issues and
pull requests, which is really nice.
We can have a look here at the history.
I can see all the last commits
and you can see there's a
bunch of new pull requests
that have been merged.
Thank you all for doing that.
And one thing which is
quite interesting, we can go
here to the settings or here
on these three dots and then click on insights.
And then if you click on
network, it shows us all
the different branches that people
have been working on and
that have been merged.
So here, you can scroll
back to the beginning.
So here, September 9th, and
I originally created this repository
based on the templates that was shown earlier.
We can now see all
the different branches that I've
created, and we can see that
many of them have been merged.
So here, for instance,
merged pull request from this user.
And you can see here, some
of them have not been merged, just a little bit.
And this gives us a really good overview.
So if you have a very
complex structure of a repository,
then you can always use these
network graphs in order to
get a better overview of how
many branches are at the
moment, how many people are working
on it and so on.
And we already see here a new owner.
So that's kind of a hint
to the exercise we do now.
And that's now to fork
repositories and faithful requests
from four repositories to
the upstream repository.
So let us go back to the lecture material.
So we are now back here and
we are now in the last section.
So this is the, how
to contribute changes to
repositories that belong to other users.
Let's open that.
Okay.
So we will now introduce
the third exercise, and then
[name] will basically show the
most important steps before we then
let you do the exercise again.
So as I already hinted, we
are now in a situation where
we want to contribute changes
to a repository that belongs to someone else.
It doesn't have to be someone we know.
It could be also like
a large repository from
a different organization.
So let's use NumPy again as an example.
So let's say you have found
a bug in NumPy, and you also
happen to know how to fix it.
So again, NumPy is this
very famous Python library that
probably many of you use.
Then you wouldn't be in
the NumPy core team, most likely.
I would be very surprised
if all team members would take this course.
So probably what you would have
to do in order to make
contributions is to fork the
repository and then create a
pull request from there.
So before we start with
the exercise, I'll just quickly
start on the bookkeeping again.
we will now use a different repository.
So we will start with the same template.
And if you are now a group leader
who is working with a
small group of participants of
this course locally, you can
generate a new template.
And the difference to the
previous case is that you now
do not have to add any collaborators.
because now people will fork
it and will contribute that way.
So there's less to do for
the people who work in these groups.
And if you want to work
together with us, then it's
a similar story again.
We have two new repositories,
so we don't use the same ones as we did before.
And again, there are
two repositories, because one will
be the recorded one, and the
other one is the one which is not recorded.
And during the stream, we
will now again focus on the recorded one.
So if you don't want
that username appears on the screen,
which then later on might
be then published to YouTube and
so on, please use the first one.
If you don't mind, please
use the second one, because if
you can show during the live stream
that many people use this
repository, then I think it's a benefit.
OK.
So if you look at the
exercise itself, a lot of it
will be very familiar.
So you will be very familiar
with a lot of the steps here.
are just a few small changes
and the first one is that we
will now fork the repository and
then create a pull request
from the fork repository to
the upstream repository and during
that we will then also
learn how to synchronize their
repositories and also again mention
the issues in the original
repository so that they are connected
And also, then we will talk
a little bit more about the tests
that you've already encountered
so we didn't expect that you would.
So many of you will encounter
the tests in the first
exercise so we'll probably do
a little bit faster than we intended to,
but we will still mention it,
so if you have any questions
about that and just let us know
when we came up with that.
Again, the solutions are down
here, so if you have any.
If you're unsure about something,
then just have a look here for the documents.
This is not cheating.
It's just reading up on how to do things.
But we will also present it fast,
since I guess everyone's coming
back from lunch break.
And maybe to give you a slower start,
we will quickly show you
the most important steps first.
Before I give the microphone to [name],
let me just quickly see
whether there are any new
questions in the collaborative document.
Let's see.
Is there an echo?
OK.
I hope that's just you.
If I ask some of my
co-teachers, do you encounter that?
I hope not.
Well, I take that as a no.
Ah, how to fork with command line, okay.
Yeah, so that's a good question.
Forking is not done on
the command line since it's a mechanism
or it's a feature that is
done inside of GitHub or
GitLab or whatever platform you use.
If you go, maybe we can
go quickly back to the first lecture.
Sorry, that was not what I intended.
I wanted to show this one.
And you remember this figure here.
You see we have this
repository and then cloning would
be down to your laptop.
So then that would mean that
you copy the whole repository
down to your machine.
But forking is inside of the cloud.
So inside of GitHub in this case.
So we just copy the,
repository from the organization
that they're in to your private one.
I can maybe quickly demonstrate that.
So if I now go to
the organization, and let's now
take the forked one.
So we see here,
centralized workflow exercise recorded.
And now I see already two
people forked it, but I want to fork it myself.
Now, if I wouldn't have to zoom in
as closely as I am right
now for the stream, then it
would actually also tell me
fork, so it's easier to find.
But now I will click on
it, and then it will show
me the organization in which it will be stored.
So in this case, it's my
private one, but I can also choose other ones.
You can see here all
the organizations that I'm part of.
But in this case, I'll
just choose my private one.
And then here, the name I
can also change, but I can
also keep it the same.
And then I can choose whether
I only want to copy the main
branch or all of the branches that are existing.
And then I can create a
fork by clicking on this.
And that will take a little bit of time.
And it's now forking the
repository into my own GitHub account.
So now if you have
a look here, unfortunately, yeah.
So if I vlog this a
little bit, maybe it's showing it properly.
Let's see.
Yeah.
Then you can see now it
is in my personal GitHub organization.
Okay, so that was walking.
[name], may I ask you to then go
through the exercise and we will, sorry,
go through the exercise here
of the third part of the lecture today.
So may I give the screenshot to you?
Yep.
And waiting for it to switch.
Oh, sorry, there we go.
All right, so looking at this,
We're going to, what's going to
be new in this thing, first
of all, we're going to
fork the repository, create a
branch, making a change, and
of course, making pull requests.
And there, of course, are going to be,
but in this case, doing the forking
and getting pull requests back
to the main or the official repository.
We'll go up here and take a look at that.
So here is the official
forking workflow exercise repository here.
And as [name] showed, we're
just going to click here to fork that.
And I'm going to call it recipe book.
OK.
Oh, I already have one forked.
Okay, and we're just going to
copy the main branch because I
don't need to modify all those
and have all those other ones
so we'll create that fork.
Oh, I I sort of skipped over.
Yeah, well, so then that
prepares us for number one.
So going back to the
exercises here, let's go ahead
and create an issue.
Now, just to see what
issues might exist here, I'm going
to go look in desserts.
Or let's see.
Sure, desserts works.
Pumpkin pie.
And we have these nice
ingredients here and instructions.
And perhaps I want to make
this to have some optional ingredients such
as marshmallows on top or
chocolate chips or something to make
it a more interesting pumpkin pie.
So let's open an issue to do that.
So new issue.
Add optional ingredients to pumpkin pie.
We need some
additional ingredients to make the
pie more interesting.
Okay, so we'll go ahead and create that.
Okay, so this issue exists
and we're going to be able to
refer to it going forward.
So now coming over here, this
is our fork of my own
local repository here of that.
And it says here forked from,
so it knows where the original came from.
And so then step two is
going to be, of course, to create a branch.
So we can create a
branch, better pumpkin pie.
Rafal Dittwald, And we'll
create that French.
Rafal Dittwald, Okay, so then
we maybe mentioned yes i'm
sorry sorry could you maybe mention
why it's a good idea to
still create a new branch, because
we are in a different repository
now just use the main branch.
Well, we may want to
have multiple changes and we don't
want to have those all intermingled.
Also, if this is under review
and we come and add
more changes, then those changes
are included because we pull branch to branch.
So we don't
want to get things all combined.
So it's it's
it's best to have you
know compartmentalization keep a
separate branch for each separate
set of modifications that you're making.
- Okay.
- So we have
better pumpkin pie here and
now let's actually go and
make that happen desserts pumpkin pie.
- And so I
want some optional ingredients.
Chocolate chips
or marshmallows.
Okay, and we can throw in.
yeah okay so there,
there they are and we'll we'll
put in an instruction.
Add marshmallow
mellows on top, if included.
And now, this
is optional ingredients and then
we're going to put this and
call it required ingredients.
so that we can make use of
that in a future discussion.
Okay, so I'm going to go
ahead and commit changes there.
And I'm going to go ahead
and commit this directly to
my own branch because I'm doing it.
But I do like better
commit messages and optional ingredients.
Okay, so that's been committed.
All right, so now if we
go back to files here, not files,
go back to the main code location.
Okay, so we now have this
and you'll see here that
we have this indication where
it says this branch is now
one commit ahead of the repository
it was forked from.
And so we then have an
option to contribute this
particular branch that we've
constructed back to the original repository.
So let's look just looking
briefly at our list of steps.
We want to then, of course,
Make a pull request.
So we can do that here.
Open pull request.
And this is, well, sure.
Add optional agreements to pumpkin pie.
And here, if
we look back at our original
this was issue number four.
We need more ingredients.
In pumpkin I recipe.
Okay.
highlights the
branch names.
Yes.
Because that's the difference
to previously.
This addresses issue number four.
And there is the issue
that we're addressing.
Okay.
So here,
uh we were uh we forked
from a branch called main here um
but in our uh uh repository
we're um have this fork the
the branch is called better pumpkin pie
and so that's uh we're
committing it back into there uh
in in a different repository which
we can see the difference there
is that uh did you want additional comment okay
Yeah, so you can see
here the base repository and
the head repository is different,
but it's there to make sure
that we are forking into the
original one and not accidentally
into our own main branch.
Yeah.
So we wouldn't want it to
be this because that wouldn't be
much of a change.
Um, of course now having done
that, it, uh, just goes away.
So, um, let's do that again.
Um, okay.
Contribute.
Oh yes.
Okay.
Let's go to our better pumpkin pie.
There we are.
Okay.
Now it's one commit ahead.
We can contribute, um, open
the pull request.
Okay.
Add more ingredients to pumpkin pie.
This fixes issue number four.
Okay.
And so then we create that pull request.
and allow
as maintainers and for now we're
going to just do this like that okay.
And that creates
our pull request and it heads
off to to now now, you can see that this is.
In the exercises.
account under
the original.
repository and
it's now listed here in the pull requests.
Okay, [name], you wanna now review that?
Sure, let's do that together.
So I'm gonna wait until the
screen share is on my side again.
Okay, no, it's not right yet.
Yeah, that's yours.
Okay, okay.
Yeah, so we are back in the repository.
So we see here now the issue that
[name] has created.
Okay.
We need some additional ingredients
to make this part more interesting.
Sounds good.
And again, since [name] mentioned
the issue in this pull request,
it is already shown here that
we have this pull request,
which is addressing this issue.
Let's click on it.
Okay.
So same as before, we can
check now the name.
That seems to make sense.
We also see here from where
to where the pull request is
supposed to take place.
So we see here from
[name]'s forked repository into
the main branch of the
code refinery repository.
So that's what we want to have.
So let's look here further
down and see, okay, these tests,
they seem to fail.
So that's maybe something
we should address.
But before that, let's have a
look at the files itself.
Okay, so we see here there
are a few changes to this file.
We have optional ingredients.
So again, you can comment.
Developing ingredients.
So we can start to review.
Let's see, okay, we add
this, this looks also good.
And then here, okay, I might
spot what the problem is.
The problem is that our
test script requires there to
be an ingredient section and
not required ingredients.
So this is not something that
I can suggest to change.
And this time I will use
this plus minus sign again.
So I'll now make some suggestions.
So I'll suggest to remove
this required and add that as a new comment.
Okay, so now I can finish up the review.
So I can choose between
just commenting, I can approve it,
or I can request changes.
And since there is this one
change that I suggested, you could use that.
But I mean, in this case,
it's such a small one that I
might just do it myself.
Right, so I will approve this pull request.
Let's click on Submit Review.
Let's go to here, the overview
of the pull request.
So we see here the comment that I made,
and then we also see
here the suggestions that I made.
So I can now click
on commit suggestions, and I
can basically create a new
commit with the suggestions that
I made earlier.
So let's just maybe use
a more meaningful commit message than this.
Let's say fix subtitle, or what is this?
This title or section title.
to make it compatible with tests.
Hopefully that's fair enough.
And if I do this again,
let's see what the tests are passing this time.
So we see that they're running.
So we can click on this and
it will show us the details.
So we see the different steps in this test.
So it's setting up the job.
So setting a Python, installing PyTest,
which is the library that we
use for doing these tests.
And then we see, okay,
everything seems to work.
Nice.
The checks agree.
It's ready to be merged.
So let's go back to the pull request.
So we have to go back
to, sorry, not from action set,
click on pull request, of course.
Go to this pull request.
And now it can be merged.
So now I can merge it.
Okay.
[name], do you want to show
how it looks now on your
end, in the fork repository?
Sure.
So I'll give the screenshot back to you.
Maybe just one thing.
I'll just show you the history.
So the last thing in the
history of the main repository now
is I can see here that
I managed this pull request.
Okay.
But now there's a next
step in the exercise, [name], which
you have to do on your side.
synchronizing the two repositories?
Yeah.
Okay.
So as it says here, after
a few pull requests are
merged, your update your fork with changes.
So let's see what that's all about.
So here we are at main
here in my own repository.
There's
My account, this is the
repository that I named it.
And this is where it's from.
And we have this little information here.
This branch is three commits
behind this particular, I mean,
the original branch, the original, yeah.
repository and branch.
And so then we have the
option to update this branch
and pull the changes from it
into our local fork of the repository.
So we can click there and
then click update branch.
And then they come and now
it's all is there.
And so we have here the commits there.
We have the additional optional,
fix the section title and the
merge of the request.
So that has it there.
And if we wanted to just
see what that looks like, we
can go to the, oops, the forks.
Which was.
Right.
I think maybe.
Yes.
And I'm just going to move this.
And so there, we can see
how we have this fork and
that we've merged it back in,
into our main repository.
So there it is.
So this is something you
have to do yourself
because synchronization between
four repositories does not
happen automatically.
It's easy to do, to update it
as you have just seen now,
but you should keep in mind
that this is not something
that is done automatically.
So if you want to make
sure that you are not working
on an outdated one, regularly
check whether you can synchronize it.
Okay, I think we have
now 25 minutes planned again.
So I will share my screen again.
Okay, so if you go down
here, we have 25 minutes.
So that would mean that
the exercise will end by 10 to the full hour.
And then we have a 10 minute break.
So in 25 minutes, I will
just announce that the break will start.
And then in 35 minutes, we
are back to discuss any
remaining questions and wrap up
what we've learned today.
So having said that, good
luck with the last exercise and
see you in 25 minutes.
Bye.
Okay, we're back online.
Welcome back.
I see that a lot of
pull requests have already been
created and managed.
Thank you for that.
There was one question which
I quickly wanted to address since
I think it's not something
we have mentioned and can be quite confusing.
And that's this question here.
How do you create a folder on GitHub?
So let me just go to
one of the repositories.
This is maybe a bit counterintuitive,
but in GitHub, it doesn't
track any folders, only files.
So, but you can trick
it into creating folders by
creating a file inside of that folder.
So I just quickly want to
show how to do that.
If you're in your GitHub
repository like this one, you
can click here on plus and
then create new file.
And then you can choose the file name here.
And by making a directory, we can do
that by choosing the directory
name, let's say fish with this.
And then we do slash.
And now we've created a directory,
and now we've created a file
inside of the directory.
So we can have, I don't
know, let's see, I don't know, .
So if I do it like this,
and I commit the changes, which I
now do, by the way, in my
own repository, so I'm not
I'm not screwing up the central one.
If I commit this, cool, but
I was thinking of a nice commit message.
Yeah, okay, I'm happy with that.
If I now go to the code,
and now I see there is an additional directory,
and inside of this directory,
I have now the file that I created.
So this might not be really
intuitive, at least.
I run into this problem also
myself a few times where I
was confused about not being
able to add directories.
So hopefully this answers the question.
Let's see whether there are
any other questions.
Yeah, so should you make
a draft pull request or a pull request?
This is something we addressed
earlier, but I think it's good to repeat it.
So you would create a draft pull request
if you have some changes that
are not done yet, but that you want to
get feedback on.
So it can already show
other people, look, this is
what I'm working on.
This is the structure of the
code that I envisioned.
These are the topics that I want to tackle.
And then you can already
get feedback before you actually
have to implement every single bit.
But if you have a really clear idea of
what you want to do, and
you already have everything with
mouse, then you would try to
no local requests because then
it can be crashed.
Okay.
We said that we would have
a 10 minute break now.
So that would be the last break.
So we have it now.
1452 in Central Europe.
So let's say we meet at
two past the full hour for
the last Q&A session and to wrap up
what we've learned today and
give you an outlook on the
lectures that will follow up in
the next couple of weeks in
the Codify Me seminar.
So with that said, see you all at two past.
Okay, welcome back everyone to
the last part of today's
seminar, of today's lectures.
I see there was actually quite
a few good questions here in the document.
Most of them are already answered,
but the last one I would
like to discuss here on stream as well.
So the question is, when
we have modified our own fork,
and in the meantime, the
original repository has moved on.
how do we deal with these situations?
Like when do we sync and
how do we make sure that, or
what is the best approach in this situation?
So this is hinting one concept
that we have not discussed
today, but yesterday, and
that's merge conflicts.
So if the changes that you have made
and the changes which have
happened on the upstream repository,
if they don't address the same
files or the same lines in
the same file, then this is
not a problem really.
But of course you can
run into merge conflicts.
So let's say like you
are working on changing a recipe.
Let's say this baked salmon recipe
that I made previously, like
in the instructions I added a certain tool.
And then in the meantime,
someone else has done something similar
and the other one has been merged
and there will be a
merge conflict which then needs to be resolved.
And then you need actually
one person during the review
then deciding which, which,
commits to or like which
changed to actually then commit to the branch.
So merge conflicts can still occur,
even if you use pull requests
and if you work
between different repositories, that's
not something you can magically escape from.
So I think, yeah, so thank
you very much for this question.
I think it kind of pinpointed, well,
like it's good that you asked
because it's reminded me
of mentioning merge conflicts once again.
In general, I would try to always think
branch that I work on as frequently
as possible with the upstream
branch to make sure that
they don't diverge too far.
Because if you get kind of,
if you end up working with
an outdated version of the
curves, then your changes are
probably not going to be very
welcome in the original repository.
Okay.
So let's wrap up.
Let's go to the
summary section of the lecture material.
So we've learned now how
we can approach other people's repositories.
And we have here this nice summary,
which tells you what to do
depending on the size of the
project or the changes that
you want to propose.
So if it's just a very
small one, then the go-to suggestion
would be to clone the repository,
create a new branch, push your
changes to the repository, and
then create a pull request.
If you work on the largest system,
or sorry, a larger project
with more people or with someone
that you don't know as well,
let's say you want to reach
out to the maintainers of the Python library,
or it could be Julia library, whatever,
you might want to actually
discuss it first via an issue
or a draft pull request, whether
what you intend to do makes
sense to them and whether
that's something, or whether that's
a direction they want the project to go in.
So in this case, you will
also create a issue first,
But you describe the problem,
so always over-describe, how would
you say, like over-explain what the issue is.
Like you're not talking to
people in person, you're doing
everything by text.
So you be very specific
and be very concrete.
And then in the best case, like wait
for feedback before you start
writing 5,000 lines of code to make sure
that your contributions are
actually welcomed by the contributors
or by the maintainers of the project.
And then if you have received feedback
and if they give the green
lights to go on and work
on this project, then you can
put in the hours and actually
write the code that you want to contribute.
And also by creating this
issue, you also indicate that
this is something that you work
on to make sure that not
other people have the same, find
out the same problem.
And then you have three,
four people working on the
same, fixing the same issue if
only one would be required.
Okay.
Yeah, similar story if you have an idea
for a new feature in a
codebase and you want to suggest that.
Let's see, I mean, we've
already spoken about all these things.
So in principle, we are done
with most of, or basically all
of the lectures for today.
Let me just click to see
in the document if there are
any questions that came up.
No, there's a longer answer.
If there are no questions, then
I think we can wrap up
lecture for today.
And in which case I will
then give the words to [name]
to give an outline on the
upcoming lectures of the Code
of Pioneering workshop now.
But before I do that, I
just want to thank everyone who's involved.
You only see people in front of the camera.
So that's me and [name] and [name].
So thank you all for
volunteering to work on this.
It's always a pleasure to work with you.
But there are also many
more people behind the camera
which have not been
directly seen, which I also want to thank.
So [name], [name], [name], and
all the others who have worked on this.
It's quite a find we wouldn't work
if there wouldn't be that
many people putting in so
much effort and volunteer to work on this.
So thank you all for doing that.
And also thank you for
coming to the course.
And I hope that the
concepts that you've learned today
will help you in your
future academic careers and make
your life and your everyday
life as a researcher easier.
So with that said, [name], may
I give the word to you?
Thank you so much, [name] and [name].
I hope all the participants felt
how important this day was and
how fun it is to
collaborate with other people and
or improve somebody else's repository.
So if you, and we can
also switch here to the notes
document so that we can see it.
in the at the bottom of
the notes document you can
keep on asking questions of
course that's the feedback for today
and the news box is
of course the interesting one
today we cover everything as is
in the schedule and please
feel free to continue to
explore the github interface this
is actually a great opportunity
because you know
Even if you do mistakes, even
if you, I don't know, break
one of these exercise repositories,
that's the purpose of it.
So you can play with the buttons
and any other features that we
did not have time to cover.
For next week, for the part
two of Code Refinery, so back until last year,
until last springtime, we used
to have it again as a second week.
but now from the feedback
from previous year we decided to
change it a little bit and
instead of having a second week
and that's it we're gonna
have single episodes every Wednesday
for the next six weeks
there will be shorter episodes of two
and a half hours each and
they will still cover the
usual Code Refinery workshop materials
but the idea is more
that they are self-contained episodes
so that if there's something
that is truly interesting you
can also share it with your colleagues
who maybe are happy just to join
for that for that workshop let's say
that you're planning to
write documentation together and you
want all your colleagues to
watch the documentation episode and
so on so feel free to browse
the topics for the future days
the next one will be next wednesday
at 12 o'clock oslo stockholm
rome time zone and that's
the main workshop about reproducibility
and we will cover everything
from the reproducibility crisis
to data management out organized folders
and also considering the
whole computer because sometimes
when you change computer things
are not reproducible anymore and
so we will introduce concepts like
containers and environments and
things like that.
Right, so we're actually a
little bit early, meaning that
we will still have a few minutes.
So if there's questions, please,
you can keep on sending them.
Maybe I can ask a
question to our instructors here.
Do you often contribute to
other people, people that you don't know?
Do you contribute to
their repositories, like with pull requests,
with the techniques that
you've shown today, [name]?
Not frequently, but I have
created sample requests to
the documentation of some
programming languages and so on.
There were some smaller fixes here
and there, but I saw that
there was a small typo
or something which clearly was wrong.
Yeah, definitely.
Which project was there?
Was it some library?
Plasma Pi.
So in plasma physics, that
is the biggest Python package that,
as far as I know, exists.
And I contributed some of
the routines through my postdoc
that we developed in our research group.
So that's more people than
just our research group have access to.
I see, I see.
Yeah, definitely fixing typos
and small things.
It's something that now all of you
who are watching can
actually immediately start doing.
I've been also doing that.
And in the end, you might
read a nice documentation or even books
because with Git, you can
also create books and you find
a typo or there's a way to improve something.
And it's very easy with
forking and pull request.
What about you, [name]?
Have you contributed to
some strangers repository?
uh yes um i come i've sent
some uh fixes to some code that
was in a git repository
associated with some published papers
as well as for some code
that was used in our clinics
in their some of their utilities cool
great so hopefully you know
this motivates all of you who
are watching to go out find
little errors typos there's a
specific type of label what is
the label easy first issue
or something like that i
never remember yes yeah so that
you can you know take
a challenge and contribute to
open source software right is
there anything to lift up from the notes
yeah somebody's asking this general
in the general questions will
there be exercises or just
lectures in the next weeks and
actually this is the main reason
of the change because in the previous way
that we did it there were only lectures
and the exercises were just
demos but now with having two
and a half hours for each
episodes we will have time for exercises
Which also means that now
the exercises will use Python.
It doesn't mean that you need
to know how to use Python.
But the goal is just to
show, for example, how to run some scripts.
Like, for example, in the next day,
next Wednesday, we will look
at a tool called SnakeMake, which
is a tool for pipelines.
And then it will run,
SnakeMake will call some Python scripts.
and basically long story short
I'm trying to tell you that we need
or you need to install conda
and the conda environment that
we have defined because then
through conda it takes care of
all the python dependencies that you need
and so please before next Wednesday
if you plan to do the
exercises with us here on the
stream try to have conda on
your computer if you have
troubles installing conda just send
us an email and we can
arrange even more zoom sessions for hands-on
installations and someone's asking
for the requirements link and
we will post it yeah the i would say
that in general the language
agnostic we try to be as general
as possible then if the examples
in the end are for python
and conda conda is actually
quite a flexible tool itself
you can manage other environments
not just python environments
But of course, some other languages like R,
for example, also have other
tools for managing R environments.
But I'm a bit spoiling the fun here.
I'm really talking about
environments without defining environments.
So, you know, let's resume
this question next Wednesday.
Right.
So I guess we covered everything.
I don't see any.
and answer questions.
Did I forgot anything, [name]?
I think we've covered everything.
fine to end a bit ahead of time.
Yeah, people can get Well, it's Thursday.
So don't quite start the
weekend yet unless you have a good reason to.
But the mode is already towards Friday.
So yeah.
And it was a long day.
And thank you for following
us and for doing the exercises.
So what were you saying?
I do have any questions,
please feel free to add them
in the notes and then we can still
And so to answer any
further questions today.
All right, so thanks again
to our instructors of today, [name]
and [name], and thank you,
[name], for the broadcasting and the help.
And thank you everyone in
those in-person rooms, managing, learners,
and whatever, what's the
word, enthusiastic people about
Git and version control.
We can close this Git part
of the Code Refinery workshop, and
I will see you in six days.
Have a good weekend.
Bye.