I got a PhD position offer, then a postdoc,
and now at this position
here in the research
software engineering group.
All right, interesting.
I wasn't planning to stay
here for much longer than I
never managed to leave.
Yeah, I've seen this so many times
that nobody's sometimes planning
where to go, but then they
end up there and they will
stay there maybe for the rest of their lives.
What about you, [name]?
How did you end up in terms of
Well, I came to University in Tromsø
for doing a PhD and stuck around
and got hired to do
research software engineering and
high performance computing.
well this is really great so you
both kind of went there liked it there
but also on the other hand the people
who have been hiring you
they didn't want you to leave
because often you know we have the issue
that amazing doctoral doctoral
researchers they just leave because
they have a postdoc offer
somewhere else in the planet and
it's just lots of you know
knowledge and and clever people
that are leaving every time
that they finish but it's
good that some universities invest
and keep the people we try
to do the same sometimes at Aalto University
so in the icebreaker i see
some people are writing yeah no
need to sleep that's the superpower
you know we need to sleep
especially our brain needs need
sleep but also the body
Yeah, the any language, being
able to code speak in any
language, this is a very interesting one.
And I was watching the news
that they are planning, I don't know
if they are available, some
sort of like headphones, earphones
that you could, that would
do live translation.
so that you could talk
your language with anybody else
in talking another language and
they would live translate.
So if we talk about languages, not
yet programming languages, how
is your Norwegian, [name] and
[name], because I'm assuming you
are not native in Norway?
No, but I think Norwegian
is relatively easy to learn
if you speak German as a
native language and if you
speak English already.
So I guess I had an easier time than most.
Do you need to do
teaching or supporting Norwegian or
is it that you just do everything in English?
As a PhD student in postdoc,
I had to teach in Norwegian
in some bachelor class.
I see.
But I think it's easier in physics
than if it would be linguistics
or so because no one really cares
whether your Norwegian is perfect
as long as you're able
to communicate concepts.
Yeah.
In Finland, it's a bit
more challenging to learn the language.
I can do the very basics.
So [name], I noticed that you
had a little crash.
Yes, Zoom was being annoying.
All right.
Hopefully, it will not happen
during the stream.
If it happens, we know that
you will be back a few seconds after.
And eventually [name] can scream for help.
We're all here with our camera off.
Right.
Then there's another icebreaker,
an important one before we start,
which is in preparation for today,
unless you are part of
an in-person classroom, we have
open an access request, or we are asking you
if you have opened an
access request issue so that
basically we can see your
GitHub handle username and, um,
and what and yeah actually this
is a good point that streaming
i think is showing
It's not showing my screen yet.
Oh, it got switched, I guess.
My screen is the one
with the icebreakers, yeah.
Yeah, so it's also going
to break the screen share.
That's good to remember.
That's good.
Let me know if the
screen share doesn't work or
if it's not showing the right thing.
So I was just showing these icebreakers.
And yeah, basically just a reminder,
if you click the link that
is there, you can request for access.
And then you will get an
email from GitHub to say that
you have been invited to be
a collaborator in this Git repository.
and then you need to
accept the invitation so it's
not enough just to request you
also need to wait for the
email and accept it and as
you know sometimes it might go to spam folder
or something like that so please check
and double check and we
will be checking this throughout the
day so if you see that you
don't have access or if you
are not sure just ask
All right, we have a couple
of minutes to go.
And anything else you want to say,
[name] and [name], before
we actually start?
Are you excited?
I am.
I think this is the most fun
day out of the course.
This is really the best day.
This is where you clearly see
the power of everything.
I know it.
how it joins together oh