Hello, hello.
Can you hear us?
Let's see if the Zoom or
not Zoom, if our Zulip audience is hearing us.
Hello, [name].
Hi.
tried to make the title
visible and I clicked on
the wrong slider again.
So the sound might be
slightly different from the way it was before.
I wonder what the number
was originally, but everyone can
adjust the volume.
So this point is probably fine.
I'll just keep it the way
it is for the rest of the session.
Can people hear us though?
Did you check this?
Okay.
Anyone on Twitch, Zulip, can you hear us?
Yeah.
so basically we are at day five
as usual if you were
already in the previous four days
of this code refinery workshop
you might already know how we
are going to operate together
so you're watching the twitch
tv stream and then there
is this collaborative document that
i'm showing right now
and there in this collaborative document
if you were not pressing
the previous days it's actually
very intuitive system at the very
top there is a pencil and
so for example now let's go to
the very top you might not
see my pencil but it's okay
All right.
Okay.
So you see there's a pencil.
I click the pencil and there
the page turns into like
an editor and basically you can just edit.
And so I added a
couple of icebreaker questions.
How is the weather at your location?
I think it was quite cold this morning.
Is it that you're in Oslo [name], right?
I'm not sure how it's in Oslo,
but Trondheim was, I used
clothes on my bike here to office today.
So I see it's starting
to getting colder here.
And last weekend, I think there
was snow in the mountains around 900 meters.
So winter is coming.
Winter is coming.
Definitely.
even though it's what the
second day of autumn but anyway
so those of you who are online
you can open this notes document
i guess you just received an
email with the with the notes document
so and basically write down
the weather but maybe more
interesting and i can ask this
question also to the others here in the room
I'm sure you have shared some
of your code or maybe you helped because
both of you are research
software engineers and maybe you
helped some researchers writing some
code for them.
So how do you usually give
codes to others, for example, [name]?
Yeah, well, I think I mostly emailed
or pasted into I can
on GitLab issues example code
and I haven't licensed it in any way just
I haven't said whether I had
gotten it from either.
But it's been mostly snippets of code.
And I think that's quite common
in all of just in university setting
and also the software industry
that small snippets of codes
are shared and copied.
Yeah.
What about you, [name]?
Well, I mean, I'm a
research software engineer.
It's my job to share code with researchers.
So essentially whatever they
want, usually Git on GitHub or
a local GitLab instance.
Also attachments and email.
shared folders.
What else?
I haven't used a thumb drive
yet in this job.
I have in previous jobs, like a USB drive.
Whatever works, whatever they can use.
is the best.
But of course, I prefer to use Git
and publish it so I can
make it available for everyone.
But then is it that when you give the code,
let's say that you, I don't
know, write the function or a script
for someone you're helping,
do you explicitly tell them
you can do whatever you want
with this code or you need
to cite my whatever copyright?
um if i make it public then
i use a license um but not explicitly
because we are i mean
we are essentially always been
working at the same university
and been collaborating on the code
so it's um the university owns
the code to some extent but
it's a good point like if
they want to publish it at
some point then in principle they
would need to ask my permission
which you if i have given you
some code you have my permission
to publish it but
This is not the best
channel for doing that.
I guess we'll come to that later.
And this is exactly basically
the topic of today that
sometimes you might even share,
okay, this is the bit of
code that whatever this postdoc
before me was using, and now I
pass it on to you.
And maybe it's all fine
and there's no issues, but
you can understand that maybe
is this whatever mysterious postdoc,
are they going to be cited?
or at least you know will
there be some mentions that
they actually were the original
writers of the code so this
is what we will basically cover
in this topic today which is
a kind of an interesting topic
because it's a mixture of
kind of legal reasons that
sometimes you you know you need
to be in order with the law
when you share the code or
use somebody else's code but then
it goes also towards more ethics that
if you you know if someone
was helping you it's good to
mention that this person was
helping you right so anything else
do you want to mention
Yeah, I worked for a startup
once that was acquired by Sun Microsystems.
And then there was a
huge due diligence process.
And one of the major things
was the source code of the
product that they were buying.
Where did this source code come from?
And it was developed in-house,
but they more or less went
through all of the code to make sure that
there wasn't parts that were copied from,
especially open source GPL
products or projects.
So they had a very
thorough process going through all
of the source code to make sure
that it was in fact written in-house.
yeah i agree and this
is also sometimes important that
maybe some of you might now
just starting to share code some
of you have been sharing
code and writing whatever
libraries extensions for for many
years you never know where
your code might actually end up
and then this type of
commercial slash legal issues might
you know, maybe even come
back in a positive sense that maybe, you know,
you get famous and hired
by whatever larger company in the world
or maybe, you know, as
most likely happens with researchers,
you will never see any penny out of your code .
But, you know, let's try to keep positive.