All right.
And here we are live.
Very welcome everyone to day
six of the Code Refinery workshop.
How is everyone doing?
I had my lunch here in Germany.
It's a bit later than in Iceland, I guess.
Right.
How about [name]?
Yeah, not bad.
Had my lunch.
Great.
We are here in the
studio together with [name], our streamer
for today and [name] and [name]
who will be teaching today's lesson.
And the next, is it still eight minutes?
We're going to have a
little chat here before the
actual workshop starts at the hour
to get used to our
ways of working with
our collaborative notes and see
what you all had for lunch.
And let's also do the audio check now.
And all right.
[name]'s already saying that
volumes are fine.
Okay.
What's the order that I see people at?
That's me, [name], you and [name].
Let's go in that order.
One, two, three, four.
One.
Two.
Three.
Four.
Okay, I think it's roughly the same.
All right.
Okay, so what I'm sharing
here on the screen is
our collaborative notes document.
Every one of you, if you
registered to our workshop, has
just, probably just right now,
gotten an email with the link
to that document and also
to our workshop webpage and
our virtual help room.
So this document is used
for connecting with the instructors,
so that we can connect with you
and you have a bunch of links up here
as well, for example, to
our code of conduct general just
be nice to one another.
And archives and also the
schedule is linked from here, and
if we scroll down.
we actually have some
icebreakers for everyone to get
used to this document.
So if you've never used
a HedgeDoc document or also
HackMD, it works very similar,
then you will see something
like I'm showing here right now.
And if you want to edit
something, you can find the little pen symbol,
which is either where it is
for me right now, up here
to the right, or somewhere here
in a group of three.
And if you click that,
you switch to edit mode,
then you can scroll down to
our icebreaker and add your answer here.
And you can go ahead and do
that now if you want to.
So we would like to know
what did you all have for lunch today?
Maybe we get some new ideas for tomorrow.
How would you explain your
current job to someone in the year 1700s?
That's always fun to see.
what people are actually doing.
And maybe we can guess what
what is your current job title.
And then related to our today's lesson,
what's the best documented project
you have seen?
So maybe we ask our
instructors first, what did you
have for lunch today, [name]?
Well, I think I was the
one who said some vegan dish.
I had some vegetables, something
light to just keep me alive
during the next two hours and a half.
Sounds good.
Very good, by the way.
Yeah, pretty similar.
I had some cucumbers, tomatoes.
Yeah, vegan dish.
How about [name]?
Did you have any lunch?
I had breakfast for lunch,
I guess, several hours ago.
Someone's saying the sound is
low in the classroom, even though
they have it on max volume.
So since we haven't started
yet, I'm going to adjust the gain a bit.
Okay.
So I hope your ears don't break.
We can continue talking something
to see if it helps.
Now it should be a bit louder.
So you can respond in the
document to the question.
If it's okay or not.
It helps.
Yes.
Okay, great.
And this is actually a great
use of the document.
These are all things that
please let us know as early as possible.
If you cannot hear someone or
if you think we are
sharing the wrong screen or anything like that,
the document is also used for
you to tell us if there's
anything we need to know during
the next two and a half hours.
So for everyone who joined
us now, sorry, go ahead.
No, I wanted to say
that actually this document is
the zero exercise for us because
we are going to practice a bit of Markdown
and that's exactly the, you
know, and this document is written in Markdown.
So you can practice some Markdown.
So it will also come during the lesson.
That's great.
Yes.
So the document will
be available throughout the lesson
and you can use it to ask
questions, let us know about
things during the exercise session,
let us know how it's going or
if you have any specific questions.
And once more for everyone who joined now,
you can find the little pen
symbol up here to go into
edit mode and then you can share
if you want to what you had for lunch today.
I will also add mine here.
I also had breakfast for lunch.
It was kind of a late breakfast.
And then some more sessions here.
Oh, we get some explanations of job titles.
How about you, [name]?
How would you explain your
current job to someone in 1700?
Well, I think that people in
the 1700 may know what a
scientist is or a philosopher is.
I mean, I'm, I guess, you know,
I'm not, I'm not a farmer.
So possibly to a person from
there, I could just pose as
one of those people that work,
you know, in an office and stay.
I think that's, you know, stay
on the desk and think more or less, I think.
How about you?
Maybe I would say I
do calculations by using
more advanced tools.
If people had some calculators
back then, they may understand.
Calculator was a job title,
so they had, yeah.
Yeah.
I don't know about 1700s if
it was an actual job title actually.
It's a bit early maybe.
Yeah.
So we also have
mechanical calculator operator here.
Yes.
Conceptual workflow.
That's some more points here.
The chemistry or alchemy.
Yes.
So I mentioned about of chemistry.
Okay.
Alchemy is dangerous.
So it's much better to do it on paper.
Yes.
And then we also have
the last icebreaker question here
leading us to today's topic
about the best documented project.
For the last one minute, [name]
and [name], what are the ones
that you find best documented
out there that you have encountered?
numpy is well documented i
would say yeah yeah i guess
that uh numpy is and the
python documentation in general it's
uh it's really it's really nice
i think i've learned uh so in
the the the re package in python the package
for uh regular expressions i
think i've learned working
with regular expressions there
on the documentation for that
package and also yeah
Yeah, NumPy I've used a lot.
And it's really nice to it's
a really good documentation, I
would say for for anybody who
wants to use NumPy.
Yeah.
Right.
And today we might learn how
to write such nice documentation.
It is one o'clock finish time.
So let's get started.
Let me just go back to the
normal view.
So welcome everyone to this
code refinery workshop day six.
Today, we're going to
talk about documentation, how
to write documentation for your
code, a topic that is sometimes overlooked,
and maybe seen as not
so interesting, or also maybe
a little bit hard.
So hopefully, today's lesson will
help you with that.
Let me go to the workshop webpage.
Hopefully all of you know this page.
This is where you registered.
This is also where you can
find all the information for today.
So if we scroll down here to day six,
you can find the link
to the lesson material today, if
you want to follow.
And then you also just got an email
that includes the link to
this page, the link to a virtual help room.
So if during today you have
any kind of technical trouble,
you can join there and ask
[name] all your questions that you have.
And then we have the link
to the notes document.
This is where you can find
another way to find all the links for today.
also to our code of conduct
and how we suggest that you
can set up your screen.
And here you can find the icebreakers
that we just briefly discussed
in the 10 minutes before we started.
And this document is also
here for your questions.
It is how we ask you
to interact with the instructors.
And we will also share all
the links to the materials or
any further links via this document.
And the way you can use
this document is you find
this little pen symbol, which is
either up here to the right
or somewhere up here to the left for you.
You click that, you go into edit mode,
and then you can also join
here, filling in the icebreakers,
testing a little bit how this works.
And then later you can
fill in your questions in the
bottom of the document, or let
us know if volume is off or
anything else that is happening
during the stream.
And with that, I will give
over to today's instructors, [name] and [name].
Yeah, I will be sharing my screen now.
Have a wonderful workshop, everyone.