Yes.
So very welcome everyone to
this session of the CodeRefinery Workshop,
where we are going to
talk about Jupyter Notebooks.
I'm here with [name], who
is manning the stream today
and handling that you can all see and hear us.
And then we have [name] and
[name], who will be instructing today's session.
My name is [name].
I'm the project manager for
the CodeRefinery project and
just introducing today's topic.
And you will also see me
briefly in the very end.
We are now showing on
stream our event webpage where
you can always find all the
latest news, what is going on.
You can also find the
questions from previous sessions
and what's gonna happen in the next session.
And if we scroll quite a bit down,
There is also the schedule
with all the different days.
This is the same page where
you also all registered.
And there you can find
behind Jupyter Notebooks.
That's the link to today's materials.
And then you have gotten
an email probably just a few
moments ago where we shared also
the link to our collaborative notes.
So let's switch to that one.
So that is the link
to our collaborative notes.
Again, all the links, also
a suggestion on screen set
up and our icebreakers.
And this is also the place
where you can ask questions
throughout the session today.
And in order to do that,
you will need to go into
edit mode of this document.
So if you arrive at this
page, you can look at the
very top of the document.
There will be either on the left
where it is for [name] right now,
or on the top right, a
little pen symbol that turns the
page into edit mode.
And then you can start
filling in the icebreaker.
Let us know if you're
using paper notebooks.
for example, at this moment, or also
what is your way of working
when you are writing code?
Are you having any
experiences with Jupyter, for example?
And then during the session,
like it is happening right now, very nicely,
someone will add headers to
this document and also the
links to the respective material
session that you can always
follow along what [name] and [name]
are doing at the time.
And then you can ask the questions
there whenever they come up
during the session.
One last word about code
of conduct, please.
Since everyone can edit this
document, be nice to one
another, be considerate.
Everyone here is on a
different journey at a different
stage in their learning experience.
So take that into consideration.
when you are also answering question,
which you are very free to do
if you know the answer to
some of the questions that are appearing here.
And with that, I'll give over
to [name] and [name] and have
fun with Jupyter today.
Yeah.
Thank you, [name].
Thanks.