All right, and live we are.
Hello, everyone.
Welcome to pre-workshop hangout.
Today, only five minutes, but
we are still here.
And let's do a quick sound check.
So we have [name] here
as our streamer today, connecting
from Aalto University.
Then we have [name] and
[name] as our instructors for today.
[name], do you want to
start this audio check?
Yeah.
So we'll count
one, two, three, four.
One.
Two.
Okay.
So order is [name], [name], [name], [name].
One.
Two.
Three.
Four.
Okay.
At least on my screen it looks good.
Sounds fine.
If
someone who's listening on Twitch
can let us know.
That's great.
All right.
Yes, let's take a look
at our notes document.
So for everyone who is here and not
yet familiar with that, it's
what we're showing on screen.
It's what you got via email.
Unfortunately, today, not right
before this stream,
because of technical difficulties,
but you got it like when
you registered to the workshop,
there's a link to the notes document.
And this is what you're
seeing here on screen.
And [name], if you could show
us how this can be edited.
So everyone can find a
little pen symbol either on the
upper left or upper right of the document.
Trying to hide.
Okay.
Now it's visible.
Yes, so for [name], it's on the upper left.
So there is a pen symbol
which brings you into edit mode or
what [name] just clicked is
the both double view or however it is called.
to see both the rendered
version and the edit version.
And if we scroll down there,
now we will have some
icebreaker questions prepared for you.
So you can get used to the document
and get to know a little
bit about each other who is
here all in the workshop.
So first question there is
what programming languages are
you normally working with?
And I will ask that to
our instructors for today.
So what are your
daily programming languages, [name]?
Well, it's mostly Python, I'd say,
and then it's occasionally
some Bash for smaller scripting,
but that's mostly it.
Okay.
How about [name]?
Yeah.
So I'm working a lot with
Bash in Python in daily work.
Then in some code projects where
I'm one of the main
developers, I'm using Fortran and
also CUDA for GPU programming.
Okay.
So for everyone watching today, know
that you can ask also
questions about these languages today.
And then we have also a
few people working here behind
the scenes and answering questions
in this document.
So this document is also used
for asking questions during the
workshop to our instructors and
our friends behind the scenes.
And you can also, if you
know the answer to some
questions appearing here, you can
of course also answer yourself.
Then we have
Another icebreaker question.
What does testing your code
mean for you and how do you test?
So in your daily life, do you test, [name]?
So well, not in my
work day to day stuff, but
in the in the projects that
I'm doing some more actual programming
that I do test quite a lot.
Yes.
Yeah, we'll talk
more later a little bit
about the different types of
testing that are relevant.
Yeah.
How about [name]?
Yes, I'm
I'm using testing in various contexts,
both for a product where I'm
one of the developers, and also
when I install codes on a
supercomputer at PDC in Stockholm
where I'm working.
Then, yeah, by default,
we run through some test
suites after having built and
installed a program.
Okay.
So we still have one
minute before we're officially
starting to briefly want to
introduce yourself to our
participants, where you are.
Located Where do you work, what
do you work [name].
Yeah, sure.
So I work at CSC at
CSC as a machine learning specialist.
And yeah, so I mostly help
users use our supercomputers, mostly
in the machine learning context,
GPU stuff.
And then I work in
several like research projects, also
in a similar support role, but
a little bit more like
embedded in a in a group
that does the actual research.
Okay, how about [name]?
Yeah, so I work at the PDC Center
for High Performance Computing at
KTH in Stockholm, where we
are currently operating the
largest supercomputer in the country.
And that's a machine named
Dardel, which has AMD CPUs and GPUs.
So some of you might recognize this
as the similar configuration as
you have on the LUMI supercomputer in Finland.
So it's a lot of commonalities there.
And I have a background
in material science research.
So a lot of the work that
I do at PDC is connecting
to material science simulations and programs.
And related to that, I
am then working quite a
bit with product traditional languages
such as Fortran and C++.
Okay, now we have one minute
after the hour so we can
officially get started here.
Welcome everyone to day
eight of the CodeRefinery workshop,
where we'll be talking
and practicing automated testing.
For those of you that have just been here,
we have here with me, [name]
and [name], who will be
the instructors for today.
And also [name] is here doing
the behind the scenes, the streaming
set up for you.
My name is [name].
I'm project manager for CodeRefinery
and just briefly here to say
hi and in the very end.
So what I wanted to show
you is, first, our workshop event page.
[name], if you could switch to that one.
Yes, so hopefully
that that's the page where you registered
and here you can find the
link to our lesson materials for today.
If you scroll down,
through the schedule towards
day eight behind the automated
testing name, there's a link to the materials.
And there you can also
find all the questions and
answers from the previous days.
If you go in the upper
navigation bar under questions
and also information about their certificates.
Let's wait a moment for
scrolling all the way up.
Okay, and then let's switch
to our notes document.
That's the main document that
you will need for today.
So this link you got
with the registration to this workshop,
and that will be our
communication channel for today.
So here you can ask questions.
We will in between ask some questions,
how it's going during the
exercises to identify if we need
more or less time for them.
And it's also the place where
you can find our icebreaker.
So when you are clicking the
link in the email to the
notes document, you will find it in view mode.
So that looks something like
what is shown right now on screen to the right.
To go and edit this document,
you can go all the way to
the top of the document and
find the little pen symbol.
It's either up to the right somewhere.
or up to the left where it is
for [name] showing the clicking
right now that brings you into edit mode.
And then you can practice
editing this document with plain
text by adding an O
for the programming language
that you're generally using.
And then also let us know
how you currently do testing.
And yes, we also have
[name] behind the scenes who
is the notes manager.
So there will be headers
appearing during the lesson that
give you the exact links
to the lesson materials where we
are at each moment.
And when there's exercises, you
will put the information on where
you can find the exercise.
Yes, so we will have
two exercise sessions and one break today.
And a quick outro with a
little bit of hints for the
next session as well on
modular code development in the very end.
And with that, I remind you
about the code of conduct.
Everyone here is at a
different level and that's okay.
You can ask questions freely.
You can answer them as well,
but please be nice and
considerate with each other.
And with that, I'll give over to [name]
for starting today's automated
testing session.