Hello.
Can anyone hear us out there?
Yeah, so hi, I'm [name].
I don't think you've seen me here before.
I've been around CodeRefinery
for a while, but haven't
been teaching much this time.
I guess you know [name] from previous.
Yeah, I was here for
the documentation session.
So maybe most of you have seen me before.
Yeah.
But yeah.
So welcome to the last day.
Who's excited?
I'm kind of super excited.
Yeah.
I mean, this is a day.
Ever since we had the, we redefined
or rewrote this last day's
lesson, it's always been one
of my favorite days of
CodeRefinery, just because it's
such a, like it wraps things up
so well and so interactive.
Maybe first we should do the audio check.
Yeah.
So can people hear us and
are we fairly balanced?
Yeah.
Should we say something, some
numbers or I already said something.
Is the voice okay?
It seems good.
I guess so.
Well, we can wait and see.
No.
Okay, well, if you can't, is it balanced?
That's the most important thing.
Yeah, are we like the same volume?
Okay, good.
Someone writes down it's balanced
in the notes.
Yes.
Okay.
So yeah, how should we start?
My checklist says we should
summarize what happened last time.
So what was the previous session?
It was automated testing.
I guess [name] wasn't there last time.
No, I wasn't there.
But that's also a quite
good sort of wrapping up lesson.
It combines everything together,
the version control, the coding
and stuff like that, and sort
of lets you, well,
It's a really nice thing.
It's nice whenever I can
make some code modifications and
then push it to GitHub.
And then when I get
an email automatically from GitHub
that says, oh, you broke your code.
It's like, OK, well, good.
Now I can fix it sooner rather than later.
It actually takes a lot of
stress off of me and helps
me find problems earlier rather than later.
Was there any particular feedback
from last time?
I guess none of us were here then.
Yeah, I haven't got time
to read the feedback from last time.
Sorry.
But what are the expectations for today?
And why should people stay?
So
Yeah.
Basically, yeah.
The topic today is
modular code development, but it
will connect everything together.
Yeah.
And you get to see us live code.
So you get to see us
take suggestions from the audience
and we'll add it to our stuff and make
try to take something and
we slowly migrate it from a
Jupyter Notebook to something that
can be reused.
And it really is a
kind of realistic arrangement of
things or something like that.
Yes.
For the icebreaker we have here,
what programming languages do
you normally work in?
Yeah, we can see someone selected Python.
Actually, that's also the language
I used most of the time.
Same.
But it doesn't matter if
you're not comfortable with Python
for this session, I mean.
Right, yeah.
Yeah, we're mainly talking why
we should do modular code
development than how to.
Yeah, my understanding is our
example is in Python, but if
you don't know Python, like
we're not talking about Python
itself, we're talking about what we do.
And that's pretty much the
same in any language.
Yes, and actually we encourage people,
if you can like contribute
some examples with the other
languages, you can send a pull
request to our GitHub repo.
The link is listed under
here in the materials, but
that's for the future.
Yeah.
Do you use any of
these other programming languages
that are mentioned here?
I use the C++ a bit.
Yeah, and I also know a bit about CUDA.
Okay.
Yeah.
Yeah, which actually should
be super modularized for CUDA.
Otherwise, it's messy.
That's a good point.
Like the whole idea of CUDA, isn't it
that you sort of break
things down into these individual
Yes.
Kernels like data parallelism
and divide it up and
runs it all separately, so.
Yeah, yeah.
My understanding is that each
piece in CUDA should take a very specific task.
Yeah.
But we are not going to use CUDA today.
I'd be interested in learning.
I've never messed with CUDA before, so.
Yeah.
Oh, there's this second question.
What's one small habit or
workflow that helps you stay
organized when coding?
I guess I can say these
days I have a directory called Git.
And within that, I make
a new project folder for each
new thing I start.
And that sort of keeps
the things separate and understandable
and any one thing from
getting too complex unless I
really want to spend time on it.
Yeah.
And then of course, within
each one, use version control somehow.
Yes, that's good.
Well, for me, it's not a
habit developed at the very
beginning of my career, but
somehow I learned after a while
that I should think about
the file system before starting something.
Because at the very beginning of my work
as a software engineer, I
would start with a big block of code.
Yeah.
Okay.
So you mean like dividing
it into separate files or
somehow organizing it on disk?
Yeah.
Better.
Mm-hmm.
Maybe not necessary for all
projects, but it's good to keep
that in mind, I think.
Yeah.
Yeah, I can say my
project organization has gotten a
lot better in the last 10 years.
Yeah, me too.
Anyway, I guess it's 1 o'clock
now, so we should begin.
Yes.