us we can't do stuff so to
go to the outro I will click
to the schedule and go
to day nine including remarks and
where to go from here and open
that in a tab fix the font
size so I have the privilege
of greeting you and sarah
including the workshop, even
though I haven't been around much.
All our other hosts are
occupied with other stuff today.
So first off, we'd like
to thank everyone who's attended.
So all the participants, of course.
We've had a whole lot of team leaders
and hosts in other
different locations scattered around
who are basically running
the local breakout teams and stuff like that.
That's great.
I think we think that
having this local connection
while the centralized teaching is
a good way to do things.
So make sure you give them a thanks.
We should thank all
the different instructors.
I don't know how many we
even had this time.
10 or more?
So it's actually been quite
well and it's been quite
nicely distributed here.
So we'd like to thank all of them.
In addition to the people
you've actually seen, we've had
more people in the background
who have been answering questions
in the notes and stuff like that.
That is.
They've basically been able to
help us focus on teaching.
And all the local partners who
helped to do stuff.
So I'm not saying the names here
so that the names don't
get recorded in YouTube, but all
the names are on the website so.
please go take a look.
You can give us feedback.
So of course there's feedback
within the notes that are there.
You can give it for both today
and the whole workshop, or you
can let us know by email.
This is our chat if you
want to join and talk with us live.
Since you know how to use git now,
if you see things that are
wrong, you can go and make
git issues directly in all
of our different lessons and improve things.
Basically, everything we've taught
you now is exactly what we
use to do the development of these lessons.
What we've given you so far
is only the starting point.
So we've said a lot of stuff.
We've had to give one version
of the lesson for everyone
at every different level.
And it is quite, I mean, we're not
even pretending that we
have something that's the endpoint here.
But you can review all of
the things that we've done here.
We hope that you're not done here,
but you can keep reviewing
and using what we have.
You can also ask for help.
So our model here is we give the teaching.
It's live.
It's almost like a MOOC course we have.
But then you have all the
local support to go and
ask them questions about these things.
Basically, all of the people
you see here and all the different countries,
these are places where you can
ask and say, hey, you know,
like this is my team here.
You can come and ask us,
hey, you know, I have
trouble with version control.
Can you help?
tell me what my problem is
or can you help me add unit
testing to this program i'm writing
or things like that and same
for some of the other different groups here
also these are the organizations
where many of the instructors came from
so you can find them through that
and follow up if you'd
like invite personal lessons or
things like that okay if
you like a certificate you can
see the course web page this
will tell you what we've got
there I don't remember the
details but I think you've discussed it before
If you'd like to support
us, there's different ways.
The most important way is
to tell others about the workshop
and let them know that
it's relevant for their starting
as a researcher.
Our next workshop has just been scheduled.
I don't think it's written
on this page right now, but
in about six months, we have the next workshop.
And it will be a lot like this.
So you can practice and then
you can send your friends here
next time so they can work with you.
you can follow us and boost
us on different social media
if you want to you can bring your colleagues
as a team next time and you
know rely on us doing the main instructing
and you help with the
exercise leaders or help as
an exercise leader and help
with the exercises then
There's our chat that I
mentioned and newsletter.
Both of these you can sign
up for to hear more about what's going on.
And finally, if you're really
interested in the topics here, so
if you like what you see,
if you think that, hey, you
know, I'm actually interested in
doing more of this kind of software
or data or code things as
part of your career and
you're a researcher, there's a
term for that now.
called the research
software engineers and different
groups behind this so it's
basically a community of people
who are in research but their
skills lie in getting the
code data software stuff like
that working better and they're
very important parts of the
you know, the research process.
I mean, computing and data
is in almost every field of science these days,
but not everyone can take the
time to learn it all themselves
unless we have specialization.
And if you want to specialize in
that kind of stuff, many
of the instructors here, we basically work
as some sort of research
software engineer or research engineer
of some sort and have made
our career out of this.
So it's something that you
can think about also.
If you really like it,
next summer in Tromsø, Norway, we
have a third in-person Nordic
Research Software Engineers Conference.
And maybe it's the kind of
place that you can join and visit.
So yes, any feedback we
should discuss in the notes?
Well, that's not a lot of feedback, please.
Please add more here.
And yeah, anything else?
Or should we call it good?
Yeah, I think we have
all the topics covered.
And it's exactly the ending time.
So I guess.
Thank you everyone for
listening and watching.
It's been a pleasure to have
you have so many people
attending this and Yeah.
See you later.
Yep.
See you.
Okay.
Bye bye.