Hello, everyone.
Can you hear me online?
Can you hear me here in the room?
Yes.
Good morning, [name].
How are you?
Good morning.
So I have just emailed
our 426 participants.
Hopefully, the email will soon travel.
to all the maybe more than 30 countries
who have registered for this
Code Refinery workshop.
But we still have more
than 10 minutes before, you
know, the actual start.
So are you all excited?
Are you all energized, [name]?
I mean, adequately, not too much.
Of course, of course.
It's somewhat early in the morning.
Well, maybe not that early in Norway.
It's 10.50.
But what about Iceland, [name]?
It's about 8.50.
All right.
So it is an early morning
for the people in Iceland.
Right.
So let's have a look
if our participants are joining the streaming.
So I'm watching another computer right now.
Well, we still don't have
many people there.
I guess they are still
booting up their computers.
So
so I will not yet start
with the fun part but in
general I guess our volumes
are quite balanced so if our colleagues in the
in the Zulip have any
comments related to our volumes I
can say let's have a round where I say one
and then [name] says two and
then [name] says three and [name]
says four and then we can
continue in this module four so
one two three four one two three
or for me it's quite okay but
and i don't see anyone
commenting in the zulip right so
i can see people are joining
the zulip stream so i'm gonna
do or [name] do you know
how well what's what's the number
of the how many workshops you
have done before this
Yeah, I think this is the
number 12, if I'm correct.
So it's been, it's been a
while, number 12 of this
large, big online workshop,
which practically means that every
year we do a couple.
So it's the sixth year
that we basically started 2019 and now 2025.
So yeah.
course there's many other
in-person smaller code refinery workshops
that have happened in the past
and that goes back to many
many years ago yes so i can
website we have a like list
of past workshops i see that uh
we are on the ninth year
now yeah so almost eight nights
and many, many workshops behind us.
So in this first 10 minutes,
we are just kind of warming up.
The listeners, the learners are
joining the streaming on Twitch TV.
But the actual workshop will
start at the o'clock.
This time it's very interesting
because we have so many time zones.
I'm so happy actually that Iceland
Thank you, [name], for the motivation
and for bringing your
colleagues from Iceland, because
it's three hours difference
compared to Helsinki, where I am right now.
And, you know, it's also
challenging to find a time
that suits all these time zones.
but of course time zones are
relative in a sense that we
have learners also register I
think the most eastern maybe was
India the more in the east
and there's also some registration
from South America so I
don't know whether those people are there
awake in the middle of
the night listening to us or
in India guess right now is afternoon
but hopefully everyone is as excited
as us so in this little
little how can I say ten
minutes that we have together
I can briefly show this notes document
that everyone should have
received via email and the idea
of this notes document is
that everyone can write where they're from
or test it and then
during the workshop this is
great for asking questions.
So in this few minutes that we have
before the actual workshop, feel
free to test the document.
I'm the first one here
who wrote Helsinki Sunny.
I put a question mark because
I'm in a room, but there's
no windows, at least in the morning.
So [name], apart from our,
we have some classrooms as well.
Some people are going together
in different places.
For example, we have a
group in Oslo as well with
I think around 12-13 people with some helpers.
So that's actually a very
exciting way to learn as well
in addition to learning one by yourself.
Yeah, it's very interesting.
Do you have one in Alto as well?
In Finland, basically CSC
is organizing, CSC, which is the
center for IT center for
science here in Finland.
It's kind of maybe 500
meters walk from here, from
Aalto University where I'm right now.
And so it's a nice spot
because then we can get
people from Aalto University
and Aalto University.
So they have the local hub.
What about Iceland and Reykjavik?
Is it that also there you have a group?
Yeah, it's like we also have
a local room here.
We reserved for that.
And it's about 12 participants registered.
And coming back to the
weather, it is raining outside.
Luckily, I have a window.
Yes.
But unfortunately, our participants
are in a closed room.
And of course, I mean, we understand
that some people are alone
in their office or bedroom
watching the stream and learning with us.
And some people are together
with other people.
In the end, we all be
watching kind of TV together.
But this is the advantage
of this notes document that
we can actually interact with the TV hosts.
so i can already see
that people are writing also we have Carlsruhe,
Prague, Belgrade so yeah we
are covering a nice a nice
set of european countries so
there's still three minutes to go and
I mentioned in the email
that everyone had just received
that there is also a Zoom room.
Now, the idea of the Zoom is that
if you need help during
exercises, you can join that room
and there are some helpers
there, but it's not something
that you actually need for learning.
In the end, this notes document
that I'm showing right now is the best
for interacting with the
instructors, interacting with the
helpers and so on.
there's many of us watching
it behind the scenes so i
guess you will give some
more instructions on how to write
on it exactly that will be part of the intro
Right.
There's another icebreaker here
at the bottom.
Have you ever wished you had
a code time machine?
So maybe I'm going to ask [name].
Have you ever wished you had
the code time machine?
Or maybe you have a code time machine?
Yeah, in fact, I have.
I'm going to show it today.
What about you, [name]?
yeah i had the same thing
like uh mostly using the
same time machine everyone like i suppose
so it's good too that is for some
for certain things we can
build time machines so now
the time machine the the issue
with my machine is only for the
past i can't go off to the
future yet but it's coming
that's interesting is it that
some large language model will
predict your next whatever year of code
so that you know well let's
not go there maybe all right
what else do we have yeah
i'm gonna start by showing the yeah go ahead
So I'd just like to say
hello to our Oslo instructors,
[name], [name], and [name].
Hi, I'll meet you tomorrow.
Today I have to be away
from the room because it's
difficult to teach in the class itself.
And all the classrooms, hello as well.
Make sure your projector is
set up and people can hear us properly.
And also the screen font
is large enough for them to read.
That's a very good point
about the screen phone, because
Twitch TV being a broadcast,
sometimes they try to save
the bandwidth, save the bits.
And so you really need to
set the quality of the Twitch TV stream
so that it's not trying
to compress everything and
make everything pixelated.
and so for those at home
and for those in these rooms
please set the twitch tv quality to source
so that you you get all
the pixels from our from our workshop
so that's 10 seconds before
finish 12 o'clock ice line
the nine o'clock and so i think we can start
Hello everyone and welcome to
yet another Code Refinery
workshop, September-October 2025.
We have a format that
is slightly different when it
comes to the schedule compared
to previous workshops, so if this
is not the first Code Refinery workshop
that you follow, you will
find some interesting changes,
more exercises basically.
what I'm showing right now
on the twitch.tv stream is
the main workshop web page which
is our kind of communication channel
so that here you can
follow the schedule you get all
the links to the materials and
you will also get access to
the questions and answer document
that we will soon introduce
so right now we are at
day one i'm scrolling down to day one
and i'm gonna talk about this welcome
and introduction to the workshop
so when i click the link
that is there it will actually
go to the presentation material
that we will use
so we will not use
any powerpoints here they're all materials
and they're all hosted in github
so that if you find a
typo you will learn how to
submit an amendment all right but
we are glad that you are
here briefly about code refinery
so code refinery is an ordi
project focused on teaching
scientific computing tools
But Code Refinery is especially
a large community of
research software engineers, researchers
who need to work with computers
and code and data and
in general enthusiasts about
research software and anything that
is related to that.
But Code Refinery is also
this workshop where we are.
here right now and lots of lessons
and open learning materials that
some of them are covered in this workshop
but we also have other
learning materials that go beyond
for more advanced topic
there's many founders and
organizations that are involved
in code refinery
The main funder is
the Nordic E-Infrastructure Collaboration
and the partners are
Aalto University, where I'm from,
CSC, IT Centre for Science, also in Finland.
Then we have from Denmark the Centre
for Humanities Computing and
the Danish E-Infrastructure Cooperation.
Sweden is there with the EuroCC, ENCCS
and also the National
Academic Infrastructure for Supercomputing.
And then we have Norway
with the University of Oslo, where
one of our first instructors is from.
And then RIS Sigma 2
and University of Iceland, where
our second instructor of the day is also from.
So I'm already going to say hi.
You might see their faces here to [name].
Hi, hello.
Good morning.
Yeah, hi.
I will introduce you properly, don't worry.
So with all your expertise and titles.
But briefly to motivate a little bit,
there's this nice image by
[name] that kind of tries
to give you the
what are the six useful steps
or helpful steps for
making reproducible research.
I'm not now going to
start talking about
reproducibility, reproducibility crisis
because I don't want to spoil the fun.
That is for next week and
you will hear all about
reproducibility issues in science.
But in general, all the bits
that you will learn throughout
the workshop are related to what you see here.
So getting your project folders
and files in order, making sure
that you can travel in
time, specifically that you can
travel back in time.
Travel in the future, it's still not there.
and in general so make your research
that is transparent in a
way that other people can look
at your code maybe look at your data
if possible and look at
your documentation so that you
are able to open your software
or open your data and follow the best practices
Sometimes we don't really like
the term best practices.
It's much more inclusive to
say good enough practices,
because sometimes the good enough
practices is truly what really matters.
So how does this workshop works?
Well, the format, as you
are seeing, it happens on Twitch TV.
And the reason is, well,
you know, most likely you've been
to some Zoom teaching with
hundreds of people there.
It's not very...
It can be stressful to
keep people microphone off and so on.
Here it's more like a TV show.
We are here in a small studio
and we are broadcasting to
anyone in the planet who wants
to hear about reproducible research.
And by doing this also, it's
easier to take care of the recordings,
that the recordings will
be immediately available on Twitch TV.
And later, after we basically
cut them and subtitle them, they
will be also on YouTube.
The attendance is kind of
choose your own adventure.
There are the first part,
which is happened this week.
It's all about version control
and Git with GitHub.
but then after that we
have different episodes happening
multiple weeks and come join the topics
that you find more useful
could it be reproducible research
could it be software licenses
could it be whatever you need
or follow them all we
don't really track attendance and
you can watch them live or
you can watch them later
materials are always available
they are linked in the workshop schedule
as I showed earlier and when
it comes to the actual schedule
we try to have at least a
10 minutes break every hour and
for this first part in the
first week we will have a one
hour break in the middle
so in when it comes to time zones
because we try to fit
multiple time zones this will
be a convenient break for maybe
people in UK and Iceland and
for the Oslo and Finland it would
be more like a afternoon coffee break
then i briefly mentioned
about this collaborative notes document
that i was showing earlier and
the idea of the collaborative
notes document is that it's
somewhat like a google docs
so that everyone can edit at the same time
and this is much more
convenient than using a chat
for example the zoom chat that
i was mentioning earlier
because here the questions
are basically forming a nice
documented set of questions and answers.
What is really interesting
that sometimes it's not just
the experts or the helpers that
are going to answer.
Sometimes you might know the answer.
You might have experienced the same bug,
the same issue with some
operating system and you can
share your experience.
So it's truly a
collaborative document where we can
all edit at the same time.
To edit the document, if you
open the page that you received
in your email, there is a
pencil in the top right corner.
So if you click on the
pencil, the view mode will change
from view to edit.
So I will briefly show it.
Now I have another window
here with the notes document.
I scroll up I see this
pencil I click the pencil and
now I'm in this edit mode and
I can see here there's
already 93 people watching this
page maybe editing this page and
many of you everything here
where you're from is it sunny
is it not sunny it's a
nice data set of locations and weather
and this is how we
run sometimes polls where basically
you can add in this case an
O to say you know if you wished to get them
and here you can already
start asking questions and you see
we use with this indentation
we have nice colors and different questions
Maybe the only thing that
it's important that you always write
on top of the last line so
that it's easier to know when is
the end of the document.
And if you feel that
the document is getting very
slow, then it's good to, you
know, we have a good server
that hosts this document.
But sometimes if I would say
if the number goes above
150 simultaneous edits, it starts
to get difficult.
So then it's good to click
on this eye icon.
in the very top part of
the screen and so that it goes
back to this view mode.
All right, back to the introduction.
Try to please don't put
personal data or passwords into
this share not documents.
At the end of the day,
we will archive it so that
after the whole workshop, we have
a nice set of question.
very briefly about the practical setup
so you might have noticed
that this screen share streaming
that we are doing right now
is not the usual landscape whole
screen type of setup but we
have this vertical stream and the
idea of the vertical stream share
is that it really helps those
who have a single monitor
for example laptop users
because then you can keep
the twitch tv open in let's
say like you show here on the
left hand side of the screen
and then you have all the
right hand side free where you can put
for example the web browser
with the with the lessons with the materials
or your terminal if you
are learning it with the terminal
or vs code or any other
window that you might need
so this is very useful if
you have a single screen of course those
who have multiple screens they
can arrange the windows as they prefer
All right, I'm soon done
with all these intros.
I promise you I will.
This is the only day where
we do this long intro, but
I'm just very happy that there's
so many people involved in this workshop.
Again, we have now here it says 370,
which was the number from a few days ago,
but this morning it was
426 people registered from really
all over the world.
and behind the scenes
there's 15 coordinators and
helpers, instructors, facilitators.
It's a big work but we
hope that there is value in
all this energy that we put into this.
briefly on the workshop etiquette
as usual we try to be
nice to each other and you
have to understand that we
are very different some people
might be experienced coders who
have coded all their life
some people might have just started
or maybe not even will
never code they're just here to
learn the tools that their
coding colleagues are using so
let's just respect everybody else's
space and differences let's try
to be helpful in the collaborative document
And if something is not right,
if you feel that something is wrong,
we have a code of conduct
and you can get in touch
with the workshop organizer, Samantha
and I, or with the
general support at coderefinery.org address.
final notes well most of
you are registered if you register
you will get more emails from me reminders
and links and anything helpful
but of course you can also
just watch the the twitch tv stream
and and don't worry about it for those
who need certificates there's
a clear instructions there if
they're not clear please ask
in the notes document
And finally, Code Refinery is
an open project.
Anyone can join us.
If you follow the link
here, there are multiple ways to join us,
whether you like to receive emails
once in a while, not too
many, don't worry, or maybe
you want to actively join us.
For example, we host a Zulip channel
where many, many, many researchers
and software engineers and HPC admins,
they're all there and
answering each other's questions, sharing.
interesting links and sometimes
also funny memes.
But I think I've talked enough.
So maybe I'm going to ask [name].
Hello, [name].
[name] is here with us today
and he will be with us for
many days as the broadcasting
expert or broadcaster.
Is that broadcaster?
Broadcaster is good.
Expert is saying so much.
Well, as I was explaining earlier,
if you look at the distribution
of all the broadcasters in the
world, you are falling in
a quite high percentile.
But I'm asking you if you
can switch to the notes document
so that we can have a
look if there's already any.
This is the wrong one.
So sorry.
Okay.
Yes, this is.
Yes.
Okay.
so that we can have a look at
if there's anything relevant
in the questions and in the
meantime our first speaker or
our instructor can set up their screen share.
[name], there is one question.
Someone says that they are
not going through the
installation session because we see
that some people are very new.
That's a good question.
In our installation pages, there
is this minimum required installation,
which is just the fact if
you have a GitHub account, that's enough.
You can do the exercises
only using the GitHub web pages and
so you know you don't need
to worry i would say that
the more heavier part of the installation
which is the setting up
of a conda environment it's more needed
for from next week so for the part two
but for today and for the
next days having a github account
is all you need if you want
to of course not just use
the github website to work with
git because you want to do
vs code or the terminal
then you know if you didn't
have time to do it today you
can do it later in the afternoon and
if you need help we can set
up some ad hoc installations
sessions all right so I guess
[name] you want to set up
your screen share if there's
any other relevant questions
At least by quickly having a
look, I don't see.
Sorry, I have started sharing my screen.
And also, [name], if they have
not done the installation session,
I would recommend that in
the morning they don't try to install things.
Maybe apply for a GitHub account
and just follow because they
don't need the rest of
installation for the rest of the day.
But maybe later today they
could attend to it.
Sounds good, [name]?
That's very good.
And if you register, you
receive this email.
There's a Zoom link there.
So for example, during the break, you can,
if you need help, we are
most likely in that Zoom trying to help you.
All right.
But I see that [name]
started the screen share.
So we can actually start.
So Jana, do you want
to show [name]'s screen?
and now i'm going to
introduce the first day of
code refinery with the topic
of introduction to git version control
and with us today we have
um so we have [name]
who is chief engineer at the
university of oslo is an
expert in high performance
computing working with the nris sigma 2
cluster and with [name] from
Oslo we also have [name],
I hope I pronounced it well,
who is professor at the University of Iceland.
He's an expert of quantum
simulations and HPC as well.
So I'm very happy to have
both of you here today.
It talked enough so the floor is yours
and let's learn some git
virtual control together.
Thanks, [name].
Thank you, [name].
And I would like to, in
advance, I would like to thank
all the effort from the
helpers, our fellow colleagues
from Ford Refinery, the video
directors and everybody for the
hard work, upcoming hard work.
So we can thank them later
on today as well.
So how are you, [name]?
Are you ready for some git?
Yeah, yeah, I'm really excited.
This is the first time I
was doing, but yeah, I'm really into it.
It's nice to do this with you, this lesson.
And [name] quite kindly introduced
us as like experts of HPC, etc.
But today we are going to
come to you as fellow learners.
You know, we use Git and
we would like to share
some experience that might be useful for you.
So we kind of portray
as mutual learning experience rather
than like we teach and you
have to study everything and go for exam.
But it's just try to get something from us.
The first part of the lesson is
that we're going to have
some motivation about Git, why
we sort of selected this technology
and why we are going to talk about it.
After that, [name] would come
with the basic part of the
browsing, and then we'll go for a break.
And then the next part would start.
So I will start with the motivation.
and the human the material
i'm following is already there
in the internet okay yeah yeah
could could you point out where
i can find it so yes so uh you could uh
so the the easiest way to
find out is uh from if you
got an email from with
the shared document there's a
link in this document but that
is only for the
registered participants otherwise if
you really really get lost you
could go to code refinery
And you could go for
workshops or events and upcoming events here.
And then code refinery workshops online.
Okay.
And then I recommend that
we bookmark this so we can come back to this.
So this is the place where I am.
And I'm only going to
show things already here.
I'm not going to show anything extra.
But if I type, if I had to type,
for example, when answering a question
that something extra, we have
to transfer it to the
shared document so people will not get lost.
Okay.
Sounds good.
Sounds good?
Yep.
Yes.
So then let's go for the motivation part.
So, the motivation for using Git
is to keep track of changes.
So, the Indrika was talking
about this time machine.
So, this is a code time machine.
When you develop code, you
can keep snapshots of different stages.
and go back to a past stage
if you need, if you keep track of this.
For this, do you use Git as well, [name]?
And could you briefly mention
how you use it?
Yeah, actually, I mostly use
the Git for writing some codes.
You know, it's like, for suppose,
if I want to add,
contribute to some existing code,
so I just clone the
code, take the repository and
add some features, maybe test it
and then like try to push it back.
So, this is all, like, I
would like to contribute.
Basically, it's, like, and sometimes
if I also want to, like,
keep track of some documents, so
I also use it for keeping track of that.
Okay.
How about you, like...
Yeah.
So I also, when I'm developing a code,
instead of keeping copies of folders,
for example, the code in
May, code in April, code in June, you know,
some sort of my own
version control system, I use Git
so I can keep track and I
can also work with collaborators.
So different people can work
on the same code base without
stepping on each other's toes
and then combine the work.
So we can
We'll talk about all those things.
First thing I will show
is this example repository to
show this snapshot feature.
So the snapshot feature is that Git,
by the way, I start
using version control with
something called subversion.
So Git is not the
only version control system that's around,
but it's the most popular
and most convenient and most integrated one.
So that's why we are talking.
um and now this code is hosted on github
so code refinery we are
not promoting github as as a company
so we are showing github
because it's the most popular
and there's high chance that
you'll interact with github than
any other services in my personal
life i use more gitlab
because we have hosted our own GitLab.
But here we are showing
this because this is the
most likely interface that you
will interact with.
So here, [name], this is a
history of a single file here, run.py.
And if I scroll slowly
downwards to see where it was first created.
So this was created in 2016
by a person called Bast.
And then there is some
identifier for that version.
And then there are some links here.
So first thing I want to
mention here is that this
detail about this file is
in context with everything else around it.
So this is not just this
snapshot of that file, but a
snapshot of the entire code base
The time this was, we call
in Git, we call it the commit was made.
That's interesting.
Yes.
So do you know why, I
mean, there is this cryptic
identifier, FF48 something.
Do you know why it is
like not numbers, like integers,
like one, two, three?
Do you see the advantage of this?
Or do you know why this,
because we'll see this, we'll be
seeing this a lot.
Yeah, I think it's a
unique identifier or something like that.
Yes.
That's a unique generated identifier.
This also comes with the fact
that Git is a distributed
version control system that we'll
mention a little later in this lesson,
which means that if you
modify the same file in
the same repository, you'll get
a unique identifier yourself.
And if I do it, I'll
get a different identifier.
which makes it easier to
combine things later because Git
would know unambiguously how to
do the combination.
And also this identifier would say
that which copy was used
before the identification.
We call it the parent.
So all this information are
put together through an algorithm
and this is a generator.
So it's a generated uniform identifier.
And then if I click that here,
I go to a page.
Where should I click?
So I clicked on the hash.
So I will show you again.
So here, you see this identify here?
Yeah, I see that.
By clicking it, I can
get more details about that snapshot.
Okay.
So as you can see, there are three files.
So this init file, the runpy,
and then there's another file,
which is ugly.py.
So this is a snapshot of
the three changes in one snapshot.
And this is the first
commit in GitSense data, the
first recorded history that this
file was introduced to this repository.
So we get that information by this hash.
So this is the sort of advantage for,
let's say, if I want to,
if I do some change here,
like in 2022, they have done
some change and something broke.
Let's say a test fails.
Okay.
Then what we can do is we
can go to the previous version.
Here it says view code at this point.
So when I click that, it will
not go to the code itself,
but the snapshot of the
repository, all the files.
So if I click that, then I
go to the file at that point,
and I could run this file.
and see not only the
snapshot would include not only that file,
but the other files as well,
if there's a change and we
could run this and see whether test passes.
Would that make sense?
So could you explain, do
you want to explain a little
bit more what I said a little bit?
yeah basically i think uh
you are uh looking at this run.py
and just uh looking at
the timestamps basically it's like
when it is created when
someone modified it a bit and
then when you try to like uh
push it back there are like uh
some checks to be done like a
Yes.
So if something breaks, you can
go back and test it.
And then also you could take
only parts of it.
In the first, the example
I showed that there were
three files here modified.
You could take parts that were like
replace the broken parts, for example.
So basically you can time travel back.
Yes.
Okay.
Yeah, yeah.
So here, today we'll be
working on the browser.
So the web browser, all you
need is a web browser and a GitHub account.
But normally, if you use a
lot of coding, you would not
follow a workflow like this.
But for example, I use
the terminal for this kind of work.
And most people, they
use integrated development environment,
VS Code and et cetera.
But the reason that we are
showing today on the browser is
that on the first day, we
would like everybody to get
on board, even people who has never
seen Git before.
So we minimize the amount
of things like terminal.
If people are very much
used to Windows environments, they
might not be very familiar with the terminal.
So we remove all the extra
stuff that you need to know
in order to understand Git.
And we narrow down only
on the Git concepts.
And we'll talk today, you and me, all day.
And try to understand that concept.
And then in the next
days, the concepts will be transferable.
So this is an example.
So this is how it would
look like on a terminal.
So there's a commit with
a hash, the author, the author's email,
and the date, and a short
log message of what has happened.
So [name], what is the
difference between this one and
the one you showed before, like the
Yes.
So this is the one, as we
see it on the web browser, on the internet.
So this is the, we can
call it the cloud, GitHub cloud.
And you can also do it
on your local computer, on your terminal.
You can download it on
your terminal and then look at it.
So we used, tomorrow we'll
use terms like pool, push,
Um, so this being, this
is like uploading and downloading,
but in Git, when you do this pool push,
the difference between upload
download is that it will
only download or upload the differences.
It will not download, upload
the entire thing back and forth.
Uh, so this terminal, we have pulled it,
you know, you mean, uh, I mean, um,
it, uh, download it to a computer
and we can have a look
at it and, but you'll, you'll
see the same concepts here as well.
Um,
We already talked much about, you know,
why we kind of need track to keep track,
like something is broken, you
know, what version that we were talking about.
We saw that there's a timestamp
and we saw that there's a unique identifier.
We can go back and check
and there's some versioning, you
know, we could unambiguously
refer to something, you know,
this is the version that
worked without, you know, sending
a folder, for example.
And then when there's especially a bug,
like something is broken, you
can find out where it was broken.
You know, when it was
broken, what broke it?
And then you could...
go to the, go to the
point where it was last worked
and then figure out more things.
Um, yes.
Uh, and also there is this, um, I mean,
if you look, if you, this
is about, you know, somebody,
um, wrote a thesis, but I had to, um,
give an advanced warning that,
you know, the Git word works with simple text.
Uh, do, can you explain
what simple text is?
It's maybe mostly like text
files like TXT or like this
kind of extensions, or you can
also use some LaTeX.
Yeah.
And may not be like, how about DocX?
Does it work like DocX or PPT?
No.
So the Git works best when
what you see and what your
computer sees is the same.
For example, if you have a docs file,
LibreOffice or Microsoft or Google Doc
or whatever, when you bold
the text, for example, there's
a lot of metadata behind.
So the actual text, what you
see and what's on the
computer is very different.
So even if you change one
text or if you make a text
bold, it will change a lot.
So it's difficult to track changes.
So if you have a thesis, for example,
so this means that it's not a PDF
or a Word document or a
kind of document format with a
lot of metadata, but it's plain text.
For example, the document we see here,
the markdown document, it's easy
to version control this.
You can version control this document.
Okay.
Is there any limit on how
many files I can share?
Yeah, so there could be some
limits in the server side, but
Git, it works, it's not for very large files.
It's for like code, computer code.
But if you learn Git, then
you can use other technology
which uses Git terminology and
Git techniques to version control.
For example, if you are
in machine learning, for example,
you might use this hugging face.
Yeah.
They have like big models.
And now the latest version
of the hugging face use
something similar to Git.
It's like XGit or something.
So you can use the Git,
add Git, all the commands we
use, but with big data.
So conceptually, it's the same.
But this Git we are
talking today is focused on
plain text, smaller files, larger
files are okay.
But for smaller plain text,
you'll keep repositories.
Not for data.
Okay.
I mean, data in the sense
there could be like smaller data files.
That's something different.
But let's say terabytes of
data is not version control in this way.
But for that, you have
Git LFS, for example, Git large file.
And then the version that
the hugging phase is using.
And there are other technologies.
But if you know the concepts
of Git, you can also use those setups.
Okay.
And then another thing, [name], is
that I said like
collaborative virtual control.
Let's say there is code.
There is, let's say, a web interface.
Here we are showing with a cartoon with,
we want to try out a
sunglass and a hat, and we
want to decide which one to use.
Let's say you are implementing
the sunglass part of it,
and I'm implementing the hat part of it.
And we can independently,
without stepping on each other's toe,
we can do a test and we
can check, and then we can
collaborate to see what's good.
And then we can combine at the end.
without affecting the main
line of development so um the the code
that works will remain and
users will use it while that's
happening we can have our own
uh i wouldn't call it like
a full copies but but the
Because when you create a
branch, you don't actually
make multiple copies.
You just have some pointers to this.
Then you can experiment.
And then at the end, we can combine.
Or maybe we can throw away
the hat and then keep the sunglass.
We call this merging.
So we can come together at
some point to make a consensus
and then combine the code.
Okay.
Yeah, we will talk more about this later.
Do you have anything more
to mention about this, Iman?
No, nothing much.
So then we have the graph
that I can show you a little bit.
So how the development works.
I hope the screen is good enough.
If not, colleagues, please give me a shout.
So different people have made
branches and they did some development.
And the arrow pointing to
the black one means that
They have brought in the
changes to the main branch.
So the main branch would have that change.
So you can branch out and
branch in and merge.
So this is like adding the sunglasses.
Yes.
Correct.
So this will be like the green.
If they check the sunglass, it's good.
Now the main code has
that sunglass feature.
Okay.
And also the reproducibility,
which means that, let's say,
if you publish a paper today
with a certain code that works
with a certain set of data,
and then you can, in the
paper, you can mention that I use this version.
So after the paper is published, two
or three years in the future,
you did some modifications and
it's not the same thing, then
you don't have to worry about
looking for what worked.
You can point out, you
know, our paper talks about this version.
Here also we have an
example that shows something called git blame.
So the blame is not
necessarily to blame somebody
for something they did.
Savit, could you zoom in?
Yes, yes.
Let me make it a little bigger.
Would that be okay?
Yeah, this is good.
Yeah.
So no need to read the fine text here.
What I want to show is
that each line is annotated with
who did what when.
So we can get help from
that person, why you did that
change, and we can get help
from that person to get more details.
So Git records all this line by line.
So another thing is that Git
Actually, it version code was
like lines, not like text by text.
So you could mention which
line was modified by whom and when.
Apart from that, you could mention, like
if you want to send a part
of a code to somebody else,
you could, I'll close this additional windows.
You could send a link.
So this permanent link.
do you use permanent links uh
can't i send the file itself like uh
Yes.
I mean, that's a very good point.
You could send the file, then
you have to write a lot
of text about, you know, you
have to look, I'm sending this
file and I'm referring to line 40 to 44.
But if you send a link
like this, it highlights and
it shows unambiguously, this is
what I'm talking about.
They can copy and this code
is in a way that, you know, let's say
if you type this in an
email, for example, it might not be aligned.
You know, especially if like
Python script, for example, you
might not be able to
make it work sometimes.
And also email, some email,
like firewalls, for example, might block code.
All this could be avoided by this.
The way to generate a link is
that you go to the place where the code is,
you click that, and you
click this, the three dots, and
you can get a permanent link.
Okay.
If you want multiple lines,
you can click this.
Hold that shift key on the keyboard.
Okay.
And then you can get a
range for a permanent link.
Nice.
Right.
Typically, we take snapshots
of software scripts, as we
mentioned, not complicated metadata
included documents, even images.
You could make versions of images,
but the Git works best when
the text is plain text.
We have some discussion here.
Our learners are also welcome
to contribute in the shared document.
um so we see that there
are somebody who's trying to
version control i mean invent
a new version control system um
create a folder with the specific date
and make a copy do some modifications
and create another folder yeah
what is the issue with this
so i think they are also
doing the time stamping right
here like they're keeping track of the files it
Yes, but I mean, let's say
if they want to combine 2020, some file
and 2023, some file, that will
not be very obvious how to do it.
And also like maybe they
had to uncompress it, look for
the file, and there's no
metadata associated with it.
Like line by line annotation,
like who did what was changed.
That kind of things.
And it's not easy to go and, I mean,
the timestamp is there, but
maybe the 2024 February folder
has some file that was changed on February,
the last day on maybe some
files on March 1st, but all
these things are in the February folder.
We don't want to keep that
track in this way.
You could also mention more
details in the shared documents if you wish.
And also we would like to
point out some issues with
version control as well.
You need to learn some things
like Git, the things we teach you.
But if you can manage the
first part of Code Refinery,
I think you're more than
equipped to start using Git.
Okay.
So that's something you get
from this class is that you
can learn more later on as you needed.
But today we'll get started.
Sometimes collaborators, they don't
like to use version control.
Personally, I have never encountered it.
There was instances where there
was some resistance, but at the
end, when we see the benefits,
they start using it.
Even if they don't use it,
we could use version control.
And then, for example, for
this repository that we are talking about,
collaborator could download a
compressed file if they wish but
we can still use you know
this could be like kind
of one-way um contribution but
you know it's possible to share it
if somebody don't want to use
gift at all okay um so you know the the
when i move windows is it
too fast for the streaming or
is it okay all right so it
seems okay for me like okay
let's see the document
Then by Git, not something
else, it's easy to use.
As we slightly mentioned,
it's very popular.
You might encounter it at some point.
And also if you learn Git,
you can use GitLab, Bitbucket,
and GitHub interchangeably.
If the code is in Git,
you can transfer the Git.
But the issues and other
additional things might not be transferable.
But if you start using any
of this, it's easier to
move to another platform.
That's all I want to
introduce during motivation, [name].
I'll just have a look
at the shared document to
see whether there's any interesting questions.
Until you set up your
screen and inform [name] that
you're going to share it.
OK.
Yeah, this is about in general.
Yeah, the conda environments and all,
please do that after the
workshop, today's workshop, so then
you can be prepared.
Okay, I think [name] managed
to make it bigger without me making it,
but please [name] and [name]
and [name], please inform us if
we had to do something.
How the change are marked?
There are some color code.
Yeah, I think it's all covered.
Yeah, so they ask about the size.
Our collaborators have mentioned
there's some size or limitations,
but if you learn how to
use Git, you can use the
same commands to control it.
Yes.
I'm switching the size to
be correct, but yeah, I...
cannot select which uh screen
share is showing so it was uh him
and screenshot now it's zapris
okay maybe in any case go
ahead and yeah can you zoom in
a bit more i don't see
my screen on the streaming at
least is it now human only yes okay
okay hey man can you go
through the things because it's
already shared um yeah question nine
for example yeah i will go
through i will just need to
change a few things but give me
a second so can you see the
okay i can see the edit mode
of your uh yeah now i can see the yeah
Yeah, so the question nine, for example,
so the way I did goes
on GitHub is maybe GitHub
related, but also GitLab, there is
a way to do it.
Please do zoom.
Okay, the zoom in, we have
to fix a little bit.
Sorry for that inconvenience.
If the text was too small, we will fix it.
I think, [name], you could
start with your part already.
And [name], I'm going to
stop sharing my screen now.
so can you see my screen or
like i see your share document
okay it's like uh let me top
the share and yeah give me a second
So until [name] set up that screen,
so the next lesson would be
about some more basics and we
will start with the browsing part
that also you could, you only
need the GitHub to do that.
Yes, I can still see
your shared document, [name].
Okay.
And actually I can't see the zoom controls.
Yes.
Okay.
We are currently showing
the shared document.
Okay.
Nobody's currently sharing the screen.
Yeah.
Okay.
Now I find it.
Let me share that.
All right.
So can you see it?
I'm switching over to your screen share.
Okay.
That's good.
Is it better?
Just a moment.
Let's try again.
And yes, now it looks good.
Let me zoom in a bit.
Okay.
Yep.
Yes.
so yeah we can currently i
am in this uh the main page of the workshop
so now uh i will talk
about the browsing which you can
access in the day one okay
so basically what we are going
to do today is like uh we
are going to look at an existing repository
basically, and then we try
to understand how the repository is built.
And then later we try
to fork the repository, which means
that we are taking a copy
of the repository and then try
to modify and do some changes.
So that's what we are going to do now.
So basically, it's like different
ways of doing it.
Today, we will mostly focus on the GitHub,
but you can also use your
favorite like a VS Code or
command line and then try to do it.
So in the day one, we
will mostly focus on GitHub.
In the coming days, we will
talk about the rest of the things.
So what I'm going to do
is I'm going to take this repository,
which was created for this workshop,
which is CR workshop exercises,
and you can actually access
this using the links here.
So the first link is for
participants and the second link is
for uh the people for the instructors
which is [name] and me so basically
what you're going to do now
is like uh you try to open
this link in a new tab and
then we will go through it okay so
so the thing with these two
links him on is the difference
is that the one would people
see it in the camera on
the during the recording so we
have created two links so the
we we can avoid showing
other people's usernames so
when you use it use the
recipe book not the recipe
book dash record recorded so only
use this one okay the one the first one
so now i'm going to open
the link so i'm opening the link
in a new tab so i will slightly zoom in so yeah
So basically, it's like this
is the repository.
And is the font enough, [name]?
Yeah, I think it's good enough, yes.
OK, OK, yeah.
So yeah, basically, this is the repository,
which is you can see the
name of the repository, which
is recipe book recorded.
and then it is under
this organization cr-workshop-exercises, okay?
So basically what we are going
to do today is we are
going to first navigate what is there,
what is here, and then we
are going to basically take a
copy of this repository and
do some changes, okay?
So in order to do
the fork, basically, there should
be a fork icon.
Yes.
If you slightly zoom in, you
can see the fork icon here.
So what is a fork?
Why do we need that, [name]?
Okay, basically, it's like,
so this repository belongs to someone else.
And basically, if you want
to do some changes, okay, it's
better to make a copy of
the documents, like all the files,
and then you can modify the
changes in your local repository
in your local files.
Okay.
And basically, that's what we do.
in while doing the forking
okay copy uh copy for yourself
in the cloud itself so maybe
you don't have access to
modify these files because this
is somebody else's repository but
if you are allowed to copy
it you can make a copy and
do things by yourself today
today that's what you want to
sort of practice on your own yeah
so now if you click on this fork
then it will open this create
a new fork window.
Basically here, it's like we
write some name.
So it is automatically predefined,
which is recipe book, recipe
dash book dash recorded.
Here you can write some optional.
Okay, we will use it for teaching.
Okay, basically so.
And then when you click on
this, I will uncheck this box,
copy the main branch only, and
then try to create the fork.
So if you press the screen.
What does that mean?
What happens if you clicked it?
Basically, it will copy all
the files, including other
people's branches also.
Right now, we just want to
copy only the main branch.
But then we should uncheck it, isn't it?
yeah sorry yeah we should
check this yeah but i think it's it's good
that we copy everybody else's
branches then they can see that branch
and everything yeah because i
also did some changes so in
case if yeah go ahead but
but let's see okay either way is
fine so it will take a time like i'm
So yeah, basically, yes.
Now I forked this branch.
So what you can see is like, so this,
I forked from this CR
workshop exercises, the one highlighted here.
This is what we call upstream.
This is where we actually
forked the repository.
Now, if you see the link
above, it should be your user account.
Basically, it's your username
for the GitHub.
That is what you should
be following for the next of the
for the today's lectures okay
and so now we will go
back to the main window and
then we will mostly like do
some exercises okay so uh now
uh [name] is this the time for
like uh should we take a break
now or should we do the exercises
So what we do is, Sehman,
now we break for 10 minutes.
Okay.
And then when we come back,
we can discuss the exercise.
Because when we say break,
we expect people to walk around
a little bit and have a break,
not look at the exercise.
Okay.
So [name] and [name], we're going
to have a break now.
If you could share the
shared document with 10 minutes break.
And we'll come back in
another 10 minutes according to the time zone.
Are you ready, [name]?
Sorry, [name]?
Let's go on a break.
All right.
Bye.
Yes.
Bye for now.
Hi, welcome back from the break.
I hope you had you
just stretched your legs.
And so you can hear me
right like all of you.
Yeah, OK, great.
So what we're going to do
now is like this exercise.
So basically it's like you just
took a copy like a fork
of the repository which was shown above.
OK, so using this link.
Now, what you're going to do
is go to that link and do these exercises.
There are eight exercise questions.
First, you try to look
into each question and there
are some hints here and how to do that.
For suppose in the first one,
you try to look at the commit history.
To look at the commit history,
Basically, what you're going to
do is here is a small icon,
which is like, can you see the icon?
Maybe a little.
The circle.
It may be.
The circle, if you go to this repository,
which you just forked, you
should see here your username and
then on the URL.
Here, when you zoom in, you
can see a small circle, like a timestamp.
When you click on it,
basically what you can see is
some commits made earlier.
Basically, you have to go
through this commit history and
try to see what has been done.
and then later like uh you
will also try to find another
way of looking at it like which
is uh you can use this insights
on the on this main page okay
and then try to see what
is happening in this ins when
you click on insights and when
you click on the network
within that insights okay
so then also try to find
out when the recipe was last modified
so what you're going to see
is like this is a like
basically a recipe book for food
like cooking so you are going
to find like some food recipes okay it's like
and you try to find take one recipe
for suppose a salad or something
and then see like when
the this repository was modified
or when the file was the
recipe not not like python or c code
Basically, it's like when you
look at this Git page.
Here you can see there
are some desserts, pasta, salad, side soups.
Let's first suppose we look at salads.
Here there are different salads
in this file.
So first, suppose this is a Andhra salad.
And basically, this is from my home place.
And you can find what this recipe is about.
If you want to cook something,
then you can actually look into this recipe.
So basically, it's like each
one has different recipes in this codebook.
One reason that it is a
codebook, like not a programming
language is that we want to
be just focusing on the Git
concept itself and the GitHub
and the interface.
So even people don't know, understand,
if you're not working with
Python, you still understand the concept.
So that's why it's abstracted
into a cooking recipe instead of like code.
But in real life, you
will be interacting with code when you do this.
Nice.
So yeah, let's go back to the exercise.
So then you will also
find this guacamole recipe, okay,
which is under the sides.
So basically, you try to
like look into these exercises and
try to do these exercises
following on the repository, which
you just made a copy of
it, or which is forking it.
Okay.
Yeah, that's very important.
You know, look at your copy.
yeah one one one one that
says you know without the recorded
uh prefix uh yeah it should be
like uh here is your it
should be your username the
one highlighted your repository will
be like this one https
colon slash slash github.com
slash your username slash recipe
dash book and yeah please go
uh take a look into this one
and try to do the exercises
Yes.
So now what we're going to
do is we're going to break now.
I mean, break means that we will not talk.
And we'll give you 25 minutes.
And [name] will share the
shared document now.
And we give you 25 minutes.
Is that enough for him on?
Yeah, I think 25 minutes is good.
And I think they also
have local instructors, like basically
at each hosting site.
Now we expect you to
go through this exercise and do that.
And if you have any
questions, use the shared document
to inform us, you know, any issues
that you have or any
discussions that you want to participate in.
And also maybe we can place
a poll in the...
share document to see if
you are finished give us some notice
that so we don't have to wait
if you're already finished and
i would recommend him on that
maybe up to six is enough so
six is the number six okay
yeah sixth question up to go
out to six question and the
seven and eight is bonus for
you yeah and we'll see within
the first 25 minutes try to go up to six okay
Okay, Anu, now we're going
to share the shared document
and indicate that 25 minutes of exercise time.
And then we come back
and Haman will explain the answers.
Is that a good plan, Haman?
Yeah, it sounds good.
hi welcome back so i hope
you guys were doing the exercises i see
that about 20 people finished
the exercise so now i will
just quickly go through the
solutions okay so let's look at the first uh
exercise which is like browsing
the commit history.
Now I will switch the tab.
Basically, if I go to the
code to the main page, so for
you it is the user.
If you click on this time circle here,
It will then go to this
page where you can see like
the commits, all the commits
which were made from all the people.
So this one is the commits
which I made yesterday and
[name] made few commits also.
And then we have also some
commits from the last year.
and what you can see here
is like each commit has a
some specific like a is a name like
for suppose restoring the tests
and when it is committed and
there is a unique id like
as a subrim mentioned in the
motivation for each commit you
make you will have a one
id associated to it okay
so that you can easily revert back
or you can look into uh
what has been in the commit okay so
if you click on that uh
hash code you can see this one okay
so these are the green ones
are the changes which are made
and the minus ones are some
like the previous ones so that
is about uh basically so the green one
Now let's go to the next
question, which is about the network graph.
I will again go back to the main code page.
This is the main page which you forked.
So far we looked at the
commits which were changed linearly.
Now, if you basically click
these three dots, like basically
for me, since I am zooming
in, so it is here for me in this insights.
If you click on this insights,
you will you can then see all these things.
So now I'm going to
click this network here.
When you click on the network,
what you can see is here
is the history of the commits.
I will just drag it.
Here is these are the
commits which we made, [name] and me.
The main black line is
the main repository when we took the branch.
You can see the timestamp
and other things, what each commit we did.
With this, you get a big overview of
what has been done, like
when you forked the branch and
then when you started committing it back.
These are the big overlook of the commits.
Each dot is a commit.
For suppose here, you are
just forking that part.
Next, let's look at the next question.
How can you find out when
a recipe was last modified?
So let's go back to the repository.
And let's go to the main page.
So let's say let's pick up some recipe,
say for suppose salads and
let's make a mixed salad.
So here basically it's like
here is the recipe and you
can look at the history.
Oh, maybe, yeah, you can
look, you can click on the code.
So the question was, um, how can,
if I read last modified, so I see that,
uh, on the top, um, like
near the clock, it says it
was modified last year.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, and then, okay, that is the question.
So now it's like to see
when is it last modified.
Here again, when you open the file,
you can see this again,
this circle, the time circle.
And if you click on this circle,
which shows you all the
history of the commits of this file.
Okay.
So these are the commits,
which you can see, like it
was created in March 5th, and
there are some fixes to this file.
okay so that is this uh
the third question and now let's go back
and see what is the next question
so the next question is
how many changes did the
coca-cola recipe receive so you
can find this coca-cola recipe under sites
and then try to click on
some of the comments to see
what changed okay let's do that
so now i'm going back i
can read the question for him so
you can stay in the github
okay yeah that would be great
okay now i will go back yeah okay
so let's uh look at the
salads it's in the salads right go come on
how many changes the goku molly
is i think the side i think
it's a side sites and actually
if you don't know where to find
it there is a search button here
and you can use the search
button yeah with this zooming in
i don't it's on the top the
So here you can.
I'm sorry here go to file.
Here you can look for a guacamole.
So let me, I think I did it fast.
If you click, if you look
here, you can find go to file.
And basically what you can do is like,
you can, if you know the
file name, you can type here
and you can click find the file.
Okay.
It only works for the file names.
so here is the guacamole recipe okay
and then now the question is like
how many how many how many changes okay
so now let's again look
at the history using this time stamp circle
and so how many are there actually
so one two three four five
so there are five changes five
commits okay yes so the number
five is which recipe includes
the ingredient salt salt
salt okay so now i will
again go back to the main one code now
since we already looked in
terms of searching for the file okay
but we can't know we don't know
whether the salt is in within
the file okay so what we are
going to do is like we
are using this search button which
you can see on the top right
top right and you can search
here salt okay so if you are using yeah
and then press enter then it
will oh okay but the first
time when you search for the
files i mean content of a
file it's indexed a little bit
so you could also search on
the original repo if you want yes
yeah i will do that too
Let me go there.
So this is the original repo.
Yeah.
This is the original repo.
Okay.
So basically now what I'm going
to do is like I'm searching here.
So now you can see wherever
the salt is mentioned, you can
see all the files.
So for suppose it is in
the salts backslash mixit.md, and
then it is also in the deserts.
And then it is also in the guacamole
and in this Andhra salad
and the mushroom soup, pumpkin
pipe, and then Andhra mango
pickle and vegetarian lasagna.
Okay.
So basically it's like if
you want to search for this
salt, you use this search button,
which was on the top.
Okay.
Now I will go back to the,
I can read the, I can read the question.
The sixth one is that
in the Gokumala recipe, find
out who modified each line last and when.
Okay.
So let's go to the
Gokumala recipe, which is in the sites.
So the question is who modified last?
Yes.
So it's actually the blame they're asking.
Yeah, OK, yeah.
So to see, you can click on the file, OK?
And when you click on the
file, you should see, where is this blame?
Yeah, OK.
I need to zoom a bit.
Yeah, so another way to do
that is, [name], is that if you
go back to the file.
Yeah.
So that is what the
answer for the recommended answer
is that you go back to the
file and click on blame, yes.
Yes, yes.
So yeah, I went back to the file.
OK, and let me do it again.
So here is the file.
You click on this file.
Then you can see here, right
now you are in the preview mode,
so you need to now go to the blame.
When you click on the blame,
you can see when the file was modified
and you can see who added
this line or who changed this
line by clicking on this blame.
This is the three rectangles.
So when you click on it,
you can see who has changed this.
So the question number seven
is more about, you know, are
we allowed to use it?
It's talking about some license.
Okay.
So it would be in the report.
Do you have anything to
mention about license?
So here, yeah, it's like
they basically when I clone the
repo, there is a license
associated to it, which is
like a creative common license 1.0.
so it's like either you can
see on the main page like with this license
or else what is more nice is like
when you click on this
license basically you can look
see all this what are the permissions
and how can you use
this permissions okay so that's
very later on in this course
so yeah no more but this
this basically tells you what
you are allowed to do and
what you are not allowed yeah
So what kind of license
do you use normally?
It's like a Creative Commons.
Creative Commons or MIT for code.
So GNU public license.
Mostly open source copyright.
Yeah, because now if the
funding agencies are now pushing
towards the fair, like sharing the code fair.
So it's important to have a license.
Yeah, it's really important.
Yeah.
Okay, so the last question,
Iman, is that it's in the main repository.
Is there any pull requests?
Okay, yeah.
Later on, but the pull
request in general is that what I did was,
Iman, is that I did some
modification and I send it upstream.
Upstream is the place where I copied.
Downstream is my local copy.
And I made some changes.
I asked from the authors, would
you like to incorporate it?
Okay.
Basically, I'm now at the upstream,
which is where I started
forking my repository, which is
like a CR workshop exercises.
Then this is the main page
and you can see these icons,
issues and pull requests.
Now the question is about the pull request.
When you click this pull request,
what you can see is like,
are there any open issues?
[name], you will be talking
about it later, right?
Yeah, we can just talk about it now.
If you click on that salad
recipe, so that is a new change I propose.
Would you like to incorporate it?
Yeah.
If you see that the commits are there,
what changed, you could also
click and see what file was changed.
and what the commits were.
And then as the owner of the repo
or some of the review, we
call it the review process, which means
that you go through the
code and see whether it's
appropriate to be incorporated into
the main line of development.
And then you could do
something called merge to...
make it um combined to the
main branch yeah yeah i would
also like to mention a little
bit about the the pull request
before i send the request i
opened an issue him on so if
you click on the issue so there
is a yeah this is what
right one working awaiting approval
this is what you are waiting
for yes but uh yeah so where
should i go uh issues issues okay yeah
So before I send the request,
I made an issue.
Just like anyone has a good salad.
So somebody asking, you know, salad.
And then before I send the change
or start working on it, I
opened an issue and said, you
know, I'm going to send a salad recipe.
So everybody else would know
that somebody is working on something.
So we don't have to, you
know, do the same thing.
So after that, in the
next episode, we'll talk about,
you know, in the issue, it
could be, we could record.
what happened and it also
tells the public that somebody is
working on it so others could help
or not to do the same
thing in parallel and also
what has somebody done up to
now okay and what is this sub issue
That is to create another issue.
So if you could create another issue,
but that's, we're not going
to talk today, but you could
create like a related issue.
Let's say something related to
this salad recipe, but somebody
wants to work on, I don't
know, maybe a topping, for example.
Okay.
So, yeah.
Yes, so those are the questions, [name].
Then now what I will do is
I will share the shared document
to see whether there are
any interesting questions.
Is that okay?
Okay, yeah.
But for everyone, you can
also get the solutions in the main page.
So if you browse down, you
also can see the solutions.
Yes.
Over to [name].
Yeah, so now I'm going to
share the shared document from
my screen share now.
Is this my screen, Janu?
It's collaborative notes, I see.
So currently we are showing
the notes, and Herman's screen
is still being shared.
Can you stop?
Yeah, I will stop the share.
Once again.
So in this one question is
that there was some configuration,
for example, how to do
this on Visual Studio Code and...
I stopped the share.
Yeah.
So those questions, those are
needed for the rest of the day.
And at the end of the day,
I will show some Git
configurations, some things you
needed for later on that you could go and...
make sure those are working
before the rest of the course.
And the other thing is, [name], is
that some people have
mentioned about GitHub, I mean,
Google Drive, for example, Google
Docs, you could have some versions.
And even in like a
Microsoft ecosystem, you have
the Microsoft Word and also
the LibreOffice in the free
version, open source versions that
you have something called track changes.
So those also have some sort
of a version controlling.
But for the code, it's
not that convenient to combine things
and do a lot of things,
but there is some version control.
But if you try to version
control a Word document on
Git, I don't recommend it.
It's not going to work well.
Okay.
So then it's a plain
text is the recommended one.
Is there anything else, [name],
you see that here that we should mention?
Yeah, that's, I'm trying to see this.
What is
My search for salt result
in this repository's code being
indexed right now.
Yeah.
So the indexing is that people
who know about databases, they know
that when you want to
search some things, you have
to get the keywords and create
some sort of index.
So that takes a little bit of time.
It will take about two
or three minutes maximum.
And then you can search the GitHub.
So that's a normal thing.
Yeah.
We are, I'm ready to go
to your screen share separate.
Okay, go ahead.
All right.
Yeah, good.
And anything else, Ayman, that
you want to mention before we move on?
No, nothing.
It's mostly they were asking
about the license, but yeah,
the helpers were answering them.
Okay.
So the license is important
to choose like even before
you commit your first piece
of code, it's better that you
create a license and in
the upcoming, between the same
course upcoming lessons, we'll talk
a little bit about licensing.
So now what we do is,
Iman, that I will introduce the
next lesson a little bit before
we go to a break, which is the longer break.
okay um so we have done
now the browsing part and
then the committing part so
what does committing means uh to
you um hey man and there
is this interchangeable word which
is used uh commit and record
a little bit in this lessons
do you have any comment about
this uh it's like uh basically
I create some changes and I want to like,
uh, basically right now we
created some salads, right?
Like a guacamole salad and
trying to add new salads.
And now I want to push
this to the upstream.
So this is what, uh, I
mean, uh, I think the commit means,
or I want to record these changes.
Is that right?
Um, that's kind of right.
But the technical word for that
is we call it push.
Yeah.
So the commit in Git and
the recording is interchangeably used.
In the Git technology, if you
sort of dig a little bit, I
don't want to kind of go
deep into technical details, but
when we look at the terminal,
you will see there's something
called a .git folder, which tracks
all of these snapshots.
There's a place where the
snapshots are kept.
So it's a timestamp.
Yeah, with the timestamp and
everything and also the metadata,
it's kept somewhere.
Even in the cloud, there
is .git folder where it's like
a database of all these changes.
So the changes I kept in a way as diffs.
Diff is like a difference
between what was last and what was now.
So it doesn't keep copies of each snapshot,
but instead it keeps the
difference between the parent.
So in this sense, in
the browser, it's difficult to show this.
So the Git works in a two-step process.
You have to add and
commit, which means that you
have to suggest that you're
going to add something and then
permanent make it permanent so
as soon as you suggest to git
that you know i want
version control this it's actually
get recorded but in a subsequent
step it also incorporates the
metadata like timestamp and everything
and then it creates a
message log message and it make
it permanent so in this sense in this
lesson, what we're going to
talk about is how to make
a change permanently recorded in
a snapshot on your local copy.
Then we come to what you
said later on tomorrow, you
make permanent in your copy, and
then you send that change
upstream, which is the place you
copied it from to incorporate.
We call that the push.
So those are the two
concepts that we're going to talk about.
But now we're going to talk
about only on the local copy
and then how to make that
Here we have a
different terminology background that
we are going to talk about.
Repository is where all these
files are all together.
And commit is, we know
that that's a snapshot, which is
the status of that, the set
of files with some metadata.
And when you have a
snapshot entire project in time,
like that we also had a look.
and a branch, we had
to try different things.
Then you could combine them later on.
And then this one, I would
like to hold on for a
moment about the reference to
like a sticky note, because
we need some context to understand that.
And then we have tags,
which are like sticky notes that
you stick to someplace, but it doesn't move.
A commit is also like that, but it moves.
So in this sense, in
order to understand all this, the best way,
[name], is that I can show us
how to do it a little bit.
Okay.
We will not talk about the exercise now.
I mean, exercise we will
talk about after the lunch.
But we will get some
context within the next four
or five minutes that what we need.
So if you remember that the...
the browsing lesson you used a repository.
Yes.
Which is called the recorded version.
So, in that recorded version I
am going to right click and
open it in another tab.
And for the users, they go to their own.
So right now it is only the demo, right?
Yes.
So I'm going to show some concepts here,
but describing the text, but
I'm going to show it on the GitHub itself.
Here, as you see that
there are three defaults, but
don't fork from this because if
you fork it, people will see
your username in the video.
So please try to use
the version without the recorder,
but the same, you could do the same things.
So if you see the fork here,
I see that I have a fork here.
So the idea is to add
something in this, some contribution
that I have to make.
So in order to make
the contribution, the idea is
that I will create a branch,
as that sunglass branch and the hat branch.
Then I could mention that my
name to be more explanatory,
new recipe, because I'm not
sure what I'm going to suggest yet.
Then when you type something, a
name of a branch, if it
is not already there, it will
suggest to create it.
So if somebody asks you to
create a branch and if you're
working on the web browser itself, you see
that this is a recipe branch
and you also have the main
branch, but now you see the
branch that I created.
So in that branch, what I could do is
if I want to contribute something,
for example, I don't know,
a soup, for example, I'll go
to that place and then I could
you know, create a file.
So when, what we do after lunch is
that we will see how to,
you know, I created a branch now,
so you could also, you know,
try to create now, but you
know, now we'll have a break very soon.
After that, I will show how
to make a contribution onto the
local copy of your copy.
As you can see from the top here, [name],
I'm working on my copy, the
[name]-recipes, not on the main,
the place I copied.
And then I will try to
make my changes there.
Now what we'll do is that,
now we'll break for the lunch now.
And those things I mentioned,
I will show them again.
So we will come back to this.
So the line is one hour.
And then we will indicate that time,
you know, we are to convert
it according to your time.
Local time.
Local time, yes.
And it's very important that
you come back at one.
I would say bye for now
and we'll see after lunch.
Hello, welcome back.
Did you have a good lunch break, [name]?
Yeah, yeah, I had a nice lunch.
How about you?
Yes, I had a smaller lunch.
I don't want to fall asleep while teaching.
That wouldn't be nice, isn't it?
Yes, yes.
So before we start, [name],
there's this question about
whether the learners need to
keep the solutions.
So the solutions are needed if
they want a certificate.
So the certificate must probably
be able to be converted
into one European credit.
And the details are here in
this link for question 39.
And you can go through them
and then ask back if that's not clear enough.
Okay.
Is there anything, any other
question that we need to
check before we proceed on?
I think this is the key
question apart from this because now
since we are moving to exercise two,
so the students have to
submit the exercise to like in
order to get the one ECTS.
But apart from that, nothing
else is seems important.
Uh, so then we move to the next lesson,
uh, the committing, if you remember
before the lunch break, I went to the,
I went to the committee lesson
and I just show you a little
bit and I went and create a fork.
So the fork would be ready,
you know, just in case if it takes time.
Um, and then, um, in this
lesson, um, what we did was that, um, um,
to another local copy of the copy
that we made from the forking exercise
that we were trying to
contribute something from our side, right?
And then what we did was that I clicked,
I went to the recipe and make sure
that it's your, the recipe of your,
I mean, the copy of
the repository, that's what we
call the fork, that you are here.
And then I went, I clicked
on this place where it says
main, the branch, you know,
the branch symbol and the main.
And I went there and I typed
a name of a branch.
so that branch was not there
so gitlab said you know do
you want to create that so i created that branch
Now I switch to that branch.
So when you're creating a
branch, this will be more important during the,
when we go on the terminal
on the Visual Studio or any other IDE as well.
Just creating the branch is not enough.
You have to switch to that.
Otherwise, you will be creating
a branch, but you will be
working on the main branch.
So you have to do the switching first.
So here you have switched.
What was that?
How do you do that?
How do you do the switching?
Yeah, switching means I went
there and I selected that branch.
So now I'm here.
If I select main, now I'm
in the main branch.
Although I had created a
branch for myself, I'm still
in the main branch.
So I had to explicitly switch to that.
So then I need to
contribute something to the recipe.
Let me see if there's anything already.
available for me to paste in.
So then,
There's another thing that
important thing about this is
that there's a small check when
you submit a recipe.
So a check means that usually
if it's a code, you have
to make sure some basic tests
are passed before you integrate
into the main line of development.
So excuse me a little bit.
I'm going to show something
further down the page.
So I'm going to scroll down.
and show you that there
are basic things you need.
So there should be a title
for the name of the recipe,
and then you should have
some ingredients and instructions.
So these things are needed.
If this is missing, the test would fail.
It would say that you
don't have instructions.
So it has to be in
the same spellings, for example.
So to make sure that
my first commit doesn't fail, I'm
going to copy this and I'm
slowly going to move up again
And then I'm going back to
the other tab, which is the copy
of the, or the fork.
And then I want to create
like a contribute something.
So here I'm going to contribute a soup.
So I'm going to that folder.
So we have a mushroom soup already.
So again, I'm making sure that
I'm in the correct repository here.
So here it says that I
have copied from the place that
we forked from, but I had to
make sure that I'm in my place.
And then what I will do
is that I would click on this.
If you see this button, it says add file.
Do you see this, [name]?
Yeah, I see that.
Yeah.
So then I would say create a file.
So in the creator file place, I'm going to,
you know, some recipe for the
sake of like showing the Git,
you know, not to show my recipe skills.
I'm going to copy something from the web.
So that's a simple and creamy carrot soup.
Right.
So get this characters
correct, period, simple and,
you know, correct.
So should I increase the font
a little bit, maybe?
Yeah, I think it's better to increase.
Yeah.
How is it now?
Yeah, it's good.
Yes.
So then I need the ingredients.
I'm going to cheat a little bit.
So I'm going to copy the ingredients now.
Right.
So they are this this ingredients.
And then the instructions.
Uh, instructions also, I'm going
to copy it.
Yeah.
So this is the content of my, um, file.
So I'm going to go
size, write something like, um, tasty soup.
then you need a file name here
so the file name I would say
that this is a markdown file
so that is the document I'm going
to it could be a text file for example
but as we discussed before the
git we don't version control
like you know complex document
types like pdfs and docs and all
I'm going to call it MD
to indicate that it's a markdown.
When you indicate that the file type,
for example, Python, C, Git
actually try to interpret that file
and you can actually see the
preview, how it looks like.
For example, if I show you
this hash here and these two hashes,
which means a subheading and
a heading, GitHub figured out it's a
um heading and it make
the heading bigger like this um
and then you can see the
preview so this magic happened
because i named the file it
used the file extension so then uh
what we do is i will go
here i'll click on this commit
button you see this green
commit button here yeah i will i
will do the so the commit is
to i'm going to make that permanent
and then you see that that
new branch i created before the
break i created this branch so
it's going to land on this
not on the new branch um sap
i'll type a small message and
this is this will be the
message on the if you see
that in the in the hash there
was a small like a short
message short log message so this is
what going to appear so
instead of this file name I'm
going to say carrot soup so that is
what will appear in the log
message then I would say
create commit the changes do
you want to discover no
let's let's commit again maybe
it didn't happen properly commit
Maybe it's trying to navigate to
a new tab, but let's see.
Let's try again.
Okay, now we faced an error.
This was not planned, but
the error was that git actually committed
when I clicked the commit button before,
but due to some redirection in the browser,
it didn't actually give
me enough information that it has happened.
So I tried to do it again,
but now Git has deleted a
file with the same name already exists.
So that's additional help that
we got from GitHub, not the Git itself,
but GitHub, that it went
and detected that there's a file
that we don't want to commit.
And then...
it's give me some option, you
know what to do.
So I'm going to now do a cancel here.
I would have preferred that
I didn't have to do it.
But you know, some technical
problems I didn't.
But you might you might also
see that if there's some delay.
So I'm going back to the recipe book now.
Now the git will say
there's unsafe changes.
But GitHub said that it committed.
So let's say okay, let's see what happens.
then I will go to the soups.
And then if you can see
here, that file I committed is not here.
Could you guess why it's not here?
What do you think?
Maybe because you are in
a different branch?
Correct.
So in the main branch, that
file is not there.
So it's in the...
new recipe branch, right?
So the thing I wanted to show
before the exercise is that how
to create a branch and how to
place a file in a specific branch.
And we also saw
like unexpectedly encountered error.
So when I- [name].
Yes.
I think a few people from
Denmark lost the live connection.
Okay.
so maybe can we take uh some questions
if there are any questions
in the collaborator notes in
the main right okay yeah
now they're back actually they're
back okay yeah they're back okay
so then um what we do is
we'll go to the exercise now so
we are we are in this the
main lesson page and we are
going to the commit committing lesson
And then I kind of showed
the branch and the commit to start with.
Now you have to practice yourself
how to do it.
And the exercise is for 20 minutes.
And what you should do is,
First, make sure you're on your fork.
So that I showed several times
there on the top that I'm not in the main,
the place where I forked it
from, or we call this
upstream in technical sense.
You had to be on your fork
or the copy you made.
First, create a new branch.
That also, I did in a way, you know,
the clicked on the main,
the place where that branch
symbol is and created one.
And then...
you have to modify a recipe
you just added so um so
first you need to create a new new branch
and add a recipe so like i did
but then you have to modify
that recipe a little bit so
first you commit it and then you modify
that file then you have to
switch back to the main branch
uh by clicking on the top
browser i could go back again
uh to the reserve the the
Could you maybe repeat?
I think a few people are
saying like a bit fast or something like that.
Okay.
Let's see.
So here first, you have to
make sure you're in the correct fork.
Okay.
Right?
So the fork is this.
So if you see, for example,
here, if I click it,
Click this one.
This is the upstream, the way
I copied it from.
You shouldn't work here.
So instead, you should work
on your fork, the copy you created.
Then you have to go and
click the main branch and create
a branch from that place.
Right?
Yes.
As I did, I created
this subreddit recipe branch.
So after that, I'm going
back to the lesson.
After that, you have to do as I did,
contribute a recipe to your branch,
and then you have to open
it up again and do some modification.
Then after modifying that, you
have to come back to the main branch.
So you'll have to switch again here.
So first you do is that
you work on this branch,
create a file and commit it
open it up again and edit
it and then commit again and
then switch back to the main
branch and then change uh
change change modify a recipe there so the
As you also show briefly,
the file I committed is not
there in the main branch.
It's in the branch that I created.
So when you switch back to
the main branch, you would not
see the file you created.
But soon you have to
modify something in the main branch.
To make things easier, I would
say go and modify something in the
the sites for maybe, for
example, inside sites, you have this
Gokomole file.
So modify that Gokomole file.
Here it doesn't specify which
file, but you know, it's okay.
You can select whichever you want,
but maybe you could, if you
don't have a preference, go
and modify the Gokomole file
and then follow the instructions
as even here from five onwards,
maybe at least number seven.
You could come, but this will
also, we will check after you arrive back.
Is that clear enough, [name],
or do you want to say something?
Yeah, it's clear, yes.
Yes.
So you go here, go to
your fork, create a branch, create a file,
modify it, and then go back
to the main branch, modify
something in that branch, and
then commit that, and then
follow the instructions.
there's anything unclear we
could discuss in the notes yeah for suppose
if yes so what we do is exercise
until 20 minutes so we'll give
a 20 minutes exercise now uh
starting now and uh bye for
now but we'll meet after 20
minutes to discuss the answers
We'll come back.
I see there were some
questions regarding the exercise as well.
So what I'll try to do is
I'll keep in mind the questions
and I will try to go
through the solutions and try to
explain them at the same time.
And when we come back, you
could point me to the things I missed.
Okay, sure.
So we were in this...
repository, which is a fork or
a copy from the Code
Refinery CR workshop exercise
recipe book branch.
As you can see, to find
out which branch you are in,
there was a question on how to
find out where I am.
The best way is to look
here, and also the URL on the top.
I'm not sure, yeah, you could
see the URL as well.
So in the URL, it will
say GitHub, my name, and
then the repository name.
And then the first thing in the exercise,
what we were supposed to do
in the first one is to make.
Let me check.
Make sure you are on the on your same fork.
Same fork.
So this we make sure.
Was that clear enough that to
how to find out about that?
Yes.
Then the second point they're
asking is was to create a new branch, was it?
Yes.
There was one question as well.
When the branch was created,
somebody already saw some commits
and that person wondering
whether somebody has modified
the original, the upstream version.
So the upstream version would be,
even if it is modified, if
you don't click this button
here, the sync fork.
So this is a sync fork
means to sync with upstream.
If you have not clicked that,
whatever done upstream will not
arrive to your repository.
Most likely thing that might
have happened is that when you
wrote your name of your
branch, maybe you selected one
already created instead of creating your own.
For example, if I go here and
if I try to create a new recipe,
That branch is already there,
but my intention is to create
a new branch, but that one was already there.
When I clicked, instead of
creating a new branch, I
switched to that branch instead.
So then if I go to the
soups, I will see that carrot soup.
so again i'll go back to
the the front the the main
page of the repository and then
i'll create a new repo new branch
so the new branch i'll create uh soup 2
for example then it will
say create branch and when i
switch to that branch i should
not see that carrot soup but let's see
As you can see, it's
only the mushroom soup.
But when I'm creating the branch,
if I had created it from
my previous branch instead of
the main branch, then
my carrot soup would also be here.
So a branch could also
be created from another branch.
So it doesn't have to be
from a main branch.
So that one thing that
might have happened during the exercise.
So there are a few things to figure out.
I think everything you've figured
out is a learning experience.
And what was the third question, Iman?
It was to create?
New commit, basically.
New commit, okay.
Yeah.
okay so i'm going to soup too
and then i'm going to go to the branch
and then if you remember that
i said create a new file i
could also upload a file from
my computer then create a file
for the sake of explanation i'm
going to just call it um
Carrot soup.
Yeah.
It's already there.
So I'm going to call it 2.md.
And then I'm going to cheat
a little bit and copy those must-have fields.
Recipe.
Carrot soup 2.
Ingredients.
carrots and water.
For the instructions, I will just boil it.
Not a great recipe, but
you know, don't judge me for the recipe.
Just focus on the git part of it.
I will go and see the review.
So, it looks good.
Then I should commit that.
When I committing it, it will
commit to the soup2 branch.
new soup.
So if you include some detailed details
for the person who's reading
it, it'll be helpful.
You could write some detail about it here.
I'm writing create a carrot soup.
I would say simple alternate
view and commit to this branch.
Again, that message of
not redirected properly.
Then in the fourth question, I
was asked to modify.
Was it, Iman?
Oh, the same file, was it?
Yes, you have to modify the same file.
Yeah, same file I should modify.
So I would open this file
and I will click this edit button.
Do you see the edit pencil here?
Yeah, maybe could you zoom a bit there?
yeah okay so I'll go back
yeah yeah it's good and then
I'll click on the file that I
want to edit then I will say
uh there's a pencil button somewhere
I had to zoom out a little
bit because I don't see the
pencil yeah here I think it
should be yeah and then I
would say maybe salt and then
I would again click
this button commit changes and
here I would say and noted
salt updated salt and then commit that.
So, in that branch I would
see that this is salt is also added.
Then I was asked to browse the network.
So what I'll do is.
I think you have to go to the main.
Okay.
Main branch.
Yeah.
And modify one file there.
Modify one file.
Okay.
Thank you.
So then I will go back
to the main branch here by clicking on the main.
And that was actually a
very good thing happened.
I'll do that again to show you.
I'm going to soups.
And I'm going to change back
to that soup two branch.
And I'm going to click this carrot soup.
And I'm going to change to
the main branch here.
Now it's going to throw an error.
See whether you can see that error.
It says page not found,
which means that file is not
there in the main branch, right?
So that was the reason.
So then I'll go to...
the main the root folder
of that repository and then I will go to sites,
I will go to the guacamole
recipe and then edit this and
I will add maybe make 2 tablespoons of salt.
and then press commit changes.
I added a message for log message
and then I clicked on the...
Do you see my microphone where
my mouse pointer is, Saman?
Or is it not clear that much?
Yeah, but yes, now I can see that.
I see the commit.
Again, my browser is not
directly reading properly.
That's fine.
Now it's two tablespoons.
So next one is the network, right?
Yes, next one is the network.
Then I will go to Insights.
So if your browser is a
little more zoomed out, then you
will see the button.
But here, you will see a
menu entry called Insight.
Go to Insight and click on Network.
Then you see, as many of
you experience, it sometimes takes
time to render this.
So when I copied from
the upstream, I copied all the branches.
So if I had copied only
the main branch, then I would not see.
But these are all the
changes that were done in the
past in that repository.
So I see all the changes.
So I see this my change here.
We have to rotate our head.
What is that?
yes so let me check where my branches
so this is here you see if
it came from the main branch
they were here yeah and then
i have done some changes and
then um the main branch itself
has moved um so this is the latest one
This is not the latest one.
Because you have two accounts, I think.
So this was the earlier one.
And this is now integrated.
The one I did now is this one.
Yeah.
So this is the main branch
that has moved forward.
And this is the branch
I created, create correct sub
branch, and it's not joined yet.
So the main branch has something.
the correct, the suggestion
branch has something, but because
of this is now little, like
too many things are there.
Might be little complicated, but
the thing you should notice is that there is,
there are two commits, these
two dots, which are not in the main branch.
And there is this dot,
the main branch, which is not
in the blue branch.
So in the next part of the lesson
that [name] would show you
how to combine this, right?
Yes.
Yeah.
So then what they're asking
switch to the main project, modify the recipe.
I've been the fifth question now.
Now we are in the seventh
because now we compared Okay,
compare the branch that you created.
Yeah.
With the main part.
So that comparison, we did
that visually, but there's a better
way to do that.
Like we could use this URL to compare it.
Here we use the, if you,
so this is a little tricky.
So if you see my URL,
maybe [name], could you reduce
the video a little bit so
the URL will be visible?
Maybe even off the video for a while.
Oh, yes.
Yeah.
In the top URL, you go to the recipe,
that repository, and then I
will post this in the shared
document and type compare.
The word compare, if you type compare,
it opens up a way
to compare the repositories.
What's the difference?
for example with the main and
the main I have so that
the top the repository is the upstream
and the main I have there's one change
that I change sort but what
we want to do now is to
check the change between my
repository main and with the
soup to rest repository.
So is this a expected,
uh, change, uh, Haman or not?
You are still in your repository, right?
In the main repository.
Yeah.
So I'm comparing with the main
branch of my repository, my, my
copy with the soup to a branch of my copy.
So these are the two changes I did.
So it clearly shows that I
have added a file compared to the main branch.
But it did not show that I changed salt.
Remember that I also changed salt.
So in order to do that,
you have to perform this
comparison other way around.
So you have to select soup 2 here.
And then main here.
In that comparison, it will
show that there's a difference of sort here.
The green is added, red is removed.
So you have to make sure
the direction of comparison
to see the changes.
So there's a change.
There are some commits that are
not in the main branch, but
in the SUP2 branch that I could see in one way.
And there are changes in the main branch,
which are not in the SUP2 branch
that also you could see, but
you have to make sure you
select the correct direction here.
also commits, you could compare
in this way with this URL.
So, the way to compare is
that let us say we want to,
I will go to this repository,
the base of that repository.
And I will go to the soups folder here.
And I will change back
to the soup two branch.
So then I see my carrot soup.
So this is the place where
we did the changes.
So I will, the file and the change.
Then I will go here and
then I will click on blame.
So this showed that, you
know, I created this file, who
created the file and then the
change I did by adding salt in this case.
Now I want to find out
the commit hashes of this.
Do you know how to?
I think you showed in your
lesson how to find the commit hashes.
Do you remember?
Can you remind me again, [name]?
Was it history?
Yes, you can add this.
So here we want to
compare between these two versions.
So I want to see
the difference between these two versions.
So what I will do is I will copy this hash,
but it will copy the entire
big, like the long string, but
I only need the seven strings in the beginning.
Again, I need to go
here, recipe book, recorded, and
I have to remove all this.
and I typed compare.
So this, what I'm typing is
given in the answer.
So I'm relying on that text
to be, you know, for you to reference.
And then for this, I don't
need the whole hash.
I only need about seven, eight.
It doesn't matter one, two,
three, four, five, six, seven, eight.
Okay.
Then you need two dots.
You can also remove zero.
Okay.
dots.
So even if you have the
zero, it doesn't matter.
But you need minimum of seven.
And I copy this hash.
And I paste it.
I just paste it as it is.
I hope let me check whether
you can see that.
Yeah, I can see that on the screen.
Yeah, so I'll copy this.
Yes.
And the text here is that
I'll go back to the
our lesson material.
I can show you again.
Then I press enter.
Then it will go and find
out the difference between those two hashes
or those two commits were that
one had sort and one did not have sort.
So I'll go back to that the
and I will show you where it is written.
I am going to, I am
scrolling down, browse commits and
then compare branches.
So, here you will see that command.
So, if you if you did not see
that on the URL, especially
on Twitch, it might be a little blurred.
The way you should type the
URL is here and also
comparing arbitrary commits.
way I did was the repository's
name I typed compare in the front
and the hashes that I copied
you could use the whole the cache
as it is that the hash as it is
or you know you minimum seven
needed to get that answer then
there is a rename your branch so
let's see if I go back here
I want to rename this branch that I created
For that, there are several ways
to do this in the GitHub interface.
So the first thing is you
need to find the branch.
You could go and click on
your recipe to go to the home
page of this, the base of the repository.
Then you could click this branches here.
Near main, you have this...
tap for branches then you will
see all the branches that's the easiest way
for me to find out is
there any other way to find
the branch Iman I think if you
go again the same place I mean
you can also look at view
all branches but if you click
on the main I think there is one last icon which
we've all branches yeah this
is other way but the one
you showed is much better in
terms of one click right here yeah
so you you have to come to this place
and let's say if you want
to rename this branch to a
little bit get some space here
because i can see all the
the buttons you have to go
here click on this three dots
and then rename the branch and
you could say soup three for example
And now it is called SUP3.
You might see, don't see it immediately.
You don't see it here,
but you could refresh the page
and you'll see that it's SUP3.
So that is how you rename the branch.
And tag also you could create.
So the tag is like when
you're publishing a paper, for
example, you could attach, you
know, this is the version I published a paper.
Or if you are releasing a code base,
you could say, you know,
release one, release two, that kind of things.
for that also you could go
to the front page to your repository
and here there is this
sticky tape sticky note kind of
thing tag then you could click that
and then I have some one
tag here already created you could
create a tag by using releases
and then create a new release
I'll call it release one.
Tag, I would say beta 01.
Usually, it'll be something
like version one, for example, version B1.
It's a tag.
And then the version used in the
publication, for example.
And you are releasing the main one?
Yes.
So I'm going to release the main branch.
Then you publish it.
So when that is done, you will see
that if I go to the front
page of this, if I click on
tags, I'll see that one I created as well.
So, before we go for a
break, I could show some
discussions here as well.
You know, as part, so this,
you could have the branches.
If only you are working,
you could also commit to the
main branch if you wish.
You could commit to branches
if there are multiple lines of work at
once and you could want
them to interfere with each other.
I mean,
So to be honest, we don't
work with code this way.
We don't work on the browser this way.
Either we use the terminal or
we use the integrated development environment.
So in those environment,
we collect relevant changes together
when we make a commit.
So you don't just collect
some random files and make a commit.
So it's like a collection of files.
And then if you don't want to
some file to be like in the Git.
For example, maybe there's
some password file or maybe
if you're working with cloud,
there might be some like a
key that you are using for
testing so that you don't want to
send it to the GitHub.
Then there is this gitignore
that would be useful.
So everything that is included
in the gitignore would not end
up in the GitHub.
So that's the end of that exercise.
And let me check the nodes.
Did I miss anything here?
What does it mean for one of the commits?
Okay.
So that is like the tag
referred to a commit.
So when I said the main branch
and created a tag, it created
the late tag on the latest commit.
uh where where did somebody
find the must have content for
the new file could my file
lacking this content means okay
so the must have content is
there on the document um so if
you if you see this uh answers uh antique answer
under 2, number 2, you will
find this must have content.
You could also try misspelling
this and see what happens.
And then the next one is
when trying to make a tag
and associated it with the commit.
This may be due to that
you're in a different branch.
So the latest commit might be in a branch.
You have to make sure that
you're in a branch.
If you try to tag it, if
you don't see a commit,
most likely scenario would, you
know, one scenario would be that
you might be in a different branch.
Okay, so these things we will
talk about a little bit
this in the collaborative version part as well.
But I would think that now we go
for a break, [name], and when we come back,
we'll discuss more and we will
see how to integrate this.
So then we can answer those questions.
Somebody has used the term push here,
but first we need to merge
this content to the main branch.
So now we break [name] for 10 minutes
and we'll come back and then
when we come back, [name]
would continue the merging part
and bye for now.
Yep.
[name], I could hear you.
No, [name], can you hear him?
Hey, I can hear you.
Can you hear Iman?
I guess not.
OK.
I think it's a network issue, maybe.
Yeah, now I can hear you.
OK, fine.
Good, good.
OK, welcome back.
Welcome back from the break.
So yeah, this is the
last session today, which is about merging.
OK, so let me increase the screen, maybe.
Till now what we saw is like we did this,
we started with looking at
the existing repository and then
we forked the repository, which is
like we took a copy of it
and then we started editing it.
Now you try to add some new features
and now you want to like
push it back to the main repository.
So that is what you're going to do now.
So basically, yeah.
And just a quick remark, basically
when you are doing this
pushing emerging changes, so
you're satisfied with whatever the
fixes you made or what are
the features you want to add,
now you want to propose the changes.
So that is what you are
here in your branch where you just forked
and added your new features and
now you ask for a pull request.
which means that we are asking for,
we have these changes and
just include these changes in the main branch.
For this tutorial, we will
stick with your own branch,
with your own repository.
Please don't push any changes
to the upstream recipe book.
There are three different ways
of doing this, but today we
will focus on the GitHub path,
and maybe in the coming days
you will learn the other ways.
If you are happy with the VS Code
or command line, you will
come across in the next few days.
Okay.
So here is the exercise.
And what you're going to do
is like, let's start with this branch.
So this is like the branch.
Currently, what you are looking is.
I'm losing sound.
No, I couldn't hear you.
I guess we have.
If you haven't created a new
recipe, try to create the new
recipe and then you now try
to do the pull request.
and to do the pull request
what you do is like you go
to the main branch to the code
and then here you can see the contribute
and then you can look for
the open pull request so that's
uh this is the exercise you are
now you will be doing now so
we have uh say uh maybe
[name] how many minutes like i
think we are running out of time
Uh, say 10 minutes so that
we have, uh, uh, yeah, say 10 50.
Yeah.
I can't hear you.
So this exercise, uh, human,
you had to walk through because
of, um, yeah, so they can do it as homework.
You could walk through.
Yeah.
So then I will walk through this exercise.
Okay.
Basically, uh, what you see
here is like, uh, I created a new recipe here.
Okay.
So when you click on the new recipe,
what you next do is like
a click on this contribute button.
When you click on this contribute button,
you can then request for
the open pull request.
So if you click on this green button,
which is open pull request,
then it will ask you to fill a few things.
As [name] mentioned before,
Basically, we need to choose where to push.
Here it will be your branch.
It is my name and my
recipe book, and then here it
should be your new recipe.
Then you can add some comments here,
add push the new recipe, and
you can add some description if
you want, and then create pull request.
So once you create the
pull request, it starts checking.
And if there are no conflicts,
then you can basically just
do the merging part.
Okay.
And here you can also just
write a new recipe.
Okay.
And then just do a confirm.
And once you merge the pull
request, if you want, you
can delete the branch.
OK, or else you can leave it.
It's up to you.
And let me go quickly to
the code and see what are the branches created.
OK.
So you can again go to the code
and look into these branches
using this fork button.
And then here you can see.
OK.
Yeah.
One thing is, even if we
decide to delete the branch,
the commits, that branch will remain.
It's just that point for
that branch disappeared.
All the commits would remain
if it is merged.
Okay.
So, yeah.
What is next, [name]?
Is there anything?
What we can do is, while
we wait a little bit, we have about, I mean,
like five minutes, we can
stay and see whether we can
ask the learners to try it out, the merging.
not necessarily go out for exercise,
but we can see while you
browse, ask them to merge and
ask questions if they have, or
if they feel any, face any difficulty.
Sorry, I lost you for a while.
Okay.
Yeah.
So I would recommend that
maybe the learners, the
participants could also try to
merge and see where they face any issues.
If they face an issue, then
maybe you can show how to
solve it on the screen.
Okay, fine.
Someone is asking, what is
the history behind a pull request?
Why not merge request instead
of because of direction seems makes sense.
So this pull request,
merge request, there's actually a platform.
So those are not like
fundamentally Git stuff.
For example, it's named
differently in GitLab, for example.
So GitHub, GitLab, they use
different terms sometimes.
But what it means is to
integrate with the main line of work.
Um, so if you see a conflict, um,
that also, uh, like if you, um, um,
[name], could you show that,
um, uh, that picture with
that sunglass and hats?
Okay.
And that's in the rosin, right?
Um, yes.
The.
Oh, sorry.
Motivation.
Uh, maybe one before.
Yeah, here.
So here, if instead of the sunglass,
if you are trying a red
hat and a black hat, then
when you are combining it, it
might not know automatically how to combine it.
So then a human is needed to decide.
here because it's a sunglass and
a hat it just combined so if it is this
for example if two people
um modify the same line of
code then git won't know which
one to keep because if it takes one
and discard the other there's
a loss of information so as
long as there's no loss of information
it'll do automatically.
But as soon as there's
a possibility of losing information,
it'll ask the intervention of a human.
So that we call a conflict.
So the conflict, there's a kind
of a demo here as well.
At the end, I think, let
me check in the merging part.
If you go further down,
it's all in conflict.
in the in the in the
in the document that you are showing.
So yeah, so in the in the yeah,
so in the in the in the as an example,
there's one example in the same lesson
that you are showing before
in the merging changes and
contributing to the project lesson.
Yeah.
So okay, let's go there then.
So at the end, there's a
simple example for demonstrating a conflict.
Resolving conflicts and demonstration.
It's a demonstration, but I
don't think we have time
for that demonstration, but I
think we'll talk about it later
on as well in the lessons when we...
especially when we entertain
pooled requests from different users.
So a conflict is mainly when
Git want to combine two
things from two different, like
combine two different branches and
the file that it's trying to
combine has been modified on the
same line that by two different people.
So it's to avoid loss of information.
Okay, now let's go for the
day two, like the preparation for the day two.
Okay.
I think, yeah, since we are
at the last 10 minutes.
Yeah, should I share my
screen in that case?
I think if you want, you can just... Yes.
Yeah, I don't know.
I'm sharing my screen now.
We can show my one.
Sorry, it's not.
It will not show up correctly if, okay.
So now there's only one
person sharing and I can set it to here.
Yes, okay.
Got it showing correctly.
All right.
Yeah.
So while I'm talking that, Erno
and [name], that it's also
important that you give us
some feedback about how the day was.
So please do that as well.
And then I'll give you
some details about the,
next lesson um tomorrow we'll
be doing most realistic stuff
so today we worked on the
browser this is not necessarily the
way we work because um when
you have code you have to
work on the terminal or
on an integrated development
um environment like you know vs
code or so there are so
many environments for this you need
to um do certain things by tomorrow
First thing is that to
create a GitHub account that
you have already done, and then
you have to configure the Git a little bit.
Some, you know, you have to
inform Git your name and information like that.
Let me go down here and
point you to where that information is.
Configuring Git command line editor.
So now I'm going to pull
up a terminal like today, the
first time I'm going to pull
this up and then I'm going to
show you the way it should be configured.
So in the git terminal, so
you see my terminal now, maybe
I make the font a little
bit bigger and maybe make it
a little lighter, even lighter maybe.
yes the first thing you need is git
so you should when you type
git version it should print something
so i have 241 so any any version
that close by should be
okay the other thing you need
is when you type ssh version
that should print something but
that's not how you type the
value you have to type a
capital V here it should
print something not like command
not found then the next command
is to see whether you can
connect to GitHub GitHub.com so
the first one is to check the version of git
Second one is to SSH, whether you have SSH.
Normally you have it on
Windows, you have it in the
PowerShell and even the terminal you have it.
And then what you do is with
a capital T to see whether
you can connect to github.com.
The first time when you issue
that command, it will ask, it
will tell you that you are
going to connect to something that
you are never connected before.
Do you trust that?
So if you had typed
the address correctly, github.com,
then you should trust that.
And you could also cross-check
this hash with GitHub if you want.
Then it says permission denied.
So this is the most likely
case that you will get if you
have not used Git before.
Because I have been using Git
and I have configured it, if I
use it on my laptop,
github.com sorry not git ssh
ssh it would return that okay
still public is not accepted so when you
when you get this message
the thing you should do is
mentioned here you have to go and set up
SSH key pair.
So what this basically do
is that there's some credentials
in your computer that you
create some credentials, we
call the certificate.
And you place that in GitHub.
And whenever you reach GitHub,
GitHub knows that it is you.
So let me try with this
command again with the git
task username, because it went
with my username.
github.com task my uh need
to unlock then if you if
you had configured it you had to
be you get this message as
successful i'll just do it again
in my virtual machine which
is not configured to get
the correct message what's this
then it should say public key it says denied
So by tomorrow, you should be
able to issue this command and be
able to get a successful authentication.
How to do that is explained here.
So installation instructions,
how to create a key and
what that is, what this means.
I hope that you could do
this today and make sure that
you are ready for tomorrow's
workshop um did that explain him
or should i explain a little
bit more no that is good
actually uh there will be i'm
just looking at the note
uh notebook basically there is
an installation help available on
zoom zoom one hour before
for oslo so basically more
details will be followed like uh
and you will receive any
email regarding this so
Good.
So, will the learners will
get an email about this?
I guess, yeah.
We'll try to.
Try to, yes.
So, basically, what you try to
do is to follow the instructions here.
So, when you issue this
command, ssh dash capital T
GitHub, git at github.com, it should
get you into a place where
it says it was successful.
Yeah.
Shall we take the notebook then?
Like the final questions?
Yes.
So we'll go for the final questions.
Can you comment on your
GitHub desktop versus VS Code command?
Yeah.
So, so the,
mean if you can go for
the command line vs code or the terminal
or any other command line
you get more transparent outputs
when you do git and you can do more steps
for example when you when you
want to make a commit you
could commit like git add to
collect all the relevant commits
into one place and then git push
Git commit.
But in the GitHub interface,
most things are not that transparent.
So the close commit, so this is, I mean,
when you have merge request and then
when you say close the
merge request without merging,
which means that
that the changes in that
branch would not be merged,
which not be integrated.
It will remain in the branch.
But if that branch is deleted, then
that commit, that change
is disappeared, that gone forever.
But after it merged without
closing, if you delete it, it will not go away.
Okay.
Yeah.
So this conflict, we didn't go
through too much today about
the conflict because of the
the complexity of like, we want
to make it very least complex today.
Um, but that is some
natural thing that you'll encounter.
If two people modify the same
line of a file, for example,
or, uh, you modify the same line
of a file in different branches,
Git would ask your help to select what to keep.
Yeah.
Anything else, [name], that you
need to mention before we close?
Yeah.
Should we move to the, um,
to the close, basically.
So yeah, it's a couple of
things in the end of the notes.
The most important thing is
the feedback section.
So yeah, please do give us
feedback for how this day went.
There's some standard questions
we always ask.
If it was too fast, too slow, just right.
And we'll try to adjust.
And...
Well, let's take a look at
those in a moment.
But first, news.
So if you scroll a little bit up,
there's an info section, a
blue box with news on it.
Scroll a little bit up.
I could, of course, also move
to the notes that I have
on the broadcaster computer.
But okay.
So yeah, there were basics of Git today.
We covered GitHub, mostly using
GitHub user interface.
tomorrow we'll move to your local computer.
So if today was either like
too much GitHub or too abstract or too easy,
don't worry, tomorrow you'll do
more work on your own computer.
But it should not be
that much more complicated.
So we're kind of doing these
steps also to prepare so that
a lot of the concepts are familiar tomorrow.
But yeah, so tomorrow we'll
move on more working on your own computer.
And that also does mean
either the terminal or VS Code or similar.
So if you haven't already,
please check the installation instructions.
Okay, so it really should
be exciting tomorrow because it
will then directly apply to
your current work, to your
coding and paper writing and so on.
on your own computer.
Okay, if you have issues,
yeah, there will be already
mentioned the support, zoom
or installation help.
Another good thing to know is
that Twitch will store this
video for seven days.
So you can come back and
take a look at well, any part
that you felt like it went too fast.
Anything that was
complicated, you can try to
do the exercises again, when
maybe GitHub has less load and
some of the or some of the
other issues might be resolved.
And yeah, then it will be on YouTube.
So all of our old
workshops, these online workshops
that are streamed, they will
also be okay, they are already also on YouTube.
So you can go see the same things
or similar things explained
by different people in different ways.
If so, hopefully, that's helpful.
Um, and then, yeah, so I
mentioned to do tomorrow, we'll
move to your own computer and
on day three, then we'll
move more to collaborating with people.
So sharing the code and working
on the same project and, uh,
also we'll see more conflicts
and resolve conflicts.
So, um, that should be interesting.
Okay.
Uh, let's take a look at the, um,
the feedback a bit more.
There are a lot of votes on write speed,
a few votes on too
slow, too fast sometimes,
which means essentially we need
to pay attention.
But at least it's an average good.
Some on write level, some on too basic.
Tomorrow will be a bit more advanced.
So if you're starting with
already knowing some Git, then
maybe today was not that much
new stuff, but tomorrow should be more.
So, but yeah, people are
saying they will use what they learned today,
which is really good to hear,
and that they would recommend for others.
So that's nice.
So let's see what specific,
what catches your eye, [name], [name].
somebody accidentally asked to
brand merge their branch with mine.
So I think I made a new friend.
That's nice to hear.
Yeah.
And yeah, to collaborate
document, we always like that.
Okay, somebody is calling
the stream professional, which is
nice for me to hear because I
made a lot of mistakes.
But it wasn't that bad.
Yeah, the font size was small for a
for some period of time,
and we didn't communicate either
clearly enough or loudly enough
when it happened.
So yeah, next time, I
guess I'll escalate to speaking up and see.
So because it is like you concentrate
when I know when I've
been at the instructor, you
really, you focus on what
you're doing, and then you don't
look at the chat and so on.
So I
It was essentially on me,
I should have spoken up more quickly.
But yeah, so that's important feedback.
Okay.
I think we're done for the end.
Thank you all the assistance
from our colleagues to answer
all the questions.
It was very well answered as well.
And thank you, [name], and thank you,
[name], [name], and everybody
else, and also the helpers.
And we'll see you tomorrow.
I hope you'll come back
tomorrow to learn more.
Yeah, tomorrow will be really
more, even more hands-on.
It will look more familiar
compared to what your normal,
at least, coding workflow is.
So it should be exciting.
Thank you all.
But I do write more feedback
in that we will read everything right there.
This is not the end of the workshop.
And in any case, we're
interested to know what you have to say.
Please continue writing in the feedback.
Okay, then.
Bye-bye.
All right.
Bye.
See you tomorrow, everyone.