Let's see.
What could affect this?
I don't know.
Let us know if you can hear us.
Is the headphone muted?
Okay.
Now people can hear us.
Now can they hear us online?
I'm assuming it was the headphone.
Okay.
It is not muted now.
and I can hear my own
voice coming from there.
So now that was probably the issue.
But okay, so I guess we'll
start from the top then.
Yes, it's okay.
Like if you didn't hear what
we were saying in the
past minutes, it's totally fine.
What I was just mentioning is
that I'm now showing this
notes document that we've been using today.
If you were not here with
us today, it's great that you made it today.
You just open this
notes.coderefinery.org link that I've
sent you.
And there you can start editing
and for example, tell us what
was the last animal you saw
by clicking this pencil here.
And I was just asking to
our instructors of the day,
And [name] said that when you grow up,
you want to be an inventor
or you always want to be an inventor.
And what are you doing today as a career?
Yeah, well, so I went into research
because that seemed the
more traditional thing is most
closely to inventing than
just inventing stuff.
And then
I was always more
technically interested than really
just finding things out.
So then I became a
research software engineer, which
is basically, at least to me, the ideal
middle midway between doing
something technical like coding
and doing research so I guess
I'm in a quite a good place now yeah
I also feel the same.
I'm so happy to be, you
know, I don't have to worry
about applying for grants.
And of course, I'm super happy
that we have great postdocs
and professors and doctoral researchers
who are applying for grants
and keeping the whole system working.
But as I can, it's nice
to just focus on the software
and methods and, you know,
and what about [name] what do
you want to do when you grow
up or maybe you can also think
it what did you want to do
when you were younger what
were you thinking that you were
going to be when you grew
up i'm not really sure whether what i
whether i had dreams i would
say um yeah i would i wanted
to be useful um i guess
that engineer would maybe describe
that but yeah good way to be
useful and in the end and
what are you doing today
Well, at CSC, I work as
a machine learning specialist.
So I, most of the time
I help researchers use HPC
resources to do machine learning research.
And that's, I think that's,
that fits quite well.
Yeah.
So any plans for where
you're gonna grow up?
Or are you happy where you are now?
i haven't been doing this for
so long so i'm still learning a lot
and that's i think so long
as i'm still learning i think
that's why i agree so excellent i see
that people are editing this
notes document i will remind
later when we start with the
actual intro but basically with this pencil
that i'm showing here now
maybe that's the cameras on top of my mouse
but in the top what is
that in the top right corner
of this notes document there is a pencil
if you click the pencil you see
that now the view of
this document has changed and looks
like a code editor and this
is the idea that it's a simple text editor
that everyone can edit at the same time.
Right now there's 73 people who are,
some of them are editing, some
of them are just watching like I'm doing now.
And so here you can tell us which animal.
Someone saw a bee.
I saw the Otanian geese in the morning.
They wanted to walk in the
middle of the road.
I don't know why.
I scared them.
And, um, and also what do
you want to do when you, when you grow up?
Right.
But it's basically one minute to go.
Anything else you want to
mention before we start with
the show, [name] and [name]?
No.
Are you excited?
Yes, of course, so I will
switch back to the view
mode, which is something that
I recommend also for the learners
that it's lighter for the server
that is hosting this tool,
if you don't plan to edit
you can switch to this view mode.
and I was mentioning when
you could not hear us but
since now you can hear us I was mentioning
that we have also left
the feedback from yesterday so
if you were around yesterday and
you did not have time to
write say something about the
feedback from yesterday so you
still have a chance to edit that in the notes
but now it's 12 o'clock in
finland and so we can actually
start with the workshop
Hello everyone and welcome to
day two of the Code
Refinery workshop, September-October 2025.
I'm [name] here, your
workshop organizer for this time
along with [name].
And with me today we
have [name] from CSC
Finland and [name] also
from Aalto University Finland.
And [name] also from
our team is the broadcaster for today.
so a bit of reminder if
you were not with us yesterday
it's totally fine you can
still understand everything and
do everything that will be done today
and if you want to re-watch
what was done yesterday on twitch
tv on the same link that
you watch in this stream you
can also watch yesterday's videos
later for example if you want to catch up
but in general today you
are good to understand what's been doing
and also be able to do
the exercises along with the
instructors in the workshop web page
that I'm showing right now
you find the materials for today and
so now I'm scrolling down to
day two and today we will
continue with this git version
control and I'm gonna briefly give
you a mini intro
so yesterday we learned about
all this terminology around
git version control so you
heard all these terms like forking
and pull requests and commits
and it's okay if not
everything is fully clear because
these terms will be repeated
today and also tomorrow
But the goal, what was important is
that you understood the motivation,
why it is so important to
work with virtual control as a
time machine to go back in
time in a previous version of
your code or whatever project
that you are version controlling.
today for day two we'll move
to local work so if yesterday
we were using this github.com
web browser web server meaning
that the files were stored
somewhere in the cloud in
actually microsoft cloud because
github is microsoft today
now it's good that we have github.com
as a remote repository but
it's also good to work locally so
and this is what will happen today
so the files instead of
being just in github.com will
come to your computer you will
be able to edit them do changes and
when you're happy you can push
them back to the cloud
github.com servers or you know i
don't want to spoil the fun
you will see today what we will do
In the links that you have
received in your email there is
also this notes document and
just a reminder although I
was just chatting about it when
you visit this notes document
it looks like this and you
can use this to basically
interactively ask questions to
our instructors and our helpers
by clicking in the very top
there is a pencil which will
switch the notes from this view
mode to this editor mode
and it's basically a simple text editor
so that many hundreds of people
can edit at the same time.
I think it's like a Google Doc
but a bit more reliable
because Google Doc has
limitations of simultaneous editing
and also simplified.
I can already see some questions there
and our helpers are already answering
so keep the questions coming
and I don't want to steal
any other precious time to our
I believe now it's a good
moment to switch to [name]'s screen.
I guess you're going to be
the first one, right, [name]?
Yes, I'm going to share.
Excellent.
I'm sharing [name]'s screen.
All right.
Right.
So the floor is yours.
I will move out from the
scene and have a great workshop, everyone.
Right.
So the first thing we're going
to do is looking at working
locally on our computers instead of
on the on GitHub, on the website.
So I'll, I'll open the
lesson from our overview.
And then now, [name], what
are we doing today?
And why are we doing it?
Well, yeah.
So well, as [name] already said,
we are now instead of
working remotely on GitHub on
the website, we will now move
home to our own computer.
And so there's several different
ways you could do that.
So we will probably mostly focus
on the VS Code way because
that's sort of beginner friendly.
um but uh we'll also
show some terminal things um yeah
and you can also do a
lot of the stuff still on on github
so just cloning or just
the copying that's difficult but
um yeah most of the other stuff
uh you can also just do
remotely on github um yeah um
so maybe just to ask you do
you how do you work mostly do you
Well, I do work locally on my machine.
I do work mostly with IDE studies, VS Code.
But there are a few steps
that you can only do in Terminal.
And we'll show a way to
do that from VS Code as well.
OK.
And so why?
Why do you not just work on GitHub?
So there are some things that
you can only do in a certain way.
So I like to have my
work on my computer and
not just somewhere online.
And then the web interfaces,
they don't have all the tools.
And then if I want to run something,
if it's actual code, I want
to have it on my computer where
I can test run it without
having to have the connection and everything.
I mean, it's usually what I
do is I start locally, I
start doing something on my
computer, and then it's there.
And then I start publishing it.
I don't
go to the web and have this
big idea of a project that I want.
I've got a problem that I want to solve
and then I write some code for it
and then it grows bigger and
then I notice this should be
its own project and then I put
it in a folder and then I
realize maybe I want to share
this with some other people and then
that is the latest place that
that is the latest time where
it needs to go somewhere
that is actually shareable okay
we'll also get to that later
in a later lesson where when how
to turn like a local project
that you started into into
something into a into a good
thing that you can then easily
share with other people or publishers great um
Yeah, and yeah, that's so those
are sort of two of the
lessons we go to download something, then
how to do some archaeology,
some some poking around in there,
if you are searching for
a problem, for example.
Then we will talk about how
to turn a project that you
have locally into a Git repository
that you can easily share with others.
And then we'll do some
general discussion and maybe
some lived experience.
Yes.
And what to do and what not to do.
Great.
Then I guess, should we
talk about, discuss anything else
or should we just go to the first exercise?
Well, maybe as a little recap,
like a Git repository.
What is a Git repository actually?
Yeah.
So, well, I think those things were,
discussed a lot yesterday as well.
Indeed, they were just the
very short version.
So yeah, it's just a collection
of all of the files.
And it also does not just
contain the sort of the
current incarnation of all of
that information, but also all
of the history and a lot of metadata
um that describes how it got to
that state and so um
each commit is essentially a sort
of can be used as a
snapshot of the entire project at
any at a specific point in time
and it has a kind of
official name which is called its hash and um
can also be sort of it
can branch off in different directions
which can then also be
merged again together so there's
a well an arbitrarily complicated graph
that uh is often um future
you will thank you for keeping it
as simple as possible um and
um yeah all of that there's
a sort of secret hidden directory
inside of that uh repository
that's called dot git
And everything, so all of the
files of the current state that you have,
as it's called, checked out,
they are just in the directory,
in the normal repository directory.
And all of the other information
that is sort of hidden away
is in that .git directory.
And you can use certain
git commands in order
relatively conveniently interface with
that or the GitHub interface or
all the VS code interfaces we'll show later.
Yeah.
So then when we clone it, we
make a copy of that the whole thing.
Well, yes.
Not necessarily the entire thing.
You can copy everything.
But most of the time when you copy,
when you just git clone,
it does not necessarily by
default download, for example, all
of the branches.
It just downloads sort of
the default things that you would need.
You can also tell it to
clone a specific commit or a specific branch.
But yeah, it's sort of
flexible in that way.
When you fork something, then
that copies everything.
Okay, so that's basically
the difference between forking and cloning.
If you fork something, it'll do
a full copy of everything.
And with cloning, you get
the option to copy it all,
but not necessarily everything done
for you automatically.
Okay.
Yeah, okay.
So why do we not fork it to our computers?
Well, I guess you could do it,
but most of the time
when you fork something, that is
sort of the sort of a central thing.
If like, for example, if multiple people,
they work on a fork or
if there's a project and then
new people want to add
and take over development or add
things to that project, then
you would need everything.
And that's when you fork it.
But when you just clone
something from your own fork
or from the development fork, then
you clone it because then
you don't necessarily need everything.
And yeah, I think that's just part of
that is probably just historically
how it developed.
And yeah.
Okay, so how do we?
I mean, now that we've got
the the command line and the
VS code path, right?
And so maybe we start
with the exercise, right?
Sure, sure.
So there's the this exercise in the
the lesson page um where you
if you've got vs code you can
um you can clone it with vs
code and um could you maybe
our faces are partially obscuring the
URL, I think, if you move
it a little bit, I can just move this bit.
And then, but the basic idea is
that you go to the code
with the overview page, and then
you click on on the day two,
you click on the local work,
and then it'll get you to this one.
And then the exercise is to um,
Yeah, so, so we'll give you
25 minutes to try this out on your own before.
And then after that, don't
worry about it when you if
you struggle with anything, just
give it your best try.
You got to decide which
repository to clone side, it can
be any one really, then.
clone it, create a new branch, um,
try to make a commit on that new branch,
then switching to the main
branch and try to merge that
new branch into the main.
This will work if you have
merge access to that repository.
So it should be a
repository you have access to, like
for example, the recipe book
that you made the fork
that you forked yesterday.
And then, um,
you can compare those, like you
can see the steps of the exercise
and after the exercise time is done,
we will walk through the
exercise with VS Code as I would do it.
So I would say we'll do
25 minute exercise now.
That makes it...
exercise until dreadful with times.
1240 1240.
Okay.
Yeah, also, you can sort
down a little further down
there are instructions for command
line vs code and also our studio now.
And well, as we mentioned
previously, you can do most of
the things also just on GitHub itself.
So making a new branch, adding
a new commit and so forth.
But yeah, the first step
you can't do because, yeah.
So the instructions are here.
Yeah.
Switch whatever you want with these tabs.
But we will go over those
as well after the exercise.
Right.
Then see you in 25 minutes.
Yes.
i'll come back i see a
lot of people have finished no
one has indicated that they are
stuck uh i guess we didn't mention
but you you can indicate your progress
or your state uh in
the collaborative document as well
um but yeah a lot of you have found that
by themselves.
Before we continue, I want
to make maybe two small
corrections because, or yeah,
verifications at least.
So I mentioned that a clone
does not copy everything does.
I messed that up, mixed that
up with with something that we're
going to talk about later.
And that's why a fork is something
that you do on GitHub and
a clone is something that you do in Git.
So there's sometimes a distinction
or there is an
important distinction between Git and GitHub.
um and github when you
fork something it just clones it um
so uh yeah just to sort
of um make sure that's uh yeah
but uh well then uh let's continue um so um
Yes, we do the exercise.
And we're doing it with VS Code.
So here's my VS Code window.
And the first step says to
have a welcome screen and then
go to clone git repository.
And then I've copied my URL.
Actually, the one I copied
is the SSH version.
And the instructions say to
use the HTTPS version.
Yeah, that's what I was wondering about.
So I'm also not a VS Code user, typically.
So can you use either?
Or does it matter?
I think you can use either.
OK.
And then you need to.
But in order to use the
SSH version, you probably need to
upload a key pair and do
all of that jazz, right?
Oh, it couldn't read.
Yeah, apparently.
Let's try the same with the SSH version.
Well, it wasn't the SSH version
because it says it was trying
to exchange a key, right?
And it's... Yes.
Well, maybe I messed it up.
Let's try this one.
Hmm.
And that URL still looked
like the SSH version.
Yeah.
Okay.
So I will have to go
back to the instructions.
Probably have to remove
the failed attempts.
So it doesn't remember any,
any weird things.
I will do that off screen.
Okay, that's me.
In the meantime, if just
because I'm interested, curious as to
what people have been
using, whether they're using the
command line or another tool.
So I'll just add that
here, the progress thing.
And now we can open it.
Yeah, very good.
Right.
So what is the next?
The next was to make a new branch, right?
I believe so.
Make a branch and then make
a commit to that branch.
Oh, I'm all alone here.
You're back.
My Zoom apparently crashed.
It might be that we are
completely out of it, that
something happened on the outer side.
Oh, I am.
Yes.
Yeah, no, you're not everything is fine.
Okay, okay, then it was just my zoom.
The stream or the at least
my preview of it is
It's frozen to what [name]
was sharing before the crash.
And so I can reset it
to either [name]'s share or if
[name] shares, then that's fine.
I can start sharing again.
It will change the things.
So I will start sharing again now.
Yeah.
Go ahead.
Okay.
Okay, most people seem to
have been using the command line
so far, at least the people who responded.
Okay, that's okay as well.
So say, can you see my screen again?
Like the VS code screen?
I can.
It's on the stream.
Yeah.
Okay, so you get a pop up that
allows you to put in a new
like a name for the branch.
So yes, so you click on
on the three dots beside changes,
go to branch and create branch
and then you get a little window
at the at the top little pop up window.
That way you can type the
name for the branch and then
you hit enter and then it
It creates a branch, but
it creates a branch only locally.
So now maybe I can go back
and I can say, um, under this
is I create a new file, call it, um,
But instant powder, what makes it?
Yes.
Yeah.
Easy peasy.
Right.
So this is this file is now on
And so there's an indicator
that it's untracked, right?
So it's green and there's a U
next to it in the file browser.
Yes, that says it's untracked.
And if I want to actually
add it to the branch now, I
need to tick the plus to add
it to the staging area.
And then the command line that
will be the same as git add and then that file.
Yes.
So if the hitting the plus is the same
as on the command line saying
git add, and then the file name.
And then if you if I
want to commit, I've got a
nice little window here to put
in the commit message.
So that that
windows, maybe a little bit small,
if I wanted to write as like,
if this is if I wanted to write a like,
if this is a complicated
commit, and I wanted to write
a longer commit message.
Okay, I guess I can do that.
But so normally, so when I'm
on the command line, it has to get commit,
then it opens a text editor,
and I can indeed, okay,
and there's something similar happen
if I don't add anything.
It will
Just do not do that.
It wasn't saved.
OK, so you have to.
Yes, you have to save.
Then you get a text editor
that allows you to edit the message.
And maybe we'll talk about
the philosophy of how to think about auto
Uh, think of commit messages a bit later.
Yes.
And then, so, um, and then you can,
once you, you're done editing,
you can click the check mark thing.
Mm-hmm .
and then it will commit.
To be honest, I usually
use the short commit message because I'm lazy.
I dislike typing more
than absolutely necessary.
Yeah, I also, I mostly
make relatively small commits, so
then I also only write a short message there.
Yes, so let's go, let's see
what the next exercise is.
So we created a branch, then
we did a commit,
then well um i guess right
now we're on your new branch
how would i switch back to
the to the main branch so um
make this a bit wider so you
can see it what i do is
So you can, you can get
click at the bottom on the branch name.
And then you can you have
a selection of branches.
And then you can go back to the main batch.
Okay, and merging.
I guess now we want to
merge the new branch back to the main branch.
Yes.
So if we want to, for
some reason, I've got the
there.
I lost the repositories tab.
So that's this repository changes.
And then so I guess if you
want to wish to for the
zoom, then it's different.
If you want to go to if
you want to merge a branch,
you go here, you select the
branch that you just had, and then you can
merge this into the main batch.
Note that this is there's a
main and then there's an origin main.
So that means that the this,
this is what's on GitHub.
And this is what's on my computer.
Right, what was the next?
What's the next exercise?
uh we still also have to
uh look at the graph maybe
that might be yes well i
think with extensions you can but
um i don't have them so i'm
going to do it in the terminal
and maybe you can tell me how
to do it in the terminal but
so first thing to do on vs code
if you want to do something in the terminal
is you go to the to your menu
and then you go to the view menu
and you open the terminal
or hit the shortcuts and then
I will actually hide this and
Make this smaller.
So you can see actually
someone in the notes document
say whether the font size is
isn't as big enough.
For me, it's fine, but Right.
So I'd be typing here.
Okay.
So
That was just an ls, this directory.
Okay.
Then maybe, so there is
this command git log that
just lets you interact with the
sort of the history and you
can give it all sorts of additional parameters.
And what we're looking for
is dash dash graph.
it log dash dash graph dash
dash one line dash dash one
line dash dash decorate yes and
then dash dash all um okay
yeah that's that's it enter here
uh and then we want to see
Because it's right.
This is from the beginning.
Where's yours?
It's mine.
It's not there.
We did merge, right?
we did much yes can you just
do git log is that just so
there we should here we see we
did the pudding recipe.
So there is good news.
Don't show up in the graph.
But it seems to me that all the that
Simplify, restore.
It's all the way up there.
Yeah, it was.
It skipped a bunch, and that's I. OK.
OK, well, I don't tend to
use that kind of view very often.
I kind of poke around in the log itself.
But I guess the more complicated
a sort of branching
graph you have, the more
useful this kind of US and
then also the more useful it might
be to use an additional tool that
can maybe do a visualization a
little bit better than.
Yes.
Okay, just think we're already
very much over time.
Yes, I guess.
Sorry.
And we will come to that.
how to poke in the history
um after a short break um
Yes.
So we'll have a 10 minute break.
Yes, but we will first.
So to recap this, we
cloned the repository to our local computer
and did something that we
already did yesterday online.
We did now on our local computer
and we will continue exploring
how to work locally in
the rest of the day.
So for now, we'll have a 10 minute break.
And after that, we will
start with poking at the history.
So bye for now.
Okay, so welcome back from the break.
Hopefully, you got a chance
to stretch your legs a bit.
So now we have we have
loaned a repository to our own local computer.
And now we will look at how we can
we can poke at the history and explore
what has been going on
in that Git repository a bit
from the local site.
So as a first like a bit of a warm up,
let's look at a graphical way
to look at the history and
So there is this tool,
the git history browser, which you
can get by just adding this
specific string to the front
of the repository you want to look at.
And [name] is
Maybe now showing.
So yeah, so this is
the the repository we're going
to look at networks.
And then if you go if
you replace the front bit by
this get history string.
So, or just follow the link
on the yeah, on the lesson materials.
Then you will see
that there is a, that you
can browse the history, like you
can use your left and right keys
to go back in history
through the different commits, and
it will tell you what has
changed, who changed it.
And when it was.
So that's a sort of
more graphical way to browse the history,
which is, it's nice if you
want to take a look.
But in the end, if you're looking
for something very specific, you
will spend a lot of time
looking if you only use this kind of way.
So maybe we can go and go
to tools that are a bit more to the point.
So say you were
you were looking for a bit of text,
like you were looking for places
where you had before in
the code written fix me because
you wanted to go come back to
it at a later point and fix places.
Then, and we'll try this
on this NetworkX repository.
So have you already cloned it or?
I have not done anything yet,
so I will clone it.
Okay, so you clone it
from the command line, which it was a bit fast,
but you basically say git
clone, and then there you go.
You can see the history down
here, if you want.
Yeah.
Right?
So now I'm in, we are
in the network X directory in
the on the main branch.
And then if we wanted to say, search
for the string, fix me
anywhere in the repository, you
could use git grep.
And then minus, I fix the minus I do.
I'm not quite sure actually at the moment.
Well, that's just doesn't find
any fix me this way and this
way it finds even an uppercase.
Okay.
So there are some, there are
some to do's in here.
Yes, indeed.
But that's the current state
of the repository, right?
So if you wanted to do something of
that same type, you could use
the git log command that we
used earlier as well.
And then I think it's
uppercase S for search.
Mm-hmm.
And then the same text.
Oh, let's try this again.
So, yeah.
Yeah.
And then you get where it
was and it should also be.
So this shows me.
At what commit you have found it.
Okay.
So for example, this first
commit, it would be a commit
that has changed the fix me.
It has either removed or added one.
Yeah.
Okay.
I think so.
And because it is not explicit.
Okay.
Okay, so if you then wanted to,
because if you found with your git log,
for example, and a commit that
you want to look at in more detail.
For example, this first one.
For example, this first one,
and then you just copy the commit hash.
And then you can use git show.
You can get show and then the hash.
You can look at the commit.
And here you can see sort
of all of the differences.
So it always shows it has
removed a line and added a line instead.
Yes.
But you can also do is so if you
or whatever reason I'm not copying it,
you can try to just like
type in the first two, for
example, I'm just trying having
the first two letters and it also finds it.
I try the first four, then
you can see Oh, no.
It is this ambiguous, you're
giving it too little information,
but you don't always need to
give it the entire hash prefixes enough.
Yes.
But if you know the full
hash, you can copy this.
Because then this is the exact hash.
You know you'll get it.
So that's how to show it.
And we'll later get to how to have it more.
How to how to look at it a bit more like
if you do get show it'll show you in
that terminal what the commit was
but there's that doesn't mean
that you can browse the files
that were on the commit.
We get to how to do
that later, but first if you want to.
See for a given file who.
who did what in that file
on the terminal, you can use git annotate.
But you need to give it
a specific file in the current repository.
Which file do you want to look at?
Well, the lesson suggests convert matrix.
So
Convert underscore matrix.
Yes.
And then in this view, you
will see for each line when
it was changed, who changed it.
Yeah.
And I guess the way I'm
showing it is maybe a little bit
standard.
So because I'm squishing everything
to be better for viewing if you have a,
if you have some more real
estate in your for your terminal,
then it looks a little bit
more easier to to it's easier on the eyes.
Yes.
Because like this, it's hard to see
where the lines and but
usually you will have one line.
And that will have the the annotations.
So um,
Maybe I show it like this
when you only see part of it,
but you can see, oops, sorry.
And you can see more about,
uh, sort of what the lines
look like or what look like for you.
Um, one thing, um, that we
maybe wanted to, um,
quickly mention if you are
on GitHub and you want to find a hash.
You maybe want to show that quickly.
Yeah, right.
In, yeah, you go ahead.
So, yeah, so on GitHub,
you can, for example, right now
we're on the main branch.
You can, if you just want to
look at all of the commits or,
yeah, you can, so this would
be, again, a specific commit.
This is the prefix for that hash.
And then these are just all the commits.
And yeah, you've seen this already.
But so if we look at
a specific file, let's look at
the readme, for example.
Or let's look at the same
file that we just looked at.
So network, and then it
was convert matrix, this one.
Then you can, so in
here, instead of annotate, it's called blame.
uh for historical reasons again um
so here you can see basically
for every line who last changed it
and you can so at the
very right there's this blame
prior to change so here you can find the commit
this one here then, that is
the last commit before the change.
So if you have a breaking change
and you know sort of this
line is the problem, then you
can find the commit that sort
of last commit before the change to that line.
So it's just a convenience feature
if you wanted to go back
to that particular thing to try
out, or yeah, to investigate further.
Right.
So then, um, last thing before
we go to the exercise is exercise is
how do we actually go to, um,
how do we actually get to
look at the code that is in a historical commit?
And, um, that's basically, if
you go back to the, to the command line, um,
you use git switch to change a branch
and you can use git switch
with the create flag to create
a new branch, like call it
historic or whatever you want to call it.
And then you can give it
the hash of the commit that you.
I was too eager.
Sorry.
It is main.
Okay.
Give it a typo.
And then now some.
Now some hash.
Do you still have the hash
that you just earlier copied?
I'll just use the one that's down there.
Yeah.
Let's try that.
There we are.
Yeah.
And now you are on the
state of the repository when that,
when that commit was done and
then you can look at it and
look at the state of the files
as well and look at all the files.
Right.
So, um,
I think it is now time
to explore these for yourself in the exercise.
We've planned 20 minutes for this exercise.
And if you're absolutely stuck,
you can look at the solution
in the lesson notes or the lesson document.
I guess some of these things,
they are a bit tricky to do in VS Code.
Yeah.
Oh, yes.
If you are doing this with VS Code,
because most of these things
will be only possible on the command line,
but you can always use the
terminal in the command in VS
Code, as I showed in the last
part of the lesson for exercise seven.
So open the terminal and then
just use it normally.
And you can always ask
questions in the notes document.
There aren't any stupid
questions, only stupid answers.
And there is also, I think,
a Zoom room where you can go to get help.
But I'm not quite sure, maybe.
It should be one of the emails.
Yes, you should have gotten
an email where to go if you need help.
And yeah, let's start the break now.
Exercise break now.
Exercise goes on for 20 minutes.
So bye for now.
See you in 20 minutes.
Good luck.
Right welcome back from the exercise um.
It seems like there was quite a lot of.
discussion in the notes
about this exercise.
So we will.
Maybe.
go through the next.
um.
through the next part, only
go through it and discuss it
a bit, but not show a lot.
And then you have a little
more time to return to the
exercises if you want to, or
get some more other thinking done.
So the next thing we wanted
to discuss is what do you
do if you notice there
was something going wrong, but I
don't know how long this has been
going on how long when when
did this happen i'm i'm sure
it happened it was working at some point
but it's not working now i don't know
when it changed so um maybe we
can do it um without looking
at the lessons notes so far
so what would you do [name]
well knowing the knowing the the uh uh
the exercise is, well, I
guess one could randomly look
at previous commits or one, I
guess I would just start looking
at the last commit.
It's not bad.
I would look at the commit before that.
And at some point I would
probably do a more systematic
search, probably a bisection search.
So basically a divide and conquer approach.
I guess, yes.
I guess it's what you always
do in computer science.
At least that is one very
fast way to find things.
So it's nice, isn't it?
So yeah, Git actually does or
offers you a way to do just that.
To actually do the exercise,
you will have to have some way to find out
to decide whether your code
was working or not.
So this is not something
that's easily demoed quickly, but
we will go through the theory,
I think, and maybe show what's in the lesson.
So maybe you can scroll down a little bit.
So the command that you want
to use is git bisect.
And git bisect does the
So it's a multi-step process.
So first you say, I
want to start bisecting.
I want to find my problem.
Then you say git bisect
start on the command line.
This is only working on command line.
So if you're working in VS
code, you will want the terminal again.
And then you find a commit where you,
that's way, way back that
you know that's good.
then you tell git bisect
that this command this hash
was good with saying git bisect good
and then you give it the
the command hash or the the commit hash
and so we we have an exercise code
that you can use so this
gets bisect into uh exercise here
uh yeah and i guess in that exercise
You don't know when it last worked,
so you would probably just
start at the first, at the very first commit.
Yeah.
Or that's how I would do it.
If I don't know anything.
So you can start there.
And then you find the
commit where it's bad.
And then that's probably the
last commit that you've got.
Because that's when you
notice that something was going wrong.
So you do git bisect start.
Okay.
Then I know that bad is now.
Yeah, like.
And then.
Oh, for example, like this.
So the first one is this one.
OK, and then you can see we
are now on an entirely different.
So it shows you here the
beginning of the hash, or also
when you do get status, it shows you that hash.
And then you can try.
So for example, here, 3.57,
that's not quite pi.
So you know this one is also bad.
And then it gives you a new.
And well, yeah, it does
it by section search.
I won't go through the
entire thing now, but this is the gist.
And you try it again.
And then you can say, is it good or bad?
That one's good.
OK.
And yeah, it tells you,
it estimates how many times you
have to do this.
Yeah, it is for, I think
in total, this had, what, 500 commits
or so, so it, to
search it, that's relatively quickly,
like a few iterations and you'll find it.
Right.
So this is a quick view on the git bisect.
And that is all the content for the lesson.
Um, we had a look at how to, um,
how to look at the history
in, in a repository, how to,
um, show specific commits of
the repository once, once we've
got the hash, where to get the
hash and how to, um,
look at who did what change
with the git annotate, which
is the equivalent of the blame
that you saw on GitHub yesterday.
Sorry.
There was someone that said
that the explanation of bisect was too fast.
Well, okay, yes.
So maybe, and then we had
a very short excursion to the Git bisect,
which is a way of doing a
search on a Git repository to
where a specific change happened.
What you need for it is
a way to test whether that
was the commit that you wanted or not.
And
So yes, the idea with the
git bisect was not for you
to follow along so much as to
show that there is this option.
It's actually something that
doesn't really happen all that
often in my experience.
But if you are ever in
that situation, you should know that
there is a command called git bisect.
That's what you should know.
And then you can look up
in the manual what the actual commands are.
So we are now at seven minutes to the hour.
I would say there's something,
so the next thing that will
happen is the rather longer lunch break.
And to make up for it,
we will do the lunch, we will
have a lunch until the full hour again.
And so it's one hour and
five minutes at the moment.
So that's it from the instructors.
Do we have anything else?
You said one hour and five minutes.
So for me, it's right now 1355.
So five minutes to the full hour.
So the lunch hour, the lunch is one hour.
Yes.
but we have it is five minutes
before the hour so we have one hour
and five minutes lunch break
very well okay um yeah so for anyone
who is uh who wants to you
can have a look at the at
the get bisect maybe yourself
you're interested um yeah um
If you can show the
course page quickly, show the
schedule on the course page.
So yeah, so we'll be back in, well,
at the hour, and we'll then
talk about how you can use
Git to share your work.
Allows you to, well, I
mean, we already talked about
GitHub, so how you can get your work
to be visible for others so
that they can use it.
And some of your practical advice,
how we actually do things,
which parts of these are
actually useful and which are not.
So, and what to avoid.
So hopefully this wasn't
too complicated, but we did go
into some more advanced things.
So the next session should again be,
well, compared to Git bisect,
we're going back to more,
more everyday things, more
practical things that hopefully you
can not just follow along,
but actually do yourself in your own work.
Okay.
But yeah, it is also good to know
how powerful KDE is, how you
can do things that, you can
do these more advanced things
that wouldn't be possible if
you didn't track the whole history.
We can go and find the
bug that you're having trouble with.
Okay.
But yeah, so we'll be back
after the lunch break.
What should I say?
Have a good time.
Not everybody's having lunch, but
if you are.
So yeah, bye and see you.
And we're back.
I hope everybody had a good break.
Yeah, so I'm going to
briefly again go through the bisection part.
And then we will move on
to how you can publish a
project that you've already started
and version control it with
Git and also then publish it on GitHub.
Yeah, so this bisection is supposed
to be a tool that you can
use if you have a problem.
You find that the current
commit doesn't work anymore,
whatever that means.
So something that is not
the way it's supposed to be.
And you are certain that at
some point in the past, it worked.
And then you can go back
to that commit and check
whether it actually worked back then.
And then you can tell Git that, well,
first you tell it that you
want to do a bisection now.
So you do git bisect start.
And then you can tell it
the good commit that is still
working and the latest.
So the latest good commit
and the earliest bad commit.
And then it will automatically
check out commits in the middle.
And you can then test whether
they are good or bad and tell Git.
And then it sort of
conveniently, most efficiently searches
for you the commits that are
like it gives you commits that you can test.
and then tell Git whether that
was a good one or a bad one.
And when you do it, we'll
then give you the next one.
This way, you'll find
really efficiently the last commit
that broke things.
And for the exercise itself,
so there is this repository
that we prepared that you can use.
So you would just clone that
and then start bisecting on that.
To do that exercise, you will
need a Python installation, because
the test that you can use
in order to determine whether or
not this is a good or a
bad commit, you will need Python
to run that bit of code.
And it will then return a number,
and you can decide whether
that is close enough to pi
for you, for your purposes.
yeah i think that is all on bisect
that made things a bit clearer
than my last attempt um but
yeah then let's move on to
the next part which is
sharing the work.
So yeah, we're going back
to the schedule of and then
there's the current session is linked there.
So click on sharing work.
And then we have the lesson.
Okay, so maybe first, why?
Why do why does one do that?
Well, usually you don't really
start with a Git repository, right?
Usually you just start with some code.
Well, after today, you
hopefully always start with a Git repository.
Oh, but still, it doesn't
really matter whether you start
with the empty Git repository or
you start with a folder on
your machine and connect that
to a Git repository.
But first thing you need to do is turn
that folder on your disk
into a Git repository, into a local repository.
And now we're going to
practice and go through how to do that.
Very well.
So yeah, for this exercise,
you will just start with creating
a new folder and put some stuff into
that folder that you want
to version control, ideally some text.
And then you can turn this
directory into a Git repository.
And then you push it to
GitHub or GitLab if you're using that.
But for this, we will focus on GitHub.
and then you can share it there.
So the exercise offers
three different paths, only using
GitHub, the VS Code way and
with a command line.
The RStudio is currently
under construction.
So you're a bit on your
own if you wanted to try it with RStudio.
We are going to show,
after even the exercise, we're going
to show it with VS Code,
which is really, really quick.
And then maybe discuss a bit
how it would go on the command line.
But you're free to do it
whichever way you like.
All right.
Is there anything else or
should we just let loose?
No, I think that's about it.
There's 25 minutes scheduled
for this exercise.
So that would make it half past.
As always, the notes document
will stay open.
You're free to ask questions
in the notes document or go to
your other sources of possible help.
And yeah, we will see each
other again at half past.
So bye for now.
And we're back.
We're still working our way
through some of the questions, but yeah.
So you've now initialized a
repository in the folder, your
personal paper project, and pushed it to Git.
or some other place where
you wanted to push it.
Yeah, so we'll maybe do a
little bit of a demo, how
you would go about doing this in VS Code.
So I'll switch over to my VS Code window.
And I am here in a folder that has
two files, a license and a
README that I haven't been on Git at any point.
So I just made them up myself.
Now we go to the source control
and then we can either
initialize the repository and then set up the
Git connection, or we can
just directly publish to Git.
And then we need to, then
VS Code asks whether I want
to publish as a private repository
or as a public repository.
What would I, what should I select there?
[name], what do you think?
So it depends a little bit.
So if you
through the private repository,
then for now only you can see it.
But you can also give
other people access to it.
So you can still collaborate
with other people.
For a public repository, everybody
can see it immediately.
So if you have something
that you don't mind just
publishing, like sharing it with
anyone, then you can pick a public one.
And otherwise, it would probably
be better to go for private.
Well, there isn't anything in here,
so I think it's fine to put
it as a public repository.
I want both these files.
And then it's waiting.
Now it wants to commit.
Commit message.
I hate writing commit messages.
Metal commit is a good one.
Very classic.
Yes.
I used to be thinking
quite hard about that.
I don't know.
Okay.
So now I can even open it on GitHub.
Okay, so this creates now
a new repository on GitHub?
It creates a new repository
on GitHub with the name of the repository.
And it's got my license.
When did you pick that name?
Is that just the name of the folder?
Or?
Yes.
That was when I
there was a message asking, is this,
so it's the name of the
folder, and then it was asking
me whether this name was okay.
And it was checking, is that a valid name?
Is it taken?
And then it says, we suggest
this name, is it okay?
And then you could probably
also change that name, but I didn't.
And I guess it's possible that
that name is not allowed
because you already have a
repository with that name in your namespace.
Yeah, it might be.
So then it would probably give
an error or something.
I think it would actually
just make a suggestion of
a slightly different name.
Okay.
Yeah.
So it's got the two files here on Git.
Okay.
That's it.
Very good.
Well, that was easy then.
Yes, that is really, really easy.
It's not that much more work
on the command line, isn't it?
Well, I guess usually on the command line,
the command line does not
create a GitHub repository for you.
Yes, if I go back to the to the lesson,
and then we can use
the command line instructions for the exercise.
So you on on the command
line, you need to make you do
need to do get in it first, right?
Yes.
So that creates this dot git folder.
That that contains all of the history
and everything and sets all
of the metadata and then
I guess the dash B
main, usually it's probably gives
you a default branch.
And I think these days that is main.
In the olden times it was master.
But yeah, then you just add
your files as you are used to.
And then commit.
And then you've got a local Git repository.
And then that's where the
slightly more difficult
thing step begins for at
least from from my, from
my perspective, because you need
to create an empty repository on GitHub.
But GitHub gives you all
these tries to push creating
a readme and everything on you.
So you need to remember to
not to do not let make it add a readme.
Because otherwise, there's going
to be something in that repository.
Yes.
And then... But if that turns out,
like if you add a readme,
if you are convinced by GitHub
to add a readme, then that's
also not a huge problem.
Then it will just, when you
try to push to it, it will
just say, well, you have to
resolve all of these conflicts first.
So then you will have to
pull first and resolve the
conflicts and then you can push.
But yeah, if you want
to avoid jumping through those
hoops, then you just create
a completely empty one.
Yes.
Because some of the things
that GitHub suggests to you
are actually quite useful.
Like the default gitignore that
it has are often quite handy.
I like those.
Yeah.
So I think VS Code actually
does also have the option to
add a default gitignore.
Oh.
I'm not quite sure where it
is at the moment though.
So I'm not gonna try to find it on screen.
Yeah.
And then, but from the command line,
now that went to, if you
got a repository, then you have
this, you want the SSH version, right?
Because HTTPS.
uh so normally anymore yeah
normally you cannot like the
for security reasons the authentication
uh you cannot sort of
https password authenticate anymore
so you would need to have
set up ssh keys and then you
would need to use the ssh version
of the url to push to oh
yes that's one thing that vs
code does more or less automatically for you so
This didn't happen when we were showing,
but the first time you use VS Code,
you will get a pop-up
asking you to authenticate to GitHub.
And then it will save
your authentication and use
that to authenticate you towards GitHub.
So you don't even need to,
I don't think you even need to set up SSH keys.
Well, only, I guess earlier,
you could also use the SSH
version, but you didn't have to.
It also worked with the HTTPS for this one.
Yeah, I'm trying to think
whether there's a,
sort of a compelling reason
why one should recommend setting
up SSH keys anyway, if it works with HTTPS,
someday that you might run
into a situation where you would
need it, but then just do it then.
So yeah, do whatever.
I mean, it's not a big deal, right?
You create an SSH key and
then, I mean, there's instructions
in the install session
Yeah, there's instructions on
GitHub itself also that are,
I would say, quite comprehensive
that are useful.
Right.
Yeah, I think everything else just works.
As soon as you've set that
up, you just continue working in VS Code.
as you normally would or on
the terminal or whatever you're using.
And then you can just as not
as we saw with the other
ways where you can commit your
changes and push them.
But I think we will
discuss pushing and using
the remote repository more
in tomorrow, actually, in the
when we're working about when
we're talking about collaborative working.
Yeah, then it gets a
little bit more interesting when
you have to actually content
with other people also messing around in there.
Okay.
Well,
But, so there's a little
bit of discussion on the
lesson about remote repository, what
is a remote repository?
But I think, yeah, you can read that.
But I think is more
interesting is why would you
say you're working on something just yourself?
Why would you actually use
a remote repository?
So I guess there's a number of reasons.
So I always work in Git
whenever I work on any kind of text.
And then, well, A, it's useful to just,
for example, if I'm working
on different machines, then I can
use that to synchronize it
to different machines.
To have a backup is usually quite useful.
If one of those
aforementioned machines gets lost, then
not my entire work is gone.
Yeah, I think, and then just
if I at some point needed
to share with someone after all,
then it's right there and then it's easy.
And at least for my
work, that happens quite a lot that I
that at some point, I've
so I've been working on on
some on some piece of code for some time.
And at some point, somebody
else would find that useful.
So I just can, I can
just share the GitHub link with
them and they have it.
And they also have all of
the sort of metadata that is
in that GitHub repository to
uh understand sort of the history
and how things came to be yeah i think
for me the the most often
the reason uh why i put
something on on github or gitlab
or wherever is because i
work on different computers
So I work in the office on
a computer and I work on
a different computer at home.
And when I'm working remotely,
sometimes I even have to use
my own private computer for some things.
And that is very convenient.
It can get a bit confusing
because you can maneuver yourself into...
into situations where you've
got your remote mounted a repository,
and a folder from a different computer
that has the repository and
you have your own local repository copy.
Like it's confusing to try to avoid that.
Yeah, I pretty much never
remote mount anything anymore.
Yeah, so one thing maybe that's also
might be interesting to mention is
that so if you're working, for example,
on our HPC machines, then you
are at some point also working
on a different machine.
And you might sometimes also
want to remote mount something on that machine.
Or you can use Git to synchronize things.
So there's different ways of
doing this, again, in whatever works for you.
I tend to just use Git
and loan stuff around.
Yeah.
One more thing that's really, I
think a lot of my older
projects, I don't have them
anymore locally, but they are
still on Git somewhere, on GitHub.
So if I ever have this time
to pick them up again, they'll be there.
And I know I've got that
sort of safety net that it's
not going to be lost.
Yeah.
If you just kept them on a local drive
and then use at some point
have a new machine or something,
then you might lose track of things.
Yeah.
Right, so maybe we should
be heading into the break a bit earlier.
There's maybe one more thing
to discuss the last step or
the last part there on the lesson plan.
True, yes.
So the question is, is
putting software on GitHub
or somewhere publishing?
Well, I guess technically it is public.
If it's a public repository, yes.
Publish does not mean findable in
a lot of cases.
It also goes for other locations
where you traditionally publish
things, but yes.
So it is not fair in
the fair science sense.
For that you might want
to do some additional things?
especially for the science
thing, citability is maybe something
that is useful.
Well, that's not just software,
but also data, like citability
is really useful for lots
of kinds of different kinds of information.
And for that, there's
different services that you can use.
Yeah.
I've only ever used Zenodo,
but- Yeah, me too.
I hear there are similar
services that you can use.
Yeah.
But yeah, so technically, it's publicing,
but in practice, it is only
the first step to actually
getting it published.
And because it doesn't make
sense if you publish it, and
no one can find it.
So for that, there are other
And since the search engines
are getting worse and worse these days,
and the AI doesn't necessarily
know about your stuff either.
Yes.
With that said, I think we
have about 10 minutes break now.
And then after that, we will
discuss a bit more about how
we actually use Git.
and what are good practices,
good enough practices, what are
maybe not so good ideas.
Yeah.
We'll also, if there's any,
we'll pick out some questions
maybe to discuss in some more detail.
And yeah, if we have
not extensively replied to all
of them, then we'll catch up on that.
Okay, so we would go into the break now,
and break time will stop
at two minutes before the hour, so at 58.
[name], can you start the break?
All right, welcome back after the break.
We are now on the last bit of today's date.
And we will maybe do a
bit of a more discussion like thing about what
what to do and what not
to do, what are good practices.
So we will first look
at the practical advice.
If you go back to the
schedule, you can click on the
link as I do now, and then
it will open the current lesson.
And then, yeah, here's a few
topics that we think might
be useful to discuss.
The first one is if you're
working on the command line
to use Git status.
So maybe I'd like to
talk about command line versus
more graphic user interface ways first.
[name], what do you like
better, command line or UI?
I don't use any IDEs.
I use just command line.
I use Vim as a text editor, and I
kind of when I started
writing things on the computer
about 20 years ago or so I
started in an IDE actually and I found
that sort of frustrating because
it I always felt it was
hiding things from me of like
about it wasn't really showing me
how what was going on I
found that annoying and then I
found it a lot more uh
yeah easier to understand what what
things are actually going on,
and there's just terminal.
So how do you not lose
track of where you are on the command line?
Well, it's similar to when you
just sort of get specific, but
you just use a lot of LS
and PWD in order to know where
you are, and then you will
get some sort of sense of
where you currently are.
And yeah, then just use good
status a lot in the same
way to remind yourself.
Yeah, I guess.
Git status is the one command
that I use most often.
When I start working on a Git repo
or I open something, I start
by typing git status.
And then I remember something
might have changed.
So I go git fetch and then
I do git status again.
Yeah.
But so also, because I'm
mostly working on the command line,
I have the command line configured
in a way that is helpful for me.
So I think someone already
mentioned in the notes, I have
like my like shell prompt
already gives me information about
my the status of my Git
repository that I'm currently in.
And the editor does as well,
similar to an IDE.
And so then you sort of
use it maybe a little bit less,
but still you do it all of the time.
Yeah.
Right.
Then commit messages.
I already said at some point,
I think I hate writing commit messages.
I think in a sense it's
similar to writing comments.
Except I like commit messages
kind of more because
comments, because everybody doesn't
really enjoy writing them, they
then get stale because they
then describe a state of the
code that is not actually there anymore.
But the nice thing about
commit messages is that that's not true.
They are only specific to that very commit.
So I actually like them a lot more.
And, well, I don't think I
spend a long time thinking
about commit messages.
Yeah, I would say I
write relatively like small commits
and then also relatively
short commit messages.
And yeah, I don't know.
What do you do?
Well, what I do is mostly
I commit small things.
Yes.
So and then the commit.
Usually I do things in a branch.
So the branch name tells what's going on.
and then the commit is a
lot of the time what i do is
i commit at the end when at
the end of the day like um
and then i just say status
and the date just really a
null commit message right it
doesn't really tell you anything
about the commit
I'm not sure about that.
I think the last thing I did.
If I read that, I would think, okay,
this is sort of, this
might be broken, which is
already something that's good to know.
I know this is sort of
not a complete, this is sort
of an in-between state.
And I think that's a
useful information to have.
So it's better than this
is a commit message.
Yes.
Okay.
True.
True in that way.
But yeah, I do write very,
very, very short commit messages.
But I try to keep branches small.
And then I do write, when
I do a merge commit, then
I write a longer description of
what's going on and why.
Yeah, I think that's also similar.
working in branches, and then
like a sort of description or justification
for that branch is then
more deserves a little bit
more thought than just some any
of hundreds of thousands commits your writing.
Yeah, I mean, sometimes I put
in a commit message where I think it is broken.
Like,
still not doing this or this or whatever
so i know where to pick it up back
when when i'm getting back to it
but yeah mostly i work i
don't work with lots of people
on the same on the same branch
on the same topic so it's
mostly internal yeah to remind
me and that's yeah but
I think commit messages get
more important if you're working,
the more people you're working
with, the more important the
commit messages get.
Yes.
And also the less you know
the people that you're working with.
If you're in a huge project where you,
if you're just working with
one other person and you know
them really well and you know
how they sort of think about commit messages,
then you can sort of infer more.
And if you know these people
not at all, then that's more difficult.
Yeah.
But one really, really important
thing is the last advice.
It's better to make any
commit than no commit.
And if writing the commit
message means that you're not
going to commit it because it's
too much effort to write the commit message,
then this is a better
commit message than not committing at all.
Yes.
And also, well, if stuff
breaks, then we can also look
at the commits that are coming
before and after and at the context.
So even, yeah, not all is
lost if you don't have to.
The important thing is that
you commit your stuff.
Yes.
And often.
How often do you commit?
So I don't do the end of the day thing.
I currently am thinking of repository
that I'm working on that
has uncommitted things in it
because I am working on it.
So sometimes I still have
like a virtual terminal session
floating around on a remote
computer somewhere that I need to get back to.
And so sort of when I finish that thought,
I commit what's going on and
then I close everything and
sort of start again.
Um, that's normally how I do it.
I'm not sure whether that is, um,
kind of ideal or even recommendable,
but I guess, uh, I, uh,
I'm still sort of kind of
attached to, to, um, at
least finishing a thought in order to, yeah.
So, uh, yeah, I, I, I have to say
that I don't quite follow
this advice, but maybe I should.
Quite often.
And.
the way my life is at the moment, it's,
I can't finish the thought before
I have to do something else.
Yeah.
So, um, and leaving it floating around,
I know that I will not get
back to it and still have
that same thought and know where I've been.
So it's safer to commit it.
Yeah.
That's why it's nice.
So these, these, that, uh,
sort of the terminal state
that I'm working in is preserved.
So I'm, I can, it is
relatively easy for me to
return to something that I left.
But yeah.
What level of branching
complexity is necessary for each project?
Hmm.
That really depends on the
people involved with it, I would say.
What do they like?
What's the most complicated
branching structure you've ever seen?
So I've worked on relatively
few large and really complicated projects.
And most of them are really, I would say,
quite good about the way they
do it is you make a new branch for a feature.
And I'm not sure how
much we discussed this, but there's
when you merge a branch back to main,
you can just sort of do
this via like a merge commit,
or you can also rebase.
So rebasing means you sort
of, you take that branch and you
cut it off and then you put it back on top.
And this way you can have essentially
that in that tree that you're building,
the trunk just gets ever
longer and the sort of more
recent branches are all at the top.
And this way you have a
relatively sort of tidy history in a sense.
And the, the most of the projects
that I've worked were involved
with in any way kind of followed that, uh,
that rough idea that, um,
that you always rebase before
you merge a feature branch back into main.
Um, yeah.
How about you?
Oh.
Nothing.
I mean, like the usual, you branch
and then you merge and then
the main moves forward.
I don't think we do much rebasing.
Yeah, rebasing, it's sort of
It is a little bit of
a hassle in the beginning, or it
can be when you have to do it.
But if you then have to
at some point return and
dig through the history, then
you can be rewarded for doing that.
And if you do it
consequently from the beginning, then
it's also easier.
Yeah, maybe we can have a few more people,
a few more opinions from
a few more seasoned people.
So I don't know, [name],
would you maybe join us or [name]?
Yes.
Hello.
Can you hear or see me out there?
I can see you in here.
I'm losing my voice, but... Yeah.
So... Yeah.
You've been in this business
much longer, I think, at least.
Maybe.
No, but anyway, yeah.
It's good to get more thoughts about stuff.
What was the most
complicated branching structure you've
ever seen?
I mean, most projects I do
at most have a pull
request based workflow, which
is something you'll see tomorrow.
So basically there's one main branch
and then people can work
on features separately, test them,
and then get them merged to
the main code that everyone's using.
I guess the main reason it
would get more complex than that is
if you have like multiple deployments
or multiple versions of the
code that need to be used
by everyone at the same time.
And yeah, like it can work,
but to be honest, most
of our scientific projects aren't
really like that.
I mean, maybe something like
NumPy or SciPy or R or Python.
I mean, it will have the
old version that's still being
maintained for a few years.
Well, a new one's coming, but that's...
That's not really relevant to
most of our stuff.
So yeah, as simple as possible.
Most of my projects, I
just push directly to main because
I'm the only one using it.
There's no reason to make a
pull request if no one else
is going to know about it.
And if I break it, it's my job to fix it.
So I'm fine with that trade-off.
I guess if you're working
alone, the only reason to
use multiple branders at all is
if you are working on multiple
features at the same time.
And I guess maybe some
people work like that, but
I guess probably most people
will finish one thing before
they start another thing.
But yeah, it depends on
how you organize things.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, there's some reasons,
but I definitely say like some
other people in the notes
are saying the simpler, the
simplest thing that works for you
is the best for you.
Yeah.
Unless you just want to
learn stuff in which case, yeah, go try stuff.
But yeah.
What else is there to discuss?
What other practical stuff?
Well, the next topic that we've
got on the lesson is staging and committing.
Is that something we even
talked about today?
I think that's now mostly... Well, no,
I think it was... I
think that the committing was
discussed on day one.
Okay, yeah.
And we briefly mentioned that in the
in the, um, when we showed how to,
um, how to put a repository
on, on GitHub that you then
need to make you commit.
Yeah.
To make it, to put it,
put things into the repository.
But, um, yeah.
So how often do you
commit, Bridget, if you're
working on something?
Mm-hmm.
I guess it depends on if
it's a new project or an old project.
If it's a brand new project
and I don't know what I'm
doing yet, it might either be quickly
because I might break it at any time
or it might be not so
quickly, more like every day
or something once I get to
a good benchmark because I
figure smaller commits don't really
give me much.
I mean,
I'm probably going to break
it no matter what, but I'm
just right there so I can fix it.
I really want to start committing
when I'm worried I'll do
something that will break something else.
And then it would take me
days to go backwards and
figure out what happened.
I fix it, which definitely
has happened more times than
I'd like to admit.
I'm here working on my research code,
and suddenly there's some obvious
bug to it.
And I didn't commit in several days.
And I don't know where the bug started.
And it takes several more
days to figure out what I did
in an hour and undo that.
And that's enough to scare
anyone into committing often, if you ask me.
And for that, you know,
it doesn't matter what the commit message is,
you know, how small it is, as long
as there was anything before I
did this, I would be able
to go backwards to it.
So
Yeah.
To me, it's a bit, the
more people are involved in
the project, the more often I commit.
Like, if it's just me
doing something, it's like, okay,
yeah, I'll do, I'll commit at
the end of the day.
Or I try to commit, I
try to remember to commit at the
end of the day, let's put it like that.
But for things where we've
been working with others, yeah.
I did commit quite often.
Yeah.
In a way to have things to go back to.
If someone said, can you merge
now so I can see where you're at?
Yeah.
That I could quickly.
And it's like the way
to explain what happened.
So to tell people what I've
done to the code, I don't have
to go tell them I've changed this, that they can
look at the recent commits, see, okay,
yeah, X and Y and Z
has happened, and none of it
affects me, so I'm just going to go on.
And then they can ask more later if needed.
I think that's more or less
the topics of things.
And then we have one last
thing, which is what to avoid when using Git.
What to avoid when committing, right?
Don't add your SSH keys.
Yes.
So don't add private data.
Yes, yes.
Don't add private data.
Especially don't add sensitive
private data.
Yeah.
Because it is a real, real
hassle to get it out again.
Yeah, I think there was an
analysis done at some point
about how many secrets are
just public on GitHub.
And there's a lot of them.
Yes.
Because even if you delete
something, it won't be deleted
unless you retroactively delete
it from history as well.
Which is... For some things, it is just,
like, if you want to be
absolutely sure, it is impossible.
It is, like, actually, because
you don't know who cloned it
in the meantime, and all of those things.
So for those things, you just have to,
like, regenerate all secrets
and, like, invalidate them.
If it's a public repository.
Also if it's a private one.
There are exploits.
So while pushing stuff on
GitHub is not publishing it, it
is also no longer any more
secret in the sense that... Yeah, well,
but if it were, say, you
had something in a Git
repository on your computer just
to make the versioning, then you
can be pretty sure that no one else cloned it.
Yes.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So yeah, but it's still it is
I had to do that once when
I just started my, my first postdoc.
It's a hassle.
Don't do it.
So that is where the
gitignore file comes in.
Anything that needs to be
in the same folder as your Git repository
but should never, ever be
committed, you can put it
in the gitignore file.
And this also helps with
the generated files.
And if you're using IDEs,
they all create their own
workspace files or whatever they are called.
Nope.
They actually create a hidden folder
that has their settings and
everything and stuff for that workspace.
The IDE.
And you don't want to come across.
It's not going to be
useful for anyone else.
It's like your own stuff or something.
So that's something that you...
If you're using VS Code or RStudio or...
Yeah.
Maybe we could say, can
we define what generated files means?
What's a good example?
Maybe like LaTeX documents.
So if you're writing a paper in LaTeX
and you're using version control,
you have the source code for
the paper in LaTeX, and then
you have the PDF that comes out of it.
And there's no need to
commit the PDF because it
can automatically be made from the other stuff.
But also some intermediate files.
It also creates this dot
out and some... Right, yeah.
So all this other stuff.
And then you'll always get messages
that say all these files
have changed every time you rebuilt the paper.
But it's not really useful to see that.
And it just distracts you
from what's actually being changed.
Actually, sometimes, especially in
the writing paper case...
I would be tempted to say,
if you have a version that
you discussed with other collaborators
that you send to your
supervisor or something for
comments, save that as a permanent version.
I mean, you can get it
back, but maybe you want it permanently there.
I would tag that.
You can tag it, sure.
Then you need to have an
extra step if you want to go back to it.
If you want two versions at
the same time, you can put
them in there and they will stay.
But then I would also rename
the PDF files to something that's
not the same generated file.
Right.
Yeah.
Mm-hmm.
But, yeah, that's, I
guess, personal preference.
Yeah.
Just compilation output.
So if you're writing in
the, like, old-school compiled
languages, then all of the
actual executables and libraries
and stuff would probably not be permitted.
Yes.
Then more things that you shouldn't commit.
I guess we already talked
about postponing commits before.
Yes.
Yeah.
But let's talk about huge files first.
Because these are files that
you don't always, you don't
ever want to commit, at least to GitHub.
That's probably your data files.
Mm-hmm.
GitHub is for code and,
well, maybe paper writing and
that, but it's not for data.
Enrique, do we have any advice on
where to store data if you
want to have it version
controlled and published?
yeah this is actually something
that we will cover next week
on the kind of sharing
aspects and social aspects of
coding sharing code and sharing data
and there are different practices
but for example keeping the
data in one repository or with
one system we will mention this
type of other extensions to git like git-annex
and the code with the
different repository this is also
a good way to keep the
truly private stuff which could
still use a repository that
never leaves the computer and
the public stuff that can go to github
and so on but i don't want
to spoil the fun this is next
week and the week after stopping so yeah
By the way, there's feedback
in the bottom of the notes
that you can be editing while
we're doing stuff here.
Yeah.
And we have five minutes to wrap up.
So we already discussed
the postponing commits, committing
unrelated changes together.
I think it's better to, if
you don't have the time to
put them in separate commits,
it's better to commit them than
to not commit them at all.
So yeah.
Yeah.
Like, you know, a few times when I've
hurt myself by breaking
something has always been when it said,
I don't want to commit
now because they have to
separate out the different stuff I've done.
So I don't have time to do that now.
I'll do it later.
And then I add something
more and everything goes bad.
So yeah, I mean, definitely
if it's better to commit something,
then try to make it too perfect.
Okay.
Yeah.
And then what to avoid
when working with batches.
Who here has the problem?
Sometimes you begin doing some work
and then it comes time to commit it
and then share it to push
it, which we'll learn more about tomorrow.
And then you forgot to pull first.
So you're not working on the latest copy.
And then it's like so much
work to recover those.
Too often.
Which...
Well, it happens to me all
the time, but usually it's not that difficult.
You just try to push, and
then it tells you, no, you can't do that,
and you pull, and then you fix the... Yeah,
well, that's the best case,
but the few times when
it actually is difficult, then...
Yeah, I really am regretting my life then.
And I mean, it is not
like this is a problem with Git.
Basically, it's like saying
you start working on a document
before you ask the other
collaborators, can you send me
the latest version of it?
And then like, yeah.
Well, then I will also do
like a lot of duplicate work usually.
Yeah, yeah.
I guess for code that
doesn't happen that often.
Yeah.
Anyway, yeah.
Yeah, and these other
things, like overengineering stuff,
trying to make your little
project too advanced, most stuff is small.
So that's completely fine.
Don't make it more complicated
than it has to be.
That's a KISS principle, right?
Yeah.
KISS do everything.
Should we begin wrapping up for the day?
We can keep having more
comments or questions from people down below.
Change to the notes.
So what did we cover today?
Was it basically everything
in the schedule?
Yes, basically everything in the schedule.
So we started out by...
cloning a project from GitHub
to our local machine and looking at it locally.
Then we looked at how to,
once we've got it locally, how to
get it, to dig into it,
what's happened in the history.
Then after the lunch break,
we did the inverse version of
when we have a folder on our,
or a project on our machine and
want to put it on GitHub.
And then now we're discussing,
or for the last few minutes
we have been discussing, what we
actually do or not do.
And that's it.
So what's coming tomorrow?
Yes.
So tomorrow, day three, will
be about collaborative Git.
And in my opinion, it's the
best day of this day.
No offense to you.
You did an amazing day today.
But what I'm trying to say is
that you really see the power
of Git, that you can really...
After tomorrow, you can literally go out,
find the project that you
like, find a typo, find an
error, suggest an improvement
and start submitting pull requests
and help any software projects
or it doesn't even have to be software.
It can be web pages,
documentations that are hosted with Git.
So it's really the best that
you can get out of it.
and so because of this
there will actually be we
already mentioned this in the
email last evening afternoon there
will be also in this other
evening in this other in the
second email that will be sent
today so for those of you who
are not in an in-person room
and are planning to do this
type of you know collaborative work
with us on the stream you
will need to request access so
that then we can add you to the repository
so that you basically have
the rights to push changes
accept other people proposals and
so on so please follow the
instructions in the email
And we will also highlight them
here at the ends of the notes.
And thanks for the feedback.
This is fantastic.
It's really what we need.
Anything else?
We would be one minute over time.
Yeah, I guess we should call it good.
Any comments or feedback?
yes so well maybe wrapping
up the feedback is there thank you
so much to [name] [name] [name] [name]
and all the helpers visible
and invisible that have been
there answering all the
questions helping people in zoom
i think it was successful day
we will continue tomorrow the videos
as soon as we press stop
the video will be immediately
available twitch tv
And write all the feedback you want.
We always take feedback into account.
So I think we are good to go.
Yeah, great.
So see you tomorrow, we hope.
Okay, bye.
Bye, everyone.