hello hello hello everybody let's check
if our zoom colleagues are able
to hear us because you know
behind the scenes we have a
zoom channel that actually everyone
is welcome to join
right so the stream should be live
and here we are for day
four code refinery in this first
10 minutes we just chit chat
that's [name] hello [name] hey
that's [name] hello [name] hello and [name] hey
So I still don't see any
feedback from our Zoom chat.
If you hear us, if you
see us, please make some noise.
But anyway, so today it's
an interesting day.
It's maybe, I mean, it sounds, of course,
if every time I say this
is the most important day of
Code Refinery, it feels a
bit, you know, hyperbolic.
But maybe this is the most
important day of Code Refinery
because it's really the day where
we link all together the why
are we here and what's the final goal.
In this notes document that
I just shared with you
via email, there's already some icebreakers.
So if you were with us
last week, you should be
already familiar with this.
But if you are just joining for this day,
basically you can scroll at the
top of the document, of
this notes document that I'm sharing.
and at the top there's a pencil
so if you click on the
pencil you can answer these icebreakers
and the first one is interesting
and of course i'm going
to ask our instructors of the day
what do they think of have
you ever heard the sentence
works on my computer what does
this mean in practice how do
you solve this problem what about
[name] have you ever heard it
Yeah, well, I guess I've heard it,
and it was usually just very simple stuff,
some missing packages, dependencies,
so generally...
looking at error messages or
how the problem presents itself
has been easy to solve in my hands.
But I think maybe [name]
has some more stories to share.
I just wrote one down.
We just yesterday had a user
where they had a program, a Python program
that is running on several
of the machines in the lab,
but for some reason doesn't run on his machine.
Admittedly, we tried to figure out,
we didn't find the final reason,
but the assumption that
I'm currently working on is,
yeah, different environments.
So we do know that
there are version differences
between his machine and another one.
And in the end, we told him that, yeah,
maybe get the environment that's
working on the other machine and
use it on your machine.
Where you're using Conda.
They had an environment.
So the installation
instructions essentially had an
environment, but in that case,
it was installed PyTorch.
And the program is from 2023.
So, well, the PyTorch version
that it depends on in
the setup is something like 1.10
and we are now at 2.8 and
there are quite a bit of
changes and not only there, but
yeah, that's a relatively
typical situation where it works
here, it works on different
machines, but it doesn't work on mine.
Why?
Yeah.
We have this internal joke with our team.
[name], by the way, is part of our team.
We have a daily support Zoom session
and we usually have, you
know, that Conda is mentioned every day.
How many days since Conda
was mentioned in the support?
And it's usually zero.
which is, conda is an important tool.
You will hear more about conda today.
In general, if you think in your work,
I think Inna has been
mostly using Python and [name] a
bit of Matlab, a bit of Python.
Have you ever experienced this,
that maybe after many months or
even more, many years, the
same code that used to work stopped working?
Was it easier?
Was it easy to make it work
again or was it impossible?
Yes, I have had that experience.
It's very often the problem
that I come back to something
old from myself and
Depending on how much of a
rush I was in when doing
that stuff, it's difficult to
see what I actually did.
And getting back in, like what
the user is writing as well.
And the other thing is,
yeah, particularly recently with what
I just mentioned, PyTorch changes where
The library is, or at least
has been, now it starts to
slowly, well, settle down.
But in the beginning, this was changing
so rapidly that the library
that was working two months ago
is not working now.
So you really had to be careful
what versions you were using
for what code and things.
And what about [name], have
you experienced this, what can I
call it, lack of self-reproducibility?
I think actually not that much
in my hands because I tend
to have fairly self-contained code
for many of my projects,
but working with others and
then especially also working with
PyTorch, I have similar experiences.
So especially when the versions
were in quite a lot of
flux and the change between version one and two
that made things interesting, to
say the least.
Yeah.
I personally had the, sometimes
we need to maybe help somebody
to run a tool that came from
a paper for a few years back.
And I remember once that
tool was specifically working with
a certain combination of versions.
So I had to go back and
see in 2021 which NumPy was
there and which whatever.
package was there try to
see those numbers and then in
the end we managed to
recreate the environment but
it's just sometimes traveling back
in time with code try to
reuse code from other paper
also require this type of
investigation on versions of
different packages.
And maybe Python in this sense
is one of the, I mean, Python is amazing,
but it's one of the worst
when it comes to these dependencies and chains.
And in a way, MATLAB, you
can say anything bad about MATLAB.
I've been using MATLAB for many years,
but being self-contained that
if I'm using MATLAB, whatever,
2021, I can just tell [name]
I'm using MATLAB 2021.
Of course, there can
still be reproducibility issues.
But in this sense, you know.
But essentially what you're doing
there is you said, I'm using MATLAB 2021.
So yes, you have a version
number for the software you're using.
So you have exactly the same
as a, I'm using Python 3.10 with PyTorch 1.0.
That's...
a clear version definition.
If you would say I'm using MATLAB
or I have some MATLAB code,
I remember a situation where
we were teaching something and
MATLAB decided that they will
change the default output of
a function to assuming that a
parameter is set versus it
wasn't assuming that parameter before.
So we had examples that were
running on, I think it was
MATLAB 2018 or something.
And in 2019, they changed the
default for a parameter.
And I was like, why do
our scripts no longer work?
We are just using Matlab functionality.
They should work.
Oh, oh, great.
So now we are not getting
the full output anymore.
We need to add this parameter
to get the full output that we got before.
So I think all languages have this issue.
You were actually in a good scenario.
You were able to see that
the script would not work.
What if the change was so subtle
that the output is still similar,
but I don't know, maybe just
the order with things are sorted is different.
Well, we noticed that the scripts were,
well, the scripts were
actually working, but the answers
were not the same anymore.
Because it was essentially
about solving differential equations.
And before they gave
out parameterized solutions by
default, and after the change, they didn't.
So they gave one solution.
And yeah, that essentially led to,
yeah, the script works, but
it only shows one of the
multiple solutions.
So you kind of got already
a feeling of what we're going to cover today.
It's one o'clock in Helsinki, Finland.
So we can now start with
day four of the code refinery workshop.
Hello everyone and welcome to day
4 of the Code Refinery
workshop September-October 2025.
With me today we have
[name] from University of
Eastern Finland and [name]
from Aalto University.
As you can see I'm
sharing the workshop webpage.
As usual this is the
reference point for all the links
and all the material.
that we will share today and
today starts a different kind of
part of the workshop we often
call it part two so then
instead of having every day like
we had last week and a
little bit longer days the next
days are a little bit shorter
and instead of being one after
the other it will be a week so in practice
for the next sixth or for
the next five Wednesday and for
today we will start at 1
p.m finish time and whatever is
that in your time zone
and the workshop will be
more kind of episodes that
don't really depend on each other
but they are of course
linked all together and today I'm
very happy to talk about I'm very happy
that we are covering this
lesson on reproducible research
because it's really that it
links all the different episodes
whether it's the version control
or you know how do you
work with other people how do
you document your software and so on
so when it comes to the
recap of the previous week so
far we learned about version
control you learn all the terms
that are used how to
commit whether you're using
the github interface or your
favorite editor if you work locally
and also of course what's
very the most exciting bit
of version control is to
work with others fixing
other people repositories or
accepting changes to your own repository
Now for this part two that
is starting we are going to
go more broadly in topics
that sometimes maybe don't
have practical exercises but compared
to the previous years where
this second part was mostly kind of demo based.
this year we decided to
introduce more exercises and so
hopefully you will have fun
today with some interesting
reproducibility exercises when it
comes to the notes document
you should always receive
this collaborative notes document
and for those who are not
familiar with this document at the very top
now there's our cameras there
but under our webcams there
would be a pencil and so that if you
if you click the okay now
it's you see that my mouse is
on top of the pencil
Now I click the pencil
and the interface changes into
some sort of like a editor
mode and here everyone can edit.
So for example you could
already answer one of these
icebreakers like have you heard
this sentence works on my computer
and it's nice to hear your
stories of you know where
this type of computational
reproducibility has failed.
but I'm still in precious
times from our instructors.
So I scroll back up and switch to this eye,
which is the view mode,
meaning that I don't need to
edit this document anymore.
And so I'm very happy that
today we have [name] from
University of Eastern Finland.
She's a researcher working
with computational methods for
drug discovery.
At least this is what I understood.
I hope it's correct.
And [name] from our team at
Aalto is a Research Software
Engineer having lots of fun,
especially with web development
and applications and things like that.
So the stage is yours and
I think we should switch to
[name]'s screen if I'm correct.
Yes.
Okay, thank you very much
for the kind introduction, [name].
And as [name] mentioned, so
we're here today to talk
about reproducible research.
And as [name] has also already mentioned,
this kind of connects all
the different parts of this workshop together.
And let's actually start from there.
How it all connects.
So what I think is pretty clear
when we talk about how
do we get reproducible results in
the end is, well, we need the data.
That's pretty straightforward, right?
And also, of course, we need
the code used to generate the results.
But then there is another thing
that we need to think about
that is called here are my tools.
And that might be a little
bit more alien to you on the surface.
But we are going to talk
about that quite a bit today.
So think of tools as all
the other things you need to
know, all the prerequisites and
everything else you need to
have in addition to code and
data to make reproducible results.
And what has this got to
do with this workshop altogether?
So actually the whole workshop
gives you all the tools you need
for computational reproducibility from
a computational perspective.
So this here is my code.
Those of you who have been
there during the first week
or already know version control
with Git, have a sense of
how this can help you.
And there's a lot more
coming on topics like social coding,
so licensing, how to get credit
for your code, documentation,
Jupyter Notebooks, annotated executable
code blocks, and automated
testing, modular code development.
All of this helps you to
make your code reproducible.
But then what about the other stuff?
So this here are my tools
is what we are going to cover today.
General reproducibility, how you
can actually prepare your code and
put it in context so others and
you can use it again in the future.
And what is important, and I
want to stress that right at
the very beginning of today's
lesson is this might feel
a little bit overwhelming.
So we are going to cover
a lot of ground today.
And you might think that
maybe I don't really need
these things right now.
So
what am I going to
do with this information?
And what we really want to
stress is we want to show you what's out there.
We want to give you an
idea how can you achieve
different things in case this
becomes relevant to you in future.
But don't overthink it.
Don't fret.
What we really want to
point out is focus on
good enough start somewhere start
with small steps that's already a big step
for overall reproducibility think
of one topic maybe we cover
today you can get inspired perhaps
if you know that you want
to submit to a certain journal
then look at the journal requirements
or look at your funder
requirements or talk with colleagues
maybe your work group has
some requirements that have to do with
data structure, reproducibility aspects.
So get inspired by something
that you need that helps you right now
and start with one topic and
just try to learn and implement that.
And if you don't really
know where to start, a great way we find
that helps you to
identify bottlenecks, problems, missing
links is always to just give
your code to somebody else
and every question they need to ask you
tells you probably something
where you could improve a
little bit on reproducibility.
And
Now, I think based on
the icebreaker, this is something
you are all here because you
already have some idea about reproducibility.
And I think at least some
of you can quite nicely connect
to this PhD comic that
you have suffered through the
great fun of starting from
somebody else's work.
Nonetheless, why are we talking about this?
So what's the motivation
overall behind reproducible science?
And we have here a scary anecdote for you.
And in fact, this is a
true story that we have really
seen happen in real life.
So it's not just something that
we put here to convince you.
So imagine this.
You're in a group of researchers
and you obtain really good results,
so obviously you want to
submit that work to a high profile journal.
And then a month or
two later, reviewers ask you
to make some changes, get
some additional figures in, do
some more analysis.
And as you try to implement those changes,
you realize that actually
there's something odd happening.
You can't even quite reproduce
the original figures.
There seems to be some
data missing that you can't find.
And you can't really reproduce
the results of the original submission.
And maybe you don't even know
what parameters were used
for generating the original data.
And this can just mean
that the manuscript never sees the
light of the day.
So it's still left in the drawer.
And well, of course, this can
be quite bad for you if,
for example, your PhD depends
on that paper, your next grant,
maybe your next job.
Expected that this paper
would eventually be published and
now it's not happening.
So this is a bad situation
that I think we can all agree we want to avoid.
But then you could argue, hey,
this is just an isolated thing.
And obviously this happens to
some people, but it's not going
to happen to me.
And it's not really something
that happens very often.
And well, some of you
might be familiar with this
already, but in case you have
not seen this conversation,
quite telltale survey published
in Nature now nine years
back about reproducible research
asking researchers across the
life sciences have they ever
failed to reproduce an experiment
and now it might not be
such a big surprise that quite
many failed in reproducing
someone else's experiment but what's
a lot more depressing is that you see that
almost as many have also
failed to actually reproduce
their own experiments.
So that's rather bad.
And it's probably the publication
that kind of coined that term
that we really accept that, hey,
we have a reproducibility crisis.
So more than half of
the surveyed researchers said, okay,
there is a crisis going on
in science right now.
But this is all from experimental sciences.
And what was among the
reasons they asked about was
that methods and code were
simply not available.
So then you can't reproduce it.
And hopefully, since you're in
the code refinery workshop, you
already know how to avoid that
one and how to do better.
And also, as I said, experimental sciences,
there can be any number of reasons,
but you would naively think
we're talking about computational
methods today.
So this is kind of deterministic.
You feed it some data into
the same code, you get the same result out.
So this should be an easy
one for us to solve.
But in practice, well, I can tell you
that we have quite recently
done a reproducibility study with
my team and trying to actually
run over 200 published research codes.
and it's easily as grim as
what you have seen here
in the experimental sciences so
a lot of failure cases actually
the majority of them
had reproducibility problems more
than half at any rate and
top reasons were for example
complete lack of documentation
so that's something for you to learn more
during day six of this workshop.
And then the other topics
were things like environment
definition problems, missing dependencies.
So a lot of reasons that have not
so much to do with the code itself
or the data, but actually with
that environment, with these
additional tools and requirements
that we mentioned in the beginning.
And hopefully after today's workshop,
what we will teach you helps
you to avoid at least some
of these pitfalls and do better.
And when we think
about reproducibility, that's also
important to recognize that we
often kind of think just about code and data.
We might acknowledge that
documentation is important and we
might be very focused at this end goal.
OK, we want to write an
article or maybe you have a different end goal.
Maybe you just want to publish software.
software, but whatever your end goal is,
this rests on top of
documentation, code, data, that's
all very nice.
But it's just not enough.
And all of this rests on
a foundation that has to
do with the environment.
And if we don't really know
what to do with your code and your data,
how these things come together,
and where you executed them
with what other tools in mind,
then the whole thing just breaks down.
And that's just important to recognize,
that reproducibility is more than
just code and data and documentation,
but there is something underneath
it that we should also take into account.
And yeah, I have now already
shared my own experience with
trying to reproduce code.
And I think we have a
couple of interesting stories by
now also in the icebreaker
questions about your experiences
with rerunning codes, adjusting
scripts, figuring out what you
have done a couple of months
ago, continuing to work from
somebody else's code.
So maybe I think it's time
to maybe switch to [name]'s screen to see
what interesting stories we have
by now in the collaborated notes.
Overall, the most interesting thing
that I saw here is when
coming back to their own code,
a lot of people are saying that
they do need to take a couple
of days to get back into
what they were actually doing.
And I can completely understand that.
It's the same for me.
Even with good documentation, you
just need some time to get into a...
new project, even if it's
a project that you have been working on before.
Often code styling, code
considerations are somewhat different
between different projects and
then it's just, yeah, you need
some time to get back in.
So have you ever experienced that
if you're looking back at code
that you wrote two or three years ago,
that it feels like it has
been written by a different person?
Yes, definitely.
It's also, especially if you
are working in a field
where things are evolving, things are changing,
you look back at code that
you wrote a couple of years back or
even sometimes even a couple
of months back and think like,
why the heck did I even do this like that?
Because this doesn't... Well, yeah,
okay, it works, but it's not
what it should be.
It's not...
how I recently found style for
this kind of library or how
this type of library should be used.
And it's very often that you, yeah,
as I said, you come from
a certain style of writing code.
And if a library has
a different approach to coding in general,
what you write and how
you interface with that library
might look very, very, very different.
And at some point, if you
use the library enough, you
start to understand how they
were thinking, how they want things
to be used with this library.
And then you start writing
your code that way.
And then you look back at some old code
and you think like, this
shouldn't be written like this.
It should be written
completely differently.
And when it comes to
continuing work from other people, yeah,
I think the first one is
quite telling was, yeah, there's
a lot of errors coming up.
You need to find which versions
where to put things and
it's pretty much undocumented.
And I think we will
come to the documentation will
be in three weeks, I think.
And documentation is probably also
one of the most important
bits about code development.
And then the problem that
if you have really old things then, well,
you just can't find the right versions
that were used to compile that
because if you have something from,
yeah, here it's from 2003,
you don't necessarily know whether
that was compiled with the
latest version or maybe a
Linux three years from, three or
four years old that didn't
have the latest versions.
and was just about at its end of life.
And yeah, it was compiled
with something even older and
only worked with that.
So like [name] mentioned in
the Icebreaker time, that is something
that very often comes in the way of,
yeah, reproducing things, either
your own or continuing work from others.
And I think we have already
now talked a lot about the
aspect of versions that you
don't really know what versions
people have been using.
And that's, for example, also
in our study was a huge
problem that, you know, when a
code has been published.
But if they don't report
the versions, it can like
simply mean any number of things.
You can roughly guesstimate
what package versions were relevant
in 23 versions.
But then they might have
worked with versions and they
might have worked on a
project since, let's say, 2018.
And they have never
changed their environment.
So they are using even
more outdated versions than you would think.
And if there's no information
about that, you have no way of knowing.
And there's actually, sorry to interrupt,
there's actually one good question here,
whether if a scientific findings
depend on the specific version of libraries,
if it then is actually
reproducible or if it cannot
be repeated with different libraries.
I think this very much plays
in here as well because
there's two different things.
There is the science behind
a certain code where, yeah,
if this works properly and is
not dependent on things like
numerics or other non-code-based
issues, let's phrase it like that,
then I think it's okay
and it's also reproducible even
if it doesn't work with a
newer version because the newer
version is essentially a different tool.
So it's the same as if you would say,
well, if I have a
completely different machine to
analyze things, it should still be working.
Yeah, but only if that
machine actually produces the same
kind of outputs and takes the
same kind of samples from preparation.
It's really this, if a
library changes, sometimes functionality
stays the same.
But if the functionalities do change
and do change, for example,
an underlying algorithm for
a certain functionality, because
someone found that there is
a more efficient one for
some type of approximation.
And now, well, it gives
slightly different results because,
well, it's an approximation.
It's also, I think, important
in this context that we
distinguish a little bit between
kind of technical reproducibility.
So can you even rerun the code in itself?
Can you generate output in the first place?
And a lot of this versioning
is going to break that first
rerun ability or technical reproducibility.
And then it's a whole
different matter that depends on
other things out there.
changes in the libraries, like
you just explained, can of
course also affect the results.
Can you reproduce the exact output
or at least in reality, when
we work with approximations, it's
quite often more a question, can
you get the ballpark right?
So it will not be exactly
the same floating point number,
but it should at least give you the same
general direction and general idea
and that's kind of more
the actual reproducibility of the
results of a computational study
but quite often unfortunately I
can attest to the fact that
you fail already in the first step
so you cannot even get
this technical reproducible you cannot
run the code and if you
can't run the code then there's
no point in even talking about
would I get the same results
with the information I have,
because, well, it's not running.
So I hope, since we've talked
a lot now about versions, and there, of course,
when you work with somebody else's code,
and you run into a lot
of errors, not everything is
related to versions and environment.
But I think we have heard
a couple of examples and seen a couple of
comments that link to, for
example, the ENV and conda environments
and versions that you install
that kind of tell you that
this is very much at the core of the issue,
that we simply do not
know enough about these tools
and about the environment to reproduce code.
But before we dive even deeper into
that topic, I think let's
talk about something that is
maybe even easier.
And if you don't really know
what is the first step, where
to start in order to
improve reproducibility, then this is
a good place for you to begin.
And it might seem really obvious,
but trust me when I tell
you in practice, sadly, it's quite often not.
And start from organizing your
projects in a logical fashion,
because like we heard in that
anecdote in the beginning, it
might actually be quite useful
to simply know where are my files?
Where are those scripts that I've executed?
How does it link to the data and so on?
And well...
Some of the repositories we
tested, you look at the code repository
and you get this wall of files
that are like script one,
script two, script three, data
one, two, three.
Personally, I think this is
even for the authors themselves.
At a point, impossible to
know what is script one, two, three, four.
And this is actually a
really low hanging fruit that
if you just structure your
projects cleverly and you name
things in a reasonable way
that is descriptive, that's
already documentation in itself.
And it kind of really
becomes natural to you after some
time that you structure projects
in a different way.
It becomes normal and then
it's not really that much effort anymore.
And we just want to share
with you some ideas on that topic.
What is a directory structure
that people have really found
to work for that kind of project basis?
So, for example, that you
collect all the project related
files, at least what you have
related to a certain project,
if you're just working in
a multidisciplinary project on, let's say,
computational part, then collect
all the data you have in a single directory.
and put different projects to
live in their own directory.
And then, as I said, try
to use the naming to already
give you a hint, what am
I actually looking at here?
So not script one, two,
three, but actually tell what
the script is doing.
And yeah, this is maybe...
I think we are mostly Linux people,
so we hate spaces in
file names and directory names.
But generally, it's a good
idea to avoid spaces on other systems as well.
Use dashes, use underscore or
camel case if you prefer.
It's just nicer to work with
and there's no ambiguity.
What's like really the full path
and you don't have to
worry about escaping spaces and
other things like that.
And if you need, let's
say you actually work with
some personalized data, sensitive data,
then of course you should
have private directories where
it's really clear that this
is something you don't want to
share with the outside world.
And at least those of you
who have been there in week
one have heard of that git ignore.
So just if you need a
refresher, you can check the lessons there.
during the first week, but
this is basically a file that tells you
when you version control
that whole structure, this is
the stuff you won't get to ignore.
So this is not gonna be put anywhere.
And then have README files.
So have a README for the whole project
that describes what is this
project about, what do I have in here.
And then also have a
readme file, for example, for the data.
There log where did the data come from?
When did you get the data?
Especially when you get data
online, the data might change.
So also put timestamp information there
and pull the data down
into specific subdirectories.
And then you will always
know exactly what version of the data you used.
If you manipulate data
throughout your pipeline, then
create another folder, have a
separate folder for all the
intermediate files that helps you
if something goes wrong or if
you later on need to track
what has maybe changed in
my data processing code, then
you can actually compare the
first intermediate files with the
second ones and get some idea
is this a problem, for instance.
Then have a folder for
your final results where you
put things like your final
data, your tables, your figures.
Maybe you want to have a
folder for the manuscript
describing those results.
And you want to have a
documentation of the whole project.
And inside all of this,
you have your source folder.
where all your code lives
with a license ideally and the requirements
or dependencies we are going
to talk a little bit
more about requirements and
dependencies today and you can
learn a bit more about licensing
I think next week in the social coding session
But anyway, this just is
already a project structure that
is very much self-explanatory and
that would help you to avoid
a lot of the problems we
have mentioned in that scary
anecdote in the beginning.
So if you consistently followed
that kind of project
structure, you probably won't end
up in a situation where you
don't know where is the
data, what parameters were used or
Simply, you can't really trace
how did you get to
the intermediate files and you have
a chance to rescue your manuscript.
And now you can really track
what is inside your source folder.
You can, in principle, within
some limits, also track your data
if it's not very big.
If it's sensitive or large,
then again, untrack it with git ignore.
keep all the intermediate files
and consider those git tags
to mark specific versions.
So, for example, if you have something
that is related to your
thesis, to your manuscript or
a poster presentation, then you
can use the git tags so
you know exactly, OK, this is
the status when I generated that poster.
And that can be really helpful.
And there are even a
bunch of templates that you are
welcome to try for R and Python.
We have some examples and
some more general guidelines and
many more in this blog.
That can help you with some ideas
how to structure things,
with what components to put and where.
These are really great starting points
if you don't quite know
how to best organize things.
One small request though,
please remember to actually
populated do not just copy a template
and then forget to
write actual documentation about
your code because we also
had a repository where I was
thrilled to see hey this
has everything documentation all
the intermediate files that whole
structure I have shown to you and
when I looked into the
data structure there was just
nothing so the documentation said
okay enter your documentation here
so thanks very much
All of this is nice and
gives you a guidance what you
need to fill and where you need to fill it.
But just please remember that
it won't autofill.
We will give you some
tools throughout the workshop that
help you to make this easier.
Still, it requires some input
from your site to really
write specific documentation for
your project and populate
that with information that you actually need.
And this is also something
that should grow kind of
organically as your project progresses.
You have to also remember
to update the documentation.
It might seem like a lot
of hassle at times, but I
think it's an important step
to avoid such things like
you basically can't publish
a manuscript because you have
lost track of what you
were doing somewhere along the way.
And the more often and
consistently you are doing this,
the more natural it becomes.
And it's not really a hustle
when you do it the fifth
or sixth or seventh time.
At some point, it's just natural.
So hopefully, hopefully we will
give you all the tools to
just get you started along that line.
I think the bottom line of all
of this is a good structure
can be a very important
part of documentation, documentation in
its own right.
And it's a fairly easy thing to do
and usually quite applicable to
any number of projects.
So if you don't know where else to start,
this is maybe where we
would recommend you just get
going because this is going to really.
have a huge contribution to reproducibility.
And especially then if you're
in a larger collaborative project,
you know where to find things
if you get reviewer comments and
you can also help others to
find things in your own structure more easily.
And yeah, speaking of
collaboration, I think now let's
take a quick excursion
to talk about collaborative
writing of academic papers.
So now we have covered a
bit of the bottom of this
pyramid and we have talked a lot about versions,
directory structure, how this is
a bit of documentation, where
to put data, where to put code.
And then we have this final
top of the pyramid, the article.
So what are your experiences?
How do you collaborate on
writing academic papers?
How do you handle issues
like conflicting changes?
Maybe, [name], can you share
some of the stories and
experiences in writing papers with us?
So also from the notes
here, I've personally done two
of the three approaches that
I, or four approaches, three
that are mentioned in the notes now.
I have done the drafting
things on Google Docs and
doing a final submission, then
putting it into LaTeX.
So taking the templates that
the journalist offering
because if you need to write
this to some other journal you
will have to fill it into
their template again anyway so
having draft where you just have text
that you can just put
into certain places and no
notes like figure here figure
here makes it easier to do
these kind of adaptions
I've also done the Overleaf approach
where multiple people were working on it,
but that was mainly working
because it was primarily
computer scientists that were
accustomed to LaTeX.
So everyone was on the LaTeX thing.
And I have had the
unfortunate pleasure to have
Word documents sent around and edited
and version X, final version
one, final version 17, final version 17 v2.
final version 17 your
initials their initials whatever
so yeah I can share a fun story on
that too so word documents
sent around via email I was
not carbon copied on several of those emails
Then I was asked to
revise the manuscript and I did.
Then I got a very angry
email by the first author saying,
hey, but you used the wrong version.
And I was like, I used
the latest version I had.
And then it turned out
that they actually sent another
two versions around that I never got.
So...
This is just unpleasant and
I think one important motivation
because this kind of goes
into version control and why also
we suggest to think about
version control maybe for manuscripts
and to try to have
it somewhere there everybody can
see what is really the latest version.
to avoid those kind of problems.
But also, this has also been, I think,
published in Nature a while back
that somebody wrote that they
used version control and basically Git
mainly to show that their
manuscript was not written by AI.
And this is now something
that I think becomes more
timely and relevant every day, that
it's not a bad idea if you
can kind of show how your
manuscript, how your text evolved over time.
So you avoid that reviewer say, hey,
obviously this just came at the
click of a button from chat GPT.
So another thing simply to
keep in mind that having
version control, having a protocol
that really shows when and
how things changed can also help
you to fend off such
nasty reviewer comments and suspicions a bit.
I think what I would
in general recommend from
personal experience is we have
nowadays the option to
have collaborative documents where
multiple people can edit and comment on.
And I think one should make
use of these tools.
The times of sending around
version drafts should be over.
in my opinion because that's
to me the worst possible option
because you end up exactly
what you said someone gets
dropped from an email chain works
on an old version where all
the typos have already been fixed
and the next one yeah
sends their comments and then
someone has to try to compile
the things and it's just a complete mess
So this is kind of, yeah, don't do this.
Do something else.
Do some collaborative document.
Personally, I'm not that big of
a fan of using Git for
version controlling a paper, at
least not for version controlling
the actual process of writing.
Maybe for some revisions, but
for the writing process,
I'm not that big of a
fan because you end up with
exactly the second question that we have here,
where you have multiple people
working on the document and submitting
and then you get merge
conflicts or, well, if you're
unlucky, you get merge conflicts.
If you're lucky, you don't
get merge conflicts, but you
might end up with...
two people writing the same
kind of comment that needs to
be added to some paragraph and
they write it at slightly different places
and then you have it in twice
because yeah it merges nicely
it doesn't complain with a rebase
or something and then you
notice it somewhere sometime later
or you unfortunately don't notice
it at all and submit something
that feels like why is
this mentioned twice that review
is getting annoyed so
That's where I personally would prefer
or would recommend using
a collaborative editor nowadays.
Because they are available and
make use of the tech.
Yeah and I think I mean
word is still at least
in our field unfortunately very very common
and people have a certain
resilience to changing but I have
to say that I've been with LaTeX for
quite some time also Overleaf a
while back did not have
the functionalities that you would
find in Word but now it
does so the argument that for
example you can't use LaTeX with people
who don't know how to write
LaTeX I have had a couple
of people who really have
never used LaTeX before working
fine with Overleaf
you can write comments, you
have track changes.
So all of these things, I
think also in TypeST, if
you prefer Markdown, these tools are there.
So the argument that people
love to give for having to use Word,
that you can't comment on the files
or you don't see track
changes, that just doesn't apply anymore.
And yeah.
Then all of these tools
also provide Git integrations that
help at least with some of these things.
So you work together on one document,
but then you commit versions
on a regular basis that just
shows the track record.
And even if you have to work with Word,
you can use something like
SharePoint or some other central source.
Just avoid having to
send around manuscripts.
And yes, I think with that,
maybe one other thing.
As a little teaser, there's going
to be a whole session
dedicated to Jupyter Notebooks that
tells you a lot more about that.
But if you really want
to have essentially an
executable manuscript where you
write things in Markdown and
then you have code blocks
embedded into the manuscript, there
are now also
tools available where you can
basically run those online
directly without actually having
to install anything.
So reviewers can really go
read the manuscript and execute
the code as they go.
So there's a lot of things happening
that are interesting in this
context of making things
reproducible, making collaboration easier
that I think
are worth being aware of and
trying out if you haven't.
There's also some additional
reading material if you're interested.
But yeah, I think with
that, we're about done with that
first part of our workshop for today.
And I think the key take
home message at this point is that
if you have an organized
project directory structure,
That's already a huge
step towards reproducibility.
And although it might seem
obvious, I think also a nod to myself
that I'm sometimes sloppy in
how I organize my projects and
it tends to backfire.
So this is the first step
to work on that doesn't
really require any tools.
Requires a bit of effort,
but it becomes quite natural quite fast.
And really helps a ton.
And yeah, also think about
version control for the future
when writing your manuscripts.
And now, [name], I don't know.
Shall we do a short break now?
Or do you want to actually...
I would say let's do a short
break now for 10 minutes.
And then... [name], was the
timing that we go for lunch soonish?
Or...
We can have a break now.
Okay, then let's do a 10-minute break now.
Alright, so... Meet back at 5 to the hour.
10-minute break.
See you in 10 minutes, and
then we will hear some
more about directory structures,
computational steps, dependencies, and
lots of other fun things.
Bye!
and welcome back so we have
talked a bit about the upper
parts of the pyramid that
we've shown earlier and now we
have started to get further
down this pyramid after having
talked a bit about the structure now
if you have a project
that you have something that you
need to need to do like having a workflow
This is something that also
needs to be reported and
very often this reported in scripts,
but it can also be reported
in other ways and depending on
what you have it's like or
more easily or more difficult to reproduce.
So.
There are commonly a couple
of steps from input data that
you have from experiments or
from other sources to the results
that you want to present for a paper.
And we are using an example
project that is essentially just word counting.
And even in this very simple thing
where we want to count
words and create some statistics
for the amount of words that
are occurring in some books, it
has a couple of steps.
So we first have to
analyze the frequencies of the words.
That's done in a counterpy file.
for all the books that
we currently have, which is
in this data directory.
So data directory currently
contains these four books and
the books essentially just contain
the plain text of these books
that we are investigating here.
And the counterpy file simply says
that we are checking how
often does a certain word occur in this book.
And then we want to plot them
and generate these nice plots
so that we can put into our paper.
And for a single book,
this is essentially what we would be doing.
So I have this in here.
I'm creating this counter pi,
and then I have a aisles.data
that I can have a look at.
How does this look like?
So yeah, this is the off and O
and two, and then I
can plot this relatively easily and
can get a file that is
essentially showing this plot.
Let's see.
My machine being slow.
But yeah, I get this file.
And this is all nice and well,
but now if we imagine that
we have to repeat this
multiple times, that would
essentially happen in our run all, which is...
a script that essentially just
says okay for the first file
for the first file for the second file
for the third file for the fourth file
and yeah this is this works
for the four books that we have
but if we want to have 500
books now this script
becomes essentially unmaintainable
because there are so many
different files now and there is
so likely to be some kind of typo or whatever.
We can of course create
this file automatically and stuff,
but it's just getting more and more crowded.
I think maybe one thing is
that quite many people would
actually execute those steps
manually, then it's very easy
to forget something.
So already the script is one
step towards a certain degree
of reproducibility that I think
It's important to recognize here
that having a script that makes sure
that it's actually executed in
order for everything is not a
bad thing per se.
That's already a good starting point.
So better than doing it by hand
and forgetting half of
the books, especially if you get 500.
Yeah, that definitely.
But it just, even if you
do it in the script, it becomes unmaintainable.
So this is something that you can do
for a few things and for
a quite simplistic workflow where
you have some fixed input data
and some fixed output data, that's okay.
That's perfectly fine.
But as soon as you start to, for example,
collect more and more data over time
and you need to run this again
and again and again for new things
that are coming in, you
commonly don't want to run
everything again because, yeah, in
this case, the computation takes
a second or something.
But let's assume that each
calculation here or each individual
data entry takes an hour or two.
you don't want to rerun this
all the time if nothing has changed
and one more thing to mention here is
that this kind of stating
every individual element is
also called imperative style where
you tell a script every single
thing that it has to do one after another and
Well, there are some advantages
to this solution compared to
processing all one by one.
And yeah, as Ninash already
mentioned, this run all is
better reproducible, because you're
not forgetting one or the other.
So having this in a script,
yeah, is the first step.
But as I said, if we have more
and more things coming in,
then there start to be more and more problems.
And that's where workflow tools come in.
So workflow tools are
essentially tools that help you
to organize workflows that you have
to do in a repetitive fashion
or that are more complex.
And we will focus here on SnakeMake,
but there are multiple
different other tools that are
also mentioned later on.
And SnakeMake, in contrast
to this imperative style,
uses something that's called
a declarative style, sorry.
And this will also be
the exercise, will also be used
in the exercise that you're going
to be doing soonish.
But I quickly go over how
this snake make or how snake make works.
So in snake make, you
define rules and snake make
tries to satisfy all rules.
And that means that a rule
or to satisfy a rule, all the
inputs of the rule have to
be created or satisfied.
And in our bookcase, the rule
the one rule to rule them all,
that is essentially indicating, okay,
this is the final rule, the final rule,
or this is the target requires
as inputs, you could also
call inputs requirements for
this, that everything in statistics
book data exists and
the book here will be
replaced by whatever is in the data array.
So this is somewhat of
a Pythonic syntax that you can
use Python code in the snake files.
And this data is generated by looking
through the data folder,
through everything that matches
this placeholder.txt, and then
saying, okay, this becomes the data book,
or no, this is the book field of this
and this glob wildcards
generates these book fields for
all elements in here.
So for the rule all, we
want everything in the statistics
book data to exist and we
want everything in the book PNG
to exist and they have to be
as recent as any requirements
that or in each rule it
will be checked whether there
have been updates in the inputs
and then the rule has to be executed
and for example count words
here requires as an input the
count.py so your script file so
if you change your script
you will have to rerun
this for all elements and
it requires the different book files.
So if one of the book files changes
or there's a new book file,
then it has to generate this
for the new book file.
And the output from this is
defined as this is the statistics file data.
So this essentially satisfies this input.
And so it will look up
in the underlying rules what
rules could satisfy one of my
inputs or one of my requirements.
And then there is the command
that is being called when
this rule is being executed.
And that's essentially just, in
this case, a Python command.
This could be anything else.
This could also be R,
MATLAB, or whatever language you want.
SnakeMate doesn't make a difference here.
And it essentially says, okay, well,
for each input, the input.script
value is being used, and
that's the code count.py.
And the input.book, that's the data,
whatever the file is that
came from that, again, comes
from the requirement here.
and is passed kind of downwards.
And this generates the output,
which is again for each file.
And this is how SnakeMake
builds these rules and goes
through the graph and essentially checks
for every input if it
changed and then generates the outputs.
We'll also check whether
the outputs changed if there
are dependencies because the make
plot then depends on the outputs
of the count words and so on.
I think this is going to
be maybe easier and more clear
once people have gone through the exercises.
So there are two different
options how you can do this.
You can do this on your own computer.
If you have the code
refinery conda environment, then
just conduct code refinery and
all and everything you need will be in there.
And then you can go through
the exercise on your own machine,
or you can do this on binder
where there is a binder
link on the repository.
And if you launch it in
Binder, you get a online
machine that essentially gives you
the same infrastructure that
would be available with the conda environment.
There's a small difference
between Binder and your local machine in
that due to the way how
Binder works, some files might
need to be reproduced more often.
Because I think because of
indexing, if I remember that right.
It caches some files and then
it will also update the cache.
So you will not get the
counts you would maybe expect
because there are additional files
in the background changing.
Okay, but you have 15 minutes for this.
Essentially go through all the
steps in the workflow here
and report on whatever errors
you encounter and see you at 23.
Bye.
And welcome back.
So there were a couple of questions
as to why we are doing
this, and I will demonstrate a few commands
that hopefully explain why SnakeMake
or any workflow manager can be a useful tool.
So I've cleaned up my repository here.
There's nothing in statistics.
There's nothing in the, in,
in the plots.
So at the moment I'm
essentially in just having the data.
So if I now run
the snake make command minus j
just to say okay well use one
core i don't want to do
this parallel it will run this
and it will run seeing that
okay there there needs to be things done
and it tells you okay things
need to be updated because they
are missing and now i do
have in the statistics all of
my statistics and in the plots
i have all my plots generated
Now, the nice thing with snake make is
that we can now, for example,
if I take, let's say one
of the input files and just
copy it over into, so I just
create a copy of it.
Assume this is a new book that comes in.
If I now run snake make
again, it'll say, okay, well,
I'm looking in here.
There is overall one thing to do with all.
There's one count word that
needs to be done and one make plot
that needs to be done
and everything else is already done.
So it's only doing the thing
once while if I look back what happened before.
It's a lot of things.
So there's one time the rule
all needs to be done.
Well, yeah, it's the final rule.
So it only executes once and
four times it needs to count
words and four times it needs to make plots.
So at this point,
I now, looking into the plots,
I have a sierra2.png.
If, for example, some of
my input data changes, let's
take the abyss.txt and remove this, the people.
And I run snake make again.
it'll say, oh, something changed
and it's the abyss that
has changed and that needs to be updated.
So it updates only the abyss.
And that is kind of the
power of these tools that you,
can run them again and again and again,
and they will only do what
is necessary to be done.
They will not repeat things
that are already done.
If you have, for example,
a quite long lasting preprocessing step
that is data independent, but
that you need to do, you can
have that as a prerequisite in your rules.
And as long as
the code that's generating
this preprocessing doesn't change.
So if you have that separated
into its own file, you can run this again
and it will know that,
okay, well, the preprocessing
file that generates my
preprocessing data hasn't changed.
So I can run everything else.
But if my preprocessing data has changed,
then I need to run everything else
because the dependencies of all
the other rules have changed.
And that's what's making these
snake make or general workflow managers
so powerful that they take
away you needing to remember, okay,
what have I already done?
And what new data do I have
to now run my things on?
And you can keep all of
the data in one folder.
And if they're separated by file name,
it's able to essentially go
through all the files in there
and do something for all the files.
You can also visualize how things,
how it's essentially doing these things
and the command for that,
oops, that was not what I wanted to do.
And the command for that is outlined here.
So we create the, the
direct acyclic graph, I think, and
put it into, put it into a image.
And this also shows you
how the different rules that
it will execute are built.
So in our case, all depends
on both the statistics and the make plot.
The make plot depends on
the statistics and then feeds into all.
So we have a double dependency.
We could essentially remove
the statistics from the all rule
and it would still do
the same steps because it
looks back, okay, this depends
on this and would redo the things.
And one question for us, why
do we use SnakeMake for this
and not a different workflow manager?
And the main reason is it
has a relatively gentle learning curve.
Yeah, it is something where you
need to get your head around
how the rules are being generated.
but that's the typical different
style of different style of
coding essentially and you just
need to get your head around okay this is
how it works inputs are
essentially the requirements outputs
are the products of each rule
and the rules are somewhat
the functions that are being called
in some way and so on and
the all function i think you know
told me once that she compares
that somewhat with the main
function of a program.
It's not really a function.
I agree to that.
But if you sort of think of this
as where it tells all the
other things it needs to execute,
that is kind of where this analogy came from.
But I think it helps
in understanding how SnakeMake
builds these things.
And the second thing is
SnakeMake is free and open source.
It also installs pretty easily
via condo or via pip and
can be used cross-platform.
There are several things in SnakeMake
that allow you to run things in parallel,
which can be quite convenient
on high performance computing systems
because SnakeMake also has built
in support for, for example,
Slurm queue management, where
it can essentially run
large workflows as individual slurm
jobs it will submit the jobs
they will will run on the on the cluster
and it can and it will
then continue where it away where
the jobs left off essentially um
it's also possible to do
individual steps in individual
environments by having by
essentially just adding conda
environment.yaml so indicating this
is the environment that is necessary
for this or this is
the environment yaml and will
create these environments if
necessary and that's
quite important for example as
we mentioned very early with
things like pytorch if you
have multiple different tools that
depend on different pytorch versions
but you want to chain
them because they because the
one does something that you
want in your workflow and the
other one does also something that
you want in your workflow you
can't run them in the same environment
So by using SnakeMake,
you essentially separate them
into different environments and you
can run them again.
It's also possible to directly
use Docker container containers
by indicating, okay, which container
to use for a certain rule.
And then this will be
executed within this container.
So it's very flexible and has support
for a lot of high-performance computing
or things that you need
in a high-performance computing
system environment.
It's also quite heavily
used in bioinformatics, but it
is completely general.
You can write any workflow
into a snake make file.
And that's just making it
quite nice to use.
and as mentioned these tools
like snake make help a
lot with reproducibility because they
help you in not forgetting
to add certain things not
forgetting to rerun something and
if you essentially run your
snake make file at the end of your
or before you want to submit
and you have defined your
snake make file correctly i you
also have the um the script
files as inputs and so on you
will run the right code
for your data with the
right data that's now there and
you can be sure that okay i
know what i was running on
when i built this this does
not help against you running
it then modifying things then
running it again and having
done something with intermediary
results that's where the
The project structure comes back in a bit.
Okay, if you have something like,
or general versioning, if I
have something at submission version,
I should make sure that I
know this is the data
at submission version, this is
the code at submission version, and
so that I can rebuild this.
So it doesn't help you against that,
but it helps you to keep
the data in itself or the
data and the results in itself consistent.
I think for this version
tracking, just to mention that
again, really git tags are quite useful.
So you can just make sure,
okay, this is the script
version, data version and so on
that you use to submit and
then there's no ambiguity.
Okay, yeah, there are, of course,
a lot of similar tools
like Make, Nextflow, CWL.
I think it's sometimes interesting
to see Make here because most people know
that Make is a tool that
is being used for compiling C
or C++ code or Fortran code.
And don't really think of this
as a workflow manager, but in the end,
it has the same structure as
a snake file, it has rules.
And rules can depend on other rules.
And it just executes these rules.
So in the end, it is
exactly the same thing.
Let's go on from having
recorded the flow of how you execute your code,
how the different steps in
your code are being executed
one after another, to what's
necessary to be able to actually run your code.
and that is dependencies.
And we have talked about
this already quite a bit
that version numbers are
important and versioning is quite important.
And I like this image here
from XKCD where you can and
it's very, very true.
You have a lot
of programming infrastructure, a lot
of code infrastructure for a
lot of systems and
there are always some
small libraries somewhere that
are maintained by maybe a person
or two in their spare time
and that are underlying a lot of things.
And I want to give an anecdote
that is from 2024 where
essentially exactly this thing
almost brought this whole
thing down collapsing.
And that's the XC story.
XC is a small zipping library.
where essentially it's just
about compressing some data.
But this library is very, very basic
or very, very much below a
lot of operating system code and so on.
And in 2024, someone after
a couple of years had
managed to social engineer themselves
into a maintainer position on
the project and added a backdoor.
quite sophisticated and it
was essentially very, very short
before coming into a lot
of major Linux distributions
until someone noticed a timing increase of,
I think a couple of milliseconds
for some requests that they
were doing and started investigating
and found that, oh yeah,
there's now a backdoor in there.
So yeah, we have this situation.
This is not,
artificial, this is exactly what we have.
We have exactly this situation
and it's so easy even
for a relatively simple project
like a PhD project to depend
on some things that might or
might not be maintained and
that exists somewhere and needs
some software, yeah.
I think also what I
realized is quite often, at least with Python,
that some of my students, without
even thinking, they find that
there is a module that can do the job.
And without thinking twice, they
will just pip install the
module, then another module, and
then they have 15 modules to
do very simple things that would
be there in base Python, and
that's okay on some level.
But they don't really think
that every module creates
dependencies of their own and
that sometimes you kind of
engineer a dependency hell into
your own code by installing
those things without thinking
about the potential consequences.
And sometimes it's a good
idea to think about exactly that.
That everything you depend
on has dependencies in their own right.
And it's just it can spiral out of control.
So it is just something that
we should keep in the back of our heads
when we install someone else's
code that we do not necessarily know.
How is this maintained and
what does it build on in it?
Overall, I would say it's
a general good principle to
try to minimize your dependencies,
but at the same time, don't
try to reinvent the wheel.
Have it in a balance.
If there's complex stuff that
a library does really well,
take that library however if
there is a relatively simple thing uh
that oh yeah there is
a convenient function in this huge
i don't know there is a
convenient function in pytorch for
my small um i need to flip some matrix
or something uh don't install
pytorch to flip the matrix
either do it yourself or use
some other smaller library that
does the same thing
I mean, we don't want
to discourage anyone from using
other people's code.
It's just in my experience, exactly.
It's just something people
don't necessarily think about.
And it can be a good
idea to just be mindful of those things.
That's what I just wanted to say.
But to make this whole
what are dependencies and so on
a bit more obvious, we
have this kitchen analogy where
essentially the software that
you're running or that you
have been writing, that's
essentially the recipe for what
needs to be done.
The data that your software
uses are the ingredients.
And the libraries are the pots
and tools that are necessary
to actually do the processing.
And that's something that's
very often forgotten.
How many recipes do you see
that mention a pot and a
pan as requirements for them?
Yeah, well, if you just buy the stuff
and you don't have a pot and a pan,
you will probably not be able
to run this or do this recipe.
And it's the same with a computer.
If you don't mention this library
and this library, then yeah,
you have some code, but it
requires things that we don't know about.
And we often use these
tools from others and that's perfectly fine,
but we just have to remember
that they are being used.
And if we want someone else
to use our code, they need
to know what they have to use.
So there's the idea of
dependency and environment management.
And tools like conda,
pip, virtualenv, pipenv and so
on, they all record dependencies
in different files like these.
like requirements.txt for pip
or environment.yamls for conda,
mamba and so on.
And they try to solve a problem
that you need to define a
specific set of dependencies for your project.
So listing everything that
is actually necessary for your project.
The tools then aim to, and
that's done in the requirement
60 or environment.yaml.
The tools then try to
make, automate installing these
dependencies based on the file
that you have provided or
based on the dependency file you have provided.
They also often do record versions
for all dependencies if they
install them themselves.
And one more very, very
useful thing with having these
environments is you can isolate environments.
So if you have a project
that uses packages A, B, and C,
you can have those run
in one environment and you can
have a project that needs D, E
and F in a different environment.
And while if they are completely separate,
you could probably run them
in the same environment.
You might get in a
situation where for project A, you
need A, B and C at version five.
And for the second project, you
need C at version seven and E and F.
and then you can't use them
at the same time anymore.
You would essentially need to uninstall
and reinstall system packages all
the time just to have
your two different projects still running.
Yeah, and having these environment
or requirements file also allows
you to essentially list things for others
so that you can more
easily share the package and share
the code and share what you
have done and what you're using.
And one more thing that I
think is quite useful, if
you have recorded these environments
and you at some point want to try out
Let's say a pip package
that you found that, oh,
that sounds very promising.
And you install it and
it changes five versions because pip says,
okay, well, you will now
want to install this package.
I will make sure that this package works.
And at the same time, pip
at least doesn't care about
whether it breaks some other things.
And then suddenly your code
doesn't work anymore and it's
sometimes very difficult to figure out
what exactly went wrong so
having this environment file that
you know is working allows you
to just say okay well
i'll delete that environment I
recreated and I have my stuff working again.
So um.
We'll give you I think 10
minutes again to go through
the time capsule exercise here.
which is essentially to be
answered in the collaborative document
and allowing you to have a
look at the different types
of projects that you can see.
And I think we have talked
about quite a bit of this already.
So hopefully this will not
be taking too long, but I
think, yeah, should we give five or 10?
Yeah, maybe.
Let's start with 10 minutes
and people can tell how it goes.
So see you back at 55.
Will come back so yeah we
have seen quite a few people
i'm marking down the right
comments to the different types of
what can be found in
the in the repositories and I
think we can all agree that
a is pretty useless be.
might be difficult to create
the software maybe we at least know
what kind of libraries there are
but we have no idea
what versions were being used and
so on um seam is already a
bit better and that it at least gives
for some of the things a bit more, well,
it gives the file that you
can actually get the data from,
but it still lacks the versions
and master is nothing that's stable.
um d has stable links um
main issue is yeah git
repositories can disappear if
someone decides that i don't
want this anymore then it
can become well obsolete and can
and can't be found anymore but
at the same time the same can
also happen with a conda package
It's a question.
These two are, in my
opinion, pretty much same quality.
It's a bit probably from ease of use,
preferable if you have the information
that they are on conda already,
because the dependency resolution
is better if they are on
conda, but sometimes the code just
isn't on the conda repositories.
I will go over the time capsule
for the future thing here
myself and not have it as an exercise.
So if we have an environment,
we can create an environment, or
if you have an environment
file, for example, myenv.yaml.
Come on.
and I think I just called it ML,
but luckily it doesn't matter
what file name I give it.
I can create an environment
quite easily by saying, okay,
well, I want this.
I want to create this
environment based from my.yaml and
it does matter, okay.
It does care about what
the file extension is,
And I created the environment already.
That I shouldn't have done.
But let's rename that.
So now it will be myEnv2.
And it will essentially
create that environment.
And then I will have
these dependencies listed there.
Of course, these dependencies don't
help me a lot because at least
if I get this from a project, I don't know
which NumPy version, I don't
know which Pandas version, I
don't know which Seaborn version.
And this is quite inconvenient.
Come on.
taking a bit longer today.
Okay.
We'll cancel that.
And just.
and just use the one that
I already have, which is my end.
So I can create that or can enter it.
And what I can do then is
I can export the environment.
And if I do that and
look into the environment file that
I have now created, it lists a lot of things.
And that is all things
that were installed by Conda with the version,
and the build version.
The problem with this is something
that build versions are
sometimes machine dependent.
That can be, for example,
some might work on Linux, some
might work on Windows.
that can be that they are GPU specific
or you have a library that
can use GPUs or doesn't use GPUs.
And depending on whether it finds
a GPU, it will install the one or the other.
So this can be a bit,
too much detail.
It's great to provide in
your final repository as a,
this was the environment that was being used
so that anyone who wants to reproduce this,
they can know exactly what
builds were being used for running your code.
And I would personally recommend
to have a full export available, but
what's for installation often
more convenient is something like
the from history.
And this essentially creates a file that,
just contains what you
originally installed.
So all dependencies below that
is something that it will pull independently.
One more thing that's not in
the notes, but that is relatively recent.
You can also do a
so-called no-builds export.
Oops.
Well, it went into from history now,
which is the same as the
first one, except that it
doesn't contain the builds.
This is a lot more easy to install
because it does not have
operating system dependent things,
which wouldn't install on
a different operating system.
but it can still have things
that are a bit tricky because
it can still have things
that are somewhat operating system dependent.
So it might still be too precise
because for some things you
need underlying operating system things,
operating system libraries that
are just not part of conda or
of one of these package managers.
And for example, pip assumes
that all system dependencies are
provided by the system.
It doesn't care about this.
While conda has a bunch
of more system-like libraries that
it also ships into the environments.
And this is also where we
can now step into the next area in this lecture,
where it's essentially about
shipping your whole operating system, i.e.
containers.
And well, there's this meme where,
and we had it in the
beginning, it works on my machine.
well then ship your machine.
And that is somewhat how Docker
and containers were born because
it sounds nice to ship a machine,
but you can't always just
take a computer and yeah, okay,
I'll just take that computer somewhere else.
No, it doesn't work.
However, what does work is
depending and a bit on the
operating system and on things,
to encapsulate as much as
possible of a computer into
a somewhat, into essentially a
kind of virtual machine, and
then run a simulated machine in the machine.
And containers are a small step above that.
They are not creating a
whole simulated environment, but
they are creating a,
largely simulated environment
where you have all the
system all the system level
dependencies in the in this container
and to come back to our
kitchen analogy so our codes
and scripts we said are the cooking recipes
And if we go for
containers, we have container
definition files that essentially
define what is in a container.
What does the container contain?
And they are somewhat like
blueprints on how to build the kitchen.
so what things need what plugs
need to be there what kind
of appliances need to be there and
so on then you have
the container images and those
are essentially showroom kitchens
similar to the build based
on these definition files
So built based on the
blueprints, you have built a
showroom kitchen on its own,
but it's not connected to anything.
It's just standing there.
The sinks are not connected
to the water supply and so on.
And when you then start
the container, you're taking one
of these images and you're starting
to plug in the different
cables and different pipes so
that your kitchen actually works.
And yeah, you can have a
look at these example kitchens
and think about what operating
systems they might represent.
So if we talk about
containers, we always go from
these definition files that just indicate,
okay, this is in there
to the actual container that's being run and
Containers can be built
to essentially bundle all necessary
tools and ingredients.
So they can even, also the ingredients.
So you can even bundle the
data into your container if you really want to.
It blows up the container
size-wise if your data is large,
but you can do that.
And the advantage to that is
that you have a stable thing that you can say,
okay, you can take this and
you can run it and it
should produce the same thing
that it produced locally for
me because it contains everything.
And a container and the
image is then essentially this thing
that you hand over to someone
else and it contains essentially anything.
And when you run it, you put, yeah,
kind of an additional layer on
top of that similar way
you can make modifications.
But if you shut down the running container,
this layer gets removed and you
are back at the image essentially.
And the definition files are
then the text files that define
a series of instructions on how
to build the container images.
And where and how can
you use these containers?
Well, they are mainly used
for two different purposes.
One is software installations
that are tricky.
For example, some database systems
or similar things where it's
just difficult to install them.
because they need administrative
privileges and so on.
And depending on the system,
you just don't have them and
you still want to use it.
So having something that allows
you to plug that in and to
still run it can be very handy.
Or if it's just a
very complicated installation where you
need a lot of
difficult to obtain libraries
that are necessary to run this.
What I can also imagine is something
where there is code from way
back and it's a lot easier to build a container
that can run the code,
then starting to write instructions
on how to run it.
Because when you write
these instructions, you can essentially
take a container definition file,
write these instructions inside
the container definition file, and
then you have the tool working.
And if you provide them
the container, you just have
the tool working and you don't
need to install them anymore.
And it's also making sure
that this is encapsulated.
This is not doing stuff
with your operating system.
So if I install a database
via a container, it's not modifying my system.
And I'm not, after shutting it down
and restarting my computer,
I don't suddenly have a
certain database running on
my computer because it,
Because if I had it
containerized, it was just running
in that container.
And if that container shut
down, the database is not active
and cannot be accessed from
the outside anymore.
So how do these container
recipes or reference files look?
This is an example
for Singularity definition file.
Singularity can use Docker images,
but you have to define that,
okay, this is coming from Docker
and this is using the image for Ubuntu 24.04.
And then when I have this
image, I want to install, I
want to do some installation,
some instructions that need to be done.
And in this case, it wants
to update the package cache
and then install Fortune, Kause and Lolcat.
Yeah, this is pretty,
well, useless container image, but
it's just for explaining how the things work.
You could have anything else
that you want to install here.
You could do compilations of
code that you have in there.
And you can also, by having a files field,
you can also copy files
from your operating system into the container.
and then for example compile them
and run and have them as compiled
as a compiled program you
can set environment variables based
on in this environment field
and then you define what
this container should do when it's being
when it's being used in this
case it would use fortune to
pipe it into cow say to
pipe it into lolcat which is more
of a more of a joke
than anything useful however there
There are definitely more
useful containers than this.
And we will come to one
of them a little bit later.
So what are the pros and
cons of containers in general?
The pro is definitely that
you can move workflows
across different platforms.
That being said, there's one caveat here.
At the moment, it's mostly
you can move Linux workflows
to other platforms.
I haven't really seen
Windows containers there because I
think the problem is that
the container softwares don't
really support Windows containers
mostly or Mac containers for that.
It can solve the works
on my machine situation
because you essentially, well,
somewhat ship your machine.
It allows for a more
stable future reproducibility because
if you have created the container
and you can provide the
container to someone else, they
can reproduce it because it has the software.
It has everything in there.
It's not, oh, this software
is not available anymore because
yeah, it is available.
It is in the container.
It doesn't need to be available.
Note here that this I'm
talking about the images, so if
they have been stored somewhere,
if you only have the
container definition file you're in
the same you're again at the
same point where Okay, well,
this can change versions and so on.
You can potentially use it
to send your computer to the data
when the data set is either too large
or cannot be transferred for
legal reasons like it needs to
be in a highly secure environment
and then you most often have the thing.
No, you can't install anything
from the internet.
The only thing that you can
do is you can provide us with a container
that we can put on the machine
and then you can use
whatever you have installed in
that container to analyze the data.
And yeah, that's in research
I think the most common thing
where it's really needed to use containers.
it's also possible to yeah
install software into a file
instead of into your computer
um you essentially transfer the file
this is a somewhat executable in
its in its own right um if you have a
if you have an execution
environment as so the so
docker potman obtainer or anything
There are some drawbacks to containers.
And one thing is that
containers can hide complexity
and hide problems that are
never solved because, oh yeah,
we are just hiding that in the container.
And that should realistically
be solved because yeah, they are a problem.
Otherwise they wouldn't be hidden.
So if the installation is so complex, then
Yeah, maybe it might be better
to get the installation a bit more easily done,
if possible, than in contrast
to just providing a container.
You can get into the, well,
works on my machine works
only in this container problem, because
if a container is not
recreatable anymore, because it
has some software that is
not available anymore,
Yeah, it works in the
container, but it doesn't work anywhere else.
Doesn't make things, well, at
least it works somewhere.
but it's still a bit problematic.
They can be difficult to modify.
So if you are in the situation
that it works only in
this container, then starting to modify
that container and modifying
the code that's in that container
can be a pain.
And container images can
become quite large.
We are talking about easily
having things like 10, 20
gigabyte container files very, very quickly.
So, and like with any software,
if you have, if you want
to install or use a container,
not all images can be trusted.
Be sure where you get the image from,
don't just take anything, especially
if you're using Docker,
because containers on tendency
run with administrative privileges.
So especially in Docker.
So if you run something in
a container, it essentially has
admin rights on your machine.
That's somewhat overcome on HPC
system with tools like AppTainer
or also Podman in non-root mode,
which run differently, but
on most workstations that run
Docker, you have a tool that
essentially can do anything and
runs on your system as root.
So be careful what kind
of containers you are using.
So, since exactly that problem
that Docker needs a route for installation,
we will do the exercise here
as a demo because I'm creating this,
or actually no, the
first exercise, something that you
can have a quick look for
five minutes as to how
reproducible you think this is.
And the second example I will demo
for so that you see where
things can be useful or how
containers can be useful.
So let's have a look for
five minutes at this time travel exercise.
It's essentially about
um writing down what you
notice with the with this
docker container um how reproducible
that is how good the docker
uh the docker file is um or
the uh in this case the singularity file
as in specifying what goes in there
and if we can reproduce this
just based on the um on
the docker on the singularity definition file
Okay, see you back at 22.
And then we are probably
also quickly getting to the wrap up.
and welcome back so um to
quickly go over what they um
what the file has i think
the biggest issue um if you
really want to reproduce this one
is that we have a latest
here which essentially means that
this is some version
There's also the copying of
local files that specifically say
in some folder that's not in the same folder.
So this could be from anywhere.
And we don't even know if
this is part of the repository
itself or from somewhere else.
So these are the two biggest
flags in here that make
reproduction somewhat difficult.
I will quickly show you
one thing where containers come in handy.
And that is, for example,
running an RStudio server.
And I've already started with Docker Run.
I don't have RStudio on
my machine normally because I
rarely work with R nowadays.
But like this, I can
essentially get an online RStudio
and have RStudio loaded and can
run my R stuff.
And if I have something that
says it needs R 3.3 or
whatever, or some older R version,
I can specify which version I
want by simply changing my docker run command.
And that's quite convenient just
to get things to run, just to try things out.
So as I mentioned, containers
are quite useful in helping
setting up complex systems and
complex setups for specific software,
and they can help you isolating things
for testing stuff without messing
up your own computing environment
in your own system.
So you don't need to
install more complex things and
thereby put trash into your
system that you actually don't want
to have in there.
So where to go from here?
Well,
We've mentioned a lot of
different things in this lecture.
And I just want to come
back to what [name] said in the beginning.
Don't get stressed with these.
It's not, you have to use
this all the time.
It's, we wanted to present
you tools that exist.
And we wanted to give you something
that helps in reproducing things,
that helps in making you be
able to come back to your code and reuse it.
because this is something
that's quite important for you
and for people that want to use your code.
As for the workflow tools,
as also mentioned in the
lecture, probably in a lot
of situations, they are not really needed.
But if the workflows that you
need to run become more complex
or you start continuously collecting data,
They become more and more useful
and you might really want
to think about starting to build
a workflow in a workflow tool and
not just in a script.
Containers, they...
are sometimes amazing and
sometimes really annoying because
it's another level of complexity
that you need to understand
and that you need to be able to run.
But on the other end,
sometimes you just can't get
around using containers because
the situation requires it, or it's
so difficult to get something
to run otherwise that the
container complexity is a lot simpler.
And you can run tools, Linux
tools on your Windows or on
your Mac that weren't
easily runnable otherwise.
It might allow you to have
a lot more easy installation instructions.
Yeah.
And you get a fully configured environment.
So I think what we want
to really stress that is
something that's useful for every
project is having a clear
directory and file structure sticking
to it and keeping it up to date.
So not just having the
structure, but also filling the
structure with life.
record your workflow in a script
and write it down in a script
so that once someone else wants to do it,
they can run a script and
they can get the resource that you present.
Or also, if I may
interject, I mean workflow, if you
have to have any other manipulation steps
and you have to modify data
and you maybe are not using
code for that, which is always the best idea.
But if you can't automate certain steps,
also then write down a
workflow that details those steps.
So it doesn't have to be
in a workflow management tool.
It doesn't have to be a script,
but it has to be documented
what to do in which order.
I think that's the important thing to note.
For me, one very, very,
very important point is create
a dependency list and keep it updated.
Optimally do it in an environment file,
but keep a list of
the dependencies with versions
that you're using.
And personally, if I would
be running something in a
conda environment nowadays and publish that,
I would provide the full export
and probably the from
history version because that's
what I installed and this is
what I got kind of.
So you can follow the exact
steps that I did
which might not lead to the same results,
but it can also look into, okay,
what has now changed between
what he was doing and what I am doing now.
And you can always take
the from history export and
populate it with additional
version information.
So in the example, we had
NumPy without a version, but of
course you can take that
from your full environment export
and add the versions for the
major packages in there.
And finally, if you at least consider
that someone wants to reproduce your work,
and hopefully people will,
and anything that you can do
to make their life easier and your life,
very likely actually your life,
if you build on your previous
work, is really helping yourself and others.
There's a lot of additional
further reading that you can have a look into.
And I think with that, I
would give the head over to
[name] for some final words.
yes thank you [name] so we
are perfect on time because we
have one minute left with our
day four of code refinery at
the bottom of the notes document
maybe if you are not could
switch to the notes document
we have this feedback so if
you click on the notes document
and edit you can add on the
top there's a poll where you can specify
if it was too fast too slow and
so on and i can see
already some people are answering
and in general something good
something to improve and any
other feedback or questions i
think more or less we
have covered everything and we try to give
useful answers, hopefully, to
the notes document.
So we are perfect on
time, unless there's anything else
that we should discuss, you know, [name]?
not on my side all right
so thank you again so much to
[name] and to [name] for being
instructors of day four and we
will meet again next week for
day five where we will kind of continue on this
same topics but more related
to the collaborative side of things
when you need to basically
agree with others whether
they are collaborators or stranger
how you will work together
on a specific project or on
a specific software and so thank
you again for the feedback and
see you in seven days bye bye bye see you