Hello, hello.
Can you hear us?
Let's see if the Zoom or
not Zoom, if our Zulip audience is hearing us.
Hello, [name].
Hi.
tried to make the title
visible and I clicked on
the wrong slider again.
So the sound might be
slightly different from the way it was before.
I wonder what the number
was originally, but everyone can
adjust the volume.
So this point is probably fine.
I'll just keep it the way
it is for the rest of the session.
Can people hear us though?
Did you check this?
Okay.
Anyone on Twitch, Zulip, can you hear us?
Yeah.
so basically we are at day five
as usual if you were
already in the previous four days
of this code refinery workshop
you might already know how we
are going to operate together
so you're watching the twitch
tv stream and then there
is this collaborative document that
i'm showing right now
and there in this collaborative document
if you were not pressing
the previous days it's actually
very intuitive system at the very
top there is a pencil and
so for example now let's go to
the very top you might not
see my pencil but it's okay
All right.
Okay.
So you see there's a pencil.
I click the pencil and there
the page turns into like
an editor and basically you can just edit.
And so I added a
couple of icebreaker questions.
How is the weather at your location?
I think it was quite cold this morning.
Is it that you're in Oslo [name], right?
I'm not sure how it's in Oslo,
but Trondheim was, I used
clothes on my bike here to office today.
So I see it's starting
to getting colder here.
And last weekend, I think there
was snow in the mountains around 900 meters.
So winter is coming.
Winter is coming.
Definitely.
even though it's what the
second day of autumn but anyway
so those of you who are online
you can open this notes document
i guess you just received an
email with the with the notes document
so and basically write down
the weather but maybe more
interesting and i can ask this
question also to the others here in the room
I'm sure you have shared some
of your code or maybe you helped because
both of you are research
software engineers and maybe you
helped some researchers writing some
code for them.
So how do you usually give
codes to others, for example, [name]?
Yeah, well, I think I mostly emailed
or pasted into I can
on GitLab issues example code
and I haven't licensed it in any way just
I haven't said whether I had
gotten it from either.
But it's been mostly snippets of code.
And I think that's quite common
in all of just in university setting
and also the software industry
that small snippets of codes
are shared and copied.
Yeah.
What about you, [name]?
Well, I mean, I'm a
research software engineer.
It's my job to share code with researchers.
So essentially whatever they
want, usually Git on GitHub or
a local GitLab instance.
Also attachments and email.
shared folders.
What else?
I haven't used a thumb drive
yet in this job.
I have in previous jobs, like a USB drive.
Whatever works, whatever they can use.
is the best.
But of course, I prefer to use Git
and publish it so I can
make it available for everyone.
But then is it that when you give the code,
let's say that you, I don't
know, write the function or a script
for someone you're helping,
do you explicitly tell them
you can do whatever you want
with this code or you need
to cite my whatever copyright?
um if i make it public then
i use a license um but not explicitly
because we are i mean
we are essentially always been
working at the same university
and been collaborating on the code
so it's um the university owns
the code to some extent but
it's a good point like if
they want to publish it at
some point then in principle they
would need to ask my permission
which you if i have given you
some code you have my permission
to publish it but
This is not the best
channel for doing that.
I guess we'll come to that later.
And this is exactly basically
the topic of today that
sometimes you might even share,
okay, this is the bit of
code that whatever this postdoc
before me was using, and now I
pass it on to you.
And maybe it's all fine
and there's no issues, but
you can understand that maybe
is this whatever mysterious postdoc,
are they going to be cited?
or at least you know will
there be some mentions that
they actually were the original
writers of the code so this
is what we will basically cover
in this topic today which is
a kind of an interesting topic
because it's a mixture of
kind of legal reasons that
sometimes you you know you need
to be in order with the law
when you share the code or
use somebody else's code but then
it goes also towards more ethics that
if you you know if someone
was helping you it's good to
mention that this person was
helping you right so anything else
do you want to mention
Yeah, I worked for a startup
once that was acquired by Sun Microsystems.
And then there was a
huge due diligence process.
And one of the major things
was the source code of the
product that they were buying.
Where did this source code come from?
And it was developed in-house,
but they more or less went
through all of the code to make sure that
there wasn't parts that were copied from,
especially open source GPL
products or projects.
So they had a very
thorough process going through all
of the source code to make sure
that it was in fact written in-house.
yeah i agree and this
is also sometimes important that
maybe some of you might now
just starting to share code some
of you have been sharing
code and writing whatever
libraries extensions for for many
years you never know where
your code might actually end up
and then this type of
commercial slash legal issues might
you know, maybe even come
back in a positive sense that maybe, you know,
you get famous and hired
by whatever larger company in the world
or maybe, you know, as
most likely happens with researchers,
you will never see any penny out of your code .
But, you know, let's try to keep positive.
Alright, so let me check the clock
and the clock is saying that
in 20 seconds it's time to start.
I can switch back to the view mode.
and i guess we can now
start so good afternoon everyone
and welcome to episode 5 of
the code refinery workshop and
we have already covered so far
in the first part three
consecutive days all that is related to git
and also github and how to
work with git locally and how
to work with other people
and collaborate with them through github
in the fourth day we then
had a look at kind of at
the core topic of
reproducibility specifically computational
reproducibility and today we kind
of build on top of this
previous part but we kind of add some sort of
how can i call it like a legal angle
but also ethical angle on
how to reuse other people's code but also
how to tell others that how
they can reuse our core how
can basically we get cited so
with me today there is [name]
lindy hi [name] hi [name]
And [name] is a research
software engineer at NTNU, am I right?
Did I spell it right?
Norwegian University of Technology
and Science, yes.
So do you want to briefly mention
how is your normal day at
work and what do you do at NTNU?
Yeah, you see the logo behind me here.
It's Endris.
It's Norwegian research infrastructure.
So that's a lot with data storage and HPC.
So last week I had a
full support week on the
national supercomputing systems.
So my job is to support
on HPC systems, but also support
research software locally at
the university.
Yes, it's nice that in this
run of the Code Refinery workshop,
we had many people actually involved with HPC.
And in general, for those of you
who are affiliated with
the university, most likely you
have access to an HPC cluster,
whether it's the university cluster
or some national cluster.
And this is something that
maybe you want to bring at
some point into your workflows.
But anyway, I'm now sharing,
I'm now showing this, how do
you call it, the homepage of
the workshop and today's day five.
So if you click on the
link that there says social coding,
this will be the materials for today.
A quick reminder when it comes
to the intro that we have
been using this notes document
that you should have just received via email.
and so if you open this
notes document in a browser
window there's a pencil at the very top
so if you click on the
pencil you can basically edit
the document and ask questions
or interact with us in the studio
and especially today the
notes document will be very important
because the exercises that we
will have they're not going
to be writing code, running
code or running some git
commands the exercises will be
kind of discussion based exercises
that will happen on the notes
so please everyone open your
notes document and of course
any questions you can write them here
You can see how I can add.
All right, but let's then
get actually started with the topic of today.
So social coding, it's nice that the name,
I remember the first time I
took the Code Refinery workshop,
and heard about this social
coding, I thought, is this
about, I don't know, sitting in
the same room and coding together or,
you know, but later I
kind of understood that it's
more related to the fact that we are not
isolated coders that most likely
we work in a system whether
we reuse other people code or
whether we create code that
our people will reuse or often
we belong to a team for
example a research group and it might be
that maybe you're the only one
who codes there or maybe
there's someone else who's coding
there and you need to share
or you know reproduce what
other people have been doing
So in general, in this
lesson, we will discuss kind of how
and why to share code, but
also data, which is important.
And when it comes to sharing code
and data, you will hear
often the concept of licenses
that are basically kind of like contracts
that are defining the rules on
how do we share what we
created and how do we reuse
what someone else has created.
so again here it mentions
the FAIR principles this was
also we touched on the FAIR
principle last week last wednesday
which is this findable
accessible interoperable and reusable
four principles that are
basically making sure that the
code but also the data can be reused and
in a way that is legal ethical
and kind of you know sustainable
so that other people can build
on top of your work like
most likely in your research
work you're building on top
of existing research
So why software licenses matter?
Well, you find for example
some great code or data that
you want to reuse and you kind
of want to give credit to whoever wrote
that code or published the data
so that you can actually cite,
like you would normally cite a publication.
but then sometimes you might
need to modify the code a
little bit to adapt it to your
case it's kind of we will
often talk about remixing bits of code
or bits of data and then it
might be a bit less less clear
how much can you change are
you allowed to change can you
do whatever you want and so
for for clarifying this basically
we have licenses
I mentioned that if you're
citing a paper, then there's no license.
You can easily build on
other people's research or doing
your own research.
But when it comes to software,
you have to be careful because
you have to know that you can build on it.
Yeah that's true that in a
way I mean of course the equivalent is
that I might write things
in the paper without actually
citing you know the original source
who wrote some statement and maybe
that is not illegal but it's
kind of you know in the
point of research ethics it's
you know you can't just
copy paste somebody else's paper
and plagiarize but with
code there's another layer like
like like you just said
there's another layer of difficulty
that immediately from from the
first day can i just reuse
this bit of code that i
found online on stackoverflow or
or like we will see later
that some chat gpt has made for me
So hopefully we will
basically clarify this.
So maybe very briefly, because
before I pass the microphone to [name],
in general, maybe today is
a little bit more for those of you
who are actually coding reusable
code so that you can share
it and other people can use it.
but in general this will
be important knowledge for anyone
who has to work with coders
whether in a research environment
or maybe later in your life if you go
even outside academia so in
general we will try to cover
the basics but also practical
stuff related to all these aspects
so I move to the
social coding page and I pass the
so [name] what are the
objectives of this first part
of the lesson yeah thank
you [name] the objectives of
the social coding is that we're
going to get an overview
of motivations and benefits but
also risks of sharing and reusing code
we'll learn to identify whether
you can use other people's software.
And then we can start
out with a discussion, a poll.
We'll paste in the four
questions into the shared document.
Yes, I just pasted them.
Yeah, so you can ponder on this
for 10 minutes and then
we'll discuss them together.
so let's have a exercise
where it's this social one 10
minutes so we can be back in 19 past
Hi everybody.
Welcome back again.
I hope you had a good
time answering the questions.
We'll take a look at your
answers and your votes.
So starting with question one,
why would you want to share
your scripts code data?
And we see many votes for
easier to find and reproducibility.
That's good.
and increased trustworthiness.
Others can verify and find bugs.
Enable others to build your
own portfolio code.
Others can submit improvements
and help fixing.
um we say that there's
less there's just one vote
on the scarring competitors
and that's interesting um uh uh
i i i'm impressed by a
library like armadillo which is a liner
algebra c++ library and I
think they kind of take up the space
for others and they use
Apache 2 license what do you think [name]?
of this first question in general?
no this yeah the response on
h the letter h in the first
question oh yeah the
discouraging the competitors well I don't know
It's interesting that there's just
one vote for that, but it's true
that sometimes competition in academia
and science is quite, you
know, people cut corners and if, you know,
But on the other hand, we
are often drive by good ethical principles,
so maybe it's nice to see at least
that this is reflected in
the audience here that the
majority are openly sharing or
to ensure reproducibility and trustworthiness.
Me personally, I never
thought of discouraging competitors.
I'm actually encouraging competitors
to find errors in my scripts.
Has it ever happened to you that someone
It's quite rare, but it's
not impossible that someone has found
a bug or something in your published code.
No, not my code.
I haven't published that much code.
It's just been more or
less snippets to individuals.
It also goes to the fact
what someone was writing the
extra questions at the bottom
that do reviewers like peer
reviewers actually review also the
code of the paper because you
know in theory people can find
bug in your code but if
nobody's gonna review it it's you know.
Yeah and
a real instructor from the
previous lessons from the East
University of Finland.
Yeah.
No.
What's she called?
You know, she had published a
paper on that together with others.
where it showed that it was
pretty, it was not good when
it comes to reproducing results
and using published software.
Right, so question two.
Yeah, that that's what's
the concerning thing for me or for you.
And then we see that exposing
ugly code is Is very
present I have less problems now
than previously I do horrible
things on github publicly just using it
if I have a learning project
I establish it on github so at
least I have it I don't mind having it publicly
I have the personal
motivational factor that from day zero,
I start coding as if
everything that I'm coding is public.
So then, even though I might not even,
you know, push it to any GitHub
or something, but already knowing this,
that someone is watching me,
then it's like, you know,
I named the variables with
meaningful names, not just A, B,
C, and D, and try to add
some comments that, you know,
which is in general, at the
end of the day, it's not
going to help maybe anyone else.
It's more going to help me in a week
or in a month to actually
know what I was doing if the
code is not that terribly ugly.
But question three and four
are more interesting and more nuanced.
Is there anything that you
picked from question three, Björk?
Yeah, the first ones, I have no idea.
What's your opinion on this question?
Is software treated differently
from papers?
It's definitely treated differently.
I mean, papers are the things
you get your CVs and credit
from, much less so with software.
yeah but we see that there
are some answers around that
papers are usually one-time publications
and software is constantly
being improved but then of
course one could also argue that
I might, and it has
happened to me actually, I
have published some software with
some paper, but then they never
went back to that software.
So in the end, it's
whatever, you know, version used to
be 10 years ago.
So nobody in a way should
be forced to keep the
software maintained and improved.
Like with papers, they were
not supposed to go back and suggest edits or
And you have here some
code might consider a
research infrastructure more than
a research output.
But if code, code have to
be maintained and will be improved.
So these add-ons and changes
are often results of research.
Someone did this metaphor.
yeah that software is like
a recorded song so like basically
what a dj would do instead
the papers i like this you
know written notes sheet music
you can just copy the notes you must create the
original composition but building
for the ideas yeah yeah
it's an interesting metaphor i
have to think about it if
it works in our context but it's right
what about question four yeah
when you find a repository
with code would you like to use
it what are you looking for yes
Usually go from a paper to
the code and then check
whether you understand the code.
Yes, that's possible.
I would check for the dates
that things are committed.
And also see if there
are frequent updates to the software.
What about you, [name]?
Yeah, I mean, I agree with
what the people brought here.
Especially this, I find it
really important that it's maintained.
I know that sometimes there's
very specific software that maybe
has not been updated in five years,
but because there's just that
and you specifically need to
use that, you know, what can you do?
But if I'm choosing between libraries
that might do something similar,
I'd rather go for the one that
I can see in their GitHub
or GitLab repository that they
that a few weeks ago
they were doing changes and things like
that so definitely the last
point here tests that's a good
one tests which shows you how
software can be used so that's very good
But what we now and then
experience on HPC system is that you take,
download the software, install it,
run the tests, and there are
200 tests and 175 of them passes.
What do you do then?
Yeah, this is a very important aspect
that me, for example, I
rarely consider that, okay, this
library does what I want, just
import and use, but it's
true, it's very important.
All right, so now if we
go back to the lesson, so
what about these two pictures here, [name]?
Yeah, well, we know that we can cite others
papers and from all this
research, we get new ideas.
And so that's, if you have
a PhD, you don't start out from scratch.
With PhD, if you are a PhD student
and a part of a PhD
program, you don't start out from scratch.
Somebody has written more or
less the task for you.
And so you have to read a lot of papers and
often cite these papers at
your progress in your work.
Doing the same thing with software is,
well, we should probably cite software,
but you could then have
either that your code are part
of what others do or
And then you have to relate to others
that send you improvements of
your code and others that also
want to cite your code.
So this is somewhat different
than citing a paper which has a much more
a natural natural a common
and established way of of doing
it what about like if we consider
Because, for example, journal policies,
I've been at least changing
a little bit, for example, when
it comes to sharing data.
Now many journals require a
so-called data availability statement.
What about the code?
Can this be a motivation
for sharing the code?
Yeah, I think this can be
a motivation for sharing the code, absolutely.
But then, as studies have
shown, it's not always possible
to reuse the code, though it's shared.
Things stop despite being shared.
But we see here both Science
and Nature has editorial policies
for sharing code.
And Nature has also
requirements for sharing the data.
And that can be a lot,
quite a large volume.
Yeah.
And so here in the bottom of the page,
we have this motivation for
open source software, but also
this type of scaring aspects.
I guess that most people kind of,
this was already mentioned by
many in question one.
Yes, it was.
And also when it came to what's scary,
being scoped and also published
the ugly code was quite many thought of.
And the scare that someone
might find bugs or mistake.
Also somebody that's on the phone.
On the other hand, one
could even consider that actually
it's a good thing.
I mean, maybe it's not a
good thing from the perspective
of a researcher that, okay, well,
there was a bug in my code
and now all my papers are wrong.
I need to retract them all.
But then on the other hand,
from the point of view of science
and research, it's good that
some bug was actually found.
Yes, yes.
it's a double-edged sword exactly yeah
what about this and this
maybe also comes um comes also
with the fact that if i now
look also at the research
software engineers that sometimes we
need to help researchers to
reuse somebody else's code but the person
who maybe invented that code
created that code they're not
supporting it they're not you
know sometimes you can't even ask them
so is this also something
that maybe people don't want
to share their code because they
will feel this pressure that
forever they will need to support
the code and answer to
frequent questions around the code
yeah yes that can be
all right so then basically at
the end is code reusability
so what contributes to reusability
Yeah, we partly discussed it,
but that it's licensed and
so you are allowed to use it.
And that we will discuss a
little bit later on which license to choose.
Install the instructions or tests
so we can show how the
software is used or the code is used.
And that it's not 10 years old,
but updated with issues and
requests and commits.
Yeah.
Well, maybe we don't need
to do this exercise here because
maybe this is a bit more
kind of a reflection on this type of issues
that we discussed that you
aren't required to support anyone,
that it's important to publish
the code, even though, you
know, maybe you will never touch
it again, but to wrap up this page.
So, so yeah.
What do you want to
mention, [name], before we move to the next one?
yes here is the here we see whether
and what we can share depends on
how we obtain the components
but here is your work kind of
used in us as a source as
a software used by others
to write articles and promote ideas.
And your work is also dependent on others.
So to promote science and
create more bang for the
buck, it's important that software
are citable and licensed for others to use.
And this is what we will
cover basically in the rest
of these hours together.
Right.
So if I click next and turn the page,
now we finally introduce
software licensing.
And well, the idea here is
to kind of know about the
type of basically derivative work,
the type of reuse of remix that you can do.
with others people software and
of course how can you share
what you've done and now can
you also you know get uh
you know citations from from this
from the work that you do and more generally
as i was mentioning earlier
it's important to get familiar
with the terminology it might be
that it's not something that you
need today it might be that
you will have helpers at your
research organization or even in
a company when it comes to
this type of issues that start
to become legal issues but
in general it's important that you
are aware of these things if
you work with software so in
when it comes to copyright so
copyright is a type of
intellectual property rights and
there are different types
of intellectual property rights
more related to kind of
trademark or bad events or, you know,
kind of, you know, this type of
how to protect ideas or
better to protect implementation of ideas.
But if you write a piece
of software, then it's you
as implementer that has the
copyright to the code.
It's not the university, right?
Well, I've been hanging around
too much with lawyers, so
they would always say, it depends.
But at least in all the universities
that I've seen, the deal is
this, that yes, you have the
copyright of the code.
I've seen sometimes people writing
in the license copyright by
name and surname, and I
don't know, Aalto University.
So that it's like, I did
this work when I was at Aalto University,
and you share the copyright
but in general when it comes to
how can I say to the copyright
of an idea of an algorithm
those are something that they
basically you can't read the
copyright in this legal sense you
can't put the patent
so that in general
copyright and intellectual property
rights they try to protect systems
so the specific implementation
of an algorithm of a
software embedded maybe in other
parts of a digital system infrastructure
and that you can patent it
and copyright it but if it's
they just invent a new method
and it's just a pseudo code algorithms that's
kind of not copyrightable but
then it's the i just added
this well here it's um here
the page starts talking about
the concept of derivative work meaning
that sometimes we want to like like
when we write paper that we
want might want to reuse what
other people did and we might want to cite them
The same is also with software
that luckily we don't have
to always rewrite all the
libraries from scratch and any
bits of whatever we need to
do with our data can actually
be a combination of reusing
existing libraries that other people
have made public.
And of course the question for us
as users of various libraries
that are building code is to understand
Okay, I built some software
that requires kind of installing
or calling these other libraries.
Am I allowed to do that?
Can I then share my code
that is built on that?
Do I need to cite the
libraries that I've been using?
Changing and distributing software
is similar to changing
and distributing music, so sometimes
you are not allowed to just reuse or
take verbatim some piece of
code some other times you
are actually fully allow and this
is the why these software
licenses are basically enabling how
much you can reuse and
remix in your derivative work and
how much you basically can touch
with this exercise maybe we take
it in a minute i want
to add a little parenthesis something
that i added recently to this page
which is something that came
up in previous code refinery workshops
because sometimes at least for
for researchers is more
familiar the concept of plagiarism
which is not exactly the
same as intellectual property rights
So plagiarism is more related
to research ethics and so you can plagiarize,
let's say that you copy paste the paper,
the scientific paper of someone
else's and just pass it as yours.
And of course, you know,
if your organization or whatever
journal you submit that they
use something like Turnitin, they
would see that your paper
is plagiarized because it's, you know,
it's basically copy pasted
from someone else's work that
you didn't acknowledge.
So plagiarism is this
type of unacknowledged.
work, but intellectual property
rights infringement is more that
you are not authorized to
use someone else's work, that
I'm not authorized to use, I don't know,
some seconds of [name]'s song to
make my own new song unless
I ask for the permission.
And this is basically the main idea
that stands behind this
copyright licenses or patents, that
it's not just about citing like
we would do with the plagiarism
from an ethics perspective.
It's more saying, okay,
I still cite you, of course,
I still say I use your code,
but I also follow the rule
that come with your code, that
come with your patent or
whatever intellectual property rights
you have.
and so this is maybe something
that sometimes it's not clear
these two aspects but they're
both important because plagiarism
from research ethics perspective
can basically end in misconduct
so your papers get actually
retracted if you you know
plagiarize somebody without
giving acknowledgement
with the software maybe your
paper will not be retracted if
you break the license of some other code
that you have included in your software
but of course the people
who might have intellectual property
right they could potentially come
back to you and that is
like a criminal offense so
eventually you will need to pay
a fine or if not you your organization
I don't want to scare
anyone with this thing.
Actually, I want to motivate people
that the good thing of
open source software and open
licenses is to avoid the
mess of proprietary intellectual
property rights, copyrighted materials.
But I'm talking a lot and
it's nice to always see our clever audience.
So let me paste this question
to the notes document.
Now, maybe we don't need to
go away from the stream, but
we can ask everyone to vote by
adding this O or zero, whatever
is your favorite in this example.
So which of these are derivative works?
I will switch to the notes
to see what people are answering.
And these are interesting cases,
I would say, let me check
I think I've done them all So
we can see that A is getting lots of traction
download some code from a website
and add it onto it so yeah a and b
and do a lot yeah also what
we said at the beginning changing
code you got from somewhere
because maybe like you mentioned
you help some researcher you
give them a snippet yeah
But then, I mean, for example,
this is a clear case that
you didn't give a license.
You are not claiming any copyright.
You will never, you know,
see you a researcher from your university.
You did.
But then do you expect that, for example,
your help or your services are,
for example, in the acknowledged
section of the paper that
they could acknowledge the
research software engineer or NTNU?
In some instances, the
group are acknowledged, not
the individual, but the kind
of service that we provide.
Yeah, but so then this is, it's still,
you know, it kind of
goes with this legally, they
don't need to acknowledge you,
but ethically it's good that
they acknowledge your group.
We have the same at
Aalto University with the
research software engineers and
our HPC cluster.
so when it comes to
e so completely rewriting code
you got from somewhere is it
derivative work in your opinion [name]
I'm not sure.
I think it's rewriting, it can
be done in several ways.
You have an HDR, which
is clean room design, which I
think is an AMD that designs
the Intel processor or the x86
processor from a clean room
designer to just get a
described and i'm not sure
there are some stories computer
stories around clean room this kind
so it's through age it's
a bit different than e because i could
even take a library and all i
do is copy it line by
line just changing the name of
the variables and the name
of the functions that's not
true that's not real writing
But it's like people,
unfortunately, they write essays with ChatGPT,
so they copy whatever line of text
and then they just add an
adjective and so making it their own.
Well, but there again, I mean, you like,
you have in JetBrains or VS
Code, you have GitHub client,
which then expands code for you.
And what kind of code is that?
Is that code it has seen on the internet?
Or does it generate it purely for you?
I don't think it does the last one.
I think it's get it somewhere.
yeah it's a mesh it's a
it's a puzzle of different pieces
but yeah this was good and i would say
that you kind of got the
got the right answer in the i
go back to the page in
the page there's a solution that
um but i still think that
sometimes it's always you know
It's always nuanced and tricky.
We mentioned last Wednesday,
we talked about containers and
containers are interesting because
they are like
that you can basically look
at containers as a recipe of
all the system that you need
to run your software so that
if i distribute just a recipe this is
how you build my kitchen i'm
not giving you the whole
kitchen just the recipe of how to build it
so that you can run whatever
food that i'm asking you to
make but one can also basically
create build the container image
and then distribute the binary kind of
and this is again another nuanced thing
and tricky thing because in
the end when you aggregate
all these things together
I added the reference there from the GPL
if it's just aggregation that
you collect some libraries and
put them together but they're
still you know that someone
can basically look at the
container image look inside and see
that different libraries have
their different licenses it's okay
but when the moment that you
just wrap the container around
a run script that in the
end is just whatever name of the command
and then some input file that
you pass then you're creating
like a new software like a binary
that would have inside all
the libraries and then it
gets more tricky because of these licenses
that I will you can already
see the picture below because
then it's then you can't just
release it with whatever license that you want
to release this container image
but you might need to
follow you know whatever more
strict license that is so so
if you have a have gpl copy
left inside in your software
stack that then goes for
the whole container that you're creating
exactly and this is why these licenses
that are still open source licenses
but they're called viral because
they kind of infect all the
rest of the code or software that you are
that you are sharing the
idea made basically that let's say
that you build the software
so that it within this
pipeline or whatever tool that
you build is going to call libraries
that have different licenses that
the very permissive open license
that you might want to use
well then some licenses of other tools are
so strict that they would
basically force their license on your license
So to understand this with
this picture which comes from a
paper of the European
Commission specifically for the
European Union public license one
type of open source license.
So you can think of the
code that exists in the world
to be divided between proprietary code
that basically follows proprietary
licenses full copyright and then
you have open source code.
Now in the open source code,
so this green triangle that you see here,
that is like a continuum
of different type of licenses
that you can attach to the open source code.
So some here at the
bottom, dark green, they are
very permissive licenses.
There's basically no condition.
Sometimes the only condition is that
Well, actually, let's start from
the very bottom.
At the very bottom, we
have this gray block, which is public domain.
This basically means that
there's absolutely no license or
some type of licenses are
called the unlicensed or this.
For data, they're called
Creative Commons Zero.
So this is public knowledge.
Nobody owns it.
And you can release code
under this unlicensed.
So this is the hello world in C.
Right.
Exactly.
Public domain.
nobody you don't need to you
know make sure that you
don't offend any developer of C
hello world in C is public domain
but then you start of
course having this open source licensee
and the very permissive one all
they ask is that you keep the license
if you reuse the code and just
what we said earlier
acknowledge that you've been
reusing somebody else's code
that you're building on top of it
The good thing of this
permissive license is that if
you have a company, if you
work in a company and you
need to include some libraries or
some pieces of code that are
released with this permissive
license, then it's possible.
So this red arrow means that
yes, you can actually include them.
So, for example, I mentioned Armadillo
as a linear algebra library,
which has Apache 2.0.
So then you can include that
and use that in your
proprietary product that you sell.
exactly and i'm pretty sure
that many codes that researchers
have written are actually now they
do exist in actual products that
can be in our smartphones or
you know whatever because they've
been released with permissive
open source licenses and then
they can be reused basically
for commercial proprietary use
But the more we keep on
going up in this type of
continuum of strictness of the
open source licenses, the more
we introduce the concept of copyleft.
And the idea of copyleft, I don't know
how to explain it in an intuitive way,
but it would be... I think
the concept is, if you go
to copyright, Richard Stallman...
coined this phrase copy left and
he took it from copyright
and copyright is strong it's
somebody's work right and but
copy left then is also strong
but it goes the opposite way
it kind of influences everything
it's included in
Exactly.
And I guess this is
the kind of motivational factor of Stalma
and others who started, who
promoted these various copyleft licenses
so that you find my
product useful, you find my
code useful, and you want to
include it in your
proprietary package, software, whatever.
Well, actually, you also need
to make your proprietary
software basically following the same license.
Yes.
But there is an interesting
link on the weak copyleft
into proprietary licenses.
Because the difference between
weak and strong is worth mentioning.
And LGPL
and also the Mozilla license, which is MPL.
There you can have a
library that's licensed under LGPL.
So everything you do to
the library itself has to be public
or open source, but you can
use the library in your
proprietary software or closed source project.
And for Mozilla, that goes
for individual files, so you can
use the MPL to then go
public with individual files, but
it can be used in
closed source projects without
having any consequences for the
closed source project.
yeah this is a great explanation
because then it really
makes people understand the importance
of this continuum and I've
been reflecting with others in
Code Refinery we have a nice
Zulip chat where we have sometimes this type of
conversation on one hand I feel
that sometimes we should
release our software with a
strong copy left so that if
whoever big tech giant will
actually reuse our software they
need to also join the strong copy left
But the problem is that most
likely the big tech giant is
just going to rewrite my code and not cite me.
So in the end, the strong copy left,
although in principle I totally agree,
is going to create troubles
to actually to my peers,
to other scientists who just want
to reuse my function or my
library or my method.
So most of the time you
will see research code released
under this MIT or Apache or
BSD because then you know that
you make the life of other
people like you easier, that
they can just reuse it, don't
worry too much about licenses
and get their papers out basically.
So I don't know.
Do you ever?
Where do you sit in this spectrum?
My heart is on the GPL,
but my praxis is MIT.
so basically we agree and
then in this picture here there
are also some licenses that
are not really related to
code they're more related to data
we will touch on this data aspects
so even though this is
code refinery there will be a
data refinery at the end of
today but we basically have
two minutes before the break and
we kind of already covered all of this
maybe we could have a
break 10 minutes break starting now
and then there's interesting
questions on what about stack
overflow not there but in the
if you go licensing situations
I pasted the stack overflow
questionnaire into Claude from
Antrofic isn't it
And Claude answered that the
Stack Overflow or the code
from Stack Overflow wouldn't be
licensed under creative commons.
But the practice for small
code snippets was that you just could copy
and paste it and not refer
to where you didn't get it from.
Yeah.
But in the end, I think
that the terms of service of
Stack Overflow is that it follows this.
Yeah, that you have to
attribute where you didn't get it from, yeah.
of course who does it and
i sometimes i add it in
the comments this was taken from yeah
but i've seen comments where
the link to the stack overflow dialogue is so
All right, but it's 2 p.m.
o'clock in Finland, so it's
perfect time for a break.
Let's say 10 minutes break and
get back at 10 past.
I will edit the notes document
and we can switch to the notes here now.
Bye.
hello hopefully you had a short break
and stretch your legs it was
a nice comment important comment
in the notes document on kind
of what are these arrows so we
try to explain a bit but i
agree also with the commenter that
maybe this is not the most
clear picture for expressing you know
how licenses interplays but I
think the take-home message is you know
if for your work for
your daily research work try
to use a permissive license and maybe
when you start working in
a larger project that could
enforce stronger licenses you
know remember that then those
who want to write proprietary
software with your work they will
not be able unless they fully reopen everything
so maybe we will not
do this licensee exercise there
are interesting questions and
that's the solutions there for
you just to wrap up this
license episode it's in general
when should i add a license
where i would say choose a license
as early as possible in the project
if you remember what we did
on the first week where we
created a github repository using
the github interface
When you create the repository
through the web interface,
it would actually immediately ask
you, do you want to add a license?
So already that's a good
moment that you can already pick a license.
Sometimes you don't have all
the possible list of all
the possible licenses that exist
in this world, which brings us
to the next topic.
that how to choose a license
and it's there are so many
licenses out there and I'm
sure every license has a reason to exist
but you can see already
in the software that you use
if you find the source code
of whatever library that there's
a subset of licenses that are
more used than others
But maybe what is important
for you to remember is that
do not rewrite your own license.
Do not invent the wheel.
These specific licenses, the wordings
that they include, they are
built exactly for those purposes.
So it's much easier and better
that you find the right license
for your case and then
just reuse that license
without any modification.
And the reason for not rewriting
or writing your own license is
that your license will not
be recognized and then people have
to use a lot of effort
trying to understand what the
implications of your license are.
Exactly.
There are different tools out there.
I think in the links in
the bottom we list more other
of this, how to choose a license.
This one here, which is
part of the Interopable Europe,
it's like a European Commission
website all related to licenses
and software and things like that.
And here, for example, you
can look at various types of licenses
that are available by specifying,
you know, what the license can
do or must do or cannot do.
And you can also show here,
for example, if I write MIT.
that we mentioned earlier so
we can see that you know
others can use reproduce
distribute modify whatever you
work they release what they must
do is that they must include basically your
name and surname and copyright
that is there in your
version of the license and you
cannot be hold liable if they
misuse your your software this
license is compatible with
anything basically it's a very permissive
and so you know it
is strong community-based license it's
a it's so it's a it's a good good license
so this this type of
tools again personally what i
recommend is to check what
other people what the people
that are making the software
the language that you use what they use
and kind of join their community
and use a similar license.
It's a kind of a no brainer.
But then maybe if you
go work outside academia in a company
where maybe code is actually
a product of the company,
then maybe depending on where you will work,
maybe they will specifically use
some other type of licenses
that might be more.
more strict so let me go back
Then here in the practical steps
for incorporating a license,
I already mentioned that what
the GitHub interface does, but
in practice one way of doing it
is to create a license folder
in your project and basically
put the unmodified licenses that
you use inside that project.
again here if you are not sure
how to do it the best way is to copy
what other libraries are doing
but basically the idea is that
if you reuse in your code
if you embed somebody else's code
that was released under their
MIT license with their name
and surname inside the MIT license
so you can just copy all
the licenses from all the
codes into this licenses folder
And again, it's a bit
like this citation that it's a small effort
for you to include these licenses,
but then it keeps track of
the kind of, you know,
acknowledging other people's work.
And, you know, maybe right
now in universities and academia,
it's not a metric that is already.
used in careers and CV, but
maybe I feel that it's coming in a sense
that if you share your data,
if you share your code and
you do it properly and
acknowledge others, this is also going
to be an important metric for your academic CV.
Something else to mention from this page.
So if your work is not derivative work,
Well basically we were kind
of already mentioned this that
if you don't reuse code of others
and what I mean that you
don't include it in your repository
so you can of course still
import with the whatever Python
or use whatever R library but
if your work is not derivative
in the sense that you are
not editing other people code
then what is important is that
you do not invent your own license.
So pick a standard license
and the tool that I was just
showing is one of them.
And then again, you would like
to make sure that this is
visible in your repository, again
with the license folders that
we mentioned earlier, so that
those who will find your code
and want to reuse it, they know how to cite you.
if you create the github repository
and click on the license
or select the license then the
the license file will be at
the root of the repository yeah
yeah yeah that's how that's the
that's what i do basically normally
Before we switch to the
next topic, maybe just small
brackets on something that I
might ask everyone who is
listening to the stream as anyone here.
not used chatgpt or cloud or grok
or whatever github copilot to
generate code so if there's
usually always one person who has
not used this tool for for generating code
or generating text so that
person please write something in
the notes document
But most likely you have
played or maybe you're using
these tools for work.
And these AI systems, they
are able to take, they basically
are text to code systems.
So they take a description of
the task as text and they generate code.
and of course they are very useful
but when it comes to licenses the code
that is generated doesn't belong
to anyone or in in a way
just belongs to you means
that the responsibility fully fully
lays on you who have generated the code
and decide what to do with
the code will you decide to
publish the code that was
generated well then you take
the full responsibility
that you're not publishing
actually some verbatim copy paste
from a library that is proprietary
or a library that requires
one of these very strong copyleft licenses
and unfortunately how these AI
systems out there make they're
not giving you they're not telling
you okay I generated this code
for you it's actually 95% similar
to this existing code from
whatever from this library so
please cite the library as I wrote here
as a metaphor you can
never blame the autopilot or the company
who invented the autopilot but
only the driver is the one
to blame so please be
careful with the autopilots
Beyond this type of risks
of licenses, generated code has
been shown to have other types of risks.
Well, the most basic one is the risk
for your results that you
have from the generated work.
So you might think that
your code is actually doing.
What do you ask?
But without code review, you
might be that your results are false.
There are the risk for the systems in use.
Sometimes the generated code
actually has malicious code.
And I give you one example.
So [name], what does it say?
Are you able to read what is written there?
Yeah, I'm reading Microsoft
in both instances.
Yeah, so this is, it
looks like Microsoft, but it's
actually RN Microsoft.
So again, you know, of course, maybe
if one would zoom in, you
would see that this is not Microsoft, it's RN.
And often these editors that we use
for writing code, they have
this monospace fonts so that you, you know,
In theory, you would be able to see
that you're not importing
something from Microsoft, but
from whatever type of squatted.
But these things are happening
and it's a risk.
But if we stick to the
topic of these lessons, so
to licenses, a recent paper estimates
that around 2% of AI
generated code is strikingly
similar to existing open source implementation.
so two percent is very little
it might well be that none
in this room nobody in this
room and nobody who's watching
the stream has ever actually
experienced to generate something
that is strikingly similar
to something existing but then
again something that maybe you
should consider the way i
use this technology sometimes to
you know, maybe convert a
couple of lines into a
function or refactor some small bits of code,
but I don't, I personally find
it too risky to, you know,
generate 500 lines of code.
I don't have time to read
500 lines of code and I'm not
just going to copy paste them.
And even though when I run
them, I see that they, that
they do what I expect.
I don't know if you'll be
on, what is your, whatever,
moral policy in using this type of tools.
Do you find them useful?
Yeah, I find them very useful.
And also being surprised how
good they are to write algorithms.
You ask for something and then
you get a full algorithm.
Well, I haven't seen algorithms
500 lines long, but 50 lines long.
And when you run it, it
does things as you are supposed to.
But I only used it for experimenting.
I haven't published any code
generated from GitHub Copilot.
Yeah.
I totally agree, especially as
part of my work, we work
with users who maybe they have
not been trained as coders.
And it's amazing that now
finally everyone can code and
they can understand, they can read the code.
It's also a learning tool because
you see a good example of a code.
But at least I'm happy
to always remind them of the risks
that if they don't understand
what a specific line is doing, maybe,
you know, talk with your
local software engineer or try
to uncomment that line, everything
fails or what happens.
So I don't know where we will go.
Maybe one possible future that
I wrote here is that if
future version of these tools
that generate code, let's say
that they would be trained only on MIT code,
then most likely what they
synthesize is MIT code and then
we don't have issue.
But right now the issue
with these AI systems is that nobody knows
what went there, which most
likely means that everything went there.
yeah yes absolutely so you know
but yes so maybe a quick
look at the notes if
there's any interesting comment
okay well nothing maybe too
relevant we can we can
maybe continue already with the
next page oh yeah the bottom
of the page there's many
many many good resources on how
to choose a license and and so on
so you can happily browse all
of them and i switch to the
next page which is now
software citations so beyond
yeah well that was one
question in the comments why do
we use licensee folder with
many licenses uh with them
licenses clash pass each other
one will allow something while
other will commit it uh after
now i would strictly i was
need thought with it stick
to explicitly one license
Yes I'm not sure what you
refer to several licenses but it could be
that if you have imported
the licensee folder were used for things
that you build on if you
did import of a library from
somewhere else that you had
that license for that library
for instance that folder um
exactly that that that if
i because sometimes you uh
let's take the example of
python sometimes you can pip
install whatever you need and import it
but sometimes you take a bit of code
that was in some appendix of
a paper with an mit license
but you can't pip install it
so then you will need to
include that bit of code and
this component that you add you
also need to have the
MIT license for that component.
So if you start building
a code, then inside the
same repository would have all
these other codes, not just import on linking.
Then you also need to
include these other people's licenses.
So I don't know if this clarifies.
Okay, then we'll discuss software citation.
We start with some basic questions here.
Is putting software on GitHub
the GitLab publishing?
Or where to publish software
and how can software be cited?
How can I make my software citable?
So we learned about the
FAIR principles in the previous
code refinery lecture.
So we're now talking about the FAIR,
how to get the FAIR principles
to apply for software.
So is it enough to make
the code public for the codes
to remain findable and accessible?
Well, we don't know what happens to GitHub.
GitHub has been around for
a very long time.
and github repositories can
be deleted accounts can be deleted
so we have to make a step
if we want our software and
the software that we depend on
to be to be persistent
we need to use a service like Zenodo
and get a digital object
identifier related to the software.
Yes, so we can have a
short discussion in the chat or
not the chat, but on the shared document.
yeah i can copy this too
yeah do you cite your software and
how and if i wanted to
cite your code scripts what would
i need to do so i pasted
these two questions in the notes document
so you can now those who
are watching the stream and
have the notes document open you can
Add your answers.
Yes, I might say [name]'s
voice is not coming for me.
It's fine.
It could also be this Twitch TV
that you need to set the
quality of the Twitch TV stream to source.
Otherwise Twitch will forever
compress video and audio.
So if that helps.
All right, so do you cite
software that you use and how?
Let's see what people are writing.
What about you, [name]?
How could I cite your software?
Well, at least in my
field, my background is in
neuroscience, the usual practice,
or I don't know if it's the best practice,
but people write papers about
the software or then they
want a specific paper to be
cited when the software is used.
It's not maybe the most...
how can I say research
software engineering best way of
doing it I guess the reason
is to maximize citations to some papers
so I've seen in neuroscience
that there are some papers of
these usual tools used for
statistics that they have I don't
know 10 000 citations just because you know
maybe this most likely people
who are citing those papers
they don't didn't even read the papers
but because whatever you use
the tool you cite the paper
so this is what they do
in neuroscience at least yeah
But if I wanted to cite
your code script, what would I need to do?
Yeah, so there people are
writing, citing the paper.
I think what I've seen, I don't know
if you ever noticed, sometimes
in the readme file of the
GitHub, they might write something like,
if you find this code
useful, please cite conference
paper or whatever, journal article.
So yeah, this is kind of,
Of course, all checks that
people do cite in those
papers, that's a different story.
So how to make your software citable?
Yes.
So here's a checklist for
making a release of your software citable.
We talked about assigning
appropriate license.
a description of the
software, clear version numbering,
author's credit, a persistent identifier,
and added a recommended citation
to the software documentation, often
in the README file.
We have an example of
a citation.csf file that can be
added to the repository.
Should I check this example?
It's further down there, isn't it?
Yeah, there you have it.
So a message, if you use this software,
please cite it as below, and the author,
title, version, and date, and
the digital object identifier also.
So then this citation CFF,
it's like a machine readable citation
that then it makes it
easier, for example, to track
which software is cited then.
I go back to the webpage of the course.
And then how to get
the digital object identifier.
because you were mentioning
that it's important.
You did that in, what was
it, day three of the
macro refinery course, where you got
a DOI from Senodo, I think.
Or was it day four?
Yeah, in day four, it's mentioned.
But in general, if we have
a look at this example here,
Zenodo is a tool that is very useful
for sharing anything, can be your slides,
can be your code and the
interface is very intuitive that
you can basically
create a new object in
this specific case would be a repository code.
And then you can get the
DOI and kind of this persistent identifier.
Maybe I could ask for those
who are writing in the notes that
if I know that in
different fields, they might
have other repositories.
So if there's something specific of some,
that is something field
specific, please let us know.
So, oh yeah, yeah, this is
the same example that I clicked.
Oh no, this is another
more anonymous example.
Yeah.
You see, it's the same
thing mentioned here.
Yeah.
Yes.
So, and then we mentioned
there is papers that focus
on scientific software.
So if you click the link,
we will get to the
Software Sustainable Institute.
And there's a long list
of different journals sorted by topic
or fields and engineering
humanities and different which are
you can publish software.
it's nice that this in a
way compared to the example
that i was mentioning from
neuroscience it's i would rather
cite this paper that clearly explains
what the software does and
what is novel rather than some
you know random paper that that
they tell me to to decide
but then again i also see
that maybe this is a i don't know
how recent this practice it is
but um but i would say
that now this type of
development work is recognized even
in doctoral thesis so that
there are doctoral thesis that
one paper is just a software
actually and it's good that
it's finally like this that
you know software is not some
sort of class b or or
product of the research
world, it's actually as important
as other papers, as other type of work.
Yeah, so there are several sources on
how to decide software and we
also see the recommended format
that is shared by the different authors.
Coming to FAIR for research
software or FAIR for RS.
That's how to apply the
FAIR principles for research software.
Software should have a global
unique and persistent identifier, DOI.
It should be accessible, so
it should be retrievable by
using open protocols.
Interruptible.
Software should use open
formats and standards to work
with other tools.
That's like CSV files or
HDF4 and formats like that, NetCDF.
And it should be really usable.
Software should have a
clear licensing documentation and provenance.
So there's a checklist, bare software,
and bare software NL highlights
with nice visuals, the five
most important elements of bare software.
I really like this.
In a way, this FAIR principle
for research software are really
the core summary of these lessons
that if your software, if
whatever you're going to publish
along with your paper has
these elements, then you know
that you're fine and you
know that everything is in order.
I like this website here,
this FAIR software.
in from the Netherlands that
it's a nice visual website and they you know
if you spend time it's not
gonna take too long you can
they also guide you you know
how to choose a license so
it's they're very good kind
of basic but fundamental important information
so let me go back we
basically have covered everything
so far i wonder should we
already have a break now
and then basically this is the
last part of our lesson and then
we can finish a little bit
earlier should we do like that
yeah you can do it like that
so let's have another 10
minutes break we will finish
a little bit earlier today so
that you have more time to
explore all the links that we
are throwing to you and so
let's get back to the streaming
at 10 to the hour so whatever 50. okay bye
and welcome back so now it's
the last part if we have
a look at the structure of this episode
that we covered today we
talked about the kind of
general motivation of social coding
then we went deeper on the licenses
and software licensing and then
we wrapped up with the software citation
and kind of a practical checklist
for you on how to cite
in this last 20 minutes together
we want just to mention also
that sharing data is closely
related to software but the
tools that we might use for sharing data
they are a little bit
different of course you might have seen
that in some python libraries
or even maybe in your own code
if the data is very small
in a way there's nothing wrong
to you know attach a little
csv into the same github repository
but from a kind of
metadata findability fair principle
point of view depositing the data
in a data specific repository
makes it easier for others to find it
because if i'm looking for a
data set most likely i search
in a data repository and not on github
So a very useful website
is this read3data which is like
a list of all possible registry
to where they post the data.
There are some generic repositories
of data that we list here for example this
Zenodo that we mentioned earlier
but in some specific fields
there might be a field specific repository
for example in the case
of neuroscience there is OpenNeuro
in the United States and so
there you might find with
this search engine for data
repositories you might find the
right one for your case.
CodeRefinery
although we have participants
from everywhere but at least
we are strongly involved with the nordics
and there's a list here
of some available repositories in
sweden norway denmark and finland
in general if you are not
sure get in touch with your local support people
Basically, when it comes to
the licenses of data, licensing of datasets
and databases, they are a
little bit different than the
licenses that we have.
consider right now so in there
is there are basically this
type of creative common licenses
which one could consider that
they are like the open
software license open source
software licenses for data and
maybe it's worth spending maybe
this is not the best website to show
But in general, the
Creative Commons licenses, they
also allow this type of, how
can I call it, viral component.
So you might be releasing something
that is completely public domain
and that's the CC0.
So the data that you
publish, anyone can use it for any purpose.
or then very common in research
is the CC BY and the
BY would basically mean that
people have to specify where they
got the data so cite your
paper or mention the dataset and
more strict it goes towards the
CC BY SA which stands for share alike
So that if you reuse that
data, then you need to also for your data,
you need to also basically
release it with the same license.
And the most strict one would be
that there's no commercial, how
can I say, work that can be
done with that type of data.
Maybe very briefly, in the
previous rounds of these episodes
there have been always
questions, often questions when it
comes to the licensing of
machine learning and AI models.
So when it comes to data,
AI models are a little bit
tricky that it's not clear if
an AI model is considered data
or if the AI model is considered software.
Maybe it's good to define what
we mean is the AI model in
the metaphor of the car that
I already used earlier.
So the AI model is like
the engine of the car.
And so the model on its
own, it can go anywhere, it can kill anyone.
But once the AI model is
put inside an AI system, so
it's like the engine goes
inside the whole infrastructure of
the car and the software, then
it becomes an AI system.
And then it can actually be used.
So for those of you who
develop AI models and AI systems,
there are or let's say
that people are still figuring out
what is the best way to
release these AI models and the
I guess most famous examples
of shared AI models are
large language models because of
what has happened with the AI
hype in the past two years
And so if you know GitHub,
if you've been experiencing with GitHub
for sharing code, Hugging Face
is like the GitHub of AI models.
I will show now one example
of this Olmo model.
model, large language model by
the Allen Institute is one of the few
that is truly open in the sense
that they disclosed everything,
the training data, the
training process, checkpoints and all
sorts of that.
And so you see, of course,
this is Hacking Phase.
It doesn't really look like GitHub,
but there are basically the files
and kind of the key version
of the model, because in the
end, the AI model will be just a gigantic file.
And so if I click on
files here, you see that these
are all the files that are
distributed with this AI model.
The actual model, so the
weights, is basically this PyTorch bin
or whatever safe tensor, so
this really big file, but then
there are other metadata files
that might be needed.
The training data is there
as well, you said?
Yeah.
So in their paper, they,
I don't think they, the training
data is now in this specific
link that I'm showing right now.
This is just for the release
of the model, but they also have a repository.
I think it's, they have it
even in, in again phase.
So in this, under this Allen
AI is the Allen Institute.
actually the model this model
was trained on the lumi supercomputer
so it's one of the products
of the eu ai factories but
anyway back to the content so
so this ai models it's a
bit difficult to if they would
be called data or if they
would be called software
But at least the AI models
that you see in AgInPhase, they
are now released under software licenses.
It's also a bit, I would
say, kind of funny.
I don't know if funny is the right word.
many of these AI models
they are considered open source model
but actually when one really goes
and check there's nothing open
source at all so even
the various Facebook meta or
whatever big tech that is
releasing these open source
models actually everything is
quite kept proprietary
but as there is this kind
of open washing so that by
attaching the label open source
they can think that they can
get away with whatever secret
practices but the lack of
transparencies and so on and compared to
of course there's no
authority forcing these companies
to change their practice exactly
so you can they can just
use the open licenses as much
as they want so it's not
it's actually this this paper
that i linked here for those
who it's it's also you know
this type of open washi in
the au artificial intelligence act
which i will cover briefly soon
that it's also exactly this
that maybe this regulation that we
now have in Europe to regulate AI models
and AI systems is using open source
even in the text of the
regulation in a way that is
not what we've been discussing today
and in the previous episodes
of Code Refinery Workshop.
But anyway, of course, I
would understand that there's maybe
a minority of you who will
develop AI models and release AI models,
but in general, as I
just mentioned, for those of you
who are doing research
this type of regulations that
don't apply so for researchers
in practice you don't need to
worry about AI regulation but
you might still need to worry about ethics
that if you're building a model
that I don't know is
for operating automatically some
drone machine gun maybe you know
do you really need to do
that can you do something else
with your clever brain
So this of course is you are the judge
and your community is the judge
of what is good and what is wrong.
But in general researchers have
the freedom even under the EU
AI Act to explore what they want.
The kind of open questions that
is with the data.
that is inside these big AI
models it has been shown that
you can actually that these
large models they can memorize
some of the training data and if you
what we were saying earlier that
even with the code that
you might generate from some
large language models there is
a two percent chance that some
of the code that it spits
is basically verbatim copy paste
of existing code
and of course this raises
concerns about copyright materials
or you know copyleft licenses
when it comes to the code
or any other stuff that is
inside these models right now there's no
decisions the companies for
example the large new york
time and whatever these big
publishers they are trying to
sue their companies for misuse
of copyright materials and but
right now there's no how can i say judgment
or final final verdict there
was recently some big fine
to anthropic like really in
the order of billions but
they are still pending so
because apparently they used
some books that they shouldn't
even have had access to to
train their AI model.
all right but the ending part
in the way we went quite
quickly in this data kind of licensing
because it goes a bit
beyond code refinery but it's something
that is very important
many universities they cover this
type of data management and
opening data workshops so I
highly recommend you to check what your
organizations are are for
example suggesting when it
comes to repositories for data
and here in this final
list of references there's very
very good tools and very good
resources i'm a huge fan of
the touring way which is like
an open ebook that covers all these topics
and um and in general i
mean there are also field
field specific things so try
to try to basically check for your field
if there's something specific right
so we're basically done with
this episode we this was a
bit of a different episode compared
to the other ones in the
code refinery because it was
more discussion based
I can already ask [name], for example,
if you could paste to
the notes the feedback for today.
Yes, just a moment.
and of course there might be questions
that we didn't answer we
will answer you know we will
not forget your unanswered questions
we will come back to those maybe
a bit in the next episode
of code refinery so today was
day five all about social
coding software licenses
Day six next Wednesday will
be about documentation and really
how to basically build documentations
and the pages actually that
you see with our contents
and exercises, they're all built
with a similar system.
So this will be more
practical day six where you
will actually have to build a documentation.
for a software that maybe you made
or you will make day seven
will be more of introduction
jupyter notebooks and so for those of you
who maybe have never used them
or are not familiar with
all the possible tricks that you
can do with jupyter notebooks
it's definitely an interesting episode
Day 8 and day 9 they go
closer to kind of concepts
of research software engineering or
in general software engineering
even without research.
And day 8 will be automated testing.
We kind of touched a bit
on this in the week 1 when
you were trying to push your
changes to somebody else's repository
there was a test running
that the ingredients were missing
or something like that.
So we touched also on this
idea of the importance of testing also today.
So definitely this is the
type of lesson that you want
to join to understand how
you can introduce this type
of automated tests in your code.
And it integrates with GitHub.
So you get to use the
test setup on GitHub, which is very useful.
Exactly, because then the
advantage of GitHub is that
these tests don't need to
happen on your computer and if
someone wants to edit your GitHub
or suggest the testing can
already, you know, be
basically automatically performed.
And the last day is maybe
this type of more general kind
of type of software engineering concepts on
how to write good code
and specifically how to write
modular code and pure kind of functions.
so I hope this was
an interesting day although different
a bit different than the others
you can still ask us questions
in the in the notes document but
we as usual we have the
we have this feedback section so if you edit
the notes and scroll to
the very bottom, you can add some comments.
So as you can see, we
try to change the lessons
so that every different run of
the workshop, we include new
materials based on your feedback.
So if you think that
something was missing and something
should be expanded or that there
was some too much of
something, you know, please comment
so that we can improve for the next run.
All right.
I don't think we have anything else.
We end up some 20 minutes earlier today.
Thank you, [name], for being with us today.
Thank you, [name].
And thank you, [name].
Yes, thank you, [name], for
the broadcasting studio.
And thanks to the audience,
to the participants.
Exactly.
Thanks for showing up.
Thank you also for the feedback
that I can already see here appearing.
And so keep on writing.
And if there's other questions,
write them there and we can answer.
All right.
See you in seven days then.
Bye-bye.