All right.
And here we are live.
Very welcome everyone to day
six of the Code Refinery workshop.
How is everyone doing?
I had my lunch here in Germany.
It's a bit later than in Iceland, I guess.
Right.
How about [name]?
Yeah, not bad.
Had my lunch.
Great.
We are here in the
studio together with [name], our streamer
for today and [name] and [name]
who will be teaching today's lesson.
And the next, is it still eight minutes?
We're going to have a
little chat here before the
actual workshop starts at the hour
to get used to our
ways of working with
our collaborative notes and see
what you all had for lunch.
And let's also do the audio check now.
And all right.
[name]'s already saying that
volumes are fine.
Okay.
What's the order that I see people at?
That's me, [name], you and [name].
Let's go in that order.
One, two, three, four.
One.
Two.
Three.
Four.
Okay, I think it's roughly the same.
All right.
Okay, so what I'm sharing
here on the screen is
our collaborative notes document.
Every one of you, if you
registered to our workshop, has
just, probably just right now,
gotten an email with the link
to that document and also
to our workshop webpage and
our virtual help room.
So this document is used
for connecting with the instructors,
so that we can connect with you
and you have a bunch of links up here
as well, for example, to
our code of conduct general just
be nice to one another.
And archives and also the
schedule is linked from here, and
if we scroll down.
we actually have some
icebreakers for everyone to get
used to this document.
So if you've never used
a HedgeDoc document or also
HackMD, it works very similar,
then you will see something
like I'm showing here right now.
And if you want to edit
something, you can find the little pen symbol,
which is either where it is
for me right now, up here
to the right, or somewhere here
in a group of three.
And if you click that,
you switch to edit mode,
then you can scroll down to
our icebreaker and add your answer here.
And you can go ahead and do
that now if you want to.
So we would like to know
what did you all have for lunch today?
Maybe we get some new ideas for tomorrow.
How would you explain your
current job to someone in the year 1700s?
That's always fun to see.
what people are actually doing.
And maybe we can guess what
what is your current job title.
And then related to our today's lesson,
what's the best documented project
you have seen?
So maybe we ask our
instructors first, what did you
have for lunch today, [name]?
Well, I think I was the
one who said some vegan dish.
I had some vegetables, something
light to just keep me alive
during the next two hours and a half.
Sounds good.
Very good, by the way.
Yeah, pretty similar.
I had some cucumbers, tomatoes.
Yeah, vegan dish.
How about [name]?
Did you have any lunch?
I had breakfast for lunch,
I guess, several hours ago.
Someone's saying the sound is
low in the classroom, even though
they have it on max volume.
So since we haven't started
yet, I'm going to adjust the gain a bit.
Okay.
So I hope your ears don't break.
We can continue talking something
to see if it helps.
Now it should be a bit louder.
So you can respond in the
document to the question.
If it's okay or not.
It helps.
Yes.
Okay, great.
And this is actually a great
use of the document.
These are all things that
please let us know as early as possible.
If you cannot hear someone or
if you think we are
sharing the wrong screen or anything like that,
the document is also used for
you to tell us if there's
anything we need to know during
the next two and a half hours.
So for everyone who joined
us now, sorry, go ahead.
No, I wanted to say
that actually this document is
the zero exercise for us because
we are going to practice a bit of Markdown
and that's exactly the, you
know, and this document is written in Markdown.
So you can practice some Markdown.
So it will also come during the lesson.
That's great.
Yes.
So the document will
be available throughout the lesson
and you can use it to ask
questions, let us know about
things during the exercise session,
let us know how it's going or
if you have any specific questions.
And once more for everyone who joined now,
you can find the little pen
symbol up here to go into
edit mode and then you can share
if you want to what you had for lunch today.
I will also add mine here.
I also had breakfast for lunch.
It was kind of a late breakfast.
And then some more sessions here.
Oh, we get some explanations of job titles.
How about you, [name]?
How would you explain your
current job to someone in 1700?
Well, I think that people in
the 1700 may know what a
scientist is or a philosopher is.
I mean, I'm, I guess, you know,
I'm not, I'm not a farmer.
So possibly to a person from
there, I could just pose as
one of those people that work,
you know, in an office and stay.
I think that's, you know, stay
on the desk and think more or less, I think.
How about you?
Maybe I would say I
do calculations by using
more advanced tools.
If people had some calculators
back then, they may understand.
Calculator was a job title,
so they had, yeah.
Yeah.
I don't know about 1700s if
it was an actual job title actually.
It's a bit early maybe.
Yeah.
So we also have
mechanical calculator operator here.
Yes.
Conceptual workflow.
That's some more points here.
The chemistry or alchemy.
Yes.
So I mentioned about of chemistry.
Okay.
Alchemy is dangerous.
So it's much better to do it on paper.
Yes.
And then we also have
the last icebreaker question here
leading us to today's topic
about the best documented project.
For the last one minute, [name]
and [name], what are the ones
that you find best documented
out there that you have encountered?
numpy is well documented i
would say yeah yeah i guess
that uh numpy is and the
python documentation in general it's
uh it's really it's really nice
i think i've learned uh so in
the the the re package in python the package
for uh regular expressions i
think i've learned working
with regular expressions there
on the documentation for that
package and also yeah
Yeah, NumPy I've used a lot.
And it's really nice to it's
a really good documentation, I
would say for for anybody who
wants to use NumPy.
Yeah.
Right.
And today we might learn how
to write such nice documentation.
It is one o'clock finish time.
So let's get started.
Let me just go back to the
normal view.
So welcome everyone to this
code refinery workshop day six.
Today, we're going to
talk about documentation, how
to write documentation for your
code, a topic that is sometimes overlooked,
and maybe seen as not
so interesting, or also maybe
a little bit hard.
So hopefully, today's lesson will
help you with that.
Let me go to the workshop webpage.
Hopefully all of you know this page.
This is where you registered.
This is also where you can
find all the information for today.
So if we scroll down here to day six,
you can find the link
to the lesson material today, if
you want to follow.
And then you also just got an email
that includes the link to
this page, the link to a virtual help room.
So if during today you have
any kind of technical trouble,
you can join there and ask
[name] all your questions that you have.
And then we have the link
to the notes document.
This is where you can find
another way to find all the links for today.
also to our code of conduct
and how we suggest that you
can set up your screen.
And here you can find the icebreakers
that we just briefly discussed
in the 10 minutes before we started.
And this document is also
here for your questions.
It is how we ask you
to interact with the instructors.
And we will also share all
the links to the materials or
any further links via this document.
And the way you can use
this document is you find
this little pen symbol, which is
either up here to the right
or somewhere up here to the left for you.
You click that, you go into edit mode,
and then you can also join
here, filling in the icebreakers,
testing a little bit how this works.
And then later you can
fill in your questions in the
bottom of the document, or let
us know if volume is off or
anything else that is happening
during the stream.
And with that, I will give
over to today's instructors, [name] and [name].
Yeah, I will be sharing my screen now.
Have a wonderful workshop, everyone.
Let's go to [name]'s screen.
Okay.
Thank you, [name].
Then I'm going to hide in the background.
Good.
So, um, just let me have a look at.
Okay, so thank you.
Thanks.
Thanks, [name], and everybody for
for the nice introduction.
So today, we're going to talk
about how to document research software.
And we have we have a couple of
of topics to talk about.
We'll discuss first about what
we want from the documentation, right?
So why we do that?
Why is documentation important?
Then we're going to talk
about some tools and solutions
to the problem of documenting
your code, and we'll discuss pros and cons.
Then we are going to talk about
how to write documentation in
your code, how to write README files
And we'll have some exercise
and some examples on that.
And then we are going to be to
do something more complex.
So we are going to see
how to generate beautiful
documentation like the one for
many Python projects through Sphinx.
And we also talk about how
to host that documentation on GitHub.
Okay, so that people can go on the web
and see the documentation of
your that you've written, just
going on, on the web and GitHub.
So first thing,
is uh just a moment uh motivation
and wish list so if you go
to the first uh episode in the lesson okay
so um what would we like
to have in the code and
why we would like document
to document our research code do
you have any opinion [name]
Well, for me, if it's a small project
for myself, I would do
some documentation in case I
forgot stuff after several days or
a week or even months.
If it's a project I'm
collaborating with people, it would
be more important to have good documentation.
it would make it easier
for your colleagues or your
collaborators to work with you.
Yeah.
And of course, just let me interrupt you.
Our listeners, our audience,
well, they can, you can
write whatever comes to your
mind regarding this in
the collaborative notes.
So please add comments.
add any consideration there.
The idea for this lesson in general is
that we talk a bit about a topic,
but you can also write at
the same time some comments in
the notes, and then we will
typically go to the notes and
have a look and see what
how people are written comment on
that so we'll try to keep
it interactive in this way
you write something in the note
and we comment on it and we praise you
for your courage in writing
something there okay so yeah the
the first the first like
interactive activity we have here is yeah so
describe why you wouldn't
want documentation.
We have already mentioned some reasons why.
And also, there's a second question.
Once we've defined why
we want documentation, how would
you describe a useful documentation
body let's say okay and
there's also another question uh
how can you motivate your
colleagues to contribute to
the documentation okay this
is actually something which is still useful
if if it's a collaborative project
and there's many people involved
how do you make that easy
and how do you motivate people to
do uh to do this to
write documentation okay so let's maybe wait
some seconds here and see
what people come up with in
the notes, in the collaborative part.
And then we'll also show
our motivations, adding to what
[name] has just said.
Yeah, so we can start commenting
a bit on what we see, right?
On what we see in the pad, in the notes.
Well, yeah, so I and
others can understand at any
future time what we're doing
and why we're doing this in this way.
So this is in the why section.
Okay.
And yeah, so like
future-proofing your understanding.
Future-proofing your understanding is
a very important thing.
It was...
and get a paper published.
I guess that's a good reason,
a big reason at some time.
So basically, right starting
writing something in the in
the documentation in some form so
that you can then put that
into the paper paper.
Yeah, okay.
Okay.
Yeah.
Um,
projects are living things.
Yeah, yeah.
So people come and go.
And it's, it's, it's a way
to future proof the code also,
when not only for your
understanding, but also for, for
other people for the poor.
whomever may join in the future, yeah.
Yeah, otherwise you may need, sorry.
Yeah, no, go ahead, go ahead.
Yeah, I mean, if you don't
have a good documentation, you
may need to explain things
to different people multiple times.
Yeah, that's an important thing.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And so how would you
describe useful documentation?
Yeah, so easy, okay, easier understanding.
Can you share the notes or
I can share the notes.
What you want me to share the notes?
No, I can share the notes here.
Yeah, it's a good thing to do now.
Just, yeah.
Wait, these are actually, I
need to scroll down a little more.
Yes, okay.
I see that useful documentation
needs to be easy to understand.
There are need to make
few assumption on what people know.
I have something to say
about that, I think.
Then also appropriate to the
scale of the project be documented.
That's cool.
If you don't want to write too much
for a small project, you
don't want to write too little
for a big project, I guess.
And how can you motivate
your colleagues to contribute
to the documentation?
It's actually, yeah, there's about
a cake on Friday.
Maybe, you know, more in
general, some social repercussions
for those who don't contribute.
Yes.
So maybe we can have a look
at our, what we would recommend at the moment.
So,
Our motivations, well, you
will probably use the code in
the future and may forget details.
You may want others to use your code,
and you may want others
to contribute to the code.
This is also an important thing.
So contributions to many
open source projects actually
happen first through documentation.
people will use your code,
find, read the documentation, find
that something maybe it's
not well documented, or
because that's actually very difficult
to keep the documentation up to date.
And that's the usually first problem
that people find with the code, it's okay,
there's a problem in the
documentation, it doesn't say this,
or it's not, it's not up to date.
So they may actually open
the pull request on your documentation,
that on your documentation,
that's the first time the first way that they
interact and, you know, contribute
to the code.
Okay.
And that's the thing that
can you mentioned that?
So
it's very useful to have
a list of questions or a list of problems
that have been already solved, let's say,
and their solution in the documentation
so that you can save your time
and also the time of
your colleagues from asking, from,
you know, helping people in trivial ways.
It's very nice to help people, but
Maybe if we can do
away with some repetitive work,
sometimes it's nice.
Okay.
So what do we expect from
a suitably good documentation?
Okay.
So it very depends on the
goal of the competition, right?
So maybe you do you want
to comment on that?
Yeah, I would say, well, documentation.
are in different forms.
But we have actually have
a good picture here showing
different types of documentation.
Yeah, this is from the company Divio.
And the author of this,
this is a documentation itself.
They divide the documentation
into four parts here.
the four quadrants here you can
see in the picture, the tutorials,
how to get reference and the explanation.
So reference means, usually it
means the automatically generated
API reference.
It has information about the interface
and the doc strings of a
function, a method or module.
And then how to get its problem oriented.
If you have a certain problem
you want to solve, you can
check out this kind of documentation.
It usually involves steps showing
how to solve the problem,
step one, step two, and so on.
Basically, very practically.
Yeah, very practically.
You don't need to know exactly
what each step is doing,
but by following this
documentation, you probably will
solve your problem.
And then tutorials are also very common.
It's learning oriented.
basically telling you what's
the best practice, what's the process
and what kind of techniques here
you use to solve certain problems.
The last one is explanation.
It's understanding oriented.
My understanding is it involves
the design logic of a certain
uh project uh maybe also the
history of a project uh yeah so
it's a it's a it's a more
general he has a more um yeah scope
which is wider let's say and
i think in in the research
software uh this has uh very much
to do with the the research
domain as you mentioned right so
um yeah so yeah may also
involves domain knowledge, especially
if it's a multi-discipline
project, then yeah, it gives
you some explanation of the domain knowledge.
I think the idea of
having these four quadrants is also
because different people or even
the same people in different
parts at different times may
need something different.
More experienced developers,
more experienced people may
actually need just the reference.
uh some beginners may need a
how to guide just because i
want to do something simple but uh people
that have nothing no domain experience
or no domain knowledge they
may need some explanations some
more tutorials and so on right
i guess it's uh the point
is different people need different things
and these are like kind
of taxonomy of documentation types
okay and uh so as we
mentioned here there's there's no
one size fits all okay
often right a readme may be enough okay
but uh so and that's
something we recommend to start with
but uh but uh yeah
different people be different kinds
of user may need different things
and and you need to be aware of this
when you write documentation if
you want that to be useful
to each one of these different
uses um okay uh so i would say
because we have a lot of stuff to cover.
We would have another
collaborative exercise here about
a wish list.
But I think we could skip
the exercise and comment on what
we would like to have.
Do you agree?
Yes, I agree.
Okay.
So what would you like to
have in the documentation?
And how would you like to develop it?
And what are the practices
you would like to adopt?
I will just here unfold
this because we have quite some
things to touch upon.
Versioning, versions, right?
Versions are important.
So if you have a
long-running software project that
evolves over time, its features may change.
And so the documentation
itself should change with the code.
A version of the documentation
should match the version of the code.
This is especially true for reference,
for things like explanations
or more domain-specific things.
This is not necessary, but actually
for things that relate to
the code more precisely, you
need to have version control.
You need to version control your
documentation with the code okay
yeah uh yeah and then there's
this uh about and uh one
thing um whenever you want
interrupting right it's just that
i'm going to go through this uh just
So documentation should be
placed and tracked close to the source code.
But why we want that?
Because if you keep it
this way, it's easier for
the developers to contribute
to documentation and to make
sure that these things are kept in sync.
So another thing is, please
use a standard markup language.
By markup language, we
mentioned, for example, the Markdown.
It's called Markdown if it's, we
call it a markup language here.
Markdown is not typically exactly
a markup language, I think technically,
but still it's something that
you can write using the same editor.
and the same editor that you
use to write code.
And also, you can use the same tools
that you use to version your
code, Git, for example.
You can do Git diffs
of your documentation as well as the code.
And here we mentioned two
different file formats, which are
plain text files.
the plain text file formats,
which is restructured text and markdown.
We'll comment on the
difference between these two in later.
One thing we want to,
I think it's important is
These are plain text file types.
And one thing which is not
a plain text file type is,
for example, Word documents or even PDF files.
So you can still generate
PDF files from documentation, but
these things should not be the
main source of the documentation.
We'll talk about this also later.
Other things?
We see PDFs actually, it may
be good for some user manuals.
I think people in some domains
use PDF a lot.
But yeah, it has some disadvantages here.
Yeah, for example, it's
difficult to copy-paste out of a PDF document.
So if you have a code
snippet in a PDF document,
it's typically hard to copy-paste.
There's actually another thing
written by humans.
Maybe now it's a bit...
I mean, would you use
AI to write documentation?
Well, to be honest, I would use.
AI could actually do many
kinds of documentations.
The four formats we mentioned
before, AI can do all of them.
But I think we need to clarify a bit here.
Automatically generated documentation,
we mean the API documentation
extracted from the doc strings
or function interfaces.
It's not the AI generated.
But of course, AI
generated documentation is also
automatically generated.
But I think it needs still
to be reviewed by a human.
But yeah, I think here we are saying,
yeah, the reference documentation
that the tools you use
generate, like, and we'll see
later, well, these are not enough.
You also need some kind of prose.
You need also some kind
of something written by humans.
in plain English, or plain,
you know, natural language.
That's it.
I think that also, there
are some other things that needs
to be added to, to your to the documentation.
So installation instructions,
It can be just a pip
install, just a simple command sometimes.
But depending on the domain
you come from and the tooling you're using,
maybe the installation instructions
are much more complicated.
And then, please, that should
be written, documented precisely.
And that's one thing.
So step-by-step instructions are
actually very welcome.
There's another thing about licenses.
Licenses should be in the
repository of the code.
That's true.
But it's nice if in
the documentation you specify which
kind of license you are
licensing your code with.
And also, if you want people to contribute,
to your code, or to
your project in general, you
should give them some guidelines
how to contribute to my code.
So should I open the pull request?
Should I open an issue?
And then we discuss it.
So there are different ways
people work on code and on the project.
And it's better to point
these things out in explicitly
in the documentation in some way.
At different stages, you may
want people to contribute in different ways.
That also means documentation
is something you need to iterate.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Also, there's different ways
why documentation can change over
time and you should version control it.
It's not just the code changes,
but also that the documentation
itself can be improved and that
need should be under version control.
So here in the notes, there's a checklist.
So in principle, well, you
could use this checklist to
to compare this with some projects
that you have or that you're using
and see if actually
those documentations have all these
entries in them.
Okay, so let's move on to the next part.
okay uh popular tools and solutions
so what are the um the
tools that people can use for this
and what are the trade-offs there
and the objective here is that you know
if we do a brief review
of of what is available and um
and and then you can choose
what is the best thing to you
So in-code documentation, this is
a big thing.
It's code.
Code has, you can write comments there.
There's a lot to be said about this.
But we are going to talk about this later.
So I'm not going to spend much time here.
So readme.
Readme files.
The advantage of using
readme files compared to other
things is that, well, they are versioned.
They stay in the same file.
repository as the code.
It's often enough to have
a readme.md markdown or readme
in restructured text.
RST stands for restructured text.
And yeah, so it's a very
typical thing to have a readme in your code.
So talking about these two different
formats.
Here in the notes, you see
that there are these two, there's
like a side by side comparison
of a very simple example of Markdown.
So you may be actually
familiar with Markdown, because as
I said before,
This is the same format that
we use in our collaborative notes.
You see that they have
sections and subsections.
They start with a hash or
the double hash and the triple hash
or a quadruple hash, depending
on the nestedness you have for the section.
Then paragraphs are simple.
You can have code blocks or indented
bits that can be quotations or code blocks.
You have standard ways for bold or italics.
You can make lists, and there
can be also number lists, and
there are ways to put in images, links, tables.
We'll see a bit about this.
In the restructured text, you
have very similar mechanism.
At least in this little
example, they look very similar,
except that you have some additional
like punctuation that you need to add
so restructure a full example
of a structured text of a
structured text file can look
quite full of little punctuation
that is very significant for the formatting
so the idea is that
restructure text has more
features than markdown but markdown
is simpler okay there are
many flavors of markdown
Unfortunately, things are
possibly improving in the last decade
or so in the sense that
people have come up with some kind of standards.
And so now things that you write and appear
and look good on GitHub, they
may also look quite as expected
on GitLab, for example.
Or Bitbucket, if you have a readme
and you want it to
appear consistently in different platforms.
Nowadays, more or less, to
an extent, it's almost guaranteed.
But at the beginning, it was not so.
Yeah, so in our case, for this,
when we are going to talk about Sphinx
and the documentation generation,
we are going to use a
flavor of Markdown, which is
called MyST, which I don't
remember what it stands for.
But it's a kind of hybrid between Markdown,
which is very simple, as
Markdown is, but it has some
features of a structured text.
That's why MyST is.
looks reminds a bit of restructure text.
So so these are the we mentioned, readmes,
how to write them, what are
the what are the formats you may have, okay.
And another piece of the puzzle, another
piece of technology that we
need to talk about are
HTML static site generators.
So these are tools that
take your markdown or structure
text files, and then they output HTML files.
So basically documentation that
you can host on the web.
Okay.
There's many of them.
There's Sphinx, which is the
one that we are going to talk about.
There's Jekyll, which is the one that it
GitHub uses by default.
There's pkgdown, which is
something which is very popular
in the R community.
I think that if
you're writing documentation for an R project,
you typically use pkgdown or
things related to that community.
There's mkdocs, which is something
which is getting more and
more popular nowadays, I think.
And there's many, many of those.
And yeah, so if you want
your HTML static site to be visible,
to the web, then you can
host it in different places.
GitHub pages, we'll see GitHub pages.
Bitbucket pages is really
similar, and GitLab pages as well.
It's yet another flavor, the same thing,
a service that allows you
to host HTML documentation on the web.
Yeah.
Other things, there are some
things we are not going to
talk about much is our wikis.
Wikis are easy to...
to interact with, typically,
especially for non-developers.
But the problem is that
they are not version controlled with the code.
So that's something which is
a bit suboptimal for us.
Other formats, LaTeX and PDF, we can...
So Sphinx can generate PDFs for you,
and many of these
documentation generators can actually
create a PDF output or even
just a LaTeX output out of your Markdown file.
So there's a way to convert this.
But as we said, PDF
has some little problems for us,
so we're not going to talk about this further.
Yeah, Doxygen is yet
another documentation generator that
takes some kind of information
and generates HTML files out of this.
The cool thing about Doxygen,
for those who have never heard about this,
is that it auto-generates
API documentation, typically for C
and C++ code, but also for other languages.
And Sphinx can also do that.
So the idea is that many of these tools,
they not only generate HTML
code, HTML documentation, starting
from Markdown, but they can
also scrape your code and look for comments,
some special comments, and create
an API reference for this,
exactly like Doxygen does.
Okay.
And yeah.
So I would say let's move on.
and go to the next one,
which is about in-code documentation.
Yeah, that's probably the first place
you write some documentation
because it's just an access to your code.
We can see the regular comments
is the most commonly used one.
We can see different types comments
as shown here, comment A
and comment B. Which one do
you think is more useful?
Well, I think it depends on
the on the person, right?
So if, if someone does not know
how to code at all, okay,
then the first comment would be okay,
so it's explaining me is
it explains me what what the
code is doing, right?
But if instead, I know what the code does,
okay, more or less, because
I can read Python, okay, then
I think the second one, which
tells me the second one
tells me more information.
It gives me some background, I would say.
And we should always try
to write comments for those
who can already code, I think.
So I think I like comment to be more.
Yeah.
Yeah, we should assume that
the users know about a certain language.
Yeah, that's a regular
documentation, a regular comment.
We can write to the commenter
in the more standard ways,
which is called docstrings.
Let me scroll down.
Yes.
Docstrings gives more information
about your code.
As we can see some examples,
with regular comments in Python
or the other languages.
They come with different format,
but the purpose is the same.
For docstrings, for example,
for Python, the docstrings
will look like this.
You give some information about
the purpose of this function or method.
And what's the input?
What is the output?
Should we show another line?
So actually, this is restructured text.
Doesn't look like, but it's
actually a string of text
written in restructured text that
then Sphinx can extract.
Can look at, for example, R, I guess.
Okay, yeah, that's the standard
format for R comments.
Or oxygen too, so this
is a particular, yeah.
Or oxygen is like the oxygen for R though.
Yeah, it also has the input
output and the other explanations of the code.
yeah so uh with this kind
of format uh some tools like
spins can extract the information
from here to generate a
well api reference documentation for
us and we will see this
later in the hands-on yeah yes
uh should we move on
Yeah, so yeah, I think
we have mentioned everything here, right?
I guess there was a
mention about comments in the code.
The people that do with
commenting, I also do it quite
a lot that I misuse comment
to just silence code.
Yeah, that's something we know
that we shouldn't do that.
I think that, yeah, it's
better to avoid this.
Yeah, I also do a bit,
but it's not recommended.
We should use GitHub version control.
instead of this.
Yeah, instead of like keeping
zombie code just in case.
Or if you want, you can maybe
put it into a module, a
separate module that, you know, yeah.
So there's different things you
can do to avoid this.
Just take it, try not to do this.
I think we know, everybody knows
that it's better to avoid
misusing comments for what comments
are not meant for.
Yes.
Okay, so...
Let's go on.
Yes.
So this is about writing good README files.
So there's going to be
a bit of hands-on-ish part.
We'll have a couple of exercises here.
So
So the important thing to
say about READMEs is that READMEs
are the first thing that a
user sees when they visit your
code page on GitHub or GitLab or wherever.
And also, since it's an
imperative, it's written in all capitals,
even if I get just code
from someone on my computer and
I look at the directory and I
see that there's a README file,
then I typically go to that thing first.
It's quite important for this reason.
I would like to show this thing right away.
Have fun testing some README features.
I will do this interactively.
I will just copy this into
this URL in another browser window.
Then I will go to GitHub and
Let's see if I, just to show you how, yeah.
So I have my own, I
mean, my own GitHub account.
And I created just a
new repository with the readme so
that I can test these things quickly.
So I will create something
like, this repository needs to
be my repository.
Then I will say, readme.
readme-example, example, okay, I'll
call it readme-example2.
I thought I actually read
the other there, but it's okay.
Yeah, so I will add a readme
so that I can go, it's
public also, so it's fine.
Readme, yeah, readme repository, okay.
And now I want to open
here this readme and modify it.
and try some cool stuff.
Okay.
Yeah, so Michael is going to
show us some markdown, some readme
files in the Git repo.
Of course, you can do it
in a local editor, like VS
Code or something else.
Yeah, the cool thing about
doing this here on GitHub is that
then I have a preview, which
may not be that easy on
your own computer, let's say.
So first thing is that we can have like...
different highlights the different
uh text highlighted in different
ways okay uh so if you want
to uh stress some information in
addition to you know what we
have already seen with the bold italics
and sections so these are
some interesting features here i
can see the preview here so
yeah uh warning important notes
there's other things uh if you
look at the notes actually uh here
You can see that there's more kind of,
if you want to really be
colorful in your readme, you can do that.
There are other things.
One thing which I want to
show you now is this.
Wait a moment.
I will need to slightly
correct this because there was... Okay,
so here, what I've done is
that I have pasted some
text, which actually, if you
know anything about HTML, well,
this looks like HTML code.
And it is indeed HTML code.
And what it does is this.
So I have...
basically, a short summary visible, okay.
And then if I click on
this, also, I have some
text which becomes readable only
when I click, okay.
And so this is a way that you can,
like, hide details that maybe
can be omitted in the first
reading of your readme, for example.
It's a way to structure
readme in yet another way.
And
this is an example of the fact
that you can use html code
in principle in markdown files
that's actually something that
markdown recommends markdown is a
simple it's a simple format so
if you want to do something
more fancy well the recommendation
used to be just write in
like html and it's that's the
reason why it's possible nowadays
i would say maybe you know
the more recent flavors of
markdown have also some features
that allow you that that so
that can spare you from
actually writing html inline html
code in the background but yeah
yeah um yeah now there's some
cool things at least things that
look cool uh we go for badges
badges what is a badge so if i
put something like this in my, um,
uh, uh, in my code, in my, uh, read me,
well, this is actually a link
and this is a link, uh,
to a little, uh, picture.
So you can see that there are links.
Uh, so this will be just a link.
Okay.
If you remove the exclamation mark,
but with the exclamation mark,
this is a link, uh, to a picture.
Let's look how it looks like.
Okay.
and yeah so here then i have
a link to a to a picture
that it will be rendered just
like a picture picture and i can
if you want i can uh click on it okay
and well but it's not that
i get much out of this it's
just a picture okay um but i
can also create um something a
bit more fancy which is like a a picture
that links to something else,
to another page.
For example, here I have
created, I have the picture
that I had described above that
links to this other address, example.org.
So let's have a look, preview.
And yeah, so the first one
is the one that has no real link attached to it.
The second has instead a link to another
page to another page, which is example.org.
This can be useful if you
want to have some, you will
see badges later, but the idea
is these badges are quick
to find entry points to
some other things on the web, which could be,
you know, if you have a test suit,
if you have like, yeah, if
you have a test suit, for
example, you want to link there
the results of your test suit, you can do that.
If you have some coverage
reports, if you have other things, if you have,
like a way to say if
it's very positive to add
some Jupyter notebooks and you want
to link a binder set up so
that you can run those
Jupyter notebooks interactively in the web.
Yeah, you can put these links using,
you can have these kind
of links with badges instead
of just having plain links.
Yeah.
So now we have some time for an exercise.
So let's have a look at, I
need to get back to this.
So we have an exercise block, let's say.
There are these two exercises,
README 2 and README 3.
In the first case, if you
have a project on your own with the README,
you may want to spend
some time improving it or
just testing some features that
we just shown on your own README file.
If you don't own a project, I don't know,
for any other reason, this
thing doesn't work for you, you
can choose a README for a project
that you have used, okay, and
write in the notes what other strengths
and what you think you would
change or, you know, some
observations about this in the
notes, which I will switch to.
And, yeah.
Yeah.
For those of you who want to discuss,
which have no clear idea what to discuss,
we do have actually a
suggestion of a relatively nice...
Yeah, I'm adding them to the notes.
To the notes, yeah.
So I will say, as we
switch now to the notes,
let's scroll down, okay?
So,
We should have a 10-minute
exercise break for this.
I'll put also here in the
notes a link to the exercises.
Yeah, so let's let you do this.
So the exercises are, wait,
I'll close this one, just
to confuse anybody, leave page, and then here.
So either draft or improve a
README of a project or comment
on a README that you have used.
If you have nothing to
comment on, please use the link
that we provide here.
So let's see each other in 10 minutes.
And we are back.
So I guess we can look at,
can have a look at the notes.
Okay, there have been some
questions about the badges.
I think we've been discussing
those, answer them.
Okay, so there's this question about
what tools can I use
to properly render markup language
on a README file on my computer?
Well, maybe README is not exactly,
but if you are using, well,
we can do Sphinx, and then
you can render markdown files
in the Sphinx documentation on your computer.
We'll show how to do this.
Regarding the exercises, so our...
Let's have a look at this readme file.
This is an example that
[name] has found, and I
think it's an interesting one.
What would you say, [name]?
Yeah, I would say this
project's purpose is very obvious.
It's a tool you use to
convert PDF files to some
machine readable formats like
Markdown, HTML, or JSON.
So I think the project
introduction is very easy to read.
Yeah, I think I would have
liked to put the project
introduction above, just before the changelog.
I like the changelog, very nice.
But I would like to put it, I mean,
just because if I know that
what this is, okay, then I
don't need the introduction.
But if I land on this
page like this and say, okay, so.
Yeah, it's more natural to have
it at the beginning.
Yeah, but I guess because I'm a user
that does not know what
this project is about, I guess.
Instead, if I could be a user
and other users, maybe they
would like to see the changelog first.
And we can see a lot of badges here.
quite yeah it's a really
colorful uh yeah yeah and yeah you can see
for example here open issues that is 100
so if you click there then
it will bring you to the uh
to the issue page so i
think that these badges are
provided by github uh yeah this
one open issues close the issues
uh then for example this opening
call up uh yeah possibly it's
a a badge that would
possibly provided by call up.
Let's see.
I mean, you can actually see
if you look at this, read me where
what what is so you can see that
that link that this points to
but you can also see the the image
where the image comes from,
just referring to some questions
that we had in the past before.
Yes.
We have a question in the notes.
One of the readmes has link
to the wiki in the GitHub repo.
I suppose it's talking about
this readme, the ManorU.
Is this a good idea?
Well, I would say yes.
Yeah, I think this is a deep wiki.
If you go a bit upper, a bit lower, sorry.
with lower so maybe i can search
for wiki with control f yes
it has a link to this um i
would say it is a good idea
because you can't have
a very long readme file it
will be difficult to read if
you have something more some more
content and a deep wiki is one of the options
What do you think?
I would say that the thing is
that a wiki, I mean, we
said that we don't like wikis.
It's not that we don't
like wikis, it's just that
wikis have the problem that may
not be, they may be a bit
hard to keep in sync with the code.
And so what I can say here is
that it makes sense to have
a link to a wiki or
even to have any information, any
content in a wiki if it
doesn't change very often or
if it's something very stable, let's say.
Yeah, but in general, if you
have much more content than
link to another more structured,
easy to navigate site,
documentation is a good idea
but maybe wiki is not the best choice yeah
but we have many other options
so there are trade-offs wikis
are easy to modify for
non-developers and uh that's why
they exist basically yes okay um
I think we've been active for one hour
and I think we deserve,
everybody here deserves a little
break because we are facing
the computer we're sitting in.
So I guess we will have a 10-minute break.
And during this break, I
would recommend really for you
to reactivate your cardiovascular
system or whatever it works for you.
But yeah, so...
anything we need to say before
that we just say i think
that that's that's all uh maybe
let's see each other uh in
10 minutes great so then bye bye
Hello.
Welcome back.
I hope you had a refreshing break.
So I need to apologize possibly
for not being too clear about
what needs to be done in this exercise.
I will try to be clear in what follows.
So before we move on to other topics,
we have still to say one
thing about readme files and
especially about markdown and
different formats.
So if your README file is
very long, you may want to
have a table of content there.
And GitHub use at least
to automatically generate a table
of content for README files.
And on GitLab instead, you
may have to generate a table
of content using this little
directive here let's say and in
if you instead are using
a restructure text then you you
can use this this snippet of
code let's say by adding at
some point in your in your
readme this this code okay so in
Now we are going to talk
about something a bit more complex
and more powerful than readme files,
which is Sphinx, which is
one of those documentation generators
that we mentioned before.
And so the objectives for
this section is to understand
how static site generators build
website out of plain text
files, not only Sphinx, but
there's many other siblings, let's say.
And we are going to do it.
We are going to create an
example of a documentation
system, documentation corpus with Sphinx.
And we are going to
learn some Markdown along the
way, some special kind of Markdown.
One thing to notice is
that actually this very lesson
that I'm sharing now, it's
been built with Sphinx.
So it's something that, so this is,
if you want, basically in
front of your very high eyes,
there is a real example of Sphinx.
So I'll guide you through a...
series of steps to create
your first Sphinx project.
Okay.
And in order to do that,
though, I'm going to, first of
all, switch my share to a
terminal where I will run some commands.
And in order for you to follow along,
you should have a code
refinery conda environment installed.
And in the notes, we have
that there should be already some commands.
links that just you know to
make sure you can follow along
if you have problems maybe you
can ask in the in the zoom support room
One thing I need to say
is that Conda may be not the
only way you have to
install the accessory software for
this, but it's the most
convenient, so that's why we chose that.
I will now keep the notes
aside and show you an
empty terminal, which is...
a bit daunting for some people,
but that's a very natural
way to interact with a computer,
at least for me.
And I'm going to type some commands.
So first of all, I need
to conda activate code refinery.
So in this way, I
activate the conda environment
for code refinery, and this will
give me the possibility to use the
the commands I want to
use, the things around Sphinx, basically.
You see that my prompt
has changed here, and I'm happy about that.
So we should check just
if Python is available.
These are commands that you
should run on your, if you
want to follow along, I'm going
to be quite slow.
You should try to type
these commands and see if there's any error.
So your output could vary a little,
but you shouldn't see any
errors when you run these few
commands that I'm going to type.
Python version.
This is just to check
that Python is installed and works.
Then the other thing we need
to look at is Sphinx build.
Let's check the version again.
Here I have version 8.2.
You may have a different
version, it's still okay.
Then another thing we need to
use is the so-called Sphinx Quick Start.
It's the same version.
It's expected.
Okay.
And the last thing.
Sorry, someone else.
Oh.
Yeah, I have the version 7.4,
but it also works.
Yeah, by checking versions, if
we spot something strange, we may
know it may come from the version difference.
Yeah.
And after that, we will
run some small command, some
simple thing to check out if
we have the necessary extensions
of Sphinx also installed here.
Yeah, with the Python command.
Yeah, this is the shortest
possible Python program, let's say.
If it works without errors,
then it means that we are okay.
And now, if my throat allows
me, we should be able to
start our first Sphinx project.
So for that, I will create
a new directory called doc-example.
I will also need to change my directory.
my current directory to that.
So that I am inside it.
This is very important.
And then I can invoke
this command, Sphinx quick start
that I already used before.
Sphinx dash quick start
without arguments this time.
This command is going to
give me an interactive, a
quick interactive, a short
interactive session where it asks
me some questions and I'll show you.
So I will just zoom out
a little so that it's more readable.
So it will ask me if
we want to separate the source
and the build directories.
So the source for the documentation
and for the build,
because the documentation is going
to be built in HTML files.
It's okay if we accept
the default option, which is no,
so we don't split anything.
Then project name.
So here I need to type something.
I will say Sphinx test.
test okay and it's okay
author name there could be one
other one i will just put
my name here then enter project
release i should possibly give a
version here i will put 0.1
of course this is not a it's just a
an example.
Okay.
0.1.
And then I have another
question here, which is about
the project language.
I will make sure it's visible.
English is okay.
Okay.
So now I got back my
prompt, my shell prompt.
And if I look at the
content of the current directory,
I see that something has
been created by Sphinx.
Okay.
So I will comment on some of these.
There's conf.py.
So Sphinx is a Python
package that still works with Python.
So it needs Python.
Conf.py contains the configuration
of my project, which extensions
I need, other things.
So a lot of the things
that you decide here,
you tell the quick start
facility about they're going to end
up in this configuration.py file,
and you may have to change
it later if you want to add
some, to have some more features, let's say.
There's index.rst, possibly the
most important file here it's
the like the root of
the documentation here it's the
first page of the documentation
and it also will contain all
the links to the other parts
of it okay then there is
a directory called underscore build
which is the one in by
default the the where the the
html files are going to to end and what else uh
Yeah, okay, so there's a Makefile.
Makefile is something that you
can use on Linux and macOS.
And it contains, we're not going
to use it today, but in
principle, there's a list of
commands you can use to
automatically generate the documentation
with just Make and something.
And Make.bat is something for
Windows users instead.
Uh, but yeah.
Okay.
So what am I going to have a look at now?
It's we're going to look at,
uh, index dot RST.
Now in what follows, uh, I'm
going to, um, to use an editor.
And the editor I use is
Vim, because I like it.
But you can use any editor you want.
So when you see Vim, you
don't have to type Vim.
You can open it with, let's say, code.
If you want to use Visual
Studio Code, you can use code, for example.
So what I want to do now
is to have a look at the content of indexed.rst.
Okay?
There's also nano.
Let's do this.
I will use nano because
I don't want anybody of you to
end up in Vim and become a prisoner of that.
So nano index.rst.
So this is a way to open it with nano.
Okay.
So this is the skeleton of a...
of an index file of the main page.
So it has quite some
like some documentation, some
like some directives that actually
not going to be printed.
But then there is this title line.
Okay.
A paragraph.
There's also a link.
Okay.
And then there is a table of content here,
actually a tree, something which
is a table of content tree.
Okay.
And so if you have an
older version of Sphinx
Quickstart, actually you get
some additional content here, which
we do not care.
So you could have an index and table,
indices and tables section, but
we don't need it.
So you can remove it.
Okay.
So what I'm going to do now is,
since I want to add some
content to the documentation to show
what are the possibilities, I
will add here a file name called somefeature.md.
Maybe this is a file called
in a markdown file.
So this is just a name.
I will create the file later.
So this, in this file,
call some feature.md, I may
be discussing, describing the feature
of my code.
That's it.
One thing to notice, I'm typing it here,
and it needs to be indented
at the same level as caption.
So here there are three
empty, three spaces, and before
caption here, and there needs
to be three spaces here as well.
So this is restructured
text and restructured text is
like white space like Python.
I can also add a space if I want just
for clarity, but there needs
to be always the same indentation level.
And now I can
Save this in whatever way
my editor allows me to do so.
And save and exit.
Now I need to open
conf.py, the configuration file.
And I need to go down to
the line where the extensions are listed.
And the extension I need to
add here is the myst.
my st parser okay so this
is the extension that i need uh in order
for sphinx to uh to
parse the markdown files i'm
going to create okay
So the syntax here is
exactly Python syntax, right?
It's a dictionary in Python.
Yes, yeah.
So actually, extensions, in this case,
it's a list of strings, and
each string is the name of a package, okay?
And I will save and exit, okay?
So these are the two files I've modified.
First, index.rsc, adding...
somefeatures.md and then adding
conf.py okay good and now I mentioned
before I wanted to add
a file called somefeatures.md so
I will do exactly that open
this plain text file and in
the interest of time I will go to the notes
which I can possibly show here
and take, wait, I take this
text here that is available, copy it.
There's actually a copy button,
copy that and paste it here.
Okay.
And I leave it like this,
but maybe I should comment a bit.
So you see there are like,
there's a main title of the,
of the file, let's say that
of the page, notice that this
is a different thing.
This is a markdown.
It's not, it's not restructured text now.
So the main title, title of the subsection,
and then the paragraph and
then there are there's like a
list, there are lists.
One thing to notice that
the empty surrounding lines are
required in this flavor markdown,
for you to understand that
these are items in the same list.
So, we need to be careful
about white space here.
So, we'll save now.
and exit.
I will clear my terminal and
show again the content of this directory.
So now everything should be fine.
If I want, I can try
to build with Sphinx build.
So with Sphinx Build, I need
to pass two arguments.
The first one is the
source of the documentation, and
the other is the destination.
So the build documentation will
end up in the underscore build directory.
We'll see, okay, everything has worked.
So what can I do now?
I can open, so if I now
go to build, let's do it with an ls,
There's many things there, but
the most important is index.html.
So if I open that with
a browser, then I should
see my HTML documentation.
So how do I do this?
On Linux, I use XTG.
That's supposed to work on
Linux, and then build index.html.
So this is Linux.
On Mac OS, you can use just open.
So if I do just open,
this works also on Linux, but
Mac OS, Linux maybe.
So if you are on
Windows instead, you should use,
and you still do this from
the terminal, you can use start.
Okay, since I'm on Linux, I
will go back here and I just
type xtg and say that this is Linux.
And somewhere in, so I
have quite some message here.
What has happened, and I'll
show you now, is that in my
browser, I managed to
open my documentation, which has,
so this is the index, which
is what was generated out of index.rst.
And then if I click here on the left,
I have some feature, and
that's the content of the file
that I just created.
Okay.
And yeah, so if I zoom
in or out, of course, the
layout is going to change.
Okay.
There's also a searching
box generated that's generated automatically.
Yeah.
So yeah, searching is a
very important feature.
So should I check like I
want to go back here and say...
Okay, so I guess it, yeah,
it gives me pages that
are matching this feature, so it's quite,
I think the Sphinx feature
testing is not the best, but
it's still very useful, very useful.
Okay, so I will go back
to, again, to the My Browser, but now showing,
the exercises that we can work on.
So we should have like a
20 minute session, a quite
long exercise section.
Maybe we should, should we try
to short it to 15 minutes
just to save some time?
Do you agree?
Can you?
Yeah, maybe 15 minutes is a better choice.
Yeah, so if you manage to follow along
so far, you should have now
a scaffold of a Sphinx project.
And you should be able
to add some additional files.
And in these text files, you
should be able to try
different features like links,
tables, numbered lists, code blocks,
and then also try LaTeX.
So equations.
So this is a chance to
actually get used to Markdown
and its most important features.
There's then a third exercise
about Sphinx Autodoc.
Here you need to create
an additional example.py file.
that, no, sorry, example Python module,
which is like, which you will
store in a file called multiply.py.
You need to put this stuff,
the idea is that you put
this content in the file, and
you see that there is a doc string,
docstring written actually in
a structured text and so you can make
so that your your sphinx
project actually harvests this
this code, this doc string
by modifying the configuration in
the way that's written here.
And also you need to modify
your index and then you
can rebuild the documentation.
You should see an additional
page with the API reference for
this very small and simple module.
So we'll put links of
to the possibility already there.
Okay.
So we have this exercise section.
Yeah, a bit upper to the latex block.
Yeah, yeah.
I think the configuration extensions.
Yeah, here for different
versions of Sphinx, it might
be a bit different for older
Sphinx version, you may
need this Sphinx.ext.massjax.
For the new version, maybe this
is not very necessary, but it doesn't hurt.
Yeah.
So you can try without
changing the configuration or as you wish.
But yeah, this shouldn't be
needed if you have a very recent.
So if you are using a
very recent version of Sphinx,
it doesn't, it shouldn't work,
shouldn't be needed.
So I let you,
go to the exercises and
we should reconvene in 15 minutes.
So I will switch to the notes perhaps.
Yeah, the notes are here.
Okay, so see you in 15 minutes.
And have fun.
Bye.
Bye bye.
Welcome back.
I hope you had an interesting,
you find the exercises on Sphinx interesting.
We will head into a break soon,
but first we would like to
discuss a little points about
Sphinx, more about this, and
then give a glimpse of what
is going to happen after the break.
So,
One thing, so if you're
confused about restructured text Markdown
and MyST, so the idea
is that restructured text is
the oldest format and Sphinx was built for it.
Okay.
Then Markdown was independently
developed because someone wanted
something simpler.
And so Markdown became more
and more popular because of
its simplicity, but it was
limited compared to restructured text.
and then my st was created
as a flavor markdown that would
sort of uh unify the two things
at least in the in the sphinx uh for
for the for for the sphinx
tunings okay uh regarding um
good practices i would say um so the
The build directory, which is the one
where we store our documentation, well,
that one should not be
under version control, so you
should not git add that directory.
So you can still have it
in the directory, but it shouldn't
be in the repository.
It shouldn't be added to the repository.
So we recommend you add
this directory to your gitignore
so you don't accidentally add
these files to your repository.
There are also some tools that
allow you to automatically refresh
the view every time you make a change.
So there's Sphinx AutoBuild.
And also, if you have
links in your documentation, you
want them to be checked
automatically to make sure that
they actually point at something,
there is this minus icon.
There is this link check
utility that is pretty useful
and pretty time-saving.
So what are we going to do after the break?
After the break, we have
all the stuff locally tested.
After break, we can try to
deploy it on the internet.
then you can share it.
Using GitHub?
Yes.
We will use GitHub as a demo.
Yeah.
And so we will have a page on github.io.
Yes.
Right?
And this one.
Okay.
So...
Shall we just head into a
break, into a 10-minute break
for the same reasons I
mentioned before, like cardiovascular
health and attention.
So I'll switch maybe to the notes.
Wait, the notes.
Go to the bottom and yeah.
So see you in 10 minutes then.
Yes.
Bye-bye.
Hello, we're back.
And the next topic is
deploying Sphinx documentation to
GitHub pages.
We have everything tested locally.
Now it's time to share it
with people then by serving it
on a website.
GitHub is a convenient way to do this.
You have the other options
like GitLab or the other like Bitbucket.
We will use GitHub here.
So two services we're going
to use to realize this.
First one is GitHub Pages.
GitHub Pages serve websites
from your GitHub repo.
And the GitHub actions will also be used.
It automatically runs code when
you push something or some people
send a pull request.
You can configure it to do this.
We will see it later.
So basically, so in real
world, you may need to push
the stuff local to the remote repo in GitHub
But here we will use a template for this.
Yes.
So you can see, okay, I
will keep this a little bit
slower such that you can code along.
Maybe I should go back again.
So this is the link
I clicked, the documentation example.
And you can see here is
a template from Code Refinery.
We'll use that and make a
copy to our own repo.
I will give it a name
like maybe docs example.
Okay, that's available.
Yes, create the repository.
It will take a few seconds.
Okay, so here is the content.
We can see there's a source folder.
Here you're supposed to have
your source code for your
project, for example, Python code
or some other language.
And the doc folder is
where the documentation is.
You can see these files
are exactly the same as showed
by Michaela in the demo.
the index file under
the configuration file.
So this is a typical file structure.
You can see that there is
a shorter readme file here.
But in order to let GitHub
pages to host this thing, we
needed to create a configuration file
for it to use.
I will create a file.
So create a new file.
We will give it a name.
The path for the file should be GitHub.
I will type a slash.
Then it will go to the
next level, which is workflows.
This name should be fixed.
It's the standard of GitHub.
Then the file name, the file
name could be something you like yourself.
Documentation, I will use this
and the extension should be YAML or YML.
So that's the file.
I will copy the content from our material.
So this is the
A configuration file used by GitHub pages.
There's a name, documentation,
and this line is telling
GitHub actions to do the
automatic update when people are
pushing or sending pull requests.
Workflow dispatch means you
can manually run the workflow.
and then we give it
a write permission because we
needed to have all Git pages
to write something to the build folder.
We can see something.
Yeah, if you're not very
familiar with Git actions, don't worry.
Well, I usually don't write
this thing myself.
I just copy it from somewhere.
Yeah, and then amend it
and change something.
Yeah, and make some changes.
So it runs on the Ubuntu
server provided by GitHub.
It's a virtual machine, I think.
And there are some actions.
Actions are some programs people
and we reuse it here.
And then there's some other
commands we write here and we specify here.
Firstly is install dependencies.
In our case, we need
to install Sphinx under Mr.
Passer and something else.
And then the next step is Sphinx build.
the commander you saw,
what Michaela showed.
In that case, it's from the present folder.
So it's a dot here.
But in this case, the file
system is a little bit different.
The contents for the documentation
are in the doc folder.
So it's from doc.
And the HTM files will be
created in the build folder as before.
And then the last step is
deployed to a GitHub page.
We're still reusing something
written by the other people.
Yeah.
And here are some arguments
for Git action to use.
So the first thing is
from which branch you're going to deploy the
GitHub page, in this case,
or by default, it's a th page.
And the GitHub token is
something generated by GitHub, I think.
And this is the folder
from where the static files should be.
And this force often means
Yeah, means that this branch
will be created without a parent.
So I will copy this stuff
and go back to here and paste it here.
I think I don't need
to modify anything here.
I will just make the changes.
So I will commit it directly
to the main branch.
So git actions will follow
the instructions in the configuration file.
Let's go back.
But there are some other things
we need to set up, which
is from which branch git
actions should deploy the
the web page as we have
seen in the configuration file
that the branch should be the
GH pages from the root of
this branch to deploy the web page.
So I will save this.
Okay.
Now let's go back
We can see there's already some actions.
If I click actions, we
can see there's already action finished.
And another one is why it's waiting.
But sometimes I guess, okay,
it seems to this.
Okay.
Refresh the under, it's done now.
Okay, we should have a link
to the webpage here, but we need
to set up this a bit.
Yeah, you can tap it here,
but it can also be
automatically filled by clicking this.
I'll save the changes.
So then this is the link,
the URL to the webpage, which is your GitHub
name and then the project name.
Let's check this out.
Yeah, so this is the
content of the documentation.
Very similar as the local one.
Okay.
I think we can make a
little bit change to the to the
file to see to the markdown
file to see if anything changed
from the web page.
I will simply add more atoms.
I will commit the changes.
This should trigger another Git action.
Yes, we can have a look
at what's going on here actually.
So the workflow here is
running all the steps in the job.
Yes.
And it did already the, I
think it did already everything.
Yeah.
It's been quite quick.
It's not always so quick.
It's very quick.
But it may take a few seconds to, I should
Yeah, but it will take a few.
Oh, okay.
That's also very quick.
So we can see item four
and item five added here.
Yeah, it can take up to a minute or so.
Yeah, sometimes it's slower.
Yeah, that's basically a
simple workflow for the deployment
by using GitHub.
Let's see.
Yeah, that's steps here.
Okay, so we're done with this.
If there's any questions, I think
that someone is trying to
follow along and they are struggling a little.
We did, I think, I think
that the part to the configuration of the
of the action.
I think we described quite well.
I don't know if there's
anything we should look again, but
maybe we can do it later.
Yeah, I think we can use
the extra minutes to recap these things.
Should we wrap up stuff today?
And maybe use some time after
that to, if someone want to
stay, we can use that time
to recap something or do something else.
Yeah, I think I want just to stress
how this GitHub Actions is
a very interesting tool because
it allows you to really automate
a lot of tasks around
software development on GitHub.
Here we have been using
it for building your documentation
and then deploying it.
But, um, but you can do
much more, many more things
like, you know, running test use and so on.
And it's cool.
Also the fact that you can reuse as,
as, uh, the, um, uh,
like actions that other people have written.
Uh, so, uh, yeah, it's,
uh, the composability is nice.
I would say, um,
Yeah.
So what could we talk a bit about?
So this lesson has actually
other things we could talk about,
but I think we should give
a bit of time for feedback
and to introduce also what's
going to happen next week.
But yeah.
Yeah, I'm sorry, it's going
a bit too faster.
But you can also join
the help sessions later and then
we can maybe redo something.
All right.
Thank you, [name] and [name] for today.
If there was one thing that
you would like people to
take from today's lesson, what would it be?
What would you like people to take home?
Well, I mean, we covered a lot of things.
So I hope that, I hope
possibly, can I choose two?
Can I choose two things?
Yes, you can choose two.
One is, I think, just how
to start using Sphinx, because
this is actually, I think,
very similar to other tools.
And if you learn a bit
the workflow here, I think you
will be fine also with other tools.
And also, I think, in
general, about readme files,
that know that you can do more,
that there are options to
organize your documentation with
the README files, with links,
with all the features that
Markdown itself only gives you,
just alone gives you for
just making your README easier to use.
Right.
And the materials, if you
go through the links that we shared in the
collaborative notes include like
a walkthrough of everything that
both [name] and you went through today.
So if you think it went
too fast, then sorry for that.
But know that you can always
go back to the material and follow step by step
there.
And let me just check where I added it.
I didn't.
Okay, I also have one quick news section.
I'll add that to the end of the document.
So also know that the code refinery
people, the Code Refinery
community, we actually have a Zulip chat
where we're hanging out and
where you can also, where you're
very free to join us.
And you can still ask
questions in that chat also about the workshop.
The link is now in that blue box.
So if you want to like
go through the exercises
yourselves afterward and there's
something coming up.
Know that you can join there
or also during the next session next Wednesday.
Feel free to bring a
question from this session.
Like it does not have
to be necessarily about next week's session.
And yeah, thank you so
much everyone for today.
Thank you to our great
instructors for guiding us through the lesson.
Really hope that you took
something away from it.
And especially something that you
can also take into your own
daily work as a researcher who codes.
And next week, we'll look
into Jupyter notebooks.
So we'll have same time, same place,
a session about Jupyter notebooks,
which in some sense is also
a way of documentation or
can be or visualization and
I know many of you probably say that,
oh, but Jupyter Notebooks, I
know that, I've used that in some course.
Even if you think that,
I think there's still something
new also part of the session,
so I would still recommend to join and find out.
We have also added, and it
is visible on the stream, yes,
in the very bottom of the
document, a feedback for today
So we know now already that
some of you found it a bit too fast.
That is also good to let
us know here so that we have it documented.
And then also share a bit
like one thing that was good about today,
one thing you liked about
today's session and one thing
that we should make sure to
improve for next time.
So
And if you have any other
feedback and you can also
still add questions here.
So we will leave the
document open still for a while today
and try to answer the
questions and then the document
will be archived on our event page.
And yes, we see that there is too fast,
but it, yeah, it is a lot
of things in a short time.
If you feel like that you
would rather have a longer
session, that's also something to let us know.
We are always trying to
develop these workshops.
And we try to find a
good balance between the amount of stuff
that we want to show you,
the amount of cool stuff, of
stuff that we really like, and
then also to not keep you here for too long.
Because we also know that
there is this Zoom fatigue going on.
And the longer a course is,
like you always have, then
some people are dropping up.
But do let us know if you feel like
that you would like longer
sessions on this and we can consider it.
Anything you would like to
still say, [name] and you?
I've talked a lot, so I
will leave you to say something first.
Yeah, I mean, documentation
is something you need to start from small.
You don't need to at the
first place to make a very
nice, very beautiful documentation
or even using Sphinx.
You can start from encode documentation.
or and then improve from
there to readme file or some other format.
And when the project scales up
and you needed to make
a more complex documentation, then
move to Sphinx.
It's a matter of iterations.
So yeah, I would say
Don't be stressful.
Start from something basic
and, yeah, iterate a lot.
Encourage people, your colleagues,
to contribute to the documentation.
Yeah, I'd say that, well, I
think one thing I would add
to this is, yeah, we try to
spend some time on the tools.
i think that it's also um
there's also a lot of practice
and a lot of like
politics around documentation because
uh documentation is not something
you do only uh once it's you
know you create a website with
uh either a reading meal or
a website with things and then
not how many as you need to
keep it up to date and uh
and it's difficult and it's it
can be work and you need to
to keep that in mind, I would say.
Yeah.
And so the idea of
keeping documentation close to
your source code, of course,
makes things easier in this sense.
But then I think there are
also some tools to make documentation nicer.
So for example, if you have
nicer to easier to maintain,
for example, Jupyter Notebooks next week,
I think there are ways
to include Jupyter Notebooks
in your documentation.
and uh so that you have
you can write tutorials if
we're using jupiter notebooks and
uh yeah it's a bit advanced
it's a bit complicated but then
you can you have all the
tool links around jupiter notebooks
which is like validations uh
you know i mean there's there's
a lot of stuff there so um
yeah all right now we're two
two minutes over time yeah yeah yeah
So let's officially close here.
But we'll still hang out here for a moment.
And for those of you who
are interested in hosting your
own website on GitHub, you has
agreed that you can still show
us how to do that.
So the last session of today,
so you can stick around and
maybe not type along, but at
least see what it's all about.
And then we'll also end here,
but thank you so much for joining today
and looking forward to, uh,
well, not really seeing, but
meeting you in the notes doc
next, uh, next week for Jupiter.
Okay.
And I think we just continue,
um, with you screen share.
But yeah, I think [name]
needs to... Well, you're still, I
think it's a yellow screen.
Okay, so are we ready to quit the stream?
No, no, let's go through
the hosting part still for five minutes.
Oh, sorry.
So we're already a bit over time.
No, no.
Yes, we ended already.
We ended already officially, but
this is now just extra.
Okay, sorry.
I'm not allowing.
So, okay.
Hello.
So you want to continue
for another five minutes?
Is that okay?
Yeah.
Okay.
So then I will not close the stream.
Thank you.
That's good to know.
Sorry.
Yeah.
Should I maybe...
recap something from this.
So basically, I think it
might be confusing because we
actually use the two services
from GitHub, the GitHub pages
and the GitHub actions.
So we basically need to configure both.
To configure GitHub actions, we
added this file, this YAML
file to configure GitHub actions.
That's for GitHub actions to
follow the steps to follow.
And we commented quite a lot
on this, I think, right?
I think we were clear on
the meanings of this.
Yeah.
Right.
So that's the thing.
And yeah, in addition to
the contents, another thing we
did is to configure Git pages.
So which is this part.
So from where to store the
built files and from where
to deploy the website.
I don't know if that's clear.
I hope so.
I guess that, yeah, we're a bit fast,
but I think that if people
look at the notes, everything
is explained relatively clearly there.
I think quite clearly there.
Yeah.
So basically two things, GitHub
Actions and GitHub Pages.
Yeah.
Did you also still want
to show the hosting, the last lesson?
They're all hosting personal
or project websites on GitHub pages.
That's the last page of
the... The homepage.
Go to the next.
Yeah.
So in addition to host a
webpage, we can also host
a homepage for ourselves.
Because the steps are very
clear from GitHub's documentation.
So we would recommend
following those instructions to
to try out to host your
own homepage on GitHub.
That's this part.
So basically, it can take the README,
if I understand correctly, you
can take the README of your, that
you have in a repository, which
needs to have a specific name.
And then out of that,
it will create automatically a web
page for you or for your project.
So there are some very clear instructions.
It's not using Sphinx, but the default
no, sorry, [name], to deploy this website.
Sorry, if someone wants to try it out,
they can follow the instructions
on the website.
And if there are any
questions, ask next week or in
our chat that is linked from the notes.
Yes, if you have any
questions regarding this or the
Sphinx Docs thing, then ask.
Yeah.
Okay.
Great.
Then I think, are we ready
to close the stream for today?
Yes.
Yeah.
All right.
Then let's do that.
Thank you for everybody
for sticking around.
Thanks.
Yes.
Thank you very much.
Bye-bye.