Hello, hello.
Can you hear us out there?
Hello.
See us out there?
Let's see if our friends on
Zulip, they can give us some feedback.
So far.
Yes, yes.
We are fine.
Should we have a quick sound check?
Let's just say our name.
Maybe the sound check could be this.
We introduce ourselves very
short, very briefly.
And so we need to all take turns.
And I will say the next person.
I'm going to start me.
I'm [name].
I'm [name] from Aalto University.
And I'm coordinating this run
of the CodeRefinery Workshop with [name].
Hi everyone, my name is [name],
Research Software Engineer at
CSC in Finland and
co-coordinating this workshop and
today doing the very short intro and outro.
And [name] is one of the teachers here.
Hi everyone, I'm [name].
I'm a Research Software Engineer
at Aalto University and I'm
going to teach about Jupyter
Notebook alongside with [name] here.
Hey, I'm [name], also a
Research Software Engineer from Aalto.
And today, instead of clicking
the camera buttons, I'm going
to be teaching Jupyter Notebooks.
And we are very excited for today's lesson.
So what you're seeing on
screen currently is our notes document.
So if you register to the
workshop, you got an email
basically right now, I guess.
With all the links for today,
and this is one of them,
and this is the most important one.
And that includes all the
links to other documents.
And this is also the way on
how you can ask questions
during the whole session today.
And we will have our
instructors, [name] and [name],
and other people behind the
scenes answering your questions there.
And we will also archive
them after the workshop, so you
can always come back.
And maybe, [name], we show
briefly how people can edit this document.
So you will probably see
something like what is shown
on screen right now, when you
follow the link to the notes and
then up to the left or
up to the right, depending on
how wide your window is, you
will find this little pen symbol.
And if you click that, you
go into edit mode and then
you can actually edit this document.
And for example, start by
filling in and answering our
icebreakers for today.
So we have prepared some for you here.
And maybe I ask today's
instructors about the first one.
So if you could have a
fully paid holiday right now,
we are covering all your costs.
What would that be?
Where would you like to go?
[name], do you have any big
dreams for a vacation?
Yeah, I guess I would go
and visit my nieces.
Yeah, that's something that I
always wanted to do.
How about you, [name]?
Right now I'm thinking just
in a forest nearby somewhere
because it might be fun to
go to some mountains or something, but...
It's still a bit too warm to go south.
And also being on an
airplane doesn't really strike me
as something I would want to do today.
Oh yeah, we're all in Finland today.
We have currently, what do we have?
Maybe 10, 15 degrees?
Quite warm.
A bit gray, but colorful.
Yeah, it's 13, but yeah, it's grayish.
How about [name]?
I'm the one who wrote that
I would like to go to a
warm place with a swimming pool or by the sea.
Maybe in October in Finland.
I don't know.
The others who are watching and
who are typing, you can
tell about your weather.
But now Finland starts this
season, which is the worst season.
The snow is not yet there.
Days are getting shorter.
The darkness is filling everything.
So it's like I miss the sun.
In neuroscience, there's usually
a big conference, which is
called Society for Neuroscience.
And that ends at the end
of November or middle of November.
And it rotates between locations.
And once every four years is in San Diego.
And so a couple of times I
was able to go there and it
was just like in the middle
of November leaving Finland and
going to San Diego for a week.
It was just, so yeah.
What about you [name]?
I think I'm with [name] there.
Like, I don't need much at the moment.
And just going out into
the forest seems like very nice.
Maybe if I could wish for
anything, then I would wish
for some like autumn sun and no rain.
But forest sounds pretty good.
A bit more sunny would be nice.
Also, there's mushrooms.
There is mushrooms.
It's the best time of
the year for mushrooms.
I always wanted to learn
about mushrooms more.
Yeah, maybe this year is the year.
We also have two more questions here.
Do you have a paper notebook at hand?
And I actually really have it at hand here.
One is my to-do list and
the other one is my brain dump notebook.
How about you?
I also have one, but it's a
bit far away to reach it.
And I also have an iPad
if that counts, I don't know.
It's not exactly paper, but
for some reason I have two pens,
but I do not have anything to write on.
It has like pencil and you
can write stuff, right?
So I guess it counts.
Well, sometimes also the notes
make it on my hand if
I need to remember something like
to do when leaving this room, for example.
And I'll write it on my
hand so that it doesn't vanish immediately.
How about [name]?
Do you use paper notebooks or any other?
I used to, but then because
I'm always in different places
and I forget things around.
So in the end post-its,
I write something on a post-it,
put it in my pocket.
And then when it's the time
to do the weekly laundry, I
have to remember to empty my
pocket from the post-its, otherwise
it's not going to be nice.
That's also nice.
And then we have one
question more related to today's session.
what is your way of working
when it comes to writing code
for your research projects?
And we have still three minutes.
So maybe [name], do you want
to share about your way of working?
Well, it depends a lot on the project.
So right now I'm working
on something with Django where there's like,
you run a command and it
runs the whole thing as a
test server and you can play around with it.
So then I just write Python code.
But otherwise, I would always
have a Jupyter notebook on the side
and essentially refresh, reload everything,
and then run some commands
to see what comes up and
be writing Python code on the other side.
How fitting with today's topic.
So an expert in the topic.
[name], how about you?
I would say it really
depends on the project that I'm doing.
If it's like a data
heavy driven project that I have
to do some experiments with the
data and I don't know the
data, the Jupyter notebooks
are the way that I'm using them.
But most of the time, I'm
not working on those kind of stuff.
I'm mainly doing AI, LLM,
neural networks and stuff.
And also, Jupyter Notebooks can
be useful in those cases as well.
But I guess these are
not the best practices for those.
So I'm usually using pure Python
or C to do some stuff.
And a reminder for everyone
joining, we are currently
discussing the icebreaker questions.
We will be starting in
about one minute with the actual course.
[name], how about you?
Do you use Jupyter notebooks?
Well, the first one is mine.
It's nice to prototype with
this type of graphical or
semi-graphical tools, Jupyter.
I also use RStudio.
But then I always, at the end, convert
that into a script so that I know
that I can kind of run
it without any, how can I
say, interactive input that the
orders are processed.
Well, I don't want to spoil the fun.
You will hear about these things today.
So...
Yes, and at least my clock
is also showing top of the
hour, one o'clock in Finnish time.
So let's get started with today's session.
And I would ask [name] to
change to the view mode again,
and for now show the event page first.
The CodeRefinery.
Yes.
So very welcome everyone to
this session of the CodeRefinery Workshop,
where we are going to
talk about Jupyter Notebooks.
I'm here with [name], who
is manning the stream today
and handling that you can all see and hear us.
And then we have [name] and
[name], who will be instructing today's session.
My name is [name].
I'm the project manager for
the CodeRefinery project and
just introducing today's topic.
And you will also see me
briefly in the very end.
We are now showing on
stream our event webpage where
you can always find all the
latest news, what is going on.
You can also find the
questions from previous sessions
and what's gonna happen in the next session.
And if we scroll quite a bit down,
There is also the schedule
with all the different days.
This is the same page where
you also all registered.
And there you can find
behind Jupyter Notebooks.
That's the link to today's materials.
And then you have gotten
an email probably just a few
moments ago where we shared also
the link to our collaborative notes.
So let's switch to that one.
So that is the link
to our collaborative notes.
Again, all the links, also
a suggestion on screen set
up and our icebreakers.
And this is also the place
where you can ask questions
throughout the session today.
And in order to do that,
you will need to go into
edit mode of this document.
So if you arrive at this
page, you can look at the
very top of the document.
There will be either on the left
where it is for [name] right now,
or on the top right, a
little pen symbol that turns the
page into edit mode.
And then you can start
filling in the icebreaker.
Let us know if you're
using paper notebooks.
for example, at this moment, or also
what is your way of working
when you are writing code?
Are you having any
experiences with Jupyter, for example?
And then during the session,
like it is happening right now, very nicely,
someone will add headers to
this document and also the
links to the respective material
session that you can always
follow along what [name] and [name]
are doing at the time.
And then you can ask the questions
there whenever they come up
during the session.
One last word about code
of conduct, please.
Since everyone can edit this
document, be nice to one
another, be considerate.
Everyone here is on a
different journey at a different
stage in their learning experience.
So take that into consideration.
when you are also answering question,
which you are very free to do
if you know the answer to
some of the questions that are appearing here.
And with that, I'll give over
to [name] and [name] and have
fun with Jupyter today.
Yeah.
Thank you, [name].
Thanks.
Okay.
I will switch to the main
page of the Jupyter Notebook course.
So if you follow the workshop page
and you click on the
Jupyter Notebooks, this is the
page that you are going to see.
And yeah, maybe I can start.
so ... when I think
about Jupyter notebooks actually I
have a double like a dual feeling
so sometimes I really like it
to you to use Jupyter notebooks
and sometimes I don't and I
don't think it's like the best
practice to use that and I
guess the whole point of this
session is to learn about Jupyter notebooks
and see what are the main
strengths of it and what are
the pitfalls of it so Jupyter
notebooks are not the answer to do everything
but it can be a very powerful use
for sharing the code, for
doing some experiments, and you're
going to learn that hopefully in this session.
So what are the Jupyter
Notebooks and what is the
main motivation behind it?
So when you think about like a pure file,
like a coding file, like a Python file
or like a C++ file that you have the code,
the only way that you can
annotate the code is to add
some comments into it, right?
But Jupyter Notebooks bring another way.
And in addition to your code,
you can have text marked down
on HTML code or like a
equation figures and everything
all integrated into a same document
so you have more ways to
annotate your code and explain
the workflow and explain the data
and also play with data
So this is a screenshot
of two different Jupyter notebooks.
And on the left, you can see
that we have a block of code.
And in Jupyter notebooks, these
blocks are called the cell.
So we have a cell of code.
And the output of the code,
which is a table essentially,
is also shown there as well.
but on the right you can
see that there are like some headings
and with the text it can
be like some equations or as
you can see there are like some tables here
as well so the code is running
and also you can see the result
and when you're saving it you
can see all of the material
at the same place not just your code
so it's ... really nice for
telling a story ... and
yeah one additional reason so you
can do nice formatting and so
on to make it like
easily readable and the tables
look better and so on.
But one big thing that to
me is especially important is
that the output is immediately after the input.
So you can actually tell it in order
and the comments are usually
pretty far from wherever the
output appears in the terminal or
Yeah, exactly.
So when you're coming back
to your experiment after a couple of months
or when you're sharing your
code with someone else, it's
very, very easy to follow because
you can see the code, you can see the output,
and you can also add
some explanation like equations or
text or plots to support that.
... so as I mentioned ...
a Jupyter notebook can be thought
as like a notebook like
your paper notebook that you have
but it also has your
code your equation your text
everything inside and it's like
very easy to share and like
to like read and follow ...
block by block or cell by cell
A fun fact is that the
Jupyter name is coming from
the combination of Julia and Python
and R, but today you can
also use it with other languages
and there are like some kernels
that you can use for other
languages to apply to Jupyter Notebook.
So Jupyter Notebook format, as we see here,
is commonly used, and I
guess it's more popular nowadays.
I have seen some entire
books written in Jupyter Notebook formats,
and I guess you have been also seeing
that here and there, especially
if you have worked with Google Colab.
Like the interface is essentially
a Jupyter Notebook that you
have different blocks that you can
add text or code in it.
But the Jupyter Notebook formats
can be also run, for example,
in VS Code, which we hopefully
show in a short demonstration.
And also GitHub Codespaces also
support the similar interface that
we can take a look.
There's also Pluto, which is
more directly like a Jupyter
notebook these days.
So it's a Julia thing and
has a somewhat different philosophy,
but I've seen it a lot lately.
I never worked with Pluto, but
when I was doing Julia, it
was mainly the JupyterLab thing
to work with Julia.
It's interesting.
I will check it out.
So actually, maybe we can take
a look at an example.
So here we have two
different examples that we can
go ahead and browse.
I guess in the past
CodeRefinery lessons previous years,
we always look at the wave discovery thing.
So maybe this year we can
look at the activity inequality study, I guess.
But maybe I can also briefly
show the first one as well.
So the activity in quality
study was a study, I guess,
in 2017 from Stanford University.
And it demonstrates inequality
of activity in different countries
and inside the country
between different genders, different
race, and different age groups.
So just to see what
the Jupyter Notebook looks like,
you can go ahead and look at the paper,
but just to see how are
the plots created in Jupyter
Notebook, maybe I can go ahead
and open the GitHub repository very briefly.
And for example, maybe I can
take a look at the figure number three.
And you can see that
IPython notebooks, these are
the Python notebooks, like Jupyter
notebooks that you can open and see.
Let's, for example, open the
figure three section B and C.
So yeah, these are essentially
the sections or the cells
in a Jupyter Notebook.
So you can see there is
a cell with code inside.
There is a cell, for example,
with a text or a heading for the weekday here.
And there are some reading of the data.
And when the code is run
and the plot is shown, as
[name] mentioned, it's very nice
that you can see actually.
Although in this world, yeah, I guess.
The gravitational wave notebook
is more like an actual story.
This is more like it's
code with very little even comments about it.
So this is essentially just
the code that produces the plot.
And it is in a Jupyter
notebook where you can see the plot.
So that's nice.
Yeah, but I guess it shows
how the Jupyter Notebook cells are created.
But maybe, yeah, that's true.
Maybe we can go back to the code.
So this is not necessarily a bad example,
but I think the gravitational
wave thing is a better example
in that it actually tells a story.
Yeah.
So maybe I can actually go
ahead and open the tutorial here.
So for example, the QuickView Notebook.
So you can either write in
Google Colab or you can open it in MyBinder.
And MyBinder is, I guess
we're going to talk about it
in the sharing section of this course.
But yeah, my MyBinder essentially
is a tool that you can share your notebooks,
and it would take care of
all of the dependencies that you have.
For example, your Python code,
all of the libraries, or if
your code isn't run with all
of the packages, it would be installed.
So when you're sharing the
code, everyone can access it,
and they can also run the
code and see the ports and everything.
So if I click on my binder
here, I guess it would take a couple of minutes.
I guess like 10 seconds or so,
but behind the scene probably
is like opening the environment
and activating the environment.
Oh, it had it pre-created.
So it is possible that it will just create,
it will build and create
the entire environment where the
code can be run.
Because the main thing about Binder is
that it doesn't just display
the notebook, you can actually run
the code in the notebook.
Exactly.
So you can see that again
that I have different blocks
or different cells and this cell
has like the markdown and
headings and everything and these
are like Python codes.
So I can go ahead and
select the cell and for example run the code.
And I can change the code as well.
For example, I can do
the experiment with changing this one
to L1, as it's mentioned here,
and run the code.
And this is a raw text, so
if I run it, it doesn't
change the headings or anything.
I can go ahead and run,
for example, the next block of
the code as well, and also
possibly running the time series.
This would possibly take a
couple of seconds as well.
And then after the time series is done,
maybe we can plot it again
so we can see the difference in plot.
But I guess because we only
changed it from H1 to L1,
the plot would just slightly change.
Oh, let's see.
Let's see.
OK, I don't actually know
if there's a difference.
Yeah, it has slightly changed
because I ran it before, but
it's a slight change.
But still, you can see that.
But you can do the beta plus.
I think I changed the
colors and everything.
But the idea is that I'm
going to talk about in more
details what you can do with the cells.
But just to give you an
idea, I think this is enough.
So yeah, maybe I can go
back to the course material.
I don't save it.
I would go back.
But you can feel free to
go and browse more figures and
see what is happening.
So as I mentioned at the beginning,
when it comes to the
Jupyter Notebooks, I have a
dual feeling about it.
And because Jupyter Notebooks are
very good in some of the
use cases, especially when you
have a workflow that is linear,
which means you have some data
and you want to do some experiments on it.
And it's like an iterative
approach that you want to apply.
So these are very, very good
use cases for Jupyter Notebooks.
Experimenting with new ideas or
with new libraries, or when you
have a new data set that
you haven't worked with it,
again, it's very good because you
can play with the data.
And as you already mentioned,
you can see the results immediately afterwards.
So you get a better sense
than writing a code that reads
the data, and then you have
to recompile the code every time.
I see Jupyter Notebooks as
like an interactive way to work
with your code and data specifically
because you're changing something
and you're seeing the
results, you're changing the
something and you're changing the results.
And with the more powerful
things like widgets that we
are going to discuss, you
can actually make your Jupyter
Notebook more interactive, which is
like a very fun way to play with your data.
These days, a lot of
HPC clusters also provide
a Jupyter-ready environment.
So for example, here at Aalto on Triton,
we have Jupyter available on
the web browser.
Also, Lumi supports that.
So in addition to playing with your data,
you can actually run it on
one of the compute nodes with
all of the fancy resources of
many CPUs to a huge memory or even
a GPU course in some of the clusters,
which makes playing with the
data even more fun, I guess.
sharing and explaining the code
to others or like to just
remember it in the future
it's actually very good ...
as you already mentioned like
telling their story behind like
why I'm doing this experiment
why these hyper parameters are set
or like just writing the story
of ... what you are doing in
the code is like a very powerful
use case of the Jupyter notebooks
If you're a teacher and
you're teaching something, it's also
a very good use case.
As I mentioned, I've seen
entire books written in Jupyter Notebook.
And I remember when I was
a student in many of
the computer science courses, we had
a lot of the assignments were in Jupyter
that the idea of the assignment were there,
the story were there as well,
and some of the blocks of
the code were empty that
the assignment was meant for
the students to fill it out.
And I guess it's also very easy
for the teacher to create
these kind of assignments as
well, because you just run all
of the code and see.
And even if you don't run
it, you would see the plots and the output.
So you get that.
There is an automated grading system
for Jupyter Notebooks, but then
you have to essentially have a correct answer.
Yeah.
a correct format also for the answer.
But when all of the cells are run,
and then you save it, all
of the plots and the outputs
are also saved along it.
So even without running all of the code,
you can get a sense that
if the student actually did it.
But I think it's not a
topic for this section, but yeah.
You can also replace your
paper notebook if you want to, I guess.
And at the moment, there
is a whole community around Jupyter Notebooks.
So there are a lot of plugins
or other side tools that, for example,
you can create slide
presentations with Jupyter Notebooks.
So it's like a powerful...
Probably the most common use
case is kind of a scratch pad.
So you're not exactly telling a story,
you're just seeing what happens
if you write this code.
And then probably discard it or
move it to the correct
function or something like that.
Which kind of does actually
bleed into the pitfalls.
Yeah, that's true.
But yeah.
But speaking of pitfalls,
Jupyter notebooks are not the answer
for everything, especially the
Jupyter notebooks are not good if
you have a very complex code flow
and it's more suitable for
a linear one that you run
the code block by block.
But if you have a more complex one,
Jupyter notebooks are not the
answer and it would just
make it very complicated.
If you have a large code base,
although there are some
approaches to create a module
and call the module and everything,
Personally, I don't recommend it.
I don't think it's a best practice.
It's just for showcasing and
telling the story, I would say.
It is not very easy to write a notebook,
like Jupyter notebook, without a
plugin or without an extra application.
Also, it's possible to do it
in any text editor
because underneath, essentially, it's
like a JSON file.
But with a plugin, it's a lot easier.
So maybe that's also a pitfall.
... notebooks can be version controlled
but again without any plugin
with an additional plugin or
like a platform it can
cause some issues specifically if
you have plots or tables embedded
which are the whole point
of the having Jupyter notebooks
I guess so that's also a limitation there
And I don't know still why, but
when you are creating the Jupyter Notebook,
it's not named by default and
it can be actually a very huge problem.
And this is specifically
about JupyterLab, actually.
... but but ... it's actually
like it doesn't look like a
very huge downside but when you are working
and ... it everyone has this experience
that ... they forgot to to
rename the file and then after
a couple of weeks they came
back and like just looking on
the untitled files so when
you're creating a one just
don't forget to rename it at the beginning
But yeah, you can look at
our internal page for more pitfalls.
And some of the good practices to follow,
as I mentioned, always,
always, always remember to rename
the file when you are working with JupyterLab.
And before sharing and also
saving the code, it's always good
to run all of the cells, all
of the blocks of the code.
So you are making sure
that everything is supposed as it
should be, as you expected it.
Yeah.
Essentially, I have over a
long period of time developed
the habit of always restarting
the kernel and always running
all the cells from top to bottom.
Even if it's a scratch pad, like
even if I'm just trying things out,
I will never go and run
the cells out of order because
that just leads to problems.
I wish there was a
way of completely disabling that feature.
Yeah, but it's very good
for the linear workflow as I mentioned.
So like going block by block, I guess.
Yeah.
Maybe we can go to the
interface and take a look at
the interface very briefly.
If you created the conda environment,
which I guess you did
already, you should be able to
run the JupyterLab.
But just to demonstrate, I
will bring my terminal over here.
And I already have the environment.
So I would just go ahead
and make a directory like JupyterLab demo.
I would go inside that library
and by calling the, actually
my environment is not activated.
Yes, I would activate my
CodeRefinery September 2025.
often this would be conda activate
or do we recommend using
mamba these days in
the installation instructions then it
would be mamba activate yes I don't know
if source activate will work
for everyone but in some cases yeah
because of the structure I'm
always like yeah exactly but yeah
but mamba activate or
either source activate then name
of the environment so it
would activate the environment and
then I can run the command
JupyterLab to to run the JupyterLab
So what happens is that
JupyterLab would be starting and
in your recent browser, it would
open a new tab or new window
and it would show the interface.
so let's wait for it so
it would be done yes and
it switched to my browser so you can see
that the interface of the
computer lab is starting which is very good
but ... for a second if I
go back to the previous ...
terminal if you look at the
logs here you can see that
The JupyterLab is starting
at my localhost with this specific port.
The port and the address
can be also changed.
And there is also this token thing.
So if you want to open it
in a new browser or like
when sometimes you're working on
a remote server and you're
doing like port forwarding to
run a Jupyter notebook, it's
always good to have this token.
Otherwise, Jupyter doesn't allow you
to log in.
So just to, I don't think
I can, it's just to demonstrate.
At least copying and pasting
that full URL should work.
I don't know if you can.
Exactly, yes.
From the terminal.
But on some terminals, just
clicking on it is enough.
Yeah.
OK.
So maybe we can talk about
the interface a bit.
So this is one of the, actually,
before that, maybe I can go
back to the course and
talk about the components and
the big picture behind it.
So what's happening behind the
scene is that we have
the Jupyter Notebook server running,
which in this case is the JupyterLab.
And inside the JupyterLab, we
are creating notebook files just
to see the interface and see
all of the cells and the segments of the code.
At the moment, we are
using my Chrome browser to
see the Jupyter, interact with the JupyterLab.
But it can be also VS
Code or any other tools, I guess.
And behind the scenes, there
is a kernel running, which can be thought
as like a virtual environment,
which has all of your dependencies
and also the dependencies for Jupyter,
which is like the
IPython kernel, essentially, to run
the code and show you the
output and also render the markdown.
So the kernel runs the code.
The notebook file is where
you essentially save everything
and the browser just shows things.
Exactly.
So now we have an understanding
of the big picture.
Maybe I can go back to the, oh, no.
Maybe I can go back to the, oh, sorry.
Maybe I can go back to the interface.
And the reason is I don't
see the tab names, but yeah.
So this is the JupyterLab interface,
and here you can create
a new notebook, which would take a look in.
You can also create a
console with IPython that you
can test some small commands.
You can open a terminal here,
create a file with markdown text.
And before creating a notebook,
maybe we can look at what
is the interface here.
... so here in the tree
explorer you would see all of
the name of the file that
has been created the folder is
empty I just created that so
there is nothing here inside
yet this blue button would open
a new launcher launcher is
this specific page so if I
create this another tab would
be created here that is
essentially the same one ... so
for now it's not useful but
when you're editing a notebook
and you're on the launcher again
that would be a useful button so
for now I will close this tab
I can create a new folder here.
I can upload a new file.
Or if I change the folder
in like my terminal or
something and this hasn't been
updated, I can refresh this file explorer.
I can, of course, clone
a Git repository and I can
like filter some of the files
with like some names or like
essentially like a search button.
I guess we'll take a look at the
Well, okay, the side panels are useful.
Like, we'll take a look at
the Git part at some point later.
Yeah.
There is maybe, like, this
circle with the square inside.
Yes.
So this is for the kernels.
At the moment, there is no kernel running,
so I haven't, like, started
any kernel, which, again, you can
think of it as, like, a...
Yeah, but this is kind of
just good to know, and you
probably will not need it today
or any time very soon.
Exactly.
But when you have
multiple notebooks running, you can, like,
restart the kernel, which is, like,
reinstall the memory of
the Python interpreter or the
R interpreter, in a sense.
But then I think... Mm-hmm.
Yeah, so I'm just thinking through
what we'll actually need for the exercise,
and I think that is creating
a file and adding cells.
Okay, so just the last one is
that with the Git, one,
you can actually clone a Git
repository, or you can actually
initialize a Git repository here.
As we mentioned, notebooks can
be version controlled, but
there are like some tricks
that [name] would show.
So let me just initialize,
I'll just get repository here so
you can like, yes, so that's good.
So maybe I can go back
to the main folder here and then
I can create a new notebook.
So as you can see, a
new notebook has been created and
this is my file and always
remember to rename the file first.
So I would right click on
this and rename it to intro.
Also, you can use the shortcuts
as well, but don't push
yourself to learn all of the shortcuts.
Using Vitek GUI is also fine.
So, sorry, I created a mistake.
So in the Jupyter Notebook, as
you can see, we have these
sections called a cell.
And in this cell, you
can, for example, write any code.
For example, I would go ahead
and from date and time, I
would import date and time,
and for example, print date and time.
you now see what is the time and ...
when I'm selecting a file
this blue indicator shows that
this specific cell is selected so
I can go ahead and with this
play button I can go ahead and run it
so you can see that the code
is run at the moment ... by
the way can people see well
is the text large enough ... you
can write in the notes if it's not
Yes, but I can also increase
the font a bit.
Is it better?
A bit, yeah.
But I can also.
I mean, also, if it's fine, then it's fine.
Okay.
I would keep it at this so
we can see all of the buttons as well.
Yeah.
So when you are selecting a
cell, the first button would
save the whole notebook and
also create the checkpoints, like
a backup that you can go back into it.
You can add a new cell
below the cell that has been
select it, you can cut a cell
and like paste it somewhere
else to the code that you, if you want,
you can copy a cell, you
can paste a cell, of course, you can run a cell.
And if it's a code one,
it would run the code.
And if it's a Markdown one,
it would just render the Markdown.
and this guy is for
interrupting the kernel and it means
that let's say you have
a computationally heavy function
or like when you're
doing something computationally heavy
heavy and the code is a
stock you can just interrupt it
so the the computation would pause
and the command is not
run completely you can restart the kernel
and also run and if you want
to run some of the some of
the cells again or you can
restart the kernel and run all of the cells
So just to show you, I
would select another cell.
And when I'm selecting a
cell, there is also this button
that it shows what is the cell type.
At the moment, by default, is a code one.
I can go ahead and, for
example, change it to Markdown.
And when it's Markdown, I
can write anything in Markdown.
So for example, I can say
this is a large heading.
And, ... for example, ... sorry,
this is a second heading and,
... this is a normal text.
... or I can like,
for example, writing bold, bold, a bold text,
or I can write, for
example, equations as well, like X
equals to, I don't know, Sigma_i.
or y to the power of i, let's say, plus 1.
And I can go ahead and run this.
And because it's a markdown,
it will just render the markdown.
So there is a heading,
the second heading, and the normal text.
So rendering means showing what
you mean by this syntax, right?
Exactly.
It's like the view mode.
Exactly, like the view mode for that, yeah.
... so now you can see like
why it can be powerful because
you can like add the equations
that you want to do before,
like doing like the coding.
And then when someone is
following the code or your Jupyter notebook,
they can see what are
the equations and they don't
have to like finding the code.
...
Yes.
Okay.
If I go back, actually
another, maybe something else that
it can be useful here is
this third button on the left, on the sidebar,
which is just a table of
content, as I mentioned, like
there are some books entirely
written in Jupyter.
So it would just show the heading
so you can see, and then
when you click on the, for
example, the second heading, it
would directly go that side.
I've never actually used this,
but I can see if you're
writing a full book in Jupyter,
then this will be useful.
Also for doing some assignments,
I would say this is very useful.
But yeah, OK.
Anything, [illegible].
So yeah, I guess now you
have a better idea.
And now you understand the
interface, at least the JupyterLab,
a bit better.
So if I go back to the course page,
I guess we covered the
navigation and what are the buttons.
And I guess people can
learn the shortcuts and so on
if they end up using JupyterLab more.
I guess this is something
that you would eventually learn,
but don't push yourself.
And also, if you prefer
a different interface, then this
is completely useless.
that's true so maybe actually
I can also use like I can
show very briefly the VS Code as well
so as I mentioned at the
at the moment ... we are using JupyterLab
as the notebook server and like
... we are using the browser
to interact with and create notebooks
and everything but this can be
done also in other tools ...
for example like in an IDE like
VS Code so if I open my
VS Code here, so my VS Code is
this like I hope you can see it
I would close this error for now.
Maybe I can increase the font a bit.
Yes.
So I'm inside the Jupyter demo
lab and this is the intro file that we created.
And as you can see, again,
I can like create a new code
cell or I can create a new markdown cell here.
So the interface is a bit different.
but you have the understanding
of what is the code cell and the markdown cell.
And for example, I can go
ahead and try to run a cell as well.
But in VS Code, it's capable
to show you the notebook, but to
be able to run the code or
the markdown codes to do the
rendering, you need an additional...
... plugin but if I go
ahead and I actually I guess
I have the plugin already installed
so maybe I can show you so if you
if you don't have the
plugin installed you have to go
here to the plugin tab
the extensions example search for
repeater the reason that it
has been installed is that
actually it wasn't installed but
it wasn't ... it wasn't really
all right you removed it but didn't update
Yes, I didn't close the VS Code.
Yeah, that was the reason.
And the reason is that, so
this is the Jupyter plugin.
And at the moment with
the latest version of VS
Code, the latest version of
Jupyter, which has been updated
two weeks ago, doesn't work.
So in order to be able
to use the Jupyter plugin with
the latest VS Code version, you
have to install a previous
version of Jupyter extension.
So if you haven't updated your VS Code,
go ahead and click on install
so you can install the
latest version of Jupyter extension.
And if you recently updated the VS Code,
you have to install the
previous version of Jupyter.
So to do that, you have
this setting button here.
So you would go here and
then go with the...
and install a specific version
and the 2025.7 for a month
of july would ... would work I
think I I used the one from three weeks ago
and that also worked it's
just the most recent work maybe
okay well then it's better to
go with the two months ago
OK, but maybe before
installing it completely, I can go
back to the code and show you what happens
if you try to install it
without to run the Jupyter
notebook without the extension.
So if I go back here and
if I try to, for example, run this Python code.
... it would suggest that this
is a Jupyter one and it
does it it's not allowed it
cannot run it without the extension
I do I don't use
the recommended version because it
would just install the latest
version so I would cancel this
go back to extension and
then install the previous version
so it's good that I installed it
before so it's already cached
I guess great so if I close
this and I now I try to run this it would ask
for the python kernel in which
I can use the code to find the one
that I created in my
conda environment and now I should
be able to run this guy
it's looking at the connecting to the kernel
And hopefully this should change.
It's a bit long for the
first time to starting the kernel,
but then it should be fine.
It should work.
It usually does, but this
is taking a while.
Yes, let's see.
Oh, well, I mean, we
already saw it running.
Should we just go to the exercise?
Oh, well, actually it's done.
This is already done.
So yeah, that's good.
Okay.
I guess you're a bit behind
the time, but yeah, we can go a bit.
I mean, it's fine.
We actually do have some extra time.
Okay.
So that's good.
So the next part is for
you to start working and
getting some hands-on experience
with the Jupyter Notebooks.
So this would be your
first computational notebook.
And in this exercise, you
are going to calculate the pi.
And...
In order to do that, we
are creating a square, like a
one by one square, and then
we are randomly throwing some darts into it.
And then by calculating the
area of the circle and also
the area of the square, we
are trying to estimate
... the pi ... of course
if you throw more dots ...
if you throw like infinity number
of dots the whole score should be covered
so the pi should be more
accurate so that's the whole
idea behind this exercise I guess
So I guess maybe we can
have 20 minutes or 15 minutes
to do the exercise.
Do you want to show the hint below?
Yes, exactly.
So go ahead and run the
JupyterLab on your time.
But actually, there is a very useful
int here so if I go
back to my Jupyter notebook a JupyterLab
and I would ... start a new launcher
because I want to create a
new file here I would start
the launcher I would create a
new notebook here always remember
to rename your notebook first I
would name it to pi
And in the exercise, we
have this code block that you can copy.
And essentially what it does,
it would create an iframe and
show you this whole page
inside the Jupyter Notebook.
So if I will go here and
copy and paste the code.
And I would run this block of code.
And as you can see, you
see that powerful point of the
Jupyter that I can render HTML5 here directly.
So if you want to follow
the exercise, you don't have
to switch the tabs.
You can just scroll here
and follow the exercise very easily.
OK.
Maybe we can add.
I mean, I think the
instructions are pretty clear.
It's mainly you create a notebook
and then you need to figure out
how to get a Markdown cell and
how to get a Python code cell.
and then copy and paste
the things inside and see how it runs.
So this is more about
the interface than writing the code.
The idea is not that you write the code.
The idea is that you
create the notebook and put the stuff inside.
And if something went wrong,
you can ask the question and
we are here to help.
So yeah, maybe we can
set 15 minutes, [name], or...
I mean, this actually, like
if there's any problems, then it
will take a while.
So I would go with 20 minutes.
20 minutes.
Or let's say until the hour.
So it's 19 minutes now.
Okay.
Good luck with the exercise.
And remember, you can ask
questions in the notebooks.
Not in the notebook, in the...
in the notes, in this
Markdown notes that we have.
You probably can ask questions
in a Jupyter Notebook as well
and get answers, but that's
way more complicated.
But in the sharing discussion,
we would like to discuss it.
It would be possible.
Great.
Good luck with the exercise.
All right.
Bye.
Hello.
Are we live?
I think we are.
And you should be seeing
my screen share now.
So I actually scrolled up
earlier, but then I scrolled back
down for some reason.
Yeah.
So I was meant to show
this picture, which is a good
thing to start with.
Okay.
A number of you have done
with the exercise and nobody else
voted for any of the other options.
So I assume it went relatively well,
but feel free to ask
any further questions if you had any problems.
So I'll essentially do the
exercise here quickly.
So I'm using the JupyterLab
interface we already showed and
using exactly the same features
that we already showed.
Whoops.
What is happening?
Okay.
To save the file, I need to click here,
not press Control and S,
because Control and S will try
to save the website.
So, okay.
So I have this file called Python Notebook.
And I'll just hide this part
of the view, maybe zoom in a little bit.
And then let's scroll down.
So I have already started JupyterLab.
Well, I don't need to do that one.
I want to use this browser.
And then I have done
this, shown this webpage here.
So going into the exercise
itself, let's make a new cell first.
And I need to turn this
cell into a Markdown cell.
Okay.
So it's, I am partly
using this interface because it's not
the one I normally use and
I don't know where things are.
So I will have to also
remember to explain what's happening.
Okay.
So run the Markdown cell and
we get nice title.
and we can paste in
some interesting formulas that explain
what we are doing.
So this is how we calculate the area of,
how we calculate pi from the
area of a circle and the area of a square.
And those are relative to
the probabilities of hitting,
well, the probability of hitting
the square is one, but
the probability of hitting the
circle is relative to the,
area of that circle okay so
then ... we have one more thing
we have the nice image ... I
did not change it into a markdown cell
and this is not proper python code
so it's failing to run it
let's change it to markdown and run it
and by the way ...
now I'm already defaulting to
running it by pressing ctrl and
enter so next time I will press
here but it is the same thing
So the first thing is we
need to import the random
module and the plotting module
to create the plots.
So let's create a new cell again.
And now it's code, so I
don't have to change it.
Okay.
And this is Python code specifically.
I'm confused about what
I'm scrolling because it's the same website.
It's a website in a website.
Okay.
So we'll set number of points.
Let's also take the comment.
Why not?
Okay.
Setting the number of points to 1000.
I think at this point I
will not be scrolling up and down.
I'll just look at the window
on the side, which you do not see.
So I'm here.
So we'll create this or run.
Add the code to actually
create these random points and see
if they are inside the circle.
And run it.
Okay, that didn't take very long.
Then this one creates the plot.
So it takes all of these
coordinates and puts them,
makes them visible on the, or
draws them onto the plot.
Let's run that.
So here is the nice little plot.
And it's only a quarter of the circle,
or quarter of the whole
dartboard here, but it is this
quarter that we show here.
Okay.
And finally this one.
So we compute pi by getting
the fraction of the two areas, or the
estimate of the fraction and
then multiply that by four to get pi.
So here we go.
And that's not exactly pi,
but it's also not the
furthest possible thing away.
So let's run this again, change
add a few more points just to
see if we get a more accurate way.
Still doesn't take you very long,
but this is starting to
look like it's basically completely covered.
Okay.
and also pi is a little bit closer.
Now I'm going to change that,
and then I'm going to talk
to you a little bit about something.
I don't actually know what.
And then I'm going to go, okay, run this.
Wait.
The mistake I was trying to
make, it didn't happen.
Okay.
Now, this is not pi.
So,
This is probably the most
common mistake anybody makes
with Jupyter notebooks, right?
So what did I do wrong?
I changed the number of points,
but then I didn't run
this cell that generates the points.
I didn't refresh the plot either, but then
This depends on the number of
hits and the number of points.
So I changed the number of
points, but I didn't recreate
this number of hits.
So the result is wrong.
My solution is interrupt the
kernel, press stop.
Did it do it?
Okay.
Maybe it did.
And then restart the kernel
and run all cells.
And then you can be sure
that everything is running in order.
Okay.
there we are I made it a lot of dots
so it took a while but
well it's still not great this
is it it's like close ish
but not cool yeah anyway ... so yeah
that is a common mistake
I'm gonna change it back to
the original and ... again run
all cells restart and run all cells yeah so
Yeah, so I just wanted to show
that because it is essentially
the most common mistake people make.
And it is something that I
really had to learn out of.
But it is also a powerful
thing that you can run things out of order.
So you can use it as a scratch pad.
You don't always have to
run the whole thing to get
the result or to change one thing.
But it doesn't remember what the state of
The notebook was after running
cell number three, just remembers
the current state.
And if you change something,
run some code, it changes the current state.
Okay.
So yeah, that is a bit
of a complicated thing.
It can be hard to debug,
but the simplest way to get around it
and avoid debugging it is to
just kill the kernel and
then run everything from the
beginning to the end.
Yeah.
Okay, but that was the
exercise and also it's time for a break.
So let's take a 10 minute
break and see you back here at 18 past the hour.
Yeah, that's all.
Take a walk, stretch your
legs, get some coffee and see you soon.
Bye.
I hope you had a good break.
So I'm, okay, I'm still on
the same page with the exercise.
And we actually have, we
have a full notebook here in
case you are joining us now,
or you were installing the
content environment while we had
the exercise time.
So you can,
You can continue from there or
you can do the exercise
and start listening when you're done.
That's also fine.
One thing I didn't mention is
that, I mean, clearly this
exercise is in Python.
We already mentioned that you
can do, you can use
other languages than Python.
You can use R and Julia
and many others as well.
So there's a list of
supported kernels here.
A kernel is essentially a
way of connecting to a
specific programming language.
and running things from the notebook.
And then yeah, our Markdown and Pluto.jl,
Pluto or Julia is our
other alternatives that are very
similar to Jupyter notebooks.
Okay, but yeah, so the main thing
though from here is we
have essentially packaged the
entire story, the calculation of
the value of pi
And the code that actually
does the calculation, the results,
and all of the reasoning into one file,
like one consistent thing that
we can then send to,
for example, our supervisor or the person
who asked us to do this
exercise for a course or
whatever the situation happens to be.
So that's really useful.
Exactly.
Okay.
Yeah.
Okay, but then there's a downside.
So version control.
And it's not actually that bad.
So Jupyter notebooks are JSON files.
Let's see, can I open this as a text file?
Have I saved it?
No.
I guess you have to rename.
There's this dot here.
It is saved, right?
Yeah, but the kernel is running.
That's why you'd see that.
Yeah.
So, oh, right, that's,
It's showing that there's a kernel.
Okay.
If I name it to JSON,
which is standard for a JSON
file, then I can open it.
And this is not exactly what I wanted to.
I mean, this contains all the
cells and all the data, but
let's do a pure text file.
So we talked about Git a few weeks ago.
a lot and we have used it all the time.
Git is really good with text files.
And this is a text file.
So there's a collection of cells.
It's a list.
There's a cell type, execution
count, which is displayed in the notebook.
There's some metadata and
the data, then there is out
if there is an output, then
this output so okay, somewhere here we have
This is still a plain text output, I think.
That's the image from the
exercise that we imported.
Okay, yes.
So this is an image.
This is not very nice text.
It's actually a binary blob.
But that wasn't actually the
plot that we made.
We finally get to an actual source code.
This is a code cell.
and here we have a code cell.
So the output, this is
source, where's the output?
Okay, here.
3.14.
Okay.
So this is an output.
This is the actual source code.
Interesting that it's not in order.
Is it alphabetical?
Yes, it is.
Okay, it's alphabetical.
That's right.
Okay.
So, I mean, it's text.
You can version control this.
might not be fun to look
through this and try to figure
out what's going on.
And this image here is not
going to look nice if you're
trying to use Git directly.
But it's not that bad.
So let's turn it into a notebook.
It's an IPython notebook.
And open it.
Okay, so...
we have an extension called
nbdime I guess we should yeah
here's a link to it so ...
this is the ... the lesson
page again the lesson materials
so there's an extension called nbdime
that works with JupyterLab and
that allows you to actually
look at this look at
these notebooks properly in a version control
interface.
So I mean, you can go here to the git tab.
And look at this, these are all new files.
So let's make a change.
Or rather than make a
comment first and then make a change.
Okay, there's also a checkpoint
file, which is nice.
Like [name] mentioned earlier,
Okay, and then I want to
make a change to the actual content.
So let's again go and
increase the number of points.
Now if I look at the change.
Okay, I need to click
this button, this with the plus and minus here.
And maybe hide the version control section.
So it looks nice.
And it actually shows you which cell and
what line on that cell and so on.
It doesn't just look like a JSON file.
Then we can also go ahead and execute.
Did I execute this one?
I think so.
Okay.
Whoop, there we have a new image as well.
So if you just look at the text again,
it will just show the entire
binary blob as a difference, which is huge.
If you look at the difference from here,
I didn't save the file.
Okay.
Now, if you look at
the difference from here, it
shows that there's a change here.
There's a change in this
cell, but that's only output.
So there's no actual changes
here in the code itself.
Same here.
Outputs changed.
I guess this doesn't look
that great either, but well,
You can actually see both images here.
If you like zoom out,
maybe it looks better.
I don't know.
Not really.
I'm actually a bit disappointed
by how it looks like right now.
I'm used to it looking much better,
but it shows that the
picture is different and you can
actually see a preview of both images.
So that's much more useful
than just saying the whole
binary blob is different.
And the output, there's an
output here and it's different.
Actually, here is only the
run count that has changed in these two cells.
Okay.
So now we can go ahead and add to this.
So what should we say?
Increase the number of points.
Okay.
Okay, so next, going back
to the materials, should I also
show this in VS Code?
If you look at the
version control interface, if you're
using VS Code, you will see
that the Jupyter extension actually
makes it look nice.
So you can see the differences
in a nice way.
One other thing is GitHub.
So we have been using that a lot as well.
If you haven't done anything
to make it look nice, then
it will not look nice.
So we can go ahead and
look at the notebook.
So this is actually the
example, this is the solution
to the exercise or the notebook
where you can continue from for the next part.
but this is now looking
at the difference between two different comets.
And this is not very useful.
I mean, I see that the
image is different, but it's
not quite, not very nice to read.
So there is a way of,
there's a feature, a feature preview.
So if you click on
your profile, feature preview, there
is this rich,
Jupyter notebook diffs.
If you enable that one, this
has been in beta for, I don't know
how long, or preview for, I
don't know, as long as
CodeRefinery has existed or
something like that.
So when you enable that and
you reload the page, now it
looks quite a bit better.
So here we again have a
better picture of what has changed on this.
cells these code cells but
also the images now actually
display correctly so this is the old image
and this is the new one
after the commit some colors have changed
and the size has changed yeah
okay ... one downside though is that
when git git remembers
everything it remembers all of
the previous versions so if
you keep changing an image or
a video and you commit
those changes, you will keep
actually all of the versions of that video.
And if it's an image, maybe
it's not that bad.
If it's a video and it's a big one,
it might take a lot of
space and take a long time
to then clone the repository or push and pull.
So yeah, that might be then
good to remove the image at
some point, but okay.
It works still pretty well.
So we did this comparing
notebooks locally already.
And there is nbdime from the command line.
I don't know, do I
have actually these commands?
Should we try?
Yeah, but I guess the
audience gets the idea that
Jupyter Notebook works with
version controlling, but there
are some limitations.
You also have to enable
some feature or install a
plugin or something like that.
Yeah, you always essentially
have to install something to make it work.
And for VS Code, it's
the same Jupyter plugin, which is nice.
But it's interesting that for JupyterLab,
you still need to install
something to make it work.
Like it doesn't work out of the box.
Yeah.
Okay.
I guess.
Yeah.
Let's go on.
You can go with the sharing.
Yes.
Yeah.
So, but yeah, I mean,
essentially you probably do want
to enable those features in
whatever editor and interface
you're using, and especially if
you're using GitHub.
Okay, but yeah, then we'll
talk about sharing notebooks.
So we have talked a lot
about sharing code and the
upsides are essentially the same.
But often it is also
useful to specifically share notebooks
for documentation and to show
how to describe how the
process works to generate your paper and so on.
So there's a bunch of ways of doing that.
And the simplest one is to
put it on GitHub or GitLab
or any interface like that and
people can see it.
You can turn it into a
website that looks nicer and it's
a bit easier to access.
Those are essentially static options.
So people cannot edit the code
and they cannot run the code,
but they can see the entire
story and they can see the results.
Those are nice ways of doing it.
But then there's also ways
of sharing it that make
it actually dynamic where you can edit it.
So we already talked about Binder
and we showed you a couple
of notebooks in Binder.
JupyterLab supports sharing via
Google Drive.
Okay.
I'm always surprised by that.
That's a relatively new feature.
And then there's a bunch of other options.
There's JupyterLite and EGI Notebooks
that helped you actually share
a live version of the page or of the notebook.
Okay.
So one option that we might
as well show you rather than
just describe is, so here we have a file cell.
What is happening?
Okay.
So we have the file selected here.
We can export, save and
export notebook as, and then we
can save it as say HTML.
Okay.
This is going into downloads, I guess.
That's fine.
And we can open it.
So, so now this is a,
this is a website that you can send.
You can put this on GitHub
and people can open it on github.io,
or you can just send it to people
and they can open it
without any editors and without
any viewers, because it is just a website.
Okay.
But it's an HTML one,
so you cannot actually run
the Python code, right?
You can just see... Yes, you
cannot run the Python code.
It's purely HTML.
There's also Google Colab, Google
Calc and so on.
These are commercial offers
with free plans, which means
they are by commercial companies.
And yeah, they are also
pretty good options.
So there's a lot of options
and it depends on what you want.
We are going to do this
as an exercise, right?
Yes.
So we're going to have an
exercise where we share a notebook on Binder.
So to do that, though, what
you need to do first is
have a Git repository with a notebook.
So if you didn't already,
there was a button here
to initialize repository.
And then, I mean, if you
were here in the first week,
you know the steps to push
the notebook to GitHub.
And I'm wondering, should I show that?
And how should I show that?
Because I do not have the,
there is no interface for it here.
I don't think you can push it from there.
I can open a terminal.
Yes.
And then I have to
create a GitHub repository.
And here it's important.
So, ... by example, okay.
So here it's important to, first of all,
make it public if you're sharing it
and start with no readme
file, no gitignore and no
license, essentially an empty repository.
And the reason for that is
that we already have files in
this existing git repository.
Actually, we can copy the
commands from here, git remote add.
So we already have files in here.
So if you create any files
in the remote repository, it
will refuse to push.
Okay, so I'm going to do
this step and I probably should
be a bit more explicit.
So this is preparation for
the exercise that you will also need to do,
but I don't think it's 100%
clear on the exercise page.
So you need to have a
Git repository that you push
to GitHub and then you can
do the binder exercise.
And preferably the Git
repository should have a notebook in it.
So the exercise notebook is a
good one to have.
So I made a branch called main.
I'm essentially, I'm just
copying these commands from here
and running them in a terminal.
Another option is to use VS Code.
There you can just publish to GitHub.
There's a button that says
publish to GitHub and that should work.
Okay, so now I have a Git repository
that I can actually push,
where I can actually push
the changes to GitHub.
So if I reload this, I probably have it.
Yes, I have the notebook here.
And that is, so let's go to the exercise.
That is essentially the
starting point here.
So first you create a repository.
And then you need to add some files.
So for Jupyter notebooks, R
notebooks, it's a bit different.
And after that, you should
be able to launch it on Binder.
So the exercise is to do
these steps and to modify
your notebook on Binder.
I definitely shouldn't go any
further in it because then I
would be just doing the exercise.
Is it clear?
Because the reason I'm still
talking is that I feel it's a bit unclear.
I think it's clear.
Yeah.
So follow the instructions here.
And if you have any questions,
then let us know.
The end result is that
your notebook should be on Binder.
It should be online and in such a way
that you can edit it and rerun things
and fiddle around with
things without actually having
Jupyter yourself.
Yeah.
So we'll go for 12
minutes enough because it says,
let's say 15 minutes.
Or 15.
15 minutes, yeah.
So it will be 55.
Okay, 55.
Yeah.
Okay.
Yeah, I guess nobody's
asking questions, so...
Hopefully it's clear enough.
If it's not clear at all,
and that's the reason you're
not asking questions, then let
us know somehow.
And otherwise, see you back
here in 15 minutes.
All right.
Bye.
Welcome back.
Only two people have voted
that they are done with the exercise.
So okay, now this one more vote.
If you have questions, or
if you have trouble, let us know.
But yes, so I think I
will start going through the steps a bit.
already.
Oh, it takes forever to launch.
Okay.
Yes.
It's building the environment for
the first time.
It does take a long time.
let's see how quickly it happens
for me and while I'm doing
this you can also finish the exercise
if you have if you're still
in the middle of it okay
so I'm going to actually move
this window out of the shared
area and we see our my
repository with the notebook in it so
And the first step was to create a file.
So here, create a new file.
It's called requirements.txt.
I should be typing here, requirements.txt.
So this is a relatively
standard way of telling what
Python packages a program needs.
And what we need is matplotlib.
And we're giving a specific version of it.
And this is telling Binder
and other programs also what
Python packages we need.
So there's different formats
for different languages usually.
Okay, let's commit to change.
Create requirements.txt is actually
a very good description.
So let's keep it.
And that is in fact enough
to run it in Binder.
So then I'll open mybinder.org.
We'll move it to this window.
Okay, good.
And I need the repository URL,
which I get by going to
the repository, to the main folder.
And actually it's probably this URL, right?
Actually, not exactly.
Yeah, it's
without the tree and the main.
So it's like this, I think.
We're taking the main branch,
so not writing anything here.
And the file is actually
called pi.ipynb, IPython notebook.
Okay, and that creates this URL.
There's also a badge for readme file.
So we can copy that and
create a readme file.
Create a new file, readme.md.
So markdown, md for markdown,
which is also relatively standard,
at least for GitHub and GitLab.
Okay.
Commit changes.
And again, the description
is actually pretty good.
So the default one, create readme.markdown.
Although the only thing we
added there is this launch binder.
So that actually is this
link essentially or link to this URL.
So we can go ahead and link here.
So now it's actually, I
don't know what's happening here.
But it's essentially creating a,
not exactly a virtual machine, a container.
that can run the notebook and
that then has the requirements,
the Python packages installed that we need.
Okay.
That was surprisingly quick
and it's displaying the notebook nicely.
So let's run all the
cells from beginning to the end.
This might actually, yeah.
Okay.
It didn't work.
This is interesting.
It's also jumping around a bit.
Oh, it's weird.
It jumps around, but...
Okay, that's better.
So it was able to run everything else,
but this one, matplotlib,
the plotting library somehow fails.
I think it's because the
inline thing, or no?
Oh, okay.
This is a new version of NumPy.
So we are using such an
old version of matplotlib.
Let's go back a bit.
Yeah, yes, leave.
So we're using such an
old version of matplotlib that it actually,
the current version of numpy
doesn't work anymore.
So we can try removing the
version and I'll just keep update.requirements.txt.
It is not a good description,
but it's good enough.
Okay.
Somebody used matplotlib 3.10
and it worked.
That's nice.
I'll just try that again and
also then see what's next in the materials.
So there was this optional
exercise about looking at
the activity repository and then
one that mentions Python widgets
or IPy widgets.
So I will actually skip those
and go directly to a section
and the next section.
So
Next section is summary, but
we'll go to examples of
Jupyter features, an optional episode,
and specifically from here,
widgets for interactive data fitting.
So I will, again, move this
out of the screen share.
And now we're in a binder window.
So it's actually here, it's
opening the binder exercise, the result.
So I can try running everything again.
Okay.
And this time it works.
So that's Binder.
It looks exactly the same
as JupyterLab, but the point is
that it's not actually running on my laptop.
So I don't have to
have anything installed to run it.
Anyone can go to this website
and see my notebook and
run it without having to install anything.
It's a very useful way
of sharing your results.
Okay.
So I'll also close this one.
Yes, leave.
And then we'll go to this,
which is for interactive data fitting section.
So this is in Jupyter/examples.
Unless there's some questions.
Okay, no, we're going well.
Doing well.
Okay, so let's create a,
I think a completely new notebook.
Oh, is it widgets or
interactive data fitting?
No, no, no, that it's,
there's a separate part that
introduces widgets and that seems
to come later.
Like are these, or did
I skip something that I was supposed to?
I also get confused.
It should be... There's a
widgets one inside the shell command.
Okay, yes.
So let's go back to
the Jupyter Notebooks main page.
And from there, go to
shell commands, metrics, and widgets.
And here it's relatively close
to the bottom of the page.
Well, actually here, halfway.
So here's the widgets section.
And the link, I will put it in the notes.
No, that's the, okay, widgets here.
Okay, so now it's in the notes.
All right, sorry about that.
We got confused about our own thing.
Okay.
I mean, mainly because widgets
is late in the title of
the page, which I should read the whole thing.
Okay, so I'll create a new notebook.
You can do it from here.
from here, from the launcher,
or you can right click and new notebook.
And it's a Python 3 notebook.
I'll close the extra one.
It's untitled.
Okay.
Let's call it widget.ipynotebook.
And if you're in the
Code Refiner environment, you have
the IPY widget installed.
So this should run.
It works.
Otherwise, you need to install
IPY widgets in your environment.
And then to use the widget,
we need to define a function.
So we'll give a function
with three arguments, X, Y, and S.
And it just returns X, Y, and
S. So it's a very simple function.
But the point is, we will
make a widget that allows you to change those
those arguments.
So we'll use the interact,
which is this one that we imported.
So the interact widget, we
give it the function as a
parameter, and then we give
initial values to the parameters.
So x equals true, y
equals, whoops, equals 1.0, okay,
comma, then s equals hello,
Okay, I managed to write it correctly.
Good.
So now when we run this,
it will give some widgets that
you can use to adjust these parameters.
So X is true.
So it's a Boolean.
It's either yes or no.
And this, by the way, this
part is the result of the function.
So it just returns the parameters.
So it looks like this.
But if you send it a
false, then it returns false.
And otherwise, it returns true.
okay you can this is
a floating point number so you
can change the value and this
one is a string so it gives
you a text box yeah so
essentially the widget is like
instead of like right changing the
code you can play with the pi parameters
and your ... the output
with some widgets and like some
buttons so it essentially it
completely oh it runs the function
with those parameters and then
produces the results.
So you can, yeah, you can show different,
you can allow people to
interact with the code in
a more user-friendly way.
So let's do another example,
because we have a few minutes.
Maybe we can do the pi
one, actually, and, like, increase
the number of the... Yeah.
So this is actually, like,
essentially next in the... Well,
there's a few useful Magix
commands, and then there's the
playing around with the widget.
So I'll essentially copy the
code from there.
So we get the interact.
from widgets and we get
widgets from widgets, API widgets.
We also get random.
Okay, run that.
Actually, we also need matplotlib inline.
We'll put it in a different
cell so that we have this magic command on top.
I don't know if that matters.
It might.
Okay, and then
The rest is creating functions.
Place this one here.
So this is the throw darts, create plot
and run the whole experiments,
which means first throw darts
and then create the plot and
then print the value of pi.
So this is the exercise we just, well,
just did, we did an
hour ago that calculates the value of pi.
So we could run experiments
with a hundred points
or a thousand points and so on.
So people can adjust it here,
but using a widget, it looks nicer.
So we previously used the interact widget,
the interact function, and we
can tell it the number of
points equals give it starting value a hundred.
Okay.
And that gives you a nice widget.
So
Did it actually run though?
I think it got an exception.
And do you have to run that?
Yeah.
OK.
Let's run that again.
Yes.
Because when it got 0, it got divided by 0.
Yeah.
So yeah, that is one of
the points of the exercise, that
there is a value that you
can slide to, but that you shouldn't use.
But it doesn't redo the image, does it?
I'm adding a lot of points
and it's not re-running, re-creating the plot.
Oh, interesting.
Did you restart the kernel already?
Yes, I did.
Restart the kernel.
Restart, run.
Okay.
Well, let's see what happens if
we make it an integer slider.
So this is why we
imported also these widgets because
this gives a
gives us some control of
this number of points value.
So we get integer slider in slider.
And there we can give it
a minimum, let's say minimum is
100 points, we can say max
is what 10,000 points.
And we adjust it in steps of 100.
Yeah,
This is going off the page.
Add some line breaks.
Okay.
And then the starting value
is 1000 and it's again going off the page.
Fine.
It's not going off by that much.
We could also do it like this.
It looks a bit better and
now you can see everything.
Okay.
So when we run this, we
should get a better slider.
Oh, now actually the plot is better.
So you can adjust it.
No.
The plot is not changing.
Oh, OK.
I don't know why.
Weird.
That's weird.
Can you stop the JupyterLab
and start it again?
Maybe that's the... Actually,
so the maximum value in the nodes is 10,000.
That is not going to
solve the plot problem.
Yeah, but I guess it's an
issue with the JupyterLab.
Can you maybe restart that as well?
Restart JupyterLab.
I can do that.
So I have it in a
terminal, so I'll just stop it from there.
Restart.
And it opens a new one.
Okay.
I'll leave the previous one.
And now we have this widget file here.
Okay.
And we can try running everything.
I mean, it's not that
bad if matplotlib doesn't work
perfectly with this, but it would
be nice to see.
There's one comment in the
notes about the inline command.
So restart and run.
Okay, that actually fixes it.
Interesting.
Okay.
Thank you.
So it works better without
the inline plots.
All right.
Okay, so yeah, that's something
to play around with.
That makes these pages
even more interactive and easier to use
for someone that doesn't
actually write Python or any
other, or some other programming
language that you're using.
So there's also rshiny, which
I should, I can display this page.
So rshiny is an alternative
similar to ipyewidgets for R.
notebooks.
And there's a gallery of
examples, nice ideas that you can look at.
There's also other useful things
here to look at.
I didn't actually prepare to
teach or check that they work on my system.
But we do have a bit of extra time,
we probably should just end
early because we don't have
that much extra time.
If you have a very good question
or even not that not such a good question,
but something that's interesting
to ask, then please ask it in the notes.
I will.
Whoops.
What did I do?
Okay.
So I will move on to the summary page.
So in Jupyter Notebooks, we
have a summary page here and
Yeah, there's some recommendations
for longer notebooks.
We have a question regarding
the Jupyter rich diff on GitHub.
Can you show it again?
Yeah.
Oh, so the question is
essentially, can you show it again?
So do we have a good example?
I mean, we probably actually
have just in my own repositories,
the last one should be
the pi_example.
And then let's update requirements.
Py, IPy-notebook, what's updated in this.
Okay.
So now we maybe have a diff of a notebook.
Can you show the feature again to see?
Yeah.
So it was here in feature preview.
There is this rich notebook diff.
So if this is disabled...
and I reload the page, then
the diff of the notebook doesn't look as nice.
Okay, now it doesn't show it at all.
So now it's essentially, it
looks like the diff of the
text that's actually the notebook file.
So it's a text file.
It's a JSON text file.
So it's not that easy
to follow what's happening,
especially the images, again, quite horrible.
Yeah.
Somehow the old image is bigger
than the new one, even though
the new one has more points.
Oh, that was not the right button.
Okay.
So let's go again to click the profile,
go to feature preview, and
here you can enable rich Jupyter notebook diffs.
and then the diffs of
Jupyter notebooks will look a lot better.
Okay, here we are.
So that's a lot clearer.
Okay.
Now...
This is the summary page that
I am already on.
Okay, so let's go through the summary.
For some reason, my doorbell is ringing.
It's ringing twice, so it
might be important, but let's
see what happens.
So, we have talked
about Jupyter, basically.
We've gone through some interesting
and useful features and there's
all sorts of things.
all sorts of details that make it useful.
Like the fact that you can
package it in a single file
and easily send it around.
And also that it shows all
of the results very close to your code.
It's very good for documentation and so on.
And also those same things, partly,
they create some problems, like
the fact that you can execute
the cells out of order,
as things happen, sometimes in
unexpected ways, that are
important to remember.
And I mean, basically, they
will just cause problems, and
you will debug those problems.
And at some point, you will remember that,
oh, well, maybe if I run
it from the beginning to the
end, and hopefully it will work and
It's also very easy to
write a Jupyter notebook, but if
you run it from the beginning
to the end, it will not work.
So it's good to test that
every now and then.
But yeah, then there's a
few, we went through a few
different ways of sharing notebooks and,
well, essentially we showed
the binder thing, but there's
plenty of other options, many different ways
of sharing them and sending them to people.
So yeah, I mean, it's one
of those, it's a very useful way of coding
and sharing code, but it also
has its own downsides, especially
if your code gets longer,
then it's impossible to follow.
So is there anything you want
to bring up specifically?
... I think everything was
everything was fine and ...
the main introduction was
why Jupyter notebooks could be useful
and why in some cases they
are not the best so but the best solution
so yeah yeah okay and of
course it's it's also important
to remember that there's other
options so there's ...
many different notebook alternatives,
even though we only
showed Jupyter notebooks and
for different languages.
And yeah, I mean, this is an example of,
well, partly the kind of
thing I was talking about
where it gets complicated, but
also you can take, when your
code gets long and gets fancy,
You can start taking parts
out of the Jupyter notebook
and putting them into your own module.
And that is essentially how
most modules are born in
scientific coding or scientific software.
So you start writing something
and you notice that it
starts getting complex enough that you want to
actually take functional pieces
and make them independent,
make them modules.
So that's something we'll talk
more about in modular coding,
but that's something that's
very, very important, very useful
for dealing with notebooks.
All right.
Thank you so much, [name]
and [name], for today's session.
I hope everyone who
watched and followed until the
end, got something out of this.
We have added a feedback
section in the very end of the notes.
Maybe [name] can move there and show it.
So if you go to our
notes and then scroll all the
way to the bottom, there's a small section
So next week, we will
actually be talking about automated
testing and the week after
will be modular code development.
So if you have no idea what testing is
and how to run it, and especially
how to run it automatically,
next week is the time and day for that.
That basically means that
You will learn how you
may prevent yourself and others
from breaking your running code.
And we will have examples
in the lesson materials for
many different programming languages.
So even if you don't code
in Python, you might get
something out from that lesson.
And then we are asking,
how was your feeling today
about the speed, about the level
of the lesson and the materials?
Did we go through things
too fast, too slow?
Did it feel too basic,
too advanced, or just right?
And also, do you feel like
you will have use for what
you learned today in your work?
In the very beginning, we
discussed briefly how [name] and
[name] also are using Jupyter
in their daily life as
research software engineers.
And then if you have
any specific things that you
liked about today, please let us know as well.
as well as if you have anything
that you think we should improve
for next time, because we
are running these workshops like twice a year.
So we always are curious on
what we can do better to make it most useful
for you as a researcher so
that you can now go home and
apply what you have learned
to your own workflow.
That is, of course, the wish.
And with that, I think
from our side, everything is said.
Do you have any last words to share here?
Not from my side.
Yeah.
I mean, a lot of this is,
is relatively like, and if
you have already used
Jupyter Notebooks, especially like this is,
this lesson might be relatively low level,
but it is also something
where a good amount of the
mistakes and bugs that happen
actually happen because of Jupyter features.
So it's like when you
actually run into them, it's good that you have
some kind of memory like this
is a thing that I should check.
Yeah.
And also know that the
materials will stay available where they are.
You are very welcome to share
it also with your colleagues or
come back to them later.
And maybe at this time, I
will also add the link to our chat.
So in case you are now
going out to work with these topics
or also other topics from the workshop
and you have any questions or
would like to ask something
more from the instructors, we're
all usually hanging out in
the CodeRefinery Zulip chat where
you are very welcome to join.
We have there one channel
that is called Help where you
can post all your questions and
then you will have some
multitude of people happy to
help you with especially topics
related to the workshop.
All right.
Then unless [name] has anything
else to share at this point,
I think we can close down the
stream and hope to see you all again
next week same time same
place we'll again send an
email with preparations and when
the stream starts and have a good afternoon
or whatever time it is where
you are and rest of the week
see you then bye bye thanks for joining