All right, and live we are.
Hello, everyone.
Welcome to pre-workshop hangout.
Today, only five minutes, but
we are still here.
And let's do maybe a quick sound check.
So we have [name] here
as our streamer today, connecting
from Aalto University.
Then we have [name] and
[name] as our instructors for today.
[name], do you want to
start this audio check?
Yeah.
So I guess we'll count
one, two, three, four.
One.
Two.
Okay.
So order is [name], [name], [name], [name].
One.
Two.
Three.
Four.
Okay.
At least on my screen it looks good.
Sounds fine.
If
someone who's listening on Twitch
can let us know.
That's great.
All right.
Yes, let's take a look
at our notes document.
So for everyone who is here and not
yet familiar with that, it's
what we're showing on screen.
It's what you got via email.
Unfortunately, today, not right
before this stream,
because of technical difficulties,
but you got it like when
you registered to the workshop,
there's a link to the notes document.
And this is what you're
seeing here on screen.
And [name], if you could show
us how this can be edited.
So everyone can find a
little pen symbol either on the
upper left or upper right of the document.
Trying to hide.
Okay.
Now it's visible maybe.
Yes, so for [name], it's on the upper left.
So there is a pen symbol
which brings you into edit mode or
what [name] just clicked is
the both double view or however it is called.
to see both the rendered
version and the edit version.
And if we scroll down there,
now we will have some
icebreaker questions prepared for you.
So you can get used to the document
and get to know a little
bit about each other who is
here all in the workshop.
So first question there is
what programming languages are
you normally working with?
And I will ask that to
our instructors for today.
So what are your
daily programming languages, [name]?
Well, it's mostly Python, I'd say,
and maybe then it's occasionally
some bash for smaller scripting,
but that's mostly it.
Okay.
How about [name]?
Yeah.
So I'm working a lot with
bash in Python in daily work.
Then in some code projects where
I'm one of the main
developers, I'm using Fortran and
also CUDA for GPU programming.
Okay.
So for everyone watching today, know
that you can ask also
questions about these languages today.
And then we have also a
few people working here behind
the scenes and answering questions
in this document.
So this document is also used
for asking questions during the
workshop to our instructors and
our friends behind the scenes.
And you can also, if you
know the answer to some
questions appearing here, you can
of course also answer yourself.
Then we have
Another icebreaker question.
What does testing your code
mean for you and how do you test?
So in your daily life, do you test, [name]?
So well, not in my sort of
work day to day stuff, but
in the in the projects that
I'm doing some more actual programming
that I do test quite a lot.
Yes.
Yeah, I guess we'll talk
more later a little bit
about the different types of
testing that are maybe relevant.
Yeah.
How about [name]?
Yes, I'm
I'm using testing in various contexts,
both for a product where I'm
one of the developers, and also
when I install codes on a
supercomputer at PDC in Stockholm
where I'm working.
Then, yeah, maybe by default,
we run through some test
suites after having built and
installed a program.
Okay.
So we still have one
minute before we're officially
starting to briefly want to
introduce yourself to our
participants, where you are.
Located Where do you work, what
do you work [name].
Yeah, sure.
So I work at CSC at
CSC as a machine learning specialist.
And yeah, so I mostly help
users use our supercomputers, mostly
in the machine learning context,
you know, GPU stuff.
And then I work in
several like research projects, also
in a similar support role, but
kind of a little bit more like
embedded in a in a group
that does the actual research.
Okay, how about [name]?
Yeah, so I work at the PDC Center
for High Performance Computing at
KTH in Stockholm, where we
are currently operating the
largest supercomputer in the country.
And that's a machine named
.del, which has AMD CPUs and GPUs.
So some of you might recognize this
as the similar configuration as
you have on the Lumi supercomputer in Finland.
So it's a lot of commonalities there.
And I have a background
in material science research.
So a lot of the work that
I do at BDC is connecting
to material science simulations and programs.
And related to that, I
am then working quite a
bit with product traditional languages
such as Fortran and C++.
Okay, now we have one minute
after the hour so we can
officially get started here.
Welcome everyone to day
eight of the Code Refinery workshop,
where we'll be talking
and practicing automated testing.
For those of you that have just been here,
we have here with me, [name]
and [name], who will be
the instructors for today.
And also [name] is here doing
the behind the scenes, the streaming
set up for you.
My name is [name].
I'm project manager for Code Refinery
and just briefly here to say
hi and in the very end.
So what I wanted to show
you is first our workshop event page.
[name], if you could switch to that one.
Yes, so hopefully you know
that that's the page where you registered
and here you can find the
link to our lesson materials for today.
If you scroll down,
through the schedule towards
day eight behind the automated
testing name, there's a link to the materials.
And there you can also
find all the questions and
answers from the previous days.
If you go in the upper
navigation bar under questions
and also information about their certificates.
Let's wait a moment for
scrolling all the way up.
Okay, and then let's switch
to our notes document.
That's the main document that
you will need for today.
So this link you got
with the registration to this workshop,
and that will be our
communication channel for today.
So here you can ask questions.
We will in between ask some questions,
how it's going during the
exercises to identify if we need
more or less time for them.
And it's also the place where
you can find our icebreaker.
So when you are clicking the
link in the email to the
notes document, you will find it in view mode.
So that looks something like
what is shown right now on screen to the right.
To go and edit this document,
you can go all the way to
the top of the document and
find the little pen symbol.
It's either up to the right somewhere.
or up to the left where it is
for [name] showing the clicking
right now that brings you into edit mode.
And then you can practice
editing this document with plain
text by adding an O
for the programming language
that you're generally using.
And then also let us know
how you currently do testing.
And yes, we also have
[name] behind the scenes who
is the notes manager.
So there will be headers
appearing during the lesson that
give you the exact links
to the lesson materials where we
are at each moment.
And when there's exercises, you
will put the information on where
you can find the exercise.
Yes, so we will have
two exercise sessions and one break today.
And a quick outro with a
little bit of hints for the
next session as well on
modular code development in the very end.
And with that, I remind you
about the code of conduct.
Everyone here is at a
different level and that's okay.
You can ask questions freely.
You can answer them as well,
but please be nice and
considerate with each other.
And with that, I'll give over to [name]
for starting today's automated
testing session.
Over to you.
Yes.
Thank you.
Thank you very much, [name].
So just briefly mentioning that
when you're not actively editing
in the shared collaborative notes,
then please press this view
button here because that then
reduces a little bit
the load on the server
side of the document.
So I will now go into
the automated testing lesson here and I'll
With me here for this lesson,
I have [name] from CSE.
Hi, [name].
Hey.
So automated testing is on the schedule.
And yeah, we have already here in the...
in the icebreaker questions, got
all of you participants to think
a little bit on what testing can be about.
So perhaps if I start with you, [name],
so what would you say
are the relevant cases for
using software testing?
Well, for me, I'd say there
are, I guess, several aspects to it.
First would be if I
implement a new feature, I would
want that to work as expected.
So I make sure that it does with tests.
And then I also want to make sure
that I haven't broken anything
that already exists.
So I'm going to test that.
And I guess slightly related
to the first point is if you
start with a test or start thinking about
how you test things, then it
helps you also think about how
you want to organize your code
or how you want to develop the
code in the first place.
Yeah, thanks.
Those are all very relevant points.
And I think in particular,
the last thing you said is
that if you have testing in
mind while designing and implementing code,
then that's a good mechanism
to guide you when you write
the code in the first place.
Here are in less material here
or also some statements here.
So a very common thing is
that you do not start from scratch.
You are perhaps you're downloading
to try out some new code
and you find, oh, this is relevant for me.
And you might then need one
or two more features which are not available.
And you would like them to implement it.
And then it's very good if
you can soon establish that, okay,
this code is working.
It's working on my machine.
And if I now go ahead
and implement a feature A and a feature B,
then this will not interfere
with the already existing functionality.
Okay.
So during this lesson here,
we will have some demonstrations
and there will also be
exercises for the exercises.
we encourage you to work
primarily with python and within
the code refinery conda environment
you have a tool pi test available
and that's a framework
for performing testing working
with python code bases there are similar
type of tools available for
other languages there are also tools
which are language agnostics that
can be used then for
for different languages and yeah
we will highlight a few of
these during the lesson
so one aspect of testing
is that maybe we're working
here with software and computing um
i can draw a little bit of
an analog to testing in in
the context of measurements
using physical devices those
could be mechanical measurements
could be electronic measurements
and within scientific research you could
it's clear that if you're, for instance,
in the physical sciences and
you have some detectors of, yeah,
that could be velocities,
could be positioning, if you
have a mechanical problem,
and could be, for instance,
in condensed matter physics or
chemistry, it could be measurements
of photo emission spectra and so forth.
And it's very important there
that you establish a base
case and to calibrate your detectors.
And where you are then in a regime
where you can be on firm
ground and perhaps have some
reference data also.
Once you have that, you can
then move into using your instrument,
be it a physical instrument or
be it a scientific code,
and then have reasonable confidence
in that your tool will do the
job also in this new situation.
And [name], what do you say?
Can one arrive to, let's
say, 100% confidence that things will work?
I would say no.
Because, well, the person who
wrote the tests, they also
had certain constraints.
For example, they were using
definitely a different or very
likely a different machine than
what you're using.
So they sort of all of
the sort of assurances they could
make are done through a specific
lens that may not sort
of completely overlap with your situation.
Yeah, precisely.
That's something that relates
to the concept.
It is known as code coverage.
We are trying to make a
code... Okay, in our sense,
code coverage would have...
is how much of the code base is tested.
But here also this, that how
much the tests will cover
the functionality of a code
and various use cases and various edge cases.
Yeah, and I'd say like coverage
is a useful metric, but
it's not infinitely strongly
correlated with those sort of safety
or security or like confidence
that all of the code works
entirely as you would want it to.
But yeah, it's a start.
Yeah, yeah, right.
So here we have some examples
here in the lesson materials with some papers.
And I think this one here,
this you can check out here.
A scientist's nightmare.
Software problem leads to five retractions.
And that's quite interesting story.
So in brief, what happened here is
that some scripts were used
on different operating systems.
And when...
The original developer of the
tool had been running for his or hers computer.
Things were all working.
Then the code was being used
also by others and they
had other computers, other operating systems.
And some of the unexpected
things happened then.
So the way that the
program executed was not as intended.
And in this case, this
had rather severe consequences
because many people were using
this for over many years without noticing.
Have you ever experienced
something similar?
Or were you lucky?
No, not of that type, no.
That could rather be... My experience of...
of things going wrong with, I mean,
in connection to testing
would perhaps rather be that
the functionality that was implemented
in a program written by me
and my colleagues that perhaps
you didn't implement what you
had intended to implement.
So yeah, for us working
with physical models that would simply be that
We did not implement
the mathematical expressions as formulated.
It is also something that can be tested.
We will come very soon here
to various kind of tests.
And I would say here, this
that I then encountered is that
we have complex numerical modeling where
I mean, naturally, you do
this on the computer because you
cannot do it with pen and paper and by hand.
Then if you can test and verify
that for the very small problems
where your calculation is of
a small problem size, you can
perhaps do it with pen and paper.
If you can then establish
that these are correct or things
are, let's say you get it to a zero result
or something is invariant,
doesn't change over time, then
you can incrementally increase
the problem size going to
the real problems and you can
then build up this confidence
that your code will do the job.
But yet here, this is also a regime where
you cannot really arrive to
the, like the full 100% confidence
is sort of an asymptotic.
But it might be that
you cannot compare things because
you don't have a full reference case.
Okay.
So we can start here by example here.
So
We have a small snippet here of code.
This is here about
conversion of temperature from
the Fahrenheit to the
Celsius temperature scale.
As you can see here,
there are multiple tabs for
Python, C++, and also other languages.
And this now will illustrate
use of the PyTest framework.
So I'll copy this code here.
You have a copy button up
to the right here.
And I call this source
code file Fahrenheit.py.
Copy and save.
And
And now I just run it.
PyTest.
So I gave no arguments here.
So what happened here is
that PyTest have looked here
in this directory and it has
picked up here in this source
code file a function definition
which starts with test underscore
and then Fahrenheit to Celsius.
So it will then
Execute this function.
And what you can see here
is that here is defined
an expected result, 37.7.
This temporary variable C here
is assigned from the call of this function,
where you call the function
with 100 degrees Fahrenheit.
And here, within here,
Fahrenheit to certain function, you
have the conversion then
from Fahrenheit to Celsius,
according to this formula.
In this test function, you
use an assert statement that
the absolute value of the
difference between the obtained
result from the function call
and the expected result should be
less than one part per million.
And yeah, indeed, that is what
came out and executed this function.
So all are good here.
So what can tests help you do?
I think we already touched
upon that right in the beginning of the lesson.
So preserving expected functionality,
You can help users to be confident
that the program has
been installed correctly and that
it is working.
You give developers, and that
can be yourself or could
be external people, the ability to
start out from something that
you know is working and then
you can add on features and
then you can check also that
the new stuff are not
breaking the already existing functionality.
So discussion, when would you say
that it's not really needed
to add the tests, [name]?
Sorry, come again.
I was looking at the document.
Yeah, okay.
So in what situations would
you say it's not necessary to
do any explicit tests?
So, well, there are also
some examples given here.
So since I mostly work in machine learning,
there are some things that
are difficult or impossible to test.
So testing an entire neural network,
That's kind of difficult because
it's kind of stochastic and it's a black box.
So, yeah, there I would say I don't bother.
Then I focus more on things
that I can test well, like if
I implement a new metric, for
example, that then evaluates that model.
But
Yeah, that's one thing, things
that are difficult to test.
For the example, things that
are sort of obviously correct, I
would say it's still very often,
it can be good to write a test.
maybe it's not very high
priority, but still, it can be
useful to do that.
Because, well, I generally
don't trust myself very much.
So I think it's still useful
to, to write the test a to make sure
that you the code is correct,
but also to make sure that
you were sort of thinking correctly.
Yeah, that's a good point.
And when it comes to this with so
It can happen that one thinks that,
okay, testing, that brings a
lot of overhead.
And let's say that the
code you're working with is 10
lines of code, but the test
stuff would be 30 lines of code.
That seems like a rather
expensive and time-consuming thing.
However, it depends a little bit on...
workflow that that you get up
and started with because with pi test
and we'll also see a
program here called catch2 for c++
code then i mean you do
have this machinery implemented and
you can then relatively quickly
set up new tests and also to
run them in in a quasi-automated manner
So I really like PyTest in
part because it does not
give you much overhead.
You saw earlier, you just
wrote a function that did the thing
and you did not even
import anything from PyTest or anything.
You just wrote a code that
called what you were doing.
And that's it.
And you made an assertion,
which is also not really part of PyTest.
It's just normal Python code.
And yeah, that's why I
really like PyTest in that sense.
I prefer it over the other
testing suits in Python and also
for most other languages where
I'm aware of any.
Yeah, indeed.
It's neat that it's readily
available and sort of not
difficult to install.
So we will soon move
into the first exercise.
However, before doing so, we
will go through here rather briefly,
but go through the various
kind of tests and testing concepts
that are out there.
And this nomenclature can be
good to be acquainted with,
because otherwise you might
misunderstand what tests are
actually being run for a code.
So UNIS tests, those are
tests when you test a function at a time.
This can be...
good to work with when you
are starting to write a
whole program from scratch
or individual modules of a
program from scratch, because then
you can implement the tests one
at a time, or let's say
perhaps multiple tests at a time.
And this Fahrenheit to Celsius
code snippet is an example of
that where this small test case was,
We can presume that that
was written right after defining the function.
So you do it as you go.
Integrating tests are when you test
how the part of the
program is working together.
So let's say you have like
10 big building blocks in your program.
You might want to see them
do this three times.
blocks, column A, B, C,
do they work together as they
should with the API, that
everything is matching with data types
and so forth, and also
then that the intended execution
is proceeding as intended.
M2M tests, that would, and
here certainly it depends a bit
on what kind of program you're working with.
But it could be that that will involve,
so to say, the whole code base,
or that it would, in any
case, do some things, so to
say, from the very start to the very end.
And I'd say that this is something which,
if you have, let's say,
in scientific computing, numerical modeling,
some use cases where you, let's say,
you start with a set of input files
and then you crank it with
a program and you get a set of output files.
That situation is something
that lends itself very natural
for end-to-end tests.
If you, on the other
hand, have something which is
more, let's say, event driven
or user interaction type of program,
then it could be perhaps
much more challenging actually to
set up end-to-end tests
that are representative for how
the program is used.
Regression tests are something
that relates a bit to end-to-end tests.
So what is rather common is
that you set up some reference
cases where you are then
confident that, okay, the program
did for given input produce the right results.
And perhaps the confidence in
these right results are both
in that the program was, I
mean, written in a correct manner,
but also that you compare with, let's say,
completely other programs that
are perhaps implementing
similar functionality.
That could be, so to
say, perhaps among your colleagues
or the science community could
be also from your, let's
say, rival research group that are
trying to do similar stuff also.
So these were a few of them.
Then we have test-driven development.
And [name], what can that be about?
So, well, normally you maybe
just start thinking about your
fantabulous new software that you
want to write.
and maybe don't think as much about
how that all of that
that what you're writing is
actually being used and
test-driven development is one way
where you can try and sort of invert
that where you first think about
how it's used because you
first write the test that
uses the software that you're
about to write and yeah then
sort of continue developing that
and continue testing it until the test
passes.
Yeah, that can be a
useful approach for some problems.
It's certainly not a universal
solution to all problems.
But yeah, it can be
an interesting approach to have
a different sort of viewpoint on
how to make software.
Yeah.
that's um yeah indeed and
and um sometimes and and uh if
if some of you in the
audience here perhaps you're working
at uh private companies and and um
What we can often see is,
I mean, comparing a little bit
the situation in academia and
in corporate settings, you often have,
I mean, you have larger
teams in companies and
test-driven development is sometimes,
I know it from my own
experience, where we have in
a unit or department where
you have some engineers who are
Really, for instance, they
write the specifications for some
program, and then they also write the tests.
And these people themselves
will perhaps not then work for the code base,
but that will then be done
by other members of the team.
So this is, I mean, it's clear here.
If you want to do all
of these various things, all
kind of different tests, it helps
if you are a large team.
But I guess usually in a scientific, well,
maybe it depends a little bit
more on the context, but as a PhD student,
for example, then you are
probably mostly writing or like
working on your own.
And then you are the same person
who writes the test will
also write the code itself oftentimes.
Yeah, yeah, indeed.
Great.
So continuous integration, code coverage,
we will come to that a
bit later and we'll define what these are then.
So I think now, in the interest of time,
that we will move now into
what will be the first exercise for today.
So we go here to the
next section of the lesson here.
So what you will do here
is that you will get some
hands-on practice on testing
some functions locally.
And testing locally is, I would say,
that's sort of the base case
where you can do everything
on your local computer.
Then in, so to say, real
life, you will often then do
testing on various services such
as GitHub and GitLab.
so we will just very
briefly introduce the exercise and
and perhaps um have some posted
it into the share document yes
i see the link is here and
there are two tests here testing
um local one and local two
and then the suggestion is that
you can get started with
this minimal example, local one.
And some of you might be
able to do it rather swiftly,
and then you can move on to the other example.
So the instructions can be
found here in the lesson material,
and you will be using PyTests.
And you will work both with
a code that will pass the test and with tests
that limit code that break the tests.
So are there any more
instructions that we would like
to give [name] or?
Well, yeah.
So implement the function,
implement the test for the function.
The function is adding two
numbers together or two anythings,
two Python objects.
And yeah, then test it.
Not much more to it, I think.
And then for the other
one, what's important is that you
are now, so the function is the same.
You're adding a new test
for what happens if you try
and add floating point numbers.
There might be something,
some special considerations, but yeah.
Yes, indeed, that adds
some extra complications to it
that one will need to deal with.
So with that, you are then
welcome to start up the exercise.
And it's now 34 past the full hour.
So we will reconvene here at
54 past the full hour.
Bye for now.
Welcome back, everyone.
so we hope that you have
now been able to to work
work through the first exercise
and perhaps also the second one
so there are a few questions
that were posed in the
collaborative document and we would
like to highlight some of of
them and yeah first one here is about
how to avoid that the
execution of the tests will not interrupt.
And so a good practice is
to put each assert in its own test function.
I think this might depend also
a bit on which testing
framework that you're using that
might also be language specific.
So second question here is
about testing in, yeah, for
machine learning, deep learning models.
So, yeah, okay, one thing
to learn from this,
discussion here the question and
answer is that um for something
like like a big deep learning model
that can take a long time
to train you might want to do the testing
for so to say smaller cases
and and it might be that
it's just too expensive if you
need to to run the
the full training and then
validation with test data.
It's not just a problem of expense,
but also the model sort
of, it's a statistical problem usually.
And so, or it's, yeah, you don't have like,
it's often not sort of
deterministic in the sense that
when you train a model twice,
it will not give you the
exact same answer probably.
And so that is then difficult to check.
Even more difficult, well, you've
done the exercise now for
your floating point numbers, it's
even more difficult then for
the floating point numbers.
Because if you have a language model,
comparing two sentences that
it produced can be tricky.
Yeah.
At least in the context of testing.
Yes, yes, indeed.
Yeah, and the question number
five here, how the testing works.
And the key here is that
you need to check up on what,
or let's say, the keyword
constructs in the respective framework.
So for PyTest, it's test underscore.
And sometimes you need to...
use some other construct to and
or to regular start the
tests with with macros so uh
yeah you you simply um need to follow
that syntax and and we will
see a bit later here one example
of how that is done with uh
catch two for c plus plus code snippets
So we will now proceed to
talk a bit about automated testing.
So the outset here is that
we would like to explore how
we could implement automated testing
that will run, for instance,
on each time that we push
changes to a repository.
And yeah, here's a little
bit of question that we can keep in mind.
So why is it good to
auto close issues with commit messages?
And yeah, you will see that in a minute.
So this part now will be
run as a demonstration and we
will then make use of
the so-called GitHub actions
There's also the GitLab
continuous integration framework.
And in addition to these
services, there are multiple of these around.
So what I will do now is
that I will set up a new
Git repository with some starting coding.
And I will configure tests to
be run as a GitHub action.
We will see that this
code will contain some bugs.
We will not notice it at first,
but when we start to run, let's say,
all parts of the code, you'll
see that, oh, here's something
which is not working.
And that will then be caught
by the tests being run on GitHub.
What one then can do is,
and this is also very important
in the context of
collaborative code development, is
that, I mean, you make a note
of it so that you don't forget it.
And one inbuilt functionality to do
that here is to use
the GitHub issues functionality.
So report a bug as an issue.
then someone that can be yourself
or could be one of your
your colleagues can spot this issue
and work out and okay how
can i fix this and then go ahead and fix it
and then contribute this fix
in a feature bronze and and and
you push it to the github repo
And as you will see then, if
I set up this automated testing machinery
as a GitHub action, then the
tests will be run directly after pushing
so that this, so to say,
the code fix will then be
tested to see whether it
actually then have resolved the bug.
And if that is affirmative,
then one can then go ahead
and merge in this new code.
And you have the answer to
say, improve the program by
correcting the bike.
So let's get started.
So I will go to my GitHub and I will
Now I have already a copy of this,
but I'll create another
example here, another repo.
So I call this repo example
dash ci for continuous integration.
It's a public repo.
And yeah, I just go with the defaults.
And here is, yeah, SSH URL for cloning it.
So I copy the URL.
Then I go here and I clone it.
and here in the terminal
window it reports an oh you
have cloned a empty repository
but that's perfectly fine so i
see it into the directory does
only include the dot git directory
So here are the code
snippets that we'll work with, and
these are in Python.
So in this file, functions.py,
we have some simple arithmetic functions.
So I create this source
code file, functions.py, paste the
code, save it.
Then we will have another
code snippet, test underscore functions.
And here is where we
have then the definition of the tests.
So I'll put that in
another source code file,
test underscore functions, py.
I paste it and save it.
And as you can see here,
this red block here is Python code,
which has been commented out
and that we will activate later.
Let's see.
The git status is that we
have two new files here, which
are untracked so far.
We will add them.
Get add functions.
Get add test functions.
I call this added functions.
And tests.
Commit.
And push.
So, okay, now I already
contributed this to the instance
of the Git repo on GitHub.
We could also then, independent
of this one, we can test the code locally.
So PyTest.
Let's see what it finds.
Yeah, okay.
It goes into the
test.FindChainSourceCode file, picks up
these test definitions and executes them.
So one test was executed and
that one test passed.
So now we will enable automated testing.
So I will now go, as you
can see, there are tabs here for
how to do that on various platforms.
So also for GitLab and for, yeah,
and for GitHub and for
R. The most straightforward thing is
to use the GUI.
So what I'll do when I go
to my GitHub page is to
click this Python applications button.
So I'll do that.
Go to actions.
Scroll down a bit and
then press the configure button.
Now there are a few things here that,
yeah, as you can see here,
what is coming up here as
a template is this within the .github
and workflows directory is
then templated here, a YAML
file, Python dash app.
In the lesson material,
we have some stuff that we
would like to add in here.
So I will copy in those lines of code from,
I do it from another window,
not shown here on the stream.
So I will here put
these permissions here, contents read,
and I add a line here, pulled.
Request.
Write.
So what this YAML file is about is
that it's in a, yeah,
within this YAML format, it
is a specification on what actions
that are to be run automatically.
Another thing we need to add
is we would like to augment here.
So after this pip
install flake8-pytest, we'll also
then add pytest-coverage.cout.
And I think there was
earlier a question about how
to measure coverage and this is a
way to do it sort of automatically.
There's existing tools and you
don't need to worry about that yourself.
Yes.
That's right.
So there are these tools that
can do it for you.
But obviously it's also
good if you bring in also
your your own insights into what
things are the most important to test
because I think the the
coverage testing here is um
simply keeping track of how
which lines of code are
being touched while executing the
tests so it's sort of a metric with this
Yeah, it's simply telling you
in terms of lines of code
where you have been traversed
by using the runway test,
but doesn't say anything about
how, let's say central or this
part of the code for the
functionality of the program.
Okay.
Then I add here at the
end, this coverage report thingy and
Yes, I think we are done with that.
Now I, in order to see
the commit button here, I need
to just increase the size temporarily here.
Now you don't see it on stream,
but I commit the changes
with the default commit message
and I commit directly to the main branch.
So I now resize the window back.
And yeah, so what we see now is
that in the last commit message
is that we created this python-app.yml file.
And here, this little status
symbol here, where it says that the tests are
or some action is pending
it's here just like red brownish color
and if we rephrase reload
the page let's see what happens ah okay
so here we have we have
a green little hook here and
yeah it tells us success here
that's a good thing
This was step four here
in the lesson material.
Verify that the tests
have automatically been run.
So now we will start with...
So now we have the base set up here.
And this last thing, we did
it on the GitHub instance
of the Git repository.
So we don't have it locally yet.
So I go to my terminal and I type git pull.
So now, yeah, this python-app.yaml
file was then pulled in here.
So now we have it here also.
So...
We will now look into
this test underscore functions file.
So we already had, so here, uh, yeah,
I removed the, the, the
Python highlighting app is to
have more clear colors on the, on the screen.
Uh,
There is here definitions
for further tests.
So now for a start, we
remove the comments here so that
you have a test definition
also to test subtraction.
We save this.
And git status.
Yeah, we have changed this file.
We add it.
And then write in the
commit message, added test or subtraction.
Save.
Push.
Then let's go to the GitHub page.
Reload.
So latest commit added test of subtraction.
It's pending.
And yeah, this, this one
should be fast, but yeah.
Okay.
Now it's wrong.
And now we can see it.
There's a, it's a red X here.
So press that one.
And yeah, all tests have failed.
Click details.
And here you can see.
So we have, yeah, the
assertion was that the test would yield
that it would return minus one.
However, we obtained five.
So it was therefore not fulfilled.
Okay.
We could have obtained that
also locally with PyChess, but now
we did it here on GitHub.
So go back here to the
main page for the repo on GitHub,
and then go to issues.
Then create a new issue.
And right then, subtraction is
not working properly.
And then I create it.
OK.
So in this case, I think
I already spotted in the code
where it goes wrong.
Let's presume now that I'm stuck here.
I need help from someone
and I've spotted the error and
I reported it as an issue.
And now, yeah, my colleague
[name] will see what he could do about it.
[name], could you switch to my screen?
Thank you.
Well, that's not quite right, I think.
Yeah, there you go.
So I just, I forked the repository.
I guess I should sync it.
I'm probably a little bit
behind because I did it earlier.
So let's do that.
And here we go.
And then I, well, I also already, so
OK, so now I have
everything locally that [name] has.
Let's run the tests again locally.
Of course, one should, of
course, do that as well.
Let's check now again.
Oh, yeah, so we see tests have failed.
Why might that be?
And I can look at the test.
So I can see the test makes sense.
2 minus 3 should indeed be minus 1.
Then look at the code that
is being run, maybe.
Subtract.
So, oh, this is a plus 2.
I found the mistake.
So I've
made a change.
So let's run the test again.
And now it passes.
Hooray.
Then let's add our change and commit.
Now, what should I write
as a commit message here?
It's a moment here.
So now, which branch are you
in for the moment?
So I'm, I believe, still
in the main branch.
Yeah.
But I am... Yeah, I guess
I could have made a branch for that fix.
But I am on my own fork.
So I'm not on... Yes.
Yeah, yeah.
Right, right.
Yes.
Yeah.
So I could not directly
commit to [name]'s repository.
But since it's my own copy of it, I can.
Yeah.
So, well, I'm about to do
that, but first I would need
to commit my changes.
So, yeah, fixed subtraction, I guess.
Should I write something about
that I fixed an issue or
should I put that in the pull request message?
So, I mean, here you tested
it locally and you saw that it worked.
So then I'd say,
I mean, you could go ahead now
and write then with the,
yeah, with the square, square
symbol fixes and then number
one, because it was issue number one.
Okay.
the most important one all right yeah
so yeah so this fixes uh or closes
or close and then probably
an hour issue we'll do some
magic then on github
let's switch to back to github
and we can see here uh
when i cloned the when i
forked the repository it also copied um
for example all of those github actions
so you don't need to
reset them just because uh
you've walked something and they
are they come with your fork
yeah because those that the ml
file is included in the github
Yeah.
And so you can also see the nice thing is,
well, I wouldn't have had
to remember to locally test anything.
If I push it, it gets tested automatically.
You don't need to, you set it
once and then you kind of
forget about it because then
whenever a test fails, you
would probably get an email from GitHub.
Yes.
Yeah.
You're right.
So see, we can see success tests have, uh,
Completed.
Yeah, it seems to look fine.
And now I, of course, want
to make a pull request to
contribute back to the original repository.
Where is that?
Do I have to be taller?
contribute maybe open pull request.
Sorry, you probably don't see that.
Let's come back.
I guess this, yeah, we will
just use the commit message as the title.
I don't think we need anything further.
And then yeah, we create the pull request.
And yeah, let's switch back
to [name]'s screen.
So we now see the repo on my GitHub.
And I press refresh.
and uh okay it didn't throw up like
that but uh with the color
but i can see here yeah issues
we have one still then here
pull requests one i click here
and yeah then i'll see it
fix subtraction fixes error number
one or issue number one and uh
maybe old but i say pound once yeah okay
uh, prove the workflows to run like this.
Um, so they actually, you see here,
there, there, there are a
few tests being run here.
So, um, what's running here,
but that's the, the spice test
stuff that was, that we had
set up with the actions.
Uh, then here, um, Oh,
What happened there?
Okay.
Well, if you look on this part here,
So the test case for
addition and subtraction, each
of these passed.
So that thing is fine.
But now here's for the Calvert thing.
Something is not working here.
Then I don't know what we are missing.
Yeah, if you spot something,
you're very welcome to write
in the shared document.
But so the coverage report...
Well, at least there are no conflicts.
That's good news.
Yeah, perhaps there was some
typo when I added it in the Jaml file.
I actually think that...
I think right now is not
the time to error check for
where it goes wrong, but I
would presume it was in the YAML file.
But we can observe here that
we have no conflicts with the base bronze.
And therefore, I feel, so to
say, happy to merge this.
Confirm the merge, and then
the code is merged.
And now refreshing here, we can see
that both the issue and
the pull requests are, I mean,
we don't have any open on these.
And I actually say, what happened now,
okay, we don't know specifically
what went wrong here with
the coverage thingy, but I
say that something like this
is happening not so seldom, I would say.
In the sense, you have
the testing in place, but you
don't have clean termination of everything.
and uh yeah i do think of course
if you have clean termination
of all the tests but if
something happens like this here
then uh yeah perhaps you
could nevertheless go ahead and merge
as long as you know what
you're doing and then you might
then get back to it and then next day um
great um we could perhaps we
will have a break shortly and
and perhaps then then we could revisit
what happened and and get back
to you on that point later
but now it's high time that
we will have the break and
it's let's see how much time
I think originally it was 10 minutes.
Yes.
So let's go for that.
It's now 28 past the full hour.
So then let's reconvene at
38 after the full hour.
Bye.
Welcome back after the break.
So right before we went into the break,
we noticed that this automated
test for my Gitria, that it failed.
Turned out that just refreshing
the web page and to look on
the test being run then after
the merge of the code,
then everything was smooth.
So what might have happened is simply
that it failed on this
particular instance when it ran
the tests at first.
And it can be good to be
aware of that this can happen.
so with that i think we
can conclude the part on automated testing
and we will now move into test design
so [name] please go ahead yeah
so this comes also with
an exercise that's uh which you
will also spend uh at least
well say 20 minutes with um it's mostly about
So different types, like
different scenarios.
There are different kinds of functions
and classes or general code
that you might want to test.
And yeah, we have in
total 10 different scenarios that
you can look at.
The first five or so are
sort of on the simpler side.
And the later ones are a bit more complex.
So I would recommend during
the exercise that you start with
a simple one and then maybe
go into the more complex ones
when you've done a simpler one.
Yeah, so there are, I
won't maybe go through all of
the ones, but yeah.
So the first one is just simple.
Number comes in, number goes out.
with a mathematical function, essentially.
Then the second one would
be like on strings and a number.
So for example, counting words,
then you have files.
So files are always interesting.
Then we have, I believe,
random, oh, no, this is external dependency.
So this is for something
when you imagine the code
that you're writing interfaces with
some kind of hardware, for
example, a sensor that is
not present necessarily while you're testing.
So you'd have to find some
way around still testing your
software or your code, even
when that hardware is not present.
Then you have something mutable,
so you can have side effects
and you have to make
sure everything still works as expected.
Then the more complex ones start.
I won't go through all of them,
but there's also some random
numbers and some more interesting
things to explore.
And yeah, if you have
any questions, then just reach
out in the collaborative document.
And I'd say then, yeah,
start with the exercises.
You have 20 minutes from now.
And yeah, so it's 42 past
the full hour now.
So we'll see you two past
the next full hour.
Have fun.
Bye.
Welcome back.
I think that's the wrong.
Yes, the screen share is wrong.
Sorry.
Okay.
Yeah, thanks.
Yeah, welcome back.
So, yeah, there were two questions.
I think we'll get to them
for the second one.
Generally, well, the testing
frameworks provide facilities for
that usually, but you can,
in Python at least, also
just handle the exception that
you're expecting and not any
of the other ones.
That would...
At least should achieve that
what you're looking for.
But yeah, let's go on
since we're already quite late.
So next would be, we'll maybe go back.
So because for now, until
now, we've mostly talked about
Python and PyTest.
And we promised that we would
also at least take a brief
look at some other frameworks.
So yeah, let's look at C++.
And we'll be using catch2.
So yeah, we are going back
to this example where we're trying
to add two numbers.
And yeah, let's look at how that works.
Right.
So I have this minimal example.
The example is, yeah, you can,
I won't type it out again, but
so we need to include these
macros that Catch2 provides, like so.
Then there is most of, so
this here is the actual,
function that we're implementing
so it takes a number and
a number could be yeah different things
and then yeah the function name
and we add them together like so
And after that comes our test case.
So we have this, well,
here, the integer test.
Maybe, [name], you can maybe
explain what does this add in square brackets?
What does that do?
Yes, I think...
Yeah, good question.
I don't know if it's a label
or if it's a keyword here.
Yeah, so add this also here,
the name of the function that we have defined.
And then here in the test
case, we have the int test.
I mean, that's int for integer.
Yeah.
Yeah, but so test case, in any case,
is a macro that is provided
by this include statement.
And this requires also, comes
out of that include.
And yeah, so whatever's in there
is just a sort of parameter to this macro.
um and in this require we
then call our function with some parameters
and it works very similar
to this assert that you saw earlier
in um in uh pi test so
that's that's our code and then
um catch two is very integrated
with cmake um so we're not
sure how familiar you are with
cmake i'm i'm not very familiar with it i
tend to avoid those kinds of things.
And in Python, you don't
really need them usually.
But yeah, so CMake is
in the broadest terms, I guess
we could call it a build system.
So you can use it, especially
for compiled languages to build
and sort of build the binaries or
Well, it's a bit more powerful
than that, but you can sort
of use it to take your
code and generate something from it.
And in our case, so most of the time,
that's just compiling it to
the binaries that you can then execute,
but you can also use it
when you're in conjunction with
Catch-2 to run tests, for example.
And so this is how the...
our CMakeLists file would look like.
So this is the description
of the project and what is
supposed to happen when you, how
you build it and whatever that means.
So first is some sort of preamble.
And then what we're doing here
is we tell CMake to download Catch2.
And so you don't need to
sort of install it yourself first,
which I have also done, but
it's not sort of strictly necessary
because you can sort of put
that in there and then CMake
will do that for you.
Then we do, so this part
down here, that is also
basically provided or sort of
Catch tool understands this.
So enable testing, then we
add an executable, which, so
this is example here.
It will also tell that
to compile that executable.
And then example CPP is the
source code for that executable.
And then you have to
link the libraries from catch to
that you would need to run the tests
and sort of do all of the things
that the testing that, for
example, in the in the other
scenario, or in the other lab
for the other other language pi
test would do and
Yeah, then we would need it
to catch to how it finds
the test that we're running.
So now, how does one actually run that?
So you can see in the description here.
You run the test, that's a
little bit more complicated again.
In Python, you just run pytest.
For catch2, you would need to run this.
So, and again, I'm not
too familiar with CMAC.
So this will kind of prepare
all of the stuff that is
just there for the testing.
itself.
And now in order to
compile the actual executable
binaries, like so.
And that takes already, I
think, unbearably long.
Why is that?
Why does it take long time here?
Because our code is very short.
Yeah, well, I would suspect
that our code is very short,
but the catch-2 test, the catch-2
code is not very short.
It can do probably a lot
more than we are currently asking of it.
And yeah, I guess it's
more relatively complex.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
No, so indeed.
So here.
as defined in this CMakeList.txt,
we are fetching the Catch2 framework,
which then is now then
also built together with
our specific application code.
This is one workflow.
One could also have
I mean, you could have
a standalone installation or catch
two on your computer.
And then instead of building
it each time, you could then link to it.
And I will include statements
while you are building your specific code.
Okay.
So if I did it again, does it cache it?
No.
Yeah, well, if you would add it here,
let's say that example.cc source
code file here, but everything
else, including the fetched code for
For the cats too, then,
yeah, CMake will then figure out
that it will need to recompile
only the source code file
that they have changed.
So in that regard, it is cats.
But still, this is just local
fetch code to be used
within this directory here.
OK, so you can see I
just made a trivial change
that goes significantly faster.
Yeah.
OK, so we've built everything now.
And we build it into the build directory.
And so now we run it.
And I believe that is the CTest command,
which you can see that
also goes relatively quickly.
And yeah, one test passed.
Hooray.
Yeah.
So, uh, since we're already quite late,
we had a more complex example
for that as well, but I would suggest
that we skip that and, uh,
move on to our next point
in the agenda, um, which
is maybe some conclusions.
Um, yeah.
Um,
What would you say?
What's the main takeaway, [name]?
So yeah, one main takeaway
is that testing is good and it's important.
Often there is a bit of
a learning curve for these tools.
So PyTest, which are mainly
used here, is rather smooth
to get started with.
For compiling with this, yeah,
certainly it can be a bit more involved.
So it's a little bit a
question of mindset here that
you simply need to...
I mean, you need to figure out
for yourself whether, let's say,
is the code that I'm working here now,
is it something, let's
say, something major, something that
I and colleagues will use over
many months of time or even years?
Yes.
If that's so, then it's worth
the effort to get going with testing.
Automated testing really helps because
that enables you to have
the tests being run without
you having to monitor it automatically.
This is a large convenience factor here.
Yeah.
I would also point out there,
so we used mostly PyTest and
for the most part, it was
kind of almost invisible.
The only thing that, or depending on
how you solve the exercise or
how you approach them, you may
be only used PyTest by calling PyTest.
But there are also additional features
that you can use inside of
the tests while you're writing them.
For example,
when you are testing
floating point numbers, then you
can use pi tests.
It offers some facilities to
set the tolerance, which might be
sort of a little bit more
robust than sort of just checking
sort of the absolute difference
between the output and what
you were expecting.
And it offers some more of those things.
And one thing you might want
to look at is that we
didn't discuss our fixtures.
And yeah, so there's a little
bit more to PyTest than we showed.
But yeah, I think the
nice thing about PyTest is that it
It provides a relatively
smooth on-ramp, very much
unlike something like Catch-2.
I was mostly exposed to
it in preparation for this lesson today.
And I would say I'm
not very comfortable with it yet.
I would need to spend a
lot more time to actually
understand everything that's going on there.
Yeah.
um but yeah and uh i would
say i i use pytest quite a
lot and i would uh yeah
recommend pick pick find one that
you find a framework that you like
and and launch um yeah and
uh as we talked about earlier
also so i mean your your code is one thing
that you need to, I mean,
as a developer of code, you
naturally have a responsibility
for its functionality, but then
there's always an environment in form of,
I mean, running on different
computers and running on
different operating systems.
And there, a common thing is
that then, I mean, you need to
be ready to, to, uh,
to work with the available resources.
And I mean, things can happen.
So just because the program
is working perfectly fine on
your personal computer doesn't
necessarily imply that a
code might flawlessly work on
some other system.
So I mean, in particular
for codes, which are rather
where you have worked through all of,
let's say, the more obvious bugs
or things that I guess you're wrong
while developing it, then it's
important to be aware of
that unexpected things could happen
if the environment changes.
Let's say you upgrade your
operating system or if you're
on another computer.
And it's clear that for some of these,
without having a testing
framework available, it would
be rather challenging to actually
test these things.
Because if you have a
large program, you cannot, let's
say, devote the time to try things out.
just on your own and by optical inspection,
because that would be much
too time consuming.
So if you then have a
test suite delivered with a
program, then it's a good habit
to just start that thing up as
soon as you are installing
or building a program.
I would also not underestimate
the kind of documentation effect testing has.
It can be really useful to see tests
and you, well, I guess at
some point you'll publish software
or you're writing the software, not
well, for the most part,
not because only you are
using it, but eventually someone
else will also be using it.
And that other person then needs to,
to some extent, understand
what's happening.
And tests can be very useful for that.
And also, I'm pretty sure that
that is happening because that's
going to happen because future you
is not the same person as you, of course.
And yeah, so future you
will be then grateful that
you've written tests in the past.
Yeah.
And here one can naturally, I mean,
reduce efforts that you devote
to your product so that material
which go into tests can also
be used like examples.
And I mean, examples then also
is part of the documentation of a code.
Yeah.
And that's actually very much
how some large projects are working.
So if you look under the
hood in the source code, you will see that,
okay, sometimes just like a
directory is called like examples
and then it's directly called tests.
But it could also be that
it's sort of intermixed.
So you have the set of examples
and you can also have then
have the scripts that can
run these example files and then
you compare, if it's an end-to-end test
or regression test, that you
compare the output that you
get with the expected reference output.
Yeah, it just strikes me here now
that one main reason why you then,
after all, perhaps let's say split,
if it comes to, let's
say, end-to-end testing, why you
have, let's say, distinct set of input files
for tests and for examples is that,
yeah, there's a practical
aspect of computation time.
So when you have examples, for a code,
you would like to have, let's say,
some basic cases, but then
also it's nice if you can
have some, let's say, more real use cases.
And those might be the annual
size so that it takes time to execute them.
And this then in contrast
with a test suite, the test cases
that you have here should
ideally be possible to run
them rather quickly.
And that's in particular important
if you set it up in
an automated workflow so that the
test suite is run
for each pull request or each
push to a repo.
And clearly here, one can also
do it a little bit in, so
to say, I mean, you can do it in different sizes.
So you can work with, let's
say, the small test suite, and
then let's say the large test
suite, and then you can
run the big thing.
I mean, not on a daily
basis, but perhaps let's say once
every week or so.
Yeah, that's a good point.
That's another feature that
these test suites also have
that you can filter for tests.
And this way, you can sort
of select maybe not test everything at once.
Sometimes you only want to
run a single test.
Or in other situations, you want
to run a certain subset of tests.
And these test suites sort
of usually provide some kind of
tools to do just that.
Yeah.
And maybe some more words just
if you are not testing currently
how to get started.
So I'd say, well, since
you probably have an end-to-end test
that you can sort of
do relatively quickly just
from the documentation or
something that you've already written.
And then the next easiest
tests are unit tests for small
units of code that are in there
sort of if you have structured
your code a little bit.
And if you haven't, then that
would be kind of maybe a
good sort of inspiration on
how to structure your code.
Yeah.
Okay, great.
No, I think we've covered
the essentials now and I'm looking here on the
collaborative document and I see yeah
for the time being no
further questions then as usual
we have the the feedback block
is here at the end of the document
and I think we can now
conclude this lesson and leave
the word to [name] who will
tell us about the program for
for next week on modular
code development yes thanks thank you both
for this session.
So we hope that you
could take something from today's
session to your own workflow
and maybe learn something new.
Please give us feedback.
It's in the very bottom
of the notes document.
Something about the speed, the
level of the session today.
If you will use if you
think that you will use what
you have learned today.
And if you have anything
one good thing about today
and one thing that we
should look into improving for the
next time we are having these workshops.
We're currently running these twice a year,
so there will be definitely options
for us to update either
materials or the way we run this workshop.
So please let us know.
And you can also still ask
questions in the very bottom of the document.
Or I also put the link or
we also put the link to our Zulip chat,
which is the place where
the Code Refinery community hangs out
and discusses, well, all kinds
of topics also like the
organization of the workshop happens there.
So if you're curious on joining us,
for example, or just if
you have any further questions
regarding the materials of this
workshop, you can join us there.
We have a help channel and you can
like, yeah, discuss and ask more there.
Then thank you also to
[name] for the streaming today.
All the helpers behind the
scenes, I think [name] and
[name] have been active in
the collaborative notes.
And of course, to you for
asking all the questions that you
had via our document.
Next week, we'll meet same
time, same place for a
modular code development lesson
And this lesson is really there
to tie it all together.
So we will revisit most of
the topics of this whole
workshop, of this whole workshop
series as it was this time,
and apply them to an example.
Currently, if you look from
the schedule at the materials,
it's all in Python.
We are working on adding
the same examples also for R.
So, and also don't worry if
those are not your languages.
I think that even by following
and looking how it works in Python
or R, you can get also
something if you are, for
example, coding in Julia or so.
So it's more about the
topic than the language itself.
And yes.
And if you have any
other feedback about the whole workshop
or anything that happened
in these sessions, we're also
very happy to hear about that.
Thank you so much also to our instructors.
Well done.
And I don't know, do we
have any last things to say for today?
Yeah, well, I could probably just say that.
So as you might have
noticed for this testing lesson,
It's rather extensive, so just
a lot of material in there
that we didn't have time to address.
In particular, there are, I
mean, the different examples
in various languages.
So if you're interested in
these, we very much encourage you
to go and have a look on these.
And then there are template
solutions for many of these in
many of the languages.
All right, then we'll give you
the last two minutes until half past
for filling in the feedback
and preparing for whatever next meetings
or courses you'll have and
wish you good rest of the day
and the week and see you next week.
Bye bye.