Hello.
Can anyone hear us out there?
Yeah, so hi, I'm [name].
I don't think you've seen me here before.
I've been around CodeRefinery
for a while, but haven't
been teaching much this time.
I guess you know [name] from previous.
Yeah, I was here for
the documentation session.
So maybe most of you have seen me before.
Yeah.
But yeah.
So welcome to the last day.
Who's excited?
I'm kind of super excited.
Yeah.
I mean, this is a day.
Ever since we had the, we redefined
or rewrote this last day's
lesson, it's always been one
of my favorite days of
CodeRefinery, just because it's
such a, like it wraps things up
so well and so interactive.
Maybe first we should do the audio check.
Yeah.
So can people hear us and
are we fairly balanced?
Yeah.
Should we say something, some
numbers or I already said something.
Is the voice okay?
It seems good.
I guess so.
Well, we can wait and see.
No.
Okay, well, if you can't, is it balanced?
That's the most important thing.
Yeah, are we like the same volume?
Okay, good.
Someone writes down it's balanced
in the notes.
Yes.
Okay.
So yeah, how should we start?
My checklist says we should
summarize what happened last time.
So what was the previous session?
It was automated testing.
I guess [name] wasn't there last time.
No, I wasn't there.
But that's also a quite
good sort of wrapping up lesson.
It combines everything together,
the version control, the coding
and stuff like that, and sort
of lets you, well,
It's a really nice thing.
It's nice whenever I can
make some code modifications and
then push it to GitHub.
And then when I get
an email automatically from GitHub
that says, oh, you broke your code.
It's like, OK, well, good.
Now I can fix it sooner rather than later.
It actually takes a lot of
stress off of me and helps
me find problems earlier rather than later.
Was there any particular feedback
from last time?
I guess none of us were here then.
Yeah, I haven't got time
to read the feedback from last time.
Sorry.
But what are the expectations for today?
And why should people stay?
So
Yeah.
Basically, yeah.
The topic today is
modular code development, but it
will connect everything together.
Yeah.
And you get to see us live code.
So you get to see us
take suggestions from the audience
and we'll add it to our stuff and make
try to take something and
we slowly migrate it from a
Jupyter Notebook to something that
can be reused.
And it really is a
kind of realistic arrangement of
things or something like that.
Yes.
For the icebreaker we have here,
what programming languages do
you normally work in?
Yeah, we can see someone selected Python.
Actually, that's also the language
I used most of the time.
Same.
But it doesn't matter if
you're not comfortable with Python
for this session, I mean.
Right, yeah.
Yeah, we're mainly talking why
we should do modular code
development than how to.
Yeah, my understanding is our
example is in Python, but if
you don't know Python, like
we're not talking about Python
itself, we're talking about what we do.
And that's pretty much the
same in any language.
Yes, and actually we encourage people,
if you can like contribute
some examples with the other
languages, you can send a pull
request to our GitHub repo.
The link is listed under
here in the materials, but
that's for the future.
Yeah.
Do you use any of
these other programming languages
that are mentioned here?
I use the C++ a bit.
Yeah, and I also know a bit about CUDA.
Okay.
Yeah.
Yeah, which actually should
be super modularized for CUDA.
Otherwise, it's messy.
That's a good point.
Like the whole idea of CUDA, isn't it
that you sort of break
things down into these individual
Yes.
Kernels like data parallelism
and divide it up and
runs it all separately, so.
Yeah, yeah.
My understanding is that each
piece in CUDA should take a very specific task.
Yeah.
But we are not going to use CUDA today.
I'd be interested in learning.
I've never messed with CUDA before, so.
Yeah.
Oh, there's this second question.
What's one small habit or
workflow that helps you stay
organized when coding?
I guess I can say these
days I have a directory called Git.
And within that, I make
a new project folder for each
new thing I start.
And that sort of keeps
the things separate and understandable
and any one thing from
getting too complex unless I
really want to spend time on it.
Yeah.
And then of course, within
each one, use version control somehow.
Yes, that's good.
Well, for me, it's not a
habit developed at the very
beginning of my career, but
somehow I learned after a while
that I should think about
the file system before starting something.
Because at the very beginning of my work
as a software engineer, I
would start with a big block of code.
Yeah.
Okay.
So you mean like dividing
it into separate files or
somehow organizing it on disk?
Yeah.
Better.
Mm-hmm.
Maybe not necessary for all
projects, but it's good to keep
that in mind, I think.
Yeah.
Yeah, I can say my
project organization has gotten a
lot better in the last 10 years.
Yeah, me too.
Anyway, I guess it's 1 o'clock
now, so we should begin.
Yes.
Yeah, so welcome everyone to
the last day of CodeRefinery.
This day really connects
everything together.
it really is a good example of
how we might approach a
real project our projects don't
start off perfect using everything
that we talk about and
immediately become something good
but it really is like we
start yeah we're starting
from some single block of code
and we'll slowly evolve it
and that's quite realistic
Our material is down here
under modular type along.
So I will open that up.
And it's here.
Let me adjust it.
Yes, you see it.
Yeah.
So [name] what's the point
of modular code development?
and this lesson?
Well, I think to me it
means to better organize the code
such that it can be used easily.
It can be iterated easily and
it's easy to collaborate with people.
But maybe we can start from
an example of not that modularized code,
There's a link, the curse
of bad code design.
Can you open that?
Yeah, let's see.
Oh, this is a good picture.
Yeah, that's...
These are many things that
can happen when you get somehow
a bigger size of code block.
Well, it happens a lot to me.
At the beginning, I have
a task to complete.
get some code from somewhere
or figure out myself, then I
will add stuff, add stuff.
Then at some point, I will
get to almost all the problems
here, like some duplications,
some unclear defined variable names.
Yeah, things like that.
Especially this duplicated code part here.
I've often seen this pattern.
You have something, and then I
make a copy to slightly adjust it,
and then maybe I make another copy,
and suddenly I have three
copies, and I might fix something
in one place, but not another place.
And if I ever have to come back to it,
it's like, okay, well, there's
just too much here.
I can't, I don't know which
one is actually the important one.
But okay, yeah, so I guess
we will try to avoid these things there.
So does this mean our code
should never be messy?
I would say no, because
there's no need to be afraid
of messy code because it's
quite inevitable to get some mess
code at some point.
Then you probably will notice,
OK, it's not efficient enough.
I needed to do something to
make the code easier to read,
easier to show to people.
Yeah, then you started to
reorganize your code with some
techniques you can see at
today's session or something you learned.
But at some point it will
get messy again because the
project is getting larger.
There are more components, there
are more logics in your code.
then maybe you should do
a second reorganization.
So it's basically an iteration
of making it a cleaner thing.
Yeah.
So no need to be afraid of.
Okay.
Yeah.
So I guess let's get started.
So the general idea of
what we're doing today.
So I should say I'm a stand-in here.
I joined relatively late.
So
I'm not entirely sure all the things
that are going on, but I
think [name] can guide me through.
So we have 20 minutes
with the introduction that
we've already started and some
example code in a notebook.
And then we have 20 minutes
for you to work on it
and think about it yourself.
Then we discuss some.
And at the end, we do
a big live coding session where
you give ideas and we keep improving things.
Yes.
Yeah.
So I guess we can begin starting here.
One thing we should say is
that the code here is in Python.
And we're sorry that we don't
have it in more languages.
We'd be happy if someone
can contribute the R example here.
It is blank right now.
But...
yeah so so how will
people participate in today's lesson
like what will they
It always works best if
people are engaged in the collaborative nodes.
You can watch us live coding
and giving us suggestions in the nodes.
I will look at the nodes
then we will fit that into our live coding.
Yeah.
Okay.
If you want to code along,
it's also an option.
Yeah.
So from what I understand,
our sample problem is here.
So it's the same sample
problem we've used for quite a few years now.
We have some weather data in
a CSV file from the Helsinki airport.
And then we do some plotting.
So we start with this
initial Python code here.
And let's just pretend that
we got this from a
content generator or something like that.
So it's been given to us.
It has these nice comments.
It does stuff.
But we aren't fully sure of
the details of what it's like.
At least different parts here
look new to me.
But we see going through there's pandas
and matplotlib, which is the
main data frame and plotting Python things.
We see it reads data, does
some sort of data mangling.
We get one month of data, apparently.
And then we do plotting.
So we plot the air
temperature and label the graph.
And that's that.
Yeah, that's basically the
starting point of the XSS and
also the demo, yeah.
Yeah.
So, okay.
So what will our learning
outcomes for this be?
Yeah, can you scroll up?
Yes, here.
I probably I want to go
to the details of the outcomes.
But the basic idea is
modular code development.
So make the code simpler,
while still doing what you want it to do.
Make it easy to understand,
and easier to maintain in the future.
Or easy for people to contribute.
Yeah.
Probably nothing too surprising
will happen today, but you can see
how we make the code
more modularized step by step,
and then you will realize that
why this is important.
Will this be very theoretical?
Yeah, let's maybe do some quick demo.
Yeah, okay, yes.
So, okay, here we are.
So our exercise is, well,
actually we're starting with a demo, right?
Yeah, we have a sample notebook here, yeah.
So I'll basically go through the steps of
making this into a Jupyter
Notebook and running some things.
OK, so my typical project starting method.
So first, I need to
activate the CodeRefinery environment.
So I don't have the
Conda activate by default.
So I run source, forge.
This is the magic word to activate a Conda.
installation and then copying from
what I know, Conda ...
"conda activate coderefinery", this
activates the software which
we've installed as part of the
things to keep stuff organized using
use idea I will "mkdir git/..."
"mkdir git/modular-exercise-2025" to
keep stuff organized.
And then I'll change that directory.
And this is stuff that you
can do some other way.
Like if you were using VS Code
or whatever, the equivalent of
this is opening a new project
and a new directory and telling
it to use the content environment.
But this is how I normally do it.
But certainly not the only way.
So now we need to start Jupyter here.
Yeah, let's start it.
So since I have many
different web browsers open here,
I don't want it to start somewhere random.
So I type "jupyter lab --no-browser".
And with luck, it will start.
And I copy one of these and paste here.
And what do you know?
It started.
Okay, good.
So I can reduce this down.
So this has started.
Yeah, so it started Jupyter
in the directory of the project.
So this is like opening a
new project in VS Code or whatever.
This is my home base.
So I make a new notebook.
And I make the new Python
thing and I will copy and paste from here.
There's a copy button.
And let me rename it to,,
So call it temperatures.ipynb.
Do you think it will work?
Yeah, I think this code probably can work.
I'll click run.
Waiting suspiciously long.
Error, read CSV.
You don't have the data file there.
There's no data file there.
Okay.
Yes.
The link is here.
So I can open this and I
can save it and I can put it in the right place.
But what I will do, I will copy this link.
and come here and go to the terminal here.
And if I type wget and
then I paste the link here,
yeah, it will download it and
put it right here.
So this is what I'll often
do when I'm getting small data
files from the web.
instead of downloading it in a browser
and then moving it, I can
tell it to download it directly
to the place it needs to be.
But there's lots of different
ways to do this.
Should I try running again?
Yes.
The moment of truth.
You can go counting how
many times something goes really
wrong with what we do and how
we need to fix it.
Yes, that's what I would expect.
Okay.
But yeah, this looks about right.
And wow, that was cold that January.
Yes.
Interesting.
Okay.
Yeah.
So it did something expected.
What should I do now?
But as you can see, there
is only a plot for the temperature values.
I think in most cases, people
want to see some statistics.
For example, the average value
of the air temperature of the month.
We're using the January data, right?
Yes.
People may want to know
the average temperature.
Yeah.
what can we do that yes
and by the way you all should know
that i'm cheating by looking
at the solutions here and copying
from it we can take suggestions later
but for now it's a you
know going for efficiency yeah
quick demo you'll see [name] doing some more
closer to real life coding later on
but that's a bit beyond me right now
but okay so we need to add a mean value
so I guess it would go
around here actually I should
make the font size larger
shouldn't I why haven't people said that
Or have they said, but I haven't seen.
No, I didn't see.
Is the font size okay?
If it's, yeah, you can write
down in the notes.
Is there some way to tell
Jupyter to go to presentation mode?
Okay, font size is okay, yeah.
Okay, good.
Okay, so yeah, around
here, here, we clearly saw we
added the plot for that.
So let's add the new thing.
First, we have to calculate the mean.
And that is with this magic thing here.
Let's see.
We are a temperature values.
Yeah.
So mean temp is sum divided by the number.
And then we add in the
plot itself, which would be here.
And I know from previous work
that there's in matplotlib, there's
this "axhline" function.
I'm sorry for doing copying and pasting.
We'll do less of this later, but.
Yeah, this is a quick, quick
demo for the, mainly for the exercise.
Mean temperature.
Okay.
I will rerun it.
Let's see what happens.
Oh, that looks nice.
Okay.
Yeah, we can see a horizontal line.
added to the plot.
Yeah.
So, but sometimes there's
only air temperatures now.
Sometimes people want to see more plots
for different measurements of
the weather data.
For example, precipitations.
That's also in this sample data actually.
Maybe
You can also do that.
Okay, so again I bring in
way too much at once I place it here, this is.
yeah so basically this actually
is a duplication thing of
the air temperature visualization.
looks.
yeah he.
kind of the similar thing.
You plot the figure and then
give it a title, give it
labels, and then save it to an image.
Yeah, I think most people
can already see the
the problem here.
But yeah, that I can, there'll
be a lot of stuff to edit if we want to say,
change it to a different month
or do little adjustments to stuff.
Yeah, but it does look nice.
And I think we're right on
time to begin the alone session time.
So yeah, if I remember right, where's the
So the exercise.
Yes.
So there's two different things
that you can do.
So there's a discussion track
where we're copying these
questions into the notes and you can discuss.
And write stuff there we can see.
and we'll talk about it when you get back.
And other than that, you can
do the coding track.
So you take and there's
some suggestions here.
So start applying these to the
code we have here.
And unlike the way I
started, there's also an
exercise repository that includes
the starting notebook and the data together.
And with this, you can
Yeah, this is a good, sort
of a good already modular starting point.
Yeah, it's basically the same code
that you have seen before
[name] added the precipitation
and average values.
The very same block of
code that's a starting point for the XSS.
Yeah.
Okay.
So let's see discussion track.
I will update stuff into
the notes and should we let you go?
Is it clear what people should do?
So there's two options.
You can either discuss in the
notes or you can take the code
and try to do stuff.
And then when we get back,
we will live code together.
Okay.
We should be back at maybe 20 to the hour.
Yes, 20 to the hour.
Or 18.
Yeah, I guess 18 to the hour.
Yeah.
Okay, sounds good.
See you soon.
Yeah.
Bye.
hello we're back I think yes okay
so yeah there's been a
lot of good discussion here so
we have 10 minutes to talk before
we go to a break so
you what did you think about
all these comments is anything
you would like to bring up
Yeah, I see really nice answers
for all of them.
Yeah, for example, the
modular code development for me,
Very similar as the answers
here, dividing code into modules,
classes, and functions.
That's something I will do.
And also, I'm very happy to
see the last answer,
something about abstraction layers
and the separating concerns.
Yeah, so you can build more complex stuff.
That always means you're
collaborating with people, I suppose.
Yeah.
To me, it's like a hierarchical thing.
Functions might be the one
level of modular, and then
you have more high-level stuff.
Yeah.
I guess, in my mind,
this abstraction layers thing,
the prototypical example is
something like the computer networking
TCP/IP, which, of course,
most people don't know a lot about.
But I've messed with it some.
And yeah, there's all these
layers that are built up.
And whatever your application is doing,
it shouldn't have to care
about what's going on down below.
And that means your application is simpler.
Yes.
What about for B here?
What do you recommend
for well-structured and modular code?
I can see the answers are very nice.
Again, I will use actually
most of the strategies here to
split code into logic blocks.
Yeah, and well, command line
interface, of course, I will do
this at some point, early point
at a project that can make
stuff easier for the future tests or workflows.
Will you demonstrate making a
command line interface in the later part?
Yes, I think if we have time.
Yeah, I will do this.
OK, that would be great.
OK, yeah.
Yeah.
I like this question.
What do we know about
programming that we wish someone
had told us earlier?
Yeah.
What would we say?
Okay, for me, actually, I
quite agree with the second
one, a main function.
That's something I knew late
than I should have known.
I mean, all of these I
agree with, and it's sort of
hard to say what's the most.
But I guess whoever wrote this one here,
it's okay to have... I mean,
all of my starting code, I
can look at things that I
was working on 10 years ago,
and there's no readme file.
It's not installable.
There's just a directory with
a bunch of Python files.
I look at that and think,
oh, I've done so much good
stuff, but it's basically...
not that usable now.
But that's okay.
I mean, you start off and as long
as you can get your work
done at the time and you want
to keep getting a little bit
better as it suits you then.
Yeah, I suppose everyone has a very,
how to say, impressive thing
that you hope you know earlier.
Yeah.
But it's great if you know
it at some point.
Yeah.
You know, also sort of related to this,
I have no idea how to
teach someone to make modular
code despite being here teaching us.
Like to me,
My background isn't software
development at all.
Me either.
Or computer science.
So somehow I've gotten to
these things that sort of work
and make my code work well.
But yeah, it's not.
Yeah, very similar here.
It's something I've just sort of picked up.
And now I'm happy with how it
is, but how I say it.
Yeah, I don't know.
It's like a...
learning yourself.
I guess most people here
are doing research in something or the other.
And that means you're pretty smart.
And, you know, you can figure
out what you need.
Hopefully, we've helped you get started.
Yes.
Do you design code on paper before coding?
Not always.
Yeah, like people answered here, sometimes.
Maybe more times nowadays than before,
because I started my career
as some data analysis thing.
That's actually what we're going
to see today.
I usually rush into the results
I want to get.
But nowadays, I will do
the designing thing more.
Yeah, like a rush to write some code.
Right.
Yeah, I sort of like that.
I rush to make a bad version and I realize,
okay, in a week or two or month
or two, I'm probably going
to rewrite it once I know
what I actually need and
do some big restructurings or whatever.
But yeah, I mean, sometimes
I've actually planned stuff out
on paper before doing and
I think it's always paid off
when I've done that.
So take that as you would like.
Yeah.
What about top down or bottom up?
Well, for me, it used to be
top down from a big picture.
But as I mentioned, I will
do more design things.
So I will start to bottom up more nowadays.
Yeah.
But it depends on the task.
I agree with this comment here.
Which one?
The top down most of the times.
It depends on the task.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
So top down to you, does
it mean like starting with
the user interface or the
command line or whatever you run there?
Yeah, kind of.
Instead of starting with
individual functions, which do?
Yeah.
Okay.
This is a good last one.
Code two times slower if
it's easier to read or understand.
Yeah.
But I guess it depends on
what it means by your code.
Because this is a good point here.
I mean, I guess a lot
of our code actually has to have
a lot of data and is somehow speed critical.
Yeah.
If you are doing some
high performance computing, then the speed
is really important.
Yeah.
But also like the whole idea of Python.
Python itself is not that fast
for numerical calculations, but
you have all the speed critical
code in other libraries that are
written in C or Fortran or
whatever, and those run really fast.
but then your code is more reasonable
and faster to do and sort
of glues together that code and
I mean, I guess, that's basically
the reason why Python is
so popular it's definitely not
unique to Python I mean MATLAB
are all these languages are
basically the same thing there's
a bunch of code written in
c and Fortran and then
some interface language on top of
it that lets you connect stuff together
Have you ever written stuff in C
or Fortran for Python and
then connected it somehow?
Maybe some small things, not
very big project.
Yeah, I think that's actually
what people do a lot.
Writing some C code, some faster
C code and make a Python interface for it.
Yeah.
I've also done it some
a few times.
And it's pretty cool to be able to do that.
And I mean, it definitely
does take more time, but
usually the time's worth it.
Yeah, it's cool.
It's very friendly to users.
You can get the performance and meanwhile,
you can have a very
easy to understand interface.
Yeah.
Okay, so my timer says it's
almost time for our break.
I guess we see some
comments from the coding track here.
Oh, yeah.
But I guess, yeah, well, we
can look at that when we get
to get back from the break.
And it will be use screen
and we will do live coding.
Live coding, yeah.
Actually, we can fit these
comments or suggestions here to
the live coding.
So let's take a break until
three past the hour.
Yes.
Okay.
See you soon.
See you.
Okay.
Bye.
Hello, we're back.
I suppose you can see my notebook.
So next I will do live coding.
I will start basically from
where [name] stopped.
like I added the precipitation
and the average values visualization.
I will be the one who
is using the keyboard and
please give your suggestions in the notes
and we will fit that
and use that suggestions to
improve the code here.
But should we have a look
at the comments from the
coding track, actually?
So what people are trying to
do is to replace comments
with functions, remove redundant comments.
Yes, good point.
We will do that.
Yes.
OK.
Maybe we can start.
Yeah.
So basically, each of
these commented blocks can become
a function of some sort.
Yes.
It takes some arguments.
Yeah, kind of.
Yeah, the comments actually
gives the information about what
this block of code is doing.
No, actually, you can already
see it's very long.
It can't fit into my screen.
There are duplications for
the precipitation and the air temperature.
But let's imagine that we
want to visualize more months.
Now we have only January.
If we want to have February and March,
I think the natural way to
do is adding a for loop.
Yeah.
OK, yeah.
I guess you don't want to
go copy and paste this three times.
No, definitely not.
OK, yeah.
Yeah.
Where does the loop start?
It's really long.
Yeah, right around there.
Yes.
I'll firstly fix the indentation
and then add the for loop.
So for months, I will give a list here.
Maybe I will copy stuff from here.
So we have for January
and March and February.
But we need to like,
actually, we don't need this.
Okay, yeah, so we need to
grab the data for each month.
I'll give it a new
variable name, like month data.
Okay, yeah.
Yeah, so basically do this thing.
We don't want to call it the same as month.
Yeah.
Yeah, okay.
Yeah, that's it.
Do you think this will work or not?
Do you think it will give us error?
So I can see we need
to replace where it says
January with month data.
But yeah, we're not just run it.
OK, yeah, let's see.
I often do the same, like
I'll run and see what works
and doesn't work, so.
Yeah, OK.
OK, there we go.
So it's an undefined variable.
Yeah, actually now we have mass data.
We needed to replace all
this stuff with it.
Here.
I guess you could define every
month to be called January, but
that would just be confusing later.
Yes.
Okay.
There, yeah.
Another one, another one.
And I guess this is the first good thing.
Now the same text or same
thing in the loop works for every month
and you don't have to
go renaming this variable ever again.
So yeah, you can use one variable name to
represented them.
But actually, there's another thing
we need to fix because it's
hard code data here as a January in the right.
Okay, yeah, I will replace that with month.
But make it a string formatted stream.
Yes.
Okay.
And this is the fancy Python
syntax to do that.
It's there.
And also here.
Well, this should work.
Let's see.
OK.
It gives the plots for each month.
This is faster than it was
when I tested it because I
was like renaming too many variables
and had to figure out what was wrong.
Yeah.
Okay, good.
Okay.
Is there any suggestions for
what to do next.
I don't see anything in the notes.
Someone in the notes said, can
we find and replace all of them at once?
And the answer is yes, in a good editor.
You can always do a find and replace,
but fancy editors will be able
to look at the context and know
that this is a variable while
this is inside of a string
or something like that.
Yes, exactly.
Someone suggests tight view for images.
I guess that's about having
less border or... Like smaller size?
Maybe.
I'm not quite sure, actually.
I'm not sure it is.
Okay.
Different rows and column in rows.
Oh, yeah.
Okay.
Yeah.
I think what I do, I do know how to do
that offhand because I can't
remember the exact syntax here.
I think it's the writing
something here like a three and a one or two.
Yeah.
Maybe I will skip this.
But also if we do too
much, we're going to later change
the number of months, so.
Yeah.
But I guess, yeah, because I think
that we're probably going to
make this a function eventually
where the function will plot
just one month and make two plots.
Yeah.
or even one plot if we use
more, if we want to make it more flexible.
Yeah, yeah.
But anyway.
Go ahead.
Oh yeah, there's still quite
a lot of repetition in the loop body.
Yes, that's very correct.
We should fix this next, I think.
So do you,
Like whenever you're making plots,
do you have a function that
makes the plot like this here?
I guess it kind of makes
sense because we have something that comes in.
Yeah, we can see a lot
of stuff like value names,
label names, colors, these kind of things.
I usually will create a function for it.
Yeah.
Yeah, let's maybe do it.
Should we do that now?
Yeah, I think so.
Okay, yeah.
So I will move this stuff to a block.
Okay, I think it's really too long now.
Yeah, the Jupyter interface is
a bit... How can you... Okay, I will copy...
Part by part.
Yeah.
I guess really you only need
to copy half of it because
there's a lot of repetition.
Yes.
Yeah.
I would define a function.
Okay.
Just call it plot.
We'll copy more stuff from here.
So what will you have the function do?
Will it make one of
the plots like temperature or precipitation?
Or will you have it make
the two plots together?
We could make the two plots together.
Or we can, if we want
to make it more flexible, we can like have a
a variable indicating which
measurement we want to plot.
That's also an option.
What should we do, actually?
Well, if we want the code to be shorter
or even easier to read, maybe
we should let it plot only one plot.
Yeah.
Okay, so you'll make a function
which plots either temperature
or precipitation.
Yeah.
I will remove this stuff.
Is there too much stuff here?
So basically, we will call the function.
Oh, sorry.
We will give some variables here.
But let's see.
Let's fix the function.
Firstly, yeah.
Okay.
Suggestions parameters in the notes.
So as parameters, the column
of the data frame.
And the string for the title of the plot.
And I guess the color.
Yeah, I think so, yeah.
Color, so what's writing?
The color, yeah.
Should a file name be
the parameter, like the file name to save to?
Yeah, the file name under,
yeah, let's do this one by one.
Yeah, someone mentioned that
doing this subplots twice a bit scary.
Yes, I agree.
So let's remove one of them.
Well, it works.
there's no error for that but
yes it's it it's not very clear
so we needed to have we
needed to know like
which months we want to plot or
maybe not yeah should
the month be captured inside
of this function or outside
maybe let's do this step by step
Capture the month later for the time.
If we do too much stuff,
maybe it's a bit confusing.
Yeah.
Like somehow I think like
the month capturing or the
filtering should happen outside the function.
Because this is often sort of
like what I do.
Let's see how would I say it.
I have some functions which
take the data and read it.
Some functions which process the
data and filter it down to
what I need to analyze.
And then some functions which
analyze and plot that subset.
Yeah.
So that means we will have
a variable for months here, right?
The data frame, so like month
data would be the first parameter.
Yes.
Yeah.
Yeah, that sounds like what
I've done before.
So let's say that we should
have a column and for the
label, someone also mentioned the
color and what else?
Well, let's check out the
hard-coded stuff, actually.
That should be the things
we replace with parameters, right?
Yeah, that's a good way to
look at it, just remove it one by one.
Yeah, so this should be
the label, the color, and then, so this is also
The column.
Column.
Yeah.
And this actually should be
replaced with the label.
Label, yeah.
And the color.
Well, line styles... Yes, that
can stay the same.
Yeah, it can stay hard-coded.
Or is it... Yeah, I guess
we can split stuff out
from being hard-coded one at a
time after we know for sure we want it.
Yeah.
Okay.
Now we also replace this with a label.
Maybe this should also be a variable.
Let's call it location.
I should add it.
Okay.
Location.
Here it should be the label.
Yeah.
So here it's the temperature.
We probably want to replace
this with Column maybe or label column.
Column.
Yeah, I guess.
I guess now we can make
it slightly less perfect to make it more
reusable and that's just a
choice we have to make yeah and
we do have a mouse here that
means we need to oh right yeah
so it has to be passed in
here anyway yeah it needs to
be passed anyway yeah could the
file name be passed in instead
of the yeah that's a good point yeah that's
Yeah, that's a good point.
We pass a file name for it.
Yeah, and then it can really
be used in even other
projects or other completely different stuff.
Yes, exactly.
Actually, in most cases, the
file name should be a
parameter instead of hard coded
in the function.
Then does that mean we
don't need this mouse?
Yeah, I guess it's not in there.
I think it should work now, but let's see.
Let's try it out and then
make some errors, maybe.
Yeah, that's the best way to see it.
Yeah.
Let's say if we want
to plot air temperature, then
the first parameter should be air.
Yeah.
It's called Celsius.
Celsius.
Yeah.
And the second parameter is label.
Label.
Color, location, found it.
Yeah.
So.
The label, we gave it
like air temperature Celsius.
Maybe something easier to understand.
Yeah.
Something shorter.
And then the color.
Red was this one.
And then location on the file name.
Location, yeah, the Helsinki one.
Yeah, because the data is taken from FMI,
there are different, you may
have different locations, I suppose.
Yeah.
Yeah, so now we have the file name.
But for file name, we still
need some pass on string.
Yeah, I guess it's.
Yeah, so months here.
What's the month?
And then the temperature.
For sure, yeah.
Yeah, temperature.
That's a good suggestion.
I would use keyword arguments
for that function.
I guess we can add that later.
Yeah.
Yeah, we should add that later.
Let's see if it works now.
Okay, it works.
Whoa, yeah.
Okay.
But for three months, yeah,
we have three months.
But there's something I'm
concerned concerning concerning
because in Jupyter Notebook,
variables are installed in a
memory all the time.
Oh, there might be some hidden errors.
Ah, yeah.
So we have to restart the
notebook and run it again.
Yes.
What I would do is to
restart the kernel and run it again.
I don't know if there is
a better practice, but that's
always what I would do.
So I would do.
Now that you mentioned, I
would do the same.
Yeah.
So I would do this.
It would be a great example
if it didn't work now.
I hope it didn't work.
Yeah, that will take some time.
Okay, it still works.
That means we didn't make mistakes.
That was a good.
Ah, there's a comment here.
Month data is a global variable.
Better to pass it as a parameter.
very great point yes okay
yes that's a very good point and
we will see it's great
that someone noticed this but imagine
if no one noticed this is there a more
how to say systematic way
to detect such kind of problems
in Python for example would some yeah
Do some of these like
code analyzers detect this stuff or?
Yes, I think yes, some
editors have this kind of
static checker thing to check
this kind of problems.
I can show that later.
But that needs you to have
everything in a function.
then it can easily capture
this kind of problems.
So maybe let's do that.
And then we will see how
to use editors to detect this
kind of problems for us.
But it's great that someone
noticed that this
Yeah, so, well, I have
another habit, actually.
I would separate the statistics
from the visualization most of the cases.
Ah, okay.
So is it like... We
can see some calculations here.
Yeah.
Yeah, but in this example, this
is just a simple averaging operation.
But in some real world
applications, it might be
something more complex than this.
I will separate this into
a different function.
Yeah.
Yeah, so for that purpose,
I will maybe remove this and
make a function that can be called in the plot.
Can we use the numpy
mean function or something like that?
Or some?
You mean instead of this?
Yeah, I think so.
Because of the values, it's a numpy array.
Yeah.
Let's try it out.
And are you going to pass
in, have a parameter be the
function to apply to do the statistic?
Yeah, I think I will do that.
That's what I will do.
Okay, sounds good.
So I will move this out.
Like define a function.
Arithmetic mean.
It should take the values.
Well, maybe instead of doing
this, we can do what you
suggested because it's basically a numpy array.
Right.
So if you use the dot mean or whatever.
Yeah.
Then we needed to have, do we need, okay.
Maybe we don't need that
because it's a dependency.
Yeah.
It's still, yeah.
It's just, that's the method
and not the, okay.
Yeah.
We need to return.
This is something for Python.
I think in some languages
you don't need this, right?
Oh, sorry.
Not mean temp anymore, but
mean value maybe.
Mean value.
Yeah.
Then I will say... So...
So the mean value should be,
I know this looks a bit unnecessary,
but the point is to
separate statistics from visualization
in case you have more.
Yeah, I guess.
Yeah.
Like if you can do it
like this, like in this
case, it's really overkill.
Like we don't need.
Yeah, in this case, it's a bit.
But I could imagine making some plot
where I plot my data and
I want to plot whatever
summary statistics I calculate and
that summary statistics may change often.
Maybe the summary statistic is
the thing I'm developing and then I would
Yeah.
Pass whatever thing in as
a parameter and say, this is what I'm doing.
Yes.
But yeah.
Okay.
Let's see if that works.
I'll run this.
Okay.
Got some error.
So mean tempo is not defined.
Yeah.
We, we, we replaced this with
the error is from here.
It's not a mean tempo
because it's not specific for temperature.
It's more general.
So we name it differently.
It's a mean value now.
Okay.
Still somewhere.
Where it is.
are here so mean value let
me run it again okay it works
now okay we got this for
three different oh it worked okay
good let's see how's our time doing
We have 20 minutes left,
around 20 minutes left.
Should we, maybe we should continue the,
I would like to show
the main function, which can
help the static checking.
Yes, yes, main function.
That's a good thing to do.
So, okay.
The main function is where we take all the
code that's all the way on the left side.
Yeah.
And we put it somewhere.
Okay.
So basically, we're eliminating
all the global variables.
Yes.
Then the checker can find the errors.
Let me do this.
I will first fix the
indentation and the define a function.
Yeah.
So this is a syntax.
OK, if name, yeah.
And if you haven't used
Python, this thing that you is
typing here is basically, it's the
way you say, when I'm running
this as a script, then run the stuff.
Yeah.
But should we move to a
Python script now, actually?
Yeah, maybe that's good.
Well, first let's just run.
Let's verify that.
I guess now we see if
we have any leaking global variables.
Do you think this works?
Should you restart and run all?
That's a good idea.
Yes, there.
A moment of truth.
Okay.
This is what we are looking forward to.
Yeah, the mass data is not defined.
So why we didn't see this
error before we put everything
into the main function?
Because it's global variable before.
But now it's a variable defined
in the min function.
It's not visible to the plot.
So in the plot function, it's not visible.
It will give you the error not defined.
But this is after we run it.
With some editors, they can
actually detect this without running the code.
They can do some static checking.
But I think for that, we
need to move this to a Python script.
Okay.
That's not the only motivation
to move this stuff to a
Python script instead of using the notebook.
There are other reasons why we
need to move this.
For example, you have learned
the auto testing before last week, I think.
For that purpose, that's also
another big motivation to move
this to a Python script and also other.
reasons, for example, how to
put this into another workflow,
then a notebook is not ideal anymore.
Yeah.
Yeah, so I will save this
to Python script then.
Okay.
And can you do that
with... Does Jupyter have some easy
way to do that?
Yeah, with Jupyter Notebook, we
can click the file and
save and export notebooks as...
executable script.
That's it.
It will ask me where to save it.
I will just save it here.
Now we can see we have demo.py script.
If I open it, it's what
we have in the notebook.
It's all the stuff.
Okay.
Yeah.
So if I take this and
do Python with this file name, does it work?
oh by the way on line 62
i saw does it need the dot png
on the end oh yes that's a
good point on the file name well it it works
but yeah I guess it
worked somehow it works you can
still save the the files
but it's definitely not a
good way to have that oh
it adds it automatically okay
That's news to me.
Okay.
Maybe, yes, yes.
But it's needed.
It will be stranger without this.
Yeah.
Okay.
So now, as I said, if we
open it in some editor, it will show the error.
Let me do that, actually.
I will...
For example, if I open it in VS Code,
I will quickly show this because
this is a very useful thing.
You're going to show that
it detects the error that we saw by running it.
Okay.
Yeah.
Can you see my notebook now?
Maybe if you can make it
a little bit larger.
Yeah.
Now you can see this
wavelength saying that most data
is not defined.
Right.
Yeah.
That's what I said without running it,
the editor can do static
checking and tell you which
ones are not defined.
It can show all the undefined things.
Yeah.
That's the point.
I hope this is clear.
It's also in the material
there also a screenshot.
Yeah, you can check later if this is not.
You can also try it out in your editor.
Maybe someone already know about
this, but I think this is very useful.
Yeah, yeah.
To be honest, I don't use this
as much as I should.
I sometimes do it, but I
haven't gone that much.
Anyway, okay, so now I guess
you'll fix it, so.
Yes, we need to fix this.
That means we needed to
give, replace these two lines.
And maybe let's think of some,
Actually, the first one is the
range of the visualization, and
the second one is the value.
Maybe I could just put
another, replace this with
two different variables.
Like the first is the range,
and the second actually is the values.
And then the index basically
is the data range.
Yeah.
And this is... Okay.
When would you pass in
the data frame compared to the
two data series individually?
I guess by passing in the
series, you don't have to give
it the column name anymore.
So that's like...
Yeah, basically, we don't
need this anymore.
We passed the series.
Yeah, OK.
Well, for plotter, plotter
can recognize both, I think.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, OK.
And now we have this.
DataFrame, yeah.
But we needed to, like here
we needed to have, so the
data range actually will be the mass data.
Sorry.
Mass data.
I think it's index, right?
Yes, yes, yeah.
And then the second one
was the column name.
Yeah.
So the values, the values could
be, so it's the, it's a mass data and then
actually we could hard
code here right yeah because now
if this is the main thing we
do I guess it's yeah because
it's already like okay
So the first parameter is the data range.
The second one is the values.
Values, okay, yeah.
And then label, color, location.
Label, color, location, and the family.
Yeah, okay.
Will this thing work?
Let's try it.
Probably we'll see some errors.
But I need to...
Yeah, please go ahead.
You need to source the environment.
Yes.
Yeah, OK.
Yeah, because I need to
have the correct pattern for this.
OK.
It worked.
Oh, yeah, I guess no output is good.
Maybe I can remove this stuff
and run it again.
Yeah, OK, good idea.
To confirm this.
Yeah.
And does it appear?
Oh, OK, I need to refresh this.
Yeah, now it plotted this,
the temperature for each month here.
Yeah.
Okay, so it worked.
We fixed the errors and it worked
and it's everything in the
code block in the script is
encapsulated into a function.
Yeah.
How much time we have?
We have maybe 10 or 20
minutes depending on what we do.
We can show test or
command line interface or both.
Can we show command line interface?
At least that's what I'm
most interested in and I always like to show.
So what's the point of
the command line interface?
Well, for me, for example,
I usually do something in parallel.
I will run many copies of
a script for data analysis.
So I want to pass different variables like
For example, here we do the for loop thing.
But if I have a command
line interface, I can pass
different variables from the command line
and fit that into a script
which can run the Python scripts in parallel.
That's really my motivation to have this.
Well, another very common reason
is you want to change something.
You want to change some
variables, some arguments, but you
don't want to touch the code.
You only want to do it
from the command line interface.
Yeah.
I guess that's always the first
one I start with and then
the parallel comes later.
But I guess so for example, in this case,
let's say we have this thing
we want to plot different months
so from the command line we
can give it the file name of the input
and the month the plot or
month the plot whatever yeah and
then give it the file name to
save it and then it will save it there I guess
yeah yeah that means we we
don't need to touch anything of the code
but we can flexibly
do different statistics on
the different visualizations for for
this data set yeah should we start yeah so
Which one do you use?
There are many different ways
to do this, to add a command line interface.
Yeah.
So I'm an old fashioned and simple person.
I always use the Python built
in arg parse library, but it is
a lot of extra typing and stuff like that.
The example in the lesson
material uses the click library.
Yeah, I think it's a kind
of newer one, right?
Yeah.
What do you like using?
Well, I kind of prefer Qlik nowadays.
Okay, yeah, let's do Qlik.
I'm always happy to see something new.
Yeah.
So I guess the purpose of Qlik
and argparse is to take
these things from the command
line, like the dash dash label
or the different arguments, and
then map them to stuff inside of the code.
it's actually not that hard you'll see
how simple it is with
something like click yeah the syntax
for click is like by
adding some decorators on top
of the the function the main
function but we need to
import click firstly import click okay
So we first add decorator,
which is a command.
Okay, I guess that somehow
labels it as being a command.
Yes, that's telling a Python, okay,
this function will take some
variables from the command line.
And then we add the arguments
one by one, it's called the clicker dot option.
For example, firstly, we want
to have a mouse.
It's a very, very, very natural way.
Yeah.
And it's required.
Yeah, it has.
The syntax here actually is
very similar to the arg parser.
You have, you indicate if
it's required and what the type is.
Yeah.
Well, for months it's a
string, and usually it's good to
have a help text here.
Then people can run help
to see the information, the instructions here.
So we could see which month.
Which are you?
Yeah.
Okay.
You already give it like the format.
Yeah, the format then.
Okay.
So people see.
Yeah, that's pretty easy.
Yeah, it's okay.
I think it's similar as Agra password.
Yeah.
So for options.
Maybe we should also have
the file name, but it's hard coded here.
Maybe it's better to have it.
Yeah, yeah, the input file
names is always a thing I
would have as the... The
output or input, that's, yeah.
This is also required.
It's not a string, but it's a path thing.
Actually, click has an object defined here.
It's called a click.path.
It has something else.
It has its own parameters.
It's good to make it explicit here.
For example, if it exists.
So this means we need this thing to exist.
Otherwise, you get errors.
Yeah, so I guess it'll give
a better error message than
just the code failing, saying
can't open or something.
Yeah, I think so.
That's a nice feature.
Yeah, maybe it's a feature that's newer.
So the pass tab, it's...
Okay, actually here I will use
an also easy to validate thing,
pass on defined path object.
Is that from the path live thing?
Yes.
I've used it a few times.
It's nice, but it's always hard
for me to remember what's in there.
I think it's like you
said, the error message should
be more specific.
Right, yeah.
And maybe can make some
validations without this.
Maybe if you give just a
string, it can do this kind
of validation for you.
Yes, yes, yes.
Makes sense.
Better to also have some help
when we can say read data.
from this file.
And I guess we don't need
to go much more than that.
File name.
Yeah.
Yeah, like we could go saying
what the format of the file should be
and all that, but it's
probably better to leave that for
the readme or whatever.
Yeah, yeah.
I guess.
Okay, yeah.
And also we can have something else here.
For example, output.
Like output.
Yeah.
Output should be similar.
Output, maybe give it, usually
I will give it a directory name.
So which, I don't want to
have every image in the current folder.
Okay, okay, yeah.
And then I guess if
you're saving multiple images, then
it needs... Yeah, it will
make the current, the present
folder very complex.
So I usually give it output.
like a output directory.
That's the same thing.
It's also a pass tab.
But instead of read data, I
will see read data to this directory.
Something like this.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, okay.
And how, I guess you'll say
how to get the data into the function.
And that is... Yeah, now we have this,
we need to have this
variables in the function, in
the main function.
First months and then the file name.
Yeah.
So file name.
It's not quite clear.
I will say data file.
Oh, yeah.
OK.
Because there's multiple file
names that could be there.
Yeah, file name sounds too general.
Data file.
Oh, should be.
OK.
And then the output.
Yeah, this.
Then we can replace it with a file name.
Sorry, sorry.
Data file, yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
Then we have, we have months.
Yeah, now we don't want to follow, right?
We want to have the, we
want to have this plot individually.
placing the for loop with
basically now we can do a
for loop by running it multiple
times from the shell
Yeah, from the shell, exactly.
Yeah, and we can automate
that if needed, but anyway.
We can automate that or parallelize that.
Yeah.
Yeah, so we have the... Right,
yeah, and it just already there.
Yeah, maybe the output should
be added here, I think.
So output directory.
And the syntax with the
slash I've seen with the
pathlib paths, it means like appending
or like adding a slash and
then file name within a directory.
Yeah.
Okay.
I'll remove the unnecessary comments.
Yeah.
Let's see if it...
Do you think it will work?
Can you show the help?
Oh, yeah.
We can actually show the help.
So it's Python demo.py.
I think that's... Help.
Okay.
Oh, yeah, this is nice.
This actually is very clear.
So the mouse should be a text.
This should be path.
Yeah, so now if you come back to this
after a while, you don't
necessarily have to go open up
the code, but you can
run dash dash help and see the basics.
Yeah, so basically, if there's
no error in the script, then
we can, most of the times,
they just with a terminal.
Yeah.
So should we try?
So one, our data file.
It's, our data file is weather data.
So CSV file.
Yeah.
Okay.
The other doesn't matter, right?
Right, yeah.
When you have these double dashes, then.
There's two types of things you
can give to command line functions.
There's these options like this
that can be in any order,
but you can also define
what's it called argument and
it has to be in the same
order but you don't need the
double dashes there yeah yeah yeah
and i'll use whichever depending
on what i'm doing yes so
output directory can I use
the current the present
Maybe, maybe that also works.
Oh yeah.
Let's try it.
Cause I did.
Ah, okay.
There's output directory.
Is there a typo?
It looks correct to me.
Huh?
Output directory.
Maybe it's a Let me see.
Could it be something about I
should have a space there.
No, I should have a space here.
Oh, Okay.
Okay.
Yeah, yeah.
Because the font says it's a bit too big.
Yeah.
It seems it worked.
Yeah, four seconds ago.
Or do we need to refresh?
Yes.
11.
Yeah, I have refreshed.
It's newly created, actually.
Yeah, OK.
Yeah, so it worked.
There is no error.
Yeah, OK, good.
So that's for the command line interface.
Yeah.
I guess we're almost out of time.
Do we want to try to
do anything else, or should we?
Well, we
There's something else we can
do, for example, auto test.
Another thing is that we can see
that actually the data reading
and the data preprocessing are
still in the main function.
I would extract this to
another function, actually.
Yeah.
But maybe we don't have time for this.
I want to mention this.
Yeah, yeah, I guess.
Maybe we should make sure we
can end early and not do too much.
But maybe, or should we discuss
after the break and put this
in the context of what we
do for our other work?
Yeah, yeah, good, yeah.
Yeah, maybe.
Yeah, and if there's time, we
can do more later.
let's yes it's been over an hour
since the last break so yeah
we should take a break oh okay
i'm adding it to the notes
break until eight minutes
past eight minutes past yeah yeah
okay great so we'll see you
after the break for the
discussion of this we'll talk about
how it relates to work we actually do
and so on the simple example
we can talk about what else we would do
and we'll have the outro
and conclusion of the whole
workshop so stick around yep okay
see you soon bye
Hello, I think we are back.
Yes.
There.
So, yeah, we've got just
a little bit of time left.
So if there's anything you'd
like us to discuss, please fill
in with the notes here.
Um,
So also other stuff we
could do or questions about what
we had before, etc.
And as usual, the feedback
is in the bottom.
So please let us know what you think.
And you can comment not
just on today's lesson, but the whole workshop.
What did you think?
Please let us know for next time.
Okay, so if we come back,
we're sort of back to where we started from.
So we did this exercise.
We thought one starting place
could be looking at these
discussion questions again.
So now after having done this,
what does modular code development
mean for you?
Can we somehow explain it?
Yeah, I think what we did
here is initially we have a block of code which
works somehow.
But when we want something more
from it, we want to avoid the duplications.
We want to make it easy to read.
And then we do something,
for example, edit functions.
I did a command line interfaces
to make it easy to use.
by doing all of these
steps, we somehow achieve
the modularizing code.
I think that's a very natural
way of doing modular code development.
Like breaking, splitting a big
block of stuff into different
logic packs sometimes functions
sometimes like classes or modules
yeah yeah for me okay yeah
now that we've done this work
I can better say what it means to me
so it means I can do
something and then get it done
and then not have to look inside
of it again but I can reuse it
so for example as you made
the command line script at the end
so this is a really simple example
and what we could do in
an hour was not that much
but it's quite reasonable that i
like the kind of thing i've
done before i've done this big analysis
or something and I know
it's really important to me so
i make the command line thing
and then in the future in all
my projects I can run the
same analysis on some files by
running it from the command
line on whatever inputs and save
it where I need to.
Or it becomes a Python library
where I can import it
directly in Python and run it
that way without command line,
whatever the case, like
there's something that's reusable that way.
Hmm.
Yeah.
What should we answer next?
Best practices?
I guess there's nothing really new there.
We tried out some.
Yeah.
Did this go OK without
designing it on paper and stuff like that?
I would say not all the time.
Yeah.
But it depends.
If it's a big project, maybe
design it on paper or even
have a meeting with people.
Yeah.
Or at least what the big pieces are.
Like, for example, we could
figure out what we want each
function to do in advance.
Yeah, like, you know, the
details don't matter, but how
they connect is good.
What do you say we built
this top down or bottom up?
I would just do more bottom, bottom up.
I mean, we got some,
we started with something that
could actually work.
So it was like, it was
connected at both the top and bottom, but
Maybe it's sort of more bottom up,
like you said, because it... I will,
like, for example, I will
define some functions, maybe not
perfect or even not working, but
I have them there, like a placeholder thing.
Then I will
call them in, for example,
the main function.
Oh, yeah.
Then I will complete those
functions one by one.
Yeah, so complete it one by
one in an order that lets stuff run.
Yeah.
I like that.
So basically, having the
modular code development concept in
mind is always good.
Yeah.
So how often do you
use modular code development processes?
So let's... I think nowadays I do a lot.
Yeah, these... I mean, this
is actually a quite... Oh, go ahead.
Sorry.
Yeah, it will save me some
troubles in the future.
Yeah.
For me, this is quite realistic.
I make a really hackish
first draft of something that
just shows it works, and then
I'll take quite a while slowly
improving it and making it
more modular until it becomes good enough.
There's some questions in the notes.
So how many AI tools do
you use when coding?
I think this is a question
for you because my experience there
is sort of limited.
Actually, yes, it's quite a good question.
We should mention this.
Yes, I use AI tools when
I'm coding all this.
Actually, AI tools are getting smarter.
They have the concept
of modularized, modular coding development.
If you give it permissions,
some AI tools can create
somehow modularized project structure for you.
But the thing is, we must
know this concept ourselves.
I guess I don't use AI
tools that much, not like
doing the whole projects for me.
But there have been some times
like, how do I do X?
Can you give me some examples?
And that's been really good.
Or for example,
I needed to code something,
some web control panel for something.
And I looked and I
couldn't understand the documentation about
how to actually set up
the whole project because I'm
just not that much of a web person.
But I could say, please use this thing
and make a working example
that connects to what I need and works.
And that got me a working starting point.
And then I could keep
working from there and I'd
be asking questions like, okay, so
how does, how does, like, how
do I do these little different things?
But usually I'm connecting it myself
and I'm copying and pasting
line by line and understanding
each line rather than doing it wholesale.
So I think that's a lot
less than most people do.
But then again, I'm not doing
that much coding these days,
not like you is, for example.
Yeah, but even with AI tools,
I think it's always good to
understand the code line by line.
Yeah.
Not like some people do.
And which one do you use?
So mostly...
VS Code has the
GitHub's Copilot integrated.
Another popular one is Cursor.
Yeah, those things.
There are many of them
and it's developing very quickly, I would say.
So I don't have best practice
in terms of AI tools,
I'm also kind of exploring something.
But I think the ideas,
for example, modular code
development still applies, even
whatever tools you are using.
If AI can achieve this, it's good.
If it couldn't, then we should
have this in mind.
I don't know if there's
something better now, but I use the free
and it claims to be
private one in DuckDuckGo that
it still uses open AI models in the back end,
but I do this so I don't
have to make any accounts and
nothing will be connected to me.
That's nice.
Maybe I'm old fashioned that
way, but that's what I do.
It's very nice.
Yeah, and it works well enough
for what I need.
I mean, it's not that advanced,
but it goes okay.
Can any other instructors
that are listening help us
to answer this question in the notes directly?
What do you use?
I guess I often use I'm
SSH to other like the computer
cluster or things like that.
And then I use a
terminal-based IDE called Emacs to
do my editing there.
I don't know if that's
common for other people to do.
I don't, well, I know some
people do this kind of stuff,
but these days with VS Code,
having the remote SSH, that's probably...
the more common and more
usable way of doing things.
Yeah, I think some of
our colleagues are using VS Code,
but I know some are like you.
Yeah.
Because we haven't talked
about using debuggers, which can
stop in the middle of code
and print out values of different things.
That's Quite good.
For the libraries part here
we have an upcoming course called Python
for scientific computing and in
that course we talked a
lot about the different Python
libraries that are commonly used
and that goes more into the actual like
code side of things that
course isn't designed to teach Python
but for people that have
sort of used Python before it's
a it's a good course
debuggers tdd I think means
test driven development
And I think that might
have been mentioned last week.
Yeah, I was not there.
Yeah.
So what test-driven development
means is before you go make a bunch of code,
you first write the test and
then you write code which passes that test.
And it sort of forces you to
think in a way that actually can be tested.
And that can be quite...
when i've tried it before
it's actually quite nice
it improves reliability and all
that should I go to the outro
of the day now yeah
please give feedback this is still
very empty so if you don't tell
us we can't do stuff so to
go to the outro I will click
to the schedule and go
to day nine including remarks and
where to go from here and open
that in a tab fix the font
size so I have the privilege
of greeting you and sarah
including the workshop, even
though I haven't been around much.
All our other hosts are
occupied with other stuff today.
So first off, we'd like
to thank everyone who's attended.
So all the participants, of course.
We've had a whole lot of team leaders
and hosts in other
different locations scattered around
who are basically running
the local breakout teams and stuff like that.
That's great.
I think we think that
having this local connection
while the centralized teaching is
a good way to do things.
So make sure you give them a thanks.
We should thank all
the different instructors.
I don't know how many we
even had this time.
10 or more?
So it's actually been quite
well and it's been quite
nicely distributed here.
So we'd like to thank all of them.
In addition to the people
you've actually seen, we've had
more people in the background
who have been answering questions
in the notes and stuff like that.
That is.
They've basically been able to
help us focus on teaching.
And all the local partners who
helped to do stuff.
So I'm not saying the names here
so that the names don't
get recorded in YouTube, but all
the names are on the website so.
please go take a look.
You can give us feedback.
So of course there's feedback
within the notes that are there.
You can give it for both today
and the whole workshop, or you
can let us know by email.
This is our chat if you
want to join and talk with us live.
Since you know how to use git now,
if you see things that are
wrong, you can go and make
git issues directly in all
of our different lessons and improve things.
Basically, everything we've taught
you now is exactly what we
use to do the development of these lessons.
What we've given you so far
is only the starting point.
So we've said a lot of stuff.
We've had to give one version
of the lesson for everyone
at every different level.
And it is quite, I mean, we're not
even pretending that we
have something that's the endpoint here.
But you can review all of
the things that we've done here.
We hope that you're not done here,
but you can keep reviewing
and using what we have.
You can also ask for help.
So our model here is we give the teaching.
It's live.
It's almost like a MOOC course we have.
But then you have all the
local support to go and
ask them questions about these things.
Basically, all of the people
you see here and all the different countries,
these are places where you can
ask and say, hey, you know,
like this is my team here.
You can come and ask us,
hey, you know, I have
trouble with version control.
Can you help?
tell me what my problem is
or can you help me add unit
testing to this program i'm writing
or things like that and same
for some of the other different groups here
also these are the organizations
where many of the instructors came from
so you can find them through that
and follow up if you'd
like invite personal lessons or
things like that okay if
you like a certificate you can
see the course web page this
will tell you what we've got
there I don't remember the
details but I think you've discussed it before
If you'd like to support
us, there's different ways.
The most important way is
to tell others about the workshop
and let them know that
it's relevant for their starting
as a researcher.
Our next workshop has just been scheduled.
I don't think it's written
on this page right now, but
in about six months, we have the next workshop.
And it will be a lot like this.
So you can practice and then
you can send your friends here
next time so they can work with you.
you can follow us and boost
us on different social media
if you want to you can bring your colleagues
as a team next time and you
know rely on us doing the main instructing
and you help with the
exercise leaders or help as
an exercise leader and help
with the exercises then
There's our chat that I
mentioned and newsletter.
Both of these you can sign
up for to hear more about what's going on.
And finally, if you're really
interested in the topics here, so
if you like what you see,
if you think that, hey, you
know, I'm actually interested in
doing more of this kind of software
or data or code things as
part of your career and
you're a researcher, there's a
term for that now.
called the research
software engineers and different
groups behind this so it's
basically a community of people
who are in research but their
skills lie in getting the
code data software stuff like
that working better and they're
very important parts of the
you know, the research process.
I mean, computing and data
is in almost every field of science these days,
but not everyone can take the
time to learn it all themselves
unless we have specialization.
And if you want to specialize in
that kind of stuff, many
of the instructors here, we basically work
as some sort of research
software engineer or research engineer
of some sort and have made
our career out of this.
So it's something that you
can think about also.
If you really like it,
next summer in Tromsø, Norway, we
have a third in-person Nordic
Research Software Engineers Conference.
And maybe it's the kind of
place that you can join and visit.
So yes, any feedback we
should discuss in the notes?
Well, that's not a lot of feedback, please.
Please add more here.
And yeah, anything else?
Or should we call it good?
Yeah, I think we have
all the topics covered.
And it's exactly the ending time.
So I guess.
Thank you everyone for
listening and watching.
It's been a pleasure to have
you have so many people
attending this and Yeah.
See you later.
Yep.
See you.
Okay.
Bye bye.