CodeRefinery.org
you
Test, test, can anyone hear us out there?
Check, check.
Test, test, one, one, two, two.
I think I need to make the instructors a little bit louder.
Can someone say something?
Saying something.
Let's see. Okay, someone says, sound okay. Good. Yeah, welcome everyone. So, here we
are. We're live. Hopefully, every will get lots of people coming. We're in the icebreaker
time now. So let's see, what do we have for icebreakers?
I've got a couple of generic demographics icebreakers.
Let's see what people are.
So how does this work?
So if you are registered, you should have a link to this
note.coderefinery.org document.
You should be able to switch to edit mode.
and then basically write stuff here.
So this is the way we use to communicate.
So instead of the Twitch chat, which is linear,
you can come here,
you can ask questions in any order.
We have a section for questions which is appearing down here,
and answer and ask anytime.
So yeah, let's see what people say.
There was a good icebreaker from last night, what was it?
How would you explain HPC to someone from a hundred years ago?
Should we add that there?
I'm adding it.
There we go, we see it coming.
is so difficult. I mean, in the 19th century, there used to be some calculators. So maybe
that would be the metaphor. And they are probably steam-operated, right?
Steam machines that keep this going. And then we need a mechanism to send messages from one
steam factory to the other, like some conveyor belts or something. That's the network. And
all just work together. Maybe the industrial revolution, is that like a metaphor for HPC?
Yeah. Or the printing machines that, you know, that you're able to
in parallel print the same book. Yeah. I guess the high performance part,
Well, computing part, do we have to explain what computing is to someone from a hundred
years ago?
I guess there's probably some mechanical calculators as an analogy.
I think so.
These ones with the, you know, the wheel that you could sum and subtract.
So can we say we made that much, much, much faster?
all using electricity. And then, say, for the high-performance part, say, we can't make
one of these fast enough, so we make a lot of them, and then they communicate together
really efficiently.
Electricity existed back then, right?
Like saying there's electric lights.
Technically.
Technically, as electricity has been there before us, but yeah.
Did telegraphs exist back then?
I think it's the last few decades of the 19th century, I think, let me check.
No, actually, it was 1835.
Okay.
like the most or yeah no that was the [?] coat
but anyway yeah it's exciting to be here because we've been planning and discussing this course
for maybe i don't know two years or something like that and today finally it's happening
so what would you say is the spirit of this course like why are you here what do you
what's the thing about what we do?
Well, I don't know.
At least I've never seen something like this
that we are putting together in this four episode
in a sense that we've been running
and I'm sure we've been taking part
to introductory courses to HPC,
but at the end of the day, okay, good.
You learned those commands that you need to run,
but it's the daily struggling with working
with these clusters and remote and local
And so something that I guess everyone has just learned by doing on their own or by watching
others.
So I wish I had this type of introduction, I don't know, 15 years ago when I started.
Yeah.
I'd say it's best practices filtered by people at different centers, so really taking the
most common, most useful.
And I think what is so fun is that we will see that many, many things are really similar
across all the centers.
We will also probably see that some things are not a little bit different.
As instructors, we hope that they are not we will not.
We are a little bit afraid that some things that we assume to work works everywhere might
not work everywhere.
But it's also to me the first first time that we try something like this cross border trying
to distill out what is what is it that is common?
And what can we learn from all of us?
And can we somehow abstract away the details and focus on the big picture?
So for me, the course is really about the big picture.
Do any of you know about other courses which actually use multiple, like is taught and
have participants with access to multiple different clusters by different organizations
and the course might work for them.
Not across borders.
No.
I guess maybe our June kickstart course is the closest then.
Yeah.
Even that is.
But yeah, so during that June kickstart course, something we always heard was people, it was
a basic course where people saw, well, how to get started.
But then there's a lot of people who want some lessons about how we actually use it,
like what's the advanced side of things, which is a little bit hard to teach because if you
have basic people just learning the cluster and command line and advanced people, you
can't really easily serve both audiences at the same time.
So here what we've done is, this is not a basic course, and in fact a lot of things
you see might be too advanced to really fit in one thing together, but, I mean not too
advanced for most people here, for everyone here to do, but instead it's cool demos.
how we actually use it, you can get some ideas, and then go back and study yourself.
Okay, did I finally say that properly?
Yep.
Okay.
So, what are the topics for today? Who are the teachers? Is it [name] and [name]?
So the first part will be [name] and me, and the second part is [name] and [name]. And today
we talk about resource use. We will do a super brief intro into what is high-performance computing,
but really like in one minute, in two minutes. And then how do we, how do we use resources
really in a good way. How should we approach it? And what are the different dimensions
there? So we'll talk about number of cores, amount of memory, time, and then input output.
So how should we think about reading from disk and writing to disk?
And I saw some really cool pictures last night, which were like, well, made by [name]. Such
an amazing metaphor for what the cluster's doing.
So...
Yeah, and there are different possible analogies.
We might mention some of them, just to get a real-world analogy to what's going on.
Okay, should we get started then?
Let's see.
So I think [name] and I, we're going to do a short introduction.
So can we do a poll, who's done a live stream course before?
Can someone add that while we're talking?
I can add it.
So this is a live stream course, which means that
you don't interact with us directly, instead we have this notes document.
So there is the Twitch chat.
We recommend you don't use that because we don't watch it really closely.
We have all the questions here, which means that you can ask any time.
We can come back and answer asynchronously.
We have multiple different people here in the background who will be answering the questions
at the same time the instructors are talking.
So feel free to dump in all your most advanced questions there, and we'll answer what we
can during the course, and in the afternoon we'll go through and answer the rest of them.
So this is really a time to answer whatever.
At the same time, there's going to be a lot of questions there.
One common problem people complain about at the end of every course is that there's too
much information, I couldn't follow all the notes.
Notes is what we call this document here.
And for that, well, what we say is, if you can't follow the notes, then don't.
It's really kind of simple when you look at it that way.
We know there's too much there, so leave it, don't try to follow it all, and go back
in the afternoon, whatever.
You can even write your question there and not look at the answer until later.
And at the same time, many people feel that this notes way works really well because you
actually can ask questions that you couldn't ask before.
And there is more interaction than usual.
So do use it.
If you happen to be watching and haven't registered, register and you will get the link.
So it's only for registered participants.
And registering does really help us to justify the time we put into here because of the number
of people we get.
This is being recorded.
We will see about publishing the recordings later versus leaving the Q&A and writing available.
Let's see, what else can go wrong?
If the stream suddenly dies, that means my computer has crashed, in which case wait a
few minutes and I will bring it back up.
So that's happened only once during a meeting, I think, because Zoom has crashed.
But anyway, something to be aware of.
If it doesn't come back up, I guess that means my computer is really broken or the internet
is completely down, in which case, well, I guess we've got a problem anyway.
What else?
The notes will always contain updates for how to, like, where we are.
So if you scroll up, you'll see right now we're in a questions mode.
We will add in sections for each page we go to, so you can always catch up again.
And here we see someone writing that we were in the intro.
What else can happen?
A cat can come and visit me, in which case I will turn on my video, because that always
entertains people.
That's what we call the opposite of a problem.
I don't know if any other people will have cats coming and visiting them.
Do use the notes immediately.
If for example you can't understand, or we're too quiet, or you can't see what you need
on the screen, whatever, just throw it in there and say, help, I can't see, I can't, whatever.
Yeah, with that said, I mean, welcome.
So should we begin then?
Yeah.
Maybe I could briefly mention because this was asked that this, the core structure in
the morning, we will have two hours of kind of lecture based and then for those who are
willing to try these things and so on in the afternoon, there will be a Zoom session that
will not be recorded so that everyone can freely ask questions, form groups and do the
exercises together. And a couple of have asked about credits. So yes, it is possible to receive
credits and I added some details on the course web page. And what else? Well, this is kind
of the first ever run of this course. So it's more like a pilot of the maybe official run
which will be later in the year, in the fall. So most likely I will send anonymous questionnaires
and feedback and any sort of feedback you can have, be as critical as you can so that we can
make it turn this beta version into the release one.
Otherwise I think I don't have any other practical details so I'm happy to pass the
voice to pass the stage to our instructors.
Super, I will take the screen share first and then let's introduce ourselves and let's
get started.
Here, I still need to adjust it a little bit.
And a question to the studio, should I make it a little bit wider?
It can be a little bit wider.
How about this?
Looks good.
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay, so then just a little adjustment here.
So first, hello everybody.
This is really exciting.
First time we do something like this.
And it's a pilot.
And then later people can say,
well, we were there when the pilot happened.
Yeah, we are really excited.
We are nervous.
My name is [name].
I will be co-teaching this.
So I'm at University of Tromsø doing support
in high-performance computing, but also in everything that is programming software development
in research. And really looking forward to teach this together with [name] from Sweden.
Yeah. Hi. Hi, everyone. I'm [name]. I'm working for Uppmax cluster at Uppsala University
in Sweden. Very happy to be here. I'm also doing support for users as [name] been telling
a little bit of RSC like. So yeah, really happy to be here. And we'll be teaching this
together with [name] and [name]. So [name], maybe they'll introduce themselves later.
Yeah. Okay. So the plan now, let me, let me show you where you can find everything. So
hopefully you have this document that I'm sharing open. This is the, these are our notes.
Please ask questions here.
And here you can also find all the links.
So if you have one, one thing open somewhere in your browser is this document.
And here, please ask us lots of questions, we will be watching this.
And this is now the best way to participate in the next two hours, we will have a break.
So we will also take a break halfway through.
And the next really two hours will be discussions demonstration.
And if you scroll up to the top, you can also find all the like the link to the material
I will open it up. So I will follow this link here. And if you open up this link, this is
the lesson. And just to make it a bit more readable, I will zoom in. So what to expect,
We will the next things we will know for the next 45 minutes.
We will talk about really what is high performance computing in like two sentences.
What is job scheduling?
How do we schedule jobs on a high performance computing resource?
We we are now on many clusters.
I see that you are from different countries, different clusters.
One thing that probably all clusters have in common these days is that they use a tool
called Slurm.
So we will tell you a little bit about the tool.
And then using a visual analogy, we will then discuss two things.
One is how to choose the number of cores.
That's very important.
And we will show you a method that almost always works.
And then how to measure and choose the right amount of memory.
why it matters, and how to do it, again, with a method that almost always works.
And then we will discuss a little bit, we will take a break.
And after that, we will talk about input output, how to use the disk in a good way.
And later, we will have an exercise session, which is optional.
The exercise session will not be streamed, not recorded.
And then we can try these things out hands on.
But now, the best way to participate is to watch what we do and ask us questions.
So you don't have to type with us.
All right, I will open up the first episode, which is job scheduling and Sloan Basics.
And we will show you a few pictures and discuss a little bit.
But very soon, I will also open up a terminal, I will log into one of these clusters, and
And I will test these things out.
The learning goals is that we really understand what the job scheduler tries to do.
What is the motivation for a job scheduler?
We know what is the motivation for the researcher.
The motivation for the researcher is to, you want your calculation to start as soon as
possible and to finish as soon as possible.
That's what you want.
But I will tell you what the job scheduler tries to do, and then we will learn how we
we can work together with the computer.
What are the dimensions of a job and how to specify them,
but also understand that choosing good parameters
will not only affect resource use,
but also how long you wait in the queue.
And these are things where you want to minimize.
And what we want to give you is a good visual understanding
of what a job scheduler does.
And I'm watching the questions, so please keep them coming.
Any comments, welcome.
What is a supercomputer or a cluster?
Probably many of you already know, so I'll try to keep it really short.
It's a large collection of computers.
They are connected together through a network.
And each of these computers is often called a node.
And some clusters have thousands of these nodes.
They have thousands of these little computers.
And these compute nodes often have multiple cores.
So when we talk about cores, we often use it synonymous to CPUs.
But some of these compute nodes also have graphical processing units.
What is surprising to when when people start working on a on a supercomputer or a cluster.
And for me, a supercomputer and a cluster is the same thing.
But what is surprising to people starting on supercomputers and clusters is that these
these cores are often not faster than the ones that are in my laptop.
But the difference is there are many more.
So in my laptop are I don't know, six, and in on on the supercomputer are there could
be 50,000.
So it's not faster, it's more sometimes faster.
And then the nodes are connected through a high speed network.
The other thing that is different is they often share a common file system.
So all of these many compute nodes, they can all read and write from a common file system.
And we will, we will discuss what that means in the second part of today.
And then when we log into clusters to do our work, we typically log in through some of
a login node, and then I will submit a job. I submit a calculation which then waits in
the queue until it starts and then it runs on the compute node. So that's just for background.
And of course, the other comment, if I forget something really essential. Now I said that
the one thing that is probably common to all the clusters that we are on today is a tool
called slurm is it is a tool that helps scheduling and queuing and monitoring jobs on these compute
nodes. Jobs often have to wait a little bit before they start, because the resource is
limited. And one analogy is, you can think of slurm as like the matter the inner at the
restaurant, so the person who is at the entrance of a restaurant, and if you want, if you come
there without a table booking, without a reservation, and you want a table for eight people, you
might need to wait a little bit. And Slurm really works the same way. We have a limited
resource, we have a lot of demand, and there needs to be somebody in charge of scheduling
and making sure that, yeah, just managing the queue. It is, Slurm is the most widely
used job scheduler these days. It's not the only one, but I think it's the most widely
use one and the visual so there are different analogies you could think
about restaurant reservation or hotel reservation the one analogy I will we
will use today is if maybe many of you remember playing this game here so the
blocks fall from the sky and you need to arrange them to fill up rows so this is
It's a Tetris game.
And we can think of a job scheduler doing something similar.
And here I try to translate it.
Like how does a job scheduler look at jobs?
These calculations for a job scheduler,
they are often rectangular.
So we don't have these like stair shape or T shape.
All of these calculations
are the first approximation rectangular.
And here in this plot, I have, there are different colors.
And then the job scheduler tries to arrange them.
And what the job scheduler really wants to do
is to keep the bottom row always full.
And here the dimension could be the number of cores
or a memory or the number of GPUs.
And the other dimension is time.
So as time goes on, new blocks fall from the sky
And Slurm is constantly busy arranging these blocks.
So we can think of that the scheduler
tries to keep the bottom row always full.
So the motivation for the job scheduler
is keep all the cores busy all the time.
That's what the computer wants because it was expensive.
It would be a waste of taxpayer money to keep them idling.
What is the motivation for me as a researcher, I want my job to get started and finished
as soon as possible.
And then there are long jobs that take a lot of time but maybe only a few course in this
case it's this violet job here.
So that it takes a number of time units but not too many resources.
And then there are the so called wide jobs this green, the green set, which is lots of
resources but not very long time.
And the cost of a job is the area of this of these rectangles, you can think of it that
way.
And that is of course just a simplification now imagine there is one more dimension.
So here we look at the 2d Tetris but imagine the Tetris is 3d, three dimensional or four
dimensional because the third dimension could be memory.
So what is maybe more realistic is that the scheduler plays kind of a cubicle Tetris all
the time.
And some of these jobs crash immediately.
Some of these jobs are added to the queue but get canceled.
So they never start.
And I think that's maybe.
So hopefully that's a useful analogy.
But now let's, what can we do with this?
If we, so first of all, something I want to tell you is that today, now in the next 40
minutes, we want to discuss these dimensions.
So how do I choose?
How do I tell my job whether it should use, you know, five blocks or 20?
How do I choose the dimension number of course?
How do I choose the number of dimension time?
And how do I choose the third dimension that we don't see here, which is the memory?
How do I do technically, but also which number should I use?
So that's the goal for the first part.
Once we accept that this is maybe a useful analogy, we can even understand concepts like
backfilling.
And to tell you what that means is, so we have this situation currently, currently what
is really running the sort of the processes they are busy computing the bottom row.
And they just finished the bottom row and now they will switch to the second row. So
now they will switch to compute this one here, the second row. And now imagine suddenly this
pink, the pink job suddenly crashes. It crashes after two seconds.
So what do you think will happen Maybe question to my co instructor
Yeah, so then the turquoise top job is going to fill in that space.
Yeah, so the schedule with notice that pink jobs crashes suddenly there are eight of these
places available. And in this situation, the job schedule doesn't have any it will notice
is that, hmm, I can actually move this one down here
and it can start immediately.
It can backfill.
It can even start before the other green job starts
because the green cannot start immediately.
It doesn't have enough space for it.
So something that the job scheduler cannot do,
it cannot turn the pieces.
It cannot do that.
So now we also understand what backfilling means.
And what I wanted to tell with this is that
It matters how long the time the time a job is scheduled for will matter on how soon it
can start.
If a job is short, and suddenly, some resources become available, I can go in and and get the
get the resources.
Okay, and now, how does it look really in real life?
Here I have an example slum script.
So this is what, this is how we tell the high performance computing cluster of what we want.
Here is my computation.
I want to compute something currently, let's not focus too much on what we do, but I need
to tell now here in this block, I tell the scheduler of what, what will I need?
And often you need to specify the account.
So this is the, you have like a quota of how many of these jobs you can run and how long
they can run.
So this is my, this is my account, you give it a name.
But here is the one dimension, this is the time dimension.
This job here would run for five minutes.
So minutes, seconds, hours, days.
Often there is a limit on how long you can run on some of clusters in Norway.
The limit is either one week or two weeks.
But there exists clusters where the limit can be one day.
Here is the other dimension and tasks and task is this number of course, approximately.
So in this case, I would ask for four course.
And here we ask also for the how much memory I need.
So this is how you do it technically.
So then the question is, is it a good idea to specify the memory needed for the job?
On some clusters, you have to, if you don't have to, or you can maybe leave it out.
And then it will take, it will assume that you want approximately the memory that the
CPU has.
On one of the clusters in Norway, where I work, we, we have to specify it because it
It depends whether multiple researchers can run their jobs simultaneously on one compute
node or not.
And if yes, you often need to specify this because this is then also a limited resource.
And depending on the cluster, you might need to specify more.
Sometimes you need to specify something called partition because there are different partitions
in the resource.
And you can do a lot more.
can specify the number of nodes or how many of the,
how many tasks per node one can do a lot.
I listed here some more options that might be handy one day,
which is how is the, how are the outputs called?
You can even make some calculations dependent
on other calculations.
So if you want one calculation to only start,
once the other one finishes, you can define dependencies
And you can even submit an entire array of jobs,
of very similar jobs.
And later in this course, it will not happen today,
but one of the future weeks,
we will show you how do we split up a computation
into smaller pieces so that we can run them as an array.
Okay, a few more things,
but then I will also demonstrate this.
And what I will then also demonstrate that once we have such a so-called run
script, once we have the job script run script, then what we will do is we will
submit it. And the command that I will use is sbatch. With sbatch I add
my job to the queue. And I wait until the job scheduler tells me that
now you can start.
And instead of putting things into a script you can also specify all of these
things on the command line, which I personally recommend not to do because if it's in the
script, I don't have to remember it. I can open it up half a year later and I can see
what I did. If I did it on the command line, I cannot remember it half a year later.
What I would add is that I also like to use the script. The only time when I don't is
If I want to do a test, a quick test job,
just to see that the inputs I have in my job script
are correct, then I would just add in the command line
a shorter time for the job,
just to see everything is working as it should.
And also another exception is when I use dependencies,
I have those in the command line,
and then I just prepare different job scripts
in different folders or as needed for different steps of my workflow.
And here I list two more useful things that I use all the time. So I really only remember
a handful of these commands. One is to list all my jobs. And sometimes I need to cancel
a job and you don't. So to all the other learners here, the goal here is not that we remember
all these slum commands. The goal is what Deanna and me will try to show you is how
do we think about the job? How do we approach a job so that we choose these parameters? Because
it's easy to look up, well, how do I specify it here? This is how, but what, what, what
is much harder and I find really important. How do I choose the number? Should it be four
or should it be 40? And should this be five minutes or should it be five hours? And that
is that is the goal of today.
So I will scroll down and this is really about
how to choose the parameters, not technically.
This we can look up, but how do I choose the number?
And for the time, well, there are often time limits.
And what we recommend is that, well, it's hard to predict.
You need to maybe run a series of jobs
and get a feeling for how much time it will take.
Hopefully you can extrapolate
and then maybe add 20%.
Don't make it too long just in case.
If I know that my job takes five minutes,
it's not a good idea to ask for seven days
because the job scheduler doesn't look,
the job scheduler doesn't know,
doesn't understand what I try to do down here.
The job scheduler doesn't know my calculation.
It doesn't know my code.
It will look at what I'm asking for.
And if I ask for seven days, then imagine back to Tetris,
imagine this gigantically long piece that lasts seven days
and it will try to fit it somewhere into the resources.
So it might then queue for a very long time.
If the job is short, ask for a short time.
Also, when you debug a problem,
try to reduce the system size to reduce the queue time.
And I will show you that in a moment.
And then in the next so now in the next half an hour we will really talk about how do I
do this if I how do I decide how many course and how do I decide how much memory we will
show you that just catching up here with questions whether anything that we should lift and discuss
and while I look there I want to give a bit of a preview of what we will also do later
in the course. One is that some jobs, if you look at them, they run for a long time, sometimes
hours days. But if you really look at them and see what do they really do is that they
they compute independent things one after the other. Sometimes there is a loop and we
iterate over lots of tasks, lots of little units, but they are independent of each other
or mostly independent of each other.
And what we will do in,
I think it will be the session number four of this course
is we will show you how do you split it up
into independent jobs.
And maybe we also understand what can be the advantage
because the advantage of doing that is that
now the pieces that are now independent,
they can fall down and they can start at the same time.
And the scheduler has much more flexibility
to fill up all the holes, and we will maybe get the result sooner, the overall result.
What is the disadvantage is that we might need to combine the individual results into
a combined result. So this is something for later. And one more thing I wanted to show
is that I told you that all the jobs are rectangular or cubic cubic. But if you really look at
them if you really open them up and see what is the actual resource use so here
the gray thing imagine the like the whole rectangle is what I asked for
maybe for CPUs and a certain amount of time but if I if I would open up the job
and look into it often the resource the actual what is actually used is not
rectangular but it varies over time at the beginning it it uses very few CPUs
use, then it uses all of the CPUs for a certain amount of time. And then at the end, it uses
half the CPUs for a certain amount of time. And why did I show that? Because sometimes
it can be beneficial to so how could we solve this? If I some if I look at this job here,
we are wasting almost half the resources. And one solution can be that we split up the
job into pieces and run them one after the other because the pieces have
different demands for resources and one way to cut here would be and I don't
know whether you can see like my mouse pointer but I could cut here after two
lines and after two lines I need a different resource and then I could cut
again after the fourth line after the fourth row sometimes it can be
beneficial to cut and then run them as independent, separate steps, separate jobs.
And each of them have different resource demands.
And I would add that if if they are not independent, then you may use dependencies to ensure that
the middle block will start after the first one is finished, for example.
Very good question on line 171.
So do I have to ask here, I will also make that more visible.
This question here, do I have to ask exactly the same amount of time and number of course
for a job to start to make a square block.
So don't ask exactly for the amount of time, add a little bit more.
Because sometimes the CPUs are a little bit busier, it takes a little bit longer.
So at 20% 25%.
But you ask for a certain amount of course of the amount of memory certain amount of time.
And even though your job internally might, the resource use might actually vary.
But now we should really look at that.
So let's talk about how do I choose the number of course.
And let's talk about how do I choose the right amount of memory.
And for this, I will open up the material, keep the questions coming, and I will also
open up my terminal and we'll try these things out.
And why it matters, I will now not go into details, but it matters both for the cluster,
because if you use, if you choose well, we will have a better resource use.
More calculations will be able to finish.
More papers will be published.
It also matters for you as a researcher because your computation will start sooner and sooner
and you will pay less, although sometimes you don't pay for it.
Sometimes it's the taxpayer who pays for it.
So you don't want to ask for too many cores.
You don't want to ask for too few, depending on what your goal is.
And we don't want to waste resources.
And the example project that I will use is
So I wrote an example code, but we don't have to if you if you want to have a look at it,
you can you can look at the code.
We don't have to understand it.
It's it's a road code written in a language called C.
The big picture is that we simulate planets, imagine a galaxy of planets.
And they all, there is gravitational force, so all of these planets attract each other.
They have random position.
They start with a random position and random velocity.
And what this code does is that it, it does a little time step.
It computes the gravitational force between all of planets.
It adjusts the velocity and moves them a little bit.
And then again, another time step, it computes gravitational force.
It moves the planets a little bit.
And we can, the code can use multiple cores and distribute the work across the cores.
And then each of the cores will only move a smaller part of the planets.
But we still need to exchange the positions of all the planets between the cores.
So that's the communication.
The cores have to communicate through the high-speed network, and they have to exchange
the positions.
But whatever, this is just an example.
So I will build the code in a moment, we can run it, and the code is called planets.
What is nice is that I can here on the command line, I will be able to specify how many planets,
So here I have 30,000 random planets in a galaxy.
And how many steps I want to run, 10,000 steps.
And I can even make the network artificially slower.
So I can increase the network penalty and simulate how long will it take if the network
communication takes longer or less long.
And here, it doesn't matter what the code does.
What I want to find out is how on how many cores should I run it here somebody somebody
ran the code on four cores, and it took a long time 11,000 seconds.
The question that we have here in the next 10 minutes 15 minutes is
Should I choose four or 40 or eight or what is the setting, how do we find out
And how, so how do you, how do you approach this typically [name], and I can also, if you
have such a question, how do we, how do we approach the problem?
Whenever, whenever I run a new piece of software, I would start to find a manual or some documentation,
some examples, as usual, someone has run this before using a certain size of the problem
and it took that much time, I would try to do that, try to do something similar,
maybe use the same input, try to play around with different sizes of the resources.
I mean, different number of cores, maybe different number of nodes if it's parallelized.
And of course, I mean, it may be different because all hardware is different.
There are going to be different interconnects.
So it's really something that one should test.
And once I know how it scales maybe for a certain size of the problem, I should actually also keep in mind that it may scale differently if the size of the problem is different.
So just because someone found certain scaling for a certain type of simulation does not mean that it's going to be the same if I change the input.
So do your own tests, I would say.
So yes, that's more or less what I would do.
Thanks and what I try to do here in the meantime is I download the code and I try to compile
it and this is so we don't expect here the learners to do that or to even remember how
to do that.
That's not the point.
And it's also really different on different clusters.
This is something we can then try later in the exercise session in the exercise session.
We can actually all test it.
I'm now loading a module on the cluster that I'm on which can then compile the code.
And I'm following, I will compile the code.
All right, and now I have the, I have the code here that I can run.
And if I could now do this, but I don't want to wait 11,000 seconds.
So I want to know, take some of these job scripts that I was talking about earlier,
and I want to create a job script.
And now how do we select the number of course, I will call it run.sh.
And inside there, I have this example, I need to specify my project, which for me on my cluster
happens to be some name.
So this will not work for everybody else.
I will start on eight course, nine minutes just though it's just a guess.
And the first insight I wanted to everybody to take away is that
if I look at this example that somebody gave me 10,000 steps, the first thing I would probably
do I will think, do I really need 10,000 steps? And something I would probably test is how
long does it take to run 10, 10 steps and 20 steps and 40 steps. And what I would then
see is that in this case, the runtime is it scales linearly with the number of steps.
Each step approximately cost the same. So I don't need to run 10,000 steps and I don't
need to wait for 11,000 seconds to, to try to run this and to study this. So the first
thing I will do, and this is also what I did here is I will do some testing and figure
out that it might be actually okay to run just 100 tests, 100 steps. And this will,
this will take a couple of seconds, minutes. What I try to achieve is a calculation that
few minutes I don't want to I don't want to wait hours few minutes in this case
it will take maybe a minute and then I often start with something and later I
will vary this so I will change from 8 to 4 and 16 and 32 and 64 and 128 and it
doesn't have to be a power of 2 but this is just was what computer people like to
do. Let me submit this and see what happens as batch. Sorry, what? Sorry for these commands.
So what I have this transcript and I can submit it. So now I sent my job to the queue. If
I want to see how it is doing, it is now running. Nice. So this was a short job it there was
somewhere there was some resource available and it immediately started
and now i will impatiently repeat the command
and i think it will take i don't know
30 seconds 40 seconds
and i did that now for eight cores now it should take approximately
60 seconds
We are going to do this exercise in, in two hours time. So you don't have to do it immediately.
So everybody just watch this. And we know that on different clusters, the scripts look
slightly different, but we will then help you help you with that. So later in the exercise,
you can try this. You can also try this with your own code. So instead of simulating planets,
you can try to do this study with your own code.
And the two steps were,
what is the shortest time that I can get away with
and still get a representative answer in terms of timing.
And then run it on a series of course.
Did my job finish?
It finished and then I can,
simulation completed.
In this case, this took almost a minute on eight cores, and I simulated 30,000 planets
and 100 steps.
If I would run it for 1000 steps, it will probably take 600 seconds.
And something I will not do now, but what we can do later is we can really try it out
instead of eight cores, 16 cores and 32 cores and so on and so on.
Here I made it a little bit more readable on the table.
And what can we see from this table?
So the big question is how many cores should I use?
And what do I see here?
If you run it on one core, it takes 420 seconds.
We double the resources, we half the time.
We double the resources, we still half the time, we still half the time, still half the
time.
And now, now it's not any more half the time.
You see that I don't doubling the resources at some point doesn't doesn't cut the time
in half anymore.
And something interesting happens here is that I went to lots of course 256 and the
time even goes up.
And why is that?
point, the communication to update the positions of the planets to communicate between all
the CPUs at some point is more costly than the computation. And in this case, where would
you how many CPUs would you choose? [name], where would you stop?
I would stop at 16. But it also depends on the number of cores on the cluster. Because
Because if it's better that we fill up the note, then maybe 42 is a better number.
So it really depends on, on the cluster configuration.
So yeah, but somewhere there, 16 or 42.
And it's important that you're thinking time spent per number of course.
Yeah.
And if you, if you don't, if you are in no hurry, maybe it is fine too.
But we clearly see that in this case, it doesn't make any sense to run this on 256 cores.
So here I would also choose 8 or 16, maybe 32 if there is a deadline and PhD has to be
ready by Friday afternoon.
But we don't move on much further.
So what is the takeaway?
Here the takeaway is two things.
It's both for timing and for debugging.
It can be really useful to reduce the time of the job so that it's so that this information
is still meaningful.
That is one skill and the other skill is run it on a series of course.
And you don't have to do this for every job that you try to do.
I do this only if I have if I plan to do 100 similar jobs.
Then before running these 100 similar jobs, I do this study for one of those.
And then all my 99 other jobs, I know what to choose.
I know that I should choose 16.
And I know that it will take so and so many seconds.
So this calibration doesn't have to do for every single job that would be unreasonable
as well.
And thanks for all the questions.
Thanks to my colleagues for answering them.
And we have now I would like to take maybe 10 more minutes on talking about the memory
part.
And then we will take a break and talk about disk.
So now I will switch over to this episode here, which is now that we know how to choose
the number of cores. And this is really a method that really almost always works. I
want to show you how do I choose the memory. Because sometimes you have to especially if
you need more memory than the processor has. Let's open this up and let's try this out.
Why does it matter similar motivation, it's
If you ask for excessive number of memory
You might block resources for for other people
If you pay for the resource use, you might pay too much
And you
Your job may wait long or forever in the queue
until these resources become available.
Also later in the course, we will take a problem and we will chop it up into smaller problems
and we will try to run them in parallel at the same time.
We will try to have jobs that are independent and can compute simultaneously.
And if I'm not careful about the memory, I might severely limit my ability to parallelize
is my job. So it matters often. And I will, I want to show you how I do that. And this
is a method that maybe I will show you two methods that are probably available on most
of the clusters that we are on. So again, before running many similar jobs, I typically
To calibrate, I don't do that for every computation,
but if I plan to run a hundred similar computations,
I do some calibration study.
And here, what I want to calibrate here is the memory.
And the example code that I will use now is a Python code.
Again, this is something you can try later in the exercise.
And this Python code, it computes,
you can tell it to compute 5,000 random numbers
between minus one and one, and to sum them up.
You can also give it a certain time to wait
between computing and summing.
And I will show you why I did that.
But let me go to, I will now go to a different cluster
for reasons.
So now I'm on a different cluster.
Again, we are not expected to remember auto-type.
I'm on a different Norwegian cluster.
I will create a new folder for this.
And I will try to run this Python code.
Example.
We don't have to look at the Python code.
The Python code creates random numbers, sums them up, prints the result.
Now, I should really...
I should run a script for this. I should write a script for this.
I should not run it directly on the command line or sorry directly on the login node so
I will again write a little script which I will adjust and we will in the exercise adjust
to our clusters that we are on I will again call it run.sh
Let me discuss what we see here.
I need to adjust my account.
In my case, it happens to be this one.
I give it a name, five minutes, absolutely enough.
On this cluster, I have to specify memory.
And I don't actually know how much.
I will start with something, two and a half gigabyte,
2,500 megabyte.
For this example, I don't need more than one core.
it will be run on one so-called task or one core.
And now I could run it like this.
I could sum up, here I want to sum up lots of numbers.
How many are these?
Million, 50 million numbers.
I want to sum up 50 million random numbers.
I want to wait for 10 seconds and then print me the result.
I could run it like this,
but one tool that is available almost everywhere,
which is really nice is that you can put this one
in front of any of your commands
and it will measure the so-called high watermark
of the memory use.
You can think of like when you imagine
there is like a flooding, you know, the water goes up
and then the water disappears again
and then you can see how far did the water reach.
So that's a high watermark.
And this tool will tell me this.
So my code will allocate memory and it will tell me
what was the highest memory allocation during the runtime.
Let me submit this and let's see what happens.
So again, I send it to the queuing system.
I send it to Slurm to...
And again, it was really short.
It needs only one core.
It started immediately.
nice. I expect this to run. So I asked for 10 seconds, it will actually run for a bit
longer than 10 seconds because the allocating 50 allocating and computing 50 million random
numbers will take a little bit of time. It takes a few seconds. So it's still running
Running 28 seconds, 31 seconds, and it will soon finish.
Still running.
Well, actually, maybe it will take a minute.
But it gives me a chance to look at the questions here on the notes.
Thanks a lot for all my colleagues for answering.
And thank you all for the good questions.
And we are maybe five minutes away from a break.
All right, job finished.
What we have here is my Python code, my job script, but now I also have an output from
slurm and I will let's see what is in this output there is stuff here okay this
doesn't belong here but the important thing with when putting /usr/bin/time -v
in front of your command you will get this block here and
And there are lots of numbers,
but the one that I'm interested in is this one.
Maximum resident set size.
So this tells me that the code used,
so this is kilobyte, so this would be,
it would be almost 2000 megabytes.
So approximately two gigabyte.
That was the highest memory allocation
during the run of the code.
So that's one tool that is almost always available.
This is the tool that I use to figure out what is the highest memory allocation and
now I know and now for all my jobs I can take this number and maybe add 20% to it just to
be on the safe side and then you know if you need to specify it.
And in the material I will show you there is one more method which is I think available
on all slurm scheduled clusters. I think so too.
And I will try that method, it will tell it will give me a similar answer. But there is
a risk to it. As act, I think this means maybe as accounting, then the job number, my job
number here was this one. And then I am only interested in this maximum resident set size,
which is the memory.
And in this case, it tells me the result.
It's again,
almost approximately two gigabytes.
The problem with this tool is that it uses sampling.
Every on our clusters in Norway, every 30 seconds,
it asks the job.
What is the memory that you use right now?
And 30 seconds later, it asks again.
And if the job is shorter than 30 seconds, well, let's try.
What happens if the job is shorter than 30 seconds?
Let's make it shorter.
Let's remove a zero here.
Because that will make it shorter.
And let's add only, I don't know, five seconds wait time.
And I will submit again.
It will finish way sooner.
Because to compute 10 times less fewer number of sticks, I think it should finish hopefully
in very soon.
Now it finished.
12 seconds in.
I have now a second output.
The the result from so this number here is still correct.
In this case, it the the memory demand was 10 times lower.
It's only 200 megabytes.
But if I ask Slurm
and now I need to replace the number by this number.
it will tell me that, whoa, why is that?
No, okay, because I made a mistake.
It's not 34, it's 44.
This is the right number, 44,
because what I expected to see that the memory is zero.
So this tool tells me that my job consumes zero memory,
and that's not true.
But to be fair to this tool,
this tool uses sampling every 30 seconds.
It had no chance to see the memory demand.
And what I want you to take away from here
is that depending on which tool you use,
it might be using sampling.
And if there is a memory peak, this tool might miss it.
The other one, the other tool, USR Bintime,
this one, to my knowledge, in my experience,
will always report you the high memory watermark.
It doesn't use sampling.
Not in the same way.
And maybe there are other tools.
We can share them on the notes.
We can then later share them in the exercise session.
And again, in the exercise session, the goal will be that you can try this out with my
example Python code.
But what is maybe more interesting for you is to try this out with your own code and
figure out how much memory does it really use.
Yes, exactly.
Sometimes it's good that you check the memory requirements
for different sizes of your arguments,
and maybe try to extrapolate, possibly,
and get an idea on what you would actually
need for your real simulations.
And of course, I mean, this is easier
to do if it's linear or square.
But it's a good way to try to estimate that.
And [name] said, I mean, at different clusters you may have different tools which can do this
memory profiling. And we'll definitely talk about more in the exercise session. So.
Yeah. And sometimes we get asked for a lot of memory.
And sometimes the answer is to change the code. And many of the people who work in,
who are instructors here and in the Code Refinery project,
really like to help you also improve the code.
So for those of you who write Python,
there is a little bonus that you can see that
just by changing two characters in the code,
memory demand can go from a lot to almost zero.
And good questions there can be,
is there any way that we can change the sampling?
To my knowledge, the user cannot change it.
We can change the configuration of the cluster,
but it happens to be configured for 30 seconds.
So at least to my knowledge, it's not something I can change
but please correct me if I'm wrong.
And I don't want to eat more into the break time.
I think so many good questions, so many good answers.
I suggest we take a break and then we talk about disk.
And how long will the break be?
Maybe my studio colleagues can help me.
Is it 15 minutes?
Should we be back at 15 past the hour, but is that also right for the instructors who
come after me?
Maybe they can have a say?
Yeah, 15 minutes works.
Good.
So then we'll be back 15 minutes past the hour, we will talk about DISC, and I will also then
here have a look at all your questions and add more answers to it.
Thanks so much for listening.
the big picture got clear, the thinking got clear, the details we can always look up.
Thanks to Deanna also for doing this here for going through the lesson here with me.
See you in now 14 minutes.
See you.
you
Hey welcome back. So we'll go back to the materials and talk about I.O. in a moment.
Let's first do some quick introduction. So I'm [name]. I work at Aalto University so
So I'm mostly familiar with the Triton cluster, and yeah, I work there as a software engineer.
Yeah.
Hi, my name is [name].
I'm also from Aalto, so the same stuff.
And today we'll talk a bit about IO best practices, or like IO in general.
Yeah. So should we go just directly into the material?
Yeah, let's do that.
So I'll open this.
So what we really want to go into is just,
we want to give a model of how input and output works,
and why it can be, or when it can be a bottleneck for your program.
So, well, let's just go into it, because it's probably just better to show
and show and tell rather than go through the objectives here.
So compared to CPU and RAM that was mentioned previously,
IO is a bit of this kind of like the eternal wallflower or like something that is not
often discussed or it's not so heavily like it's not maintained by the Slurm. So Slurm doesn't
necessarily know about the IO in the same way that memory and CPUs are like
their resources. So with the IO, you need to be a bit more conscious of what the program
does underneath it. And for this, we want to show first, what is file? And let's start
with that. What is a file in a Linux file system? And file is metadata and file contents.
And this metadata here doesn't mean metadata as in your dataset has metadata with it.
Your dataset describes what's in the data.
It means metadata as in who owns the file, when was it last modified, how big is the
file, and this kind of stuff.
And then the file contents is the actual byte data inside of it.
So that is the metadata that you would think about when you write, let's say, explanation
what your data set has. But the file system sees stuff like this. So file system sees the metadata
and the file contents. And when the metadata is accessed, this is done using these so-called
stat calls. So they check the stats or the status of the file. And the file contents are modified
by opening so-called file descriptors. So the file is opened. So if you're using like Python or
whatever like language, you usually have something like open a file and that is basically it opens
the file, it opens a file descriptor and then you can do like read and write calls to the file
that actually like take the data in and out of the file. So if we look at below,
We can see that, for example, if you run like an ls-l, that doesn't actually look at anything inside the file.
It will just check the metadata.
It will just show the permissions and ownerships of who owns the files and lists the file metadata.
And if you catenate the file with cat, so you just print it to the terminal,
know, that basically means that, okay, open the file or read only like file
descriptor, read everything that is inside the file and print it out into the
standard output.
So it will only access the file contents.
And if you don't have access to the file, or if you don't have permissions, then,
um, it doesn't, it can't, cannot do it, but, um, it, it will just try to access
the file contents and let's keep this as, as this kind of a, like a backdrop for
what we're about to demo then.
So we have a few demos.
So [name], do you want to describe the demos a bit?
Yeah.
So like in the previous one, so these are demonstrations.
So the intention is not that you follow along,
but that it's not that you type along,
but that you follow.
But there are instructions here,
and this is where the examples are.
And after each section,
is expected results which should tell you or give you an idea of whether your result if you run the
code is what I was expecting when I wrote this. So you can run them on your own and you can see
what happens. That's useful to do if you are ahead at the moment or if you want to do them later in
the exercise sessions. Okay. So what is the motivation behind the data? What is the,
like the, yeah. So let's go into the actual example. So I'll just make this a little bit
smaller so that we can see a terminal window here. Okay, maybe not quite that small.
And now I am actually in the folder with the examples. Why can't I type into this window?
I guess I have a broken connection. Good start. So I guess it's the demo effect.
Let's take a connection to the Triton cluster. Yeah, this is not working. Okay.
This is also taking a while.
So fortunately, I did already run these commands on the cluster and we have the expected results
panels.
It would still at the very least be nice to run them locally, but can you think of a reason
why I couldn't access Triton right now?
I don't know, but maybe you have them locally.
I do have the examples locally. It's just a very different disk system. It doesn't exactly
demonstrate what we wanted to demonstrate. This is a little bit annoying. It might be that login
is just slow. It's also slow to me. Okay, well, we can look at the files locally.
Oh, here we are. Great. Should I do the source? Okay.
So just that we can follow, you can more easily follow along with the commands. I'll do this.
So now when I type something here, okay, this is also not updating. Okay, that's fine.
So we'll just have this terminal now. That's fine. Can you see the lowest line? Let me know
if if the lowest line at the terminal is not visible. Can you make it a white background?
I am not sure how to do that. Right click or maybe it's too late to do it. Okay.
Okay, so I am in the folder with the examples
And the examples, let's also activate the conda repository.
I had all of this prepared.
But this is how it works, right?
Yeah, so in the example data what we have is like we have a code that just creates like a simple
example data set motivated by [name]'s like fitness tracker. Yeah, so this is an example,
it's a generated example but it's relatively close to what I have seen in actual research projects.
And I'm going to be doing things in good ways and bad ways and I don't think that anybody
in the research project is actually doing them in such bad ways, but anyway.
So there is a script to create this data, but let's just take a look.
So there's this data folder.
It includes activity data, which represents how much I have been moving according to a
fitness watch, for example, at a given time.
So let's take a look at 2008 and 10 is the month, so October.
And it includes a lot of files, well, it includes one file for each day of the month.
Let's look at 30.
And let's actually cut it so we'll see the data.
So the number here represents the activity level.
The last number here, the other one represents hour, and this is actually the index, so it's
actually the same as the hour.
So for each hour there is a number.
It's a single number, it's an integer, and we want to do some analysis on all of these
numbers.
So if you think about it, there's a large number of files here actually, I did the calculation.
So 7,300 files, it's not that bad, it's just my data, but if when I actually start doing
the research and I have the data for 200 people, 500 people, 1,000 people, that's a lot.
So it can really become a bottleneck, the number of files.
So let's go back though.
And for these examples, like throughout these examples, we will get some numbers and you
have to always think of these numbers like, okay, what are the scales between the different
things that we're doing?
What happened?
Same with the [name]'s MPI example, what is the scaling speed when you increase the number
of CPUs?
We also have to think about scaling here.
So think of these like, let's think that each file, imagine that they are 10 gigabyte files
or something like that.
So then suddenly we have a huge number, huge amount of data.
So then we can think about, okay, what are the savings that we would get if the files
would be a lot bigger or the number of files would be a lot larger.
Yeah.
If there's a, like you could have a measurement per second of this activity level, although
So I guess this particular level is really defined on a one-minute interval.
But that would already be a lot more text, but of course, it's not the only measurement.
You get the heart rate per second, for example.
You get a lot of measurements from a device like that.
And so you could have a much bigger file, but you can also have a lot more of these
really small files, which also is a problem on its own.
So let's check like a typical IO pattern now.
What happened?
The first thing I in fact wrote, and not just as an example. This is not just an example of
something that I'm purposely doing it in a bad way. This is actually the first thing I would write.
This readfiles.py. So what it does in short is just read all the
files in a for loop. We'll list all the files in the data folder. For each folder, list all of
these files in there. So this is the CSV files. Open and read. So I'm actually doing it in a
slightly better way than my first idea would be. I'm reading the text content and putting it in a
list and then turning that into a CSV file and then that into a pandas data frame. Probably the
first thing I would do is actually turn it into a pandas data frame here, but that would take a lot
of time. And actually, it would kind of obscure the fact that it's reading a lot of stuff because
it would be not just reading, but also doing useless computation between every file.
Yeah, we want to measure or demonstrate the reading.
So, I'm doing it in a much better and faster way than my first idea actually would be, but that's
That's partly to not obscure the fact that I'm really doing a lot of reads.
Okay.
So, now let's try this.
Oops.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, this actually does take a while.
You might notice that there's also a strange-looking command before the Python thing, and that
is the command called trace which is part of Linux system tools that can be used to trace.
It can trace different kinds of operations that the programs might do and what it can do is that
in this case we want to trace file descriptors so basically whenever files are being accessed or
done and then we have this -c there as well to produce like overall results or summaries
for the results. So we want to see what the Python program did
and what we get is something like this. Yeah so I guess these are how many times a file
was opened. That's 8000, so roughly the number of files we have. I guess, so this is asking
for file information. Yeah. And looking for a specific place in the file. Yeah. I mean
overall lots of operations. Yes, so we can look from the different columns that on the left we
can see what took most of the time. So it was the file opening that took most of the time and
stacking, so basically figuring out who owns the file, are we allowed to access the file,
this sort of stuff. That took the most of the time and you can see how many microseconds it took
per call or milliseconds, I don't know. What's the actual, it doesn't really matter.
I think it's percent. Yeah, it's percent of the time, so it's not quite seconds.
And then how many calls we have, and what is the call at the right side?
And the whole thing took five seconds, by the way.
So if we think about what the program was inside the program, we had a for loop that
opened files in a for loop. So for each file, it had to open the file, it had to access the
metadata and the actual data of the file, and it had to do it. And we can see that being reflected
here in the output. For each file, we did a lot of these open calls and we did a lot of these
stat calls. The files are really small. What we basically did is that we had to do it for all
files. Each of these operations was quite small, but they still have a lot of latency with them.
So let's, like a normal, normally in this kind of a situation where you want to access all of the data once, like you just want to go through the data.
A better solution is to usually bunch up the data into an archive, because then you don't have to like do these individual calls and it will speed up the code grammatically.
So one question was why did we have this many more file opens than
that we have files or data files and the answer is that we are importing Python libraries which
contain a lot of files, .py files and all sorts of different files. So we will actually
not get very close to zero at any point. So there's always going to be like a baseline
like a startup same with the like NPR programs you have a certain like startup things that you
always have to calculate as a part of the whole thing but then you can like... But that's a fixed
so when you increase the number of participants that part will not increase so it's kind of
yeah a fixed part of the computation. Let's look at the archive reading. So yeah now we have this
tar file. A tar file is a single file, but it's essentially just the contents of the files put
in right after each other. It's a very simple archive format. This is not even compressed,
so it's just actually the full contents of the files with some little bit of metadata in between.
Do you want to show the Python code quickly? Yeah, it is relatively straightforward.
Well, there is a difference between streaming mode and just read.
We want to be streaming because otherwise it will read the file multiple times.
That's just this particular tar opening library.
Otherwise we open the file once and then we get a list of, well, actually we don't get
a list of members because what this is doing is actually it's reading through this list
of files, like I said.
At the beginning, there's a marker, the file begins, then there's the file name and some
other information. This will actually contain the file name. Well, actually, this member.name
is the file name. We check that it's a CSV file from that. But then this extract file will just
go on and read the chunk of data that is the actual file. Then we read it and we append it
again to this list of texts. You notice that in this for loop, previously we had like before
we'll have for loop over the folders and then we had a for loop over the files in the folder and
then we opened each of them and you might notice that over here we have the open call at the outside
of the for loops so basically we open the tar file and then we go through the tar file each file in
there. So what we can expect from this is that okay, we probably have less open calls,
so maybe we should try it out. Before I do, just more for the audience than you,
are you expecting, if we just don't count all of the Python library importing and that stuff,
do you expect just one call to open the file and read? It is just one file.
Let's see. So I don't know actually how I would answer this question
because there are the Python file reads but the answer is not quite one.
So that was faster. It actually did take two seconds. So two compared to five.
So like it's still not trivial to process the data and to actually like stream it from the file
But we can notice that there's a complete difference in what calls are now the most
important ones. So now we notice that most of the time was actually just reading the data.
This is because now it can just go through the file and just read it from start to finish.
And it can read it in bigger blocks. So normally it can read something like 10 kilobytes
at a time, whereas previously all of the files were like only like a few hundred bytes or something.
So now it can read like multiple files at one time from the file system. So there's less read
calls. Previously there were 15 000, now there's only 2 500 and there's much less file open calls.
So in practice, if I wanted to answer the question I just started with,
it would be the block size of the system so it would be able to read one entire block at a time
but the files are stored in blocks so you actually do need to read multiple times
if the file is big enough. So at some point if the files are big enough to start
actually accumulating the read calls anyway but still you only need to have one stat call
for one file.
And there's good questions in the chat,
like can the tar file trick to use
in file transfers as well?
And definitely, like combining multiple files,
like if you need to do a transfer
between let's say your computer and the cluster,
and you need to transfer like a hundred files,
for each file, the transfer tool of your choice
has to write the files, write the metadata,
check the permissions, whatever,
and also do the transfer through the network.
And it's much faster to just process one file.
Of course, up to a point where the file is so big
that you might get into like,
it might just take too long to transfer one file
and it might crash or something,
but that's up to gigabytes.
So, so it's always faster until you reach those places.
And also there was a good question.
Uh, like, uh, can this be used with pickle objects, for example, in Python?
Like, well, there's other data formats that do this kind of stuff as well.
Like we will talk about this a bit that later, but this is just like a simple
example, but there's other formats that you can use that, that store everything
as one file and pickle is one of them, like it will store stuff in one file instead of
multiple files.
So I guess if you have a large number of pickle files storing different things, then if you
have a large number of files, you can use tar, of course, to combine them into one.
But of course, you could only create, potentially you could create just one tar file, so you
You can stream data into it if it doesn't fit in the memory, if you want to just make
one big tar file.
And remember here that tar is, like this example uses tar, but it can be other file format.
But the main point is that, do you have the files, thousands of files there, or do you
have them combined in some format?
Like it can be a mat file, it can be like a R data file, it can be a pickle file, it
can be whatever.
target is something that people quite often use and that's easy to demonstrate.
So there was one question, how did I create the tar file? One reason I chose tar here is that
it's available on essentially any Unix, POSIX file system. It's a POSIX utility. So there is this tar
command. So you can use this command. This is for reading.
This one is for creating the tar file from the data.
So this command exists on any Linux system but because of course I'm
a perfectionist and I wanted to make sure that you can run this even without the tar command
and there is also this create_archive, so if you want, you can also do this from Python.
But another thing just on that, there is this web dataset example at the end of the notes,
which we'll clearly not get into, but let's see.
But yeah, so that also uses the tar data format and has a nicer way of creating tar files and
these sharded tar files that are large. A large file with a lot of data, but still
multiple files so that you can read them in random order and all of that.
So that's a nice thing to look into. There was a good follow-up question there also that
does creating the tar file just move the slowness of opening files to another script?
And of course it does. In order to create the tar file, you first need to open all of the
the files, you need to load all of the files and create the target file.
But the thing is that, what accumulates, if you do it once, like pre-processing
step, instead of having the individual files, you collect them together, like
you do it once so that you don't have to do it again, then you can mitigate
some of the, like something you can like accumulate if you do it over and over again, like, let's
say you want to do the same analysis with different kinds of parameters and you always
access all of the files, then suddenly you can do like, I don't know, a thousand times
the same IO kind of a thing, and that will like accumulate.
If you're running the same thing many times, then it is useful to do this tar command
once, even though it of course takes some time. And the other thing is if the whole data doesn't
fit into memory once, then you will probably end up reading it multiple times, even in a single run.
So this should be common in machine learning. And then using a good data format for reading is
important. But let's go to the next example. So the next example is motivated by the machine
learning world, where basically quite often you want to load data in a random way. And in this,
tar is usually not the best way, unless you use something like the web dataset mentioned by
I don't know, because let's demonstrate what happens when you try to read the files in random.
WebDataSet kind of uses a trick in that it's not completely randomized.
But yeah, so essentially if you try to read random chunks from a file, that usually means you will
open the file and then seek until you find the place. It's like running a tape. You read through
the file until you find the place that you actually want to read and then you can read that chunk and
then you have to open the file again if the part you want to read is earlier. So random access is
not a great pattern for reading files in general. Yes. So you can imagine what the Python code
looks like. I'm just randomizing the list of files here. So let's just run this.
This takes a little bit longer, so here we had 1.73 seconds, 2.8, so not as bad as reading
all the files.
It ended up actually opening, here we open 580 times, read 2,500, okay.
Yeah, it had to open the same amount of, yeah, it had to open the same amount of files, but
like [name] said, now it has to like seek the different location where it wants to read.
So because the archive is one file, it has to suddenly like seek the correct place in the
archive and then read from there. So we get a lot more read calls because sometimes like when you
read, you might read a certain amount of data and your data is somewhere in the middle of that
like block of data that you want to read. And then you read more than you needed. So you read
basically just, you read more than you need, and then you read that part, and then you need to
go somewhere else and you need to read again. So that's why we get a lot of SQLs. It's still
faster than the individual files, but it's not good either. So for these, there are tools like
for random grids you usually want to have the data in some way that you can load the data in a
sequential order like as a one block but then randomize it in memory so instead of loading
the data from the disk in a random order you want to load the data into memory and randomize it in
memory because that is okay so I'll just show the example that comes next because that's the
chunked random access. So what we do here is this is a bit of a made-up case in that all of the
data actually does fit in the memory. But let's just think that if only 10 files fit in the memory
at a time and we want to have it somewhat randomized but not necessarily completely
randomized then we can extract the contents of 10 files and then once we have 10 files
we take a random permutation of those 10 files. So it's somewhat random but of course it's
not reading completely randomly from the file, it's just randomizing each chunk. So this
is commonly just good enough and you can also randomize the order of the chunks if you save
them in separate files. So that's a common way of doing it and it works well.
Yeah, this is what, for example, the web dataset uses. It loads, spreads the... If you have
a big dataset, the dataset is split into multiple TAR files in random ways, and then each of
those files is opened, read, and then the stuff is shuffled in memory. And because you
go load the different target files in the random order you basically get full randomness so you
don't have to ever like you don't have to read individual files you can still get one file.
Now let's see if the same thing happens as I saw previously and then I can ask you if you
can quickly say why it would happen. Yeah so why is this faster than the just reading the whole
archive in one go. And significantly faster every time.
Yeah. I think the thing here is that when you extract, well, I would guess that when
you extract the files or you read multiple chunks into memory, it can optimize the code
in a way that it doesn't have to, it can just pipe stuff into the chunks. It can
just – it doesn't have to do intermediate processing for each chunk one at a time,
but it can do it for multiple at one time. But I'm not certain.
Okay, maybe. Python usually doesn't do a lot of…
But then again, at this speed, it can be random noise as well. It's just random noise.
Yeah, but this is happening every time. This is repeatable. So, I'm just wondering. But okay,
Let's move on. One problem here is that the strace output – this is relatively good, I think,
but if you try to get all of the file read, for example, and do some proper profiling and not
just get the full sum in the end, it's not very readable. We haven't found great tools
for reading it. I don't want to say that these are not great. It's great that somebody took
the effort, took the time to write this. But there could be something better maybe around.
But in any case, these are what we found. It's great that people took the effort to write them.
Yeah, those tools can give you a bit more information of what files were accessed and
that sort of stuff which might be like if you don't know what your program is doing it might
be good to try out these tools. The second one has also like if you're running MPI programs and
you want just like only your run space on one of the tasks so you can just monitor one task
then that's pretty nice feature as well. But the main thing that we want to come across is that
this is what file access looks like and this is what the program tries to do and usually the best
like how could I say the best thing to do is to look at your program and see how it tries to access
the files if you can like if you if it's not hidden inside the program but but to think about
okay what files go into the program and what files come out of the program how many go in how many go
out and what is the way that the program tries to interact with the file system, because then you
can think about, okay, I can expect that, let's say one file access will cause certain amounts
of open calls and it might slow down the whole thing. Next, we could talk a bit about why is
this even a problem? If you run on your own computer, you might have a fast NVMe SSD or
something like that. Why is this even like a thing? Why are we talking about IO and these file calls?
The reason is that all of the HPC clusters, they usually have a network file system. We have a
low-structure file system. There might be other file systems in other clusters, but usually it's
something similar to what we have. There is a network file system. What happens when you try
to access a file there because the program doesn't know, right? The program just thinks that,
okay, there's a file system. I will try to do a file system call. It will do the same calls
whether you do it on an SSD file system or a network file system. It will do the file opens
and file writes and whatever. It doesn't care. It doesn't know what system answers those calls.
So, if you open the explanation, there is a diagram of a typical file system, like a network file system.
And what they usually are, like a Lustre file system, it's actually that there's multiple metadata servers that serve just the metadata.
data. And there's usually like corresponding or there's like
object storage service to actually store the data. And
whenever you are making a call, like you ask, let's say I want
to open this file, there is usually a file system client
that basically sends those calls then to the right places. So
when you try to access a file, you will send a call to the
metadata server that, hey, can I access this file? And we
actually is the file, because I don't know where is the actual content of the file, then that
response comes back to the client, which then if the response is like, yes, you can access it,
it will try to access the object storage server where it tries to access the actual file.
And there, the data, it will have to fetch the data from a disk where it actually gets the data
into and then it will send the data back. So you can think that there's like lots of overhead here
instead of like let's say your SSD in your computer which is fast but it's small and it's
not redundant or anything like that that is needed in the high performance computing system. What
happens is that instead of the data being right there in the SSD and the cores being served almost
immediately there's lots of network interactions like there has to be data transfer through the
network back and forth and this will call latency and then all of these individual calls
become longer and longer and this means that while they and usually in the programs while the
file system calls are being solved the program doesn't do anything like it doesn't continue
there's some programs that do like asynchronous file calls that they do stuff on the background
and this is of course good because then like it can continue working while the data is still
being fetched but but that is more complicated to program so usually it's better to not
not get the data or if you get the data from the file system like the shared file system you get
it in the right format because then you can minimize these latencies that can slow down the
program. Okay so basically is the the reading speed the bandwidth is I guess roughly the same
as you would have on a laptop or not that much slower but there's a lot of latency for accessing
the file through the network and also while making the stat call which is probably going
to a different server? Yeah, the file systems are of course very powerful, but the problem is that
there's hundreds of users using them at the same time, right? And there's a lot of people in the
network transferring MPI stuff as well, and they can be congested. And the data might just be like,
the disk is somewhere that it needs to fetch the data from the disk. So there's always going to be
like these intermediate steps that take time so that's why you don't usually want to like
waste time computing time to do this kind of IO calls. So that's another thing that
is I think good to bring up at bring back at this point so because file systems are not or just like
file access is not something you shuttle with Slurm you don't it is not a parameter that you
give the slurm and you submit your job. It's just a shared resource. If you manage to slow it down,
then you're slowing it down for everyone. You do have to do a lot to slow it down,
or multiple people need to be doing a good bit to slow it down.
If you have a thousand copies of a job and they all read a bunch of files,
that can do some damage. Then it will slow down for everyone. It's not just your job that
is slowing down for. That's an important thing to note. What else do we want to cover in six minutes?
Well, this is typical file system speeds, but I guess the latency is really the big thing
in this case. Because in the example we just did, it was all latency. The speed of reading
the file. The amount of data in the files was the same in each case.
There was also a good question in the chat about data formats to use. You should always
remember that if you can access the files using code, you can use an intermediate data
format. Let's say your original data is in CSVs, like [name]'s data. You can still have
the original data like that, but while you're working on the data, you can store it in a
better format, like a binary format or something like that, and work on it. Then at the end,
if you want to publish the results and you want to make it as readable as possible, you can
provide it in a different format. But during the processing, when the computations are being done,
it's usually important to like convert it into like a good data. So there's one more workflow
I want to mention in the last couple of minutes, a workflow thing. So it's kind of a cheat of
how to get away from having to deal with Lustre, which is if your cluster has local disks like
Triton has some subnodes then it's a very good idea to move your data into the local disk.
So by a local disk I mean something that's actually attached to the compute node.
You don't have to go through network to do any reading and that is still probably shared with
anyone else running on that same node but you don't have to use the network file system,
the shared file system. This is especially important for GPU jobs where you're doing like
GPU machine learning or whatever. Usually those machines are bought with fast SSDs for this
explicit reason because they are so data hungry, the deep learning models, that you need to have
the data locally or the GPU will idle. So it just cannot get enough data. So the local disks are
very important when you're doing like GP jobs.
Okay and there are also these RAM disks so any Linux system will have a
/dev/shm [shared memory] and that's also a file system but it's
actually in RAM so it's a really fast way of communicating.
If you have a lot of RAM you can put all of your
data into it but well you need to reserve it when queuing the job
and it is limited to RAM.
So if your data doesn't fit into RAM,
then there's no way you can use this to speed things up.
But it is still like, it's good to know about.
It can make things a lot easier and faster.
Yeah, for example, if your program
does like a lot of small intermediate files,
but it does them often or something like that,
like putting them into the RAM disk might be a good option.
Okay, so we are really probably getting right onto the lunch break.
One minute to go.
So anything you want to say before we wrap up?
We do have this web dataset example here which you can take a look at on your own and there
are also other exercises, of course, in the exercise session coming up.
That's all. Then let's go to the lunch break. If we go to the notes, there is some
feedback there. One minute while I switch. Okay, I've switched.
So, for some other daily notes, if you're registered, there's this bring your own code session. You can come and ask us questions. Or no, it's an exercise session, isn't it?
Well, I mean, you can come to have exercises, but also please do exercise code, basically, any kind of mentoring and individual follow up.
Also, many, and probably all of the partners you see listed on the website would be very happy to receive questions from about anything we discussed today.
anything we discussed today.
So go there, ask about how this applies to your cluster,
ask for help in how to configure things,
actually do it, all that stuff.
So the stream will stop now, right?
And we go only to Zoom after the lunch break.
Isn't that correct?
Yes, I think so.
Okay, so please fill in this feedback here.
Let us know all that stuff and have a good lunch.
See you later then.
See you.
Okay, bye.
Bye.
See you.
you