CodeRefinery.org
you
Test. Hello. Can anyone out there hear us?
Hello? Hello? Hello? Check, check.
So welcome back for day two of TTD for HPC. If we open our notes, which if you've registered
you should have this in your email. It's for people who have registered, so if you
haven't registered yet, please do so.
Yeah, and let's see, so what's the plan for today? We've got, well, today's theme
is interactive work. Or is it called day-to-day working with HPC?
Well, I mean, that's how the days go by when you work with HPC.
We have different names for it.
Anyway, so here you see, I guess this is all the instructors of today.
I'm [name], and with me is [name], [name], and [name].
But we can introduce ourselves a little bit more in the formal introduction time.
But for now, we've got an icebreaker. So if you open the notes, again, this should be in your
email. It's only for registered people. By the way, can anyone hear us?
I haven't seen any verification.
Let's see.
Test.
Okay.
Someone says audio is good.
Yeah.
So, what's our ice break and stuff for today?
So...
Well, I mean, there's a fun one.
What's your favorite free time activity?
I should answer it I can answer it live so in case someone doesn't know how to use this
or has never used this type of interface I click on the pencil and then I like swimming
I need to switch to [name]'s screen there we go now you can show
yeah so I clicked on this pencil here at the very top of this notes.coderefinery.org document
And then I edited another swimming.
What's the weather?
Yeah, I mean, this is terrible.
I definitely need to add skiing to the favorite things to do, just because the way it looks
outside right now.
Maybe we should have asked what's the weather and where you are.
Because that's sort of important, we can get a crowdsourced weather forecast.
So who expected to be waking up in this much snow today, wherever you are?
So, I mean, we've had on and off snow here in Helsinki for the last few weeks.
But today is another level.
This is like winter level.
And this was not in the forecast. It was completely unexpected.
Yeah. So it's a good day to be home.
Actually, should we update? Let's see. I want to add another question.
At least northern Sweden is having also snow, so it's not just in Finland.
Okay.
There were some people from Italy registered, so I don't know if they're here.
I doubt that they're having snow there.
Does it ever snow in southern Italy at all?
That's a very good question.
I don't know the statistic, but I would say it's extremely rare.
Of course, there are some mountains that it could have been there, but yeah.
Okay.
Let's see.
20 centimeters in Krukonummi.
That's more than here.
Netherlands is sunny, good.
It's getting close to 20 centimeters.
It could really well be 20 centimeters now in Espoo.
Let me look out the window again.
I mean Espoo is really big.
It's probably going to be the same everywhere.
It might be 10 centimeters here.
So if today is about day-to-day work on an HPC cluster, for people here, what's your
practices and so on?
What's your general spirit of things?
So for me, it's SSH to the cluster, and I tend to use a terminal editor on the cluster
itself to do most of my testing and development by SSH.
Yeah, same here. Opening some DMACS or screen so that I know that I can resume it later.
But yeah, terminal and cluster is... I don't know if it's the most favorite interface for
those who started later because for me terminal and cluster was something that was the only option.
I guess if you learn to code using a terminal editor anyway, if you have that skill already
then why not do the same thing on the cluster.
I'm going to show the workflow that I do but it's not maybe the best one so we're going
to talk about what you could do instead and other options that I don't actually use.
But yeah, my workflow is probably not the best
because I'm used to graphical editors
and I usually don't use them on the cluster.
But yeah, there's also some other really nice modern ways
of managing these things, like working
on the cluster, which you will see here now today.
And maybe we'll hear some ideas from you all.
So, for the Icebreaker, are there really only two working methods on the cluster?
The end-of-the-terminal and cluster in development on laptop, then transferring.
Also, how do you transfer to the cluster?
I was going to expect some notebook or something interactive, or at least I know some people
using those type of workflow, but of course it also depends on the cluster that not all
clusters support maybe notebooks or similar tools.
Right, yeah.
I, a few weeks ago, learned a new trick with Git in order for working on the cluster.
So before, my problem had always been if I'm...
So I was in a place with a really laggy internet connection.
So I just couldn't use the terminal on the cluster.
But I also didn't want to do local work, and then git commit, and then push, and then
more local work, and git commit, and push again, and so on.
And then go to the other side and have to git pull every time.
So I saw that I could configure git on the cluster, work locally, I'd always be doing
work and then commit amending it so that way I'm not making a new commit but updating the past one
and then force pushing and it would automatically check out the latest changes on the cluster
so that I could just run the thing.
Oh there's a good comment about Mosh here. Mosh is pretty neat. It's like
How would you say, it's like a SSH, but it uses UDP and has more local echoing.
So that way it can pretend to reduce the latency quite a bit.
However, since it uses UDP instead of TCP, it doesn't work at ALTO because our firewall
blocks UDP connections.
Which is also a problem for other reasons, but well, what can you do?
Yeah, so I don't have that much to say.
All right, but it's now 1 past 10 in Finland and 1 past 9 in the Central European summertime.
Should we officially start?
Yes.
Alright, so welcome to the second episode of Tuesday's Tools and Techniques for High
Performance Computing. I'm [name], I'm a staff scientist at Aalto University
and here with me today there are other colleagues from Aalto. [name], do you want to mention
something about yourself?
Yeah, so I'm [name]. I've worked in my current team here with [name] for about,
what, seven or eight years now, I guess. And I started off as a, well, HPC
system kind of person. But over time, we've gone more and more towards user support.
And now I'm part of the research software engineer team.
And with us today, there's also [name], who is actually one of the research software engineers.
[name], do you want to mention something about yourself?
Well, I'm one of the research software engineers.
What else is there to say?
That's good.
Good, and [name], do you want to say hi?
Hello everyone, yes, I'm also one of our teams.
Excellent.
So if you watched the previous episode,
the structure of the day is pretty similar.
We have two hours of kind of lecture-based streaming.
And after that in the afternoon,
for those who want to try what is being shown
during the morning, we can actually do it all together
in a Zoom session.
so because of this the morning will be recorded and the afternoon of course will not be recorded
so that people can interact. Other practicalities for the days you have all if you register for this
course you have received this notes share notes document at this notes.coderefinery.org
in practice this is like a google docs you can think it like that where by clicking the pencil
you can edit it and this is a good way to ask for questions and that's going to be us following your
questions or comments and plus other people that are involved with CodeRefinery. What else
other practicalities there's the possibility to get some credits one ECTS and for those who are
planning to get the credit you can join the zoom session in the afternoon where we can discuss more
for the exercises and these other practicalities. Anything else to mention, [name]?
Let's see, so what are the things that can go wrong?
So if the whole stream dies, that means my computer has crashed, which is very rare but possible.
Just hang around and you will return shortly.
Assuming that Helsinki still has internet connectivity.
Did you say how important it is to ask questions?
Yeah, the notes document is very useful. From the last episode last week, it was maybe one of the
the most favorite things in the survey after the episode because you can really ask any
sort of question. The goal of this course is to make it useful for you. We are not able
to cover everything and in two hours it's very difficult to go deep into any specific topic.
So feel free to ask even more advanced questions or even you know beginners questions because
any question is a good question. Yeah. It's good already if you have tested this document
now during this icebreaker, it's good to make sure that you're able to edit and so on. So
feel free to test it and type. And I can already ask for whoever in our team is going to edit
this that we could now start with the first section.
So you have also received the link to the materials and if you didn't receive it, someone
will paste it now to this notes document.
The material has various sections and the goal of today is to kind of focus on the daily
work with the cluster.
So not the kind of theory of slurm jobs or whatever resources, CPUs, GPUs, this is literally
what you do every day with the cluster. So I'm going to start with a quick motivation
that the goal of this this is the kind of lecture lesson that I wish I had 15 years ago when I
started working with this thing because yes I got introduced to SLURM, I learned how to submit jobs,
I learned the kind of peculiarities of the storage systems attached to the cluster but nobody has
has ever told me how to daily, day-to-day work
with the cluster.
Is it better to work on my computer, to work on the remote?
So the whole two hours for this morning are exactly this.
How do you work in the cluster?
Do you work on your machine?
Do you work on the remote machine?
Do you transfer the data from your local
to the remote all the time?
Or do you keep everything in the remote?
There's so many ways, and in a way,
there's not a right or wrong way to do this.
This is also important here because there's many of you,
some of you might be in the early days
of working with cluster,
some of you might have been working with cluster
for 20 years.
It's important that you also share what is good for you
in the notes document,
because we are truly learning from each other.
We don't need to go through the text of this page,
you can read it later if you want,
but I want to spend a couple of minutes on this picture.
So what I think that many users,
What I see also when I'm helping users
that are starting to work with cluster
is the difficulty in understanding
kind of the geography of an HPC cluster.
Meaning literally, where are the physical bits
and why does it work like that?
So in this simple schematic,
we have on the left-hand side,
basically the internet, this bubble, this cloud,
and attached to the internet that might be your laptop
home or your workstation in the office and usually through the internet of your university you might
have some network drive there's multiple of them whatever your university or research institution
uses for storing data on the right hand side there is the cluster of course this is a very simplified
picture of a cluster but usually it works like this that there is a login node so it's like a
server a remote computer where you can enter the cluster and then once you are in the login node
you can basically start working with the cluster you might submit a job so something that is non
interactive like we did on the first episode or you might need to do some debugging on the
actual cluster so you could request an interactive node so that you move from the login node to some
CPU node or maybe GPU node and then what is important to see that this connection between
the nodes and between the login nodes these are very fast very fast connections so that the local
storage attached to the cluster whether it's this scratch storage very large and very fast
or the kind of home folder is very different from what you be what might be the home folder
on your machine or other data storage cloud storage that your university is giving you.
So of course the speed of this type of connectivity within local cluster comes with some compromises
meaning that for example if you would truly need to run some GPU computation that is very fast but
the data is stored in the cloud storage of your university you have a bottleneck you have a data
transfer bottleneck and it's not going to work. On the other end, cluster comes with the so-called
scratch disk, whatever the name might change in different cluster, and usually the scratch disk
is really optimized for fast IO, meaning that you don't have GPUs idling, waiting for data to come,
but you have to pay this kind of speed with the price of the fact that usually, if not always,
scratch is never backed up. So it's fast, it's large, but it's not backed up. And so you understand
with this type of physical limitations and technical limitation, one is to build a workflow
on top of those, so that you can make sure that maybe when something important is done, it's over
and it's in scratch, you need to transfer it back to your university storage or to your laptop.
or maybe working interactively with GPU nodes
might be very expensive in a sense
that your cluster policies might not allow you
to stay idle on a GPU node for many hours.
So then you need to figure out how to work locally
and then deploy on the clusters.
So all this will be covered in the next two hours.
Just a brief mention that as you can understand now,
We are working in a remote system.
So it's important, yes, to understand the geography,
where you are right now with the terminal.
Are you in your local machine?
Are you in the login node?
Are you in a dedicated node?
But what is also important to remember
that these are shared system.
There's other people connected to the same system.
And so it's important to follow the cluster etiquette.
There is no, how can I say, 10 simple rules
on what to do or how to follow the cluster etiquette.
But there's a very nice research software hour episode
on this topic.
So it's an interesting one.
Adapt, of course, with the practices of your cluster.
Maybe if there's one thing of the cluster etiquette
that you must always remember
is to not run computations in the login node.
This will be most likely reminded
and remember for the next of the day.
But this is the most typical mistake
that even most advanced user are doing.
So, well, we can talk about the homework
in the afternoon Zoom.
So now [name], let's of course start
with project arrangement because your local projects
in your laptop might be a bit different
than the project in the share system.
Yeah, I will try to switch to my screen.
Yes, like it worked.
So we will head to project arrangement.
So yeah, I mean, if you asked me,
a lot of the daily work starts
with how you organize your projects.
And there's definitely some good and bad ways of doing this.
this in probably a lot of ways that are good in some cases. And this is something that people
rarely talk about. It's like, okay here's your space, go do things. You can treat it like your
computer which might be organized well or not organized well. But let's start with a story.
So there's a file which I probably have. It's a makefile and I really liked it because I
completely automated one of my first projects I ever did when I started my PhD, and I would
like to find that file again as a demo of Makefiles, but guess what?
I can't find it.
Even though I'm pretty sure it's not deleted, and I'm pretty sure it's backed up somewhere.
But it was in a directory that probably got compressed, and that was probably in another
directory that then also got compressed and is sitting around somewhere.
So this is a good metaphor, I think, for what can happen.
So if you're not careful when enough time passes, then you can lose track of what you've
got.
Even you lose track of things, how will anyone else be able to keep track of things?
Has anyone else here ever lost a file this way?
Like, do any of you have things that are so, well, that you think you have, but you can't find anymore?
I mean, there is a whole structure of backup of old computer that contains backup of the
previous computer, which contains backup of previous computer. And like everything from
high school further should be there somewhere. I have no idea where.
For me, I noticed that sometimes when joining a new project, maybe others might not be familiar
with the fact that Scratch is not backed up and not familiar that we are sharing the same
resources. So I had people deleting my folder because they thought that it was just some
temporary. They're like, oh, I didn't make this, so it must not be needed. And then,
so I guess that's another thing. When you have multiple people there, you have to
have the sharing mechanism and know who's responsible for what. Also, how do you know
if you even can clean something up in the future. Well, that's something we can talk about later.
So here is something we can start with. So in the notes, please go there and write
how your joint projects are organized, if you have any. So while we're talking,
please keep adding these and at the end we'll go through and discuss them.
There's a good question in the note, should we use English-only local language allowed,
only 8.3 format or long file names? Let's get to that at the end, but do keep adding these.
So my first thought for keeping things arranged is divide up your work into what goes together.
So, for example, this is one project of mine, this is another project of mine, and so on.
So one of my original problems was that I put all of my work into one folder, and then
in there I had subfolders for different things I was doing, and probably even subfolders
in there.
So they got recursively compressed.
Like I compressed an inside one, then an outside one, and I lost track.
So what I'd say is try to keep everything at one top level, decide what goes together,
give it a name, and that name is unique.
For example, I would call some of my projects like lgm for lattice glass model.
And then I had directories called lgm.
And wherever I saw that directory name, I knew it was supposed to represent this project.
And then once you have the projects in directories, whatever's in one of the project directories
is always managed the same way.
So for example, you always either use git for it, or you transfer data with rsync or
something like that.
And we'll talk about that next.
And then I'd recommend everything at least have a minimal readme for you that lets you
know what's in there.
to read me is useful to other people, that's even better. But a little note that says this
is what this was and how I was using it. So here's an example that might be from one
of my projects. I have something which I call project A, and then it has a bunch of data.
So the data is too much, I don't want to store it and track it with the main project things.
So I make a different directory called project-a-data.
And then whenever I start writing things, different people will have access to that.
So I make a separate directory again called project-a-paper1.
And so on.
And then these aren't subdirectories of each other, but all at the same level.
So I can easily find them.
When you're sharing these, either everyone has their own local clone with Git, for example,
and that's often used for code or papers or things like that.
Or there's one shared folder that everyone edits, which basically should only be used
for things like data, because people editing the same code is not a good idea.
So how do you organize your top-level projects?
Do you have these deeply recursive structures or do you try to keep it all flat and so on?
Anyone else here?
Well, I mean, that's a very good question, and in the code refinery lesson that is linked
to this material, we try to basically recommend a usual project structure. I think that the
advantage of sharing more or less the same project structure with the subfolders is that
others who might join the project later, they might already be familiar with the folder structure
or the usual scenario that if you win the lottery and move to a desert island, other
people know where to find the different bits. In general, of course, I really like what
you mentioned about having multiple kind of project subfolders because it on one hand
one can think that okay this is extra work but this is truly data management in practice
because you can really have let's say this project a paper one can be you know only couple
of users should have read and access there because those are the authors of the paper
and project a paper two there will be other people so you don't need to truly share everything
with everyone else, which is a bit of an issue
that we have noticed in our cluster
with these gigantic project folders.
But in general, I mean, maybe talking with each other
and agreeing on these policies is the best.
What is your experience, [name]?
Yeah, I mean, it's a good point about the master project
folders.
Actually, it will get, let's go on
maybe we can talk about our own arrangement because there's more of this later on down.
Okay, so directories within projects. So once you've got a project,
then try to keep stuff organized within that. So this is probably pretty obvious.
So for example, within my proj A, I might have the code, some original data, scratch data,
which is not tracked and can be deleted, outputs or documentation, the paper stuff, and so on.
And of course the arrangement above some of these papers and so on were separated out,
but if it is together you'd keep it unique likeness.
This is probably pretty obvious. The last thing you want to do is have to come back in
five years and someone says please can you share your code and then you have to
go looking for code everywhere or you come back in two years like okay we have
to delete the original data because of privacy or something like that and you
can't find where the original data is because it's mixed with all the other
things. So keep it organized at the start. Next is directories for teams. So oftentimes on a
cluster, you'll get allocated one directory for your project, which everyone has to share.
So same for our cluster. If you're in a group, you get a group directory. Like for example,
it might be called networks and for the complex networks group and then um how do you divide this
up so for example here we see scratch project with some big number and i think this is similar
to the naming scheme on CSC clusters for example and maybe others on our cluster it's text names
but that might be unique. So then inside of there, there's often directories for each user.
So for example, user1, user2, user3, and user4. And then inside of the user directories is the
code for different things. Code for project A, code for project B, user2, code for project A.
and then these are tracked and synchronized with git and if you need to
you can go directly looking at other people's code but you don't modify it
you only use version control or something to track but then what about
data sets and so on so then that would be in a different shared folder for
example project a common data which is managed manually or however and then the
code refers to the data in this location by either the full path or saying ../.. for
two parent directories.
Yeah, okay. And I think this is probably what most of us instructors do because we're all from the
same place. Yeah, we still have a couple of minutes, so how about this code arrangement?
Oh, I forgot about this part. So, the installable software packages. So,
wait, what's this going to be? So, if you have code directories like this, it works, and they
can import each other. But once you start getting a bunch of code that's relatively stable and
multiple people use, you can split this off into another separate package separate from your
analysis and so on. And then you would package that as, say, a Python package or C package or
whatever and then that's tracked separately and we have an example of making a python package here
and if you do this you can even install an editable version
which means that whenever you modify it the changes are directly visible
um i have a feeling something's missing here is this basically i don't know if something's missing
but maybe a question that I have that would it be like, let's say that we work in the same
research group and we maybe have agreed on a shared conda environment so that we can all
stick to the same versions at least for a few papers. Would it be the best to have a shared
place where we all store this shared conda environment or maybe even turning this
conda environment into a module if it's possible? What would be your recommendation?
I think shared Conda environments are a really good idea, and could be done.
On the other hand, once I was working on a project, and I had started writing a shared
library for this.
So a library that would read the data and do some basic preprocessing, and then everyone
else would be using this library.
But somehow the arrangement got so that people needed to make some changes to this library
for their own things. So people would go and do the changes themselves to it, and then
it would break things for other people. And I forget, maybe it was in a shared environment
on there. So someone would modify the code, and then suddenly other people's code stopped
working.
So, this is not necessarily a problem with having the shared environment, but versioning
the code better and making sure that backwards compatibility is maintained unless it's decided
to be broken.
But yeah, this is sort of an intrinsic problem when the code is going to be changing, that
you need an environment for everyone's own thing.
So at the end of the day, it's good to talk with your colleagues and agree on whatever
is your preferred policy.
So we are perfect with our timings.
And I think we could basically move to the next section, which is about data systems.
Are there any good questions in the thing?
Yeah.
Some interesting questions on the folder structures and yeah, yeah.
So there's a good comment here.
Maybe the last one.
Yeah.
Do you want to comment exactly on that?
The last one.
Well, I'm commenting on the one about recursive structures.
So yeah, I mean, recursive structure is nice and that's what I originally did.
But at some point, once I got too many projects and the recursive structure got too big,
it became too hard to find things.
So I said flat structure with the main metadata being the name.
So for example, now I know on any computer I can list my git directory.
And then it will have a list of all projects.
Or put it another way, I know on any computer I can list my git directory, or list my research
directory, and that will contain every name that I might possibly need to know.
And stuff won't be hidden too deeply.
So that works for my project directory, or my arrangement, but maybe not others.
Maybe it can be kept clean or recursive.
So yeah, for searching metadata, well,
I try to make sure the name includes everything
that I might want to search for with this kind of naming
scheme that I showed.
And yeah, for the last question, probably the paper directories
wouldn't be on this cluster, but by having it
as the separate thing, then it doesn't
to be there, for example. But yeah, it's more of an example that way. Okay.
Excellent. So now it's exactly 30 past, so we could see what would be the next adventure.
And I think we're going to talk about moving data around.
to Data Sync. Yes, so should I take over the screen share? Yeah, maybe. Let's do. How about
I start the introduction and then we'll give you the screen share. Yeah, so.
So, yeah, Data Sync. So, can someone add this to the notes?
So, we often learn about things like version control for sharing code, which works well
and definitely should be used, but what happens once you get gigabytes of data or more that
needs to be shared around between multiple clusters, or your own computer and the cluster
and so on?
How do you transfer this?
So obviously there's the answer of SSH, SCP, rsync, and so on, but are there any better
ways?
And that's what we're going to talk about now, in addition to the basic ways.
So first off is make a data plan.
So who has ever had a case where you're working on a paper and you email the manuscript to
everyone and then you get all the emails back with all the changes and now suddenly you have
five different copies. Unfortunately yes. Unfortunately yeah. So of course that's why
people these days use things like Overleaf and so on but that's a that's part of the data plan
But for data, you can't do the same thing. So first step, think about what you've got.
And the different common operations you might have are having original data and making a copy
for analysis, archiving data when you're done, moving the data from place to place during
the project and moving the data but it might be modified on both sides.
And when data might be modified on both sides, that's when you start getting really confusing
things happening.
And you have to be really careful.
So let's get started.
So here's an example of a data plan that I might use for a project.
So just to summarize, let's say I'm doing some sort of analysis.
I've collected data from some instrument, like a microscope or something, and the data
is on my computer.
And let's say I need so much computing power that I might be using multiple clusters.
plan is that the original data can get synced to clusters. So that's this input data. And input
data is only modified on my laptop. So anytime in the future, I would only, if I need to change
the data, first I update the laptop, then transfer it out everywhere. So that's one way.
The cluster can do computing. For example, making these computed directories.
And from any cluster, those are only transferred back to my laptop. So there's never a question.
So the cluster always has the latest data. And then, for example, analyzed is always
then regenerated on my laptop, for example. Okay, and that can keep things organized.
So how do we actually transfer? So, [name], are you ready to screen share?
Yes.
Okay.
So, first off is transferring data.
And I'll leave it on my screen until I'm ready for the next part.
So, transferring data is relatively easy.
So you've probably heard of tools like SCP or SFTP, and probably also Rsync.
So all of these use SSH as the transport protocol.
In fact, well, you'll see here in HPC,
almost everything uses SSH.
For that, if you set up an SSH config file,
which we might see later today,
but I won't go through now,
it will make things much easier because you can
define all the options once and just give a name.
If you have data that's very,
very massive like multi terabytes you're transferring around Europe then there's
some other protocols people might use but if you need those you'll just learn
them. And the main thing I've been emphasizing here if you have two copies
of the same data be really careful they don't get out of sync which is why I
emphasize so much, where can data be edited, and so on.
So rsync, [name], what do you like to show?
I will switch to your screen.
Yeah.
OK.
And you can make it a little bit wider now.
Yes, I can preview.
OK.
So before you walk me through the example,
I'll just show you what I have.
Because I have a data folder in one of the example folders.
I guess I should have then followed your example
and created a code folder separately.
But now we have a data folder in here in the web datasets
example that we used last week.
So, the data folder contains six files and we need to get these to the cluster.
Okay, so what should I do?
So, do you have SSH set up to the cluster?
Yes.
Okay.
In fact, I have a tab open where I already have SSH to the cluster,
because that makes it helpful to have echoing the commands down here.
Yes.
Okay so right now we're on your computer. So I guess we start with rsync, the command.
Yeah. And then the syntax is sort of like copy where it's source to destination.
Yeah so I guess we move the entire folder.
Did you say first the destination? First the source.
right so it goes source to destination so data we do 'data/' everything or
that's what I would do yeah we can do recursive if we do 'data/'
everything we need to create the folder first so I would recommend as from what
I generally do I always use the whole directory names and then a slash ('/') on the
end. And then for the destination, also the whole directory name with a slash on the end.
Yeah. So sort of like cp, whenever you copy a file with cp, it might put it inside of the
destination folder, or it might give it that exact file name as the destination. Yeah,
this is something that's always a little bit confusing to me. So yeah, I basically always
try twice. Yeah. Fail on the first time. So my recommendation is always use slashes on
the end and always give the final name you want. So if we do try to not all the F I colon
Scratch.
Work.
Maybe writing this out is not the most interesting thing, but we are already almost there.
Now, this is the same io-example/webdataset.
Okay.
okay but there is no data folder there so we do need either to do it recursively
or so if you give it'll automatically make one name on the end so if over this
should work if web data set exists and you do and you add a data slash on the
end yeah like this yeah so it will make a data directory so it wasn't recursive
So maybe this is a difference between our versions or our normal usage but well I will
make it recursive -r and it's taking some time
here so now it's not I didn't set it to interactive so it's not printing out what it's copying
It does take a moment to copy this data and a big part of this actually is just the latency
of accessing the cluster, getting a connection to the cluster.
You want to control-C and give the -i option.
Let's do that.
We'll see what's going on.
So it already copied the first two files and it's copying the third one.
So one cool thing about rsync is it will resume transfers that have already started.
It will, if you cancel a transfer in the middle, it doesn't lose the partially transferred
file.
It can't preserve timestamps.
Yeah, so all the existing ones
were already there.
So you can preserve timestamps, so that way
it will see, okay, is the timestamp the same? Then it knows it doesn't
need to check it again. It will do checksums on the files.
So basically make sure that everything
is like it will read through the file, compute a checksum of it
to make sure that bit by bit it is exactly identical
on the source and the receiver.
And if you've changed just a small part of a file,
it will only modify those same ones.
Should we demonstrate that?
Or I guess it's hard to do that.
So does it go file by file?
Yes, I think by default it goes file by file.
You can also do partial transfers and then it splits the file up.
What do you mean by partial transfer?
So it will split the file into pieces, transfer those pieces one by one,
and then reconstitute the file on the other end.
So that if for some reason the upload gets cancelled,
it doesn't have to restart from  it doesn't have to do the entire file again.
Yes.
Yes, exactly.
Yeah.
But that's mainly for the first time you transfer or  I mean, if you have reason to expect
that it might get canceled if it's a really big file, then that's useful.
But okay.
Actually, without breaking the archive, the tar archive, you can modify by just adding
stuff to the end.
So I'll do this.
So this will be modifying the last file in the archive, actually, because I don't know
how to write headers for new files, but that's not a problem.
That's fine.
Okay, so let's just do a new file content, and then the same command again.
Yes.
That was really quick.
Even the last file, I think it did actually a partial.
Yeah, it did an update instead of copy.
So it checks, it sees what's there, and would only transfer the new stuff.
So yeah, basically rsync is the thing to use.
It's got options for only transferring files which are newer on the source side than the
receiver side, very powerful include and exclude kind of options, preserving timestamps, archiving
everything, including timestamps, remissions,
that kind of things.
Dry run, so it would print what would happen before you
actually do it, and so on.
Anyway, we can play with that some more later.
Should we go to the two-way syncing?
Yeah, so this was only one way, and that's
the main downside with our sync.
Yeah.
OK.
So if I delete a file or modify a file on the other side,
Yeah, it doesn't get overwritten, I guess, unless there's a change on my laptop.
But yeah, so let's do the two-way example.
So whoever has done two-way syncing of data for clusters and stuff like that?
I mean, I did set it up once on my laptop, on my laptop and cluster, but I think I just
After I changed laptops, I just never did it again.
It was really useful as long as the network connection worked.
Okay, so the thing with syncing data two ways is that you have to remember what's updated.
So imagine you sync things. Do you always take the file that has the newer timestamp?
Well, what if it's been modified on both sides?
Then you would lose the fact that they've both been modified without warning.
So any kind of good enough two-way syncing needs to record the state of what was last
there.
And the program I've used for this before is called Unison.
So there's a different thing called Unison.
So make sure you get the right one.
Actually, yeah, there is a link there.
So I did prepare by installing Unison, but is there, do you want to make some points
about installing it before we continue?
So Unison is something that's not usually installed on clusters.
It is in typical Linux package repositories.
So it used to be Unison needed to have the exact same version on both sides, which was
a bit of a problem.
But since the latest ones, that's not necessary anymore.
But we can look at installation into exercise sessions.
That's not interesting now.
Yeah.
Okay.
The thing that I did notice is that my version at least still requires exactly the same version
on both sides.
So I have set it up correctly, but that happens.
So what options do you use here?
That's a good question.
I could check what I used when I was trying, but I think just the folder names.
Do I need anything else?
So the folder name for the source, and then it needs to be 'ssh://'.
Oh, right.
Ssh.
And then the address, and another '//'.
And now the path.
Yes.
On the other side.
Okay.
Does it already exist on the other side?
It seems to have noticed some changes.
So I think it already exists on the other side.
Because isn't it the same place you've just rsynced it?
Yes.
OK.
OK, so on the server side, it is a new directory.
It has been deleted since the last time I used Unison.
OK, but I could give it a completely new directory.
So let's call it data unison, just as a demo.
Yeah.
So now it can start from scratch.
Yes.
Okay, so we get this blurb of text
and I guess it's just warning that it's a,
it's not finding the last date.
So it's a completely new.
Yeah.
Okay, and here, it will prompt for every single directory, the new things, what is new.
And F means follow the recommendation.
So it sees that locally you have something, on the cluster you have nothing.
So if you push F, it will propagate it to the cluster.
and then push y to accept and there it's transferring.
And I guess it will take a while.
Yeah.
So now it's copying all of the files across.
Yes.
It asked only about the folder,
but it's copying all the files.
Yeah.
I mean, yeah, it will take a while.
I guess we don't have to wait for it to finish because...
Okay.
We can move on to the next thing.
Yes.
And this will transfer all five files, I guess.
Yeah, all six of them.
Yeah.
In the exercise session, I guess we
can demonstrate working on how you can modify things.
Oh, OK.
So yeah, if I'm.
Maybe let's wait for it to finish to demonstrate the syncing.
Yeah.
So there's something more to demonstrate with Unix.
And then we can just wait, because it's almost done.
Yeah.
So once it's done, can you delete one file
from the cluster and then modify one file locally?
OK, so in the data folder, we have these files.
I already modified file number 5.
So let's do that.
So I locally modified file number five.
Here I'm on the cluster.
And I have the data unison folder here.
That's the correct one.
So let's delete file number zero.
OK.
And now I should be able to run it on either side,
I guess, because it's a two-way thing.
But let's do it here.
So now I'm sorry.
on the laptop side here. Now you go back to laptop and it notices it's deleted. Okay, I'll press F
and there's a change. Number five has changed so accept and then Y. Oh, I need to press Y. Okay
Okay, and there it goes.
Yeah, it's all done.
Yeah, so Unison is pretty cool.
But I guess that for the afternoon,
if people wanna try this,
we will be there in the Zoom to help them.
Maybe we still have nine minutes before the break.
I was thinking that it would be nice to continue
and stay on this data section
to at least mention git-annex that is there in the material.
We will not have time to demo it,
but I really like the mounting data from place to place,
which in practice is SSHFS.
So we still have eight minutes.
[name] and [name], would you like to continue
and wrap up this section?
And then later-
Yes. We continue.
Sounds good.
Maybe I'll switch to my screen to talk about git-annex.
Okay.
So git-annex is a tool
So, it uses git, obviously, but it allows you to track large files.
So it doesn't check the large files into git, but only remembers the metadata about things.
And then it allows you to move these files separate from all the git history.
So maybe I won't show the whole demo because it's here, but basically I have this repository
called video processing.
If I went in here and ran git annex list ttt4hpc, it shows all these files.
So notice there's a raw file here.
And so that's a folder name in the video processing.
Correct.
Yes.
Yeah.
And here we see git annex has tracked, these are all the large files, and they are all
on here, which is my desktop.
They're also all on Triton, which is the cluster, and the output files are in Allas, which is
the web, the object storage.
So this allows us to have a git repository with all the videos and people to help with
processing them, but the data itself is stored only on places designed for big data.
There's some advanced stuff you can do here, exercises if you want, but we didn't really
intend to talk about this because it can take its whole other lesson.
Okay.
So I guess the really cool thing here is that you can version control everything like in
Git and use Git commands here, but then just download one file at a time so you don't need
to have all of them.
So it's very easy to get the data file that you need.
Yeah.
And the biggest comparison with Git LFS, Git LFS has one place you can store the files.
So the metaphor I use is Git LFS is made by GitHub, so with Git LFS you can only store
the large files in one place, which is GitHub, while Git Annex is truly distributed.
And it's a lot more complicated, but that's because there's this whole other layer of
understanding where all the big files are, and giving rules for storing some files in
some places but not other places and so on. Which is really appropriate for the big scientific
data concept. But my recommendation is if you want to use this, come talk to someone
that's used it. If you're at Alto, well, that would be me, and we'll help you get set up
because it can be confusing otherwise.
OK, should we go on?
OK, I will scroll on down.
So mounting data from place to place, which is SSHFS.
OK, OK, should I do the demonstration?
Yeah, I'll switch back to [name]'s screen.
Okay, so I'm really essentially staying on the laptop side here. Let's do pwd again.
Maybe I want to mount the entire web dataset folder so that I can access the project.
So can you clear your screen so we can be sure? Yeah. Okay, so I'm currently in my
local copy of the web dataset folder, but I want to navigate out of it.
it and create a new folder. This will be the web dataset folder on the cluster. And it's
obviously empty. So what do I do to get it to actually have the data from the Triton
folder. Should I just go on my side or do you want to? Yeah, so to do the mount the command
on Linux is sshfs. Yeah, okay. And then it's the source and the destination.
Okay, this is the other way around.
compared to the previous two commands.
But it's still the source and destination.
So it's going from...
Oh, right. It is. The source is now on Triton
and the destination is the laptop.
The meaning of source and destination are backwards.
Okay.
Made it clear, so sorry, let me get the path to the folder.
OK.
So it's the cluster name, and then colon path to the folder,
and then the local folder name.
And the local folder now needs to be empty
because it's a mount point.
Yes.
OK.
So here we go.
And that was fast because no data is being transferred.
It did an SSH connection, but not much more than that.
So now we can list and list the files in the WebData Triton, and it actually contains files.
So that's nice.
So what you're seeing here is actually on the cluster.
Every time you list...
So we have the unison folder here.
So every time you list this directory,
it's actually listing on the cluster
and transferring the results back to you.
Any time you open a file, then it's
also opening on the cluster and transferring it back to you.
Yeah, it is pretty fast.
It really works almost like it's local.
OK, so yeah, this is also nice.
All the data is now in one place,
but I can edit them locally on my laptop.
Yeah.
And this is good when you need to open and quickly browse
small files.
Like say you're opening up images that
plot that you're making.
But it's not good for opening big data
because if you opened a 1 gigabyte file,
it would have to transfer that whole 1 gigabyte file
before it opened on your side.
And that would probably be a little bit slow.
anything bigger, well, it gets even slower.
But I can run any program that I have on my laptop with the data in these files.
And I can unmount it so that I don't, oops, I can unmount it so that I don't break my file system
when if I disconnect from the internet yeah okay okay so um yeah and that's basically
the summary here should we look at any any good questions we've got I'll switch to the notes
Well, there were good questions in the notes document.
Most of them were already answered.
Maybe we could have a break now, 10 minutes, and then eventually consider some of the questions
that we received.
That's good.
So keep on writing questions, exactly.
And we can be back in the stream at 10 past the hour.
Yeah, there's good stuff here.
Okay.
See you later.
Bye team.
Bye.
you
Hey, welcome back.
So we are a little bit behind on schedule.
Should we take a quick moment to look at the questions though or just get back to them
at the end?
I've been answering many through the break.
I think we can go on.
Okay, let's move on.
So the next section here is code sync and the main thing here to talk about, so I will
skip the demo, but the main thing to talk about is why is code different or when is code different?
And the main point that you already mentioned in the motivation is that code changes quickly
and has different versions. So, if you have a code base that you've been using for a while
that the whole group is using then there's probably multiple branches and if you have
one shared repository on the cluster then you can't just go and do git branch my stuff
because everybody else will see the same change.
So you want to give multiple copies for each person and some global repository where all
of the different versions exist at the same time. You probably also have different environments,
different prerequisites or different requirements for all of these versions. That's why a lot
of the time just the things we did with the data just are syncing it from one place to
another place doesn't really work. Unison works okay, but Git does the same job better.
If you use Unison, you can have a cluster branch and a laptop branch. You just have
one set of files reflected on both sides, and it will get confused if you change the
the branch, it will be moving a lot of files back and forth.
So what I do to develop code on the cluster, SSH, I should mention, SSHFS works quite well.
So you can just use your local editor to edit the code on the cluster.
But I have often an unreliable internet connection or had in the past or had some bad experiences
with it, just kind of freezing the disk or the file system.
ways around that, but it's a bit of a pain. So what I do is not the best thing, is to just have
one repository online. In this case, we have the examples repository in GitHub, and you can have
one version on the cluster, one Git repository on the cluster for yourself, one on your laptop
for yourself and one that's in this case on GitHub that's for everybody and then you make
your changes on the laptop, you commit and push and then you go to the cluster and you
pull and then you run whatever you need to run the cluster.
Maybe you can come up with a better way of doing it, but it works.
make sure that it's always up to date on in the main version. And it is a convenient way
of transferring stuff between multiple different systems. So that's my workflow.
Yeah. Okay. So do you ever get to a place where you need to edit more frequently and
and you don't want to have to commit, push, pull, and rerun?
I do often make small changes on the cluster
that I then have to remember to commit and push.
Then just using some text editor that may be SSHFS,
maybe some of the graphical things
that we will show later, but mostly just Vim.
And I'm not very good at Vim.
So, I mean, there are people who use Vim as the main editor,
but I'm not very good at it.
So, I only do it for very small changes.
So, yeah, I mean, it is perfectly fine
to do editing on the cluster.
And I think kind of the main part of this section
is about editing on the cluster
and not doing it on the laptop.
So, but this is one good way.
It has the big upside that you can have multiple different versions and you always keep the
main version up to date. All of your branches are always getting pushed
to the main repository and pulled from there.
But should we move on to what I think is a better way? There is the demonstration there
and exercises, you can do those in the exercise session. Not quite there yet, not quite in the
better way yet, but from this one I want to do a demonstration of how to run small-ish
graphical things on the cluster. So I would not necessarily use this for a big text editor
unless i'm moving stuff around sorry unless you have a good internet connection and
all the people who run the cluster recommend doing it this way
but this is good for small like one window looking at the pot and it can be very convenient
when you're doing interactive development on the cluster how often do you use it
When I was doing research, not as a software engineer but also as a researcher, I would
use it very often to look at plots.
Essentially my SSH command was an alias to ssh -X or ssh -X because I would just want to use
GNU plot to run, to look at all of my plots and what is currently happening on the cluster
to look at just the state of the current run by looking at the plot. So yeah, I did use this very
often. So basically throwing up an image viewer or plot viewer was quite useful. Yeah, basically.
Okay, so I will bring up the terminal again. And I just tested that if I run ssh -X
Triton, it will stop echoing the command here, which is expected.
So I will not run the command.
I will switch to here where I've already run the command.
Okay.
So now you're on the cluster.
Yes.
So host name tells me that I'm on Triton, and I'm actually in my home folder now.
Okay.
No, it's not in my home folder, so I need to go to the IO examples.
And here we have this R example, which mainly I want to go to because there's this GNUplot
file plotting script here.
Actually, let's do a really simple demo first, just to check that it's actually able to open
a window.
So everybody should see a pair of eyes looking at my mouse right now over here.
It's not echoing the command, so okay.
That's too bad.
That's okay.
Now I'll have to actually stop this to get back to my terminal.
So the more useful thing to do is, of course, run the GNU plot script.
So I'm looking at this data file that exists for this R example.
It needs a -c. Unrecognized option -c. What did I do wrong?
Sorry.
I do not remember enough about GNUPlot.
Could GNUPlot be different there somehow?
GNU Plot is not a module, it's just normal GNUPlot.
plot. Okay, so I will not do that much debugging here. I don't have a new plot here. Okay,
so I must have run it on this side. So, let's look at the file. Set x11 terminal, set auto
title, that's fine. Okay, plot input.
So that's the only thing.
input file doesn't exist. Sorry. Yes. Okay. And I, in fact, did that on purpose because
one of the demonstrations that we didn't do was modifying this file. So, yes. I need to change
that so that the examples work independent of each other. Okay. So, now we can quickly open a window,
take a look at the data. It's showing some growing numbers.
Everything seems fine. Good.
What this -x option is doing is it's actually running
the whole thing on the cluster and then sending
the contents of this window to my laptop which displays it.
You can imagine if you have anything more complicated
that has more objects in the view,
it's going to get unmanageable quickly unless you have a really good internet connection.
So it does work and if you're locally close to your cluster, then it works really well.
So compared to modern good internet connections, how good does it have to be to be smooth?
I'm actually surprised that it's so good on my system now because I don't have a very
good connection, but it's also a really simple thing. I would just say experiment with it
if it's something you want to do. What would probably have been better to do is to somehow
copy this data file to my laptop and then run the script here. If you can instead run
the thing locally with local data, that's, of course, faster.
Yeah, but I guess when there's things like remote desktops and so on, those use a different
protocol, which is much faster. So what you can do, you run the remote desktop at your
your organization and then you SSH -X from there.
Let's go back here.
Oh, that's a good point.
Yeah. So if you have
a local desktop thing that has a fast connection to
your cluster then you can use
that remote desktop to run SSH -X.
Another thing that you can take a look at if you have it on
your cluster is open on-demand or similar,
CSC has a similar interface and there are predefined apps you can run so for example
the RStudio app on Triton. So you can run a graphical user interfaces much more efficiently
with a less good internet connection. So this uses the same protocol basically as
as a remote desktop would.
So these days, remote desktops do work quite well.
I remember when they were always laggy.
But now, usually, I don't notice much of a difference.
OK, yeah.
OK.
So should we move on?
Yes.
So the next section is called not graphical interfaces,
But working interactively.
Yeah.
Who should share their screen here?
So if we continue so that I do the demos,
is there something you want to say before we go into the demos?
Yeah, OK.
Should I display this thing that I'm displaying right now?
Yes, let's show this.
So working interactively from the command line.
So these are just a few tricks that are useful. They're not really that advanced,
but it's some really good stuff that can put people on the same page. So yeah,
there's four things we'll talk about here. And the first one is interactive jobs. So if you're
on the cluster and you have to, and let's say you're like me and you're doing some editing on
the cluster, you edit your file, you submit the job, you wait maybe a few minutes, you see the
output, you modify again, you submit again, you wait. This is really slow. It slows your development
down quite a bit. So there actually is a better way to do things and that's called interactive jobs
jobs, where instead of submitting your main program as a batch job, you request the resources
you need as a shell, and then you run the job yourself on the cluster.
So what do you like to show?
Yes, okay, so I will mount this.
I don't know if other people, other clusters teach this.
At our cluster, we actually teach interactive jobs first,
partly to show just one thing at a time.
Sorry, I'm in the background doing a setup.
Yeah.
OK, here we go.
So we're on the screen.
So [name] can run srun, --pty, srun, this, and then bash.
And note that different clusters may have different ways of getting interactive jobs.
Actually, on our cluster, you can also do sinteractive, and there's a dedicated
interactive partition, but this is the simple way that can give you the same
resources as anywhere else. So, if [name] pushes enter, hopefully there is a
little bit of time. Ah, and now we've got a shell.
And the echoing to command is just not working.
Okay, yeah.
Okay. Right, so where are we now?
So, here we are on hostname, so we're actually on one of the compute nodes.
And if we had requested, say, five processors and a bunch of memory, we'd have that same
amount of resources here.
So basically, in a really short loop, we could go and run the job, see if it works or doesn't
do an edit, and run the job directly without any additional queuing, which for me when debugging
things like crashes and so on that happen really quickly, this is really useful.
How often do you use these?
I mean, I just said that sometimes I use Vim to develop small changes in the cluster. Whenever
or I'm doing that, I'm actually in an interactive job.
So you start the interactive job
and then you run Vim, the editor inside of the job.
Yeah.
Okay, yeah.
Also, basically whenever I need to develop something
that runs on a GPU,
because that's how we have access to GPUs mostly,
or at least I have,
it's the easiest way for me to get access to a GPU.
And it is usually for the cluster anyway.
That's the end.
The end result is that it should run on the cluster.
So what are some of the problems here, and what can go wrong?
When would you not want to use this?
Or put another way, would we combine this with...
No, actually, that's later.
When would we not want to use this?
So I guess the biggest downside from the point of view of the cluster is that I'm now taking
a resource. It's only one CPU right now, so that's fine. But if I'm taking a whole GPU
and if it's one of the newer ones, it's mostly idling while I'm changing the code.
So I guess if you are taking a GPU anyway, whether it's on your laptop or on the cluster,
then you are taking one, but if you are taking a new really expensive GPU and just keeping
it reserved without running anything on it, that's a bit of a waste.
The same goes for having an interactive job with a thousand cores or something, like if
you take a really big part of the cluster for an interactive thing, and it's just mostly
running idle while you're editing some text file, some editing the code, then that's not really good.
So I guess don't take a huge amount of resources and do this, but take enough for testing.
Yeah. Okay. So it's a balance. Like if you want to test in a realistic environment,
and you can make some quick changes to fix some bugs, but if you're starting to make,
actually rewrite some code, then maybe don't do it in an interactive job.
or they have a smaller one at least. The other thing is you do need to queue.
So I don't use the cluster for big jobs. I use it for development for the cluster. So
I never queue for all that long. But if you're actually doing research and running big
computational workflows, maybe you need to stick in the queue for quite a while
to get the interactive job, get the resources you need.
Especially if you need a few GPUs.
Okay.
So there's a good question in the notes.
If we get disconnected from the interactive session, can we get it back?
And that's actually what we'll show next.
So there's two programs called Screen and Tmux.
Maybe more. But this is exactly what it lets you do.
log into the cluster. Can we stop the interactive job? Yeah, I will log out from the interactive job.
And now you're on the cluster itself. Can you do hostname? Okay, so on the cluster.
Can you start? Do you prefer screen or tmux? I usually use screen because I've used it before,
but if I had a good opportunity, I would like to learn tmux.
Yeah.
So let's start.
Well, let's do what you know.
Let's start screen.
Okay.
And if we run this, now it looks like there's a new terminal.
So this is running inside of screen.
If we type hostname, we're still there.
And we're still in my home folder.
Yeah.
Okay.
Do you want to run like...
So what's different?
date command.
Date?
Yeah.
Okay.
So, we see this. So, what's different
is since we're inside of screen, we can
detach. So, if [name] does
Ctrl-A and the D key,
now
look, it says detached
from this computer.
Now, [name] can log out from the cluster.
Okay.
No doubt.
And can we log in again?
Okay.
Let's just do this.
So here we are.
Now, everything's blue because of this.
It's fine.
That's okay.
I think.
Can we do screen -ls?
-ls
Yeah.
Let's list what's going there.
And we see there's one detached screen session, so if we do screen -x, or there's other things,
I always do -x, then here we are, we've restored.
And this is really cool, because you can leave stuff running, leave your editor open, leave
several windows of stuff going and come back to it. But when do we not want to do this?
I can't really think of much. It is for leaving stuff running in case you get
disconnected for example. So if there's something you don't want to leave running.
Would you want to start some interactive jobs and leave them running for a long time this way?
Well, that's the same, like, you are then just taking resources.
Fortunately, you probably can't get an interactive job for weeks at a time,
but I don't know what's the limit. You can get it for quite a few hours.
It's probably not a good idea to leave it running.
Yeah, because then if the login node crashes or something goes down, has to be rebooted,
you lose your job. So that's the most important things from here. We should, or should we show,
have you ever used the Python debugger from the command line interface? Yes, we do need
some Python code for it. Yeah. Do you want to, okay, so there is a specific example I guess
that you have in mind. Yeah, but I'm thinking, um, maybe we should go on to the next part.
This can be read. Let's, yeah. So this is, um, also left as an exercise. Yes. Yeah.
Okay, so next up, um, should we check the notes quickly while
[name] is getting ready? Yes, okay. Oh, you mean the... yes. Yeah, so there's some good questions
here. This comment of screen tmux being absolutely one of the most important things
learning with Linux, I would basically agree with that. So it is really useful.
And I usually run it on the login node itself because that means that if your
connection to the login node gets lost, it stays open. And I can, for example, move
from home, move to home, and then resume it, and so on.
OK.
So one thing is that I want to either say for the first time
or reiterate properly.
So we skipped a bunch of things that you can do as exercises,
but that's only if that is a workflow that you actually
want to either just practice or maybe make part of your own workflow, there's a lot
of ways of doing the same thing here, so it really just depends on your preference.
We are trying to demonstrate or at least give you some hints about ways you can do things
or that we do things that might help you.
So the idea is not to do all the exercises
or do all of the demos yourself.
The idea is to see what can make your workflow better.
I guess we are ready for the next part.
Yeah, so...
[name], hi.
So [name]'s here for the last part
to tell us about VS Code.
Can I share my screen?
Yes, please do.
So I will grab it from [name], sorry for that, and I should go with the portion of the screen
as we discussed, right?
Yes.
Okay.
So...
Can you see it now?
Yes, and I will switch to this.
So why are we learning about VS Code here?
Why are we talking about it?
So when we are talking about project development,
I would say there are two approaches that you can do.
There are local versions that we discussed today
that you usually keep track of your project locally
and do occasional bit pool and git push
or transfer it with rsync and everything.
And also you can do completely remote development,
as we're discussing with the terminal.
And, uh, VS Code is like more of like a second approach, but it has
a nice UI and it's also open source.
So we don't have to worry about that.
And, um, yeah, it's like very easy and nice to use.
Um, although like the rsync and code sync and data sync that we've
discussed is a very good way to go, but it adds a bit of overhead to your
full workflow and VS Code can reduce that overhead and so you can focus on
your project development, I would say.
Yeah.
Once we were thinking, this was several years ago,
about how to improve user interfaces for the cluster.
And we realized with VS Code, you
can connect to the cluster by SSH,
which handles some of the SSH complexity for you,
puts it in one place.
That can give you the terminal to submit jobs.
It can give you the editor to edit jobs.
it can let you transfer files up and down relatively easily.
And this was amazing.
We've been thinking, how do we have an easier
interface for the cluster?
And it was right here in front of us.
Yeah.
Although we are not like, although in this session
we are talking about VS Code, but I
would say it's true about most of the IDEs
if you are using PyCharm or JetBrains,
the workflow is the same.
And usually all of the features that we're discussing here
or almost the same in other IDs as well.
So other IDs can also do the remote SSH connection?
At least with PyCharm and I guess JetBrains I have tried,
and yeah, it's mostly the same.
OK, cool.
That's good to know.
Yeah.
OK, so what can we demonstrate first?
So here, as you can see, I have my local VS code.
It's running on my local computer.
and when you want to get connected to a remote server you have to have this
extension which is coming with the vs code but if for some reason it's not you have to go to the
app store and search for something like ssh remote okay and install the plugin which is the
like open ssh extension for the vs code if you are using another ide it would be pretty much the
same but at least for PyCharm I know it's coming with the icon. Once you have it installed you can
see this blue button on the left bottom side. Also you have this remote explorer icon here
and both of them can be used to get connected to a remote host. If you click on here it would
remember all of the hosts that you have been connected to and also the most recent folders
that you have been connected in that specific host. So, for example, unlike Triton, our local
HPC on Aalto, I have been connected to the folder I created for this course and other
folders for other projects that I had. Okay, that's actually new to me. I didn't know of that tab.
Okay, so that lists things, and then you click somewhere.
Yeah, you can go, and for example, if I click here, it would connect to Triton and then
go to that specific folder, but maybe it would be better for demonstration to go from the
beginning.
Right, yes.
So let's say you don't have any host previously, so you would click on this guy, and you have
two options to connect to a new host, which would open it on a new window, or you can
connect to a host with the current window and it would list all of the hosts in
your ssh-config file which is located usually on your home folder and so these
these are the same things in your .ssh/config file so it uses it, opens it
and yeah so if I go to my local file you can see that yeah so it's the same exact
configuration from my ssh config file yeah yeah so you can add new configuration here as well
by by putting the address and also in the username unfortunately you cannot add with ssh key so if
you want to do with ssh key and like put the identity file in the configure as well you have to
manually change the config file but the good thing is if you click on the configuration of
ssh host and select the file you can easily do it inside the vscode so you don't need another
editor. So the adding the ssh adding an ssh host does that automatically add a new entry to the
file? Yes, but you cannot add it with ssh key it's just the username and also the address.
Yeah. That's also new to me. Okay. So let's get connected to Triton.
So this is doing an ssh to Triton and ssh-config expands that to triton.alto.v,
which is our cluster. Yeah. At the moment, in our cluster, it would complain about a very old
OS that we have. It would be removed. You don't see this pop up if you have a newer OS on your
a cluster but it's only a security alert so it doesn't affect any of the functionalities.
Okay. I can go ahead and click allow. So as you can see here on the left, the SSH button here,
we are connected to Triton and I can go ahead and open a terminal. So anything we do here,
open directories, whatever, it's actually opening on the cluster side. Exactly. So the VS Code is
running on my computer, but everything I put down on the terminal and everything I see on the
window is actually running on the login node on the server. On the terminal if I go with hostname
you can see I'm on the login node already. So even opening the terminal is sending it to the
other side automatically? Exactly. Okay, and if you open a directory then? Yeah, I can go ahead
and open a directory. For example, the one that I created. As you can see, it's already the file
explorer for Triton. So, I will go... Okay. This is Triton. Yeah. Yeah. This is completely Triton,
as you can see. And I can go and click okay. And again, for the security, just about the git and
nothing. So now I'm again inside Triton and I'm inside the folder that I had
for this specific course and session. And is everything the same?
What do you mean? Like it's the same VS Code, same interface, is there anything different?
Exactly. No, yeah, but and yeah, it's the same VS Code. It's still
running locally on my computer and now with the remote explorer I have this folder.
So the next time that I want to get connected to this specific folder,
I don't have to get connected to Triton first and then go to File Explorer.
So this File Explorer is very nice because you can list all of the things. You can
create a new file here. For example, I can create something here or I can create a folder.
Another interesting thing is you can do drag and drop from your local computer to here.
For example, I can upload a file very easily.
You will see [name] with a cat.
Is that from another course?
Parallelization, yeah.
Yeah.
So that's what you are missing some days here.
Okay.
Anyway.
Unfortunately, the drag-and-drop from VS Code to your local machine doesn't work, but you
can go and right-click and then click download, so it would download it to your local computer.
The nice thing is it also understands the folder hierarchy, so if you download a folder,
it would create a folder on your local machine and then download all of the things inside
it, which is nice.
Yeah.
Okay, so what happens if the network connection stops or dies?
Like, do you lose your work or is this persistent to any health?
So it would try to get you reconnected and try to keep everything cached and saved.
So if you're in the middle of editing code and you didn't save it,
it would remember the latest changes almost instantly.
so I would say if you don't close the application completely, it would save all of the caches and
if you lost your connection, your changes are still there, but you have to get a connection
again so it would be synced. Okay. So if you reconnect, does it resume where you were or just
If you lose your connection, it would try to get connected to the same exact window with the same exact setup, like the files open and folder.
Is this even the case if you close your laptop and go home, for example?
Exactly. But if you close the VS Code, you would lose all of the changes that you had made, unless you have saved it on the cluster.
I guess that's pretty similar to any other editor.
Yeah. Okay. Got it. Cool. So now let's say you have like a project and you want to do
running and like testing and debugging on the cluster. Okay. Yeah. So of course you can go ahead
and try to run it here but the problem is it would be running it on local node and repo would
send an email that you're running something on the plugin node. Because it's a shared resource
it's not recommended to do any computational heavy tasks on the login node.
Also, this specific program, like estimating the pi, is very, it's not computationally heavy,
so you can, I guess, run it, but it's not recommended.
So I would show you how you can run it on the cluster.
For sure, you can go and open a new terminal, as you can see,
and try to, for example, run it with S run.
For example, I need 10 minutes of time.
And like, yeah, I need one gigabyte of memory.
And I would run the application.
And it also has a mandatory argument here for estimation.
For example, like let's say 10,000 iteration.
Oh, yeah, it should be helpful here, yeah.
So it's like a normal terminal.
It would try to dedicate the resources and run it and show me the results.
I wasn't in the same folder, I guess, or there was a mistake with, oh, yeah.
Yeah, so now the results are out there, but as you can see, I calculated the pi wrong.
So obviously there is a bug in my code, and let's say I want to do a debug.
So the best rule of practice, the best rule of thumb is to try to see what is the interactive
sessions on your local HPC or what are the partitions that are dedicated for testing,
because you can do it on normal computational nodes as well, but you are wasting the resources.
For example, if you are getting one hour of time for debugging, like on a GPU node in our cluster,
Triton, one single GPU would be dedicated to you, but sometimes in like GPU test partitions or
interactive partitions, these kind of resources are shared, so there is less space for resources.
So if I go, for example, with slurm, I can see that we have like a debug partition here,
we have interactive session partition, we have GPU short and I guess GPU test as well,
that you can do the testing. It's like dedicated for these ones. Also, usually there is a limitation
for time in these kind of partitions, so your job would be almost instantly get in the queue and
get executed. So, VS Code has this, like not VS Code, but Microsoft has this
an open source application for debugging for various languages, including Python that we
are using, which is called DebugPy.
And DebugPy is very integrated to VS Code.
So you can, I guess, use other softwares as well, but I will demonstrate DebugPy here.
Okay.
So this is some advanced debugging thing.
Actually, I've never seen it, so I'm interested.
I have to install DebugPy, so let me log into like,
let me activate my, like one of that virtual environment
I created.
Yeah.
For example, let's say this one, I know the name
and I will try to install DebugPy.
I think it has been installed in that specific one,
but let's see.
Oh yeah, so it has been installed already
And I can run it to show you how it works, debugpy.
Yeah, maybe I can close the file explorer
so it would be easier to see.
So the debugpy has two options, like listen and connect.
And you can use it on terminal as well
if you don't want to use VS Code,
but here we would use VS Code.
It also gets a host and a port, like a normal port,
has a default one and I will explain this option and like there are like some options for logging
and the PID number for that specific Python application but I will just demonstrate it.
So the only difference that you have when you want to debug your code the only difference
when you are calling the program is you have to call it with debug.py and debug.py would go to
the resources and run the program and open a port that you are specifying here and it starts
listening to that port. So another DebugPy program that gets connected to that port
and start debugging the application. So I can go ahead and say I want to do a run on, for example,
interactive partition. I still need 10 minutes of time.
For example, one gigabyte of memory. And I will try to run it with debug.py.
Okay, so use the dash m to say run this module, and then that module runs the py program.
Exactly. Okay. And the debug pi has this mandatory option for listen for connect and when you want to
open the debugger from the VS code you should go with the connect option and when you want to
run the program you should go with listen so the debugger would listen to any upcoming debugger
attaching. So I would go for listen to any host coming on a specific port. I think the default
one is five, six, seven, eight, four, five, it's not mandatory, you can change it.
And yeah, and then I can run the program with, for example, again, ten iterations.
However, the problem is when I run this, I would get allocated resources and then debug.py would get
to the program, it would start running and at the same time listening to the board, right?
The problem is because 10,000 is like a very short iteration and I want to see where is the
bug in my program. There is another option called rate for client and the debug pi would not do
anything running the code unless a debugger is attached. So I would go with this option.
Um, the partition line is okay. Interactive. It's not there. There was a 't'
There's an extra 't' there.
Extra t.
I-N-T-E-R.
Yeah, I'm trying.
Yes.
So now the resources has been allocated,
and the debug file is opening the port.
But it's not running anything unless a debugger is
get attached, because I call it with wait for client.
So now I can go to the debug tab here,
and I can go ahead and create a JSON file, which
is how I want to debug my, like, how to go and get the debugger.
So you have to take this and tell it how to connect?
OK.
Exactly.
So I would select debugger, and there are many options.
And one of them is remote attach,
which means attaching a debugger to a remote run.
Yeah.
I would go ahead and it says, like, where is it located,
as you can see.
OK.
So I don't know in which computational node
it's at the moment located.
I have to figure that out first. So I can go ahead and open another terminal and see, for example,
what are my runs. Okay. Yeah. Yeah. And I can see that, uh, in like pe8, uh, the program is running.
So I would go ahead and say, it's like pe8. What is the port? 5, 6, 7, 8, as we said it.
And it would create a normal JSON file for me. Uh, but you can like do it manually as well.
Usually, it's a good idea to change the name because we can have multiple debugger settings.
I would say, like, remote debugger.
Okay, yeah.
Debug attach.
And you don't need the pass mapping because, yeah, you don't need it, but the other,
you can see what the other configuration do, but you don't need the pass mapping for this
specific test.
Okay, okay.
So now I have it and I save the JSON file and you can see that I have multiple debuggers and
the first one is the debugger. I can go ahead and like it creates a breakpoint here in the main
function and I can go ahead and say like run. So you can see this toolbar is getting blue which
means I'm getting connected to that one and the program is exactly paused here. So I can go ahead
and normally go to the next function and create another breakout point.
So the interesting thing is I'm using UI in my local computer and everything is running and
executed on the remote server on the computational node. It's like two levels of remote. There's from
your computer to login node and from login node to the cluster node. Exactly. So you can like watch
all of the valuables and everything. When you disconnect this, the debugger pie would again
run it completely and try to give you the result. However, you can again get connected to
the debugger because still the debugger port is open and until the program is finished,
you can get connected without an issue. Yeah. Okay. So yeah, let me run it. I know where is the
bug and the bug is right here so I can go ahead and fix it and run it completely and even save it.
Excellent. So for those who are able to join over the afternoon session in the Zoom,
So this is exactly the type of thing that you can try especially if you have never tried
it before and so we were checking the notes document and we have written there some feedback
for the day.
So if you want to specify if this was too slow or too fast or too basic or too advanced
Please, mark your...
Anything else to mention, [name]?
Yeah, I guess for help in doing all these things, so a lot of the exercises are basically doing the same things we've done here,
with a little bit of extra stuff, come to the exercise session and we can work it out.
So we resume not in one week, but two weeks from now, because there is a holiday in at least Finland in, well, a week and a day.
And we're talking about containers then, is that correct?
Yeah, on the 7th of May will be an episode dedicated to containers and clusters, specifically Apptainer/Singularity.
Okay.
Yeah, I mean, this was very useful, hopefully, for many of you.
Please write down one good thing that you really liked today and also something to improve.
I guess that's all for us.
Thank you very much, everyone.
And see you.
Yes.
See you.
Thanks.
Later.
Bye.
See you.
you