CodeRefinery.org
you
Hello everybody and welcome to the fourth and
final episode of Tuesday Tools and Techniques
for High-Performance Computing, TTT for HPC.
So we are now in the warming up section.
So in these 10 minutes, we can test, for example,
this collaborative notes document
that we have been using before.
I guess that if you have been joining the previous TTT
for HPC sections or even the other courses that we arrange you should be already familiar
with how we interact with the instructors. Today with me is [name] and [name]
both from Alto Scientific Computing. I will of course introduce you how can I say officially
at 10, at 10 a.m. finish time.
But so yeah, it's important that now you test.
One thing to remember is that the Twitch TV
automatically tries to limit the bandwidth that you use.
So remember to set the quality of the Twitch TV player
to source.
So basically it's like the full quality.
And then you just receive the reminder on your email
with the link to this collaborative notes document
that [name] is sharing.
And so it's good to test that you're able to edit.
So if you click the pencil at the top of the document,
then you can add three kind of icebreaker questions.
So it's good that I'm very curious of the last one,
for example, which skill do you want to learn
or wish to improve next because we are always trying to read the mind of our researchers
that we're trying to help. So it's good to know what you are planning to learn next because
then maybe we can learn it together or teach it together or both of them. How are you doing
today, [name] and [name]?
A bit tired, but it's going okay.
this general May tiredness. Everyone is feeling it. I don't know if it's the spring or.
I don't even know what to say.
It's okay. So let's see how many people are joining. I can see a few people in this note,
collaborative notes.
And so what do you want to learn next?
Yeah, that's a that's a very difficult, difficult question.
Is our audio balanced?
Well, yeah, we should do a quick check.
So I'm going to say one, [name], we say two, and then we will say three, one, two, three,
One.
Two.
Three.
One.
Two.
Three.
From looking at this, my audio might be a little bit lower.
And of course if you're watching via the Twitch streaming, you can let us know if the audio
was balanced.
Yeah, I don't know which skill to learn next. It's very difficult. Maybe I could say that
sometimes I wish I could help more researchers who are using MPI, but MPI is something that
I never really had to learn in my past work. And so, okay, I know the basics. I know whatever
Spells, one needs to type to get things running.
Yeah, I was also thinking about wanting to learn MPI.
But then also, I don't really want to learn that much,
like not enough to actually do it since, well,
if I needed to, I could.
but doesn't seem necessary yet.
Yeah.
And the same is CUDA that I'm kind of curious.
But then again, would I really start implementing something
indirectly in CUDA myself when I know that most likely there's
already a Python package or?
That's a good point.
Yeah.
Like some of these low-level kind of
libraries and programming and not the programming but like the libraries
and dependency kind of stuff.
But yes I'm curious to see so if you are just joining the stream using the
collaborative notes document that you see now in the streaming you can answer
question number three on which skill do you want to learn or wish to improve next
so that we can get an idea what to prepare for the next academic year
yeah so we still have a couple of minutes to go before the official start
and what else I also pasted the link to the CodeRefinery YouTube channel there
so that you can actually re-watch all these videos and share them of course
also with other with other colleagues who couldn't maybe make it and there
might be something useful but it's also interesting to see that someone there
wrote that more likely to use the written materials.
We had a chat yesterday with our code refinery team,
and someone raised exactly this point,
that the written materials are so good that you don't even
need to watch any video.
You can just read the materials, follow the materials,
and learn on your pace.
I guess that's the dream or whatever, isn't it?
Yeah.
And then the videos can just be.
I mean, really, I think that's better.
You shouldn't have to watch a long video just to find some stuff.
We're not farming for engagement or whatever here.
In fact, the less engagement, the better, because that means you already know.
That definitely sounds better, at least for me as a kind of, I'm not a learn-by-watching-videos
type of person, so yeah.
But on the other hand, I think seeing a really good example is useful.
I got started in all this video thing where I saw someone explaining something, but instead
of screenshots it was a video just explaining, I click here and here and here and here, and
then my dataset is on Zenodo.
I was like, wow, you know, this is actually makes it seem really easy.
We should do more of that.
So yeah.
All right.
But it's 10 a.m. in Finland, 9 a.m. in Central Europe.
So I guess we can officially start.
Welcome to the last episode of TTT for HPC, Tuesday Tools and Techniques for High-Performance
Computing.
With me today, there is [name].
Do you want to say something about yourself, [name]?
I'm, well, I'm [name], as you just heard.
I'm a staff scientist at Aalto Scientific Computing here in Helsinki and I do
all sorts of stuff but mainly focusing on research software right now.
And talking about research software, with us today there is also [name].
Do you want to say something about yourself [name]? Yeah, hello, I'm [name]. I'm a research
software engineer at Aalto University. I help researchers with their day-to-day software issues.
Excellent and I'm [name], staff scientist and I work with [name] and them and others here
at Aalto University. So the topic of the last episode of this series is about high performance
computing, parallelization and workflows. And we have to mention that most of the material
that we will use today was actually written by [name], who is another research software
engineer at Aalto, but he couldn't make it today. But I'm sure we will be able to transfer
all the knowledge from the materials to your eager brains.
If you've been joining the previous section, you might be familiar with the share notes
document.
For those who are joining today for the first time, you have received the link to a document
that is like an online document, kind of thinking like a Google Doc.
So at this notes.coderefinery.org, you have this document that reaches now screen sharing.
And there at the top, there is a pencil icon.
So click on the pencil so you can start editing and for example you see there are some questions,
so-called icebreakers, and in general whenever you have questions or comments you can add
them at the bottom of the document.
If there's something interesting, if there's something that is important to bring on the
stream, I will make sure that your answer will be addressed during the two hours this
morning.
Please remember to set the twitch tv quality to source because otherwise the twitch
tv player will just downgrade the quality of the of the streaming in general if you
see that the streaming ends for whatever reason once it has happened that the whole internet
was was basically down no panic we will try to get back within within few few few minutes
Any other practicalities? So this morning session is about more or less two hours, so
until 12 o'clock Finnish time, 11 CET. And we will try to kind of be somewhat interactive,
but it's more kind of lecture-based. In the afternoon, instead, there will be a Zoom that
that you have in your email, a Zoom link.
So from 1 p.m. Finnish time, 12 o'clock Central European time,
we have a Zoom session that is not recorded.
So you are free to join there
and try some of the examples that you will see today.
And for those who are needing the one ECTS credit,
there's a couple of exercises that you can do basically
can do basically during this this zoom section in the in the afternoon and now it's four minutes
past the hour i think we covered all the details if you want to access the materials for the day
at the very top of this collaborative notes document there's the link to this parallel
workflows materials and maybe so maybe we should start with some motivation who
wants to motivate all of us on why we need to parallelize or should we
parallelize once maybe [name] do yeah let's see I will switch to my screen or
Or I will try.
Yes, here we go.
I'll go to the materials.
So should we start with the motivation section now?
Is that where we are?
Yeah, at least get an overview on why are we here.
Yeah.
Also, interesting notion that [name] brought up,
that should we parallelize?
Because I hadn't thought about it.
Like, I have taken it as a given that we parallelize.
Good question.
And this lesson, the other name of it is called Parallelizing Without Parallelizing.
So what does that mean?
And is that sort of what you said about not wanting to parallelize?
Yeah. Well, if I jump in here, the parallelizing without parallelizing means that we are not
doing parallelization within a language. So, if I have a Python script, I'm not using,
For example, Python's multi-processing, multi-threading properties.
So that means we're basically running the same thing multiple times, but each individual
one doesn't have any special parallelization.
Exactly.
Okay.
Yeah.
That sounds like a pretty good deal overall, I mean, if you can get parallelization without
having to do it.
I think it's a fantastic deal, because you don't have to go into the intricacies of the
language, and what you have to do is you have to learn this kind of meta layer of the HPC.
how do I efficiently submit basically the same job
with a little bit different parameters,
like multiple times.
So something changed here.
Yeah, OK.
And it's this sort of what I've heard,
like I've got the idea that in a lot of research,
this works better.
Like for example, when our team is buying GPUs,
we can spend extra for these GPUs with fast communication.
But the general feeling is, well,
people are more likely to just run multiple jobs at once.
Like if you need to run 10 GPU simulations,
and you can run, let's see, like 10 in one hour,
or 10 at the same time, each taking 10 hours,
it gets done at the same time.
So is that sort of how it is?
Yeah, and also from researchers' point of view,
learning to use this very low-level parallelization. The learning overhead is
something completely different than learning how to do this, well, the embarrassingly parallel one.
Yeah. So there's a lot of text here. I guess we can...
Yeah, and it's a good text, but I recommend reading it on your own pace.
Yeah. So what does this figure here mean?
1 to 10, do something in parallel, or...
Is this saying that if you control your parallelization, you can do 10 things at once,
But if you do 10 things at once, and each of them are trying to use 10 processors, then you've oversubscribed your...
Yeah, what does this mean?
Yeah, I think that's exactly what it means. So giving in first picture, we are doing 10,
like submitting 10 jobs to 10 CPUs, which is very nice from our point of view. It's
very understandable what's happening. And it's very nice from the point of view of the
hardware because it doesn't have to tangle itself in scheduling. But then I think the
The latter picture is, if we also try to do something in parallel, like, in, in the, yeah,
I don't even know how to describe it.
And that's the problem.
I remember this. So sometimes on our cluster, people submit jobs, and they might submit
a bunch of jobs, but they don't configure the job. So each job is trying to use every
CPU on the computing node. And that means that you're running way more than can fit
on there, and it slows down a lot. So I think it's something like that.
So each job should be isolated in a sense that they don't try to use the same CPUs.
So what does it mean to move the parallelization to the scheduler level?
So I guess this is what you've been saying.
So the scheduler is SLURM?
Yes.
on queuing system. Yeah, so basically you tell the scheduler to start many jobs and then
slurm does that and each job is not parallel.
Yeah, okay. There's a good question in the notes. Sometimes it feels like my laptop
multiprocessors are faster than the same amount of processors on HPC. Why is my laptop faster?
And that's a good question. I guess I can answer that from our cluster's hardware level.
So, I mean, the easy answer is that we don't promise it to be faster. So the cluster is
optimized for many processors that have reasonable price that can be run in parallel.
So, yeah, I mean, on average, your laptop is about more or less the single processor
power as the cluster.
The difference is that the cluster has tens of thousands or more of processors, and your
laptop has maybe four to eight, something like that.
But also for our particular cluster at our university, we keep the hardware as long as
it makes sense from the energy efficiency point of view, or until it starts literally
falling apart and becoming so unreliable it doesn't work anymore.
So that means that you might be running something on the cluster that's on one of the older
processors that might be five or more years old, while your laptop is probably not quite
that old.
So it might have more optimizations and so on there.
And that's, well, I mean, from our point of view,
we can either remove working hardware
and have to buy more or keep it there.
And it should always be better to keep it there.
And if someone needs newer, they can request newer.
And this is still processing power
that someone didn't have before.
OK, so on a cluster, the point
is that a single CPU might not be like super new and it might not be the kind of the best
of the bunch, but the point is that when you have like average CPUs in the order of tens
of thousands, then you get the kind of the scaling advantage over the laptop.
Yeah.
And I mean, there definitely are clusters that have really high single processor performance.
But anyway, I guess we should move on.
Next is concepts.
So what do I need to know to get started here?
Okay.
So, first of all, yeah, embarrassingly parallel code.
Yeah.
What does that mean?
So this is the most convenient type of parallelization.
And then what does it say here in the text?
It's code that essentially runs the same function for a large variety of input parameters, where
each step does not depend on anything other than the input data.
So basically we have jobs that are very similar.
They take input parameters, which makes them different, and the results don't depend on
the jobs, don't depend on each other.
So here, all of these calculates can be done at the same time, in theory.
Yes.
Or here for the two-dimensional scan, they can all be done separately.
So it's the whole point of today that we're going to split these out so all of these can
be run at the same time using Slurp?
Yes.
Or something like that.
Okay, yeah.
So instead of this being Python code, which is serial, the scheduler does it in parallel.
Yes, exactly.
So we are basically always moving the loop, looping into the photo scheduler.
By the way, the name embarrassingly parallel code or parallel, embarrassingly parallel
is a bit, it's a bit funny to me because it has this negative connotation when in fact
it is like, it's a super good thing that something is embarrassingly parallel.
So like, I would rather call it like happily parallel or something.
Easily parallel.
Yeah.
So, but, but this is like, uh, this is standard jargon.
So that's why we have adopted the embarrassingly parallel.
Is it like embarrassingly parallel because someone gets hired to make something parallel
and then they work on it for a year and come back and say, oh yeah, I just parallelized
it in the scheduler and didn't modify the code.
Yeah.
They're like, yeah, something.
Something like that.
Yeah.
But it's just a weird word choice.
But I guess the point is we always want to do embarrassing parallel if possible.
Yes.
Okay.
What about size of jobs?
There, I would say that the first sentence basically summarizes that in general, jobs
should not be too short on a cluster.
Because if you have tens of thousands of jobs or thousands of jobs and each take only, let's
say, a minute to run, then there's
going to be a lot of scheduling overhead
because the scheduler, or Slurm in our case,
needs to do all the scheduling and queuing work.
So it is very rough on the cluster itself.
So basically, don't make them too short, and I see there's a question in the notes where
there's some more details there. So should we go on? Okay, yeah. And I think it is pitfalls,
concurrency issues. So there's a lot here. What should I share? I think if we go through the
summary, because again, the text here is, which there is kind of a lot. I would recommend
going through that in people's own pace, but then we can, let's pick some interesting
things from the summary and talk about them. What do I need to know?
Well, in general, what does the concurrency issue mean?
To me, it means that two or more things like codes are trying to access the same resource,
which could be a file or a database.
So do you do you agree with this or yeah like I mean I guess you can ask what needs to be
accessed concurrently and I guess it's things like reading in input data and maybe writing
out data if it's going to the same place I guess the number one rule of a cluster is
don't have a bunch of processes all try to write to the same file exactly unless you're
carefully managing it. So is that the main? Is it bad to read from the same file multiple times?
That's a good question. I think I have Googled this and read the stack overflow
discussion like multiple times during my work years. And I think the answer is like reading is
fine. Yeah. I've never heard of a problem with reading unless it's, you're completely
overloading the system. But at that point, well. Yeah. There's something else also going on there.
if you, by reading a file, you overload the system. So yeah, go ahead, sorry.
But simultaneous writes, so what about that?
Yeah, that is the problem. And like you said, that the main point is don't try to write to the same
file at the same time. And the solution here in the summary is given, make sure that you,
for example, use when you write to a file that the file name has, for example, the job ID
or the parameters in it. So that way you make sure that the results and output files are
written to job-specific files.
Yeah.
Okay, so any time we're doing this embarrassing parallel, if we're saving data somewhere,
make sure it's writing it separately, and then combine it later, I guess?
Yes.
If you need to?
Okay.
Yeah, combine and use a collection script or...
Yeah, okay.
Do you know, is it safe to append to files from multiple jobs?
Like, if you're only appending and not doing other modifications.
I wouldn't.
I guess that's the safe answer.
I mean, I'm wondering if it's safe, but if it's too big, like, maybe we can ask someone
and see.
Yeah, and it's like, it's, I know it may sound weird because when you think about writing
a line of text, for example, in a file that you think of it like an instant instantaneous
thing. But it does take time. And then if you have like multiple scripts writing all the time,
then there will be conflicts. And what you end up is, well, I like to think that you end up with
corrupted files, but I guess it can be also that everything slows down because...
Yeah. From my understanding of Unix, there's certain operations that should be atomic,
meaning it all happens before anything else happens. And I'd like to think that appending
to a file is one of them. So if you append small enough data, it can always be done in one write.
It would work, but I really don't know if once it goes through the network layer and
the scratch file system layer, if that would still be the case, but okay, anyway.
Should we go on or is there more about this database access?
Well, I would think of a database access the same way as the file system, very roughly.
But the right database should handle multiple writes at the same time.
Yeah, exactly.
So that the database will have concurrency, like, not all databases, but...
I've heard of some of our users doing things like setting up a database which all the jobs
would read or write to.
I mean, I guess they can't all do a lot at the same time.
You can't have millions of things writing to there because of the database performance,
but a few things.
That's sort of the point of a database.
Yeah. And like you said, that like a proper database, for example, if we name some databases,
so if you pick SQLite, that doesn't have concurrency. So that will have the same problem as writing
to a file, but if you pick, for example, Postgres, then that will have concurrency handling.
So it is definitely better the situation to use the database.
So you don't get these conflicts, but there is this kind of like the compromises that
You have to set up and admin the database, and also the database will use some resources,
has to run somewhere.
Okay, should we go on then?
Yeah.
Okay.
Pitfalls, hardware, and server limitations.
So I guess let's look at the summary here again.
So what about this?
What do I need to know?
Did my network connection die?
No.
No, no, no.
Okay.
I'm reading the summary as well.
So that's why.
Yeah.
I mean, I guess it's saying...
...is caches...
This goes a little bit too low-level
for me. I guess a lot of it makes sense, like, if you have many small files in parallel,
then that becomes a
bottleneck for IOSpeed.
We already talked about the many
small jobs grouping, maybe we'll talk about later.
Yeah.
So,
I guess.
Yeah.
So, how I read it is that if you have slow type disks that will like spinning disks,
they will be slower, and maybe that you should know where you are writing, that what the
disks are being used, and maybe that will help you debug some problems if something comes up,
that, okay, I have something is going wrong, then maybe it could be something like this.
Yeah.
Too slow a disk.
Okay.
Should we go on then?
Yeah.
I was going to say that talk to your favorite cluster administration about this issue.
I guess every cluster is different, so maybe it's good to see what yours is optimized for.
Like I think ours is more optimized for small file access than some of the big ones and
so on.
Exactly.
Okay.
So, let's go on then, and maybe we can take a break and look at the notes here.
So we've got a lot of good questions here.
Some already answered the new questions.
Some of these I wrote here, hoping that other people would answer.
Is there a Linux command to test the IOSPEED of disks?
Hmm...
Actually, I would be really happy for a cheat sheet of all of these Linux performance measuring commands,
like test disk performance, test CPU performance, and so on.
Time definitely does show how much time your program is taking,
making, but not the raw capacity of the disks themselves.
Hmm.
Yeah.
Okay.
But yes, keep them coming.
And should we go on?
Yeah, just a second.
These three here, I...
Is that the database out of queue?
So yeah, so for this one, basically databases are designed for concurrent access.
They have their own internal queues and journaling and stuff like that.
So you can basically send all the rights to it and it holds them until it can do it safely
and in order.
Yeah.
So if it receives two requests to write something like simultaneously, it has an inner process
to make sure that they are first queued and then written safely.
Yeah.
Sorry, I think I just, I just repeated what you said.
That's good.
On here.
Yeah.
Someone pointed out the dd command.
So dd basically, what does it even stand for?
Duplicate data or something like that.
It can do raw reads and writes, not raw, but it basically reads and writes data.
So you can use it to say, how long does it take to read one gigabyte of data, or so on.
But let's let people keep adding in more stuff there.
Okay.
So now I think we get to the main part of the lesson.
Yes.
So what's our example for the rest of the time?
So from what I understand, I'll be typing out a real example, which is partly a mystery
to me.
Okay.
Yeah.
The scenario that we are starting with, it's kind of a reminder of quite a realistic scenario,
which is that people are developing their pipeline or workflow in a Jupyter notebook.
But in order to use the HPC efficiently, we want to take that one notebook and turn it
into scripts, in this case, Python scripts, and factorize it so that we have one script
doing one step of the pipeline.
So basically, the thing that I often see people needing to do.
So they come in with this Jupyter and say, I want to run it on the cluster.
Well, they can run it on one processor, but that's defeating the purpose.
Yes.
Okay.
Yeah.
When I say efficiently, then yes, I exactly, I meant that we want to use the parallelization
for it.
Yeah.
Okay.
And then, so we take a look at, about kind of like the, where, where we end up with our
scripts and what kind of workflow it is.
It's a simple two-step workflow.
And then we will run that workflow on HPC using, where we parallelize what can be parallelized
using three different methods.
Can you give me a summary of what these methods are just so I'll know what to be looking forward
to?
Okay.
So the first parallelize using scripting is that we basically, we write a Python script
or it can be actually anything, R script also.
But let's say we have a Python script and we use a sub-process module to submit the
job using the Slurm system.
So then those things are running, what is in the loop are running parallel.
And then the array jobs is kind of like a Slurm native method to parallelize.
So we can just modify the Slurm batch script to tell it to that, okay, this needs to be
running in parallel, multiple jobs in parallel.
And the third one is to parallelize or run the whole workflow using a workflow manager
tool.
Which in our case will be SnakeMake.
So what does workflow manager mean?
I've been hearing a lot about how you've been developing the lesson, and I'm really looking
forward to hearing the advantages and disadvantages.
Yeah, it's a workflow manager tool is, we take kind of a more higher view of the workflow.
So we have the whole workflow defined in one file and it is kind of a, when your workflow
is starting to get really big, then basically that is when you might want to switch to using
to workflow managers. But it works for small workflows as well, of course.
Okay, so I look forward to getting there.
Yeah.
So, do we begin?
Yeah, that wasn't a very good explanation, but yeah. You put me on the spot. This is
what you got.
Yeah, okay. So, should I begin with converting it to the Python script?
Yeah, let's start with the notebook.
So I click here.
OK, so now it's time for me to do typing.
So I guess the goal, here I am.
I am on our cluster.
And I'm in my home directory here.
And I'll be doing these examples for almost the first time.
So I will try to go as quick as I can.
But I'll also be asking questions about what it means
and how to do it.
Yeah, please do, because, yeah.
Do we expect users to follow along at the same time?
No.
OK.
Definitely, definitely not, because there
will be enough stuff going on that it will.
Yeah.
So this is just a demo.
Yeah, it's not worth splitting your focus.
Yeah, OK.
So I'll try to explain or ask questions about the parts that might be tricky, but if it's
probably not tricky, I'll just do it as quick as I can.
Okay.
But let's see how this goes.
Yeah.
So the notebook is on GitHub.
I guess I can open this and hopefully it renders.
Yeah, looks like a notebook.
But the conversion is already done.
Yes.
Is that the same one?
So it is mainly that we don't have to now start opening notebooks and running them.
So maybe the first thing I will do is make a new directory for my work.
TTT for HPC parallel.
And I will download the script, and I will do that by copying the raw link, and wginted.
Okay.
Yeah.
list. I've got it downloaded. Yeah. Okay.
So actually I would, now that I, if we go downwards, there might, it might be that the,
cause, or actually I would prefer that. Let's, let's look a bit like what, what the notebook
actually does or what the code does.
Okay.
Should I open the notebook or the code?
You can open the code because we are now, we have exported it.
So what does it do?
So in this, this is a pipeline or a workflow.
And what we do is that we have two steps.
And in the first step, we...
Or should I be sharing the screen?
Lowering the code.
This is the file.
The script file.
Yes.
Yeah.
That looks...
So this is the notebook converted to a Python script.
So there are two steps here, and the first one is called pre-processing data.
And it uses the Skykit Learn datasets.
It loads this iris flower dataset from there.
So these datasets are something that comes bundled with the Skykit Learn datasets.
So it's automatic, yeah.
Yeah.
And then we take two features from there, which are the length of the sepals of the
flowers. And then we take the classes, which are different subspecies of viruses.
Oops. What? GitHub's popping up Windows. Okay. Yeah. So we have the features and the classes.
Yeah. And then when we do the train, we split the data to train and test sets.
and then we save all this to disk.
Yeah. Okay.
So we have the train and test sets and features and classes.
Yeah.
And it's in the data pre-processed iris pickle file.
And this is, so this was the first step.
And the second step is that we want to,
we want to learn or train these nearest neighbor classifiers or a classifier on this dataset.
And then we apply the learned classifier on the whole data, the complete data,
and plot the decision boundaries.
Okay.
Yeah.
Here we are assuming that that classification
is somewhat familiar topic.
Okay.
So what happens first is we load the preprocessed data
and then we have a couple of parameters
for the classifier, which is the number of neighbors and the distance metric.
Right. Yeah. Okay.
Yeah.
And, spoiler alert, this is what we're going to be parallelizing over.
Yes.
Different.
Okay. Yeah.
Exactly.
And here I see two loops.
Yeah. So we have two loops. And what happens is that the, well, like you said, we have
a combination of parameters. And those can be run in parallel, the training and plotting,
because they don't depend on each other.
So we have, OK, this is the training here.
Yes.
And this is the plotting.
And the plotting is just of the respective parameters.
It makes a scatterplot with colors of the classes.
Yeah, so yes.
So important thing here is to, the most important
is that for each parameter settings,
we will have an output file or a result file,
which is, you can see it in the build safe fig.
So in a results folder, we have a image file,
the boundary decisions named according to the parameters,
which is exactly what we were talking about earlier,
that we should always, in order not to write over stuff
and especially not the same time.
Yeah. Okay.
Name the output files.
Good.
Okay.
Now I understand.
So, yeah.
So if we go back,
then because we have, here we have two steps
or we had two steps.
So like we said earlier that we want to factorize the code
so that each step is in its own script.
And here is exactly what we have done in the next section.
So we will have preprocess.py
which will have the first portion of the script.
So here it opens and saves it.
Yes. And the second will be train and plot.
Okay, so here it opens the pre-processed data and iterates over.
Yeah, here the lists are bigger.
Yeah.
Okay.
There are, I think, I think SkyGitLearn has like nine distance metrics that it supports.
So, yeah, we have used five.
Yeah. Okay.
So, number of neighbors goes from 1, 2, 4, 8, 16, 32, 64,
and distance matrix goes Euclidean one and L1 one.
Yeah.
Opposite and cosine.
So, should I copy the files from here or split it myself?
I think you can copy.
Okay.
just to make sure that we don't make typos.
Mess it up somewhere.
So copy, paste.
I hope this pasted correctly.
Just me or there?
There's extra lines in there.
Yeah.
For some reason, it's doubled the line, the empty lines.
Well, let's hope it works.
Interesting.
Is this a weird feature, or I'm not a weird user?
This is actually Emacs, I have the VI program alias to Emacs.
So that makes it even more confusing.
Confusing, yeah.
Okay, well, that's preprocess, and next is train and plot.py.
Did it again.
Okay, so the two files are there.
Yeah.
And then the next section here is the update code to run on a cluster.
And first, we will need the environment with the dependencies.
And that is, we will use this singularity container, or an image, and that has already
been created for us.
So we should be able to, I think you can run this, yeah.
And we can let it run while it's going.
So this is what we talked about last week.
Yeah, exactly.
I did it last night and it worked.
People are already experts with containers, so we don't have to go.
And then what we mean by running in HPC here is, of course, that we want to do the Slurm
submission.
And this is the Slurm script to submit our job.
Yes.
Okay.
So, yeah.
So what it does, it asks some basic resources, time memory, CPUs per task, and then it runs
the two scripts.
And importantly, it runs them sequentially.
So this is doing all 10 or whatever.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
So in the train and plot.py, we currently have the two for loops.
So it will run them all like one by one within the Python script.
In a real thing, would we have the preprocess in the same batch script as the training and
plotting?
I would have different batch scripts for the different scripts, at least for one reason.
There might be more, but at least one reason, which is that different steps require different
resources.
Yeah.
So, it might be that our preprocessing step requires a lot of memory and our training
doesn't for some reason.
Yeah.
So, in this case, does the preprocess script, does it need to be, like, can it be done once
and never done again?
Yes.
Okay, so again, if we were doing multiple analyses, we could have it do it once and
then just leave it at that.
Yes.
Okay.
Yeah.
So should I make a script here?
Yeah, I think, let's see, or should we do a summary of what we have at the moment?
Yeah, sure.
So we have the preprocess.py script, Python script.
We have the train and plot Python script.
And in the train and plot, we do two forward loops.
Okay, yeah.
And then we have a Slurm script
to run the code in like sequentially
without any paralysis.
Using one CPU, it seems.
Yeah. And memory is one giga and time is one hour.
Yeah. Okay.
Okay.
What should I name the script?
I think you can name it...
Submit.sh.
Or submit sequentially.
Non-parallel, maybe.
Right, yeah. It needs to have that in there.
Oh, Nano doesn't have extra lines.
Okay, good.
So now it's all here.
So do we go to the next one now?
Should we look at the notes?
What questions do people have?
Yeah, definitely.
Can you see these also?
There's questions.
SnakeMake, Fireworks...
Yeah, the what is the container used in the example. So, so it's a obtainer or a singularity
container. And, and yeah, it was made in or been created in advance. And it's okay. Yeah.
Yeah, so you made this for this lesson?
Yeah, [name] made it.
I can't take credit.
Yeah, okay.
Okay, good.
Do we need to make a container?
No, it was just easier here.
And actually it is kind of nice here.
At first I thought, oh, a container, do I want to have to use this?
But, you know, I really don't have to do anything else to just one pull command.
So yes, that feels kind of good.
Yes, exactly.
Okay.
I agree.
Yeah.
I was also kind of like, oh man,
do we have to like juggle with images,
but no, just one pool.
Okay.
Should we go on then?
Yes, yes.
So there's seven minutes to the break.
We can parallelize using scripting.
Yeah.
I guess we're running a little bit behind, but that's OK.
So what happens here?
OK, so even if we are using this happily parallel type
of approach, there still needs to be,
we need to make modifications.
OK.
So we can't just like submit stuff and it would automatically work.
And I guess this work is going to be needed for all of the methods anyway.
Yes, yes.
So the point is that if we look at what needs to be done, we have to do the same kind of
work in a form or another.
So basically, I'm wondering where is the, like, do we list that what we are going to
do?
I think it's in the intro.
So basically, because now we have the parameters hard-coded in the script.
So we're removing that.
Yeah.
So yeah, we don't want the parameters to be hard-coded in the script.
We want to give them as command line parameters for the script.
So should I basically make these edits in there?
Yes.
So this is the train and plot one, because that has the loop.
Okay.
And how we've got all these extra lines, cool.
So we add, so I'm basically adding in the emphasized lines in here, at least on my screen,
I can see some of these lines have an extra yellow, yellow.
So arg parse is the standard Python command line argument parser.
Okay, so here right above load preprocessed data.
So I copied this and paste.
Yeah.
So, well, I know what this means.
So this is the standard boilerplate for making an argument parser.
giving it one argument, which is the number of neighbors. It's int type, some help text,
and here we're getting n neighbors from the command line. Okay. And for metrics,
I see we've added more metrics. Or not. They are the same metrics, but note that we are now
giving only the number of neighbors as a parameter, and the metrics are still hard-coded as a list.
So when we run...
Yeah, so I just commented it out for clarity.
Yes, yeah, good. So what the script now does is instead of looping over two lists,
of neighbors and metrics. Now it will take the number of neighbors as an argument,
so it's a single value, and then it loops over the number of neighbors.
Okay, so I need to modify down here also. So basically I remove this loop?
Yes. Okay. I want to edit this in Emacs. Sorry. Because I know how to do that. I wish I didn't
have all these extra lines well you can tell this is a real demo yeah this this
was not pre-recorded okay so I remove this loop because now it's done yeah
from command line. And then I need to de-indent all of this, which I can do with Emacs like that.
By the way, did we read the nNeighbors from the args as a variable?
Yeah, it was.
Okay, yes.
Yeah, it's already done there. Okay, so can I save?
I think you can, yeah.
Okay, good.
Good.
Okay.
And then.
Yeah.
Do we need to update the Slurm scripts?
Okay.
So the first step was the parameters as comment line
arguments.
Yeah.
I'm making the preprocessing submission script now.
So yeah, this is what I was saying.
So yeah, it can be split into two.
It can be split into two.
And I think here we are requesting
differing amounts of resources.
Oh yeah.
This is 30 minutes and 500 megabytes.
Yeah.
Which I guess is overkill, but that's how it is.
And then what should this one be called?
So, that would be Submit Trainer Plot.
Okay, I put it there.
Yep.
Okay.
Great.
So, make the submission script.
Yeah.
I see.
Yeah, so we could, now we can run the, can you show the submit trainer?
Oh, okay, no, yeah.
Do we have the submit trainer batch script?
Submit trained. Let's see what we have.
This should have been an .sh script.
Yeah, exactly.
Okay.
Can you show it?
Yes.
There is the $1, the number of neighbors.
So, this also takes the first argument given to it in the command line, which is the number
of neighbors.
So, when we do sbatch, we have a Python script here, which for the number of neighbors, submits
a separate batch job with the submission.sh script and with a command line argument, which
get sent via Slurm to the script, and that becomes this $1.
It will not be a Slurm script, but it will, like, it will, yeah, basically what you said
was true, but there was this, that it's actually the Python script that calls the sbat submission
dot sh as a sub process. And then because it's a sub process, it's a command line command,
then the first argument will be the neighbors or I in neighbors. And important thing here is that
the sub process, when it loops over the neighbors, the sub process will not care about the
result. It will not wait for the result. So, it will submit the job and then immediately go to the
next item in the list. Okay. And maybe we can do this when we come back. I just saw a note that
it's time. But there is one good comment in the notes here. Isn't this going to be difficult
to manage if we submit many independent jobs? Yes, exactly. So what that means is that,
let's say that the job for number 16 failed. In order to rerun that, I'd have to go here,
edit this list so it just has number 16, rerun it, watch the output, and repeat it again.
And that's exactly what will be solved with the WorkflowManager method.
And if there were, like, hundreds of these neighbors here, you also wouldn't want to
do this because it's submitting many independent batch jobs, I guess.
And for that, the next step, the ArrayJobs will be better.
Yes, that's also a good point, yeah.
Okay, is there anything else before we go to the break?
There is a...
Maybe we can have a break now and then we can continue later.
Yeah, exactly.
So let's come back at 14 past the hour.
So 10 minutes starting now.
Okay.
That's good.
Bye.
you
Hello.
thanks again for watching
take care
and see you on our next video
bye
Yeah, so instead of running the thing, the idea would be that maybe we can run the scripts
uh, after lunch together.
Yeah.
Cause, cause running will basically just produce the result,
result files and take time.
So, yeah.
Okay.
So, but there is one, uh, uh, what there was this, uh, can you go back to the.
Yeah. So there are, there is this post-processing steps kind of note. So
yeah. So yeah. So this is not, we don't have a post-processing phase here now, but like
this is the, you could basically expand the pipeline or the workflow by the post-processing.
and this section talks about that.
Okay, do you want to take a look at the comments or
the interactive, no, the shared document?
Headstock. That's the one. Are there questions that should... Okay.
Okay, so next we are actually looking at the RA jobs and there is, and if we go to the,
so the last section was parallelized using scripting.
And then where, and then the next one would be parallelize using slurm array job.
So the, because the preprocessing, the preprocess.py, it has to be run only once.
So that situation will not change here.
That section or that script will be identical.
But the parallelization portion could be done with the array jobs.
So what is the array job?
It is a Slurm native way to submit these embarrassingly parallel jobs.
Is the colon to like every other or no, yeah, I don't know if you can tell, but I don't
use array jobs very much because, yeah, and the reason is like related to the question
that is this better or worse, the script.
Sorry, people couldn't hear me. I was muted.
Okay.
Yeah. Okay.
Okay. So, what was I saying? This relates to the question in the HedgeDoc.
Which is preferable? Array jobs or the scripting?
And there I would say that both are like viable options, but there are like different advantages
here.
And the main advantage of using Array Jobs is that because it's learn native, you can
add in the sbatch options, you can add, for example, email notification that you get a
notification in email when the job has been submitted and when the job is done, either
completed or failed.
That is one advantage of Array Jobs, but the scripts have one advantage that I really like
is that it's really easy to navigate with different kinds of parameters.
Because you can give the command line parameters that are eventually given to looped over and
given to the Python script here.
They can be like integers,
like the number of neighbors,
or they can be strings, like the distance metrics,
or they can be floats and they can be anything,
and it's easy to navigate with them.
On contrast or in contrast with the array jobs,
what we do with the array jobs
is that we give this kind of array of indices,
which can then be accessed with SLURM_ARRAY_TASK_ID.
And that this gets mapped.
Yes, and there is the, yeah, exactly.
So of course, these are like one, two, three, four, five,
or it can be two, from two to a hundred,
And no, it's not divided by two, but like, okay.
But okay.
Anyways.
So anyways, there are integers.
So if you want to use, if you want to use strings, then you'd need to have this
kind of extra mapping step there.
And so, so there are both.
So, the point is both techniques are viable and valid, but they have, it's a little bit
of a different flavor.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, what, do we do this or is this an exercise?
It is an exercise.
Okay.
This is something users can do themselves, or learners can do themselves.
Yeah.
Okay.
And actually, by the way, there is an exercise in the Parallelize using scripting as well.
So this is what we can do after lunch.
Yeah, exactly.
And the exercise there is that instead of looping over the number of neighbors in the
script, we loop over both number of neighbors and the distance
metrics, which is exactly this case that we have different
kinds of parameters. And so with the scripting, it's really
easy to kind of modify your code a little bit. So it takes the
arguments in and loop it over.
Yeah, okay.
Do we go on then?
Uh, yes.
Okay.
So now to the workflow manager one.
Yeah.
And this is where I think it will start
to get interesting,
or at least I hope.
Uh, yeah.
Yeah, because the scripting and
ArrayJobs are very, they are kind of
like the very straightforward ways, or as straightforward as this stuff can be.
Yeah, like it's basically using typical shell scripting in different ways to make loops,
while the workflow manager is really something new.
Yeah, exactly. And I think actually the motivation part here in the workflow manager is quite...
What's the word? Well, complete.
Oops. Okay. Yeah.
So again, to recap, we have the preprocess.py and train-and-plot.py, which are our computational
steps here. And the preprocess.py is run first.
It only needs to be run once.
And needs to be run only once.
Yeah.
So you can, if you move your cursor a bit slower, and then after that, when the preprocess has run,
we have the dataset on the disk, and then we can submit multiple jobs of train and plot
using different number of neighbors and distance metrics values.
And now I see why you made a separate preprocess.py script, because I guess you'll tell SnakeMake
to run this once and run it separately, and it's somehow all...
I think already with the previous scripts, we wanted to have them separately.
Because otherwise, if the pre-processing stuff is in the train and plot script, or they are
in the same script, then for every kind of job or parameter pair we want to run, we will
always do the pre-processing as well.
And that is not necessary and that is just wasting resources because we need to do the
dataset only once.
Yeah.
Okay.
So.
So, there is this kind of note that the submission scripts and array jobs work well for this
kind of small workflows and are usually the go-to solution because they are kind of like
low threshold. But however, if the workflow, if our workflow would be larger, so let's
say we have like multiple pre-processing steps, we can have multiple processing steps. So
instead of just one train and plot, we have like multiple training scripts and then we
We have, and then we have post-processing scripts.
So where we gather the results and maybe do a kind of like a summary of the results.
So in that case, the workflow gets larger and more complicated.
And it is, in that case, it may be a situation where we want to have this workflow manager
tool.
Yeah.
Okay.
Although, again, a reminder that you can also use workflow manager for small workflows,
but there's nothing wrong with that.
Yeah, okay.
So what is a workflow manager?
The workflow manager is, this is how I would, this is how I think of it.
So it's a tool where we define the workflow using rules.
And each rule is one of our computational steps.
So pre-processing or pre-process or training plot in our case.
And each of those rules or steps take as an input file or files.
their output is a file or files. So then you have this kind of like a graph where we create
one rule creates a file and then another rule takes that file as input and creates another file
and another step takes that as an input then.
So I guess it's like this concept, you don't say how to do it, you say
what needs to be done, and then let the workflow manager figure out
what's already done, what's not already done, the best order to do it.
It knows how to do stuff at the same time if it doesn't depend on each other.
Yeah, exactly.
Like the declarative programming language versus the
imperative or something like that. Yeah, exactly. Okay. So, so basically you,
and also just to reiterate the idea that we, we do these rules that are the steps and then,
then we have a kind of like a final rule that are the, what are the, what are the final
target files that we want to have after this workflow.
And so when you say that these are the final files that I want to ultimately end up with,
then you can go step back and step back and step back to the beginning and that the workflow
miniature does this automatically.
Yeah, OK.
OK, so.
OK, so there are three points there, so.
So the order, if it already exists, and then doesn't.
Or order and parallelization.
Yeah, so it's, yeah.
Yeah.
So it looks for the order, looks in the past for what should be done in the future.
Well, anyway, I think we've said this enough.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
Should we start doing it?
Yeah, but one more thing about that.
Here we are using SnakeMake and SnakeMake is very popular,
especially in the, is it bioinformatics field?
Okay.
And it's a, it's written in Python,
but what happens in the computational steps
is like they can be anything.
They don't have to be Python.
And the workflow script that we're gonna see
in just a moment is also,
It's basically Python.
It's a flavor of Python.
So it's a Python-like scripting language.
Yeah.
Okay.
And there are hundreds of workflow miniature tools, but SnakeMake is what we use here.
Do you know why we chose SnakeMake?
Well, people in our proximity have experience with it.
It is well known.
And also because I use Python, I do everything with Python.
So it's kind of like a lowest threshold of, or what is it, barrier of entry?
Yeah.
It's a common thing.
I didn't know the Code Refinery lessons teach it, but I wonder how that was done.
Anyway.
Oh, but that's a good point, because this is Code Refinery as well.
So in this Code Refinery context, when we're talking about workflow manager, we're probably
talking about SnakeMake.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, to access SnakeMake.
Yeah, we still don't get to the actual workflow.
This is like a common theme with workflow manager, that there is a lot of tinkering.
And the first question is, okay, we have this Python package, SnakeMake, how do I actually
access it on an HPC cluster.
And if you're on your own laptop and you want to develop locally, then you can just use
BIP to install the SnakeMake.
But then on the HPC clusters, on many clusters, the situation is that you cannot install your
own packages or software. Like, for example, on Triton, Aalto Triton, you can make, create
conda environments. But, for example, on Lumi, there isn't that kind of option.
But since I'm in Aalto, should I do the module load?
Yeah, exactly. So the important thing here is that it is up to the cluster administration
to provide a way to use Snakemake and similar tools.
If someone lets you, can you do pip install stake make yourself on your own cluster?
Yes, if the admins let you.
Yeah.
Okay.
So I will come back here.
I can make this smaller.
So there are two examples there, that on CSC Puhti and Aalto Triton, they both have,
CSC Puhti has its own SnakeMake documentation, how to use SnakeMake on Puhti.
And on Aalto Triton, if we do the module load Skype, this generic scientific computing Python
environment, then we will get that.
Oh, okay.
You already did it.
Yeah.
Okay.
So you can actually try it out, like if you write snake make and enter them, it should.
Oh, okay.
There's some.
Okay.
It definitely, it definitely like.
Why is it accessing the license server?
I don't know.
This is something that is very...
Let me try it as well.
It's definitely that.
Let's just hope this doesn't come up when we actually try to run the thing.
Yeah, exactly.
I guess there's not some random snake file here.
Huh.
Maybe it's trying to activate all of these different plugins and...
Yeah.
Oh, okay.
Well, if you run, yeah, if you run snake make help, then it will, it will print less of
that stuff.
Okay.
Yeah.
There's a little bit less.
So we have access to snake make.
Yeah.
Okay.
Hmm.
That was interesting.
That was, yeah.
That, that gave me a little bit of, uh, anxiety.
Anxiety.
Okay.
So let's see.
Yeah.
Let's see if the if it works at all then.
Let's make the workflow.
So do I make a new file called snake file?
Yes.
I guess that's a play on make file.
And try this is copy all of this into it.
Yeah.
So what we need is two files in the end, which is the snake file, which is the file that
describes and defines the workflow.
Yeah.
So I see metrics, neighbors list, yeah.
And then we need the kind of configuration, aka profile file.
That's here.
Yeah.
And we will check the profile file after this snake file.
Okay.
So, do you want to use the Emacs or like, let's look at what is in there in the...
In which one?
Snakefile?
Snakefile.
Okay.
Well, we could look here, it's colorized.
Yeah, it took so long to get there, so let's look at it.
So what we have here is that first we have the parameter values.
So this looks familiar.
Yes.
And here is the rule all, which we already mentioned.
So we have one rule, which is conventionally called rule all, that actually lists all the
output files that we are like ultimately interested in, that when the workflow is done, then these
These are the files that we want to have.
Okay.
Yeah.
So it's sort of like pooling in all of these, which are the outputs, which will be defined
below.
Yeah.
Okay.
And then here is an example of like, that, like, that this is, it looks a bit like Python,
but it's not Python per se.
And for example, this expand is one of those snake makes own like syntaxes that it's basically
it does a for loop or two for loops in this case.
So for each neighbors and metric, it creates this and it's a list in the end, what comes
out of the expand. And then the next rule is we're kind of like going from the end to
the beginning. So the next rule is train and plot. And what it does, it reads in the data
pre-processed iris pickle. And it will output the results slash neighbors metric image file.
So output, yeah, this is output PNG with the respective stuff.
And this is how it connects to the rule all because this rule's output is the same as
rule all's input. So this is the same file name. Yeah, exactly. And I guess these end
neighbors variables come automatically from here somehow. Yes, yeah, exactly. The snake make will
kind of, it will inject the values from place to another. Yeah.
And then one nice thing about this workflow is that we can just give it the container.
So in our case, the Apptainer container, and what it does, it says to SnakeMake that, okay,
we want this rule to be run in this container, which is really nice because the container
can be different for each room. So if you have computational steps that need to be run
in very different environments, that's no problem. You can make an image or container
image for each of those environments.
And shell is just the command to actually run inside the container, I guess. So it has
Exactly.
Wildcards metric. What's `wildcards.metric`?
Yeah, so the wildcards is again, snake make syntax. And for some reason, when you actually do the shell, or you run the command,
And you want to refer to the parameter.
You need to use these wildcards, don't.
Okay.
Yeah.
I'll just accept that.
As you can see in the output, you don't have to.
In the log file, you don't have to, but in the shell, you have to.
Okay.
Why?
Who knows?
Yeah.
Okay.
Next, I guess, is the preprocessing rule.
And it's basically, from what I've seen above,
I can tell this is the same.
So there's output file, which is input to this rule,
container log, and the shell command.
Yeah.
Okay.
And the container is the same, but it could be different.
Yeah.
Okay.
And how they are connected is that, again,
input of the rule train and plot is the output of the rule pre-process.
Yes. Okay. For the snake make profile file.
Yeah. So what is the snake make profile file? So profile file is basically the configuration
file, and it can have a lot of configuration, but in our case, the most important thing is that
in this profile file, we will tell SnakeMake that when it submits a Slurm job,
what resources to request. And the nice thing here again, is that we can, if you see the,
the, well, let's go from the top. So we tell the executor is learn. So if we would have
a different kind of cluster, it could be something else. And the maximum number of parallel jobs
is 10, which is good to have. It's good to have like a safety net that if you mess something
up, then you don't spam the cluster with tens of thousands of jobs.
Okay. I bet that's happened before.
Yeah.
And then...
So, threats...
Yeah, this is, so I wrote there that in Snakemake threads is equal to CPUs per task, because
there is this kind of like, because the executor can be anything.
I guess it's not just for Slurm.
So yeah, exactly.
More generic variables.
Exactly.
Yeah.
And the nice thing about, if you check the set threads, the really nice thing about is
that you can see the rule names, preprocess and train and plot.
So here we can set different resources for different rules.
So again, to throw back to the, what was it, the parallelization using scripts, then to
throw back there, there we have for each script, we have the sub slurm batch script.
And in that Slurm batch script, we have these resources defined.
So here we have defined the same resources, 500 megabytes of memory and 30 minutes of
runtime and one gigabyte of memory and one and two CPUs per task.
And one more thing, these profile files are configuration files.
So they can like, you can have like default profile file that the snake make looks in
your home folder and that kind of stuff.
So yeah.
But here we only have this one profile file.
And finally, the run comment, or do you have anything to, sorry, I'm kind of like pushing
this.
Yeah.
What should I do?
So do you have anything to comment or ask about?
Where do I make the profile file?
So it is where you put it.
Yeah.
Where do I put it?
Okay.
So you can see it in the run snakemake command.
Here?
Yeah.
So we will put it in this, we will make a dir folder profiles.
And inside that we have the slurm.
So this is a file.
No, that is also a folder.
Okay.
Yeah.
This is a kind of a confusing thing about the snake make profile in my opinion.
Okay.
Yeah.
Because you don't give the profile file that you want.
You give a folder which contains the profile file.
And what should the file name be?
It's config.yaml with an A.
Okay.
Yeah.
It's also important that it has the A.
Okay.
So, I will paste this here.
Yep.
Save.
Exit.
Okay.
Should I try running it?
Yeah, let's try.
Do you think it works the first time?
I hope so.
But, yeah, anything can happen.
And also, if it works, and even if it works, the output will be really verbose.
So you might want to, like, make the window bigger.
Ah, okay.
Well, we can let it go.
Okay.
What?
Okay, now. Okay. Yeah. Oh, what is this? I wrote password.
I'm trying to set an environment variable and nope. Nope. I haven't encountered this.
So, someone in our chat had wondered, do I, like, is it some other configuration that
I have, but I don't know where it would be?
Yeah.
There's no snake make variables, it's just that that I said.
What could be different in our, well, anything can be different in our configurations, I
guess.
Try reloading the environment.
So we have another cluster admin here in the background, fixing stuff as I'm doing it.
thing. And I've looked in my home directory here in another window and I
don't see anything obvious that looks like that looks like a snake make
make a config file, snake make, can I tell it to not load whatever these other plugins
I'm here.
Oh, okay.
Yeah.
It's trying to load some storage plugin, which I don't know why, because so storage plug-in
meaning that, cause Snakemake may can also incorporate like S3 and those kind of, I would, I would
thinking. Let's see SciBuilder, make storage plugins. But let's, let's give it like one
minute and then, and then let's do a wrap up because this was in a way, this was a perfect
ending for the SnakeMake session. Because this reflects very, very, very well my experience
with SnakeMake.
Do I have any Python packages?
It's a useful tool. This is also something that for those who would like to try the SnakeMake
after the after lunch in one hour basically you can join the zoom and we can we can try to yeah
exactly related to the questions in the notes document um someone's asking docker image or
should be obtainer well the the short answer is that apptainer is the one that will work on a share
system like an hpc system but of course in your in your computer you could you could do it with
docker for example because docker often if not always requires this super user administration
right administrator rights and then snake make will generate the slurm script in a
correct form automatically yeah that's the idea of these plugins if your system is not slurm
do i need some additional custom slurm parameters well i would say that if your system is not slurm
but you're still going to basically use something, I don't know what could be, maybe some Kubernetes
or some other type of cluster. At the end of the day, you can basically tell what would be the
executable for each of the processes that SnakeMake runs. So in theory, even on your own laptop,
if you have multiple CPUs, you can benefit of the parallelization with the multiple CPUs that
you have in your laptop. But in general, I mean, we're showing the SLURM way of doing
it just because most of them, if not all of the clusters that we support and we work with
are basically SLURM based clusters. But it's sometime for wrapping up. We have five minutes
What's left, wasn't that there was some conclusion, take on messages section in the materials?
Let me check.
So what's the conclusions?
I would like first a 30 second conclusion of this workflow miniatures, say, so what
What is the advantage of using a workflow manager compared to...
So there is definitely an advantage, especially if you have a complex workflow, that you kind
of like the workflow manager will take care of the order of execution and that everything
is. And if something is already existing, it won't run it again. And also because we
are using containers and environments, like integrated into the workflow definition, then
it promotes this reproducibility idea. And the disadvantages is that it might be very,
It might be hard to get even started because your cluster may not have SnakeMake installed
and you have to talk to your administration about it, cluster administration.
And the workflow managers have their own syntaxes for the scripting and they have their own
practices and ecosystems and you need to spend time to learn and get into them.
So yeah, there's this learning overhead.
Like I remember [name] saying when preparing for this, today's lesson, that this is going
to be very like, what was it, something about SnakeMake being so hard and having so many
problems when trying to use it and what do you know like here we had a problem it looks
really cool like once we get all these dependencies set up if I had hundreds of different jobs
it would definitely be saving me lots of time yeah yeah and for me the workflow actually
when I when I finally got it working yeah it looks really nice you have snake file and
have profile file and yeah, it just produces the results. But of course it didn't. Now a different
user uses it and there's something in the environment that doesn't work. And yeah,
because I tried it this morning and it worked for me. So I don't know. Okay. So yeah, that was the
the workflow manager comment from me.
Sorry, I took three minutes instead of 30 seconds.
Yeah.
Okay.
So can we wrap up with a couple of take home messages?
And I think you are sharing.
This is the overall conclusions talk here.
Yeah.
So, [name], what should be the take-home message from this day and where can we use them in?
Use very, very simple workflows so that the debugging is easy because there will be problems
when doing parallelization and the simpler your workflows,
then you have a chance of debugging them.
That would be mine.
Take home message.
And in general, I mean, the things we have covered
that especially at this concurrent IO,
if you clearly feel that the parallelization
seems actually to be slower, then maybe it's worth investigating is it an I.O. issue rather
than a computing issue. And so at the end of the day, there's many things that can go
wrong with heavy parallelizations, but it's good to, you know, usually visit your administrator's
help desk and figure out together where would be the good compromise. So I hope this was
a useful two hours overview on our various kind of recipes for parallelizing your code.
In one hour we will have the zoom session so that those who are interested they can actually try
this on their clusters and we will be there together in the zoom to help you trying these
examples and for those who need the credit please join the zoom session and let me know that you're
there so that I can mark your presence. I think this concludes our pilot series of TTT4HPC.
Thank you everyone who has been developing the materials and many people who you actually have
not seen in the in the streams during these four days they have helped so much and we will try to
document all the contributors and managers, whatever. There are also many, many helpers
that have been in building this series that basically took kind of almost two years from
its conception to the actual implementation. This was a pilot run, so we will really need
your feedback in the hack in the notes document there's already a simple feedback form that you
can answer using this share notes and later I will try to send them send a form like a
like a questionnaire so that in general if you can tell us how to improve things for the first run in
in the next fall, that would be great.
So, [name], do you have any last recommendation words?
Really?
Did you say something about credits?
Are we offering credits for this?
Yeah, so for those who need the credit,
please join the Zoom in one hour,
and in the end, exercises that you need to,
like, don't worry about the exercises.
It's more important that you try things out
and you're able to get them working.
All right, thank you [name] and thank you [name].
Thank you.
And thank you everyone for watching
and see you soon for our next streamings
in the CodeRefinery Twitch channel.
Next adventure.
Exactly.
Bye bye.
Thank you.
Bye.
you