So, yeah, in the notes now we have this feedback for day 1 and also a box here for what to
prepare for day 2.
So please come and this poll here, comment where things too fast, too slow, write speed,
whatever.
also have places to note. So what went well, what should we improve for next time, and any other
comments you have. We always take these into account. So today was like sort of very high
levels. So you saw lots of ideas about things, but not many ways to actually do them. But that's
the point. So today's sort of getting ready high level stuff, and then it is tomorrow where we
actually start messing with the cluster and running things. So for that, this connecting
to the cluster is very important that you have working. By the time tomorrow starts...
Ah, there goes the cat. By the time tomorrow starts, it will be too late to fix anything.
Luckily, you've got several hours tomorrow morning to work that out.
There are some other things to prepare. So, as we see here,
there's so we'll be using the cluster from the command line and that's not
something that we will teach but we do have these lessons here which go into
the details and yeah so basically if you're not very comfortable with the
command line, read one or both.
Well, they're pretty similar.
Read one of these.
And actually, maybe try some of the practices and so on.
And that way, you'll be ready for tomorrow.
Is there anything else people should do
to get ready for tomorrow?
Or any other news for the day?
Yeah, I would maybe just say that today, we
talked a lot about what is involved
in scientific computing, what sort of things
are involved in that.
And tomorrow, we'll be mainly focusing on how do you actually
like, we talked a lot about or mentioned
a lot about resources as asking for resources,
choosing the hardware you want to run on it,
that sort of stuff.
And tomorrow, we'll be talking a lot about that,
like, okay, how do you get stuff in the cluster?
How do you know where your code is running?
And for that, it's good to,
like basically the VS code is a good example of something
that you do something on your machine,
but actually it's been done in some other place.
Like actually the running has been done in a remote place.
So tomorrow we'll be basically jumping
to the never never land of the HPC cluster
where goals are different and there's different interesting kinds of adventures to be had.
So basically, just remember that and be already on the mindset that, okay, we'll be working
in a different kind of an ecosystem and different kind of a world compared to your laptop or
your computer that you're watching this way.
Yeah.
I would say like, when I think about my student days
and the first day of using Triton,
all of these data would be a bit confusing at first,
but it's something that you get used to it very fast
when you get the basic ideas of,
and the basic like fundamental definitions of the job
and the resources.
And so if it's a bit confusing for now,
I think it's completely okay.
and you will get used to it very fast.
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, I think that's sort of the core problem here.
There's so many layers of things that are built on top of each other.
There's basic Linux command line usage,
and then on top of that, we have remote connection.
On top of that, we have this whole queuing system.
And then somewhere in there is all the data things.
It is a lot, but hopefully you can get examples
and, well, work through it somehow.
It will take time.
Yeah, and in most cases, we try to, in many cases,
it's a bit of a word salad.
So there's technologies, words mentioned.
And if we use unfamiliar words, do mention that in the notes.
Because this is something that we use the words all the time.
We are in the language, we have it, but it's not meant to be like a secret club that you need to
know the handshakes in order to get into. All of these words are just that we know what the
meaning is, but we try to explain them in a way that they're not something that is impenetrable.
So just ask and we'll try to explain them if we forget to mention them.
Yeah. So please continue giving us this feedback here. There's 50 people watching and this is not
50 answers. At least this poll would be really nice to see. There is a question,
if you don't have access to a cluster, well, we can only teach it. We can't give you access if
you're not at one of our institutions. But if you're in some university, they probably have
some method of doing this. Or, you know, you can listen, and you have the knowledge, and you can
come back later when you need to. Okay. Yeah. Should we end then? I guess we're over time
already. So thanks to everyone and see you tomorrow. Please, so as it says here
you can keep joining this zoom for help with connecting and you can keep asking
us questions here and we'll keep answering for a few more minutes. Yes.
Okay, thank you. Bye. Bye. Bye-bye.