Hello, welcome back. Hopefully you had a good little break. So next up we have something
which we call the humans of scientific computing. So it's interviews where we basically talk
about ourselves. And our special guest this time here is [name], who was in the
previous talk, actually. Hi. So, [name], can you tell us a little bit about
yourself again and maybe go more into what's your background and how did you start your career?
Okay, yes. So, I did my bachelor in Germany in Geoecology or Natural Sciences and then went on to
to start my Master's in Geoinformatics from where I went on an exchange year to Finland
to Aalto University during my Master in Geoinformatics and that led me to being in
contact with the Finnish Geospatial Research Institute where I asked for a possibility
to do my master thesis here because I really liked Finland and I really wanted to stay here.
This was almost nine years ago now, I'm still in Finland, so it all worked out. I got to do
my master thesis, they actually paid me for it and even offered me a job after that at the
Research Institute where I was working with satellite remote sensing mainly and at some point
they said okay we would actually like everyone to have a PhD because that just makes life at
the Research Institute much easier. Don't you want to start one? And I hadn't thought about this
before so much but I was like hey it's the same as my normal work so why not like package it and
do a PhD. As you maybe mentioned before I'm still working on that even though this is now also
already almost seven years ago. That's mainly due to it being very short only full-time,
but mainly being part-time. So I did other work during the same time. For a short while,
I did it full-time because I got a grant from Aalto University to focus on it, but there was
a few projects that didn't go as planned. Maybe you know about these things. And yeah, nowadays,
like two years ago I got an email that CSC was looking for a geoinformatics specialist and I was
reading like through the job ad and was like yes yes yes yes oh this sounds interesting but I was
a little bit like afraid also of it because CSC like the big scientific computing center and
my background is not in like really computing or something. I learned most of it actually during
the PhD times like I learned about how to use Linux, I learned programming in Python and so on
during that time and I learned also how to use or well yeah how to use supercomputer partly
through this course, but also through CSC courses. I knew how to apply this for my research. I knew
how to run something in parallel on the supercomputer, but I had never looked behind that.
So I was a little bit like, is this really something for me? But then I talked to a lot
of people in especially the coderefinery community and they very much encouraged me to do that
still and yeah here I am nowadays. I work two years now as a geoinformatics specialist
helping geoinformatics researchers with bringing their computations
to the supercomputer and doing training and so on and nowadays a bit more general so it's not
any more geoinformatics specific, but also for other fields and to outreach, trying to reach
people in the early stages, for example, of their PhD to know that there is these CSC services and
stuff like Code Refinery available. So what does it mean trying to help people to bring their work
to the CSC supercomputers? Let's exclude the Code Refinery work and other teaching things.
What's a day in your life look like?
Well, so in that regard, it's basically like this morning we had a workshop with,
in this case, humanists. So we asked them, do you know about CSC resources,
do you know about supercomputers, that they exist for your work? And they said no.
So we had to say like, okay, this is not just for supercomputation, but it's also like if you have
something, a small thing that you need to run multiple times, like trying to explain it in a way
that they can relate to it based on their current work. And that is mainly what a lot of this is,
trying to lower the barrier towards supercomputing, HPC, all those big words that if you're not
coming from computational backgrounds are maybe not that familiar.
Yeah.
So do you actually help them to like, do you take their code or analysis and actually help
them get it started running?
Things like that.
Yes.
So if we know about that people struggle with making their own code run, for example, on
our supercomputers, then we get to help them.
And we get to tell a little bit about the maybe different way of thinking that you need
to start when you switch from your own laptop to the supercomputer.
it's very often that we don't know about it. Very many people find that their problem is too small
or they are they have not read enough documentation or have some other reason for not asking for help
and then of course we cannot help and sometimes we then get to know about it very late in the process
And then of course we also still try to help, but the best experience for us and also for the researchers that we support is like when we get involved right in the beginning.
For CSC services, for example, when we are already part of choosing the right service because we have so many of them.
And as a researcher, it's not necessarily clear what is the right service for me.
service for me. So that is also, for example, a very general question that one can ask from
us where we can say like, okay, this is perfect for this service or perfect for another service.
Yeah. Okay. What have you learned in your past research, like from your research career
to what you do now? What did you learn when studying research that helps you now?
I think the main thing that helps me in my job right now that I have learned from the
time as a researcher is how, I don't know how to put it, but how a researcher thinks.
It's not just telling, okay, we have these awesome services, here are 20 courses you
can do to learn about these services.
But it's more like also thinking about where the researchers are and what are their goals.
For most researchers, that is to get the paper out.
So, that is the main focus.
All this stuff like version control, reproducible research is like a minor thing at the side
which might even be bugging them rather than helping.
Yeah.
And I think...
It's like this researcher mindset.
Yeah, exactly.
Like being able to help on a level that is actually helpful for a researcher.
Not only like, okay, here is all the things you need to know, but also trying to convey
that there is something as good enough.
There is like small steps you can take to make your and other's life better.
You don't have to do everything.
And that we can actually help with that.
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay, so you said you were a little bit worried about the transition when you started.
I mean, were you, like, how worried were you and, like, what were the kinds of things you
worried about?
Let's put it that way.
And then how did it turn out in the end?
Was it actually anything worth worrying about?
No, it was not.
That was the first thing.
I was very worried about not being able to answer all the questions people might have,
because one big part of this job that I applied for was user support and was training.
I was not doing a lot of this at the time, mainly with Code Refinery, actually, and there
it was always a second person there.
When I didn't know something, then the second person could jump in.
about this being alone there and being alone with a user, with a researcher who asks me questions
and I might not know the answer that was a very scary thing because for me the support I have
gotten from CSC was very personal and very good and like of course like that was my picture of
how it's supposed to be and I'm still thriving for that but since then I've also learned that
like, it's okay to not know everything. We cannot know everything. There's so much to know,
like, not only about our services, but about scientific computing in general.
And very often, I still know maybe one little thing more than the researcher who is asking
the question. So even just telling, hey, I know that we have a documentation page about this,
or, hey, you could look into this tool, this might do what you want to do. That already helps
sometimes so much that the researcher is happily going away. And it feels like having accomplished
something, even though I actually didn't know the actual answer to the problem. And that was maybe
the main worry, like not being good enough with the computational side of things. Like someone who
has like programmed their whole life or studied computer science or anything like that.
So what do you say? It's like you bring your researcher mindset to the current things.
When you were a researcher, you solved problems no one knew the answer to and you do the same
now.
Yes, yes, I think so. And I have to remind myself once in a while about that, like how
it was these, let's say five years ago, when I was the researcher struggling with something and
also feeling all my questions not big enough, like what would I have needed at the time to
kind of brave off, ask my questions from the specialists and also what kind of
of support would I have needed?
Like that in many occasions,
because everyone is short on time,
it is the easy answer to find a link to documentation
and just say, hey, read this.
This is an easy solution to many of troubles
that people have.
But as a researcher,
I have gotten that answer also at some point.
And maybe I've even read the page at the time,
but I was not able to put what is written there
into the context of my work.
So nowadays I try to remember that.
And when someone asks a question,
I like try to first ask, okay,
what is this actually about before answering?
With also some links in a side sentence,
like saying, okay,
you could also take a look here at this tutorial,
but also try to explain how this relates
to the actual question that was asked.
Okay, that's good.
So we've got a question from the note.
So I'm at the beginning of my career as a master's student
and I'm considering academia.
What is the thing that one should know when starting?
I guess you're not the academic career path,
but this is similar to a common question I've asked people.
What do you know now that you wish someone
had told you years ago?
so. That this path exists, like that there is a way to not be an academic, not be a researcher,
doing your own research, trying to write papers and doing that stuff, but that there is also
stuff like you do at Aalto, the research software engineer, stuff like we do at CSC with the user
support and so on. People that are very much connected to the research but don't have to
write their own papers but rather support everyone who needs the support doing their
research and that can be more efficient, faster or just even like getting started with it.
So I wish I had known that earlier. I got to know that actually through Code Refinery because when
When I visited the Code Refinery Workshop, I got really excited about this, and asked
to get involved in the project and do stuff there, and went then from helper to instructor
to an organizer and community manager.
But only through joining that network, I got to know that there is so much more beyond
the traditional academics and research software engineering and so on.
Yeah. The next question there asks about what kind of positions are in private companies,
which I guess neither of us are really qualified to answer. Maybe next year I could try to
find someone that works at a private company and invite them.
Yeah. And I know that there is also a research position in private companies, for example.
But yeah, that as a short answer.
But I mean, I guess the point of this whole interview is that there are positions which
are related to research and quite interesting in their own right, which are not the academic
track, which many people are qualified for and don't know about.
Yeah, and it's so interesting to also, as a researcher, you are in your own little world
with your focus point, especially as PhD,
you have your little slice of the world
that you're working on.
But as what we do, we get in contact
with many different people from many different domains,
backgrounds, levels in their, or stages in their career.
And it's very interesting to be part of kind of all of that,
even when it's just a little bit through one question
that we get in our user support sessions or something.
Would you say that you have a wider variety or more interesting problems now or when you
were in the academic track doing your own stuff?
Yes, definitely.
Also partly because, well, when I was a full academic, it was just when I started with
programming and scientific computing things in general, so I worked on one big project
for very, very long because I just had to learn at the time also.
So I got very sick of that project, but it's still also with me.
But now it's more varied.
So there's many different questions that people come with.
Some are easy to solve, like within a few minutes.
Some need more hours.
Some maybe need more days.
Yeah. And very much varied. Yeah.
So we're coming a little bit close to the end here. There's still almost 10 minutes, but please, so now's the time people start writing all your random questions in the notes, the ones that are most relevant to [name], I will raise up, but other people can also answer there.
There is a question I would like to answer actually. Do people in industry use these things you mentioned earlier, like conda containers and HPC?
Conda and containers, yes, definitely, if they know about it, that's not necessarily
a given.
And for us, it's probably harder to reach people in companies.
HPC, maybe nowadays a bit more than earlier, because, for example, the Lumi supercomputer
is available for companies as well.
And if you go to the Lumi website, you can find out that there is a few companies using
Lumi.
So for those, we also offer kind of a specific training and get, oh, we wish, I don't know
how it really is in industry.
Maybe someone who's working in industry can talk.
Okay.
Yeah.
So what do you say that this course that's here now is also useful for industry track
people?
Yes.
I would say so, because you might be the one bringing that stuff to the company.
They might not know about it for whatever reason, and you might be the one that then has a solution
to a problem by, for example, knowing how to, well, organize your project to start with,
or if you visit a code refinery course, like knowing how to use Git that can make
many processes more efficient, and then the company will be very happy about that.
Yeah, yeah. So would you say that these kind of courses give you an advantage when looking for
other jobs? I mean, I guess, well, that's probably obvious. Let's say you finish a PhD and you have
a bunch of articles to your name, or you have a bunch of articles and you say,
I've trained to use supercomputers in Git. That's pretty obvious.
Yeah, that probably depends on what you're then looking for.
So what I have learned from getting the job at CSC is that just having used a supercomputer is
a very good starting point for even working in supercomputing support, for example.
because you actually know, you might not know every detail, but you can learn that also on the
job. I learned so much every day on the job. But you know where the researchers are coming from,
so you have been in the situation that you have asked some of these questions yourself. So
I think with that knowledge you can be a very good person to be between the IT admins
and the researchers to translate between them, like if the IT admin says like oh this is not
something we do here, then you can start explaining why this is not something we do here for example.
Yeah, cool. So what's your experience with the PhD overall? Would you say it was worth it?
So I'm still working on it, so yes I think it's still worth it.
Mainly because I have now also seen in my current job, it's a permanent position, so I would not necessarily need it for that.
But we are still working so close with academia that we also want to support research projects from the beginning and support them really a bit more in depth.
depth and for that we need to be part of the research project funding application and for
that it's better to have a PhD to your name because you actually have some academic
merits that help with this with the project application while without that we have only
like a few people who can be this PIs of the research project within the company so too many
research projects that want to maybe put us on the application, we have to say no,
because we don't have the people to actually cover that. And I have learned everything that brought
me right here, right now, during the time of my PhD. Basically, none of it I learned during my
actual studies, master's or bachelor.
Yeah. Okay. When do you say like the PhD is basically experience that counts for something?
Yes. And I think like, of course, you don't need to do a PhD. You can also work as a researcher after your master's.
The PhD maybe allows that you can do or also gives a bit easier the possibility to do courses.
Like for example I could get I think over 10 credits for my PhD from visiting CSC courses
for example and that also of course motivated me to do the courses because I could fill my credits
with that. If I would not have done the PhD I would have maybe done like maybe one course
a year or something just to learn something new, stay up to date and stuff.
But in that sense it was really useful. Yeah, so we're almost out of time. So
what do you hope to continue learning and what comes next?
Well, I hope to continue learning more about how things work, how many of our services work,
How to reach, like currently my focus is a lot on outreach so I hope to learn more about
how to best reach out to people that would have use for our services and that would have
use for our support because there is so much of it available, so many people that are very
happy to help with things and I'm always so sad to hear stories like that someone has
been struggling with something that we could have helped with if we had only known
after two years of struggling or something like this. Yeah. Okay.
Yeah, I guess we're basically out of time. There's a comment that you're really cool
and a good role model. So yes, I would agree with that.
Thank you.
You know, many of our visitors here are like that. So yeah, I mean, we have to keep finding
more for next year.
I'm glad to hear this was useful. Thank you for having me.
Yeah, I mean, like really, [name] and all of us, we're basically normal people that
want to keep work going, help, basically, yeah.
You're normal nerds.
Yeah.
But yeah, OK.
So I guess thank you, [name], and see you
around at the next Code Refinery workshop in September.
Yeah, and if you have any more questions,
I'll still be here and answer them in the document.
Keep them coming.
OK, great.
Thanks.
Bye.