Hello, can everyone hear us?
Can someone give a reaction, if you can?
Hello, hello.
So if you can, we are here.
What I've shared here is our notes.
If you've registered, you should have it as a link.
We can scroll down to this icebreaker and begin talking a little bit while I try to
stop my cat from destroying something on my desk.
How come the cat is very active?
It's just 11.50.
I guess it just, well, I don't know, like sometimes it comes earlier in the day.
So for anyone new here, my cat often visits during courses, especially later in the day
as it approaches 4 o'clock when it's its feeding time.
So that's the motivation for staying through the whole time.
So if you leave early, you lose cat observation possibilities.
Anyway, yeah.
So hi everyone.
gotten any indication of audio yet?
I checked the stream and it seemed to
work at least. Okay, good. But if others want to respond to the
notes that's of course a good idea. Yeah, so the next question is
is our audio balanced?
Should we do the standard test?
Yep.
Okay.
Me, [name], [name].
One.
Two.
Three.
Four.
Five.
Six.
Okay.
Let us know who might be quieter.
How can people let us know?
Well, at least the channel people could.
Yeah.
So you can write it in the notes here.
Let me open that up. Oh yeah, actually, someone is writing. I'm the loudest. Okay. Yeah,
I'll turn myself a bit up or just shout a bit louder. Okay.
So anyway, some people have already figured out how Notes and stuff works. So basically,
we have this document everyone can write. And as we're talking at any time, you can write questions
or comments. One of the co-instructors might see it, but we also have a whole bunch
of people in the background who will be reading and answering during the course. So, you can
ask as many questions as you want, and usually we get most of them answered.
And as a practice, we have icebreakers here. So, please open it up if you're registered.
If not registering, we'll get you the link automatically emailed to you.
And then scroll down to these sections.
So what's your position?
Use this O symbol to vote.
So as you see, people are adding different votes here.
It's like a dynamically generated bar graph that's a poll.
So yeah, add in your votes there.
Then you can also add in where you are now,
so as in what city or country you're in.
Or you can try to be more clever if you want to.
What's the biggest computer you've used so far?
Yeah, I mean it could be your own computer or some workstation.
And then what do you work on?
Yeah, so like what kind of scientific work or other work, basically, while you're here.
So we want to know a little bit about you. And maybe we can start by telling about
us some. So I'm [name]. I'm a, well HR considers me a staff scientist at Aalto
University. I work in the computing, the high-performance computing team at Aalto. And we also do a
lot of teaching, and then a lot of research software engineer support. So basically going
and helping you with your very code. And I'm really glad to be here. So this is one of our
best and most important courses of the year, and we're glad that we have several hundred
registrations here. [name], do you want to tell a little bit about you?
Yes, so my name is [name]. I'm a Research Software Engineer in Aalto Scientific Computing.
Previously worked on the HPC side of the team as well.
Yeah, I've been teaching this course for many years now in conjunction with other people and yeah, I think it's very good.
we try to make this course as palatable for people that are new to HPC so that they don't get scared
and people can do their research in the best way possible. So I'm very happy to be here and
see what we can achieve together during the few days. Yeah okay and [name]. And then it's me
which most likely you've seen my name in your mailbox. So I've been coordinating this
adventure as well as many other that we have had and we will have in the future. So in
general we are organizing these type of open courses. I don't know if this is the first time
that you attend a course on Twitch TV. For us it's always exciting even though we've been doing this
for what, two years now? Two years. Or is it three years? Yeah, maybe three years.
Or is it 2021 January? Yeah, anyway. And we hope even actually that this way of
teaching is inspiring in a way that maybe next time you want to join us for some broadcasting
together to talk about your research or how you solve some problems that could be helpful
for others too. So I would want to quickly mention that we mentioned Twitch. One
quality of life thing for the Twitch stream. I would highly recommend that everybody goes
in the Twitch stream and then checks the gear icon on the bottom right and sets it instead of auto
into the best possible resolution.
Because Twitch tries to modify the bandwidth
or which compression it uses in the stream.
So if you want to see the crisp clear text that we are streaming
then setting it to the best possible resolution is a good idea.
Is this new? So I thought at one point
point Twitch didn't do transcoding for free streams.
I think it does for all streams.
Yeah, it does like less time with performance.
Yeah, exactly.
So from the gear icon on the settings,
you can check the quality.
And if you set it to be the source quality,
you will get the best view of the material.
Yeah.
OK.
So my next question, what's the coolest thing about today
that people should look forward to?
Let's go backwards.
[name].
Well, I'm going to briefly talk about Code Refinery, which
is a six-day workshop, but I will
try to compress it in 20 minutes just
give them motivation for people to take it next time we run it. So at least that's the most exciting
thing that I will talk about today. But what about you [name]?
Well I would say the most interesting part for me is like new demos that we have planned for this
year. So new demos on how to run few software for softwares in the cluster and hopefully they will
demonstrate what sort of capabilities the computing cluster can have. But also I would
say that I always enjoy listening to our guest talk and the guest people who come and discuss
about how they how they do their HPC work and how they ended up in the computer like
in the field of doing computations with well scientific computations.
Yeah. Because that's something new every year for me.
Yeah. And same for me. I mean, it's easy to get courses and read about technical things,
but the way we've added this interview with how people actually find their careers in these fields,
I think, is a story that is really often not told. But with that being said,
it's almost time to get started. Should I switch to my screen for the intro?
Yep. Okay, so we've got 10 minutes. Here we go. This is the