Bye.
So now it's 11 past 12.
So we are almost perfect with the timings.
As you see in the schedule here,
there's going to be me and [name] now
talking about from data storage to your science.
It's, you know, very generic talk,
but it's good in my opinion to set the basics.
We've been doing it.
We've been doing this type of basic things over the years and it's good to start with
some definition of what people mean with computing and of course, it's always good to cite some
XKCD cartoon and this is very, very representative of the average picture of a researcher in academia
but also in industry. Honestly, the picture is the same. So the one guy is asking, this is your
machine learning system. Yep. You put the data into this big pile of linear algebra and then
collect the answers on the other side. And what if the answers are wrong? You just steer the,
you know, steer the pile until they spit, until they start looking right. So in general,
scientific computing is about getting some data in doing some magic with the data and getting
something out but of course in between it's not just a black box there's so many things to take
into account which resources do you need and i'm really talking about physical you know hardware
hardware resources or maybe what you need to be careful with the code with the environment
so that you can, for example, reproduce what you do.
So here we have a common scientific computing flow chart,
which is basically what the cartoon was saying earlier.
You get some data.
You get some models that might come from other sources.
You have hypotheses from the literature or whatever you learn from the literature.
And then everything gets gathered into this process block.
And so given the data, the models and whatever else you need to gather together, you generate
the outputs, which could be these derivatives, so-called derivatives file, they can be figures,
they can be tables. And then you write your papers, your posters and so on.
So what actually happens in practice, and I know this is super basic, maybe most of you have done
this in high school, but it's always good to set the dictionary for everyone. So there's this type
of user layer, which is where we are right now. And as a user, you might work with some applications.
You might use R, Matlab, Python, and so on. The applications are on top of a so-called
operating system. It can be Linux, it can be Windows, it can be Mac, whatever. And on top
of the operating system we have the actual hardware, the CPU central processing units where
the actual math happens, the memory random access memory which is where you want to store your
variables or your code for the time that the CPUs can access it, this SSD which is basically the
a little bit slower and bigger storage for storing the data or the code or whatever else
you need to store.
In some hardwares, we also have the GPUs,
which are like CPUs, but many of them
compressed together so that things can be
done much faster in parallel.
And we will talk about this in the day two and three.
But then, of course, you have connectivity,
because sometimes you need to download data
from external sources to your laptop,
or maybe you're not even on your laptop,
like we will show tomorrow.
and the day after, because your laptop doesn't have GPUs,
your laptop doesn't have enough RAM.
So you are in some remote system connected via the internet
where you can run your things.
So here we wrote together kind of a glossary of these terms
in case some of these are not familiar.
But now maybe if I can ask a question to [name],
like what I'm kind of started to describe what's a laptop
what's the normal workflow that people might be familiar with, but how do I know how to know when
I need to scale up to a bigger system? Maybe another question that I can add is that often
people they move their workflow from the laptop to some HPC system and they realize that it's
actually slower there. Why is it so? If we think about the previous diagram of the scientific
process that you showed, it didn't show anything about how do you plan on doing this? Or which
hardware are you planning to use for any of these things? Where do you do the processing for the raw
data and the models and what do you do with the derivatives? It doesn't have any connection or
necessary like definition of where do where should you run these where should you do these
calculations and for many of us it's of course we are using the nearest machine that we have let's
say our computer like our laptop that is provided by the department so we are using the most obvious
resource that we have to do many of these calculations and usually that machine is for you
that machine is dedicated for you, that is yours. And when we are then speaking about
high-performance computing, we are talking about the process where we're pooling resources so that
we can share the resources. Like we have usually funding from a bigger provider that gives us
possibility of getting bigger machines and the bigger machines are then shared by multiple people.
So some of that process, let's say we have an experiment that we want to do, but one part of
that process of doing the analysis is so slow with our laptop that we would want to do it
faster and for that we need to use some shared resource. But the shared resource, because of
the nature that it's shared, we need to usually ask the correct things from it, or we need to
reserve our correct portion of it. So if we don't reserve the correct portion of this resource,
we might reserve less resource than what our laptop has, or we might reserve resources that
that don't solve the correct problem
that we are currently doing.
So for example, we might reserve a GPU
and think that, well, GPUs usually make stuff faster, right?
Like that's the narrative.
So let's just reserve a GPU
and let's just hope that it runs faster,
but that doesn't necessarily work like that.
If the program you're using doesn't use GPUs,
it doesn't necessarily work.
So when we are switching from our laptop to the shared resources,
we usually switch to a different location.
So in a different location might have different things
that make the computing faster.
So we need to basically take advantage
of the specialized hardware.
So for example, our laptops might have maybe eight,
maybe 16 CPUs, and the nodes,
the computational servers in an HPC cluster,
they might have up to 256 processors,
but those processors might be slower
than the laptop processors on average,
but because there's so many of them,
if your program can utilize many processors,
program can still be faster. There's different kinds of resources in the HPC cluster that are
specialized for certain kinds of things. When we are asking, okay, I want to run my code
better or faster, we need to know what our program does and then ask for those resources that
the computational cluster can provide that makes it faster. And here are a few of the
really great questions that you can ask yourself. So, for example, do you need more CPUs? If you
can parallelize your processing. We'll talk about this on day three. You might benefit from adding
CPUs. Sometimes you don't. You might want one big computer or multiple small computers.
That might also benefit you. If your code uses GPUs, like for example, deep learning stuff
nowadays, your only option might be to run it on a computing cluster because the model might
be so big that you cannot run it on a normal laptop or computer. Your laptop might not even
have a GPU. Sometimes you have a lot of data that you need to process, so you need to get the data.
You need to make certain that the data is in the correct place so that the speed is good.
So when you're switching from your laptop to using these shared resources,
do keep in mind that you're basically switching places.
You're switching to a completely different environment.
And in that environment, there are different kinds of considerations.
It's optimized for different kinds of use cases.
And if you don't know necessarily what use case you want to do
or you don't know what your program is doing
it's usually a good idea to ask help from more experienced users
or the system administrators and so forth
so that they can figure out which program your program benefits most from
Yeah, one aspect that you see here at the bottom that sometimes maybe you don't even
need like your laptop would be totally fine with the resources that you have, but it's
the data that you're working with that cannot be taken away, that cannot be taken out from
your share folder in the university.
And so then these remote resources, these large computational resources can also be
useful that the computations and the data stay in the remote, but of course you can still
use your laptop with fake data or just for development.
But basically, yeah, this session
is kind of just to set the basics for everyone here.
There's some, how do I do scientific computing?
It's most likely you already know where to start,
whether you're a Python, R, or whatever programming languages.
There are good practices for each language and tools
available.
And you can understand already that what works on your laptop
doesn't necessarily, it's not necessarily going to work
on the remote cluster.
But what we will see in the rest of the day
and also in the next days is basically strategies to move,
for example, the same so-called Python environment
from your laptop to a remote location,
or to make sure that you have the software
that you need to run in the remote location.
Here, there's a picture of what [name] was saying earlier
that once you leave your laptop,
if you think that this is the internet,
you can basically request remote servers,
remote so-called nodes.
So there are other pieces of hardware,
there are other machines that can allow you
to do your computations, not on your laptop anymore,
but on the remote location.
This picture is generic enough in a sense
that this is not specific to Aalto.
There are some of these open services,
There's a list here in the bottom, like MyBinder or Google
Colab, where you can run this type of computations
via a so-called notebook interface with a web browser.
What we will explore more tomorrow
is this type of HPC clusters that universities usually
give access to, and also the national providers,
like CSC in Finland.
And often what you will notice, and what we will remind also
today, is that sometimes to work with this system,
you need to, it's not as easy as, you know,
opening a web browser
and using the so-called notebook interface.
You might need to be familiar with the command line interface
and access, for example, the login node,
and then later request, you know,
one of the hundreds of CPUs or GPUs and so on.
But don't worry about this.
We will cover this during the connection session
in later today.
We are perfectly on time with our schedule now because it's 12.25 and I could keep screen sharing
and give a motivational talk with [name]. [name], are you here?