And welcome back.
So now we are essentially at the next stage and we actually want to connect to our clusters.
The documents or documentation that we have is mainly for Aalto but conceptually it's the
same for any other cluster.
are plenty of different ways how you can connect to the clusters and we will talk about two of them.
Essentially we will talk about an SSH connection and we will show a bit of the
on-demand that [name] has already showed in the last session.
So if I scroll down a bit in the materials there's a long list here but some will exist on your
cluster and some will not. All of them exist on Aalto, but they show the two main things, I guess.
We will, for demonstration purposes, assume that you have direct internet access to your cluster.
That means if you are on Aalto, you need to be on the virtual private network because the
Sorry, because the Triton cluster is not directly accessible from the internet except the open
on demand approach.
So if you want to follow and want to type along, you will need to be on the VPN.
the question came up before what's the difference between the login node and the compute nodes.
I think this image shows it quite well. So the login node is the element that's connected to
the net. In this case is the Aalto network. On Lumi or other CSC machines it's directly connected to
the internet and this machine is essentially your entry point to the cluster this is the machine
where you submit jobs where you get where you put things uh onto onto the cluster or tell the
cluster okay i want this to be computed um in general why if you want to connect to the cluster
the first thing you have to do is you have to get an account i assume that all of the all of
of you have done that for your respective clusters.
And we will first go through the SSH connection,
and [name] will demonstrate that.
OK, so just to be sure, I'll just say again.
So I'm connected to the, I mean, the Aalto network through the VPN.
[name]'s, there's notes that [name]'s voice is much louder.
Okay, well, the only easy way I can access that is from here, so just a moment.
Okay, does that change the volume?
[name], can you say something? Does it change it?
I hope it changed our list.
Okay, well.
I guess we can, we should move on. Yeah, okay, sounds good.
Okay, so I have a terminal open here and yeah, I am on the Aalto network.
work. That's important. So what do I do? I will use a standard method. I have some setup
here that would make it – I could type a significantly shorter command, but I will
try to stick to whatever, something that works on whatever system you're on.
So the command is ssh.
Actually before I do that, why don't I show where I am right now.
So I can type the command hostname.
That is the name of my laptop.
That's another laptop.
have usually a name that's something like this, starting with an l and with a number.
I can also show my username, and that is, well, that is my username. It's, again, an
Aalto username, so actually you will see the same one on Triton. Maybe it would have been
more interesting to see it change, but, well, if you're going from an Aalto machine, you
always have the same username.
Okay. So I am on this machine and now I will type the command.
So username, add,
and then the name of the machine.
So that's triton.aalto.fi.
The important bit here is it's
the username that you have on the system that you want to connect.
Yes.
And you seemingly already have set up SSH keys.
Yes, that is true.
If you, I'm on the VPN,
right, it didn't ask for a password, correct, yes.
So should we demonstrate again
what it looks like if you haven't set it up?
There's not a big change.
The main difference is that you will be asked
for your password on the machine.
And there are actually systems like Lumi
where you have to have a ssh keys being set up.
Otherwise you can't.
So I think the biggest difference,
I think that people will see,
well, there is that it will ask for a password.
It will, if it's the first time connecting
to a new server, so a new machine,
it will also ask you, it will print this key
That's essentially a random string of characters and it will ask you if that is the correct
one.
So if you're connecting to something for the first time, it's pretty much safe to just
type in yes.
You can check it somewhere.
You can check that it's correct.
Yeah.
I will put that into the document, at least for Triton.
So, I will go to the shared document.
For essentially any HPC service,
there will be a page where the SSH key fingerprints
are being listed.
And you can check whether what's being shown to you
will be, or is the same as what's listed on there.
And if it is, then you are connecting to the correct.
Yeah, so this, having this key on the system
essentially proves that it is the right machine.
Nobody's trying to fake Triton.
You are actually in the actual correct Triton machine.
The main thing though is,
because when you're connecting for the first time,
it will just send it to you
and your machine has nothing to compare it to.
So it will ask you to accept it.
From then on, if it ever changes,
your machine will either just refuse to connect,
or it will at least ask you to check what's going on.
And it refuses the connection and tells you,
yeah, you can remove the old key there.
But that's the point where checking
whether the keys have actually changed makes sense.
Yes.
So if the key changes, it's either something really drastic
has happened, like we have a new version of Triton
something. It's a completely new machine or someone is actually doing an attack and trying
to get you to lock into the wrong system. So if it complains about this, it is a good thing to check
but usually it doesn't. But essentially this is how you connect via SSH. Yes. There's really
not much more to it. Actually, now in the prompt you do have the name of the machine. It's login4.
You do have my username. We can type hostname and see. It's login4.triton.aalto.fi and
who am I again? It's the same as before unfortunately, but well that is my username on Aalto.
Okay, well, are we going to do anything more here?
I guess not much.
We will, of course, be using the machine much more in the next two days.
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay, then for the on-demand, which...
So this is in the browser.
Yeah, this is a way that is quite convenient as well, depending on what you want to do.
So essentially, you go to the page that [name] had shown earlier, which is on-demand.
Yes, so there is a, well, first of all,
there's instructions for connecting with SSH.
And then there is a link to ondemand.triton.aalto.fi.
It's relatively easy to remember or bookmark.
Let's go there.
I didn't actually want to close the materials, so I'll open it back up.
Okay, so this is what the Triton Open On Demand looks like.
I'm already signed in.
I'm already logged in.
It will ask you to log in with your Aldo credentials.
which you have seen many times already.
It's using a standard multi-factor authentication for that.
So, in here you have multiple different things that you can do.
One thing, or the most convenient thing to use is the Triton Shell access,
which is essentially another...
Shell, this will do exactly the same thing as SSH, except in the browser.
browser.
Except in the browser.
So you don't even need to type in any passwords
because it already has your credentials.
So that's kind of convenient if you just
want to throw in a few commands and you haven't set up
the command line in more detail.
And this works from outside Aalto.
But you do need to log in in the browser
with the two-factor authentication.
Yep.
The second thing is something that [name] has already shown.
Essentially, the Triton desktop.
This is for any graphical applications.
It could also be if you have some software that
has a simple graphical installer,
you could essentially just request the session
and run it there and see if it installs
or if it's missing things.
If it installs and it's a graphical tool,
you might encounter some issues running things later on
if you're not running it via Triton desktop,
because the desktop does load a couple of libraries that
are only available on some of the nodes.
Because as mentioned earlier, we want
to keep the nodes themselves as nimble as possible
so that they are not wasting resources
and there are only a limited amount of things now.
So I have access now, so I can click through here.
There are, well, one or two things
that we might want to show.
So if you work with Chrome, Chrome
has the option to share the clipboard with the browser,
which is quite convenient.
If you have a browser that doesn't support that,
you have this thing on the side where you also
have a clipboard.
I'm going to copy the address from here,
so that it should now be on the clipboard.
And indeed, because I am on Chrome,
it is here on the clipboard.
But if it's not, you can paste it in,
and then you have it in a clipboard of this remote system,
this Triton session.
Might be a convenient thing if you, as I said, want to install some software and have a license
key or something like that, you can essentially copy-paste that via this method.
Otherwise, if you're used to the Linux desktop environments, this is very familiar.
And in general, it's of course very similar to any desktop environment.
I can also open a terminal from here or run any other software.
Of course, running a terminal from here is not necessarily the easiest way of accessing
a terminal in Triton.
Now I'm actually on a compute node, which is an interesting difference to the previous
one.
Yeah.
So, this is not the login node.
We can do more stuff here.
You are essentially only restricted by the amount of resources that you have requested
when you were requesting this session.
And there's one third thing that I think is worth mentioning on this on-demand, and that's
a relatively easy way to transfer files.
So we go out of the desktop.
I don't know if logging out is very important.
Can I go and delete it?
You can go and delete it from here as well.
Yeah.
If on demand, you go to this files thing.
Yes.
[name] has access to a couple of projects, obviously.
Normally, you only have your home directory,
your work directory, and potentially additional projects
that you are a member of.
And that is a relatively convenient method to at least upload smaller files and smaller things.
If we are getting into the gigabyte range, I would personally recommend to use the command
line and things like rsync or similar. But for smaller files, using this file browsing
utility for uploading and downloading is absolutely fine.
So, that's kind of the two approaches that you can, or the approaches that you can use.
On the command line, you have everything that you have on a command line.
On OOD, you are somewhat restricted with the connection to your machine by what things
can be transferred.
And, for example, on the Triton desktop, there's no copy-paste of files.
Right.
You cannot very easily move a file between the whatever laptop you're working on and Triton
from there. But you can go through the files menu here and just upload it there and it will
show up on the Triton desktop in the folder that you placed it in.
So there are also several applications that are pre-installed here.
So, Jupyter, RStudio, Paraview, you know if you want to use them.
And Speech2Text, for example, is for translating, well, spoken word into text.
So that might be very useful for you.
That's purely auto.
So yeah, so different clusters will have different ways of accessing, but many of them do have
some sort of way, this online system, something very similar to Open On Demand.
Let's see, other questions.
So the point of the rest of this session is to get connected.
And if you have questions, problems, feel free to ask.
There is also the help Zoom session.
If you are signed up, you should have received a link.
There's one question that's already mainly answered, but what if you forget to close
the desktop?
What I would like to add to the answer that's in the HackMD is,
you are essentially built for your time,
but not in the sense that you're paying money for it.
You're paying in priority, i.e.,
how fast you get resources if the resources are in high demand.
If you leave something running while it could be closed,
you might have to wait longer for resources in the future.
So there is this in jobs,
you have this active jobs.
I don't have any active jobs,
but that's one way to find what you have running.
Actually, how do I get to the view where I had all of my old jobs as well?
Well I mean there was a big red button to delete the job. I mean that will only delete it from the
list but if you see a running job there, there will be a button. I think it's a big red button
to close that job. So if you close a tab and your desktop is still running, you can always go and
close the job from there. I think you can always do it. You can also find it in here if it's still
running. And you can close it. Anything else?
Okay, it's the big picture. Okay, so our goal is, so there's lots of stuff that
can happen here, and you saw a lot of demos. For tomorrow, what do people need
know how to do. Well, the main thing is to connect to the cluster in some way. So, find a way to get
a terminal running on Triton or on your local cluster. So, either SSH into it or find a way
accessing it through a browser either on-demand or similar and open a terminal from there.
So the main thing probably would be though to use SSH to access it and there's instructions
here for different operating systems that may be slightly different, a few options for
Windows, but Windows nowadays has just SSH built in to the command line interface, so it's actually
pretty much the same as on Linux and on macOS. So yeah, at least as far as I know, the main thing is
to get access to the cluster, get a terminal running on the cluster, and it's nice if
you can check out what other features your cluster has and try them out. So if you're on Triton,
try OpenOnDemand, see what you like there and how you like to use it. Yeah. Okay. Yeah. And
you don't need this after this break, but you need it by tomorrow. So there's plenty of time to
keep figuring stuff out and to ask for support tomorrow morning and all that.
And so do keep asking stuff in the notes, and we will take a break now until the next hour, so 3 o'clock finish time or 35 minutes away from now.
You might come back a bit early, but if you can log in, go take a break and come back. Don't sit here waiting for us.
Okay.
If that's all, I'll talk to you later.
Bye.