So yeah, throughout the day we've had very interesting discussions about what computing is.
And we thought that it might be nice to have some demos showing what can be done in a computational cluster.
And these are straight out of the press, so let's see how much of a demo effect we will get.
So, to help me today, we have [name]. Do you want to introduce yourself?
Yeah, I'm a research software engineer at Aalto in [name]'s group.
been there now for three years, and still having fun.
Yeah, so it's good to hear that you're having fun.
[name], your sound might be coming from a room microphone.
Yeah, sorry.
Yeah, so what do we have for you today?
Okay, so I prepared two demos.
So these are like two demos that might interest
in like different people in our audience.
So the first demo, I will demonstrate
like how you could run this molecular dynamic simulator
called LAMMPS, which might be physicists out there
might be interested in, which uses like
Mesas passing interface on MPI for parallelization.
talk about that soonish. So, I have here a terminal. It's running on our login node. So,
these demos are very much like demos that... Yeah. Are you going to talk about the big picture of
what we're doing and what people should try to follow and not try to follow right now?
Yes. So, these are very much demos that are for our site. So, they might not work for your site.
And these demos are to show what sort of things you're capable of doing in the computing cluster.
So, you shouldn't necessarily worry about writing these up or taking notes or anything like that.
what we want you to focus on is the big picture of like, okay, you have a scientific problem,
you want to solve it in the computing cluster, so what sort of workflow you might encounter.
In this case, let's say we want to run some simulation with this LAMMPS molecular dynamics
code. First off, I would probably want to get the example. I have prepared this git clone command.
What this does is that it clones the LAMMPS repository, which contains the examples that
we want to run. On the bottom, you can see history of the commands that I'm running.
So there's like a terminal there showing what commands I'm running.
So you might encounter this kind of like a command line interface.
This is only one way of accessing the computational cluster.
But we'll be working with the command line interface quite soon.
But you can just now limit yourself to the knowledge that I'm in the computational cluster.
I'm taking out the demos.
And here I have now the lammps folder and I will go to examples and I will try this simple
like intendation example.
So in this example, we have like a 2D plane of atoms where we modify or we make an intendation
into this atom lattice by forcing a spherical indenter
into that lattice.
And first of all,
You're smashing something into it.
Yeah, we're smashing atoms, so it sounds better.
So I will first modify the input file a bit.
I'll actually use nano for them.
I will make here, I will modify one line that
make certain that we get a dump or this kind of like output
from the demo that we can then visualize later on.
So we store the atom positions every 250 time steps.
So I will modify this file.
And what we do typically in a computed cluster,
we'll talk about this in much more detail tomorrow.
But what we usually do is that we write these instructions
for the computer, what it should run on the resources,
the computational resources.
So what I would do here is I'm going
to quickly write this script.
Maybe, [name], if you want to explain shortly what I'm doing.
Essentially, when you want to submit a photo to a cluster, you need to tell it what kind of
resources you want. And that's what [name] is currently indicating. So in this case,
it's using the Slurm scheduler. And the Slurm scheduler essentially reads a bash script
and interprets these comments that are here in the beginning. Using a bash script, everything
that's starting with a hashtag is a comment and when the scheduler sees or when the submission
system sees this sbatch it knows that this is a command for the scheduler and here it's
this should be running on one node it should have should get 16 cpus the memory per cpu
should be 2 gigabytes so a total of 32 gigabytes well or 16 now yeah yeah and it should be running
for a specific time. After that time the process would essentially be killed. So in this case it's
10 minutes that this will be running at most. And below those comments, good explanation,
thank you, beyond those comments we will have instructions that we expect the code to run.
So commands that we want the code to run. So in this case we'll do this module loading. We'll
talk about this later as well, but we will basically load some pre-installed software
that is installed by the cluster people and we will preload that and then we will run it,
this lmp command, with the input that we have. Let's hope that this works.
And to quickly say, the reason why all of this software is not just available is that
you want to keep the nodes where these tools are running as clean as possible.
So if you would install lots and lots of software on all of the nodes, there would be a significant
amount of resources already taken up just by that, because not necessarily every node
has a hard drive. And if you don't have a hard drive, you need to store all of these things in
memory. And that's why these tools are installed elsewhere. So I had a mistake in the script. So
I fixed that. I had a wrong setting because I mistyped it. After fixing that, I submitted this
script to the queue. In these HPC clusters, we have a queue. We'll talk more about it later.
That will run it whenever it finds a correct place for the job to run. Currently,
you can see that actually there's an interactive session that I have open on another
So not a place open, but that job actually probably finished.
So let's see.
I just want to give one more comment here.
I'm not sure if the Slurm command as such
is available on clusters, because I
think that is a script that was created in Aalto.
So if you want to do that, or if you want to check queues,
I think we are coming to that later as well.
Yes.
There was one more mistake.
I didn't specify which MPI implementation I want to use.
But now it's run.
We can see the output.
So we see what Lammps provides is this kind of like an output,
but it also provides this dump file that, well,
is a video basically of what happened during the run.
There's a question in, yeah.
If we could introduce a bit of the background of this script.
So why do we need this script?
Why can't we just run it, like, well,
essentially on that command line as it is?
Yes, that's an excellent question.
So the question comes back to what
we were talking earlier today about computing resources,
because we are sharing resources.
We are not running this on, we could run this
on our own laptop, but in this case,
want to run it, like, this is of course like a bit of a toy example, but if we
would be running like an actual simulation, we would be, it would require
a lot more resources and we, because we're sharing the resources, there needs
to be a way of sharing these resources.
And we'll talk about this tomorrow a lot more, how the sharing happens
and how the queue system works.
But basically there's like a queue system that organizes how the different jobs
run. And I want to add to that. So normally, or in almost all clusters I've seen up until
now, if you connect to the cluster, you are actually on the login node. So if you would
run the login, the login node is kind of the access point for everyone to that cluster.
So if you start running code on this directly on that node, you would run it on one machine
that is shared by everyone.
And very often, these machines have restrictions
how much resources someone can actually use on them.
And very often, they also have kind of automated script
that kill or stops stop code that
is taking too much resources.
So running things on the login node is not a good idea,
or it shouldn't be done.
So that's why we need to write this script,
because the script has the information on how
for the scheduler that [name] mentioned
on how to put it to the actual cluster.
And the cluster is not the same here.
Maybe.
Yeah, I would quickly mention that you can think about it
more if you look at the script again,
like we asked for eight CPUs
currently, let's say my laptop, I'm watching the stream currently. I'm having a Zoom open. I have
some browsers open and anything. If I would run these on my own laptop, my laptop would basically
overheat. It's currently running at about 70 degrees anyway, so it would basically be game
over for that if I would try to run this simulation at the same time while I'm running other stuff.
So that's why I want to run it in the cluster.
So let's think in a more traditional high performance
computing situation, where if you are a physicist and you
would want to run this code, but you want to run it in a
production size, it might be thousands of times bigger.
So then you might need tens of nodes, hundreds of CPUs to
actually run a big simulation.
So in those cases, yeah, laptop isn't any more an option to do.
But we'll talk about the parallelization later on.
But this is like, OK, if we return back to the example,
OK, this is all fine and nice that I managed to run it.
But OK, if I want to now see what the result was,
like these command line interfaces, it might be good for programming what I want the computer to
do, what I want the queue to do, and what I want to run. But if I want to visualize it, this might
not be the best option. So for that, at least here in Aalto, in other sites there might be
different ones. We have this open on demand, so CSC at least has this kind of a service,
where you can launch like a temporary virtual desktop. You might have other, like in Aalto
there's also the VDI service, but this runs in a cluster that basically provides you a desktop
in a browser. So you can visualize the results that you have. So let's try that out. So
over here, I will launch one desktop with one CPU and eight gigabytes of memory. It should take
take up like a few seconds to launch.
While we're waiting for that,
I want to briefly mention that essentially
the layout of the cluster is such that
the resources are somewhat shared.
The login node, for example, has essentially,
it shares the file system with the compute node.
So anything that you create on the login node,
the compute nodes can see, that's how essentially the data
transfer, it's not really data transfer, it's stored at the
same place. It's just a network file system.
Yes. And over here, you can notice that I'm now like the
terminal that I'm starting here is starting on some pe21. So
it's a computing node. So it's one of the like computers that
we have in the system. And over there, I can start Ovito, which
this kind of like open visualization tool that is often used to simulate various simulations.
So like this molecular dynamic simulations. So over here I will browse to the folder
folder that the simulation was done in, so it was the indent simulation.
And I will visualize the dump file over here.
So you can notice that here we have the visualization.
So it's basically like this kind of like a lattice, 2D lattice of some atoms that don't
move and some atoms that do move and when we play the simulation we can see that we can see the
indentation starting to happen when the push comes to solve and the lattice will move
from the spherical indenter. So this would happen like, I don't know, like you push something into
a metal and that would happen. So this kind of a visualization, so this is just to demonstrate
like a workflow that you might have in a computing cluster. So you do something in the command line
or from some other interface where you submit your job into the queue and it runs on some machine
and once it has run you maybe use open on demand or some other way to visualize the results or
to check the results and what is the result that you want to have.
So this is the kind of like a workflow that you might have in the cluster.
So yeah, so in the simulation, there's a question in the chat.
So they say you cannot see the indenter.
It's basically like some material
with infinite density that pushes to the infinite force
pushes like so that nothing cannot go over here.
So it's some indenter that basically pushes the material
on that side.
OK, but this is like an example of,
like let's say this kind of like a traditional physics
simulation that you might do in a cluster.
We'll talk about how do you do it in more
detail in the coming days.
Another example, I hope we are not running out of time
or going too much over time.
But another example I want to give is for the deep learning people or for the
language processing people. In many cases, you might have a situation that
you want to utilize, let's say, the large language models that are
are like nowadays available everywhere basically.
So you would want to do some,
you want to run some queries to a large language model.
So in this example, what I will use is like
this already written example that we have done,
this large language model example.
And what the example does is that it uses this Lama2 large language model to batch
process multiple queries to a large language model.
So when people are doing query, like many people are using ChatGPT and programs
like that for that, but they are closed models.
So you cannot really know what happens behind the scenes.
And you will just have to send a request to OpenAI and they will give you a response of what was the prompt that you queried.
But if you're doing research into large language models or if you want to use open source alternatives for that, you might need to run it yourself.
But those models are very heavy on the GPU requirements.
like they are big models usually.
So you'd need a system that has those kinds
of resources to do it.
And in our cluster, we have GPUs that are capable
of running some of these large language models.
So in this example, let's go to the batch inference folder.
And what we have here, we have this kind
submission script that is a bit more complicated. But what we have here is that we request
quite a bit of memory, we request a certain number of CPUs, we request a GPU,
and then we use like here in Aalto we have already downloaded certain deep learning models
or pre-existing models. You could download them yourself from, let's say, HuggingFace or somewhere.
But we have already some downloaded models existing. And over here we will use an environment
that I have already pre-created to run this kind of like an inference script.
And this inference script is like a Python script that loads the models and it will
it will take some prompts that we have
and it will run it through the model.
So let's just run this.
So this is the kind of like, yeah.
You have this Python unbuffered in there.
Yes.
Why?
Well, that is so that if we want to look
at the output over here,
it will show it to us immediately.
That's normally not required,
but that is just so that we can quickly see the output.
If we would run this in a production environment,
that wouldn't be necessary because we would be more
interested in getting a lot of questions done.
But over here, for the sake of the demo,
we want to get output as soon as possible,
so that we can see what's happening there.
So now it's running on a GPU node.
Our model is being loaded and the model is being initialized
and it takes a minute to do that.
I would also say that this Python buffer too
is pretty important if you need to debug.
Yes.
Because if you have some statements,
some print statements in and don't have that,
or tail the print statements to directly write out,
you can easily end up with code that you think is running,
or think is not running anymore, but actually ran.
Yeah. So the model run,
it produced the output,
but the output is pretty hard to read from this.
so it also produced the output into like a response file so in order to visualize a bit
better I'm loading this JSON formatter called jq and running this command to open it up in
the editor so we can see what sort of responses it gave. So for example what is the history of
of the Eiffel Tower and then it describes in lots of detail
the history of the Eiffel Tower.
And these kinds of like batch processing is very important
when in our case, we had,
I'm not certain how many prompts we have here,
maybe a hundred, maybe a few hundred,
but like if we want to test out these AI models
with thousands and thousands of different prompts,
It could get pretty expensive if you want to use, let's say, OpenAI's models.
Or maybe you want to test out how different models behave, what sort of output they produce.
Or maybe you want to try different things.
For these, it might be a lot cheaper and a lot easier to do this kind of batch processing in the compute cluster compared to, let's say, using an already existing ChatGPT.
But those are also good ways of doing a research, of course.
This is only one way of doing research.
But if you need to process a huge bunch of these queries, yes, this is one way of doing that.
So but these kind of stuff you will be able or hopefully you will be able to do
after this course or you will know how you should get started on working these kinds of examples.
But we like there are many questions already in the in the chat about like many of the concepts
we introduced here. And don't worry, like we'll go through the concepts in like better detail
or in more detail like during the next upcoming two days. We won't like go through them in this
one half an hour session and expect that you would need to like learn everything from this.
This was just a demo. This is just the preview to know what kind of things you might learn.
And really to show the point that what we're learning
the next few days, we're not doing something ourselves,
but we're telling a computer how to do it.
And thus we can tell the computer to do it 10 times
or a hundred times for us automatically.
Okay.
With that being said, it's a break time.
So after the break, we begin,
we do a practice connecting to the cluster.
Let's see you then.
Bye.