and give a motivational talk with [name]. [name], are you here?
I'll jump out.
Thank you, [name]. You will hear [name] a lot in the next.
[name], do you want to say something briefly about yourself?
Yeah. Hi, everyone. I work as an application specialist at CSC, IT Center for Science.
You will hear about that also, I think, last day of this workshop more. I work there in
user support, outreach, and training. And I'm also community manager of the Code Refinery
Project, which we will be talking about now a little bit. And I also do still my PhD on
very low part-time at Aalto University about satellite remote sensing stuff.
Excellent. So what we wanted to cover in the next 25 minutes, and then we can have a break
for 10 minutes to stretch our legs, is to mention the importance of reproducibility
and open science. I don't know how many of you are familiar with the concept of reproducibility,
but most likely I know that many of the people watching are starting their summer internship
or starting their doctoral research career, you want, you know, to be reproducible. You want to
start from the first day to make sure that what you've been doing today, what you've been working
on today, you can replicate it in one month. So the materials that are linked now from this,
from the schedule of the day, are from the so-called Code Refinery workshop. And as [name]
has mentioned, Code Refinery is a larger workshop that covers various aspects of the so-called
computational reproducibility.
So in this short 25 minutes, the workshop
is actually lasting for six days, three hours every day,
three hours and a half.
Here in this short slot, we just want
to inspire you, give you a bit of a motivation of why
reproducibility is important, and then
how does it fit into the picture of the Code Refinery
Workshop.
For those who will be interested in the next Code Refinery
workshop it is now planned in the first half of September so if you register for this course and
you mark that you want to stay up to date you will receive further emails when the registrations are
open. But in general when it comes to reproducibility the situation is like this so
this is a professor with some research assistant or actually this is a doctoral researcher
and the professors say don't worry you don't have to start from you have to start your code
from scratch which is you know it's great you got some code from the previous postdoc or whoever
you can reuse the software that the previous person on the project wrote several years ago
are there instructions for how to use it i doubt it is the code commented not likely where are
the files who knows this is going to be painful isn't it it's just a scratch so i don't know
about you, [name], but I've seen this situation. I don't know, I still see it on a, maybe not daily
basis, but weekly basis, which is, I mean, yeah, it's also understandable. People join the research
project, whether they are for an internship, whether they are for those years of the doctoral
research, and then they move on, they change university. And then if there's not a culture
of preserving, archiving and making things reproducible and documented, this process will
keep on staying. So we don't need now to go through the whole page but in general what you can think
when you read a scientific article that the article is actually just the tip of the whole
process of getting the data, collecting the data, analyzing the data, producing the statistical
article results, summaries, tables, outputs, whatever. And so the article, sometimes with
the article itself, it's impossible to replicate what other people are doing. So you need the
documentation on the process, on the software, you need maybe actually access to the actual
code or to the actual data. And sometimes even if you have the same code and the same
data, you still get different numbers. And this is because maybe the environment, the
libraries, the operating system, and other things
have changed in the meantime.
So all these parameters, all the elements you see here
would actually be needed for achieving the reproducibility.
So in these materials that you see linked there,
you can browse them like this.
We cover various aspects of the so-called, you know,
pyramid that you just show,
but it's nice to put it all in the context
of the Code Refinery workshop.
So, [name], maybe it would be better than me to give an overview of this picture.
One, two, three, four, five, six steps.
Do you want to briefly?
Yes, I can do that. And here, maybe also just in addition to what [name] already mentioned.
So we have these workshops twice a year, but we also have these lesson materials that [name] is showing right now.
And there is a link to this in the collaborative notes as well.
So you can also go through the materials yourself,
see what interests you, and maybe learn
something new related to this.
So we have really liked this little figure here
by Heidi Seibold, who made it about the six helpful steps
for reproducible research.
So it all starts already from the very beginning
when you start your research journey.
And you start having files.
you start creating folders.
And there, it already is very useful to take a step back
and think about your naming and how you order things.
And there is multiple guides out there
who can give you a structure that you can follow
that's always very useful to do.
And that's something that this reproducible research lesson
that we're showing here is also about.
so we talk a little bit about different naming conventions
that you can follow,
different structures that you can follow, and so on.
So in our workshop, that's day four, like it's noted here,
but it's the first day of where it goes actually deep
into the different tools and techniques
that you can use for your research.
Yeah, then this is also already step two,
use good names for them, also for functions.
you write your own code, you can save a lot of documentation and commenting things if you just
have good names for your things. And that is also mentioned in our documentation lesson,
how to document your research software, and in the modular code development lessons that we have.
Then, I mentioned already documentation is a very important step because you might be working
on different projects, so if you have been doing something and you had a really good reason for
setting something up in a certain way, you might not remember that when you get back to it like
two days later, a week later, a year later. And then also when others take a look at your codes
or your software as a whole, it helps you to kind of keep your time free because not everyone has
to come and run to you and ask you about like, oh how do I actually use this or why is it done
that way. That's stupid. So you can do that by documenting your codes from the beginning.
And there's different levels of doing that. And that's what we also talk about in this
documentation lesson. And then the first week of the Code Refinery Workshop is all about version
control. Why you would want to use it, what it is, what it actually is, how to use it for yourself,
how to use it when you are collaborating with others and to understand a bit on what's behind
different commands that you might have already used, like commands like git clone, for example,
git push, git commit, these things. Hopefully you have heard about this before, but if not,
then the first week of the Code Refinery Workshop introduces this on a very, how do you say,
shallow learning curve, so you start with what you might already know and then you go deeper and deeper step by step into that you can in the end work together with others using version control.
Then, step five here, stabilizing the computing environment and the software, that basically
many of our lessons have in some way.
We talk about Jupyter notebooks for doing that.
That's a nice way of collaborating with others, but also to prototyping for yourself.
In the reproducible research lesson, we talk about this with, what is it called, now I waste
the word, but containers we talk about. We talk about workflows there, like how you can run
multiple steps of your analysis pipeline, for example, automatically without having to worry
too much about is it run in the right order? Is it run on all my files and so on? And then also
about like, I still don't remember the word, but these computing environments that you can create
with virtual environment, with Conda for example, you might have heard about these things before
and what's behind that, why do you want to use them and how can you use them to make your research
more reproducible. And then also a little bit about publishing your research outputs. So you will
have maybe in the end of your research project you will have code, you will have data, you will have
other documents. And those are, I don't want to say useless, but less useful for others when they
are just lying on your own computer. And there is a few things that you have to think about then,
like what kind of license do I want to add to my code? Do I want others to easily reuse it,
or do I maybe not want others to reuse it? And does my university have guidelines on this?
and these are the things that we are talking in this social coding and open software lesson.
I believe that in my opinion these six steps are extremely useful because truly if I start a new
project I'm really starting with the folders, with the files and as [name] has already mentioned
all of these six steps that you see here from the you know day zero setting up the folder and
gathering the code that you already have already some documentation some readme so-called file
already all these materials are available I can give you a demo or help you kind of browsing
these materials so the materials that are linked from the web page from today is this reproducible
research and so there for example there is the section that is about organizing your project
and here now I will not go through the teaching part but you see this is a kind of a standard
folder structure that you can create for a new project there are you can create this manually
or you can even there are how can I say automated way to create this type of folder structures we
discussed this here they are linked here but the goal actually what is important when it comes to
reproducibility is that often you're not working alone.
You maybe are working with other people,
with other colleagues,
so most likely you want to have a share place,
a share project name with share convention.
So it's very important that you actually talk
with your peers.
If you don't yet already have a standardized way
of storing the data, storing the process data,
the results, the code, and so on,
it's now a good moment to start the discussion.
And for example, use these pages for getting inspirations
and already starting from the very beginning
with reproducibility in mind.
Another aspect that [name] touched
was about the so-called computational steps.
So of course, version control for those who are using Git.
By the way, we have added in our shared notes document
a little question to know if you're already familiar
with Git version control or not.
But in general, we need to also record the computational steps
because it's very rare that you just
have one single script that will just load the data,
do some math, and save the outputs.
Most likely, there's many steps to do.
And again, this type of steps, there's
no other way to document them except having
humans writing what the actual steps are there.
So in this other part of the reproducibility lesson,
you can see some ways of how to record steps.
There's the so-called scripts,
where you could basically write the plot
of all the code that you need to run.
But in general, even have a simple so-called readme file.
So a txt file that is living there close to the code
that will just tell to the future user
in one year or in five years,
first you need to run the function
or the Python script name like this.
And second, you will need to run another one and so on.
Here in this lesson, there are also some advanced things.
This is the beauty of the code refinery materials
that they are written as accessible as possible.
So there's no prerequisite,
but also the more experienced user can learn something new.
So for example, there are workflow tools
and SnakeMake is one of them.
If you know what's Make,
SnakeMake is kind of uses the same principle,
but instead of building code like you would do with Make,
building software, you would actually use it
for basically writing a so-called acyclic pipeline
to basically go from the input data
to the actual derivatives file that you need.
In the same lesson that we're browsing here quickly,
then we go to the level of dependencies.
And this is, again, another XKCD to inspire people.
But this is truly what it is in all
modern digital infrastructure.
This is not just about research.
This is about all the services that you use,
that sometimes, if not always,
they are based on components like this little block there.
There is a project by some random person in Nebraska
that has been thanklessly maintained since 2003.
There are many, many example of this type of process.
There's the Curl, for example,
which is one of the most used protocol
tool to transfer data between systems, and it used to be for many years just a random person
somewhere, I think in Sweden, that was maintaining it. Now it's better maintained.
But in general, this is the thing, that even though you are good at documenting your code
and your data, and so that hopefully in five years or even yourself in one year after peer review
to be able to rerun things, you then realize that in the meantime the Python library that you were
using has changed, that Python 3.something had a problem and now you need to upgrade to the new
Python and nothing works anymore. So sometimes you really need to preserve not just the code
and the documentation and the data, but also all the dependencies, all the libraries that are
attached. Again here, this is just a quick intro, 10 minutes, they were working together, but if
And if you're starting a new project, it's very much important to invest in fixing the
versions of the tools that you want to use and basically agreeing on what type of libraries
you will use and defining these type of dependencies and so on.
So in this lesson, for those who are familiar with the so-called CONDA, it's one way of
taking care of Python environments where you can define all the type of dependencies that
your code has.
So if you are starting today a new project, it's good to have a discussion again with
your colleagues and agree, for example, on what type of libraries do you want to use
and what type of dependencies your project should have.
So this is at the level of the dependencies of the software.
Sometimes, in some cases, you really
need to go to the highest level that you
need to have also that the environment
that the whole operating system is reproducible.
We recently moved from an old operating system
to a new operating system with our Triton cluster.
And sometimes, most of the software
were working in the new operating system,
but there were some specific cases
that were dependent on the old operating system.
So one way to get over this type of dependency
that is related to the actual system is to adopt containers.
So with containers, they're basically,
it's like not only having the libraries that you need
and the code that you need, but it's really
having the full image of the operating system
where everything runs on top.
If you remember at the beginning,
I was talking about the operating system
and all these other layers up to the user.
So with the container, it's really this joke
that it works on my machine.
Well, then we'll ship your machine.
And this is our Docker, which is one of these container
technologies.
Again here, we don't have the time
to cover to the containers.
But you know that if you have this type of problem,
or if you ever had this type of need
that you would like to move the full pipeline from one system,
from one cluster to another, then
it's good to invest in learning containers.
Here, these are simple learning materials
that you can read by yourself and test things by yourself.
But in general, we also have more advanced courses
for those cases.
And this kind of covers everything from this reproducibility lesson
and this reproducibility summary. We still have five minutes.
I don't know if [name] is still here with me.
But in general, the Code Refinery workshop doesn't only cover,
even though the reproducibility is at the code of the Code Refinery workshop.
Code Refinery is like a large also informal network.
Let me type the address, a large informal network of basically people who are passionate
on data science, software, open science, good practices, they join together and they discuss
together.
I don't know if [name], if we still have five minutes, do you want to mention the type
of engagement that people could have with the Code Refinery, especially we are looking
for ambassadors?
Do you want to tell something? I can also open some of these other links if you want me to.
So yes, maybe the first entry point into CodeRefinery is to visit one of our workshops.
So our next workshop is coming up, like [name] already mentioned there, and it's written there September 10th to 12th and 17th to 19th.
It's always half a day, and we'll talk about all the topics that I mentioned in this reproducible research steps.
And then, if you get excited about this, or if you maybe are already excited about these topics that we have been talking about here now,
So then we're already always looking for contributors to the lesson material, for example, or also
just people in different places that will advertise the workshop to their network.
Because that's one of the hardest things that we have to do is to actually get this message
that these workshops exist to the people that have use of it.
We very often get the feedback, oh, I wish I would have known this in the beginning of
my PhD or something like this.
You can help with that. If this is something that interests you, the best way is to sign up for our
newsletter, then you will get a message when actually the registration opens for our workshop,
and then you can send that forward to your network. If you like doing that kind of stuff,
like spreading the word about CodeRefinery, maybe you go to conferences and you have talks about,
I don't know, your own topic. If you just want to add one little slide about Code Refinery,
just making your network aware that it exists, then becoming an ambassador is a nice way of
supporting us and we also want to support you doing that. So if you go in the top about join
and for individuals.
So there are all the different ways that you can engage with the community are mentioned here and
and if you scroll a little bit down there is this CodeRefinery Ambassador.
So if you want to become one then let us know and that can work either via
our contact email address which you can also find on that page
or by joining our Zulip chat or you can also
let us know via the collaborative document of this course for example.
We will read that and then we will reach out to you and we will have
meetups of the ambassadors and try to support you in any way we can. We also have stickers
that you can distribute that always gets people interested in things. And yeah, we're very happy to
connect with you. But yeah, also just joining as a learner. Joining in Aalto, for example,
we will have an in-person room where you can follow the workshop all together with [name]
and you will have [name] there answering all your questions that you might have regarding the material.
So it's a really nice and community experience to join the workshop in Otoniemi.
For those who are, well hopefully some of you who are listening actually were in some of the recent workshops, for example the March workshop,
but we are all very open with our lessons and also documentation from the workshops,
So let's say that you don't want to wait for September the 10th
and you already want to start learning,
you can click on the March workshop.
And there you see the schedule.
And for each part of the schedule,
let's say day one, Introduction to Version Control,
there are links to the lesson material.
There are links to the videos, to the recordings.
So truly, if one wanted, you could actually have,
you could actually do the full workshop by yourself
with just using the videos, the recordings,
the archive materials, the archive questions,
and all the lesson materials that are there.
But of course, yeah, it's more fun to do it together,
to do it with a colleague.
Here at Aalto, we're trying to promote
this type of hybrid room so that people can come here
and have some cookies, fruits,
and at the same time, watch the stream.
The stream still happens on Twitch TV,
so being in person is not necessary,
especially because CodeRefinery is a Nordic network,
So we have people streaming from Norway, from Denmark,
from Sweden and so on.
But then the social part is also important,
especially during the exercise is what that can be
some interesting questions or things like that.
But anyway, hopefully this was motivational enough.
Thank you so much [name] for joining us
for this overview, very quick overview
of the whole Code Refinery.
Thanks for having me.
Yes, and we are perfectly on time, it's 12.50.
So let's quickly check if there's anything in the notes
that should be mentioned.
But eventually, we can get to the notes later.
Maybe let's have the break now until 1 o'clock sharp.
And please stretch your legs, have a glass of water,
and see you.
The stream will start again at 1 PM Finnish time
and at the hour in other time zones.
Thank you.