but let's not go that far. Yeah. Okay. So monitoring. Sorry for this short distraction.
So we've already did a little bit about monitoring, but what are the main
things we might want to watch and what does it mean?
Yeah, so for the monitoring, we already talked about how can you watch the queue,
how can you monitor, and that's like monitoring basically in a workflow type of monitoring.
You monitor that is your work running and that sort of stuff. You're monitoring your workflow
and is it going through correctly. And that's, of course, the important part that
But did you manage to get your code running and is it running on there?
But then there's the question of, okay, is it running like I expected?
And is it using the resources like I expected?
And for the first part, is it running as I expect it to run?
The best way of monitoring is in your code to have monitoring output.
Basically, in your code, when there is a specific step that it's doing, it's a good idea that
your code prints those outputs.
It's a good idea that your code tells that, hey, I'm doing this part.
Maybe some timing information as well, like, okay, I'm here, time is this, I'm running
this.
Maybe at the start of your code, you might want to have output that, okay, I'm running
at this machine, I'm running here, that the code itself will tell you what it thinks it's doing.
That way, it will make it a lot easier. If you run into a problem, your code crashes or it does
something that you don't expect it to do, it's much easier to pinpoint at what part of the code
the problem occurred, especially if you're running it non-interactively. If you're running it
interactively, and let's say in Jupyter, you're running it cell by cell, it's very easy to see,
okay, the cell crashed, like it didn't run, or it crashes when I try to run this cell
in the Jupyter. But if you're not running it interactively, you want more output.
And usually you want to have the program, got to use some debugging output for yourself.
And that is something that is left for basically, we cannot do much for it. It's up to the programmers
or the people who run the code to do that. So that's the first thing to remember. It's good
to add, especially at key points of your code, what is your code doing? And the second thing
about, okay, did it actually use the resources? That's a different question. And that
that the queue system can answer, like did it actually use what it was needed.
And there are a few tools that you can use.
So first one that we already have touched on is the slurm history.
So if I look at the slurm history command, I'll make this a bit bigger.
So the font will go smaller, and it will overwrite.
So Slurm history, or with s-act, you
can get the similar kind of information.
So from this output, we can also limit to, let's say, 15 min.
I think you can, yes.
Yeah, okay, so we can tell it for jobs in the last 15 minutes, this is what's run and
all the stuff.
Yeah, so this is pretty standard, I guess.
Yeah, so from this output you can see stuff like, okay, what was the starting time of
the job, how much memory you requested, what was the actual memory usage of the job, how
much CPU time it used.
So the CPU time is basically the time it took, like how much CPU calculation seconds it used
basically, like how much actual CPU calculation it used.
And the wall time is like the real clock time.
So the CPU time, like let's say you ask for four CPUs, you would expect the CPU time to
be four times the real time.
It might sound a bit confusing here, but basically because you're using four CPUs for the same
time you're using.
So you can think about it like man hours, like we sometimes calculate stuff in man hours.
So, how many man, like if you're working for, yeah, four hours.
Yeah.
So, if something takes 10 man hours, it takes one man 10 hours or two men, five hours.
Like, because it's like a, so the CPU time is basically how many like CPU hours you used.
And you can use this as the starting point.
tool provided by Slurm is this seff. I'll make this a bit bigger now. So, if you run seff and a comma,
like one of your job IDs, you can get this sort of an output, which tells, okay, how much CPU was
utilized and what was the efficiency. So, in the case of these example codes, it's pretty bad
because they don't basically do anything and the measurements might be incorrect because they're
short. But basically, it will tell how much CPU was used and the same with the memory. So,
what is the memory utilization? So, what we talked earlier about how to decide which resources to
use, well, a good starting point might be to request as much resource as your own computer has
and then after you have run it once, then check what was actually utilized and then lower the
resources. It's good to have a bit of overhead, especially in the memory department, but not too
much. So like maybe a few gigabytes overhead or something like that. There's a really good
question. How reliable is the seff in history utilized resource estimate?
That's a great question, because the memory utilization is only measured every...
It depends on the cluster.
Yeah, every 20 seconds or something. But also, it depends how the measurement is recorded. So,
So all measurement is recorded using these so-called control groups, which is a technical
thing, but basically it should record it quite accurately, at least the maximum number, but
the averages...
Did we switch to control groups now?
Yeah.
Okay.
At least the maximum requirement, maximum memory requirement should be pretty accurate,
But the others, because they're calculated from averages, they might be all like, yeah,
it's their averages.
So they might not be ... You might have a code that, let's say it requests a huge amount
of memory when it loads a dataset or something, and then it does nothing with that afterwards.
So you might have a situation where you have a big spike in your memory usage, and these
averages don't necessarily capture that.
that you need to do a bit more like profiling of the code to capture that sort of behavior.
Yeah. Yeah. And monitoring is really a big deal, like getting good accurate measurements of the
resources your jobs use is really necessary to get any good performance out. And there's far
more things that we can do that we can talk about now. But anyway, I propose we go to an exercise
time. So yeah, we can take the break by 10.50 or a bit after.
Yeah. So in the exercises we have for you, we have a few
exercises, like first, like some verbosity exercises, and then
testing out, like checking the how that's how do the seff and
and their SLURM history, what do they look like when you actually run something?
So of course, these are pretty much a toy problem, but you can try them out and see
what the seff looks like.
Because for an actual program, they will look pretty much the same, the utilization and
those sort of numbers.
yeah okay uh i've written this in the notes now um so yeah give it a try i wrote down we can come
back at 50. So, good luck and see you soon. Bye.
Welcome back.
So, um, yeah.
I don't know how many people were trying to exercises because there wasn't much comment there but there's definitely some questions about this.
Um, did we already talked about how reliable the estimates were right.
Yes, yes.
Should we do some examples?
Yeah, let's do some.
How to execute the command run-pi.sh file.
Where did that come from?
from I think the ssh file, I don't know, like this.
Maybe it means sh.
Yeah, maybe it means sh.
We would need a bit more WebAssembly probably,
or WebAssembly example.
Okay. Well, let's do some examples. So, what should we look at? Monitoring WAND?
Yeah. So, these examples might seem a bit like, okay, they might be simple or self-evident
whatever. But I would say that they are only simple and self-evident because the program
is simple and self-evident. If you think about if we would be running some really complex program,
it would be very much harder to decipher what's happening there. For the simple program,
it's of course easy to see, but for a more complex program, this is by no means self-evident.
I think it's important to keep in mind that even though these might look simple,
you can plug whatever there and it would be immediately much more complex if the script
would be much more complex. So, in the serial example, if we, for example, look at the run
-pi.sh. So, let's, we can add here, there was already this hello user, but let's add here
some echo that says starting analysis now.
Very simple. Let's put maybe the date there as well.
Okay, yeah.
And question mark in parentheses means it runs the date command.
So you can also write it like this if you want to utilize the automatic highlighting
a bit better.
Or automatic.
So it shows that this is a command.
So let's submit this.
So let's say we would have a problem in the, oh, I may still have the error there, yeah.
And let's look at the output, yeah.
So we would have here the timestamp.
This might be really helpful if your program has tens of steps, multiple steps, having something
like that might be really good. Let's try this set-x as well. This is very good for debugging.
If we open the run-pi and we put here set-x, what that does is that it
It tells the bash interpreter to print all of the commands that we are going to be running.
So if you have, especially if you have like any sort of like if sentence or something
like that, like conditional logic, it might be good to have this because then you can
see what the script is actually like executing.
it will produce this kind of an output where we will see first the command that is being run
and then the output. You can see that before it could run the echo, the script needed to run the
date. It has these double pluses over here. It first needed to get the date before it could
to create this echo.
So that's why we have this double plus over here.
So you can use that to produce extra monitoring.
Let's maybe check the seff example.
Should we do straight up?
Like we can all, like tomorrow we'll talk about
how to do multiprocessing.
Maybe we can do this example as this kind of like a teaser on how do we utilize
or can utilize multiple processors. Let's add cpus per task to Python.
How many zeros are there?
Well, I don't want to count.
Let's just copy-paste.
OK.
So error.
Oh, Python 3?
There's no, yeah, Python 3.
A bit of a mistake.
OK.
That should be fixed.
Yeah.
So now it's using two processors to do the calculation.
So we'll talk about parallelism tomorrow.
So then we'll have a lot more stuff on that.
But for now, let's just marvel at the ease
of use of multiple processors in this example.
OK, yeah.
So let's see how long it takes.
I would expect that the default would be set, but it's, yeah.
OK, so it's done.
And if we do storm history, now we
should see something interesting.
Yeah.
I'll make this a bit.
So the CPU time and wall time is what we want, right?
Yes.
I'll put here the 15 min as well.
OK, that's still too long.
Let's hit 5 min.
Yeah.
One minute?
Well, let's, yeah.
Yeah, now it's good.
OK, there we go.
Oh, okay. Here we see the code. So this is the job that we submitted. And we see that the CPU
time, total CPU time was one minute and 14 seconds. And the wall time was 38 seconds.
So now you can like, there was a question in the notes that like some site doesn't have
seff installed. You can get it from GitHub. It's available there. And I think it's part of some
Slurm installations as well. But what the seff basically does is that calculates
this number multiplied by the number of CPUs. So that would be 38 seconds times two. So
So what's it like, 78 seconds, sorry, 76 seconds.
So and what we utilized was one minute, 14 seconds.
So that's like 74 seconds.
So 74 seconds over 76 seconds, we would expect the CPU efficiency to be, well, close to what's
it like close to a hundred percent.
So let's use seff to do this calculation so that we don't have to do it manually.
So yeah, it's 97% utilization.
But that's basically the kind of calculation it does.
So it takes the wall time, the total time that the job took.
It checks how much resources were actually requested, how many CPUs were requested.
will calculate the total amount of time used and then it checks how much CPU time was actually
utilized. We can see here that the memory utilization is pretty horrendous. This is not
nice. It's way overkill. At one gigabyte, it doesn't really matter. It's still quite small,
the memory requirement. But the CPU efficiency was pretty good. But these kind of like, okay,
you have an assumption how your program behaves. How do you see it in the numbers? This is a quite
complex task, actually. And something that you only get familiar the more you do the thing.
but basically it's easier to check usually if numbers are like, if the percentages
are closer to 100% then it's easier to check like that. Yeah. Okay, so it's time for a break.
So we'll be out for 10 minutes and then we'll come back and we'll have some, well basically,
lightning talks on several other things which we summarize but you need to read yourself.
And then there's a very long Q&A session and you can really ask us anything.
So prepare all your questions, bring your friends, whatever, and try to challenge us.
Yeah, and during the Q&A session, remember, already you can pepper whatever questions you have,
what sort of questions you have, you can already have them in your mind.
So, yeah, but let's have a break.
Yeah. Okay. 10 minutes.
See you later.
Bye.