Yes. So before we start looking at the lessons,
let's check this copy of code to the cluster section.
We will do one thing here.
So the upcoming examples,
we'll use these HPC examples repository that we have created.
So, if you want to follow along with the examples, you should clone this repository as well.
So, we'll talk about when there's time to, like, when do you want to write yourself and
when do we, when there's type along and when there's not.
But if you want to do the same commands that we do, just be mindful that you need to get
this repository.
I will do this in my terminal that I have enabled here and now I have the repository.
So I'm now in the folder of the repository.
I just made a quick poll to see how many people have gone through the cluster shell tutorial
here.
Yeah.
So, but that's quite simple.
a few commands to do if you want to follow that. But let's go to start with the interactive jobs.