Hello, we are back.
Hello.
Yeah.
So, during the break, we were thinking that, like, hopefully everything appears simple
for you.
Like, we were thinking that, like, is this simple or is it not?
Is this complicated?
Or is it not?
We don't know.
So at the end, remember to put the feedback on so that we know
that was everything clear.
And do remember to put stuff in the notes
as well so that we know what's happening.
So [name], what do we have for us
at this last lightning round of talks?
So there's, as you see from the schedule, there's four things you want to cover.
Application, software modules, data storage, remote access to data.
Each of these is itself not a very long page, but a bit involved.
But behind the scenes, there is so much going on there.
So our goal is to give you the summary of why it's important,
but you can read it and ask questions on your own time.
And that's better than what we've done before when we spent hours on all of these and everyone just
gets bored. Yeah, we'll try to like basically provide you with the cliff notes of what is
yeah what you should be like basically public service announcement or this kind of like
At this point, probably everybody's a bit already like there's so much happening already in the
course. So we try to keep it as simple as possible. So let's talk about applications.
What are applications, [name]? I mean, I guess whenever anyone wants to run something on the
cluster, you want to run some software. And it might be something that you've created completely
by yourself, but often it's something that is automatically installed. And for this,
what does it mean? So yeah, you log in and you want some software, like you want Python,
which appears to be here, or you might want R, or you might want MATLAB, or any number of more
specialized things. So if you go to the random page of some random application and ask,
how do I install it? That will probably not work on the cluster itself
because you don't have admin access there. But there are other things you can do.
So, first of all, I would say, like [name] said, the system is shared, so you cannot
get the admin access there.
But of course, in many cases, the cluster administrators try to install something that
will benefit the whole community.
So there already exists usually software
that has been installed.
We'll talk about how these pre-installed software,
we use this module system to load these,
how these can be loaded.
But yeah, this is one option.
Yeah.
Can you ever install things by yourself?
Yeah, I would say like most of the time, yes.
But for many programs, especially on Linux that the computers, like these cluster computers
usually run, you either need to compile it or you need to get it pre-compiled somewhere
else.
Like somebody already has done the dirty work for you.
If you take it from somewhere else, there are various things you can use. We use Conda nowadays
a lot to provide various kinds of softwares. You can use these Apptainer or Singularity containers
to install libraries. If your code doesn't require to compile its own libraries, it's
like interpreted code, like Matlab code or R code or Python code. In many cases, you can use
which is like the already existing software modules that we provide.
Yeah.
So when someone comes and needs to use something,
I guess this page will give the general summary.
But first you look and see, is it already there?
And then you would decide,
do you ask us or do you try to install yourself?
and it depends on how good you are at adapting installation instructions.
There's also this thing called containers.
Yeah, I already mentioned it in passing.
So there are these containers, this Apptainer or Singularity containers
that can make you so that you can run.
So if you're familiar with Docker containers, they're a bit similar but a bit different.
If you're interested, we were having this workflows course for high-performance computing
and I gave a tutorial on these there.
The recording should be in the Code Refinery YouTube page and the course page is linked
in that course as well.
We can link it into the chat as well.
those can be used to install basically if your program only runs on Ubuntu let's say
you can install it in a container and run that container in the cluster yeah
okay um should we go on so the next up is modules and
so module is one of the things that allows you to
load software. So you'll often see in order to use Python or R or whatever run the command
module load something. So for example we could like let's say we have some MATLAB users already
commented there in the in the notes. So if you want to use MATLAB we have MATLAB
installations usually. Most of the computing clusters, we all use this lmod module system.
In these, there's this command called module spider that you can use to check what versions are
installed. For example, MATLAB. You can write the search with the usual terms, for example,
module spider R or something. And there's like a R version there. And let's say if we want to use
that, we would load that module. So let's say we load that R module. And now we can use command
like which to check which R we have. And we notice that it comes from somewhere, a magical place
way it suddenly found an R for us. There's a big list of these usually by the module purge
cleans up the modules. All of the commands are documented in the page if you want to read it.
There's usually a whole bunch of this software that is available on the computing clusters.
modules. So if you're looking for something, you might find it already here. So one place
to look at it would be over here.
Yeah. And there is quite, well, you need to know a little bit about module for almost
anything you do. So I'd encourage you to read this page.
Yeah, but the modules basically do, like in one sentence, they change various parts in
the Linux terminal so that it finds, like when you look for a program, it will find
the program in different places.
And we use this, instead of installing everything at the same time, we use this so that we can
have multiple different software that might not be compatible with each other.
So let's say multiple versions of R or multiple versions of Python or something like that.
Okay, should we go on to data storage?
Now, data storage is a very big thing and complex.
I mean, the cluster without data, what's the point?
And for the cluster, it's not near as simple as add some hard drives there.
Because the cluster has, the storage has to be big. So ours is 5 petabytes.
It has to be accessible to hundreds of compute nodes and possibly thousands of jobs at the same time.
All of which are reading and writing.
Yeah, so you can basically think of it as like a big pile of disks that has some magic
that makes it so that it appears as one file system.
So it's one big file system and everybody has their own files on that system.
And they are usually these, like you can look at the documentation for the places where
should put stuff. But in Aalto, for example, you basically always want to work on the scratch
file system, which is the work directory, like the big file system that we have. We also have this
bit of a legacy home folder that is much smaller and it's not meant for high-performance computing,
so the other part is meant to store your actual data.
The important things would be to note that usually these file systems have a quota.
By default, the home folder has a 10 gigabyte quota and the scratch file system has a 200
gigabyte quota, like a personal quota. But then we also provide bigger quotas, especially for
projects. So if you belong to a resource project, we can create a shared folder for your project
and they can run to terabytes and more, the quotas. So how much files can you store?
And if you run out of file storage, then ask us and we can increase it.
To me, the most important lesson here is that there's different types of storage for different
purposes. So our big Scratch storage is, well, it's called Scratch for a reason. It's not backed
up, but it's big. Aalto has other places, for example, this hidden out Aalto network drives
here, which are not as higher. Actually, yeah, let's come here. This is good. So for example,
Aalto has network drives that are not as big, but they're very backed up. They're backed up,
They have snapshots.
They have all kinds of, um, yeah.
Sorry.
I, um, yeah, it's sort of great out there.
Yeah.
Um, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Uh, so, so whenever you have a bunch of data, you might need to,
um, put it in different places.
For example, if you're collecting some original data, you would first put it
on the project Aalto storage where it's backed up and then make a copy to Triton where it's not
backed up but available to everywhere. And same for other things. There's like some of the compute
nodes have really fast local disks which are good for some things and so on. Yeah like usually like
you want to think about like what is your overall workflow but usually you have something that is
important like the starting point of your thing. You want that to be backed up in a project folder
in the Aalto network trial and then you want to create a copy of that usually into the work
directory or into the cluster so that you can work on that in the fast file system.
Then your code might be in a version control system. You might want to put your code into the
Git version control so that you can modify it there and you can keep a better check of that.
And then you might need to navigate some of these different file systems, but it's not as
complicated as it might look initially. Because once you figure out your own workflow,
it's usually quite easy to then manage afterwards. Yeah, there's a good comment. Can we...
Okay, there was just an explosion or boom outside. Okay, more like something falling.
Okay, so someone asked to mention separate quotas for number of files and size. So this is a good
point. So on your own computer, you usually think the size is what matters, because your hard disk
is a certain number of terabytes. But on a cluster, the number of files is also quite important.
And you can have a separate quota for both of these.
Yes. So if I run quota command, for example, in our cluster, you notice that I have, well,
quite a bit of files. So you can see here that there's these quotas over here.
Yeah, let's read this. Yeah, let's make it a bit. Yeah, so under group quotas we see space,
quota limit, files, quota limit. Yes, so the space is the actual space that I'm using. So currently
because I need to do lots of tests and developments. I need to have a bit bigger
quota than normally. My quota is three terabytes and I have two terabytes of data. Then my file
quota is three million files, and I'm almost hitting that. I'm pretty certain that 50% of
that is different kinds of Conda environment installations. Many of the installations might
create huge amounts of files. This can get problematic in many clusters. Many clusters
might have different documentations on how you should mitigate problems by having too
many files and that sort of stuff. Our file system, luckily, it's designed to pretty much
handle it quite well, but the quota can still get quite full at some point. In those cases,
I personally just need to do a cleanup at some point. You should be mindful or know about that
there's a difference there. There's a number of files and then there's the actual size of
those files and both are tracked by the voter. Okay. Should we go to the remote access?
Can you scroll down and show the available data storage options?
Oh, yeah.
So hopefully your cluster has a table that looks something like this
and will show the different places that are available and all the different properties.
And it's worth looking at this and seeing what fits.
But we don't need to go into details now.
Yeah.
We also have another page for all the provided
and it's like double the size because there's so many places
is you can put your data. If you're unsure where should you put your data, just come and ask us.
That's the easiest way. Yes, I agree. And we enjoy answering these questions because it saves
others a lot of time and is quite useful. So remote access. So you somehow need to copy data
from wherever you're working to the cluster, unless you edit and write everything directly
on there. But most people need to do this. And let's be honest, the copying of data,
if you don't use the command line, it can be a little bit tricky and complex. But luckily,
we have lots of different ways to do that now. So it's getting better. There's two main different
options here. One is remote mounts of data. So mounting means, let's see, where does it come from?
like you take a hard drive and okay here we go so basically and you mount the disk into somewhere
and then it becomes available on that computer and in this case because we are mounting it through
the network but it means that the file is actually in the file system in triton or in your cluster
but you basically have the shadow of it in your computer and whenever you request,
okay, can I have that file, it will have to transfer it through the network and then if
you do a modification, it will have to transfer the file back there. For example, what we talked
earlier about VS Code yesterday, VS Code basically, it's running on Triton. If you edit the file on
your VS Code editor, it will have to send the modifications back to Triton because it's
editing the actual file in the cluster.
So that's basically how it works.
Yeah.
And this is really convenient because as files are being made in some directory, you immediately
see it on your own computer.
But for opening big files and so on.
Yeah.
Yeah, you need to transfer the whole file in order to get access to it.
So, the second picture is transferring data.
And this is what it looks like.
So there's one copy somewhere and you make another copy somewhere else.
And there's a lot of different tools that help you with this.
The benefit of this is that once you then start processing the file at your own computer,
the results of your simulation or something. You now have it locally, so it's much faster to work
on that usually. But the problem might be that now you have two copies and how do you make certain
that they are actually in sync, especially if you do modifications or that kind of stuff.
There are tools that make transferring these files or syncing these even large files very useful,
like Git Annex and DataLAD and various other tools that you can use to do this.
But you need to figure out a workflow that suits your specific use case usually.
But yeah, if you ever encounter the situation where you're like,
okay, I have a file underscore date underscore back or something like that in your folder that
everybody has at some point, then you know that, okay, you could probably come and talk to us and
we'll figure out a better tool for you to do the copying. Yeah. Okay. And for general purposes,
I see many people using the mounting these days for lightweight use and then copying for
bigger data. So with that being said, I propose that we go to the Q&A and maybe