Hello.
So we are back, and I've remembered to set the audio correct.
So were there any more questions while we were waiting?
I will quickly mention there were a few questions about various, like for example, the sinteractive
and the Slurm commands.
So these are like helper scripts that we have created.
They are available in GitHub if you are interested.
You can ask your admins to set them up or you can set them up yourself if you want to.
there's alternatives that they're basically just wrappers for the slurm commands so there's
alternatives provided in the notes if you don't have those at your site yeah okay so off to the
section on serial jobs and I sent it to [name]'s screen yes
Okay, so yeah, a serial or batch job. What does it mean? So I guess I gave the metaphor
that you don't have to sit there and wait for it. So how does that go?
Yeah, so like if you think about like what you are doing with your computer, like usually of
course, there's a lot of coding that you do interactively. You code your code and then you
do some modifications. Maybe you use a notebook interface or something like that, and then you
constantly run each individual cell in the notebook. You might do most of your job like that.
But when it comes to the parts that are actually heavy or computationally, that might take four
hours to run that you might need the HPC resources, like the cluster resources for,
you don't usually want to be there watching at it, right? It's a waste of your time
to basically watch at that. Yeah. And then you can only do one thing at a time.
Yes. Yeah. Yeah. You want to usually offload that to something else. So basically,
So basically, you want to, like what [name] said about the table reservation, you want
to, well, okay, you basically order like takeout.
Like you order that the meal be prepared and once it's prepared, let me know so that I
can fetch it and just like eat the result.
So it's prepared for you on the background, so you don't have to like worry about, you
don't have to wait for it.
Yeah.
And we do this via the batch script.
So can you go over what's the general idea here?
So we tell the cluster what we want.
And we do that by, I guess, this batch script
that we're showing here.
So can you go over what these lines mean?
Yeah, so in the batch script, like we have an example batch script over here that you can look
at and over there we have various strange looking lines but these lines basically tell the queue
manager, the slurm, what it should do for you on the background. So the first line over here,
this line is this so-called shebang line which tells which interpreter, which tool we should
use to interpret the script or which program we should use to run the script. Usually,
commonly it's the shell, so the bash shell or some other terminal so that it would be basically
like, okay, execute these commands. Previously, when we just ran the Python 3, for example,
and then we ran the PI example, then we just called commands from the command line.
So, basically, this would mean that, okay, just use the command line to run these commands.
The next two lines are directives to the queue system.
So when we want the queue to manage this script, we want it to get us the resources what we
want.
And how do we tell it?
We usually give these comments in the script, these Sbatch directives.
And this is like a format that is very like, you need to write it in this format.
So it's not S bash or S batch with a space.
So it's written like this.
Exactly like that.
Yeah.
Because like the Slurm, when it takes this script, it will look for these comments and
if it sees these comments, then it will interpret what comes after the comment as an argument
for the queue manager, basically. Like, okay, I want this time, I want this memory for this job.
And afterwards, you can have whatever your code is after that. Like, whatever commands you want
the code to run, like the queue manager to run. And what happens is that when we call this
SBATCH and then the script that we have written, we call it, we basically say we are in the login
node, we have our terminal or whatever, we have it on the login node. And when we call that command,
the queue manager takes that file and then it will like read the comments that, okay, I will,
I know that this script needs these resources, and it will find you the correct place on
the compute node, in the CPU node, where it can execute that, that has those resources,
and then it will just plow through it.
It will just run the commands.
And it will, like, done it non-interactively.
So once you give the queue manager the script, you don't have to, you can just go to something
else and the queue manager will run it for you somewhere in the background.
There was a good comment in one of the previous notes questions.
If you log out, is all your stuff saved?
So I guess the synchronization here is everything starts as a file and everything comes out
as a file.
So your program, if it writes something,
if it prints something to the screen, where does that go?
Yeah, so if you would run in an interactive session,
for example, the Python code that we previously run,
it just printed it out there.
So it's basically ephemeral.
So it just disappears once you close the terminal,
because it's just output.
But if we run it non-interactively,
then Slurm will gather whatever output your code will write, like whatever text output it will
print, and it will collect that into a file. Of course, in many cases, you would want your code to
let's say read input files in the code and then write maybe some output file.
So basically, what happened during the computation is stored in those files.
But if you want to record the printed output of your code,
it will be recorded by Slurm.
Should we run a simple example on this?
Yeah, sure.
Let's go.
So if we scroll down a bit under your first jobscript,
I guess we can do the full demo.
So the starting point is at the shell, like we've had before.
And we need to make a new file.
So I guess [name] will use the nano editor to open a file and make it, but you can use any editor
you're comfortable with, whether it's VS Code with the remote SSH or through Jupyter or some other
command line thing. So [name]'s opened the file and will paste all the contents in there.
I'll make it a bit bigger so that it doesn't look so...
Okay, so we paste it here and I guess we know what these things mean, time, memory, output
is where it writes the output.
Yeah, and control X to save and yes to save it into a file name if you are using nano.
And then we do sbatch.
So sbatch and run-pi.
And if we push enter, so we see job submit automatically setting partitions, submitted
sbatch job.
So we have a job ID.
If we do slurm history, what do we see?
Or slurm queue, I guess.
Well, it already ran.
Yeah.
We should add some sleep there or something.
Let's do that, actually.
Just for the demo, let's add a bit of a sleep here.
So you can use this command sleep to add, let's say, 10 seconds so that we can capture the output.
So I will submit it again.
but this time I will run slurm q.
You can see it's now running there. Make it a bit smaller so the whole output fits.
Yeah.
And now in the script itself, if we look at the script again over here, we have this sbatch
output.
Right.
Yeah.
Like Slurm has various flags.
There's like a huge reference.
There's one in our page, but there's also the Slurm's own reference.
lots of different parameters you can give it. And this output is basically, if we want to
name the output in a certain way, we can do that.
Yeah, okay. And can we see the output? If we do ls, do we see things here?
Yeah, let's do them.
So we see day2.out, pi.out. Yes, so that's the example. And if we use...
Do we do cat or less?
I guess we can show cat first.
Yeah.
So cat is, first of, the thing that
comes and visits me sometimes.
But also, it's the Unix program that
is short for concatenate.
So it basically writes out what's in the file.
And we see.
There's an error.
Oh, slurm.
Yeah, I'm in the wrong folder.
That's the reason.
Yeah.
So let's move the run-pi to HPC examples.
Now let's try it again.
OK.
So I guess this is a common real life thing.
You make a job, you submit it, and then you
see, oh, there's something wrong.
And you adjust it and submit again.
It happens.
I mean, it's solely iterative.
This is often why we start with interactive jobs,
just to see quickly, does it even run at all?
and then write the commands in there.
Slurm q is a shorthand for slurm queue,
but you can use either one if you use the slurm command.
OK, now we probably have the pi.out.
Yeah, OK.
So we have pi.out, and yeah.
And if you look at the script, that's
exactly what it should do.
Echo hello user, hello [username], right there.
So this line, which might look, if you are not familiar with bash shell scripting might look a
bit complicated, but basically this, we often use this bash or this terminal languages because you
can do a lot of like housekeeping work with the terminal. Like you can move folders around,
you can rename files, you can do whatever stuff in the, like, and you can programmatically
do those. Instead of drag and dropping files in your file browser, you can do it in a systematic,
programmatic way. That's why we often use the terminal and why it's a powerful tool
when you're writing these things. Over here, we always get these parameters called,
or these variables called user and host name
that tell what is our username
and where are we executing this script.
And then we here call a program date
to get the current date.
So that's the output over here.
And you notice that it's not in the script,
it's like these variables,
but they are only filled when the script is run.
So they are filled when we are running it
in the compute node.
So we actually did run it in the compute node.
Yes.
Should we go to , actually, we have a bit of time.
There's a really good question in the notes.
If you take the script and you submit it
with bash the shell instead of sbatch,
it will look like it runs, but it's not taking these resource requests and it's not running
on the other thing. Yeah. We can demonstrate this. So, this is something you shouldn't do. Like,
it's unfortunate that the sbatch and bash sound so similar. Like, it's an unfortunate thing.
But if we, like, Lee, you remember I mentioned about how this is going to be filled when it's
going to be running. Now, if we run it with bash, what we expect to happen, bash is the terminal
or the terminal emulator or the interpreter for the code language that we have written here.
We expect that it heals these according to where we are currently running.
Because we are running it on the login node currently, our current host name
So, if we now run it, you notice that we are on the login node and we have this strange
thing happening where we have job queued and waiting for resources and then job has been
allocated to cases. So what happened is that basically we wrote these commands out. So if
we would have written these commands into the terminal itself, we would get the same output.
So if we run it with bash. So don't run it with bash, that's a different thing.
If we use it with sbatch, we give it to the Slurm manager that runs it only when there's
the correct space and time to run it in the correct computer to run it.
That way, we can make certain that it runs in the correct place.
You might also be wondering, why do we have srun over here?
do we have srun in the script? Why is it there? And the reason for that is that in some cases,
especially if you're using these MPI jobs that are parallel jobs, you might want to call srun
so that the Slurm manager can allocate these jobs correctly with the MPI jobs. But also,
So if you are using this srun, you will get extra information to the history.
So if I look at the Slurm history, when I...
Let's first run it once more so that we can get like that.
We can just...
Yeah.
We run it properly with the sbatch, and if we look at the Slurm history afterwards, let's
Let's see if I did it already finish.
Yes.
We can notice here that the, I'll
have to make it a bit smaller, I guess.
You can also have it run off the edge of your screen.
Yeah.
Yeah, there.
OK, yeah.
We notice here that the last job that we run,
we see these batch, extern, and zero.
So what this batch means is that all the commands that
didn't have srun on top of them, what did they run?
So basically, all of this stuff, how much resources it used,
and then how much resources did the srun call do?
We can get more up-to-date resource users information
for each individual part of our code.
You can do also kinds of fancy stuff for that.
But the srun is optional in the sbatch script.
But if you want to get more like this kind of
gradual resource information, you can use that.
So if you have a script and you're running,
say, three different steps with
different memory and CPU requirements,
you can understand them separately.
And we'll learn more about this in the next lesson about monitoring jobs.
But I think, yeah, what we probably want to do is do more exercises so you can learn how
to write these scripts yourself.
Because this is like the meat and potatoes of the whole thing.
When we go into Parallel Jobs and everything, the power of the cluster comes from the ability
of it doing work for you while you're just doing something else. And for that, you need
to be able to tell it that they are like, do this for me. And how do you do it? You
write these scripts that you execute so that you don't have to like watch what's happening
there. So learning this is a very important skill and very useful. So I highly recommend
and find the exercises.
Yeah.
OK, so should I propose we give a nice long time?
Should we let it go on until after the break
and return at, say, 10 minutes after the hour?
Yeah.
I will also like one thing we forgot to mention actually is that how do you cancel these jobs?
Like once you have submitted a job you can also cancel them. So let's say that I open the pi
the run pi script and I put here sleep
a long time, and it's not going to finish.
And I submit this script here.
I can check the queue, and you notice this job, each job gets its own job ID, so that
the Slurm can manage them.
And once this is running, you can always cancel.
If you notice that the job is not going to finish correctly, or you made a mistake or
something, you can always use scancel and the job ID to cancel the job.
So that way, when you run the scancel, the job will be gone.
It will just kill the job.
So basically, if you look at the quick reference, you can find all the common control and monitoring
things you need.
But yeah, read the page.
There's a little bit more in there.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, yeah, I'd propose exercises until the hour and then break until 10 minutes past
the hour all combined.
what we're doing right now is sort of the most important lesson, I'd say. It combines the shell,
the batch job, the resource requirements. And from here, it should get much smoother.
Yeah. Basically, like I said, what we want to now learn is how can we utilize the resources in the
computing cluster. Like there are lots of resources there and this is the way, like these are the,
this is the language that the queue manager understands. So we want to learn that language
so that we can translate our, whatever we want to run to a language that the queue manager
understands. So that the queue manager can do it for us. Yeah. Okay, great. So see you in
what, like 30 minutes? Okay, I guess that's all. Keep asking the questions and we'll
keep reading and answering. Okay, bye.
Hello.
We are back.
So yeah, how was the exercise?
I forgot to add the poll asking how it went.
There are some good questions here,
including a lot which we're asking
about using more resources.
For example, more processors at the same time
or running several things at once.
Yeah, we'll talk about parallel processing tomorrow, so different methods of parallel
processing.
But for now, the focus is on making certain that your workflow is in a way that you can
easily then leave something for the queue system to manage.
Like basically, you can write this kind of stuff
that the queue system does non-interactively,
so you don't have to worry about it.
But we're going to do some demos of Serial 3 and 5.
I'll switch to [name]'s screen here.
Yeah. So, these are pretty helpful examples of showing a couple of interesting...
Like this kind of Gedanken experiment, as Einstein would put it. Thinking experiments would make you
think about, okay, what's really happening in the background? So, in this example,
example, we try to demonstrate basically what happens if you start modifying something that
is already submitted.
Let's look at the run-pi that we have over here.
As per the exercise, let's add sleep 120 there, but I removed this older one at the end, and
we put sleep 120 here, so it will sleep for two minutes.
Maybe we can put it into one minute so that we don't have to wait that long.
And then, after we have submitted it, let's open the script and let's add something to
the Slurm script, so to this run-pi script.
So I'll prepare myself and I will take this into clipboard already.
I'll save the script and I'll submit it.
So let's see.
it and I'll edit it and I'll add here the line modified and I'll save this okay and now we can
use the Slurm queue to check what's happening it's it's now running in the queue so now it's
sleeping for a bit okay so what do we expect to happen [name]? So I guess it depends on if
if Slurm is remembering, if Slurm already read the file and then runs it, or if it just
remembers where the file is. No, actually, no, it's not queuing, it's running. I mean,
I guess if it's running, there's no way our modifications could have any effect because
Python has already opened it.
But also, even if it wouldn't be running, it wouldn't have an effect.
Because like Slurm, when you give it the script, what the Slurm sees is that it sees the script,
it will copy that script into its memory.
You can even later on, if you want, you can view the script for what it keeps in memory.
So basically, once you press Sbatch and the script, Slurm will remember the script and
after that, you can no longer modify that.
You have fired it away.
You have written the letter and you have sent it to the post and it's basically, it's there
going already.
You cannot modify it anymore.
So when we look at the output, the pi.out, we cut and edit, we see that there's no co-modified
line there.
because Slurm already took the script. But if we, yeah, go right ahead.
What would happen if instead of modifying the script itself,
we modified some of the other libraries or files it imported or ran?
Yes, let's do that exactly. So I'll quickly...
So I'll remove this modified line over here.
here. Save the file. Now, let's submit the run.py. Now, it's basically the exercise four.
Let's modify the actual Python script. Let's do that. I'll take this already into the clipboard.
I'll sbatch the run-pi, and now I will quickly edit the slurm/pi.py, and I'll add this over
here.
Okay.
Yeah.
And we can notice that it's now doing the sleep thing over there.
So what do we expect over here now?
Like the Slurm is running.
It has taken the sh script that we have given it, but it will run through it line by line.
And because it's now stuck in the sleep line, it hasn't yet reached the Python line.
But we have now modified the Python line, but the Python isn't something that we gave
to Slurm.
It's something that Slurm will, when it executes the commands, it will find from the disk.
So it will find the file that we have modified.
So usually it's not recommended to modify either the Slurm script or the script that
you are submitting, because you're now changing the state of the system.
You're changing either the script or the code, and now it will give a different error.
So you can see that if I now print it out, it gives me an exception.
Yeah.
Okay.
Not what we expected because of something else, but still.
Yeah.
Okay.
So I guess the point of these exercises is basically, once you submit a job, it's been
recorded and what you do may or may not have an effect on it, but it's better to leave
it alone.
Not modify them at all.
You have to be very careful to understand what you submitted and what you're modifying and how
it will affect things. So, basically, what usually is recommended that you would have,
like, let's say for your experiment, you would have an Sbatch script. And for the corresponding
to the Sbatch script, you would have your code or your parameters or something. We'll talk about
Array jobs tomorrow, if you have a lot of parameters, you can use these fancy things to
do lots of code calls at one time. But yeah, that is usually...
You want to have a script that is... Basically, it shows how you can replicate the results of your
or code. If you want to do a simulation or a run, some compilation or some code run,
you can replicate it by using the Sbatch script and you don't want to mess them up while they're
running.
Okay. So, yeah.
Number five.
Yeah. So, let's look at the third example. So, let's create a Slurm script that runs
this following program that produces some output. So, this ties up neatly to the next section that
we have. So, let's call it monitor_output.sh, and I will quickly write the usual lines.
Yeah. The usual magic words, I guess.
Yeah, once you have written enough of these, these are pretty self. You become familiar with those.
Yes, so what we do here is that every 30 seconds we print date and then we,
sorry for 30 times we print date and then we sleep for 10 seconds. Okay so
this is basically pretending that you're running something and it's periodically
outputting the status. Yes. Okay. So let's submit it and now let's it's probably
morning. Someone warns that you set the sh files to output file. Oh, did I? That's a good catch.
Yeah, that's a good catch. Okay, well then, I'm in trouble. Okay. I'm in danger,
like as Aral would say. So, let's cancel this one and let's do another recap.
So these can happen, this can happen.
Like I said, once you're familiar with these,
you can write them really fast, but you can also
write problems really fast.
Yeah.
OK.
OK, let's try it again.
The repetition makes everything better.
Yeah.
So now monitor_output.out
OK.
Yes.
And then let's go here.
And let's try it again.
Yeah.
Here.
OK.
And it's going.
Yeah.
And let's.
So now, yeah.
Now we can catenate the output.
So monitor output, cut out.
Not the SH.
OK.
Ah, so there's some stuff running.
Yeah.
And yeah, so it's appearing.
Yeah, so this is typical when you're running something.
What we talked earlier, interactivity
and non-interactivity.
In many cases, there's a situation
where do you really need to get the output constantly?
Do you really need to watch it?
Do I really need to watch this every second
of the output. Most likely not. I'm just interested that it runs, it produces reasonable results and
then I can leave it running. If I have a longer simulation or something, I can just leave it
running and I don't have to look at it constantly. But of course, you want to view the output.
So you can either do here, catenate the output. One other option is to use this tail -f and there's
other tools as well, but this tail is like follow the end of the file basically, it says here,
and it keeps it open. So every time a new line appears it automatically. Okay, yeah.
Okay, so if someone submits like a long training job or something, they can check the status this
way. Yeah. I will also mention that for some cases, for example with Python, like in many
cases, the output is buffered. Once you read a certain amount of output, it will flush the buffer
into the file. If your code produces very small amounts of output at the start of the run,
it might seem that nothing is happening because it hasn't yet filled the buffer.
There are various things that you can say to make certain that the buffers are flushed every
now and then, but like there are these certain situations where the output doesn't appear
necessarily immediately. Yeah, I mean I'm actually kind of surprised it does appear so quickly here
and doesn't get buffered. But anyway, should we go on to the next one?
And this is about monitoring, like what we already started to do.
Oh, sorry. I'm just adding the link to the notes. There's a good question here. It's
still about the... Remember there's a warning on some cluster, never use tail-f or something
like that.
Yeah, it might differ on the cluster. It's about whether the file system is like how
it's syncing, like how the syncing is done, like if there is this kind of like a global
lock or not. And it might differ in some clusters. There are then other tools to view the output.
But if your cluster says that don't use those, don't use those, just because I said to use
because, like, buyer beware or something like that.
I mean, you should trust your local admin over me.
So at Aalto, we've invested significant resources
in having a strong and performant file system.
So whenever there is lots of stuff, like, yeah.
So basically, it can handle things like tail-f.
Yeah, but it's probably a technical reason that other sites wouldn't have the file system capable
of doing it. It's probably a technical system regarding the mount and whatever,
but let's not go that far. Yeah. Okay. So monitoring. Sorry for this short distraction.