Yeah.
OK, so if you notice there's feedback here,
please fill out the poll.
I see there's a lot more people watching than are answering.
We really need these answers to improve things.
Yeah, do give us as much feedback as you can,
because we are just wondering here,
are we doing stuff correctly, or should we
modify it for the next year, and what should we do?
So don't leave us hanging.
Yeah.
So for tomorrow, in case anyone's leaving already, so we'll go over we'll go through the more advanced
uses, which is mainly many different ways of running things in parallel. And this is really
the real power, like what you've done so far. Well, you could do this on most of this on your
own computer and survive. But tomorrow, yeah, we'll see how we can run tens or hundreds of
things at once with only really small changes from what we're doing now. Make sure you understand
the batch job and monitoring parts of the day because that's what we're using.
So yeah like today we have been like what the name of the job was serial jobs interactive and
serial so they are like very one way but tomorrow we'll talk about like okay what if we add a
for loop basically here or like what if we do a lot of stuff at the same time and yeah hopefully
we can get that through in the best possible way yeah
okay if there's no more questions up here should we start wrapping up
So there is some feedback that it was a bit fast and there wasn't much time for
exercises. We know, unfortunately, but luckily you can continue exploring on
your own afterwards. There's no way we could cover it all in a few days or in a
few hours. So our hope it was to give you the inspiration and big picture and then
And you can go and follow up.
So is there any other preparation or things
people should do for tomorrow?
Not really.
I don't know.
I guess that's it.
Yeah.
OK.
Like, it's pretty much like tomorrow
is pretty much the same, but on a bigger scale.
But just like whatever we have talked about today,
about Slurm and parameters and whatever,
just keep in mind that, OK, you'll
be needing those tomorrow.
Yeah.
OK.
For this comment here about a demo of these,
I can give some, I'll put some links in here.
But yeah, okay, so see you tomorrow at the usual time.
Yeah, okay, thanks a lot. Thanks a lot. Bye. Bye.