And [name], what do we mean with interactive jobs?
Yeah, so on the cluster, there's two main types of jobs you can run. So let's say you go to a
restaurant. You can go, you can tell the host, I would like to have this kind of table. And you can
sit there waiting in the queue, or you can go walk around, do something else, and come
back when your table's ready.
So this isn't actually perfect because the better metaphor would be coming back once
your food is already eaten, which doesn't make sense in that metaphor, but it's the
general idea here.
So with interactive jobs, we say we'd like these resources, and you wait until they're
there and then you can do something yourself.
So it requires your time and mental effort.
What we'll do next is called batch jobs, where we say we'd like to do this, and then it's
submitted and then you come back when it's all done.
So we start with interactive jobs because it's easy to understand, it's easy to see
what happens, and then we can get familiar with making these different resource requests
and so on.
Oh, OK.
Yeah.
Was that a good explanation?
OK.
So we'll actually do it.
Yeah, let's do it.
So let's look at the following command here.
I will make this a bit smaller.
So OK, so where are we now?
So you can try to follow along and type with us also.
Also, we will give you time.
We're going to go through some things,
you'll have a nice long exercise break where you can try yourself. So, if you can't follow
as we're typing now, don't worry. There's time later. And about the setup here, on that
window here, I will be typing some commands and [name] will explain them. And on the bottom here,
you can see the history of the commands. Yeah. And so, we assume that you already can connect
to the cluster by SSH or on-demand or something and get a terminal. This is what we demonstrated
yesterday and should have been the homework for today. If you can't already get a terminal that
looks like this and type commands, then you're a bit behind and then that's okay.
You can watch what we're doing and try to catch up later during the break.
So, [name] is there. He has cloned the HPC examples repository using the git version
control system. Which is, by the way, a good way of transferring code to the cluster in
general. And then has changed into the directory. And then is running Python3 slurm/pi.py
1000. So what does this program do? So this program does like this kind of like a
like this is like a common example in like if you do Monte Carlo simulations like this
example where we estimate pi by throwing dart at a dartboard and because dartboard is a circle
and if we take random numbers from zero to one, like either square, we can basically estimate
the pi by the ratio of how many darts hit the dartboard. So this is like a small example code
that just does something. And we use it for many examples. So where did this code now run, [name]?
Well, we haven't... I don't see anything that looks like it's requesting resources, so this must have just run on the login node, I guess.
Like, we didn't give any instructions to the host saying what we wanted.
So let's... should we do the interactive request then?
Yeah, so let's request from Slurm some resources. So srun is the program to use for it.
it. The memory option says we need 100 megabytes of memory, which by the way is very small.
We need 10 minutes of time, which is way too much. And then we give all the normal options
we would give on the command line. So the program to run, which is Python, the program,
which is Py, and 10,000 iterations. So what do I see here? It says srun,
Slurm job submit automatically setting partitions is this in the background telling it
where it's running somehow yeah so on the on our cluster it might be different in your cluster
but on our cluster like the different kinds of hardware that we have is separating the
entity set different partitions because like if somebody wants to run on a specific hardware
they might want to run only on a specific partition.
But if the user doesn't specify what hardware they want to use,
there's this automatic script that
basically use a sensible default.
In your cluster, if you're in a different cluster,
you might need to specify this dash-dash partition flag like this.
In some sites, you might also
need to specify an account that you want to use.
So there might be different projects or something
that you want to specify that, OK, use
this account for the billing of job, basically.
We'll talk about the billing in a second.
But in our cluster, these are set basically automatically,
so you don't necessarily need to do them.
But let's say you run it on a CSC machine,
you might need to set this.
Yeah.
But what happened afterwards?
So then we see srun job id, thus queued and waiting for resources, job allocated resources,
calculating pi, so that's the standard output. So yeah, basically it's telling us it
got the resources and then it ran, and I guess it ran on some other computer somewhere.
Yes. While it was running, we could have tried to see what was happening in the queue, like
how it was doing in the queue. You can either use this squeue command or this slurm q to do it.
Because it's so fast to go through the queue, it's very hard to capture this for this specific
program, but if you have a program in the queue, you can use this to check the queue status. We'll
talk about this more in the monitoring part, but yes, you can do this. Okay. Maybe we can go on
and let people explore this more themselves. Yeah. To verify, this is a good example that
that if we just run a command like hostname,
which tells us which host we are in,
we can show that if we run just hostname,
we see that we are actually in the login for.
Because in the output,
we didn't necessarily see that we
were in a different place where we were running.
But if we run srun hostname,
now it just uses some default values for time and memory.
But usually we don't want to use the defaults because they are not set by us, but in this
case, let's just run it.
It's running, waiting for resources, and it has been allocated some compute node.
So we know that, okay, this command actually run in some different system.
There's a request in the notes.
Can we show an srun with huge resource request and show it waiting in the queue?
Yes.
So, what is big?
Can we say 200 gigabytes of memory?
Yeah.
And then...
Yeah, well, it still runs quite quickly because, like, yeah, there's like...
It's kind of arranged for that.
But let's say we ask for 200 terabytes of memory.
Now it says that there's no such node.
We don't have a computer that has 200 gigabytes of memory.
So, yeah.
Could we request 200 gigabytes of memory, 50 processors, and, say, one day of time?
Is that huge?
Well, let's not do the processors.
Let's just say, like, four days of time.
So, this is the day syntax.
And it still ran immediately.
There seems to be like a node...
Okay, let's put the CPU.
Okay, now it's...
Okay, it's still...
So, this is...
Okay, but there's a free resource for you to take.
So, part of the reason why it's running so fast is that
[name] hasn't run much lately.
And the less you run, the higher your priority is.
So basically, [name] hops to the front of the queue and gets anything immediately.
And this is also one of the situations that can happen if you are dealing with interactive jobs.
If we think about the restaurant metaphor, if we go to an empty restaurant,
we can basically choose which table we want to eat anyway, right?
We can pick the biggest table, it doesn't really matter if the restaurant is empty.
If there is enough free space, then the queue manager can basically fill our strange requests.
But if the place is full, it might be that we suddenly need to wait a lot.
So let's show the interactive shell and the sinteractive command quickly.
So what we did here is we ran a command line program on a node.
But we can also request it to run just a normal shell,
and then we see things.
So here we're making the standard resource request.
This time we've told it the interactive partition.
And we get this.
So now we see it.
This is because of the recording thing.
Don't worry about that.
Like recording the history.
Yeah.
But we see here, if you read this last line,
it looks different.
It says [name] username and then PE22.
And PE22 is the name of one of these compute nodes
that's available.
So now [name] has waited once and can run things multiple times,
like this hostname command and other things.
Yeah.
Yeah, OK.
If I exit them, yeah.
I don't know why that history doesn't work.
I have an idea, but let's worry about it later.
Okay. Yeah. Okay.
So, yeah.
So, yeah, this is, like, if you want to run multiple commands,
like, you can use this if you want to temporarily get, like,
let's say you want to do, like, a big installation or something,
and the login node doesn't have the resources to do that.
like there was a question there in the notes about like if you're doing like a
big build on your laptop like it might require lots of resources like that might happen also
in the cluster you so you might want to get like temporarily lots of resources but do note that
these because these are interactive resources when you're not using them they're basically
still reserved for you, so you're reserving resources. So if you're not using them,
it's a good idea to usually give them away so that other people can use them instead.
And this other command, sinteractive, is it even still installed? Did we
install it on the new cluster? Yeah, it's installed.
Okay. So this is pretty similar to the srun one, but it sets some other defaults
and can allow graphical programs to run. But now we would recommend doing graphical things with
open on demand, so wouldn't really recommend this, I guess.
Yeah, but if you have a need to do it, then yeah. Yes. Okay. So the error is
probably because of the recording script that I'm using. Yeah. Okay.
So should we go on and we need to talk about checking the jobs so we can see the history.
I'll quickly mention that if you want to see what jobs we had previously run, you can use
the slurm history command.
I will make the terminal a bit smaller so that I can see it.
And it will show me the history of all of the jobs
that I have previously run, for example, the interactive jobs
and that sort of stuff.
We'll talk about this more about when
we talk about monitoring jobs, but it
is possible to see the history.
So but let's scroll down.
Yeah, should we?
We've got these exercises here.
So we'll give you some time to explore this yourself
and ask questions.
There are how many different things you can try?
I count five of them.
And you can also try the other things
we've demonstrated above here.
Give it a try.
See how it adapts to your own clusters.
Read some more things.
Yeah.
I will switch to the notes here.
And I see that there's many different questions here, and they've been being answered. So do
keep asking. Is there anything we want to talk about now? I think most people can probably...
The Jupyter Terminal does work, yes.
MATLAB.
Maybe we'll talk about MATLAB a bit later if someone can answer some default.
Yeah, okay, I'd say let's go on to the exercises.
How long should people have?
Should we have maybe 5 to one?
Yeah, maybe 5 to one and then we can do a brief wrap up and then have a break.
Yeah.
Okay.
Sounds good.
See you then.
Yep.
Yep, do keep asking questions and respond with your progress to our poll there.
See you later.
Bye.
Also, I will mention that this goes into the next subject that we are going to be talking
about, there's also a question of, can you attach to already existing job? And it goes to,
what we're next going to be talking about is these non-interactive jobs.
So in many cases, the interactive is fine if you are actually watching. My personal
approach is that if I'm not watching the actual screen, I'm not using interactive jobs.
Like, if I'm not actually using, like, humanly watching it, I'm not using interactive talks
because why?
I'm not interacting with it.
I realized I forgot to turn on my audio when coming back on stream.
But anyway, we're back.
What did I say that was the podcast?
If you wanted us to do a demo of one of the exercises, put a vote to the exercises.
Please vote down here.
What else did I say?
If you, do you need to close jobs when they're completed?
And that is yes.
If you don't close one of the ones that gives you a shell, then the resources will stay
reserved for you.
So there was at least one vote for exercise one.
So we can do a quick demo of that.
So let's do the most simple one over here.
I'm heading to [name]'s screen.
Yes.
In this exercise, we run this memory use script that uses memory and then we
want to see what happens when we increase the memory requirements and with various memory requirements.
So let's try first just running with just srun and no any requirements specified,
any specific requirements. So let's just try running this and see what happens.
So you can see here, yeah maybe I typed it too fast. So I wrote srun and just what I want to run.
So just add the SRUN. That's usually this one handy trick that you can use. Just add the SRUN
if you don't know what happens. And it was trying to use 50 megabytes of memory and it
allocated up to that point. It worked. So let's add an actual memory requirement here.
So I press the up arrow to get the previous command and now I will request 500 megabytes.
And because it's less than the 50, it still worked quite well.
But now let's do the C part where we try to increase the memory limit.
So let's try, we have the 500 over here.
So let's try like 500 over here.
Okay.
Ah.
Yeah.
It's memory killed because it's actually probably using a bit more than the 500.
So let's increase the memory limit a bit and let's see how much it actually used even though
it tried to use 500.
Let's see if 600 works.
Okay.
600 works.
So let's add the sleep parameter there
to check what was the actual memory usage.
We can use Slurm history to check the memory usage.
But we need to, like Slurm captures it only once
every 60 seconds or 30 seconds or something.
So, we need to let it run a bit longer.
Yeah.
Right.
And you notice here that,
let's say I would be running like a long job.
This would be really annoying to watch at the screen
to keep it open, like the terminal open constantly
or the connection open.
So, in the next session, we'll talk about
how you can avoid this kind of like situation
where you have to keep it open while it's running somewhere
in the background.
So if this would last for, let's say, multiple hours,
it would be really annoying to watch at this screen
and let it wait.
OK, there, it's done.
Yeah, I will make it a bit smaller.
Hopefully, you can still see the font.
So you notice here there is some overhead in the code, so it actually used 518 megabytes.
We'll talk about the memory usage and that sort of stuff a bit more later.
I guess this is basically how it goes when you don't know how much memory it uses.
you try a few things and you see what's happened, what happens, and then yeah. Okay, should we go
to a break now? Yeah, I will quickly say that about the interactive stuff, the most important
thing to remember is basically this diagram at the top of the documentation here, that when you're
using srun or sinteractive, you're no longer in the login node, you're suddenly over here.
So you're in the compute node. And that's the most important thing to remember that,
okay, if I ask the queue system to place me somewhere, you end up into a different place.
And that's basically the most important thing to remember.
Yeah. Okay.
Okay. Let's...
Great.
Should we take a 10 minute break until...
10-minute break until 13 past. Okay, great. See you later. Bye.