Just say one two three.
test we started. Sorry, I didn't give the countdown. Hi. So, we're here. I guess the
first order of business is adding some icebreakers here.
Yeah, let's do that.
We'll add the audio test.
Me then [name].
One.
Two.
Three.
Four.
Okay. Five.
Six.
I was listening to the audio and it was pretty confusing to hear.
Which number should I say?
Yeah.
Okay.
There's some icebreakers.
Yeah.
So, what can we...
So, one question I would have for our audience is that, have you used an HPC system before?
Like a computational cluster?
Yeah.
And let's say we have questions of never, occasionally, and then.
one and something completely fun.
I always remember this question,
what was your favorite fruit that got some of
the best response from anything.
What's your favorite ice cream flavor?
In honor of the weather the last few days.
That's a good question.
I would say maybe like an old-timey strawberry
with some jam inside of it or something like that.
That's pretty good.
Yeah.
What's yours?
Oh, that's a good question.
There's this, um, maito flavor from Suomen Jäätelötehdäs, that's pretty good.
Yeah.
So for the, how long have you used computers?
One of my interesting questions there, like, how did you get started and what did it mean
to you?
Like when I was growing up there were computers in our home and I mean I guess my parents had
one of course this was in the 90s or something like that so it wasn't really a powerful commonly
used thing but I didn't really like have a feeling that this is a thing that I could learn about and
know about until maybe my last year of high school, something like that, and then I got
one that I could mess with just for myself.
And then I could start, you know, breaking things.
And then when you break stuff, you really understand it.
So I wonder, how did this progression go for other people?
Like for you, [name], what was your starting point of?
Yeah, I would say that the starting point was when my father bought a secondhand computer from his work
that his coworker had preloaded with some shareware games or something like that, like DOS games.
It was a Windows 95 computer, but yeah, I would say that trying to even get those to work
was an effort in and of itself, like old shareware games. So yeah, that was basically like
you immediately start to do problem solving because you want to play the games and the
games don't work. So yeah, yeah, okay. So basically games seems to be the way that people start
with computers. Do we need some HPC games that people can play and get familiar with things and
so on? Like I would say that why people start, like I tried my, I learned my parents like 486
as well with MS-DOS, but what can I do with that? I can use a matrix printer and write some text,
but if I'm like six years old or something, what does a six-year-old need a matrix printer for?
The games are much more suitable, I would say, because if you only have a productivity computer,
it's not that fun. Eventually, of course, the productivity can get fun as well.
So, yeah.
Hopefully.
Yeah.
Hmm.
Does anyone want to hear what happened yesterday with the stream going down?
And some more stories behind that.
Go right ahead.
Uh, yeah, so in my home a few weeks ago, I got these messages saying electricity meters
will be replaced in your building sometime in the next few weeks, but you'll get a text
message a day or two before that happens, so you have some warning.
So I worried, ah, okay, this is going to be bad, because it's right during the kickstart
course time. But I haven't gotten a message about it yet, so, you know, I've just ignored it.
But, of course, whenever they're replacing the meter of the common
telco equipment in the building, I guess I wouldn't get notified. So my hypothesis is that
yesterday they did that. So I lost my connection for 15 minutes or so. Incidentally, like they
said yesterday, it was right at the same time before the same talk that was interrupted by
the Fastly CDN breaking several years ago. So then I... So at first I was hoping it would
come back soon. It happened towards the beginning of this long break. But then
When it was getting closer and closer to time, I switched my laptop tether to my mobile device,
which incidentally my mobile operator had some problems with their network, their mobile
network earlier in the day.
And luckily they weren't right at the same time because then I would have had zero connection
to the outside world at all.
That would be pretty funny.
And all of the fancy production tricks that you might see during the streams, [name]
is basically the person behind all of these.
So we would have been in a creek without a paddle if [name]'s internet didn't come
back.
Yeah.
And then you saw me dynamically adjusting stuff trying to recover.
So that was kind of fun.
But it did show me that it actually wasn't that hard.
My laptop could handle it with the outside screen, and if I just had a little bit more
preparation then it would have been much easier.
The hardest part is that I couldn't copy stuff by SSH from my desktop to my laptop
because there was no network and I didn't really know what to do about that problem.
Anyway, so it's almost time. Let's review what we've got here for our
answers. So most people haven't used clusters that much.
Please do go and open up the notes and answer these, so this is really important for us to see the interaction and know how many people are around.
Yeah, and also usually we have so many people watching this, or hopefully we have a lot
of people watching this.
But when we have a lot of people watching, if you encounter something during the talks
that was rushed too fast or something like that, that's something that was unclear for
you.
notes is the best way to make us notice that, and then we can elaborate on the answers that
we're giving.
So because today, [name] will talk a bit more about what we're going to be going through
today, but there's going to be this kind of like, we're building on a foundation type
of a thing where we build upon the previous things.
If something gets lost in translation or something, then it's basically like the foundation
is cracked. It's good to fix immediately so that we know how to build upon the information that we
have given. Use the notes a lot. Let us know about any questions that you have. Ask a lot
of questions that there's other people answering as well, because it really, really helps us and
it helps you. Yeah. Okay, so let's get started. I will switch to my screen here, I hope. Yes.