it helps you. Yeah. Okay, so let's get started. I will switch to my screen here, I hope. Yes.
So as usual, we have our schedule. It should say everything we're doing.
If we go down to day two, we begin with about clusters and your work.
I will also quickly mention that public service announcement, remember to put the stream to
maximum resolution if it's not already there, so that any text will appear as crisp as possible.
But we will mostly talk and look at pretty pictures, but there's text sometimes as well.
Okay, so yesterday we talked a lot about basic concepts of scientific computing, like where
you can store your data, who we are, how to ask for help, things like that.
Now we get to the real stuff.
The general plan is that today we go into basics.
So what is a cluster, what are resources, how to request them, and so on.
We get to some of the interesting parallel and GPU stuff tomorrow.
But because a cluster is easy to use if you're familiar with the command line Linux, things
like that, and hard if not, we're going nice and slow today in order to make sure that
everyone can keep up and we have this good solid background.
So yeah, what's a cluster?
Yeah, so if we think about the cluster, it's basically like a bunch of computers in a trench
coat.
But it's also a bit more than that.
So a cluster is basically a big system that has many features in it.
So what we usually have in the cluster is that we first off have a lot of computers
there that are meant for computing. So in this diagram that you can see we have the CPU nodes
like that is the main thing of the cluster really. We have a lot of hardware there that can be used
for computing. There's also specialized hardware like the GPU nodes that have GPU cards
that are used for GPU computing. And then usually a cluster has a file system as well
So it's own file system, which is connected to these nodes in some fast lane, so that you can
have big data flowing into the CPU nodes and the GPU nodes. And then, yeah.
So how big is our cluster, just as a reference? So the one at Aalto University.
So our is like a medium size, maybe. Medium, small. Medium in Finland, small in international scale.
But we have a lot smaller clusters. Some other universities might have a smaller cluster.
And for example, the CSC supercomputers, they are a lot bigger. But in our case, it's,
Well, I don't know, actually remember the numbers, like a few hundred nodes?
Yeah, I think it's like the order of 300-ish.
Yeah, and maybe a few hundred GPUs.
Yeah, a few hundred GPUs, 10,000 processors roughly, last I remembered.
Yeah.
But you can already hear from what I'm describing here that the cluster,
what is important about the cluster is not necessarily how much there is on the backend
or something, it's how you're going to be using it. And you're going to be using it through this
login systems, like login node or the on-demand. And then we will talk about how you get access to
the resources later on. But for me, at least personally, it's more of like, I know that
there's just resources there, I just need to be able to use them. But it doesn't really matter
where they come from. They are there on the background and there is a way of
getting those resources. And we'll talk about that soon. But basically, there is just a bunch
of computers and those computers are connected to each other with a fast network and there's a
a storage space for your data and then you can use those computers using certain things
that we'll be talking about.
So about our own cluster at Aalto University.
It was completely upgraded and reinstalled, well, a month ago.
And everything has changed.
So many of the things you might read might be out of date.
trying to update them or add warnings there, but just be aware that things are different now.
And we'll talk more about this later. The final thing on this page is asking for help.
So it is really hard to go and do everything alone, especially when you're starting.
So do read about getting help and come to your local support early if you need it.
don't struggle forever. And with that I think we can go on from this page.
Yes. Okay. So next up in the schedule is Slurm, the queuing system.