Yes. Okay. So next up in the schedule is Slurm, the queuing system.
So Slurm is the drink from Futurama, and it's also the simple Linux utility for resource
management. I don't even know. I think nowadays it's just a word. I don't think it's an acronym
anymore, but that's probably the original one. That was the original one. Yeah. So, we already
talked about what's a cluster. Is there anything else to add here? Yeah. So, we mentioned the
that there is a cluster and there's lots of resources.
And I also already hinted that there's
a way of getting access to those resources, and that is Slurm.
So we have this nice analog for this, what the Slurm is.
And it's this kind of like, the analog
is this HPC diner or HPC restaurant.
Do you want to, [name], explain the analog?
Oh, yeah, that's a good metaphor.
So let's say you're going to a restaurant. Do you go to a restaurant to sit at the stove and
cooking yourself? Or do you go at the restaurant for someone else to cook for you? Well, for
someone else to cook for you. That's the first thing. But when you arrive there, so that way
you can do other things while someone is cooking for you. But when you arrive there, do you
immediately go and pick any table and sit down? Or is there usually a sign when it's
busy that says, please wait to be seated? And what does this person do? You have to
tell them how many people you are. Usually you don't tell them how long you'll be eating,
but this would be a relevant piece of information if there's another reservation there. And
And this host that's there looks at everyone that's in the queue and then tries to assign
them to tables so that the most possible number of people can eat at once.
So for example, they won't have two people sit at a table for four people if there's
space for just two.
They won't go, like they'll try to save some big tables for big parties that might come
in later, especially if they have a reservation.
And this is basically what Slurm is doing.
So there's a bunch of people waiting and want to run more jobs than there's time.
So the host has the queue, they order the queue in priority somehow, and they try to
give something to all the resources in a way that will use them as optimally as possible.
Do you think of this metaphor?
Yes, I think that is very well put.
So in our case, the Slurm, what it considers
when you look at what sort of tables are you booking
and that sort of stuff, it also takes
into account stuff like your priority
or how much you have visited there before.
Basically, let's say the restaurant is very popular and they try to make certain that as many people
have an opportunity to eat at the restaurant. They try to organize it so that it's fair for
everybody. If somebody goes there every day and takes a table, they try to book other people as
well so that as many as possible have the opportunity to go there. So the queue manager
takes into account various things about what sort of things you require, so what sort of
things you need. And then it can manage this large, large restaurant from a simple lobby.
Yeah. So I guess you have to tell the host what you want if you come in and you say,
I'd like a table and they ask you, okay, how many people are you? And you're like, I don't know.
Then they'll look at you and wonder what's wrong with this person.
Yeah. But the restaurant manager is also very understanding that if you want to book a table
for four when there's only two people eating, they will book it, but you're limited to basically then
only tables of four. They will try to accommodate every kind of a guest, but at the same time,
by, well, the question what you don't need, you might be limited to some place. If we go back
into, from this analog, partly back to the actual reality of what is happening, if you, [name],
want to show the picture of the cluster. Yeah, if you show the picture of the cluster. So what
happens in the cluster is that you go into the login node with an SSH or you take the on-demand
connection to login node or VS Code connection. You are there and that is basically the lobby
of the restaurant. When you are there, you're in the lobby and now you have the sign in front of
you that, okay, wait for seating. And who is the host? That is the SLURM, like the queue manager.
And when you ask the queue manager that, hey, I would want to have these sort of resources for
this sort of time, aka I would want to have this table with these kind of seatings for this amount
of time, then the queue manager will process your request and it will, once the table is free,
it will seat you there. So in the case of a cluster, it will find you a computer that has
those resources and it will put you into that computer and then it will run your code in that
computer. So basically, we go back to the real world, what is happening, that is what's happening
in the background. Yeah. So I guess on the cluster, we're not asking for seats for people,
But what are we asking for? And that's why we come to here, the resources Slurm manages.
Yeah, so the most important or the simplest resources that Slurm considers are the amount
of processors you want. Like yesterday, there was talk in notes that do I really need to know
about these processors and do I need to really know about how the CPUs are. In a sense, you need.
There's, I will, we will show like some shorthands of how you can like estimate these things
soon, but you need to know a bit about your program, like you need to know a bit about the
like the requirements of your program, that how many processors it needs, how much memory it needs
and how much time it needs. So that Slurm can fill you a slot in one of the computers
so that your code can then run there. Of course, basically, you can think of Slurm as trying to
solve like a Tetris puzzle constantly, and you're just giving it different kinds of blocks all the
time. If you don't like the table analogy, another analogy with that. And Slurm tries to get the full
Tetris of filling the computers fully and it will consider these kinds of like slots or blocks
when it's calculating the jobs. Yeah, actually you have a good picture of this slot concept.
Should we show that? If you have it right away then sure why not. So this how big is my program
page. Yeah. So this is written last year-ish. Yeah. And yeah, so there's these good pictures.
So a typical laptop computer, what's it like? Yeah, a typical laptop, like what you might
have, these might be a bit old, maybe they're bigger now, like since last year, but it's
It's about four CPUs and 16 gigabytes of RAM, and a workstation might be eight CPUs and
maybe 32 gigabytes of RAM, and a typical computational server or compute node, compute node is another
way that we just say it's a server, it's about maybe 32 CPUs.
Nowadays, it can be up to 128 or 256 CPUs and up to terabytes of RAM or something.
But that's about the ballpark, but that's an estimate.
So you can say that one server is about four desktop computers or eight laptops.
So when you're trying to decide what the resources are
that your program needs, it's usually a good idea
to use this as sort of a natural measuring stick.
That's like, OK, let's just say that.
So if you have no idea what to request at all,
but you know it works on your laptop,
you could start with roughly this amount
and then adjust up or down.
Yes.
And the simplest option is that if you run the program on your computer,
if it runs on your computer, you can just check your task manager.
Like there's instructions below how you could do it, but basically this is the kind of like
natural number or like natural unit that you can use to measure your codes.
That's a good starting point.
So first ask what your laptop provides and then see how it works.
That's usually a good starting point.
So what are the resources we'll be requesting in our jobs?
What resources does it allocate?
So yeah, like we mentioned, there's the CPUs, then the memory, and then the time.
We'll be talking about these throughout, like, we'll first start in the first examples that
we are going to be running quite shortly, and that you can run as well.
We'll be mainly focusing on time and memory, because those are something that always need
to be basically set.
And then the processor count, when we get to the parallel stuff tomorrow, we'll talk
a lot more about the processor count.
For now, let's just focus on one CPU jobs, but we can do more on that.
There's also, of course, special hardware like GPUs.
You might need a machine with a specific hardware, so you might need a GPU.
There's also a possibility that if you want to use a certain kind of a CPU,
like our cluster, it has multiple generations of CPUs.
whenever we buy more machines, we usually don't throw the old ones away. We try to be ecological
in a sense like that. So, we use them until they are no longer usable or useful anymore.
So, you might want to limit yourself to a certain architecture or something.
And in those cases, you can do the limiting. But those are more advanced stuff and we don't
necessarily need to focus on that.
So maybe, this wasn't exactly asked in the notes, but
I questioned, so CPUs and cores and processors, do these all mean the
same thing?
Well, basically yes, like CPU can have multiple,
or CPUs usually have multiple cores, so the
actual like physical CPU chip. It usually has multiple cores, but they can be also said to be
like CPUs in many cases. So they appear as like separate GPUs in the operating system.
So they are usually referred to as cores. So practically speaking, it's the same thing.
Yeah, it's like from the user perspective, it's the same thing. And that is, yeah.
And then second, there's a good question. The new Mac processors, M1 and so on,
seem to have a lot of VRAM, and also a different architecture, and I think more
cores than usual. How does this play into this, if it usually works on my laptop?
Yeah, so what [name] said, the Mac architecture is different, so it's an ARM-based processor.
most of the computing clusters. Well, there are some ARM-based computing clusters in, I think
Amazon has some and that sort of stuff, but ours are like the x86, you might have heard that
architecture. So they are using that architecture. So they have a different kind of CPU style.
still. So they work in a bit different way. And like the VRAM stuff, like Mac has this
unified memory architecture that is like a bit different than this kind of like x86.
So it's a bit more complicated. But usually that means that's just like, yeah, you cannot
run the exact same program because you need two different CPU architecture, but usually
can get it working in both systems without any hassle. And I guess understanding the resources
your program needs actually is a big part of running on the cluster somehow. Like on your
own computer you just do it and it either works or it doesn't. But on the cluster
you have to really think about this. I will also mention that when we are going through
the examples here. And when you're starting on your work, it's a good idea to request more
than less. And we will show you various tools that Slurm provides that you can then monitor
what the code actually used. And based on that output, you can try to determine whether your
code ran correctly. But as a first step, I would request more than less and then see if I actually
managed to use all of that. So if you don't know how many people are coming to your birthday party
or something, it's better to book a table that is big enough for the biggest group that you expect
instead of maybe just book a small table and then have a problem. Important to realize we're not
running things just once usually, so it's better to request more and then look and see what it uses
And then for all the future ones, you can adjust and we'll actually talk about monitoring later today
So we don't need to go into details, but but there's this is enough theory. Let's go to actual like let's do something
So should we move on to the next lesson?
Yes to interactive jobs
So, okay. So do you want to throw the screen to my screen?
Sure. Are you ready for it? Yeah, okay
There is your screen.
Yes. So before we start looking at the lessons,