How should we divide this up?
Well, I'd say that let's go quickly through the MPI and then spend more of the time in the GPU
part, because I think a lot of people are interested in that. But I think Jules' talk was
a great introduction to what we are going to be talking about now, because these next technologies,
well, GPUs are used everywhere, but MPI is definitely the workhorse in many of the
the supercomputers, and this kind of like codes are used in this, especially what [name] was saying
about Mahti, which is this kind of like machine designed especially for running these very big
parallel programs, and those programs utilize MPI to do the parallelization.
Yeah, so what's the most important things to know? Let's say you have a program and you
know it uses MPI, because the docs say so. What options do we need for SLURP?
So the first thing with the MPI program, if you need to compile it yourself,
you need to usually use some MPI libraries that are provided by the system administrators.
Because MPI, when we talked about the different packetization strategies,
it's message passing. So a lot of stuff is transferred throughout the network.
So usually these libraries, these MPI libraries are compiled or created in a way that they can
understand the hardware very well. So they can understand the high speed in network that is
between the computers. So that's why all of these like high-performance clusters that have these
kind of like, or want to run these like big jobs, they have this usually this high-speed network
and they have their own MPI installation that knows about this high-speed network.
So when you're doing the MPI communication, the program is literally knowing about the
low-level hardware and sending messages as fast as possible.
in many cases like it tries to bypass the processor itself so in for example when there's
communication happening it tries to like go straight from the memory of the computer to
to the network card and from there through the network straight into the memory of another
computer basically injecting into the memory of another computer without ever going through the
processor to speed up these communications and that for that reason there needs to be it's called
called like remote data management access.
I think like it's the short term, RDMA like anyway,
but basically these kinds of things.
So you first need to find out,
if you need to compile something,
you need to find out the MPI libraries
that are provided by the system and then use those.
Like you need to find those in a module somewhere
and you need to remember to load these
when you're running the MPI program as well.
If you are using pre-existing MPI program
that is installed by the system administrators,
for example, when I used the LAMPS demo on the first day,
I used the LAMPS installation that we had installed.
And in that case, you don't have to compile anything,
you can just use that.
It's same with CSC,
like if you want to use something like GROMACS
or CP2K or something.
In CSC machines, they already have existing installations
and it's usually a good idea to use those
because those have been tested and designed
to use the high-speed interconnects.
But from the queue side, what do you need?
So from the queue side, you need to tell the queue
how many the so-called MPI tasks you need to specify.
So again, like there's going to be more terminology.
it's unfortunate, but because there's differences in the meaning, there's going to be new terms.
So in MPI world, there's going to be these, how many nodes do you want?
Usually you want, if all of your tasks fit into one node, so task is usually one CPU,
but it can have multiple CPUs in the task.
So previously when we asked for multiple CPUs, we had the CPUs per task, and nobody asked
what the task is, but basically that's the MPI task.
So when we are running this shared memory parallelism, we're asking for CPUs per task,
but we're asking for only one task because we're not using MPI.
But in the case of MPI, you want to ask for multiple of these MPI tasks.
And each of these is typically one CPU, but can be more.
And typically, you want to ask for either one node, or you want to divide the program
in a way that it's distributed among the computers in some even fashion.
So in the abstract, there's nodes and n tasks per node.
For example, you would want to have one computer with 20 CPUs and another computer with 20 CPUs,
because this means that then it's more balanced, the job requirement.
Usually, at least in Triton, you want to use srun to run the program because that
tells the program to use this MPI framework that is built into the system, so that the MPI asks
the Slurm, where should I place all of my tasks? And it does this communication layer underneath it
to do it. But in practice, yeah. For most users, this can all be considered magic,
and you know you need these options and that it works.
Yeah, like usually I would recommend just checking like the documentation here
and just using those like values and try to like allocate
like what how many programs you want and try to allocate it in the way that it's mentioned there.
So if we look at the example here, do we want to go through it or?
I think it's probably not needed. I mean, I'd rather go to the GPUs.
Yeah, so the MPI example here is basically just there's like an MPI implementation of the same
Pi code, but it uses multiple processors to do it. And basically what you do is you load
an MPI installation. In our case, in our cluster, it's OpenMPI that we mainly use.
use, and then you compile the code. So, this is C code. So, it's low-level code, and then
you run it. But yeah, if your program uses MPI, you'll know it because they mentioned
it. So, you'll know about it because it mentions MPI. So, if it doesn't have the letters MP
and I somewhere mentioned, it's not using MPI, really. So, try to search the documentation
that sort of stuff if you want to do this MPI programs. And come and ask us if you have problems
with this. Because all of the network layer and that sort of stuff, this is high-performance
computing that basically marries the program with the hardware in a different fashion than
the previous programs we were running. Here we have a much more closely knit connection,
So that's why there's lots of complications and that's why it's mainly used for these
very complex programs that want to run very big simulations.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay.
If you have any questions, then do ask.
For those people who don't want to use MPI, I wouldn't touch the nodes and end tasks.
I would just know that these are not meant for me.
I don't care for those.
Because I just want to use multiple processors.
I don't care for these tasks, things.
Yeah.
Okay.
There's no questions about this, which is roughly what I'd expect, to be honest.
I mean, it's a thing that you'll learn when you need it.
And if you're using it, probably there's someone around you that figured this out already.
If you know that you want to code with MPI, I highly recommend going to the CSC MPI courses.
They are very nice courses. I have taken a few of those myself just to get more information.
They are very good courses on that.
Okay. Should we go to the break now a little bit early
and come back and have a bit more time for GPU stuff?
Yeah. Sounds good.
until 58. Okay, great. So keep asking questions, if any, and see you in 10 minutes.
Yep.
Bye.