Hello.
Can anyone hear us?
Yeah, I think they can hear us, at least.
I can hear us on the stream.
You hear us?
Okay, good.
That's a good start.
Let's get all these controls going.
Yeah, we have icebreakers, like, unless you like icy weather in the chat.
What is your favorite weather?
Yeah.
OK, so yeah, so [name], what's your favorite weather?
I would say that it's like, it's a weather that changes
every two weeks or something.
Like, I don't usually like it to be
the same too long at a time.
But I do like Finnish winters.
It's great.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, a cold, dry winter is good.
Yeah, dry, yeah.
Yeah.
And you know, like once it gets to 20, it can get too hot sometimes, but maybe
15 to 20 and sunny, occasional rain every few days to keep the fire warnings away.
It's often said that, especially in the cold weather, it's a question of what are you wearing.
But I think for different kinds of weather, it's the question of what are you planning on doing.
Summer weather is very nice if you're planning on going to the beach or something like that.
But it's not very nice if you're inside and have to work.
If you say you happen to be inside with a bunch of computers running a streaming setup in a insulated building.
Yeah. Not necessarily the best weather for that sort of an activity. I don't know who would do that.
Yeah. Yeah.
Okay. The next question is which technologies have you used?
And there are some things there like Python, multi-processing, R parallel and so on.
These are all basically ways to use multiple processors at once, and maybe other people can add more of them there.
If you don't know the terminology, it's okay, you'll learn later, but if you do know it and you've used it, then mark it down.
And this is really important, because this is basically going to be... well, this is what we'll go through here.
Yeah, and don't worry about the word salad again like this, there's going to be a lot
of these terms and we'll try to explain them when we go, like when we encounter them.
But yeah, there's going to be some of these words that especially like we already encountered
yesterday the bash batch kind of a thing where you basically have to have a keen ear to differentiate
the different technologies, like which is a Bash shell and which is a Bash script,
especially depending on pronunciation, they can sound pretty much the same. We have some
similar kind of stuff happening today with MPI and MP. Don't get worried about it. If
something is unclear, just ask in the notes and we'll try to clarify the thoughts.
Okay, and the last question, which task,
not computing related,
has involved the most number of synchronized people
working on the same things?
So it could be, for example,
like what's the typical thing?
These Olympic opening ceremonies or something
where the countries try to get the most number of dancers
just to put on a show,
or it could be a sporting event,
or what else involves a lot of synchronized people?
There have been these shows, I think in Italy at least,
where people are playing, like hundreds of people
are playing like instruments together,
like guitars or drums and rocking together,
like a thousand people playing electric guitar
at the same time.
I think this summer there's going to be like a bass
playing this kind of like show in Helsinki center that will involve like hundreds of
bassists playing together with the same song so. Yeah there's an interesting comment there
street fighting with the police I hope that was well I hope that's a joke and not actual protest
in some country where that happens.
Or maybe it's like a football activity or something like that.
Ah, yeah. Is football hooliganism considered synchronized though?
That's a good question, yeah.
But anyway, yeah, protests are probably the most synchronized things I would imagine.
I mean, I guess there's different kinds of synchronized, for example, a protest is people
are working towards the same thing, but there's usually not a central leadership managing
every little operation. Maybe getting people in one place, but it's separate. While some
things like these Olympic Opening Ceremony would be... what's it called? Olympic Opening
Ceremony. This is very strongly synchronized probably with a single leader that is guiding
everyone like an orchestra so there's clearly one leader and everyone sees
this person and is following their cues. Oh army is a good one yeah some big
military exercises involve huge numbers of people and all kinds of complex
logistics. Okay now the hard part try to make a metaphor of these tasks to the
different parallel programming styles.
I didn't think that far ahead.
Like, I think, yeah, like, all of these are, like, some of them
are more in sync than others.
For example, like dancing, I would say is probably the most
in sync out of these.
And some of them are like just individuals doing stuff, but at
same time. So some of these, like we're going to be talking
about different methods of parallelization in the cluster
environment. And some of these are more synchronous, and some
of them aren't. And in many cases, probably throughout your
your work where you will encounter situations where
you're basically like middle manager for computer programs.
So instead of like, like, you need to manage all of these
different workers that try to do stuff for you. So basically you have your own small
virtual office of workers and you try to like keep them in check and then there's always one
of these programs that doesn't work correctly or something. You need to waste a lot of time
trying to get it working. So we'll talk about many of these things throughout the day.
I wish I could think of this metaphor to what we're going to talk about, but it's okay.
Technoparty, yeah, there you've got some music playing which everyone's going for, or like
dancing to it at the same time.
Yeah.
Well, should we begin?
Yeah, sure.
So are you going to play it to my screen or?
Sure.
Do you give a start of, do you start off with the day's intro?
It's going to your screen now.
You can do it.
OK.
Maybe I'll, I'm coming to my screen then.
Hey, it worked.
OK.
So yeah, we are beginning day three.
And as you see from the schedule,
it's all about Parallel.
We start with a big picture here.
And then we go to the different forms of Parallelism.
We have a brief intermission where
The CSC comes and gives a talk about their services.
And then we talk about GPUs.
And as usual, there's an Ask Us Anything session where we expect lots of good questions.
So the hardest part about today isn't so much the commands we learn, which are similar,
knowing what to use and how they fit with the programs.
So one thing I've often seen there's some program it says it runs parallel
but it's not clear about how it runs parallel and thus isn't clear how to
run a parallel on our cluster. And that's the most important thing
we can say and what we'll focus on. And of course as every day
there's a lot of different...
well we give a summary but you need to read yourself.
So with that said, I guess we go to what does parallel mean? And I push it to [name]'s screen.
There we go. So, hello. [name], parallel computing, what does it mean?