Okay. Are we done with GPU? Should we go to the Ask Us Anything and then we can also answer
more GPU questions? Or is there anything else from this page?
Yeah, I think we are good, I would say.
A huge number of the questions in our daily grad session
are about getting GPU stuff to work.
So if you can't get it, it's okay.
Just come and ask, it's normal.
And if you're interested about this,
we have a course on Python for Scientific Computing
where I've given at least talk about how to use Conda.
So the talks are in Code Refinery, I think,
Code Refinery YouTube.
And the materials are in our webpage.
You can get a link there
or in the Code Refinery page as well.
And they're like, we try to go through the process
of how do you like get the corresponding
like toolkits and stuff and that sort of stuff.
Yeah.
Okay. I'm going to switch to the notes then.
And hit auto-scroll.
Whoever has the dependency thing at the bottom of the screen, can you move it?
Because then auto-scroll doesn't work.
Yeah, there's a question there.
Can a metaphor be made for the pasta example?
for example, Conda, TensorFlow, PyTorch, et cetera.
Oh, and we can somewhat add a new section for Q&A
and maybe the feedback stuff.
My hands are a bit full.
And as you know, cat is the most important thing.
Post example, TensorFlow, PyTorch, CUDA.
That's like, I would say that, yeah.
I mean, TensorFlow is a library that helps you to use the, um,
chicken cooker because it's a lot harder than a chicken cooker to use.
And almost no one goes and tries to use the chicken cooker directly.
Yeah.
I would say that, like, maybe, maybe there, it would be something like,
Like, if you think about, you want to cook the chickens in the GPU, right?
And you don't want, you want somebody to probably, like, prepare them beforehand, like butcher
them and that sort of stuff.
So basically, like, the CUDA toolkit is the person in the store that makes certain that
the chickens are, like, prepared so that you can just buy the, like, the chicken in a way
that you can just like safely cook it and it's not like, it doesn't have a skin and everything on it
and that sort of stuff. So basically like it's an intermediate layer that makes it so that
like you can do the hard stuff on that underneath it. Yeah.
But yeah, go ahead and please tell us, like, all the questions about anything from today.
Yeah.
And also, yeah, like, we might have guests joining us, like, other RCs and other people
from us.
Yeah.
Any of the staff that are around.
You should know where to get the studio info out, you don't need to do that.
Yeah, but for the
Basically, like with the GPUs, it has moved, like the thing has moved rapidly throughout
the years.
Hi [name].
Hey.
So, it used to be that GPUs were like, the only way of coding GPUs used to be that you
write the CUDA code.
So, basically you write C or C++ code and then you compile that and use that CUDA toolkit
to like to use that and then of course people didn't find this like very nice in the long term
like they wanted to do something else on that so they created like many frameworks that that make
it possible to do this kind of like stuff so that you don't have to write the C code the low-level
code so then once you get that into that part you still need to compile against this like
low-level code. So what they do is they compile against this low-level code, but then you run
into problems. Okay, you need the dependencies for this low-level code. They need to be solved.
So, okay, how do you manage that? And then it's like, okay, you need to have these packaging
managers to manage the whole environment. And what I usually think about is that,
okay, what is the version of, let's say, PyTorch I want to install? And then let the guards of the
packaging managers decide what versions of CUDA toolkit I get. The person who decided this thing
was some guy in GitHub who made the pull request or made the build for a specific version of PyTorch.
Some guy in an open source community, most of these are nowadays installed from conda forge,
which is this open source community. Some guy who's interested about this, or maybe is hired to
do this, decided that, okay, I will build my PyTorch with these versions, and then they decided
for me which version of the CUDA toolkit needed to be used, and I will trust them to get the correct
version. I try to give an answer to that rule of thumb whether to use
GPUs or just the other CPUs. Personally, if whatever, well, if there are tools around that
support GPUs, go for them. Why not? You can see how long it takes and at some point
essentially make the decision is it worth waiting for the cpu for the gpu resources or is it worth
waiting for a long time to get the to get your results commonly the gpus are quite a substantial
bit faster but i personally would not start writing gpu specific code if if i'm not really
pressed for time. So, if I need to really start writing GPU-specific code,
yeah, I would need to have a good incentive as in my calculations take weeks and then,
okay, well, maybe it's better to think about whether GPUs could speed this up.
Yeah, and often the first question I would ask myself is that, okay, the scientific problem
that I have in hand, what toolkits and what things are there that solve this scientific
problem?
So, for example, I already mentioned, let's say, Python does NumPy, the numerical library.
uses these libraries called BLAST libraries and FFT libraries that are already existing solutions
for solving linear algebra problems, and they are underneath the whole thing very heavily.
If somebody has already created a library, reusing that library is a very good idea.
Basically, if I would want to do, let's say, machine learning, traditional machine learning,
I wouldn't create my own machine learning framework. I would use something like Scikit Learn
that is already existing and I would just extend on that or maybe PyTorch or something like that
if I want to do. If that's my goal. If I need to start from scratch then the question
like it's like creating a completely new code that doesn't have an existing like mathematical
solver for that. I still would try to look for existing mathematical solvers because
I don't trust that my matrix multiplication code is better than what the last people.
They have done it for 20 years or 30 years or even more. They have optimized it for different
kinds of systems and edge cases and for mathematical rigor. I don't trust myself to do that sort
So, I would trust to use as much as possible from people that have already done existing
libraries.
And if those support GPUs, then it's more for me, but I completely agree.
I think there are a few occasions where the worst product in basic libraries has gotten
more popular than the better one.
The only reasons, well, there are two reasons why that happens from time to time.
is that the worse speed wise one is way easier to use. So usability is a big factor also in coding.
If I have an obscure, extremely fast solver for something, then people might not use it because
it's just too difficult and people can't really be bothered to handle that and the speed up is not
or the speedup is not big enough, or where this unfortunately also has happened, but that's not
so often on open source things, where one site got better publicity. So it kind of got into the
market earlier and essentially covered the market with their product. And also with the GPU stuff,
I would mention that throughout the years, there's been a lot of this kind of situation,
because the field is still like now it's there's already like established solutions for many things
but the field is still moving so rapidly that like instructions on let's say how do you replicate
my results how do you replicate this environment like they can be like very hard to follow even
half year like after the publication. I submitted for one paper that was published like
like last spring, there was published paper
and one of our users wanted to replicate it
and the instructions were already like broken
even though it was like published like a half year earlier.
So, because the field is moving so fast,
so there's this kind of like additional,
additional, how could I say it,
like need for maintenance when it comes to these
it comes to these more cutting-edge technologies. Some of these MPI codes that have been running
since the 90s, you can see in the webpages, they don't have a pressing need to update necessarily
the installation instructions because the technology is so well orchestrated and already
existing but for many of these GPU codes you need to do a lot more like these kinds of usability
maintenance in order to make it replicable by other researchers as well. But it's
of course it's great technology for many cases but you really need to
you need to know if it's worth the effort and the hassle.
Come on, please ask us more questions. We're here. Unless everyone just wants to leave
early. But please give feedback. I see there's about 50 people watching now, and there's
not 50 answers here. Also maybe people could answer in the feedback why would
you not attend this course? So in the past few years the number of attendees
has been going down so of course that could be because all the materials
online and people don't need to attend which is actually a success but we would
just like your feedback, is this, let's see, this is like,
this would be good for us to know, is the material good
enough? We don't need to be here teaching anymore. Do you value
us taking the time to go through it? Do you value the videos
we're making? Are the videos good enough to replace them?
Yeah. And also like what form of like training do you prefer?
do you prefer reading the manuals? Do you prefer like watching videos? Do you prefer these kind of
like live courses where we were like, do you have like averaged talk through of the manuals,
basically? There's a question about, yeah, what kind of, what to do or when to come to Garage
and how much time to spend before.
Personally, I would say
if you have kind of
used the search function on our docs
and didn't immediately find a solution
for your problem, drop by.
That's, I think, or
if you have spent like 10-15 minutes
googling and you didn't find anything useful
Yeah, drop by. That's perfectly fine.
Yeah, the garages, like there was a question, are they similar to these Zoom sessions?
Yeah, it's basically like we are talking with each other about like what we are doing, like
having internal discussions and when the customer drops in, we stop that and then we
ask what the customer wants. And then we try to like,
usually we go into a breakout room and then somebody tries to help you with the problem.
It's very informal and we try to keep it that way.
I think the point with the garage sessions and attending there or coming there and asking
is we might, if it's something that we think, okay, this is already on the documents and
we have the impression we have talked about it for, I don't know how many times, we might
point you to a video or to the resources that are available, but that's perfectly fine.
Yeah, like if you can't find it. Coming in is perfectly fine.
Yeah, like if you can't find it and you come and say hey iSearch is there a
page on this and then we tell you that okay I'll
come back later. Like sometimes people come and go
several times in a day or in the hour as they try to
work themselves some.
Yeah and the overall like the goal of the thing is
to help you do stuff right.
And whatever makes it easier for you to do stuff is, like, if we can help you, that's our top
profile. So that helps keep us employed if we have people to help. So like, yeah.
So in the long term, where do you think scientific computing is going? Will HPC
clusters still be around in 10 years or is there some other solution coming up?
Or is that it really went with a with a simple question to answer yeah like i i think personally
like like there's always going to be like the more the technologies move forward like let's say
for example what has happened with the chat gpt and that sort of stuff there's always going to be
Like the more, the easier stuff gets,
like let's say by PyTorch, like also,
like when we create an interface
that makes it easier to access, let's say GPUs,
or in the case of ChatGPT,
you make it easier to use large language models.
You create more demand for that thing, right?
Like there's more people suddenly starting to use that.
And if you have more people using,
like demanding this thing,
it creates more demand on this lower end side
or the hardware and setting this up.
How does this actually work?
How do we manage this demand?
How can we do this kind of thing?
And underneath all of it,
there's going to be either like a cloud service
or high performance computing service.
But I think anyways,
there's going to be something at the bottom
that is going to require low level stuff.
And knowing about the whole, like the whole onion, like what's at the surface and what's
at the deep end is still going to be important because it makes you, makes it easier to navigate
the whole thing.
What is the eventual queue system?
Is it, is the queue system like Slurm or in the cloud infrastructure, is it Kubernetes
or something?
That doesn't really matter.
As long as you know, like that, okay, there's going to be some sort of a queue and some
sort of an account and I need to run my code in some sort of, let's say, virtual machine
or node or something.
As long as you know how the sausage is made, it makes your life easier.
I think that won't go away ever.
Maybe there will be more of these bigger systems, but I think there's still going to be these
systems.
I would like to also add to the question, is it an appropriate question?
I think the only questions where I would think a bit like, shouldn't you answer that question
is if it's really the research question you have in mind.
We can help you with expertise that we have, and we might actually have someone who has
worked in the field because most of us are originally researchers, but we are not the
people to solve your research question. We can try to help you find the right tools to
solve it, but in the end, you are the expert of your field, so you might need to explain
to us what you're actually doing and what you're actually trying to achieve so that
we can give a suggestion on, okay, this might be a good approach to do that.
But that's kind of, I think, for me, at least the limit of where questions start to not
make a lot of sense anymore for me.
Because if someone comes in with a question about a very, very specific niche concept
of their research field, yeah, it might take quite a bit of time to me to just get what
they are talking about.
Yeah.
There's also a good question about, I completely agree on [name]' answer on the previous one.
There's a good question of what's the difference between Mamba and Konda.
basically Mamba, like we nowadays recommend Mamba instead of Conda for most things. So Conda is this
packaging manager that was originally developed by this Anaconda Incorporated. It used to be
Continuum Analytics, the firm. They basically created this kind of like, okay, let's make
installing these data science environments, like virtual environments easier. Because like
the many Python packages, they depend on these libraries, like, for example, CUDA toolkits and
that sort of stuff. And installing them via peep can sometimes be quite complicated. So,
they created this kind of like packaging manager that can do this. And it, like, got popular.
And then people created this CondaForge, this kind of like distribution channel that people
can distribute basically like a Linux operating system to wherever Linux system you run. So,
you can get very reproducible, well, somewhat reproducible environments in all kinds of
different kinds of computation systems. And for that, they use some packaging manager called
Conda. And this Conda was originally written in Python, and it contains this kind of like
SAT solver that tries to solve these environments, like, okay, I want these packages,
I want these versions. And that was pretty slow. So what people did is that they did what I
mentioned previously. They used already existing low-level SAT solvers that had been created.
And on top of that, they rewrote basically Conda functionality in C++ for Mamba. It might be Go
nowadays. I'm not certain. I think it's C still. But anyway, some low-level code that
rewrote basically the Conda packaging manager. And it's much more faster than Conda when
it solves the environments because it uses these low-level SAT solvers to solve how do
these packages want to. These packets need these packets, these packets need these packets.
solves the environment for you.
Yeah.
It comes down a little bit to the different programming
languages are there for different purposes.
And the additional, if you try to stay
within one of the languages, you might
get stuck with potentially the disadvantages of it.
And Python has done a really good job
in essentially incorporating other languages and making use of other languages being really fast
while python being really convenient so you have things yeah you have things like what [name]
mentioned earlier with numpy that's calling essentially c and other highly efficient
libraries if you would implement the same thing purely in python it would be pretty slow but since
you can just call other functionality, it's fast.
That's kind of the problem of conda here.
Yeah. Somebody creates a new fast thing,
like a low-level thing that is fast, and then somebody creates an interface
for that using some higher level, I mean, like easier to understand language and easier
to write language like Python.
And then people are like, okay, that looks nice.
I would want to use that.
How do I install that?
And then you first have installation instructions that are very cryptic, very technical.
And then somebody's like, okay, I would want this to be easier.
And then they create a packaging manager or something that installs it.
And now you have a packaging manager that does something really complicated, like you
start to have this kind of cascade.
And then there are, of course, alternatives, like, for example, Julia is quite popular
nowadays that does try to be fast and easy to use at the same time.
And there's different things.
But there's this kind of like, usually there's fancy new stuff that is hard to install.
And it's because it's hard to install, nobody can use it.
And when it becomes easier to install, more people start to use it.
And then it starts to get bigger and bigger and somebody figures out, okay, let's create
a new thing.
This old thing is too bloated or it has, it's too like, it's not nice anymore.
And then they create a new fast thing.
And then that's how the circle of software life or scientific software life basically
progresses.
Yeah.
And Python is always there on the background.
Like I like that thing, I will take that thing basically, like I will incorporate that into
my ecosystem.
And they're very good at doing that.
Yeah.
I'm a good Kraken.
Okay.
Yeah.
I take that and that.
give some comments on the overall future of your careers. So there is usually comments that our
courses are both too basic and too advanced. So here we see more people said too advanced, but
it's really hard to give a course that's both simple enough for everyone and advanced enough
for everyone. Because what we're doing here is built on so many layers. I think I've said this
before, but there's like this Linux command line that underlies everything, and then there's like
data storage which sort of fits in there, then there's the connecting to Triton, then there's
the Slurm, and then finally there's your program that you're actually trying to run on there.
And when you know all of these little things down below, using the cluster is not that hard.
But most people starting your career at a discourse, that's not the case.
So you might know little bits here and there, but most people don't know all of them.
And many don't know any very well, and that's okay.
So the point of this course has been to give a big overview that has something for everyone,
but most people do need to go follow up some.
But this also means don't get frustrated here.
There is a lot of new things to learn.
And maybe you want to learn it, maybe you don't.
You have a choice on where you'll go next.
Yeah, I would add to that that, yes,
like a lot of this complexity is like technical complexities that are like for historical reasons
so there's like or like there is a reason for that and that was done like 20 years ago and
something like that like there's lots of like because it's an incremental process when these
things happen so there's like lots huge amounts of like this kind of like okay why Mamba or
something. And then I will give a 10-minute explanation why it's that way. But you don't
necessarily need to know all of that. You can just go straight to the... What we try in this course
also, we try to cut to the chase and get to the actual meat of the subject. Like, okay,
it's not so complicated if you don't care about all of that baggage that comes in these technical
things. It's a good idea to usually look at or try to go through the things and try to cut through
the technicalities and get to the actual, okay, what is the thing that I need to focus here?
Of course, it's complicated when there's so much stuff coming. This course probably is
overwhelming for many people and that's unfortunate because it would be better if the
subjects wouldn't be that overwhelming. We try to still give a condensed
version of the information but there's so much information but don't get
overwhelmed. Try to check what is important to you and your case and
Just use that information for your benefit.
Okay, let's see.
There's the question about using on-demand on Jupyter
and whether things are closing automatically.
At least for Jupyter, if you click on, I think it's shutdown, so file shutdown,
the job will be finished, so the job will stop.
If you just close the tab, the job is still run,
and you can essentially manually delete it
in the interactive sessions tab.
And delete there just means that it calls sCancel,
so it cancels the job.
So it looks bad, like, oh, do I want to delete stuff?
like what will happen, but actually it's a Slack cancels the job, so it's a bit more like, yeah.
And yes, if you click on delete while you still have the Jupyter tab open,
the Jupyter tab will essentially disconnect as well.
yeah
for advanced courses that's probably other people oh there was follow-ups
that I had started writing here what would you recommend people to do next
then we can end we have a page Python environment with conda on SciComp Aalto
I think the path is... I think this is the right path for it. But yeah, this tells
you a lot about installing your own software in Python. We have two other big
workshops that are also livestreamed. There's Code Refinery, which is more sort
version control software testing, like software development, tools for researchers, and a Python
for scientific computing. Of course, that's also live stream. Through Code Refinery, you can find
other workshops, which are by our partners. And while CSC has the big training calendars with
all kinds of advanced things. But for particular pages of SciComp Aalto fee, people should know
for Aalto usage. Is there anything else that we really have to do?
What I would just suggest for people is that repetition just makes better. Don't worry
about it too much about using the cluster. And there's never really a good time to learn new
skills, right? There's always stuff to do. You have a next deadline or next thing to write.
So at some point, every one of us has to bite the bullet and just start using a new thing.
We just have to start. If we want to use a new thing, we don't have to use new things. I still
use the Veeam, for example, when VS Code exists. We get drawn into our own habits, but if you really
want to use a new thing, the best way to use it is just to try using it as much as possible.
In the cluster, you shouldn't be able to do anything that hurts anybody else, except maybe
reserve resources that somebody else might use, but it's not a big thing. So just try using it,
and if you run into problems, then contact us. Yeah.
Okay, should we say goodbye? And hopefully you can use this later and you know how to
find this if there's more. Any final words?
I guess not. Okay, thanks a lot, [name]. Yeah, thanks for attending. Yes, thank you.
Bye. Bye.