Yeah. Okay. Yeah. And for the next two, do we give a
very high-level overview, but
we don't do as many examples? Yeah, yeah. Like, we will run
through some examples, but yeah, so we won't necessarily, because these are very dependent
on your program, so we don't necessarily like, it's very hard to do like a good example because
it depends on what program you're using, but we can demonstrate how the queue thinks about
these things. So the array job, like if we think about the array job that we just had,
But we are running basically the same serial job, but we're just running with more of those.
We are running more of those simultaneously and separately of each other.
But all of those will, like, let's say if we run one of those and that takes like an
hour to run, the other ones will also most likely take an hour to run as well if they're
quite similar jobs.
But in many cases, you would want it to run faster.
You want it to actually finish faster.
And in that case, you might want to try to use multiple processors to make it run faster.
And the first question here is that, can your program actually do it?
Does your program support multiple processors so that it can internally run faster?
If we look at the picture below, again, we see that in the shared memory jobs,
we get for the one single job, and I mean, again, let's focus, let's put the array idea that we had
and put that in the back of our mind, but let's think about the serial job. We start one,
we submit one job first to the queue and in the shared memory job, we would want to give this one
job more resources. We wanted to give that to have access to multiple CPUs.
So in the array job, we had individual jobs that are completely independent and all of those were
running with one CPU. But in this case, we want to give like, okay, let's have one of these scripts
and let this script should be able to use multiple CPUs.
And it's very easy to ask for these resources.
So you can just give this dash dash CPUs per task
and then a number in this Sbatch comment.
Yes, and you can then reserve multiple CPUs for a job.
The question is that does your program actually use those, or can it use those?
In many cases, the program might recognize that there's multiple processes there, and
in some cases it doesn't.
What is usually important in your program, if you see something like nTasks or nProcs
or nCPUs, or CPUs, or processors, something like this,
like a flag that tells that, OK, this can be run in parallel.
What you usually want to do is you
want this number that the process,
like what the program takes in, to be
equal to the number of processors
you have requested from the queue.
And this doesn't happen automatically all the time.
Yes, it doesn't because the program doesn't know where it's being run. The program doesn't
understand that it's in a computer cluster. It's being run in this allocation of, let's say,
four CPUs. The program doesn't necessarily know that, okay, I've been given four CPUs,
And it might see that there's like 40 CPUs or 100 CPUs in the machine.
And it might think that, hey, I can go full ham and I can take all of these CPUs.
But in reality, it's only been given four.
So you might get completely overloaded by having the program at start like 100 processes on those four CPUs.
So, what you usually want to do is you want to check your program, where your program
takes the value of how much parallelism I should use, how much parallelism I should do, and
then make certain that that number matches the request that's in there.
I think I remember some mention of this at the bottom of the page.
Should we look there now, or maybe come back to it after we've seen it?
We can maybe come back to it, but maybe we should just, like, this is too theoretical,
So run something and see if it's faster.
OK.
So I'll scroll down some.
Where's an example?
Here's an example.
Running an example shared memory program.
Yeah.
So the program here is the same Py Script
that we have used as an example.
And it has this flag called dash dash nprocs.
So how many procs?
like it uses Python multiprocessing to start
do the calculation in parallel and any if you give it the number then
it will use multiple processors yeah okay so
let's try running this example over here
so cpus per task equals two so i tell it two processors
Yes. And then, yeah, and the usual suspects like the memory and time and then we call it
and then the number of processes. And do note that now [name] is putting the numbers to be
like the same on like the number of CPUs per task and the number of processors.
Because it's the same over here.
So let's try running it.
Okay.
Oh, here it says using two processes.
I guess that's the program printing that out.
Yeah.
It knows that it now needs to use multiple processes.
So maybe let's try it out.
Can you put time at the start of the call?
Okay.
In Linux, there's this program called time that you can put, if you put it before the Srun.
Should I do it before Python?
Yeah, before that.
Yeah, that's good.
So what the time does is that it will give some like timing information,
like how long did the program execution take.
Let's try it out and see how long it took.
0.91 seconds, user.
or?
Maybe we should add a 0 there into the number of.
OK.
So now we're running 10 times more.
Yeah.
Processes.
So it says 8.7 seconds user time and 4.4 seconds elapsed.
So it did go about twice as fast.
Yes.
We also note that time also produces this 198% CPU.
OK, yeah.
So we can also use the seff that we previously yesterday
talked about to see the utilization.
So if you use the seff and the job ID,
we can quickly check that the utilization, what was it?
So nine seconds.
Here it says only 112.
Yeah.
It might be that maybe it didn't have time to,
because it's so short, maybe it didn't have time
to measure it correctly.
Yeah, probably.
Probably, if that is the case.
Yeah.
So it wasn't that bad, right?
Yeah, I mean, that's not easy.
What happens if I don't give the nprocs here?
Let's try it out.
So if you run it like that without the nprocs.
I remove nprocs.
So it most likely will take about 16 seconds.
So I would assume if the previous one was eight.
So it took, it used 8.4 seconds of CPU
and took 8.5.
So basically, it only ran on one CPU.
And everything, we wasted one CPU.
What happens if I use four CPUs, or I request four CPUs?
Or I go like this.
So I'm telling the program to use more CPUs.
put something bigger there, put something like 32 or something
so that we see an actual thing there.
So now we are overbooking, basically, the CPUs.
We have only requested two CPUs, but we
are running 32 processors there.
So you notice that it didn't run any faster or any slower here.
Yeah. So you notice that it runs at the same speed basically as if it would have two CPUs.
But the difference is, like this is a toy program. If the program would do something
like really complicated, it would slow down the program because it's oversubscribing.
It definitely can slow down.
Yeah. There's a good question in the notes that,
But what is the difference and benefit of allocating multiple CPUs for a single program
against allocating multiple arrays or like I assume like multiple jobs in an array?
And that's an excellent question because like it raises the question that which is better?
Like is it better to run one program twice as fast, but run it like multiple?
Like is it better to run one program twice as fast for double the parameters or is it
better to run two individual programs with different parameters?
So basically, is it better to divide the program among parameters or just run it as fast as
possible but then go through multiple parameters?
And usually the case is that it's usually easier to do the embarrassingly parallel route.
If you want to do maximum throughput or you want to do maximum amount of jobs, maximum
amount of parameters and whatever, it's usually better to use small jobs than big jobs.
So does it depend on the scaling?
So in here, this program is actually under the hood,
basically embarrassingly parallel.
It divides it up.
Each one runs separately.
But some jobs get slower the more processors you add to it.
So in that case, it's better to not use too many
and use arrays instead.
And I guess you can combine both of them at the same time.
Yeah.
The thing that you get with running with multiple processors is that if your program takes a
long time to run, let's say it takes 10 hours to run, you want the results today, not in
10 hours.
When you submit a job, you want them to be done so that you can look at them earlier.
And in that case, if your program can be parallelized, it's possible to maybe get them faster.
results and you can view them faster. And also if the program is big enough that it just
would take way too much time to run. It's good to parallelize it then. It's like the whole point
of the cluster to get stuff done faster, I guess. Yeah. Okay, yeah. So, should we continue
you scrolling down, or is there anything else here?
Tell me when to stop.
Common special cases.
Let's look at the example of the submission script,
how we would write it as a submission script.
Okay, yeah.
So, previously [name] ran the example
with the, from the, like an interactive job,
but we can also run this in, of course,
in a submission script, and that's
a better way of running it to write it into a CLI script.
Yeah.
So in this case, if you copy the script,
or modify the existing, yeah.
Modify.
The previous script wasn't a Pi example, though, so I will.
Yeah, maybe you want to do a completely new one.
OK.
I'll copy most of this over.
Yeah.
So.
So sbatch, so two per task.
Yeah.
And now, because we are running this in the script,
we can utilize the environment variable that Slurm sets.
So we can utilize this environment variable
called slurm CPUs per task, so that like slurm will fit when the code is being run,
that environment variable will contain, similar to what the array ID was, it will contain the
number of CPUs reserved for this program, so it will automatically fit that. This is very helpful
if you're running something and first you run it with, and you want to test out, for example,
scaling of the program, how well it behaves. If you run it with one CPU, if you run it with two
CPUs, four, eight, 16, so forth, it's usually a good idea to use this environment variable because
then you can easily test out different CPU numbers and you don't have to go into your
program code or something to change the number to match the request number. Yeah, okay, so let's
Submit it.
Submit, yes.
Do you think it will work?
The command.
Let's see.
If you look at the Slurm queue, it's probably run already.
It's running.
I added an extra zero there, so it would run a bit slower.
Yeah.
OK, yeah, it finished.
OK.
If we look at the output, I'll cat it.
Using two processes, yeah.
OK, should we seff?
Yeah, and also in the chat or in the notes,
there was a good question of, like,
I used the term processors and processors and like all of this million of words, like
the CPU, there's core, there's process, there's processor.
Sometimes there's thread or some and like all of these have their own like specific
different meaning, but they're basically like, like used in places like a synonyms in many
cases.
There are technical differences to all of these words, and the CPU and all of this.
You shouldn't necessarily worry about it.
The most important thing to note is that in the program, there's something that it can
do.
It can execute two programs at the same time within the same program, basically.
do that, it should have a place to run it, basically. If you go back to the pasta analogy,
instead of just cooking pasta in one pot, we are now cooking pasta in two pots or we're doing
two pots in two burners or stovetops. We just add more stuff there.
Yeah.
So yeah, like whatever term is used, like if the program developers, they will also
use all kinds of terms interchangeably all the time.
So don't worry about it too much.
And that's why I was saying that you should look for these various terms because you will
never know what is the term used by the developer.
They might talk about the process, they might talk about number of CPUs, number of processors,
of tasks, like number of jobs, like the terms might be different, but the important thing
is to know that, okay, these refer to, okay, how many processors or CPUs you want to use
and to match that with the number of CPUs that you request from the queue.
And for the queue, the important thing is the CPUs per task.
I run seff on this thing we just did? Sure. And it looks pretty much like before, so not perfect
efficiency, but it's so short that's expected. Yeah, and do note that here the CPU efficiency
refers to the size of the request, like the reservation. So the CPU efficiency is like
like, with respect to the amount of processors requested.
So 100% would mean that you're using all of the requested CPUs.
Yeah.
And I think you've said this before,
but the most important thing to me
is that this nprocs gets automatically detected
from Slurm.
So I only have to keep it up to date in one place,
which seems like it would save me a lot of time and effort and doing stuff wrong.
Yeah. Below, if we scroll a bit below, there's like this using Slurm CPUs per task efficiently.
And you can use this basically also for the array task ID. So here's a few examples on how you can
use this parameter.
So for example, in Python, like in the middle there,
you can use the OS module to get that environment variable.
So in this case, if the variable is set,
the value of that is converted into an integer.
If it's not set, the default value is now one.
Is one, yeah, OK.
So you can use this when in your program to like you can write this there so that it automatically
detects how many CPUs you're using and then you can use the end CPUs in your like to give it to
a library or something. Yeah and same to MATLAB. Okay yeah so basically programs so if programs
were well designed they would all use something like this to automatically detect number of
processors available.
Okay.
And this is, there is one
extra, like
I will add one extra
technical thing, like there is no standard
on how many CPUs you're going to be using.
The closest thing to a standard
that is used by many programs
is this so-called OMP
num threads. It's mentioned
above
there in the multi-threaded
versus multiprocess and double-booking section, but you can read the whole thing if you want.
Here's the technical stuff if you're interested, but the important thing is that many programs,
for example, like NumPy libraries in Python, they utilize internal parallelism already,
and it's done using this technology called OpenMP, open multiprocessing.
And that basically takes this variable, this OMP non-threads that describes how many processors
it should use.
And this is used in many programs.
Many programs use this as this kind of shorthand for how many processors you should use for
the parallelism.
So this is quite common for programs that don't even use OpenMP to do the parallelism.
So this is the only standard that is basically defined, otherwise it's like a wild west that
everybody uses their different environment variables for how many processors to use.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, we have three minutes before we need to go to a break.
What should we do?
I propose we can see if there's any further questions,
go to the break.
We can quickly discuss the MPI parallelism along with GPUs.
So does that sound good?
Yeah.
OK.
Yeah, so let's see.
What else is there?
I think [name] already answered the processes
versus processors.
So if you want to go deep into the computer architecture,
you can learn all kinds of things
about how Unix systems handle processes and threads
and things like that.
But for the most part, if you know
the options that are present in this page,
you can figure out how to run something,
and then you don't need to know more.
You're probably here because you want to do
science stuff and not learn about computer architecture.
I will quickly mention that a common thing that
happens to many researchers is that,
let's say you run a code in your laptop,
And your laptop, like I mentioned previously, they nowadays have multiple processors there.
And in many cases, if you run this code that can do multiprocessing internally,
it can do something with parallel, without you noticing, basically. You don't even notice.
The Zoom that I'm using now, it's doing something multiprocessing on the background.
I don't even know about it, but it's doing it to make certain that the video stream is correct.
and audio is processed correctly. It's doing multi-processing in the background.
And in my laptop, it just assumes that, okay, I can use whatever resources are available there.
And when people and resources go to the cluster where you need to actually request the resources,
the programs usually just think that, okay, they will look at the hardware that is there.
they see a server with 128 CPUs. And maybe when in the job request,
you might forget to add the CPUs per task flag. So then when you run the code in the cluster,
it's suddenly much slower. It suddenly takes four times as much time or eight times as much time.
And then you might wonder, like, okay, what's going wrong?
Like, am I doing something wrong?
Because it's so much slower in the computing cluster.
Maybe the computing cluster is a pile of crap and I don't want to use that.
But the reality is that the program doesn't necessarily know about what number of processors
it should use.
And also, the program doesn't have access to all of those processors, because those
are being reserved by other jobs in the queue. So when you're running a program in the cluster,
it's usually a good idea to just run it with multiple CPUs per task and see how it goes.
And you can also look at your own task manager in your own laptop and see how many processes,
do you see the processes being used while I run my code? And just decipher, does it use some
Multiprocessing.
Yeah.
OK, so we need to go to the break
so we don't get too far behind.
So break until one minute past the hour.
And then we have to talk on CSC resources.
So see you soon.
Bye.