Hello, we are back for the last little bit.
So GPUs.
So I can say I'm a person that hasn't used GPUs very much.
So my main questions from the next sections would be, if I have code that already uses
GPU, what options in Slurm do I need?
How do I monitor their performance?
And what do I need in my own software or Python environments or whatever in order to use these?
So do you think we can go over that?
Yeah, I think that's a great task list for this session.
Do you want to throw into my screen and maybe I can...
Sure. Here we go. Okay, there you go.
Yeah, so TPUs, this is like a topic with lots of interest and lots of things to cover,
But hopefully, we can get through the most important things in this session.
So what are TPUs? We already talked about it. They're basically the chicken skewers of the
massive parallel processors that do one thing very good. And the one thing that they do good
is the matrix multiplication and that sort of stuff.
So they do that very well.
And that's why they're used in all kinds of codes
from physics to deep learning and that sort of stuff.
And everybody wants to use them because they make stuff
go room, basically.
So when we want the GPUs, how Slurm thinks about them,
how Slurm knows about them, it knows about them
in these so-called generic resources.
So you need to specifically request for these resources.
There's two ways you can do to request these resources.
The old way is the dash-dash-gress GPU one,
but the newer way is this dash-dash-GPUs equal one.
The newer way, if it's supported, I would personally use that because it also allows
you to, like, if you need to do multi-GPU stuff and that sort of stuff later on, there's
other flags that you can use to make it so that you can, like, allocate certain number
of CPUs per GPU and that sort of stuff.
You can make certain that your job gets the correct kind of an allocation.
So the newer method has more, like, leeway on that.
both work so you can use whichever one you want to use. Some clusters have the
GPUs in a separate partition so you might need to
ask for a separate partition.
So basically just like processors and memory Slurm tracks it
and look up your own clusters info for how to request it
and then you got it. Okay that's pretty easy.
Yeah, and when Slurm allocates the job,
it basically makes certain that, OK, you get access to it
and nobody else gets access to it.
So then you will get access to the GPU.
In our cluster, there's also this debug partition
that you can use to debug short jobs, which is very nice.
If you want to do a small debug, run, see that your code runs,
and then just stop it, and then put the actual run going.
Because the GPUs are very popular,
or sometimes there's a lot of people in the queue.
And yeah, let's jump right in and let's start dealing with the actual problems of the GPU
computing or the actual things where you need to, what you need to think about.
So the first thing you need to think about is that the GPUs, like you cannot simply
like talk with the GPU, like you do it,
like you cannot write a normal program with them.
You need to discuss with the GPU
because it's just like a specialized hardware.
Okay.
You need to use this thing called CUDA toolkit
to discuss with that.
So like, because there's so many different like hardware,
there's different kinds of GPUs
and nobody wants to write to a specific like CPU
or GPU architecture.
Like you don't want to write the machine code
only for like certain GPU architecture, what the people at NVIDIA have created and which is
probably the best product, like even more important I would say maybe than the actual hardware
is this kind of like development kit called CUDA, like CUDA development kit that basically
and handle whatever GPU you have underneath it. The CUDA development kit is this kind of
thing that makes it possible for your code to discuss with the GPU. If you have a program
that is like low-level program, you need to compile your code for the GPU.
Okay. So here's an example of a, like, so, so is this like, there's the driver on the
node itself, but depending on what GPU you're using, there may be different driver versions.
So the toolkit translates your program to what's needed for this particular model of
GPU with these particular driver versions.
Yeah. Well, maybe I'll show this picture already.
Okay.
So there's a picture of how the thing actually works.
So what there is in the machine,
you have the GPU connected to the motherboard of the machine.
In the operating system,
there's this CUDA driver.
This CUDA driver can then discuss with the GPU,
but you don't want to code your code for this CUDA driver
because the driver might be updated, right?
Like [name] said, it might be updated,
it might be different.
The GPU underneath is different.
Like if you go into a different computer,
it might be a different GPU.
So you don't want to lock yourself
only to the specific hardware configuration that you have,
a hardware and operating system configuration you want.
So what the programs usually do,
like for example, PyTorch or something,
They don't actually talk with the driver that much.
They don't deal with that.
They actually are written with respect
to the CUDA libraries, so libraries
like Kublas and QFT that implement
certain mathematical operations that run on GPUs,
and then the runtime library that
can be called to, let's say, give information,
is there a GPU available.
So this topmost part is usually specific for your program.
So you have a program, and that program
needs to be compiled against a certain version of CUDA toolkit
usually.
And the driver can handle multiple different toolkits
and then handle the discussion between the program and the GP
basically.
and the CUDA toolkit and the GPM.
So if we look at the example, if we quickly go show it.
So in this example, we are dealing with quite low level
like CUDA code.
So for this, we need to compile it actually.
So for the compilation, I need to load certain modules.
So a compiler and a CUDA toolkit.
So this CUDA toolkit,
I'm now in the login node of the cluster, so this doesn't have a GPU available, but
I have a CUDA toolkit, so I can compile my code with respect to this CUDA toolkit, so
it's linking to that.
And because there's no GPU available, I need to tell my compilation that I need it to work
with different kinds of GPU architectures, so I need to give this kind of a monstrosity
of a command that, okay, build my code so that it runs on these different kinds of GPU
architectures.
So, this is the kind of stuff that usually happens, like, that somebody else has done
for you.
Usually, you don't have to, like, write these kinds of commands.
Yeah, that's a pretty crazy long line.
Yeah.
like you can, there's a link to article about this.
Well, what are these architectures?
That is great article that I always use as a reference,
like to check which GPUs these architectures,
like, well, what do they mean?
So now that we have the program,
like we have this compiled pi.gpu,
we can run it with the GPU.
So basically what I'm asking is one GPU
and then we can run it.
Okay, yeah.
And it's in the queue and it's done
and it's done basically instantaneously.
And because GPUs are so fast,
so this number is pretty similar
that we run with the CPUs.
So let's add like few zeros here.
Okay, yeah.
And let's run it with the GPU and it's basically done.
That's still instant, basically.
Yeah, it's basically like instant.
So this is like a lot faster than the Python code
that we previously run.
Like in order to get like actual some run time,
well, we need to add more zeros.
Yeah.
But this is a lot of work, right?
Like the compilation and that sort of like writing the code
as this kind of like C code and then writing the code,
like dealing with the CUDA.
And most of the programs that use GPUs don't do this.
they are built against a certain version of Huda Toolkit.
And then we just like...
Like they come from whoever else provides them.
They're built against a certain version.
Okay. Yeah.
Yes.
So let's say we have this now, this program.
The second question you asked at the start of this session
was how to do monitoring.
And in our cluster, there's this monitoring script
but because we did release an installation,
it currently doesn't work, but we will fix it.
But there's another way that you can do a monitoring,
which is like going to the compute node
while the job is running.
And this works with other jobs as well.
In different clusters,
you might have a different way of working on it.
I'll add a few zeros here so that it actually runs
a bit longer.
So, you notice that my job is now running, like I have an interactive job running.
I'll open a new terminal and I can use the Slurm queue to check which node it is running
in.
And while the job is running, I'm allowed to go there.
And what happens is that I'm basically going to the same reservation, so I'm using the
same resources.
So, if I start new programs, they are basically taking resources away from the program that
I'm currently running in the queue.
And in here, I can use this tool called NVIDIA SMI, which is provided by the driver, NVIDIA
driver.
And it will tell me the usage or the utilization.
So if I make this a bit bigger.
can see this sort of an output. What we see here is that the GPU name, we have a certain GPU name,
we have a GPU number, we have the power usage and that sort of stuff, we have a memory usage,
and then we have this GPU utilization. This basically means that is the GPU actually doing
something. And below here, we see the processes that are actually using the GPU. So this can be
used as this kind of like a measurement thing that you can go there and check is it actually
doing something. Yeah. So I see it says 100% usage here. Is that typical? Like do most people's GPU
drops hit 100%? No, no. For physics code and that sort of code, it can get to the 100% or close to
the 100%. But in many cases, the situation is that you don't necessarily reach the 100%.
And the reason for this is that quite often the GPUs need something to work on. So if you're
you're dealing with, let's say, a deep learning code,
if we look at this picture above here, this one.
The program memory RAM.
OK, yeah.
Yeah.
So in many cases, you have a situation
where your program, let's say a deep learning code,
it will need to parse a data set or process a data set that
then used for the deep learning process. And for this to happen, the CPU part of the program
usually needs to load data in and process that data and then send it to the GPU for the calculation.
And if the GPU doesn't have enough data, it will just idle and wait for the CPU to
process the data. So what can happen is that the GPU utilization gets low because the CPU part
hasn't done its job fast enough. So it's like, I think something you've said before, the GPU is so
fast it can, what's the thing, resource starvation. So the CPUs can't pump data into it fast enough to
Yeah.
Okay.
And that means that in many cases, like when using GPU code, the actual thing you're coding
is the left part of this program.
You're trying to get, let's say, a data loading system to work so that you get enough data
for the GPU.
And this also means that when you're going from, let's say, your workstation to working
on a cluster, you might encounter a situation where your code is slower again on the GPU.
And you might wonder what's happening. I thought these GPUs are really powerful,
why is it slower? And the reason isn't that the GPU is bad or slower. The reason is that the data
isn't close to the GPU. So often you need to copy, let's say, the data sets to the local
local drive in these machines.
So all of our GPU machines have a local SSD drive there,
so that you can use that as this kind of like a buffer
for your data, so that you can fill out the GPU fast enough.
Because otherwise the GPU will be starving and it won't
get enough data. And often you want to
also utilize this multi-CPU, like the shared memory
a parallelism thing where you have multiple data loaders feeding one GPU enough stuff.
And this is like a whole can of worms. But basically, nowadays, often GPU programming
isn't actually programming on the GPU. You have some existing library that uses GPU or framework,
like by torch and then you have you try to like make certain that the gpu has enough stuff to do
yeah so in the pasta metaphor but if we're in this restaurant we have the chicken cooker
and the chicken cooker can cook 20 chickens at once but we don't have enough chickens in our
restaurant so every time like oh we don't have enough and you send someone to the store to go
buy some and come back and put them on. But by the time they get back, they need even more. So,
okay, go to the store again and come back. And data transfer...
That's an excellent...
Yeah, that's excellent.
And compared to the speed of a processor, data transfer is slow, really slow.
I linked some slides up above that expanded on the kitchen metaphor,
and it was really surprising to me how slow the processing or the data transfer really is.
There's this adage in high-performance computing that computing is fast, but pipes are slow.
So basically, everything that needs to transfer data, that's the part where the stuff usually
gets slow. In the case of a GPU, the problem usually is that the slow part isn't the GPU
The slow part isn't the GPU memory or not even the transfer from the CPU memory to the
GPU part.
The slow part is outside of this picture, some hard drive or something that you need
to transfer stuff to the CPU memory.
And that's usually the bottleneck in this case situation.
There's also a great question in the chat of, do you need to separately reserve a memory
for the GPU?
The answer is no. You will get the whole GPU memory. Let's say I run here
GPUs 1, NVIDIA, SMI. I will just run the monitoring program.
.
So you notice that this run on a V100 with 16 gigabytes of memory.
So all of this VRAM in the GPU, it's for mine to use.
And so all of this memory here is mine for use, even though I didn't request CPU memory
that much.
So unlike the normal processor in one of our computers,
which can be shared by many things,
the GPU is always one GPU, one person, no sharing.
Yeah.
OK.
And also I will mention that quite often you still
need to reserve quite a bit of memory
because, for example, in order to load a large language
model or something, you need to first load it from the disk,
load it into the memory, and then give it to the GPU memory.
So you need to reserve enough memory so that the stuff can fit into the CPU's RAM before
it's transferred into the GPU's RAM.
And these memory considerations are quite important when it comes to these big models
or if you want to do large data processing, you need more and more memory.
And many of these large language models, for example, they might require so much memory
that they don't fit into one GPU. So, you have to use multiple GPUs to run those.
Yeah. Okay. I actually feel like I understand more than when I started, especially about the,
or mainly about the toolkit and the library things.
There's also one excellent question that, can you get an interactive session on a GPU? And the
Answer is in principle, yes, but I would highly recommend not doing that.
The first thing is that for the reason that the GPUs are very important for many calculations,
and they're very expensive, there's internal billing in Slurm that basically your priority
in the queue is determined by the resources you use. And because the GPUs are so important,
and the billing for the GPUs is higher.
So basically, if you use one hour of GPU interactively, you're basically using like 80 hours of CPU
time basically.
So there's this kind of like a billing factor there.
So it will lower your priority a lot.
And secondly, again, like if you're using it interactively, nobody else can use it.
So what I personally usually like to do is I write my stuff, then I run it with S run
or something like that and see how it performs.
And let's say I want to do like a deep learning training or something.
It's enough for me to know that the training starts to know that my code is correct.
And then I can like submit to a longer job.
Usually, if I want to just test it out, I can test out half an epoch or one epoch or
something like that and test out interactively this very short time and then actually submit
it for a longer time and not reserve it constantly because then my priority will suffer
and other people cannot use the GPUs. Okay.
Yeah.
So, was that all the most important things that I had said?
So, let's say there's some existing program, like a Python program, that uses GPUs, I want
to use PyTorch, so what do I need to do to make that work?
Yes, so this is the bane of many people's existence, that what actually happens, and
person in the chat was already discussing like they have a specific case where they want to use
TensorFlow and PyTorch. Both of these are these kind of like deep learning frameworks and some
extra packages on top of it and it's a lot of work to get that installed and getting that working
and that is a complicated thing to do and we have some pre-installed environments but they
they don't, of course, contain your custom packages.
And because it's so complicated,
usually we recommend that people
install their own environments.
In some sites, the recommended way
is to install these environments in containers.
For example, in CSC, the recommended way,
because all of these environments
can create millions of files,
and it can cause some problems.
But the recommended way, usually, is to use these, like...
So we, for example, recommend using Conda a lot, which is this kind of like framework
that can provide already installed, already compiled binaries for you easily.
And yeah, there's a question here.
So every time you want to use GPUs, you first need to load module load GCC CUDA.
But with Python are things you don't need to.
Yes.
Yes, so if you want to use GPUs and you want to compile yourself, you need to load the
development kit.
So basically these parts, this is provided by the module load CUDA.
It provides this part and then you can create your program with respect to these.
If you have an already existing program, let's say PyTorch or framework like PyTorch or TensorFlow,
what you want to do is that you want to install the program and you want that program to decide,
okay, I want the CUDA toolkit that I've been compiled against. Instead of going from bottom up,
you go from top to bottom. You first decide that, okay, I want PyTorch and what CUDA toolkit does
my PyTorch need. And then you let a packaging manager like Gonda decide which CUDA toolkit
fits with the PyTorch. So, you don't start with some, like, you don't basically force
the program to use a certain CUDA toolkit. You let the program decide what CUDA toolkit it needs.
So this is like the dependencies should be declared properly and then it works.
Okay.
Yeah.
So there's some instructions in our pages, in our like Conda page.
We have a separate page for how to use Conda in our cluster and how you can get the corresponding
CUDA toolkit.
If you are using these environments, you should not load the CUDA, because then you have doubled
the toolkits and now the programs don't know what they should be using and everything gets
like super complicated.
You should always have only one CUDA toolkit, either from the module system or provided
by the Conda installation.
There's also a question about MATLAB, and MATLAB is different because it does just-in-time
compilation, so it will use the modules, module CUDA.
What MATLAB does is that when you create your MATLAB GPU arrays, for example, it will just-in-time
compile these. When it needs them, it will compile a code that uses them when it's running,
so it will need the module system once. But this is a bit of a mess. There's so many different
ways of getting these toolkits and basically it means that whenever you want to install
PyTorch, you need to get like a few gigabytes of toolkits usually.
And this is currently the situation, but the reason behind this is that it's so much faster
to work with, let's say, a framework like PyTorch or TensorFlow or something and write
your code in this higher level language, like Python, instead of going to the C route and
writing everything against the CUDA toolkit.
Okay. Are we done with GPU? Should we go to the Ask Us Anything and then we can also answer