There we go. So, hello. [name], parallel computing, what does it mean?
Yeah, so like [name] said just previously, in many cases you might see a paper or something
where somebody says that, okay, we executed, or especially in a talk where people don't
have time to explain how they did a thing, they will say that, okay, we did a thing with
a massive parallel simulation and we got these results.
And then you're left wondering like, okay, how is it done actually behind it?
And in many cases, there are these different ways that you can do different things, but
they are not differentiated enough so that you can actually say simply that, okay, they
use these kinds of ways.
And there are multiple ways that you can do parallel computing.
And parallel computing in a nutshell is basically just like you run multiple processes at the
same time in some way that you can then get the results done faster. There are multiple ways of
doing this, like parallel calculations. You can either do them completely independently,
somewhat together, or you can do them completely in sync. We are going to be talking about these
different methods of parallelization throughout the session.
Right now, does anyone need to know what the methods are? Are we expecting any initial knowledge?
Not really. Not really. I would just say as a historical footnote,
If you were alive back in early 2000s or something around that time, there weren't really that
many parallel processors in any of the computers.
Most of the computing that was done, they were parallel clusters, of course, and vast
majority of those were using one of the parallelism methods that we are going to be talking about,
this MPI parallelism.
But around the year 2000, you might have heard about Moore's law that tells about the number
of transistors in a processor is going to double every two years.
Well, as the processors went smaller and smaller, suddenly at some point there was a situation
where there's not that much space anymore for the transistors.
What many processor manufacturers started to do is to add multiple processors into their computers,
like into the CPUs. So your phone might nowadays have like maybe eight processors,
and your laptop might have like eight or something like that as well.
So this change happened, but the programs didn't necessarily change. So this is kind of like
Like, lots of modern programs already are parallel, but lots of older ones might not
yet be.
And we'll see how these different methods happen.
So basically, you're saying that processors haven't gotten much more faster than 20 years
ago, but there's more of them.
So we have to be able to use more.
Yeah.
They have gotten faster, but at the same time, they haven't gotten as fast as, let's say,
from 60s to 80s or something like that.
But there are more of them, a lot more of them nowadays.
So if we look at the picture in the screen, we can see that basically in the compute cluster,
we of course have lots of processors.
So the Triton cluster has about 10,000 processors.
So yesterday we were talking what is a core, what is a CPU, well in the case of the computing
cluster, there are cores of individual CPUs, but it doesn't really matter.
You can just think of it like something that can do computations.
We have 10,000 things that can do computations.
And if you want to utilize them, we have to try to utilize them in parallel usually to
get the most out of the system.
So should we go through the different methods quickly?
OK, let's see.
Can you explain them to me?
Pretend I'm a new undergrad student
and don't know much about computers.
So in various linking parallel, what does that mean?
Yeah.
Yeah, let's look at the pretty picture about this.
So, in this picture, is each red box a single thing that's running?
Yes. So, if we think about the cluster that is compromised of different computers and
different CPUs, you can think of each of these blocks as, let's say, one core that can take one
job each. In the case of an array job, we have this kind of parallelism called an array job.
And what that means is that it's basically like a situation where if you want to do something
So if you want to do a thing, like let's say I want to cook spaghetti and then I want to cook a different kind of a pasta at the same time, I can do them separately in two different burners, like I don't necessarily have to, you know, I don't have to do the same thing over and over again.
I don't necessarily have to put them into the same pot or something like that.
So I have, so it's like I want to make five pots of pasta.
I can get five people and do it separately and that works perfectly.
Yes.
So if you have a thing that you can like split up in some way, let's say you have a simulation
and you have different parameters for that, you can embarrassingly parallel that or run
in an embarrassingly parallel way. There was another term that somebody used that was
easily parallelizable or something like that. That basically means that you can split it
in some natural way, the computation. You run a different experiment in a different calculation.
You can split it among different data sets, different models, something like that. Something
that is very easy to split up and what in the embarrassingly parallel way that utilizes these
array jobs you can like spread them out throughout the cluster or in different places and you don't
necessarily have to worry where they end up they just get done and the question is more about okay
how can you manage these jobs so that they can get to the queue how can you put all of your
different parameters into the queue. So in the picture here in below, you can see that,
let's say we have one of these array jobs that we would submit, some of them might get into
one computer and one could get into a different computer and they would be completely independent
of each other. And there was a great question in the notes that do they all have their own
copies of variables. And yes, they would all be independent. So, basically, there would be
something to differentiate them, like some sort of different task that they are supposed to do,
but they would all run completely independent of each other.
Yeah. Okay. I think I understand this. So, what's the next version?
Yeah. So the next version is this so-called shared memory parallelism.
So this is basically what your laptop is doing, like if you're running something.
So, for example, my Zoom that I'm talking to [name] and to you.
Right.
Utilizing most likely multiple processors on my computer to encode the video and do all kinds of stuff.
And what in the shared memory parallelism, what we do is that we have a process that runs on a computer.
And that computer, that process can like spawn multiple other processes and they can work together in the same computer.
And why is it called shared memory parallelism?
parallelism is that, well, they are physically in the same machine, like they are working
like the processes are in the same machine, so they can interact with each other through
the shared memory, the shared random access memory they have.
So in the image, in the top, you can see that in the shared memory parallelism, we want
all of the processes in the same physical machine so that they have access to that shared memory.
So that's like when someone in the note says do parallel runs all have their same copy of
the variables. So here they do all have the same copy because they access the same memory space.
Yes, of course they can have their own local variables. Each process can have their own
local variables. But the performance comes in the idea that, okay, they can share information
with each other and they can do a calculation together. So if you look at the picture at the
bottom, you might have a program, like a main program, and that main program might start
multiple processes that each work in a different CPU, and they communicate through the shared
memory. This is commonly used, for example, with Python multiprocessing. In R, if you're using
parallel. In MATLAB, if you're using parallel pool, those all utilize this sort of a parallelism
and various other technologies. One technology is this technology called OpenMP,
So open multiprocessing. And it's used in many kinds of libraries underneath many languages.
So for example, if you're using Python, there's this NumPy library that utilizes these OpenMP
parallelism to do these calculations automatically with multiple CPUs.
So I'm trying to think of the metaphor here. So now I have five people cooking pasta,
but they're in the same kitchen. And if we want to share the salt or something, I can put it down
on the counter and someone else can just pick it up and use it. So we all have the same workspace
or something like that. Yeah, that's a great analogy. Okay, so what's the next one?
Yeah, so the next one is this, what I already mentioned, this historically
used parallelism that is used especially in like the supercomputer kind of a thing,
supercomputer systems. And this is called message passing interface parallelism or MPI parallelism.
So if you have heard about MPI, this is the thing. So in the message passing interface
or MPI parallelism, you have a program that consists of multiple programs.
So basically, you start, let's say, a thousand copies of the same program on different computers.
And each of those programs knows that, okay, I'm a part of some greater whole.
I'm a part of this great MPI program, and I need to work together with my…
It's basically like an anthill, like everybody's working together for the common good.
In my pasta analogy, so now we can't directly share things, we have to communicate.
So is it like we have multiple cooks in different apartments, and if I make something that someone
else needs, someone has to get up there, go to the other place, knock on the door, say
say, okay, I made this for you, and they answer and receive it, and then we go back or something.
Yeah.
That would be a good analogy.
So what the MPI programs do is that when you start them up, they create this communication
layer so that they can like, they can share information through each other.
And they all like, usually what you would have is that, let's say one process would
have its own, let's say, simulation range or certain area of the simulation that they
would handle.
And what they would communicate to the other processes are the edge regions of that simulation
area.
So that they would do minimal amount of communication with each other, but they would do stuff collectively
to simulate, let's say, a weather model or something like that.
Okay yeah so like you divide it up into different domains like physical domains and each edge
condition can do things. Yeah. So what is MPI most often used for? It seems a bit harder to use or
program. Yes so it is much more complicated because the program usually needs to be designed
around the communication also like the algorithms that are used. It's quite often used in like
physics simulations. So, for example, like CP2K, GPAW, LAMMPS, OpenFOAM, many weather models,
like all weather models usually do that sort of stuff. And you usually need to build the program
around the communication layer. So, basically, you need to design your program to be an MPI program.
So compared to like the multi-processing thing or the shared memory parallelism
where the programs are usually like you can just like quite trivially usually
use them in different kinds of contexts, the MPI programs are usually like you need to
from ground up design the program to be an MPI program. But it's very powerful when you
design a program like that because then you can utilize these supercomputers.
Yeah. Okay. Are there any more methods?
Well, the last one...
Oh, yeah, GPUs. I see.
Yeah, you might have heard is GPU
parallelism. And it's a different kind of like a parallelism, basically, because
like in a GPU, you have like internal parallelism in the GPU card itself. So this graphics processing
unit. They are basically like big vector calculators that can do a lot of calculations
in parallel. Let's say they can multiply a matrix really fast, but they are in the GPU.
Usually, when you have a GPU program, it's parallel in a sense that you have a CPU part
And then usually that CPU part tells the GPU program, okay, here's some, let's say, matrix
you need to multiply, and here's another matrix that you need to multiply with.
And then they are transferred into the GPUs, this VRAM, so this video RAM.
The GPUs have their own fast memory that they can access.
And then these individual calculating units, they're often called like CUDA cores or compute
units or something like that.
They do the calculation in parallel.
So they work basically like this kind of like a fast calculator for these kinds of programs
that can do a lot of stuff in parallel.
But they don't, and of course, there's cases where you also have programs where the calculations
are done using, let's say, some communication so that you can have multiple GPUs working
together.
But usually, the GPU parallelism is internal to the program structure.
And that also means that your program needs to be designed to use GPUs or, well, it can't
use the GPUs.
So, what's a good metaphor here with my pasta analogy?
Is it like, you have one of these, well, if you want to, let's say you want to make the
pasta sauce and you have like an onion slicer or something like that, you just can slice
the whole onion with one go, but you cannot really cook pasta with that really, like you
You can, it does that one thing in parallel.
Instead of chopping with the knife,
you can just chop a full onion at one time.
Actually, I could show my slide with the GPU metaphor
for the pasta thing.
OK.
I'll switch to my screen here.
There.
So this is part of some other thing.
But in the cooking metaphor, so what we see here
is from some restaurant in Switzerland where they're cooking a bunch of chickens on a fire.
And here it's designed where you could cook probably 20 chickens at once. And sorry for
vegetarians, I am too, but this is, well, the metaphor I found. So with this, with very little
effort and quite good efficiency, we can cook so much food at once. But how much pasta can we cook
None.
Not that many.
Yeah.
So the GPU is intrinsically suitable for some types of problems, but not all types.
So if it matches the GPU model, you can do a whole lot.
But if it doesn't, well, it just doesn't run there.
With the GPUs, because why the GPUs are powerful, why they are like that, they originate, of
course, for historical reasons, designed for computer graphics.
And if you do 3D computer graphics, you need to do a lot of rotations and that sort of
stuff in order to calculate vector graphics in the computer programs.
And that's why the computers or the chips of the GPUs were designed to do lots of these
matrix calculations.
And then afterwards, people realized that, hey, what if we use these really good matrix
calculation units to do all kinds of other computations?
And then when, let's say, the deep learning boom started, people realized, okay, we can
run these models in GPUs very efficiently.
And just today I saw news that NVIDIA has surpassed Apple in the stock price.
So they are basically like the GPU trend is ongoing and it's going really fast because
these can be utilized as long as you can formulate your program in this kind of like a matrix
kind of a way, you can usually utilize GPUs to do these fast calculations.
and that's why you said it has to be completely designed around the GPU basically from the start.
So before we move forward to the actual first examples and first exercise,
I want to talk a bit about what is serial and what is parallel in your code. So not every
Every program parallelizes with the GPU parallelization or the shared memory parallelization, because
every program by design or by maths, basically, needs to have a serial part or it has some
part that is serial part.
And then you have some parallel part.
And if you parallelize the parallel part, you can get different amounts of speed up
based on well how much of the program execution was done in parallel. So for example in the first
picture you can see that there's only a small parallel part and if you parallelize that with
two CPUs so you basically divide it by half and then you run it with two CPUs you only save a
small amount of time but if you have like a larger parallel part and you parallelize it you get a
bigger time saver. So it depends on your program. And this is why the embarrassingly parallel is
often the best case. Parallelism in many cases. Because not every problem is easy to parallelize
in these more advanced ways. And it's not a problem. Not everything goes faster by adding
more power to it. So, for example, like Ferrari doesn't go faster in Finnish roads because
there's speed limits. Like, you can use an older car as well.
What about this metaphor? So, with the pasta thing again. So, if I have two people making
pasta in my house, it's probably still okay. Actually, this metaphor isn't perfect. But
Let's say I have 50 people making pasta in my home, or in one home, and it has one sink.
Eventually, everyone's going to need to use the sink, and there'll be a queue there.
That's actually not correct.
Yeah, but if you, like, let's say, like, if you break the pasta in half, like, if you
break the pasta in half and cook it in two pots, does it cook any faster?
Like, do you get it done any faster?
Most likely not, because the pasta has a set cooking time that will always, like pasta
in a sense is always, it will only cook for certain minutes.
You cannot make it faster by spreading, putting it into multiple pots, usually at least.
So that's good to keep in mind when doing parallel computations.
So should we start doing them?
There's one more question, though.
So it's a question, running same simulation,
different random sets, inside each simulation,
I use a GPU for large matrix multiplications.
Each simulation is in a different CPU,
but how to handle the GPU part?
So this is somehow related to the combining
different forms of parallelism.
Yes.
it's not exactly what's there, but yeah. Yeah, so one thing that you can remember is that you can
combine these different methods of parallelization. You can combine, like you can run, if you have
multiple different simulations, you can run this kind of an array job, this embarrassingly parallel
simulation with each job so that each job has a GPU, if your code uses GPUs.
In that case, if you have a simulation and then you need to use a GPU to do some part
of that simulation, there are methods for that, but it requires a bit more finesse so
that the different CPUs can communicate with the GPU.
In many cases, you might have a situation where you have one processor that discusses
with the GPU, and the other processors are doing the simulation.
So you have basically a shared memory part of the simulations, and then you have one
part that does the matrix multiplication with the GPU.
So you have basically these two linked by one CPU, but this is a special case.
But do remember that it's possible to combine all of these methods together.
And if you scroll down the page more, it finally says the research software engineers can help
with parallel computing.
And this is something I'd really recommend.
I mean, these things are confusing.
Even when I'm doing things, I'll often ask [name] just to make sure that I'm running it
correctly or to save me some time.
So if you get to the point where you wonder how it works,
and you're at Aalto University, we're here.
And our job is to save you time figuring out this stuff.
So come by and ask.
I will also mention that it's always a good idea
before creating your own, let's say,
computing framework or something.
It's always good to check if somebody else has done it
before you, because many of these parallel things
are complicated to write, so you don't usually
want to write your own.
There's usually, for example, for R,
there's the parallel package.
And for Python, there's multiple,
like joblib, and there's parallel.
My many parallel processing libraries
that already do this kind of stuff
so that you don't necessarily have
to worry about how it's done underneath it.
So keep that in mind.
whenever using, it's a good idea to use code because like writing the actual like communication
and that sort of stuff is super complicated. So most people that are listening to this
won't be writing their own parallel code but they'll be using existing libraries or frameworks
and yeah I would recommend at least that. You can always write your own but
But yeah, so should we move forward to the array jobs
and actually get to do something?
So I'll flip back to my screen.