Hello, welcome back.
So now with us, we have a visitor from CSC, [name].
I hope I got that correct.
Yeah, pretty, pretty good.
But [name] works at CSC, the IT Center for Science.
So CSC is the national high-performance computing center in Finland, but not just that.
It's actually a whole lot more than just the services you see here.
And even what you see here isn't just high-performance computing.
But anyway, CSC is paid by the Ministry of Culture and Education, I believe, to provide
services for free to academic researchers and others within Finland. So CSC, like all the
things we've been talking about today, CSC has similar but larger, a bigger scale. It might be
a little bit more work to use because you have to apply for the resources and migrate to there.
but if you need power or cross-university collaboration,
this is the place to go.
And was that a good intro?
Should you?
That was an excellent intro.
Okay, yeah.
So I will stay here.
I'll be looking for questions in the notes
and raise them at an appropriate time.
So go ahead.
Okay, thanks [name] for introduction.
So, I will tell, I mean, you already heard in brief what CSC is, I might tell a little bit more
and then I give a bit more details at what kind of computing services CSC provides and for what
kind of use cases you might want to use our computing services. Science for a long time,
even I mean if you're using computers hasn't been only about computing so data
is also a big aspect aspect and we have also some services more more related to
data I'll discuss them briefly and finally some something else like
training we provide and of course if you want or need to use CSC services what
you actually need to do for that. As said, we are owned by the Ministry of Education,
which owns about 80% of the shares and the rest 20% is actually owned by the Finnish
universities. We are a non-profit company and we provide a lot of different services
for the science and higher education.
I didn't actually check now
what's the latest number of staff we have,
but I think it's starting to be close to 700
or something like that.
And out from the 700, maybe 120 or 130
work actually with the scientific computing
and supercomputing.
And even though we are sort of discussing here
that CSC Computing Services and what you need to do in order to get to be used.
I actually can assure you that all of you already at this point,
you are CSC users. If you have ever used any network
within the university, the backbone that's provided by
FUNET, pretty much always when you log into your any university web
services, so you're using account authentication. If you're using Wi-Fi, you're most likely using
Eduroam. So these are sort of these other services and I think many of the
standard administration systems, probably if you look for your course results and things like that,
there is very probably some CSC mode also there. And coming back to the computing services,
And things I'm talking here, as I already said, what's probably of big interest for many of you is that you don't actually need to pay most of this any money.
So that's already paid by the Ministry of Education.
Okay, in what kind of situation you might need CSC services?
I think you can also, first question is that when you actually need to use a HPC cluster and even now
that's probably something you discussed already earlier today but just to remind you
supercomputer is not any machine which automatically makes everything faster.
So actually the supercomputer to be useful, you need to have some
parallelism in your scientific task.
Actually, if I take, I could say, pretty much any simulation or so
that runs on a single core and can fit to the memory of my laptop,
I'm pretty sure that my laptop would actually run faster
than any of the CSC supercomputers.
So you need to have something that runs parallelly.
Sometimes it also might just be that
you just need to run something for quite a long time
and because of that using your own workstation or laptop is not useful.
Second thing might be that actually the problem you are trying to solve
needs lots of memory and that's something that the supercomputers can probably have much more memory.
Same goes for storage space. You need to deal with the terabytes of data.
That's most likely something you don't want to deal with your local port space.
One more reason to use CSC or some other HPC cluster is that the application you want to use,
it might be a commercial application that the principle user pays something for that, but the
CSC has actually bought the license for that, and in terms of the license, academic users can use
that free of charge. Or even though it might be an open source application, it might be something
which is a tedious install, have a lot of dependencies, and having data set ready to use
in a supercomputing system might be might be benefit. Regarding the data,
if you need to share data for other researchers, your colleagues, some of the services that CSC
provide might turn out to be useful and especially if you actually want to publish the data that's
that's something that I'm pretty sure it's very difficult for you to do in them according
all the principles on your own. Yeah we basically don't have our own long-term repositories and
say that's CSC's job. Yeah and I mean to get some DOEs for your data and I mean
something where other people can actually also cite your data if you if you share it.
So yeah this is why you might need CSC. You have something parallel, you need lots of memory
or storage-based application or data. You've already learned quite a bit about the university
clusters, so this question is of course that how do our computers actually differ from those?
And the answer is, from a user point of view, actually very little. The main difference really is in scale.
how many GPU cores, how many GPUs you can use, how much storage space you have, etc.
As an example, in Mahti, or actually also in Lumi CPU Partition, you can, if you need,
you could be running something like 25,000 cores your simulation, or if you need to use
hundreds of GPUs that's in principle available in Lumi. The way you access
CSC supercomputers is pretty much the same as you would access for example Triton, I
mean you can use SSH from your terminal to get the command-line based
access and this is actually I realize a valid point I did not update I think
the web GUI, it's not really as such so new. So in some terms new service, but I mean that's
something we have had already for three years. And I think in Triton, how long you have actually had
that? A little bit, but it's only become a big thing in the last year. We've only really been
starting pushing it for basically the new Triton in the last month. So yeah. But once again,
then something that's also available there.
And I think especially for these web interfaces,
I mean, if you used in one system,
it's more or less same way to use that.
When using from command line,
we also have a module system to selecting compilers
and so on.
And in the batch queue system,
I think most of the supercomputing sites,
only CSC actually use Slurm.
So differences in usage are mainly
what are the partition names and et cetera.
So.
Yeah.
One big difference of course is that
when you want to use CSC computing services,
you actually need to apply project for that
and you need to apply for some billing units
which you could think as CSC money or something like that.
And when you do competitions,
so actually nowadays also for data,
you have a lot of data on the disk
that also consume these billing units.
And it's one way we try to ensure
that the users actually think what they are doing.
It's often too easy.
I mean, I've been there, I've done that,
do some stupid things with the computer and waste resources, so that tries to assure that
users use the resources wise. Yeah, that's probably the biggest difference between
CSC and us. So for us, you just apply for the account, but you don't apply for or account for
individual resources separately, but there's no guaranteed amount available to you. At CSC,
you apply for the resources but there's much more available and
you're much more likely to get what you apply for within a quick time.
I'll come in the end of the presentation what is actually
what is needed for applying this and by the way in the way you you need
to apply for resources comes also that you typically also need
to report something especially I mean when you pre-apply some resources you
you need to somehow report that, what you use them for,
what kind of publication you make, and so.
Yeah.
Okay.
Then a bit about what are the computing,
or what kind of computing resources or services we have.
At the moment, we have two national supercomputers
which are available for basically to the users
users coming from Finnish universities and higher education institutions.
So we have Puhti and we have Mahti.
They both are actually in a sort of end part of their life.
So we are currently
or we have started already the sort of process of buying the next national
supercomputer, probably by the end of next year,
2025 Puhti and Mahtti will retire and we'll have a new system. What that's going to be,
I do not know and something we'll see with the negotiation with the vendors.
Puhti and Mahtti, they have a little bit different user profiles, so Puhti's,
you can somehow think that it's a bit more general purpose for smaller parallel jobs,
having Intel CPUs and some NVIDIA bit older generation GPUs,
MAHDI, SmartWave, Kietow Arts, medium and large scale
parallel simulations. For example, for most of the partitions,
the minimum number of CPU cores you are using,
using that single node, which it's in that system
with the AMD CPUs, it's always 128.
Mahti has also a little bit smaller GPU partition
than Puhti with the newer GPUs.
And what might be useful for some of you
for interactive workloads, development, and so on,
is that some of these GPUs can also actually be
slice the smaller ones so you do not, as the resources is a bit more limited, there are I
think only 24 of these nodes but for purposes where you do not need the full computational
power of single GPU you can get only a subset of that and do some useful stuff with that.
Then, as a sort of flagship, there is also LUMi. LUMi is actually not really a CSC supercomputer,
so it's actually truly a pan-European supercomputer, funding coming from the European Union and 11
countries belonging to Lumi Consortium, but it's hosted in the CSC data center.
User support is not directly given by CSC, so it's distributed to these Lumi Consortium countries,
but if you want to use that for Finnish users, you can access it via CSC
in applied resources a similar way as to Puhti and Matti.
Lumi at the moment is the most powerful supercomputer in Europe and the fifth most
powerful in the world, having over 10 000 AMD GPUs. So it's really a massive compute resource.
There is also a CPU part of that, which still is a quad-signal count, it's around 200,000
CPU cores also there.
Now with all this multitude of different supercomputers CSC has, you might ask, okay, which one of
these I should actually use?
And as I said, it really depends a bit on what kind of satellite task they have, a bit different profiles.
As I said, Puhti is maybe more for small or medium scale parallel tasks.
It has the most extensive software selection available,
while Mahti, as I said, is more for the larger parallel calculations.
duration of your of your simulation in
market the maximum time you get random
queue
and that's also a bit shorter than in
than in Puhti.
And Lumi I would say that
Lumi is really if you have an
application that can really benefit from
AMD GPUs
that's that's when you really should
consider Lumi.
Some projects you might might want to
run also the CPUs but
they do not provide that much advantage over Mahti. Software availability in Lumi is actually
a bit more limited, and talking about the module systems, the Cray module system that is in Lumi,
it's in some ways a bit more, in some cases, a bit more complicated to use than
the ones that we have in Puhti and Mahti, which are, I would say, more similar to Triton.
About the web interface, I'd say this is something that nowadays you can use all the three supercomputers,
either Puhti, Matti or Lumi, and here you can see the sort of selection of applications
within this web interface that you can use, for example,
in Puhti.
I think, personally, I use the Jupyter Notebooks a lot.
That's quite nice.
You can use it in MATLAB or RStudio.
That also might be quite convenient.
And if you need to use some graphical applications using
the NVIDIA web desktop might be also a good option.
In addition to the kind of traditional HPC services,
CSC provides also some cloud-like resources.
They might become useful if you have the operating system,
the system libraries and so on, that are available in supercomputers,
not always the latest possible. I mean the main objective for the for the
system is that it needs to be stable and sometimes you might need a bit more
flexibility. You really would like to run your own operating system or
things like that and for this kind of usage you might want to consider some of
the cloud services. Basically we have three types of cloud services. We have a
a CPoL as a general computing cloud, then I don't know, are
the Antisodius users doing genomics or things like that
where the data is actually sensitive?
Some are. We talked about that a bit on day one, and I think we
mentioned the CSC services, so here.
So for this kind of thing, there is the ePoL, and then there is
also this Pirate Container Cloud that can be useful for some things.
I heard that some of you earlier were
somehow interested but also about the programming.
I won't go in much details how to actually do the parallel programming use.
This is just the very brief overview what kind of
approaches one typically uses using supercomputers and I mean what
you can use in if you're using a CSC. So of course the basic C, C++, C, Fortran, Python,
Archulia. For parallel programming you can use MPI for distributed memory parallelism,
more openMP for shared memory. There are some high-performance libraries and GPUs.
If you're doing machine learning you might be using PyTorch or something like that which is
be readily available in the system or if you want to do the GPU graph on yourself
you might be using OpenMP offloading, OpenACC, CUDA, the HIP. CSC provides also some
performance analysis and debugging tools for parallel applications. So maybe you mention
this later but do you have training for all of these different types of things? Yes, I mentioned
bit of I'll come to try a little bit at the end of the talk.
The technical details I think I will now
skip but I'm in the end of slides so if you're interested you can
you can have some of the actual numbers checked there. You should find pretty
much the same information also from the CSC web pages or user
documentation. I'll include that also in the
presentation. Okay, let us come then to the other
aspect I mentioned that you might be dealing directly with
data or when you're doing the computations
and you're creating data that you would like to do also a little bit
more than just have it in the
in the file system in the supercomputer.
One data service we have is the ALLAS object storage
and you can upload the data from the supercomputer or actually from
anywhere so that's something the data which is in the
supercomputer file system or HPC file system
you can only access from the HPC system but the data you put in this object
storage you can in principle access from anywhere from the internet and you can also have the data
shared to other users. Lumi has actually its own optic storage also which is
it's a physically separate from that so if you you can use Allas either from Lumi or from
Mahti and Puhti. Lumi has this Lumi own object storage, which
similar you can actually use from from different places.
Okay.
CSC provides also some, I don't know if the data findable
accessible, interoperable, reusable is a concept common to
you. But basically it means that you can you can publish your
data set and together with the data set there is also
some metadata and there is also some tools for
searching these data sets so CSC has some services
for example EDA is one such a service that we provide.
Okay, training was already mentioned by [name].
So we have a quite a large amount of training every year in various aspects.
So supercomputing, just how to use our systems, might be related just to Puhti or Mahti,
might be related how to use Lumi,
might be some programming course of parallel programming
or might be just how to use certain static applications like
like Chromux.
There is also possible to get some help if you
have a data set that you would like to visualize.
Something more than just making your xy graphs.
CSC can provide help and for example you can develop your own
scientific application and would need some help in getting more
performance from that. That's something where CSC can also
help. Yeah so if someone say wants to learn
MPI program or OpenMP programming or GPU programming you have these
kind of courses? Or links to them from Lumi or something?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, definitely. Yeah. Here are just examples of
some of the courses we are currently offering. So I think
if you're just want to learn a bit more about the
supercomputers in sort of general level, we have this
online course, Elements of Supercomputing, should be quite accessible and might be
and has been developed in principle for mostly people who don't necessarily have any previous
background of HPC, so it's quite general level. We have also this ongoing online course about
how to use CSC computing environment. We're going to have in the June-July time frame,
we have now for, I think this is now 13th time, we have in the summer school about high-performance
computing. That's a deadline for that has already passed, but that's sort of 10 days
is where you really go through all the basic aspects of how to
do parallel programming with the MPI, how to use OpenMP, how to
do GPU programming. So I think that's something if you if you
think that you will be doing a parallel program, something you
might want to look for in next year, I think that for next year
registration probably opens somewhere in January, February. Some of the courses we
already have in calendar of these hardware formats are in September.
Okay. Yeah, did you have some comment [name]? No, no, please continue. Okay, so all these
wonderful services we provide, so how you how you get to use them. First of all, similar to for
example Triton, you need to have an account and for CSC if you already have Haka available, I mean
you have been using Haka in your university, you can just go to my.csc.fi and with a few mouse
clicks you will get the csc user account. Username will probably be different.
Fast forward ssh keys so that you will be using the DNS cluster but you do not need any
really extra steps other than the account navigates. As discussed, in order to really
get some computational resources and use them there needs to be a project for that and you
one needs to apply billing units for the project and for that not not quite anybody can apply for
the project but on the other hand it doesn't have to be the big processor so basically
experienced researcher postdoc or something like that. I mean if you're doing some research work
there is typically some more experienced researcher that can apply for the project
and he or she can apply for billing unit and with the project the project manager can in principle
add any CSC user to the project. Maybe not so relevant for this audience but just to let you
know that if you're teaching a course and you want to use some CSC resources for that so that is also
possible to apply for a project for that. For courses you typically do not need to apply
billing units. So there is always a fixed amount of resources given there. The duration
is also typically fixed to six months, so it's a bit shorter too. And once a month
you need to then have the CSC account in order to actually use these resources within the
course.
Yeah. And I can say sometimes people come and ask us, oh, what do these questions mean
when applying for resources, but when in doubt, just send an email to the CSC service desk
or even in, if you're that brave, call and ask for details.
And I've always gotten good answers that way and, you know, some solution.
So yeah, it is some work, but don't be afraid.
Yeah.
Okay.
And I mean, when you have these questions, so yeah, we have the service desk.
If you go to our main webpages, you can actually find the phone numbers there, all the user
guides and so on.
You can go to indux.csc.fi, free data and so on, and all the trainings we have coming
there.
You can see there.
So us, the Aalto Scientific Computing team here, we also do, we support CSC things,
if you bring questions to us. So maybe you wouldn't want to for things, but for example,
for using Lumi, our recommendation is to come to us and let us try to figure out how GPU stuff
works there and then you do it yourself. We have people come and asking about CSC virtual machines
or other small debugging things on CSC resources. Okay, yeah. Yeah, that's pretty much what I have
to present and I mean if there are any still more questions or something like that I'm
happy to answer. Let's see, I'll flip to the notes here. So there was a question
where does the abbreviation CSC come from and from Finnish Wikipedia I see it
does come from Center for Scientific Computing decades ago. Decades ago and at
some point I think that was sort of abandoned. There was a time when
Then actually the official name was Center for Scientific Computing, and then at some
point, I don't know, somewhere, someone made the decision that, okay, now it's just CIC,
IT Center for Science, is what the original comes from.
Yeah.
Which is more appropriate these days, anyway.
There's a question, my code is not using GPUs, so Lumi's only beneficial for GPU work.
Lumi, as said, it has also this CPU partition,
which, I mean, it's basically the same type of CPUs
than in Mahti, one generation newer.
I guess whether you should be using Lumi or Mahti
or Puhti in that case is really how...
Is it really just how big and where you're used to
and what has enough spare resources right now?
Something like that, and sometimes it might be just a matter of that depending on time of year or whatever there is more free resources in one supercomputer than in another.
Yeah.
I would say that for Finnish users having only CPU code marked is probably big.
I mean, for Volumio also, you can apply access via this my.csc.dev file.
But for some things, I would say that it's probably easier to work with.
Yeah. Okay. Someone put in the notes here a pointer to the CSC weekly user support session.
Ah, that's actually, yeah.
This is really good. It's like our daily garage at Aalto.
So you can go there and ask questions and join some experts and figure out stuff live.
Yeah definitely something I should add also to the slide something we
we already had for quite some time but yeah that's that's true something I mean there was this that
okay you you can send email and but I mean this is this is a member Wednesday you can just online
join and hopefully be like a low barrier place to ask questions. Yeah and so is CSC a non-profit
organization, or is it a company? Yes, yes. We are a private company, but a special company,
non-profit company. We're actually not allowed to make any real profit than a
sale loan by the Ministry of Education, so. Okay, yeah, yeah. We are here to make the world a better
place, not to make money. Yeah, and yes, our taxes go to supporting CSC, just like they go to
supporting research because CSC is part of research.
Yes, exactly. Anyway, yeah, thank you very much for coming. I
guess UC can stay around in the
notes and answer any further questions that appear there.
I'll just put it in the chat with UC. So yeah, thanks a lot and
see you next year or maybe before next year.
Yeah, we'll see.
Yeah, OK.
Thanks a lot.
Bye.