So I'll flip back to my screen.
Yes.
OK, so here we are, to array jobs.
So I guess we go like before.
So let's look at the abstract here.
So what's an array job?
So array makes me think a bunch of things in parallel.
And from before, I know it's somehow related to embarrassing parallel.
So how would you explain it?
Yeah.
So an array is basically like what the name says.
It's like a list of numbers, basically.
And in this case, let's say we want
to do a simulation with multiple different data sets.
We have data set one.
We have data set two, data set three, and so forth.
We want to do the same simulation with we
have something that we want to iterate over, basically.
And all of these simulations would
be independent of each other.
So we have independent simulations that we can do, but we just want to do them all.
And what we could do is we could write our Sbatch script for each simulation at a time.
So we would have like n Sbatch scripts to run like serial jobs.
But what we can do in Slurm, there's this feature called array, where you can give this
slurm comment that we previously already see called array and give it a list of numbers or
different kinds of numbers and then it will launch basically one job that consists of
multiple of these independent jobs. So basically it launches copies of the same job
but with the key difference that each job gets one number different. So each job gets its own
Slurm_Array_Task_Id. So, each one gets its own environment variable, which is the number
of that job's number in that array. So, that job's number in that list of jobs.
Yeah. So, this variable right here, this runs 10 times with input underscore one,
input underscore 2 and so on up to 10. Okay. So when the job is running, if we look at the
minimal example script over here, when the job is running, that number, the slurm array task ID,
will go from numbers 1 to 10 because we have specified there in the comment that we want
them to run an array from 1 to 10. That number will change. That number then we can, for example,
In that code, we can run input one, input two, input three, and they all run independently
at the same time. The Slurm will try to allocate all of those into the queue, and they will run
independent of each other in different computers, different nodes, and whatever.
All of the other requirements that we have specified, if we require a certain amount of
of memory, certain amount of time, whatever, they are copied as well.
The rest of the script is basically copied between all of the jobs, but the array index
is just different.
Yeah.
So I run sbatch once, but 10 things come out the other end.
Yes.
Yes, basically.
So we can do this.
What you can do then, or what is the question usually, is that, okay, you have a number,
like the array is a number, and how can you convert that number into something else, let's
say a parameter or something.
We'll go through a few examples of this.
Yeah.
Maybe we could-
Should we do the example?
Yeah.
Let's do an example.
Okay.
And run that.
There's some good questions in the notes.
we can answer those first. Simulation is relatively fast. So yeah, if the array jobs take
a few minutes or less, then it's better not to have thousands of them. Try to group them together.
And there's some hints about this later in the page. It's exactly like an overall for loop
kind of thing. The number assigned to the array randomly done. I'm not sure exactly what that
means. So the Slurm_Array_Task_IDs come exactly from this here.
And you can skip values. You can choose different number ranges. You can do it like
you can do like every fifth number or something like that. There's different
syntaxes you can use to which numbers you want to use. But you will get like each of these jobs
will get one of those numbers that you have specified in the dash dash array comment.
The array jobs result in multiple sessions. Yes, so they can run at the same time,
but they might run at different times, and they're all completely independent
and have no knowledge of each other.
Yes.
Okay.
Let's go on.
So, if I scroll down.
Yeah.
Let's look at that example.
Where's the first example we get?
My first array job.
Yeah.
This seems like the place to start, right?
Yes.
Okay.
Yeah.
If we look at the script.
So, if we look at the script over here, we have, like, we have the usual suspects.
So, we have the first line.
We have the shebang, shebang, how it's pronounced.
And then we have a few of these comments, so if [name], you want to open our editor and copy the script there.
I've just realized I haven't cloned the HPC Examples repository or gotten set up.
Yeah.
Okay.
Well, in the meantime, I can, while [name] is copying the repository, I can, oh, yeah,
yeah.
Actually, for this, you don't need that, yeah.
The next ones, maybe, yes.
OK.
What?
Yes.
So, in the script, we have the time and the memory requirements at the start.
So these are the usual suspects that we always want to give anyways.
And after that, we have the output.
And this time in the output comment, we have a directive for the Sbatch.
We have a few different characters there.
We have this %A and %a, and what these do is that because we now launch multiple jobs
at the same time, we don't want them all to write in the same output file because it would
get really cluttered and it would be really hard to see what each of these would do.
What we can do is that we can divert each output into a separate file where the person's
capital A is like a shorthand for the job ID as a whole, like the whole array will get
one job ID.
So that will be the job ID for the array job, for the whole SLURM submission basically.
So basically, they all have the same capital A.
Yes.
The lowercase a is the number from it?
Yeah, that's the Slurm array task ID.
So each we will get, like if we submit in this example,
we submit from 0 to 15, so we get 16 outputs
when we calculate them together.
So we get 16 output files in this case.
And then, in the example, we run this echo.
And here, I'm just printing it out.
Yes.
OK, does this look correct?
Yeah, let's try and run it.
OK, I Control-X and Y, and Enter to save.
If I list, I see array example.
So I run with sbatch?
Yes.
So we do one submission.
And now if you run slurmq, we can see, hopefully.
It already ran.
The thing you saw pending was something I have.
Yeah, we need to put maybe a sleep there.
But OK, it already ran.
And now we already see the output.
So we see there that we have generated the overall job ID was 476680, and then we have
from 0 to 50 in these output files.
If [name] now looks at the output 0, you can see that the task ID is 0.
And if you pick, let's say, 1 is 1 and so forth.
You can notice that each process, when they were running, or each array task, when they
were running, they all got a different number for the slow array task ID.
There was a question also in the chat, but can you map this number into two parameters?
Yes, you can.
You can basically, whatever countable set you have, you can map into that, like whatever,
like two dimensions, three dimensions.
The question is just like, how complicated does the thing start to be?
And usually, we will look at a few examples on what you can do with this or what sort
of things you can do with this.
But in many cases, if it starts to get really complicated, the mapping, it's easier to just
the number to your program and then write it in your program. Okay, what should it do
with numbers? So, quite often, let's say it loads a line from a configuration file and
then loads the parameters from there or something like that.
Yeah. Okay. So, is that basically what there is? Do we, I think...
Maybe we could run the same example, but with a sleep in there and just demo, just to verify
that it actually runs on separate jobs.
I'm pushing the up arrow key to go up in history to find my nano command.
Yeah.
I push enter.
So what we get when we run this, we get 15 different individual jobs that all run the
same except the task ID is different.
And if we, based on that Slurm task ID, we do something different, or use a different
data set or different parameters or something, we will get 15 different results.
Yeah.
Okay. Should I do it?
Yes. Let's do it.
Press Enter.
Okay. I push Enter and then I run Slurm q immediately.
Yeah.
So here it looks like.
Yeah. They all got running immediately.
They're all running very quickly.
You can notice on the left,
you can see that they have this underscore there,
where you have the different array indices separated. So you have the same thing running
with different indices. And on the right, you can see where the node list is. Some are running in
PE40, some are running in PE41, and some are running in PE43, I think, or something.
So the computers where they are running might be completely different because they are independent.
But using this array thing makes it possible for you to run a lot of simulations at the
same time and it also is very nice for the queue manager because the queue manager doesn't
now have to consider each job independently.
It can consider the array job as a whole and it's much better for the queue manager to
do this for you to do this this way you don't get you don't accidentally like cause like a denial
of service and this could be the denial of service by submitting like thousands of jobs
so many of our users might run arrays that have like hundreds or maybe even maybe thousands of
jobs in the array so if they want to do like really big lots of simulations like different
random numbers or different parameters or something like that.
So there's a question, does it run the same program ten times?
Yes, and it has, but your program has to be able to use this variable to do different things each time.
If that's what you want. And below, I think we have a bunch of examples of this.
So we won't really go through the examples, but maybe we can show the spirit of them.
Yeah.
Maybe we can show the first two as this kind of like, yeah.
So here we see it's the array job.
There's 30 things in the array.
And I see there's some application that says input.
And here every program will take a different piece of input data.
if you have your input data all numbered, then that's relatively easy.
Yeah, and if you scroll a bit down, there's two examples of how can you map those numbers
into some parameters. One example is that you can use this case structure in Bash.
If the Slurm array task ID is something, set the seed in this case to be some other value.
And there is also below, there's another example where you can use, if you don't want to write,
you can write it a bit more concise.
you can use this bash array. This is a different array than the slurm array we are talking
about. Basically, bash has this list or all this kind of array structure. So, you can
list the numbers there and then pick from this array that specific number based on the
index of the, like, there.
And I guess the whole thing could be done in Python, basically, where you give a single
number to your Python or R MATLAB program, whatever, and internally it maps to whatever
parameters it's supposed to use.
Yes.
Okay.
Yeah.
You can also, like, read a line from a file, like, below this example also, like, if you
want to write your different parameters in a file and then read it from there.
But maybe we should go into exercises and let people try them out themselves.
Yeah, I agree.
There's a little bit more here you can read yourself.
So for exercises, what should we recommend people to work on?
I would probably say that the exercise 1 would be probably best.
So you can choose whichever of these previous examples
that we provide in the page and try
to give this pi.py different seed numbers.
So you can try out one of these exercises.
I would say that run one of these, at least,
and try it out.
Also, there was a good question, what
a difference between job and a program. Job, in this case, often refers to Slurm job. Basically,
like an allocation that Slurm needs to fulfill for you. When you submit with sbatch some script,
then Slurm thinks of it as a job that it needs to do. I need to do this thing.
thing. I need to execute this thing. If you give it an array job, it knows that, okay,
I need to execute this like 100 times, but with different array index each time. That's
a slurm job. Inside the script in that job, it can have multiple programs that you run
and then one after the other.
Yeah.
OK.
And how long should we give?
I guess this has to be combined with the break
because it will be break time.
So assuming people start 10 minutes from now
after the break, should we give 20 minutes maybe?
Would you say this is the most important one,
so we should give the most time here?
I think it would be good to have enough time to really test
these examples, because this is something that can give you a lot of power with minimal changes
to your code. And that's why this is very good to learn, because you can then utilize it in
multiple different ways. So yeah, I would say 20 minutes at least. Yeah. Okay. Sounds good.
So I wrote down until 20.
20 pounds.
So that's.
And do ask the questions.
It's very good to have the questions in the notes.
Yeah.
This is the most important interactive lesson
we're doing today.
So OK, see you in half an hour.
Yeah.
Thanks.
Bye.
Hello, we're back.
And there have been really many very good questions here, and I think most have been
answered.
There's a good question about how does the program understand Slurm_Array_Task_ID.
is called an environment variable and it's not specific to Slurm. Environment variable is a thing
which all Unix and probably Windows programs have a concept of and many languages can read
them and get the values. We're showing how to do it with Bash but there's other ways too.
Yeah, we will quickly mention when in the next session that we start soon, how you can like
calculate or get the CPU number, how many CPUs you have allocated in the script,
like in your code, how you can get that number and you can use the same kind of structure for the
array ID as well. Yeah.
There's a good thing here about confusing terminology.
And yes, it's confusing. My recommendation is to
run it several times and see what happens.
And also, I would say that
try to look beyond the terminology and look at the
functionality. All of these have so
many conflicting terms that it's very hard to keep it in check, even in speech. We might
use confusing terminologies all the time that are not correct because there's so many different
terms. But what I think the most important thing is to keep in mind that, okay, you have
this workflow that you might write your serial job. You might do an interactive, first interactive
job on your program, then you write it into a serial script. And then when you have run it
through the serial script, like we did yesterday, after that, you want to do it with, let's say,
multiple parameters or something. So, then you add the array constructor. And then in your code,
you write some way that, okay, it understands that there's different things that it needs to do.
Yeah, like there's multiple ways of doing that.
And usually it's a good idea to recommend a way is that first you launch like one array
job.
Like I mean, like one array index.
So let's say array equals, that's just array equals zero.
So you basically launch, it would be basically the serial job, right?
Okay.
Yeah.
Like because you're launching only one of them and you see that, okay, did it work correctly?
And then maybe you launch the array, and that's just array equals one, and you launch the
next one.
Okay.
Yeah.
And you see that, okay, did it do the different thing that you expected?
And then you launch array from zero to thousand or something.
Because like, so you basically like copy paste the same code without doing the copy paste.
And that's this kind of workflow, once you get hang of that, that is the most important
thing.
call it is not the most important issue, I would say.
Okay, yeah. So what's coming up next?
Do we do some examples of the array jobs? Or should we go on?
I think we should move on because we have a lot of
ground to cover. But, yeah, so maybe we should...
My screen. So it's a shared memory parallelism.
Yeah. Okay. Yeah. And for the next two, do we give a