CodeRefinery.org
you
Hello.
Hello, hello.
Anyone can.
Anyone out there hear us?
Yeah, the stream seems to work.
Okay.
At least I see us there.
Can also hear us over there.
Yeah.
can also hear us over there.
So we're starting off.
Oh, should we do a sound check?
On the stream, does my sound sound
the same as other people's sound?
That's the real question.
Hopefully, require other people to talk as well.
Correct.
Probably does, yes.
Should we count?
I can start with one and mention the next person,
which is [name].
two or one one
one and one i guess zero
did we say was saying can you try your microphone i couldn't hear
okay is it good yeah it's fine to me everything everyone sounds balanced
All right, so, oh, who's talking now?
Well, yeah, welcome. So we're here just chatting a bit before we get started to encourage everyone
to join nice and early. Those of you who are registered should have a link to this document.
the URL comes from note.coderefinery.org, but it's what we call the notes. So if you take this
and you switch to edit mode, which you can find from up here in the desktop view,
you'll you click the little pencil icon and then you can scroll down and you see questions and
stuff here. So basically instead of people raising hands or using the Twitch chat, what we do,
you can switch this to edit mode and then ask whatever you want whenever you want. So the basic
rules or way it works, always be writing at the bottom because that's the place we'll be looking.
We'll always put whatever section we're on, whatever links there should be, whatever you
you should do towards the bottom.
Usually answers are in bullet points like this.
So yeah.
And when you're not actively editing for a while,
if you switch back to view mode, we
think that will save a little bit of the performance
of this for other people.
And let's see what people are answering. So for icebreakers, we've got
Where are you and what's the weather? Okay, actually we're not all in Helsinki now.
We're in Helsinki, Espoo and Kirkkonummi in Finland.
Maybe we should introduce ourselves. So I'm [name]. I work at Aalto University
in what officials would call the Science IT team, what
we call Aalto Scientific Computing.
Basically, we do the high-performance computing
cluster.
We do teaching like this where you are now.
And we help you with your work.
And everyone else here is also in the team.
So next on my screen is [name].
Yeah, for some reason, the shortcut
unmute didn't work, I don't know. I'm [name]. I'm also working at the
Aalto Scientific computing team. I'm a research software
engineer, which is hard to define, I would say.
But yeah, I work with researchers and help
them to optimize their code and to focus their research, I would say, and
dedicate the computational tasks to us.
[name]'s next on my screen. Hi, my name is [name]. I'm one of the instructors in this
course and I work also on the other side of the computing. Recently I switched from
the High Performance Computing part to the research software engineering part, so now I'm a research
software engineer here in the team. I do similar work as [name] and I think many others here.
Yeah. Next on my screen is [name].
Hi, I'm [name]. I'm also a research software engineer with Aalto Scientific Computing.
I'll be hopefully helping people with getting connected to the clusters a little bit later.
And yeah, that's mainly about me at the moment.
Great. [name].
Yeah, hi, I'm [name]. I'm also an RSE with the people at Aalto. I try to help, mostly
I try to help researchers do their research with whatever problems they have in terms
of computing. And yeah, I'll try to help [name] with the connecting today.
Yeah. And [name].
Hello, I believe you got some emails from me, a few tens of emails from me, you will
receive more.
You know, you can always unsubscribe, I'm a big fan of data protection, so you know
GDPR is, I truly believe in GDPR, so feel free to unsubscribe if you want to, but in
general here I'm coordinating the training with the same team at Aalto University and
I'm also very happy that we have Helsinki University
and Oulu University joining with us.
So it's a really nice distributed experience.
Okay, great.
So the first question I'll ask everyone here
and you've sort of gotten to it a bit.
What is a research software engineer?
And in one sentence, what do people need to know?
I know what I would say, but what do y'all say?
I would say someone who helps researchers concentrate
on the research and not care so much
about the computation problems.
Yeah.
Exactly what I want someone to say.
So the one thing to remember is we're
going to say a lot of stuff here.
And how many hours is the course?
10 hours over three days?
There's no way we can teach enough to do everything.
Some people may know more about Linux and computing.
Some people may know less,
but when you have problems after this,
if you're at Aalto University,
then come to us, come to our team,
come to our daily garage,
which by the way, I should update to say
that it's busy today.
Maybe someone can do that.
And we can help with all of the computing problems.
So you can focus on what you need.
It can be giving you some little hints.
it can be doing some bigger project for you if you're not in a computing field at all.
Maybe that's the most important thing to take from this whole course.
And also throughout the course we will have contributors and friends from Finland and
beyond and we'll talk about other collaborators we do lots of our courses with. So you might
have noticed that we are in the Code Refinery channel here in Twitch being streamed, so we'll
be talking about the Code Refinery project as well. If you're not in Aalto, there's plenty of
other resources, some other supporting infrastructure for computational stuff,
so we'll be talking about that later throughout the course. Yes.
I guess anything interesting from the icebreakers
before we start.
It's about time.
Let's see, at least the Helsinki people have sunny weather.
That's good.
Olu's not so lucky.
Should we just start?
I guess we can talk about these computing things later.
But I do see there's a quite big diversity of how
people do computing.
And that really is one of the hardest things
about teaching this course.
We could say, here's what you can do.
But people start in so many different ways
from so many different places.
And there's so many different ways
to do things these days that it's hard to cover all of them.
And favorite animal, that's a good variety there.
By the way, you can put a plus one symbol next to something
if you agree with it.
That's a common way to upvote questions that are relevant.
And with that being said, I guess
it's time for the intro, which I believe is [name] talking.
Yes.
All right.
Your screen shared.
If you could share the intro page, actually.
Or someone else who is going to share later.
Let's see.
I need to get this set up.
Hey it worked so I shrink this down some so here we are this is the
my cursor is some random place on my screen so this is the course page if you scroll down
there's the schedule and this is the way you can figure out where we are and we're starting with
the intro. So, welcome to Introduction to Scientific Computing and HPC. Very briefly,
what is this course about? Well, it's structured over three days and we kind of gradually build
on the skills, on the basic skills that are needed for basically scaling up your computations. So,
in Finland, and also for those of you who are not in Finland, most likely you
have access to an high-performance computing cluster, which basically means lots and lots
of servers connected by a very fast network so that they can run lots of computations.
And it might well be that you don't need thousands of servers connected in parallel,
but what is useful is that you can just request one for yourself, do your work in a secure way,
and then happily, you know, continue with publishing paper and things like that.
So who is attending this workshop, this course? Well, there's multiple people
from multiple universities. We are very happy that today with us, beyond Aalto
University, there's also Helsinki University and Oulu University, but in general we
span across borders. We have people from all over the Nordics, Europe and even
beyond so the practicalities this is not your typical kind of zoom workshop or
zoom course where we are all in the in the same zoom here we use this type of
live stream strategy which you can understand that it's very useful because
this is like a TV studio and we're like all watching the TV together and by
doing this we can make sure that we can provide immediately high quality
recordings of all the training that we have today and more broadly you will later see
that everything is to be stored in our YouTube channel so that you can re-watch something
that we're going to mention in these days but also sometimes we don't cover things that
we have already covered well in the past and so there's more videos that we will refer
to.
The communication with the instructors happens through this type of asynchronous chat and
you can understand already that this is much better than something like the Zoom chat which
makes it impossible to communicate with this type of shared document that we are all editing.
Right now there's 105 people editing it in parallel.
You can basically ask questions and then maybe some of you could answer or one of the helpers
can answer and so on. At the end this document basically forms a nice diary of the whole
day which will then archive and you can later go back to it and check it. As you might have
already tested this once you open the link that you have received in your registration
email there's a pencil at the top, the screenshot there is showing that. By clicking on the
pencil basically you enter the edit mode and then you're able to add the text
where you need to add it. The share document is powerful but of course if
there's hundreds of people editing in parallel it can be you know challenging
even to just type so if you're if you know that you don't need to write
anything you can switch back to the view mode by clicking that eye icon so that
you know the load of the service is is smaller and other people can write freely
Right. So where do we focus or where to focus because you can understand that there's different windows and
In general focus on the on the streaming on the twitch TV window
We provide this type of vertical
layout so that, as you can see in the picture there,
you can kind of keep the Twitch window
on one side of your laptop screen, for example,
and then you can keep, let's say,
this notes document in another browser window
or your terminal.
We would use a lot the terminal
to connect to the remote cluster.
Of course, if you have multiple screens,
then you don't have these issues,
but we are thinking for those of you
who are working with a laptop
so that they have enough desktop space to arrange all the windows together.
Maybe one thing that I did not mention when it comes to Twitch.tv streaming,
it is important that you set the bandwidth to basically source,
which means the same bandwidth of the original broadcasting stream.
Otherwise, Twitch will do some sort of compression,
and so things will start to get blurry.
but if you make it so that the bandwidth
is basically the maximum available,
you will see the stream.
All right, anything else that we are missing?
Yeah, maybe on the learning styles
that there's many learning styles.
I think in general, we've been running this
kind of new way of online teaching for a few years.
We really like the fact that it can happen
at everybody's, at anyone's pace.
Those who want to learn live with us,
they can watch right now.
Some others might learn later.
And when we chat with our previous course participants,
some people find this also useful months after,
so they can go back to the stream,
watching the videos, checking the notes document.
In general, to conclude,
when it comes to the community and to good rules,
let's just try to be respectful.
At Aalto, we have our code of conduct
any universities we have a good code of conduct. If you see some inappropriate
behavior just let us know and we can do the best to kind of you know compensate
for that or make sure that it doesn't happen. There's few things that could go
wrong but usually they don't get wrong. In general if you feel that there's too
much information coming in too short time it's totally normal especially if
it's the first time that you work with this type of HPC systems but this is why
it's it's it's great to have everything recorded and you can later you know
rewatch at your own pace if the notes are too fast to follow don't worry you
don't need to follow the notes you don't need to you know we basically will
highlight some important notes on the on the stream and then again later you can
always go back to the notes and have a look.
I already mentioned this that sometimes if there's too many people editing at the same
time the notes document might feel slow so please switch to the view mode and we won't
have time to cover everything so some of the materials that are linked in our main page
course page are actually videos from previous rounds of this course or there's other videos
for example this kitchen metaphor to HPC, in general we encourage you to, you know,
explore all the materials we have and what we will show here in these 10 hours together is kind of,
you know, a small or a large subset of all the materials. What else? Well, we try not to deviate
from the schedule but you know things happen and when it comes to possible technical issues
it has happened only once that the whole internet collapsed during the streaming hopefully
the internet will be up again but eventually if something goes wrong just wait a little bit and
the stream might come back or then you will receive another email from me saying that
I don't know, we could have a plan B. All right, well I guess maybe the most
important thing is to mention that the cat, [name]'s cat, will visit the stream.
I think it's too early now. Is the cat still sleeping, [name]?
Yeah, it's in the room but sleeping. It's usually later in the afternoon,
so motivation to stay to the end.
Exactly. All right, well, final notes. Everything is recorded. Credits I think
already wrote in the notes that for this course specifically we don't give credits
and at the very bottom there's a link to our mailing list and for those of you who have ticked
in the registration that you would like to hear about future courses you will be added to this
mailing list and now it's exactly 10 past 10 so I'm happy to pass the ball back to [name]
And [name].
Hello.
So, if we look through the notes, you see some people have already asked questions here. So, yeah, um, do, do keep using it.
So now, if someone can add a link to the slides I'm about to share while I get that set up.
I have many different computers in this room.
All making tons of heat.
OK, here we are.
So we're talking about parallel computing in the kitchen.
So this is sort of a metaphor we've
been developing to make, oh, you need to see me.
Yeah, this is a metaphor we've been developing, because oftentimes people will come to our
courses and expect to start using the cluster and think, ah, well, this is a supercomputer,
so everything must be super fast. Well, actually, it doesn't quite work that way. It's a bit
more subtle than that. So after many years of working here, we've sort of found a way to explain
it using a kitchen. And if you look at the video playlist that's here, you see one of us basically
going to the kitchen and pointing to different things and explaining how this is a computer.
But we don't have time to watch all that. Hopefully you could watch before or will
a watch later, but let's just summarize it a little bit.
So first off, what is a computer?
What do all the parts do?
This is why we're here right now,
to explain what these are.
So on the left side is a blade server from a server computer.
This is probably part of the old Triton.
And on the left side is a desktop computer
that has what looks like four GPUs in there.
So how do these compare?
They're actually more similar than you think.
So in this metaphor, what are the different parts
of a computer?
So first off, there's the, well, in the metaphor,
I take the stoves to be the different computer cores.
So the stove is where you actually do the computing
and you cook stuff.
The processor has multiple cores inside of it.
So these days, four is a pretty typical number
for processors for cores in a processor
of a general purpose computer.
The people doing the cooking are the processes.
So basically, you need some code that's
running to actually use the processors and do things.
The memory is the counter space, so basically where
you can leave all the stuff lying around
and things that happen.
The food you're cooking is the data.
And you have to do things like move the data
from the refrigerator first to the counter,
and then prepare it, and then copy it into the pot
on the stove to do the actual cooking.
recipes, or programs, and so on.
So this is the main point here.
So is a cluster faster than your own computer?
So here I have, on the left side,
a about 1.8 kilowatt induction countertop cooker.
And on the right side, my stove.
So does the stove let you cook something like pasta
faster than this induction cooker?
And the answer is probably not.
Their power output is really quite comparable.
So it might be a little bit faster, but really not much.
So why do people use the stove?
Can even be slower, I would say.
Yeah.
So why do people use the stove?
So actually, recently, a few months ago,
I had a friend that their stove broke.
So they borrowed this induction cooker and were they happy?
So they were not happy
because they could only cook one thing at once.
And that's the main thing here.
The supercomputer lets you do a relatively normal thing
but many things at the same time.
So imagine a factory kitchen that has
you know, hundreds or like 10,000 different stove
or burners in it,
then you can start cooking a lot of stuff.
So what else?
So it's really important when you're doing your cooking
to understand the memory hierarchy.
So if the data are ingredients,
there's different tiers of storage places you can put that.
For example, stuff can start in the fridge.
And if when you're cooking,
have to go to the fridge to take every single thing you work on, that's pretty slow. But if
you take it out of the fridge and put it on your counter close to the stove, then you can do your
preparations and stuff a lot faster. And managing this sort of data flow is one of the big things
on the cluster. Also on your own computer, but it's sort of too small to really notice.
It's also very often that on your own computer you do have a comparatively fast hard disk which a lot of the compute nodes in a cluster just don't have.
So there is no local disk that it can quickly access and that essentially means that you need to go to something slower on Tendency or keep it in memory.
there are some machines that have local disks but even there you if you want to use it you need to
first move this move your data over from the fridge to the local disk kind of yeah
let's see is there anything else to talk about maybe i won't go over this um you can read it
yourself. But the main point is that it's not that much slower to take something from your fridge
as it is from the countertop. But on a computer, the processor cache and main memory is many orders
of magnitude slower. The difference there is orders of magnitude. So you really have to start
worrying about this. Imagine if every time you needed to get something out of the fridge, it took
took you several hours to go grab it.
That would really change the way you do the cooking,
and you need to do much more planning there.
This is one of my favorite pictures.
So what happens when you don't have enough CPU or memory?
If you don't have enough processor,
then stuff is just slower.
You cook it a little bit slower.
But once you don't have enough memory, you can't do anything,
and stuff becomes really slow.
And that's why when you get a better kitchen,
it's not really more burners you get.
It's more counter space.
And this is something I wish more people would realize,
not mentioning anyone or anything.
But yes, so I think let's stop here.
Maybe we discuss a little bit before we go to the next part.
There. So any questions or comments?
Nothing in the slides yet.
Or yeah, in the documents yet.
One comment that I give is that
you might really experience
the situation that something runs in a certain time on your local
local machine, and it's actually running slower on the cluster, on a single CPU, if it's single
CPU. So, most desktop machines are actually pretty fast nowadays, if they are not purely
office machines. That's a good point, yes. It's just something I want to mention, to lower
expectations as to what the cluster can do again. You can do more things at the same time,
you can run the same computation a lot of times at the same time compared to your own desktop.
But the computation itself will not be faster. Yeah and that's something I think if you go
deeper into the slides you eventually get this and at least I cover it in the videos.
So when you start to use a cluster you're not a cook anymore. You're not someone that's making
one dish in one kitchen. Instead, you're becoming the manager of all the chefs.
You have to take your problem, divide it into something that 10 or 100 or 1,000 people can do
at the same time. You make the script to divide up all the data or all the problems so that all
these different cooks are working separately and then recombine things together. And that's why
why the cluster seems so difficult and interesting.
And if you don't need to divide stuff up
among lots of people to do it more quickly,
then a lot of what we're talking about
isn't that important overall.
It just sort of, you know, it's OK.
But when you do, the cluster saves a lot of time.
And one more comment I want to give,
because that's also mentioned now in the notes here.
But it commonly takes quite a bit of effort to go or to make
your code actually use multiple CPUs if the libraries you're
using do not, under the hood, already do that.
So it's also often a question of,
is it really worth it spending the time to make something
work in parallel when you could potentially just run it
multiple times for smaller problems.
So how you divide things can be important as
to getting quick and useful results
and how much time to invest into certain parts of the code.
And on a general principle, if you
can divide your problem into smaller parts it's way preferable to trying to actually parallelize
in code. So rather run the same thing or the almost same thing 50 times than try to implement
that this is now using 50 CPUs. Yeah there's a question about what's a GPU and I just really
like this picture I got, not because I eat chickens.
But so the CPU, the processor, can do basically,
and you can cook anything on the stove.
But a GPU is a very specialized cooking appliance.
So with this appliance, you can cook one thing.
You can do some things in parallel, in high parallel.
And very fast.
So this, I think, you could cook maybe 20 chickens at the same time on here.
But how much pasta can you make with this chicken cooking device?
And the answer is basically nothing. It's not designed for it.
So if your problem, like the GPU lets you do something in parallel a lot and very fast,
but only certain types of problems can be adapted to the thing that the GPU is made for.
And if you haven't adapted the code
and put it in the right modes and all that kind of stuff,
the GPU will just be wasted.
OK, well, I think we should go on.
Yeah, it's time to go.
And go towards connecting to a cluster.
Yes.
Yeah.
So what's next is [name] and [name] will talk about how you connect. So they'll talk now
for a little bit. They'll give demos. You'll have some time to try it yourself. Then there'll be a
break for another presentation and a lunch break. If you can't get connected right during this time,
you have a few hours before we get to the next demos. And if in the end you don't have a
have a cluster or can't do it, it's OK.
You can do the rest of the stuff as demos.
So now I switch to the screen of whoever is sharing.
And I'll see you later.
Bye.
OK, so now about connecting to a cluster.
Essentially, there are many, many different ways
how you connect, how you can connect.
and it also depends a bit on what cluster you're trying to connect to, what things are being
offered. We are mainly focusing here on the options that we give at Aalto, so with Triton,
but most of them are also applicable for other HPC systems. The traditional way to connect
to a cluster is essentially SSH. You have a command line tool, be that Windows command
line, Windows PowerShell, the WSL, Windows Subsystem for Linux on a Windows machine or
on any terminal on a Linux or Mac machine, and using the SSH command, which is just secure
a shell which lets you connect to a cluster.
Maybe we can just show that quickly.
Yep.
I've opened a Windows command prompt.
Let me see, you should be able to see it.
So it's SSH and there will be.
Your username?
triton.aalto.fi, in the case of Triton.
In the case of Triton or in the case of Aalto, you need to be connected to the virtual private
network or have SSH keys set up, but for this demo, [name], it's connected to the VPN?
Yep.
And then, where am I here now?
It says Login4.
Where is this on the cluster?
So essentially, what you get to when you connect to a cluster is not one of the compute machines.
It's normally a login node, which is kind of a control node where you submit jobs, where
you send jobs to the cluster, which will be discussed about later.
important thing to know about this is that this logger node is not a place
where you should actually run computations because on most systems
your resources that you can use on the logger node are restricted and if they
are in use you might really get problems actually connecting again to the cluster
because if the let's say 10 gigabytes of memory or so that you are allocated and
the two CPUs are in full use by some Python computation process even your
terminals might start to become really sluggish or not react at all
because you don't have more resources on this machine because it's a shared
resource and everyone should be should be able to work on there without the risk of someone saying
okay I'm just running a computation here and slowing it down for everyone. So this is just
the place where you connect to and where you start then distributing the work and we can also
maybe quickly show this via OnDemand. OnDemand is a service that also
many HPC systems nowadays provide and it's essentially a web interface to the cluster.
On Triton, it's ondemand.triton.aalto.fi.
So then, when I open this.
And commonly, you can get a shell access there, you can get a desktop access.
And there's one big difference here.
If you want the shell, if you get shell access on Triton, this is, again, just a shell, so
a command line for the login node.
Essentially, exactly the same as what we
had with the terminal connection earlier.
But if you would request a desktop session,
that's commonly a job that is actually
running on one of the compute nodes.
So that's, if you request a desktop or interactive graphical session, that is normally
some type of job on the node where you can also then run computations and similar things in a
user interface way. Which is why you need to define the resources that you want there.
And then you maybe need to wait a little while. Yeah. Another important note here is that
very often these interactive resources are rather limited.
And the reason for that is that
interactive resources on tendency are kind of inefficient
in the sense that
you are very often sitting in front of this and thinking.
And that means the whole time you're thinking about something,
the computational power of whatever you requested
is idling on tendency.
If it's currently running something, then that's fine, but very often
it's just idling. For heavy
computation jobs, you normally need to go through
the queue system and submit jobs that are explicitly
just running one thing. It's also this UI and the
whole user interface thing, of course, takes resources.
So you are essentially spending some resources
just to have this UI.
And if you want to have an as efficient job as possible,
getting rid of that overhead is definitely beneficial.
So it's actually not good for what the cluster's made for,
namely running big computations.
But if you have results on the cluster
that you want to just quickly check,
you use it as one way to have a graphical user interface
to look at the figures or something that would be produced.
And that's well connected to the cluster
in contrast to trying to mount this remotely
where network connections might be slower and so on.
Yes, and it's available also from outside.
So you don't have to be on the VPN or close by.
Yeah, there's one last way
that we want to quickly show
because it has become quite popular recently
and that's VSCode.
VSCode has a couple of features,
mainly one extension that's called the Remote SSH plugin.
So I look for remote SSH like this.
SSH like this, there it is, and I can install it.
With that plugin, you can essentially do an SSH connection almost the same way as you
would do it with the shell.
When you have installed this, you will see this remote explorer icon.
You can then either add or [name] already has it added.
So you can add it by clicking the plus on this H to tell new remote or if you already
have one, you can go on that and essentially indicate location.
If you wanted to add, you would add this, like the same command at Triton.
And why we want to show the VS Code in particular is there are a few issues with VS Code.
It can be a great tool, but if you connect to a cluster with VS Code, on general principle,
never open a folder or never connect opening a folder that has lots and lots of files in
there.
Open things that actually have code and not data.
And also don't open, for example, your home folder.
And the reason for this is that if you would do that, VS Code tries to index files that
are in the folder, and it does this for all files in the folder, which means that it will
constantly ask, has this file changed, has this file changed?
And if you do this for a folder that has a lot of files in there, you are essentially
starting to run a small denial-of-service attack on the file system servers that are
around on the cluster.
Please don't do that.
So that's why we want to mention here that, yeah, use the subfolder that actually has your
code to connect to it and use it like that.
One more thing with VS Code,
in general, try not to run VS Code Jupyter Notebooks.
Because VS Code, essentially,
when you use this remote SSH plugin,
it starts a VS Code server on the other side.
If you have Jupyter Notebooks open on the other side,
that is not being closed, that is not being shut down when you disconnect.
The server will keep running.
And that means if you have computations done in that Jupyter Notebook,
you still have this running and you're running this on the logger node.
So, when you use VS Code, try not to use Jupyter Notebooks interactively.
So, is it that I shouldn't even open this ipynb file?
That I think depends a little bit on the plugins that you actually have installed.
But I personally wouldn't edit Jupyter Notebooks on VS Code with the remote SSH plugin.
You can potentially run VS Code on a cluster node and do things like that, but I wouldn't
do it on the remote SSH.
But with that, I think we will stop here to leave enough time for questions, for individual
questions if things don't work during connection, so that we can get as many of you as possible
it on the cluster and connect it to the cluster. People from Aalto or Helsinki should all have
a link to Zoom where we can help with connecting to their respective clusters. I think we will
to pause the stream here now till 11 finish time.
Or is it no?
Wait.
Yeah, essentially till 11 Finnish time
and allow people to try to get connected to the cluster.
OK, so yeah, we're going to the break time.
So yeah, so this is the first exercise time.
So we will mute the stream.
We will go to the notes here.
You see there's lots of questions
that have been asked about this.
We'll put in the bottom a little thing that says what
you should be doing right now.
So yes, there are lots of things that can go wrong here. Don't worry. Don't be afraid.
You can keep asking questions here. If you're in Finland, we have a Zoom that you can join,
and we have breakout rooms for some universities there, and you can ask for live help. And
remember, if you don't have time before the next presentation starts, there's still two hours until
we actually start doing stuff on the cluster. So you can keep asking questions in the notes
during the time. We'll try to figure out what can happen. If you're at Aalto you can send us
emails to the addresses and we can look because you shouldn't be adding your usernames to this
document. Yeah, and good luck! Now you have time to read stuff. Okay, talk to you later then. Bye!
you
Let's see, hello, hopefully you can hear me out there.
So now we're going to a break pretty quickly.
So if you look at the notes here,
you see there's many questions happening.
So that just goes to show how hard it
can be to even get connected to the cluster.
So I wouldn't say it's necessarily hard,
just there's so many different things for everyone. Where you are, what university you are,
how you're trying to connect, how your computer is set up, is your account new or old, and so on.
So, like we said before, if you can't do it now, it's okay. You're welcome to keep watching the
course. Next, we have a demo of the cluster after a short break. A demo of a cluster from CSC,
see. So you still have more time to work on this. What else? Yeah. And you notice here
in the notes, there's this little poll here. So you can add an O to done if you finished.
If you couldn't get connected, then you could put an O under trying connected and an O under
not trying if you weren't even trying, and that way we can sort of see what the status is.
Yeah, overall, basically, don't worry. If this seems hard, it's one of the hardest parts,
unfortunately, and just keep coming back. Don't worry. And with that, see you in 10 minutes
for the next session, bye.
you
Hello, and we are back.
So now that hopefully most of you have managed to connect to the cluster of your choice or
like some of our connected to Triton,
some of our friends outside of our university
have connected to their own clusters.
So now we are going to have a bit of a different tangent.
So we are going to be now having a guest lecture,
our guest talk from our friends at CSC.
So in this talk, we'll be like,
I won't say what's in it
because I haven't yet seen it,
but we will be talking about various things
about what it comes to scale,
because CSC is the biggest player here in Finland,
and what will be happening.
So there will be probably a lot of new things for you
over here, and it's a bit different
than the rest of the course.
For the rest of the course,
we'll be working more on the local scale.
So don't worry about catching everything,
And don't worry about trying to remember everything, every small detail, just focus on the main topics.
And with these sending words, let me introduce our friend from CSC, [name].
Do you want to introduce yourself?
Yeah, yeah. So, yeah, I'm an application specialist at CSC, so that means I've been doing customer
support for a long time. Yeah, and the idea of this talk is about to a little bit introduce how
to use CSC's resources, and kind of the main message, if I can, if the main message of the
kitchen talk was that you need to parallelize your computation to get
anything out of the cluster other than the same same stuff that you get from
your laptop. The main kind of point from this talk is that you can use CSC's
resources if you are a student or researcher at Finnish University or
or polytechnic or research institute like FMI or VTT.
And you can use CSC resources for free in a way,
because it's already been paid
for academic research in Finland.
In addition, you can also invite your colleagues
even from abroad or elsewhere into your projects.
When you have a project, then you can invite people there.
But anyways, the main message is that you are allowed to use
and even encouraged to use CSC's resources.
And in some universities,
this might even be the only option.
Like in Aalto, you have Triton
and you have really good support in Aalto
for doing computational science.
But if you don't get that local support,
then you can always ask us.
So we are there for you if you can't find support locally.
course, doing everything locally is always a little bit more flexible and quicker, so you need to be
a little bit patient with CSC services always, but they are there and definitely we should come back
to you. And I would also add that it's not like an either-or situation. We do a lot of
collaboration with CSC. We use CSC resources as well throughout our work and when helping our
researchers and we use CSC trainings all the time. CSC trainings come to Aalto as well and
we try to collaborate as much as possible because it's not like a zero-sum game of
using resources. Everybody benefits when people get stuff done and CSC is a big player for getting
stuff done here in Finland. Yeah, okay, thanks. So, let's go then to the slides. So, I was asked to
keep the slides set thin, so I wrote them myself. So, this is not that official maybe, but anyways.
So, CSC's HPC resources, and this was the main point that I already told you, you are allowed
to use it and it's free of charge. What we have is HPC clusters, sometimes you call these
supercomputers. Currently we have Puhti, Mahti and Lumi and Puhti and Mahti will be replaced by Roihu
next year, maybe let's say springtime, early summer, but the machine will be basically the
same. All these clusters are about the same when you get familiar with them, so it's a cluster
computer. Then we have object storage services, so for data storage which is like project lifetime
data storage, and I will talk a little bit, and also for sharing data.
And then we have cloud platform Pouta, which I also include in our kind of HPC resources that
you can use. And cloud stuff is for services that you want to be running all the time,
like web service. So, if you host a web page or this kind of service that you can connect
from internet, then cloud stuff is for that. HPC clusters are more like one-shot
computations or a bunch of them or during the, let's say, course of your PhD or something like
that. You run the computations there, but it's not a service. But if you want to set up a service,
then it would be cloud. Yeah, Mahti is on service break today, so that's planned service,
which is kind of good. Sometimes the machines are on not planned service breaks, and those are
usually not the good ones. Yeah. So, these are like huge computers with lots of moving parts,
and I think it's a miracle that they are up at any point of the time.
So, on the three computers, how would you describe them shortly, if people are not
familiar with them, like the differentiations between Puhti, Mahti and Lumia?
Puhti and Mahti are our national resources so it's kind of easy and quick to get access to those
and Puhti is for like all kinds of things and Mahti was originally targeted for large parallel
jobs so lots of stoves in one calculation type of things but you can do all kinds of calculations
in both machines, Puhti and Mahti. And Lumi is then, that's the EU machine, and Finland has a
huge part of that, so maybe a third or something like that, I don't remember. But also the scale
of the machines is interesting, like Puhti is already usually enough, Mahti is more, and Lumi
is like crazy big. And usually also the complexity goes about the same way a little bit. It's not as
steep as the size of the resources, but always when you get the bigger machine, you expect a
little bit more, you know, complexity. And usually like the, I would say that
like previously this talk was often highlighted as this laptop sloomy kind of a situation where
Like, what are the stepping stones that people need to take in order to be able to use the
biggest computers? And usually it's like, it's not that complicated. Like the complexity increases,
but it doesn't increase. Like if you go to next stepping stone, you can usually get to the next
one. So because like, let's say our local clusters, they're pretty similar to Puhti.
And if you jump from a local cluster to Puhti, you can get more resources. And if you go from
Puhti to Mahti, you can give even more. And if you go to Puhti to Lumi, you can get even more
and different kinds of resources. So it's usually this kind of like, you don't necessarily have to
jump straight to the most complex machine. You can take these intermediate steps throughout the
whole ecosystem and use them to your benefit. That said, it's just the kind of small details
that differ in these clusters. They are all clusters and in this course you go very thoroughly
through what is a cluster and how to use it. Maybe I do a quick overview on that stuff and
when you go during these two and a half days you go into more detail. So how the access
to the resources is organized and this this is particular to CSC now so so how
do you get access to resources? First you need a user account which is kind of
you put your contact information to CSC and you get the username but this
doesn't grant you any resources so you can't even log in to Puhti or Mahti I
think with just an account because you need to have also a computing project which then you well
it's organized so that the computing projects can have services attached to them so a service could
be Mahti or Puhti or Allas or Lumi and and that belongs to kind of the computing project and if
you are a member of the project, then you can use all the resources that the project has.
So this is the kind of organization of how we share resources between all the users.
Often it might be a situation like if you are a summer student or if you are a
starting PhD student or something, you might not have the privileges or you're not yet that high
up in the ladder that you can request a new project, but your professor or maybe a postdoc
can do. I don't know what are the breaking points there, but usually it's like if you talk to your
professor and ask them, hey, can you do this few clicks on the CSC side to ask for a new project
and then add me to that project, then you usually get the resources quite quickly.
But usually it needs to be someone in a more senior position who requests these projects,
am I right? Yeah, that's exactly how it works. And these projects are like small projects where
you can start. These are granted automatically if you are like a staff member or researcher or
professor or something like that and then the professor can invite all the students from his
group to the project or have multiple projects for different parts of the research group.
So this is how it's organized and it becomes a little bit more clear when I show you
my.csc.fi portal which is our portal for managing accounts, your own account information
and also your projects. So all this I hope will become more clear when you see how it is done.
Okay, then another thing that was already discussed is cluster architecture. So this is
kind of important, always kind of understanding why do you have batch queue system, what is wrong
with parallel file system? Why is it worse than my laptop's NVMe disk and stuff like that?
So, if you look hard at this picture, and like instead of I have what 16 compute nodes here,
imagine way more compute nodes. Yeah, way, way, way more. Yeah, and also parallel file system,
that's actually like a storage cluster so there's multiple servers and then when you understand that
when one of the compute nodes wants to get data from one of the storage servers it needs to ask
from metadata server where is my data and then you see that there's only one metadata server
active at one time because you need to kind of coordinate so that no two guys write to the
same place at the same time or stuff like that.
Then you understand that this might be a bottleneck.
So if every one of these compute nodes goes
to the metadata server at once and wants to find
20 000 files at once, which is like the smallest Python environment you
can make, usually it's like 60 000 files, then
you understand why stuff like why we put our Python
environments in containers. Yeah. There's many technical things that will come throughout this
course, and they might be like, okay, why are these technical things like they are?
And the reason is that there's usually at some point a system has crashed because there's a...
Something is not performant enough, and now it's just done this way. And most of the clusters
are organized in this sort of a way where you have like the login node where you go in and you
deal with the queue system that we'll be using later to ask stuff to run on the computing
cluster and then it will use data stored on the shared file system. This is basically what all of
the computing clusters use, the format, of course, the amount of computing nodes, what are the
computing nodes and everything differs, but this sort of structure applies.
Yeah, basic principle is the same. And this also, when you log into supercomputer, you actually log
into one of the login nodes. So it's a separate small computer there. Well, it's not separate,
but it's part of the cluster. But when you want to compute something, then you want the actual
computation to go to the compute node. And the way to get there is through batch queue system.
And this is another story. And I think this is one of the things that we might go into more detail
in this presentation, if you like. So kind of stuff that differs from your laptop in cluster
is batch queue system. Software tree is also way more complex. So we usually use module system.
So the thing is that in your laptop you have operating system and then the maintainers of the
operating system basically put all the libraries. So when you have a program it will depend on
library which will depend on other library and that will depend on other library etc.
No piece of software lives in isolation basically so you always need lots of other pieces of
software, and these pieces are usually put into software libraries, and then
the thing is that in a regular Linux distribution or operating system,
the list of libraries is flat, so that's the distribution basically. So the developers and
maintainers of the distribution take versions of the libraries so that they work together.
But then in supercomputers this usually we use this for something like six years and then we
get a new one, five or six years, and during that time lots of software evolves because we want
always to have the kind of the newest and best of the programs. So we need to kind of update the
software stack also, because they will depend on different versions of the libraries. And this is
why we have modules in supercomputers, which kind of select what part of the software tree
you want to use.
Yeah, so if you've ever
shared a computer
with your sibling or something like that
and then you
install something
in your computer and then next time
you come back, your sibling
has installed, I don't know,
a really annoying
mobile game there
or something like that that suddenly
breaks everything you are doing and makes
stuff annoying,
These module systems are designed to avoid that.
So they're designed in a way that like everybody can run their, their own
software without like the hassle of breaking everybody else's stuff.
Like it would be really annoying if somebody is doing their PhD studies,
uh, using certain version or let's say console or something like some, some
program and now like somebody else asked it to be updated and now like you don't
have the version that you were using before.
So, in order to make it possible for hundreds of people to have their own software in the
same environment or in the same cluster, there's usually this kind of like different way of
distributing software, because you need to be able to support what you said, like six
years of maybe software throughout the lifetime, so that some people can run the old version,
people can run a new version and they still work, and people don't get angry about losing
a version of software that they wanted to use.
If you are familiar how libraries and Linux and linkers and loaders work, then this is
like, of course, it works like that.
But usually people tend to have problems with this a little bit, but for us it's kind of
easy to figure out what's wrong. So, this is kind of my ending topic. Don't be afraid to ask for help
and I've been saying a long time now that I especially like the easy questions. So,
the questions that are easy for me but hard for you. That's the best bang for the buck.
It takes very little time from me to answer, but it saves a lot of your time.
So that's why you should always ask help immediately if you get stuck.
That could be even the main point of this talk.
Yeah, that's a good point.
Don't waste your time too much when there's a person that you can ask immediately how to do it.
And especially, like, I would say that in this cluster environments,
because there's hundreds of users, like, if you have a problem,
there's a chance that somebody else has encountered the same problem.
So it's also like collects the best practices and collects the information
and who disseminates that information is usually the people who maintain the cluster,
who hear the problems from the users.
So if you have a problem and you ask the maintainers of the system,
them why I encountered that problem, they might have figured that out for some other
user already and now they have an existing solution or they might not be aware of it
and then they can help everybody else who might encounter the problem in the future.
So it's a really good practice to, if you have problems, ask for help.
We already discussed a little bit about parallel file system, so it's a little bit different.
So it's good in some things and bad in some things.
Then data management is something that has come up in the last, let's say, 10 or 20 years
to the HPC stuff.
So you have lots of data nowadays.
And as already, I think, discussed, you can, at the same time, have easily accessible storage,
huge storage, cheap storage, and fast storage in same package.
Usually you need to do something.
And this is data management.
And please consider this if your project needs lots of data.
And if you think you need lots of data,
reconsider, because sometimes you can actually
manage with less data than you think.
My kind of saying is that big data, big problems, small data,
small problems. Yeah. And we always want to aim for small problems.
And like I would add, there was a question in the notes about the Packetify system, like
what is needed. And basically, it is to serve this kind of big data problems. It's there
because no single disk would be big enough alone. So you need to have multiple disks
to support the needs of the people. And with this system, it's a different kind of hard drive
to what you normally use. So the laws are a bit different. So it's a bit like if you go to,
let's say, you go to a kitchen or a place in a foreign country and then you notice that, hey,
why is there one knob for hot water and one knob for cold water? It's this kind of situation where
you need to adapt to a different kind of a system, a different kind of a file system.
And there might be some things are bad in the big file system, like in the parallel file system,
and some things that would be normal in your situation. So it's a good idea to read the
documentation and ask the admins, like, is my data correctly set up? Do I need all of these
kind of questions and have a rapport with the support people so that you can figure out what
is the best solution for that specific file system? Basically, the issue with
parallel file systems is that they are not very good with lots of small files. So, if you have
100,000 20 kilobyte files, the performance is bad compared to your local NVMe on your laptop.
This is like the basic thing. Yes. And then on the other end, if you think about big files,
transferring terabyte size files is horrible. So you usually also want to limit the
largest files to, let's say, if you can limit them to five gigabytes everything
is easy. If you go above five gigabyte files then you may start to get some
issues in some places. Okay, but data management is something that you need to
consider for bigger projects a little bit and always ask first before
pushing all the stuff to the disk. And then the practical thing that you
kind of benefit is if you already know how to use Linux command line
and some text editor like Vi or Emacs, or there are others, Pico and whatnot.
So those benefit you in practice.
Okay, so as a senior I have to give some advice. So always keep it simple because these things tend to
be complex anyway, but try to keep it as simple as possible and ask for help. This is my kind of
advice. And then where to find information. So CSC has three websites,
basically well for HPC. Okay this I forgot to tell like HPC stuff is about
third of what CSC does maybe so two-thirds of CSC stuff have never even
logged into a supercomputer most likely so this is kind of the scale. CSC is
doing lots of other things but let's concentrate on HPC here. Yeah so what
csc. So this is kind of the company site. Let's see. It looks like this. So this is
like your typical company site. What csc is basically.
Then what services are available. So there's research.csc.fi
And this is a little bit more detailed, so this goes into what kind of, well, services
we have, like HPC services, Archive services, services for education and culture and whatnot.
But the site that probably is most useful for you is docs.csc.fi
Yes, that's a great place.
Yeah, so this has all the tutorials that we have for anything.
So, like, accounts has a lot of stuff on how you create an account,
CSC account, and how you manage your project and stuff like that.
So this is kind of the page that I would link.
So docs.csc.fi.
this has all the all the info and even this search is kind of okay for one word I think
so if you already know the keyword you can find it otherwise there's lots of material because
yeah and and but don't be afraid you only need to kind of read part of that so maybe just read the
kind of what's in it, but you don't need to go into details at once, because this is a lot.
But to start, it's accounts, and then computing, and data, and maybe applications. Those are the
kind of... Yeah, and during the course when we're also going to be talking about queue -systems and stuff
like that, most of the stuff is going to be similar. We'll be using our documentation
as the material, but most of the stuff will be similar to what's in the CSC.
Of course, there's small differences in the clusters, and there's stuff changes based on
that. But if you're using a different cluster, just look at the documentation for that specific
page and you will see that most of it reminds you of the same things. It's not the exact same,
but it looks similar. So it's like you can then fill out the gaps of what things are specific
for this cluster and try to figure out, okay, what are the differences? And then just look at
those ones. And like [name] said, look at the ones that are relevant for your use case.
Yeah. And, of course, the best way to know what is relevant is to ask from your senior colleagues.
Yes.
That's the quickest way to get to the right page.
And you can also ask us, the local people in the universities, because we often use the CSC system.
Even though we are not like CSC helpers or whatever, we often use the CSC system so we can either help you or direct you towards the right place to ask you in CSC.
Yeah, so yeah, so this is kind of like your local support is of course the, whoops, this is getting jumpy.
Your local support is always the best, your colleagues, that's the quickest and they are probably doing the same thing in your group that you are supposed to do.
Somebody has done it before, most of the time, or a very similar thing.
And this is true for all computing stuff and almost all research also.
And then you have servicedesk@csc.fi and there's no barrier asking questions from there either.
We are happy to pick up also easy questions, like I'm preferring easy questions.
And maybe other stuff at CSC can get the hard ones.
I would add one more site to the list, which was the CSC trainings.
So CSC has a lot of great courses throughout their calendar, like training calendar.
There's also the summer school retreats and all of these kind of like things.
So if you go to the online training site, there's also some MOOC courses and stuff like that,
like these online MOOC courses that you can do.
And there's lots of other courses and we often, like, we go to these courses as well.
Like sometimes when we think that, okay, we want to see how CSE does stuff, we join the courses and we do them as well.
Just to disseminate the information.
And I can highly recommend going to these courses for learning.
Of course, many of these can be specific to, let's say, one system or some field or something.
But there's a whole smorgasbord of courses, so you can choose whatever you want, so I can highly recommend those.
Yeah, especially this CSC Computing Environment Self-Learning course.
I think it was called at some point, Using CSC Resources Efficiently or something like that.
I highly recommend that if you start using CSC services.
So that's a kind of first course that you should take if you use CSC's resources and you can basically read it yourself.
Good. Yeah, so this is the base that you...
Yeah, this is the one I told about.
Yeah, very good. Yeah, I forgot that one. I haven't given trainings for a long time.
Like I do them, let's say, once or twice a year.
Yeah.
Yeah. All right.
Then to demos.
So, maybe we go to docs first.
So, let's say that you want to get an account and you want to get a computing project.
And the information creating a new user account, that's where you get it.
So basically what you do with everything here is that you log into my.csc.fi service.
So it's based like this and then you click there and then if you are
at Finnish universities you have HAKA identification. So that's really kind of the
simplest way and if you don't have Haka then you either need to ask someone some project let's say
some somebody who is already who already has a CSC project they can invite you to like a CSC
but as a student or researcher in Finnish universities you can log in with Haka.
I have now a kind of demo account here, so I use this password log in, so you use [a seprate] csc password for this [but not for your normal accounts].
And that was really like...
How do I get this?
Sorry, I need to look up the password for this one. This is not my own account.
Yeah, but if you're a Finnish university affiliate, if you use the Haka login, you usually log in with your university's own account and you can use the same.
same. That's much more convenient. Yeah. But if you are not a Finnish university member then you
have to use the CSC password. Yes. And usually it asks for a multi-factor or second factor
for authentication. So you should have some authentication app in your phone for example
like Google Authenticator or Microsoft Authenticator.
And I think when you first time log in, then you don't need it,
but then you need to set it up for the subsequent logins.
So, okay, this is a little bit too much detail maybe, and it's all documented in
the docs. But what you do is you go to profile
and then you enable this multi-factor authentication. So for web services,
most of CSC's web services already require you to have like some kind of password or
if you come in with HAKA and you have already done this two-factor authentication,
then you get immediately in and you don't even notice this stuff. But if you don't, you need to
kind of enable that and here and the next time you log in it will
ask for the authentication thingy. But I think most of the
people are kind of familiar with this already when
you use something like Mobiliavain and stuff like that.
This is basically the same thing. Well, maybe not but pretty close.
So that's one way to access CSC's resources is to use
your web browser. So, you can use web interfaces also to supercomputers and to object storage
but the kind of the more traditional way is to use SSH logins and for those you need to set up
SSH keys. So, you generate on your local machine, you generate SSH key pair and then you upload
the public part of the key to this service, and then this is the one that I have uploaded already.
And then you wait for one hour for the information to go from MyCSC to the computing servers,
and then you can log in with SSH to CSC's machines. This is how it works, and there's
lots of details, how you do the details in Windows machines. Macs and Linux are the same.
Those are really simple. I highly recommend having one good look through the SSH documentation and
getting one good setup where you have, let's say, an SSH key with a passphrase.
So it's like other people cannot use it if you lose access to it or if you by mistake
upload it to the internet or whatever.
You have a passphrase in it and then you have this so-called agent that remembers the keys
so you don't have to type the passphrase all the time.
And it's usually like, this all sounds like a mumbo-jumbo currently for many of you,
But if you read the documentations and go through the process once and read it, hopefully
you will get a system where it's very easy to log into all of these systems afterwards.
For many of us, people who have been using these sorts of systems all the time, we don't
even think about it.
like we just go to different systems without thinking about it even.
So, of course, the first time you do these authentication kinds of things,
it sounds like a lot of cryptography and whatever, like,
why do I need to know all of this?
But it's because the logins need to be secure.
Yeah. And once you have kind of figured it out,
it's almost automatic and you don't need to do much.
Okay, but the kind of point here is that you have this multi-factor authentication MFA for the web
services and then for the terminal logins you have this SSH key pair business. So, two ways to
log in or access the machines and they use a little bit different authentication systems.
But before you can go into CSC machines, you need a project, so this
dummy account probably has a project. Yeah, demo and testing.
And then you can have a look at details of your project and you can see that this project has
as Allas and Mahti Supercomputer Services.
So when I kind of belong to this project,
I can access these resources.
And then we are using billing units.
So all our resources, we try to share it fairly
among all the researchers and students.
So we are using this kind of monopoly money
called billing units.
And you can kind of, well, there's a procedure how to get more billing units.
But the thing is that 100,000 is given automatically.
Yeah.
And then you need to maybe later have some, so that I will use this to make my PhD or I have, I'm preparing this and this article and this is why I need it.
But it's always like academic stuff that you show.
And like [name] mentioned previously, all of this is paid for by mainly, I think, the Ministry of Education in Finland.
Yeah.
So it's monopoly money, so it's not...
Yeah, you don't have to put your credit card anywhere.
And usually your supervisor or professor takes care of this.
Yes, yes.
Yeah, you just belong to some project and then you like to use the resources efficiently and then everybody's pretty much happy.
Yeah.
So maybe I show next how to go to Mahti through web interface.
Yeah, sounds good.
So if I just go mahti.csc.fi, I land into this kind of page, which shows what's going on in the machine currently.
So the machine seems to be pretty full. That's why we have batch systems.
Yeah, so batch system, we didn't talk too much about those yet, but the idea is that
there's lots of people who want to run their calculations in the machine, and then we want
to fill the machine so that it's running at full steam all the time, and this is why we
are arranging the jobs or calculations.
You can think of it as a packing problem, so like lots of different sizes of boxes and
you try to fit as many of them into the machine at once.
And also the system takes into account
who has run lots of stuff recently and this
tries to share the resources fairly so that no one user will use the
system all the time.
We'll talk about the priorities and
everything later on. Those are details, yeah. But anyways, and this shows some stuff. Let's say
if we log in, what do we get? Okay, again, you would probably use this
haka and then it's probably just one click and I need to go here.
And then I need the password again, but you probably use the other one.
Yeah, okay. That's bound to happen.
That was a good question in the chat. Will the commands we learn on Triton work the same
on the CSC cluster for like 90% yes, there's the 10% of the extra spice that you need to put
for different cluster, like maybe you need to, when you're reserving jobs, you need to
set which project you want it to be built and that sort of stuff like in CSC clusters.
And there's small differences in different clusters, but the vast majority of the commands are the same.
We use the same kind of batch systems.
Puhti and Mahti use a similar kind of file system that we have, and there's small differences.
Yeah, the partitions may be different.
Yeah, but this is how the web interface looks, and this is, I think, easier for the new users,
so you can immediately see lots of stuff, and if you are, let's say, if you want to run
Jupyter notebooks, this is an easy way to get something started quickly.
Yeah, so you can browse your files, you can check your quotas, so these machines have
something like maybe six petabytes of disk.
You notice that my numbers are all off, completely off, because I've lost interest in technical
details many years ago, that's why I'm doing a little bit different things.
people who like technical details are in the hardware side of CSC. But anyways, you have
disk quotas, so your project will have a certain amount of disk space available. And then
just a moment.
Yeah. And then you have cloud storage configuration. This is quite a nice tool
Because, yeah, using this object storage, that's another thing, that's a longer talk.
Maybe we skip it now because we have so little time left.
So, we should probably also leave some time for discussion.
Yes, and there's many questions. There's a very enthusiastic crowd in the chat which is great.
Okay, so, but there's lots of stuff here that you can do almost with clicking.
So, for example, generating a batch job is basically quite easy here.
So, you get the compute nodes there, and then you say what project will be charged,
what billing units will be eaten from there, what partition you will use,
how many CPUs you want, do you want local disk, for how long you want it to run,
and stuff like that. And then you launch, and what it does now, now it created a batch job,
and it gave it to the batch queue system, and now batch queue system is trying to find
some compute node which can run, which has these resources available that you requested,
And when it's done, it says that you can connect to that thingy.
You might need to answer yes, because you haven't yet ever connected to that machine before.
Yeah, this is the first time I ever logged in.
So now I'm already in the compute node. You can see the name of the compute node here.
So this is c3101.
Can you zoom in some?
Now you can see.
Okay, that's good.
So this is the easiest way to get to compute node.
And now you are in the compute node.
So now you can do compute-intensive stuff.
Yes. Yeah, if you want to do this interactive session,
you can get it quite quickly and quite easily.
Yeah, so this is the quickest way to get to computing, I would say.
You can also, the nice thing is that you can close this one
and then you can come back to it.
Yeah, the font is not remembered, but anyways. Yeah, yeah, okay. And when you are done,
One, you want to stop the batch queue system, so the resources will be available for others
and also your billing will end when you stop the batch job.
And this is just some log, so you can even remove the log thing now.
And this is the way you can see what you have running in the machine currently.
So this is kind of the easiest way to get into the machine.
The more traditional way is to use the command line and then just like ssh your username
mahti.csc.fi then you log in like this.
Yeah, with your SSH key.
need to have set up the SSH in the my.csc.fi service. So where
was it? You need to have the public key here. Otherwise, it
doesn't work that nice, or at all. And here you can do
basically the same thing that you can do on the on the web
interface and plus some more okay so i really i'm running out of actual doing any demo
but we can have a look a little bit what
computing project might look like so you might have something you want to run let's say you
have some Python program, some task, what was there.
So this is some Python program.
This basically, what this does is it just prints its arguments to the file.
So this is an example program. Then I had a wrapper. What was that one?
Okay, so I want to run that Python program five times in parallel, so here there are different
ways to do parallelism and I think the first one you should do is within the application. So this
is like within the Python and Python parallelization that works within one node pretty well. If you want
to go beyond one node or you want to use multiple nodes, then you need to use something like MPI for
Python, some library like that, or Python package. But anyways, what this does is if you run this
thing on your local machine, it will run the same thing like in your local machine normally, but
five times in parallel. But if you want to submit that thing to a compute node,
then you need the batch job script, and that's the last one that I'll show.
So this is how batch jobs basically look like, without all the comments.
So first you tell that this is a bash script, so you could in principle execute this and all the
comments would be ignored, but you usually specify here with these special comments,
you specify what kind of resources you want. So the first one is what kind of nodes, so p for
partition. A is account, what account will be charged. How many tasks you want to start at once.
So I want to start one Python program. Then how many CPU cores do I want to give to this one
Python program. That would be number of cores. And Mahti has 128 cores in a node. And you also
reserve whole nodes, so it doesn't make any sense to reserve less because you are already taking
them. But if you put a smaller number here, then you can't just use them. And then the last one is
for how long time, so for 10 years. We'll talk about how do you write these scripts and what
is the syntax here. We'll talk about in the afternoon, like after the lunch, we'll start
actually writing these sorts of instructions. The kind of basic structure of a batch job script is
you have to describe what kind of resources you want, then you set up your software environment.
So here's the module load command that I said this picks up Python, particular Python from the
machine. Then you kind of do the calculation, change to the directory where your data is,
for example, and then you launch the application. So, I'm running Python
and then there are some arguments and stuff, but usually you have some kind of
special program that knows what resources you have reserved. So if this were, instead of Python, if
this were, let's say, MPI parallel program, that's a program that can use multiple nodes,
then you would need this srun command to launch it. Yes, it will do some magic behind the scenes
to make certain that all of the different processes know about each other. But yeah,
for this one, it's not necessary, but it's nice to have.
Basically, what this command does, this is not absolutely necessary here.
But basically, that command, what it does, it launches this many copies of the thing.
So I have one copy, launch one copy of Python, but if n would be 10, then it would launch 10 copies of Python.
And yeah, that's how it works. And then as a last step, you probably want to kind of copy the important data that you want to save from the calculation to some storage space.
So you may use temporary disk for doing the calculation and then you want to probably
clean it up and save only what you actually really need from the whole thing.
Usually programs run lots of garbage to the directory system.
Okay, but yeah.
And how you run it is batch.
Of course, in this quick demo, there's no time to go through all of the intricacies
of writing this.
That's why we have the three-day course, where we'll be using three days to go through basically
what [name] is showing here, and we'll start in the afternoon.
But basically, everything [name] has shown here, after the course, you should basically be
able to do.
So this is kind of like a teaser of what you will be able to do after the course.
And then you can choose, okay, do I want to use CSC machines?
Do I want to use Triton?
Do I want to use my local university machines?
All of this is at your fingertips, basically, after you have done this course, hopefully.
So even though the supercomputer is in the name, there's nothing super complicated in
there.
It's still a similar kind of a system as the other universities and other places.
So basically, if you learn it once, you can scale your program bigger.
was a good question in the HackMD of how do you know what my jobs need in terms of computing?
And how would you say that? How people should scale towards the CSC systems? How should they
move towards CSC systems? How do they know what their jobs need and how will they figure it out?
Scaling is a good question. Even when you have written your program so that it can run in parallel,
so it can use multiple CPU cores, at some point the overhead of the parallelization will actually
stop it from being faster and it will actually start running slower if you use more and more and more CPU cores.
And this depends on the particular program and also the size of the data.
So you can easily think this as, for example, data.
If you have a grid of data and you split it to small pieces and give different pieces to different CPUs and they can compute it,
Usually they need to kind of communicate the border pieces to the next kind of datapiece or CPU.
And this communication is an overhead.
And you can think that at some point, if you split it to two small pieces, there's very little computing and a lot of communication.
and then it actually happens that it's not faster even though you have split it into small pieces
because well the overhead eats it so and then there are other bottlenecks than communication
let's say of bottleneck like like disk io might become a bottleneck because there's only one file
system it doesn't get multiplied the same same way you you can get more and more compute
So do you think that the roadmap for users would be like first run their programs as
they currently do in the cluster, like try to get them running in the cluster and then
try to parallelize them within one computer and then maybe start experiencing the choice
of trying to do this parallelization across multiple computers and experience the scaling
bottlenecks that you just described?
You can test parallelization in local machine, in laptop also.
Like a single CPU can actually run multiple processes at the same time.
So I always encourage to try to develop on laptop,
because that's most agile.
And the supercomputers, they tend to be a little bit slower to use,
and you are dependent of the network connection and stuff like that.
So always develop locally as far as you can.
then at some point you can't anymore develop locally. You need to try the scaling.
Because the scaling you basically only know by trying. So you try out and you let's say plot
data points. I'm using 100 cores, 200, 400, 800, 1600 and then you plot how fast it runs and you
see that every time you double, it's taking half the time. Then everything is good or perfect.
Life is never perfect, so usually you don't get that good scaling. But you want to see scaling.
So if you use 800 cores and 1600 cores and it runs the same time, you are not getting any
benefit from it. And basically, you just need to test. There's no way you can say it beforehand.
But I think we are running to the end of the session, so do you have any closing thoughts
that you would want to leave for the learners about CSC systems or SBC computing in general?
I think that CSC services are available to you and please ask for help before you're not getting stuck for too long time.
These are the two main points.
Yeah, I think those are like good words of wisdom to live by.
So, I think, like, lots of thanks from our side, [name], great talk, nice, very nice introduction to the CSC services.
And I think we have lunch next in the schedule.
Yes.
So there's lunch.
And when we get back, let's see, do we go straight to our hands-on stuff?
Yes.
So once we come back from lunch, we start getting hands-on.
So we will start using the cluster access we got in the last hour to
actually, you know, copy data and run stuff on the cluster.
So if you haven't got to set up yet, work on it during lunch.
And, well, let's hope it goes well after that.
It will be interesting to see how all the ways things might go wrong then.
But yes, thanks for coming.
Between the sessions, I would just note that between sessions, we will archive some of the
notes or the notes answers, because it's getting long, which is great.
We have a lot of questions.
That's amazing.
But the editing becomes slower.
So if you have some questions that you want to look backwards, check the archive.
And yeah.
Thanks a lot, [name].
Okay.
Thanks.
Yeah.
Thank you.
I will also go and check the questions and answer them now.
Okay.
Great.
Within the next half an hour.
Yeah.
Have a nice rest of the course.
Bye.
And you can keep asking us questions
during lunch, so we'll
see eventually.
So, with that said, see you
in an hour. Bye.
Bye.
you
Hello, we're back.
I hope you had a good lunch.
So, [name], what's coming up now?
Yeah, so, now we already got from the great CSC talk that we had before the launch,
we had a quick glimpse of what it actually looks like to run stuff on the HPC clusters.
We saw some magical terminal stuff happening there and that sort of stuff.
And here now we are going to be actually like, now hopefully you had a good lunch and you're
full of energy to type a lot of commands. So now we're actually going to go through various things
on how to run stuff in the cluster. And we will start working on the clusters itself.
So we had a glimpse of what it is to work in a cluster. Now we're going to be working
on a cluster and these are easily transferable, this information to the other sites. So there
might be some differences between sites, but in the notes, if you ask questions, if you
encounter any problems, just ask there. And all of these lessons that we are coming up to,
we will talk a bit about what's what, like theory, but we'll mainly focus on demos
demos that we have prepared. And then we'll have plenty of time for exercises where you
can do the same demos as well and do the same things that we do, plus some extra exercises
if you feel like it. And yeah, first, we'll look at the clusters. What are they? So was
that a good intro, [name]?
That's good.
Yeah.
So, we've already gone over clusters a bit, but remind us, so what's the important part
and what's going to make these exercises difficult?
Well, hopefully not difficult, but it might be a bit different than what you have been
used to.
So in the previous talk, we already had a bit of a mention regarding what is a cluster
And what is a cluster? Well, it's a collection of computers, basically,
like computers that have special jobs, and you can use them through this queue system.
And how it's organized, typically, a cluster is that it has some login node, a place where you
can log into the computer and then it has some data storage in case of Triton we have two file
systems we have this home for like small scripts and maybe your logging information and then we
have this scratch storage which is the main work storage and here is where you usually spend most
of your like you put all of your code here you put your data here and here's what stores your
results and stores your code. But when you want to run stuff, you actually run the code through
the queue system in these computers called nodes often. A node just means a computer.
So we have CPU nodes that have only CPUs and memory, of course. And then we have GPU nodes
that have CPUs and memory, but they also have GPU cards that you can reserve to run your code if it
can run on GPUs.
Yes.
Okay.
That's a good introduction.
So, once we're
actually, or was there something else?
Once we're actually using it,
what do we do?
I mean, I start with my own computer
and I guess I've developed
something there.
Yeah, how it usually
goes, like when you start working
in a cluster, it has a
workflow something akin to this setup here. So often you just like when you start a new project
you have this initial setup phase where you usually like have to set up everything to work
and then you run stuff in the cluster. So the initial setup is basically you go to the cluster
usually you immediately go to your work directory because that's the main place where you want to
store your stuff and when I say you go to the like we are going to be using terminals to to like
change directories you change the directory to your work directory and then usually you get your
code into the cluster you get the data that your code uses into the cluster somewhere in the work
directory and then you install the software needed by your code and this is like the initial setup
that you usually do. How long does this initial setup usually take?
Well, it depends on a project. If it's a code that you have already created and you have,
let's say, a version control, your code in version control, you can easily transfer the code over
there. And if you have your data already in order, you can usually quite easily transfer it there.
So that shouldn't take long. Sometimes the software installation, if the cluster has
all the software you need, no problem, then you just use that. Otherwise, you might need to do
some installations or ask help doing the installations for the code. And that might take
some time. But usually this is like, when we talk about a project, it's like a few days,
is maybe like a week if it doesn't go smoothly
kind of a thing.
But usually, you start it up from minutes to a few days,
maybe.
But the actual meet, yeah.
So basically, be prepared.
It's not instant to just get running, but reserve some time
and yeah like yeah it's like like if you if if you think about your computer is your home your
laptop is your home and you go abroad on a hotel you stay in a hotel you want to like first put
your stuff into the right place so maybe you go to like a cottage you have rented a cottage you
want to put your stuff in the right places and then you can start actually like seeing what are
the sites in your city or start hiking now that you have your base set up.
Yeah, okay. So in this little loop where you run something, you see if it works,
you edit code and you run again, how does that work? What are these options for?
So most of the time, usually when you do stuff in the cluster, you are in this sort of a loop where
you run something in the queue system, you usually submit it through the queue system,
and then you check the results, okay, whether good, and then you just keep going until you
reach, get the results that you want. And here, the edit your code basically carries a lot of
weight. So, because this is, and checking the results, it's like very, like self-evident,
but how do you actually do it? There's multiple ways you can do it. It involves what editor,
what way do you want to use the cluster? Here's some examples. I hope the text is not too small,
but examples that you could use. In this course, we will be mainly editing the code in a terminal
because that's available for everybody. What you can do is in a command line terminal,
you can open the files and you can edit the code directly. And then you can do modifications to the
files and then you can submit them to the queue. Some people want to edit the codes in their own
computers and then use something like Git to, like a version control system to push the stuff
into like let's say github or version alter file is kind of version control systems and then get it
into the cluster and use that to transfer like changes to your code some people like easier
option is usually to to get the file system available in your laptop so you can you can
basically mount so mounting means that you you basically make it available in your computer
the Triton file system or the cluster file system.
So you can do the edits with the editor,
whatever edit you want in your laptop,
and it will transfer all of the changes into the cluster.
Or you can use an editor
that remotely connects to the cluster.
So this might be like VS Code remote shell,
or it might be like you use the Jupyter
in the on-demand or something like that.
or you might use the virtual desktop through the on-demand.
But there's multiple ways you can do it.
And it's really important to pick one that suits your work style
because in the grand scheme of things of the workflow,
you are going to be spending most of your time over here in the loop.
So try to pick a style that makes it easiest to do the edits in the cluster itself
so that you don't have to constantly transfer stuff back and forth. It's easier to do the
things in the cluster itself. But okay, enough about the workflows. We should move forward
and look at an actual example. Yeah, so what's our example? What are we going to demonstrate?
Yeah. Go a bit back. So, let's, we need to get our code to the cluster.
Well, first, can you talk a little bit about what the example will be and what our overall plan for the day?
Yeah. So, the, yeah, I think the example is an example about the calculating these n-grams.
And it's stored in this examples repository that we have.
And maybe, [name], you can explain what are ngrams and what does the code do?
Yeah. So, what this example is... Okay, there's a cat that's trying to sit on keyboards and
stuff like that, so I can't type that well. Okay. So, in this example, we have books from
Project Gutenberg, which are open source book or no, it's public. It's digital copies of public
domain books from long ago. And with the books, we'll do some text analysis. So, the sample code
we have divides the books into words and then computes all the sequences of words. So, for
For example, there might be the house.
So how many occurrences do you have of the house,
or every pair of two words, or three words, or one words,
or whatever?
And this gives us sort of an interesting insight
to what the books are.
And well, people like doing text processing these days
because it's close to what language models are doing.
We're not anywhere near close to that,
but you can see the starting point there.
We have this code, it's called the n-grams example,
and we'll keep doing it through the whole rest of the day,
and keep developing it slowly over time.
Maybe we should start demoing,
how can you get the code in the cluster?
First things first, I have
Logged into the cluster over here.
Oh, and I guess we should say first,
are we going to do some demos and then we'll give
time for people to do the exercises? Is that?
Yeah. So you can focus on what we'll be typing here,
and then you can do it in peace afterwards.
Yeah. So I'd recommend focus on watching what we're doing,
And then later, focus on typing and doing it yourself.
Because trying to follow and type along at the same time
will be hard.
Also, for what we're doing, we'll
demonstrate something that works on the Triton cluster.
But you'll have to adapt it for other clusters.
Because every cluster is different.
It may have different storage locations,
different options you need.
So ask in the notes in whatever.
And if you can't do it on whatever cluster you're on,
that's OK.
Just if it goes completely off the rails,
then just stop, switch to watching mode, and just watch.
And then take the time later to figure out what went wrong.
Remember, all the materials in the videos
will be available for later.
OK, so copying the code.
Yeah, so the code is currently in a version control repository in, I guess it's in GitHub.
So that, which means anyone can clone it with the git command.
And hopefully every cluster has git installed by default without any extra stuff.
Yeah.
And now we are, I have a terminal open here.
I have taken an SSH connection to Triton beforehand,
so I won't be showing that.
All of the commands I'm going to be typing
are going to be shown here at the bottom,
so you can see the history of the commands.
And that's, I've set it up,
so I don't want to break it
by doing another connection to Triton.
But first things first,
what we usually want to do in a cluster
is go to the working directory.
So and this is the first place that clusters may be different.
So on Triton, we have this variable
called work directory, which will
lead to our Scratch directory, which we'll actually
talk about shortly.
And other clusters, every cluster probably
has a variable called home, which is a home directory, which
works there.
Actually, should we just use home
because that works for everyone?
like if you don't have a working directory or if you don't know what the cluster working directory
is you can use the home directory but I would recommend using the work directory because it's
like it's good to get the muscle memory in there to go to your cluster's work directory always
because usually you want to do everything there anyway so it's good to do that but if you don't
know what the work directory is, you can use the home directory, of course.
And you can use the command pwd to print working directory. So, which directory you are currently
in or which directory the terminal is in. So, in the terminal, you are basically always in some
directory and all the commands that you're going to be running are running relative to that
directory so if like when i did the pwd it shows now that i'm here and the cd is changed directory
so you can change directory to a new directory yes okay so we've changed there and next up is a
command a git clone command which should work for everyone.
` git clone https://github.com/AaltoSciComp/hpc-examples.git` yes and if we do this now if [name] runs the `ls` command
um we see there's a bunch of directories here which are from previous work but now we see
hpc-examples. And we can change to that directory with the command `cd`. So right now we're not
going through the details of what all these shell commands means. The first time we use it we'll try
to say what it is but this is not a shell course. We've listed some shell courses and materials
as part of the preparation for the course and you can go read there or later. Yeah ls is a list
So list files in the directory.
So you can use that to check what files are available.
Okay.
And now we've got the code here.
So now we need to get the data.
Yeah.
So how do we do that?
So for that, let's try for this case,
we'll try using on demand to do that.
Okay.
So we're going to, yeah.
we're going to demonstrate a somewhat realistic way of doing things so that we're pretending the
data is not available online. So first you download the data to your computer and then
we'll upload it via the on-demand service to the cluster. So basically using a web interface.
There's many different ways to copy data. We're trying to give a couple options that will work
for most people without problems.
So I will copy it by, I'll first download it into my own computer by going to the link.
We'll post a link to the notes for the data and I'll store it into my computer's temp
folder for now.
And now it has been downloaded there.
It's quite a small file, so it's already downloaded.
So next step is to log into the on-demand server that we are using.
You can also use these to get the terminal if you don't, like with the Triton shell access,
if you don't want to take an SSH connection
or if you have problems with the SSH connection.
But let me make this a bit.
So yeah, so on the top bar, there's files over here.
And over here, I can go to work directory.
OK, got it, yeah.
And now what we see here corresponds
to what we saw in the terminal.
Yes.
So two views of the same thing.
Let's create a new directory for that so that we don't
immediately lose track of where the files will be stored.
So let's create a new directory.
So `gutenberg-fiction` is what the examples say.
Okay.
Yeah. So now I get a new folder over here,
And if I go over here, I can now see
that there's nothing over here in the file system.
I can upload a file.
Yes.
Browse files.
Here's the Gutenberg.
Gutenberg Fiction.
And let's upload it.
Upload, OK.
Takes a little bit longer.
And now should we go back to the terminal
and see if we can see the new data visible there.
So I'm currently in the SBC examples folder.
So if I want to go one folder back,
I can type `cd ..`
So I will be then in the work directory,
and if we go to the gutenberg-fiction folder,
I can see that now the file is there.
I'll navigate back into the HPC examples, because that's where we want to be.
You can usually use a tab to autocomplete, like the tab character, you can use that to
autocomplete, like if you have started writing something, if you see that I'm typing something
and something appears, it's just that I'm so used to pressing the autocomplete, I forget
that I use it.
So don't worry about it.
So there, we've transferred the data.
Should we do an initial test to see if the code runs?
Yes.
Yeah.
OK.
So which folder is it?
We can stay in this folder.
So if you do Python, and then space, then ngrams.
Yes, Python 3 ngrams.
It is count.py.
Actually, you can first run it with the dash dash help option.
This is something that each program has to do itself.
But when a program has a dash dash help option,
it usually tells you a bit about how you use the program.
It can really be helpful when
figuring out some new command line stuff.
Most commands like if you run,
let's say `cd --help`,
it has a help manual that shows what it does. Most of the commands in Linux,
at least system commands, they have this `--help` included. So let's check the ngrams.
So I happen to know that we need the one input argument, which is the input text file,
But it can also be an input zip file.
So we will do Python 3 and grams count.py.
And now we're going to refer to the data that's
in a different directory.
So we start with that dot dot, which means
go up to the parent directory.
And then gutenberg-fiction as the directory.
And then the zip file name.
Yeah. Yes. So now should I run it? Yeah, let's push enter and see what happens.
So this should analyze 100 books in there and print out all the word frequencies.
Sorry, cats is getting hungry and starting to look for cables to eat.
It's a good time to have the exercise in a second so that you can feed the cat.
Yeah.
OK, well, it finished.
So what do we see?
So by default, it prints out just word frequencies,
so word one grams.
And then it also prints out just letters.
So let's modify how it runs.
Can we run it again, but with a dash dash words option?
Yeah.
I press the up arrow on my keyboard
to get the previous command.
is very useful for if you want to do modifications or something.
You can press up arrow to get the previous command.
And you're going to use the left and right arrows
to go scroll in the command itself.
So we can write something in the middle of the place.
In the middle.
Yeah.
We're modifying.
Yes.
OK.
Yeah, so I hope it's `--words`.
That doesn't, well.
Yeah, okay.
At least seemed to work.
Yeah, and I guess while we're waiting now,
so what will come next?
This will be an example for you.
So it looked pretty simple when we did it,
of course, lots of things can go wrong for you. For example, how you copy data to your cluster.
If you don't have on-demand, you need to copy it either by the command line or you can use this
wget command in order to download file from the internet by the command line.
So it's like web get, get something from the internet, download some file.
You need to figure out where to store the data, whether it's in your home directory
or some other scratch or work directory that's available on your cluster.
You need to be connected.
So different things can go wrong here.
But let's not focus on what can go wrong.
Let's focus on what you're able to do.
So what if you, like throughout this exercise, we have basically completed the initial setup
because this code doesn't require any installation or specific installation.
We have basically completed the initial setup of our program and now we can start working
in the cluster.
So in the exercise, like basically we now, this is the thing you usually need to do when
you do any initial setup.
You get usually a code repository into the cluster and then you move your data into the
cluster.
you get that done, the vast majority of stuff ends there,
and then you can start running.
Yeah.
And this is definitely an artificial example
compared to usual work, because it's
designed to have no dependencies and work only by Python.
And the data file is nice and small.
But anyway, we're about to go now.
I've put the exercise here in the notes so you can see try to repeat what we just did
that kind of stuff. If you have problems, ask questions down here and don't worry,
we expect there to be plenty of problems. We will give some time. You can also report
Oh, why is this not updating?
Oh, I'm writing in the wrong place. Many windows open.
Done.
And then comment on the problems you have down below, and we'll try to help you.
If you're in Finland, you can join the Zoom we have and get interactive help.
Is now when we wish people good luck?
Yeah.
Is now when we apologize for needing luck to get it to work?
I think this is the kind of problem that it's annoying first, and it's annoying because of
historical reasons and lots of stuff. But once you get it sorted, then it quickly becomes a
row thing that you do often. Yeah. Yeah. And there's already one person saying it's too easy.
In that case, if you look at the different links from the schedule, there's a lot of more advanced
stuff to try that lets you really see a little bit deeper into things here. So I'd say do that,
scroll down to the exercises and try that.
And in the boat, just add an O character there,
because then there's less risk of people
adding counting at the same time and doing this kind of like,
if you ever played the game where
you need to count up to a certain number,
you know how hard it is.
So it's easier to just add an O there.
So yes.
So let's set up the projects.
And are there any problems that you have into the chat?
We'll try to answer them.
So yeah.
How long should we give?
I'd say 15 minutes.
Let's say 15.
OK.
Yeah.
Great.
Good luck.
And see you soon.
Bye.
you
Okay, hello, welcome back.
And from looking at the notes here,
it seems things went pretty well.
Y'all actually did really well.
You make me proud.
So yeah, really what we do now is probably
one of the hardest things we've done,
or we'll do the whole course.
This idea of having all these abstract folders
on some other remote system,
needing to keep track of what is where
and where all the data goes,
is quite a hard thing.
Yeah, usually like if it's like the cluster is beat up,
like it's like your computer,
but it's like, again, it's like different.
And so stuff is in different places
especially if you're used to using graphical interfaces and stuff, the terminal can become
a seem daunting to do. But basically, it's the same kind of thing that you would do in your
normal operating system, like opening a file browser or something and going to a folder and
opening a file. But all of that is done via the command line, because then you can program
basically, and you can tell the computer exactly what you want to do. And that's why the command
line is so popular in the HPC clusters, because you need to be able to tell the computer what sort
of operations, like file system operations, you need to do, like go to this folder, move this file
around, and that sort of stuff. And this is often the most annoying part when it comes to using the
the clusters, like the transferring files and managing this kind of like, especially if you have
like copy of your code in your computer and then you want it to be in sync with the code in the
cluster. So yeah, like the getting accustomed to the like, okay, there's another place that has
this only, I cannot see, but I can only ask it like it's like, you can only use the terminal
interface. Often you only use the terminal interface to interact with it. It can be a
bit abstract, but once you get a hold of it, it becomes easier. [name], if you want to share
my screen for a second, I might show a refresher of a few of the commands that we did.
So, when it comes to these kind of terminal files, it looks like we just have a blank
screen over here, but it's always in a folder.
We are always in some folder, and the folders are organized in Linux.
They are organized with these slashes, and everything starts at a root.
And then usually you have, let's say, in our case, we have the work directory is like slash
scratch work and whatever.
And this is the so-called absolute path to the folder.
So if we have the HPC examples over here, we can see here's the folder.
And if I run pwd, I can see that this is my current directory, and I'm currently here.
And of course, you can also have relative parts.
So you can have parts relative to this folder.
So you can, let's say, have the dash dot dot meaning folder above me, one folder above,
and then gutenberg-fiction.
So it's basically like you have this, like every folder is separated by these forward
slashes and then like you have this hierarchy of folders inside of it.
So getting accustomed to navigating this kind of like maze of folders can be a bit haunting
at first, but it's always good to remember that PWD shows what folder you are in.
You can use ls to list whatever files you have in that current directory.
if you want, you can always use CD to go back into your home directory. So you know where you
start. If you run just CD without any commands, and you can give it the whole path if you want
to go back into some directory, you can get CD apart and then you can go back into directory.
And this is what it's first daunting, but once you get accustomed and you know that now your
files are in this kind of folder structure,
it becomes easier all the time.
Yeah.
Did you talk about what the `..` means, to go up one directory?
Yes, and you can chain it as well [../../.. etc].
You can have dot dot go one level up,
and then you have go two levels up, and so forth.
And you're going to go up and up and up until you reach the end.
But yeah.
So one other thing I saw in the notes several times
was about the zip files.
So this is sort of interesting.
So we've written the program where
it can analyze books directly from the zip file
without you needing to uncompress it yourself.
So this was an interesting choice of ours.
it meant that it didn't take up as many files, like it's more efficient in some ways.
Yeah, but it's just an interesting design choice. Also, there was a good question about where the
data was saved. And for that, well, I don't know, I can't find it in here.
Yeah, here it is. Where is it saved?
In this case, right now,
the program is just printing it out
from the terminal and not saving it anywhere.
There's an option to save the output somewhere,
which actually we will start using later on.
Were there any other very important things we should talk about?
I will quickly mention that all of the commands in Linux, they have this syntax, this form
that you can follow.
That first command is the actual name of the command that will be executed.
So let's say the Python 3 will be the command that we executed.
And whatever you give after that are so-called arguments.
You can give arguments to the command.
Let's say if I have the count at pi, I can give it as an argument.
I will run the command Python 3, and this is called an argument.
It's usually called a positional argument if it doesn't have anything to highlight it.
It's the next one in the line.
And then you can give more arguments.
For example, we gave the name of the input file, the zip file, that we want to process.
That's another argument.
And you can also have these dash-dash arguments or sometimes with single-dash arguments that are like special toggles or options that toggle different features of the program.
So, for example, the words was this kind of thing.
And all of the commands usually are written in such syntax.
Of course, there's always exceptions to the rule, but all of the operating system commands,
they follow this syntax.
It's like back from the Unix days.
It's very old syntax.
Once you figure this out, you know that and use the `--help`, for example, it will
make everything easier in the terminal.
There's several questions of similar things up above.
So when you're running it from the command line,
or really anytime you run things,
but things are really
picky about how you give the paths and what you use.
So for example, if someone gives the path to a directory,
then it expects a file that doesn't work.
In this case, I think the problem is this person.
You need to give a .zip as part of the filename on here.
So in Unix, well, yeah, really anywhere.
But Unix, what you give is what it uses.
So it doesn't automatically add or remove
filenames from anywhere.
I propose we go to a break now.
We can keep answering some questions
and we'll come back and move on.
And if things are still not working quite right,
please let us know you had problems down here
and we will be aware of that for next time.
But during the break, even if this hasn't worked yet,
consider how cool it is what we just did.
So since we're typing things on a terminal,
it has several effects.
One, you can copy what you typed
and put it in another notepad and remember what you did.
And that's much easier than remembering
where you did a bunch of clicking.
Second, since we're typing it here,
we can make another program called the shell script
that will run these programs automatically for us.
So instead of having to sit there
and click buttons to run something 100 times or 1,000
times, we can run 100 things at once
with just a little bit of work.
And this is our first step in that direction.
And that is, without a doubt, cool
and what makes clusters useful.
So with that said, I guess we have a 10-minute break.
And we'll come back at 8 minutes past the hour.
Sounds good.
OK.
See you then.
Bye.
you
Hello. Hello. Hello. We're back. Yeah. So yeah. Yeah, that's like the recovered. Yeah,
that's the like the like the shortest Linux terminal crash course ever. So it's like,
Yeah, it can be a bit like, okay, what is happening here, like kind of a situation.
But it gets better once you get accustomed to it.
But if you still have problems with it, don't hesitate to put the stuff into the notes,
because we'll be using that example as a stepping stone for the next things.
So do check that if you can run the code that we put there.
There's an example solution now.
Sorry about not having an example solution ready.
We are moving some of the materials around.
But now there's an example solution there in the notes.
So you can try it out if you had problems.
Yeah, over here.
Okay. Here, I guess.
Yes, you can try that one out if you still haven't managed to.
Yeah.
But don't worry about this too much. Don't worry about if this seems quite complicated.
The idea is that you will get more accustomed to the terminal once we start writing the
scripts and everything like that and we start using the terminal more and more. But now,
should we move towards like, we've been talking about the terminal, how to use the terminal
and where's the HPC, where is the computing stuff? But this is needed for us to be able to
actually do the HPC stuff. So, [name], maybe we should talk about the next step,
which is the queuing system. So, let's view again our cluster here. So, what is the queue?
Yeah. Actually, you know, I could grab my demo materials from one of the HPC kitchen
videos and go and give a live demo here, but I'm not prepared for that.
that. So let's see. In short, when you have hundreds of computers and thousands or hundreds
of thousands or millions of processors available, how do you know what each person can use and
for how long? So Slurm is the thing that takes all the requests. So you might say, I have
this job where I want 10 processors and 200 gigabytes
of memory, and it will find the resources
and tell you where you can run it.
Or someone might come and say, I need between 1,000
and 1 million processors with 4 gigabytes of memory
per processor, and it will find what's available,
wait for them to be there, and then give them to you
and let your thing run.
All in the background without you having to be there
and wait for it to happen.
Yeah, and the queue manager is called Slurm.
So whenever we are talking about Slurm,
the name sounds strange and it is, but that's what it is.
But whenever we're talking about Slurm,
we mean the queue manager.
And many clusters or some clusters
use different queue managers,
but at least here in Finland,
I think everybody's using Slurm.
CSC is using Slurm, we're using Slurm.
It just rolls out of your tongue once you get used to the word, but once you know how
to reserve resources with Slurm, you can use it in various other clusters as well.
So once you know the parameters that the Slurm takes, you can get resources.
So if we look at the picture, we can see that most of the time we are spending our time
in the login node, or maybe you have reserved like an interactive session with the on-demand,
but anyways, you're in some interactive session and you want to run the stuff in the actual
like CPU nodes in the other computers.
So should we now check how can you reserve those resources?
Yeah.
Oh, actually, can you scroll down?
I think there's a nice picture here that shows
the box that's scheduled.
There, yeah.
So whenever you are scheduling a job,
it's basically a rectangle that the number of CPUs,
the amount of memory, and the time.
And then optionally, you can throw
in some number of GPUs there.
So that's the kind of thing.
So we need to define what these boxes are.
And usually, the good way of starting to approximate the boxes is compare them to your own computer.
So if your computer has four CPUs, you might want to request four CPUs.
If your computer has 16 gigabytes of memory or 8 gigabytes of memory, you might take the
same one.
And if you have, if you put outcome rounds on your laptop for an hour, you might want
to request something like two hours.
So you have this kind of like size of what is your job?
What does it need for it to run?
And then you can estimate the first guess, what is the size of the job?
then you can refine the guess later on.
Yeah.
So, [name], what happens when you tell Slurm these requests?
What does it do?
So you tell it a request and it first, you tell it what the
requests are and then the batch scripts.
So basically what will be run and then it adds it to a database
of everything that's requested.
and then it stores it,
it sorts it by priority.
Most clusters, actually,
isn't most clusters in Finland and the world now,
use something called fairshare.
So basically, it's not
a strict queue where the first person to submit something goes first.
Instead, it takes all the requests,
and the more you run,
the lower your priority goes.
so that it sort of tries to balance it out
so everyone gets about the same amount of stuff.
So it's something like CSC, where
there's a limited number of billing units
that might take that into account.
But at least in our university, it's
designed to be relatively equal.
And if we check the resources, so we already
mentioned that there's the time memory, CPUs and GPUs.
And for each of these, there's usually
some arguments or parameters that are listed over here.
We'll go through them when we are actually
going to be submitting the jobs.
But you can always come back and reference, let's say,
this page or the relevant tutorial pages
to figure out what were the magic flags that Slurm needed
to know about these resources.
Yeah, there's also on some other clusters, there's other parameters you might need to tell,
like for example in CSC you need to tell which account you're using, like which is the
one who will be built, and in some cases you need to also give partitions. So often
the cluster, if you look at the cluster here, the cluster is split into different partitions based
on what sort of job they need to be running or what sort of architecture they have.
For example, the GPU nodes are often separated into their own partitions.
So sometimes you need to give this information as well when you're submitting a job.
So in these cases, please refer to your own clusters, documentation, what magic flags you
you need to add in order to get the job running on the compute
nodes.
Usually it's like partition and then the name of a partition.
Yeah.
Is there anything else here, or should we
go on to the examples?
I think probably, yeah, I would say,
do we have anything in the chat?
Any good questions?
No, nothing we need to.
There is one question, how to decide how many resources
to allocate for the job.
And actually, yeah, maybe we can briefly mention that.
Yeah.
So you made a page on this once.
Yes, yes.
There's like a, you can check, there's
this quick guide on the job size, like what is the program size.
Yeah, and you can check that and basically, it's like I said, you can often compare it
to your own computer, like what are the resources over there.
And often you can use the, let's say, if you don't know if your program uses multiple processors,
you can run it on your own computer and check the process manager in your machine.
There's hints in the guide, like you can check how many processes are being used by the program
and then determine from that how big is the program.
But what you usually give these resources, you don't want to give exactly the limit what the program uses.
want to give it a bit leeway so that it doesn't get throttled or anything like that. So basically,
if your program uses one CPU, then you usually want to have it one CPU. If it uses like eight
gigabytes of memory, you might want to give it like 10, just to have a bit of option of going
a bit over. And if it takes like an hour, you usually give it like hour and a half. So you
you give it a bit leeway that if it runs slower this day,
then it will still finish.
And usually it goes like you first guess some number,
if it crashes, like if it is too small,
then you just increase the number.
If it's too big,
we will talk about job monitoring tomorrow.
So we will talk about how you can get the numbers out
after the job has run,
like how much it actually used,
and then you can like limit it.
And you usually want the submission
to be quite close to the size of the box
because then the queue knows that, OK, this
is the amount of things needed by the job.
So you can fit it best into the queue.
So then you won't get a bad priority
because the job you're requesting
more than you actually use.
But should we start running?
Let's go on.
OK.
So the way we usually present this
is first we run things interactively.
So that means, unlike what we've been saying,
we don't make a batch script and set it to run in the background.
But we're going to see the results right here
in front of us.
So we do that by running the same command as before.
So [name] can push the up arrow key.
And then if we go to the beginning of the line,
now we add a wrapper here that tells it to run through Slurm,
and that is srun.
So srun means like Slurm run, whatever.
Different clusters may have different practices
you should use, but this is the generic Slurm one.
And you can give, first we tell it what resources it needs,
how much memory is needed.
How much should we get?
The input data file is 18 megabytes, at least
the 100-book one.
Yeah.
And it has to make a copy of most of the books, so I mean.
Be safe and put 1 gigabyte.
Yeah, that's not enough, probably.
And for reference, on the cluster, 1 gigabyte is tiny.
So there's no need to even think about going
less than a gigabyte.
So it's not even worth trying to see how small it should be.
And then we should give it, what, the time.
So how long did it take to run?
Like 10 seconds, something?
10 seconds, yeah.
So we can put like 10 minutes, maybe.
10 minutes, yeah.
Usually, you don't want to have very small jobs.
But in this case, because we're just testing out,
it doesn't matter.
And the time syntax is like hours, minutes, seconds.
There's also days.
if you run really long jobs but that's not necessary for here yeah and we didn't tell
the number of processors to use so it probably defaulted to one and here immediately we see
something interesting so we see it says s run job some job id has been submitted in waiting
allocation then it said job has run yeah it's so maybe we should uh add the output there so that
so that we can see the output.
So we can push the up arrow key.
And then at the end, do dash o or double dash output,
whichever one.
And then give it some file name.
And it will now save the output to that file, which is words 1.
Yeah, let's say like that.
Oh, OK, now we can see a bit more clearly.
So job srun queued, waiting for resources.
srun job has been allocated resources.
It found the files.
It's waiting.
And it says it found about 111,000 unique words in there
for however it defines words.
Do you want to look at the output of the file?
Yes. We can use a pager. Maybe you can explain what is a pager, like a list to view it.
So by paging, it means pagination. So since the file's too long to just print to the screen,
it will show us one screen at a time. And less is the most common pager these days.
So once it opens, now [name] can push page up and page down to scroll through. So if we
go to the top, what are the most common words in the books? Yeah, not surprisingly in the English
language book, like many of the pronouns. Yeah, so that looks about like what we'd expect.
Yeah, and to quit the pager, you can press the Q button. Yeah, so there's a good
question in the notes. The SRUN outputs wall time, user time, system time. So actually,
that wall time, user time, system time is coming from the program itself. So we programmed it to
say what the output is. But Slurm also tracks these. So wall time is like the physical time
that passed. So like the real time. User time is how many core seconds was used. So if it ran for
10 seconds, but use two processors, user time would be 20 seconds. System time is the amount
of time spent with the operating system doing stuff, which would usually be things like reading
data or managing memory, something like that. Usually you want it to be low in your programs,
And Max RSS tells it how much memory was used.
So now in order to, well, let's check
Slurm to see how much resources it used.
Or should we do that later?
We can do that, I think, later in the monitoring.
Like maybe we should first check.
Yeah, first focus on this one.
Yeah.
So should we advance and do the batch job now?
I think that's what was next in the notes.
Yes, if you didn't.
Yeah.
So let's do a batch job for this one.
Yes.
So now in the batch job, we introduce you
to what's called a slurm script or shell script.
So this is the first time we're going
make a new file on the cluster and in this file we will put the instructions to slurm to say what
resources are needed and the instructions to our code to tell it what to run and it will all look
quite familiar with what we've done so far. So to edit a file on the cluster we'll use the
editor named nano so it's a really basic editor it's not fancy at all but it's simple to use it
It tells you how to quit it from within the editor.
And from what we can tell, it's on every cluster.
So it's a good starting point.
So we're calling the new shell scripts count1grams.sh,
where the .sh means it's a shell script.
So [name] pushes Enter, and Nano opens.
So the shell scripts always start
with what we call a shabanglang for like hash bang
with bang being exclamation mark.
And it tells it this will be a bash script.
So bin bash, bash is the shell that we're using.
So it's the-
And this is basically like the kind of magic
that is like, like you will always just write this.
Like how often, like when you start writing these scripts
you often get into the automation
that you will always write the shabang this.
You can use different ones
But usually, it's easier to just.
It's like some magic words.
You open the, you're making a magic spell.
You give the standard magic words at the beginning.
And it's something that you copy from the cheat sheet
every time you do it.
So now we see the comment symbol and sbatch here.
So this sbatch is an instruction for Slurm
to read and do something here.
And now we add the same options we did from the command line.
So for example, we'll tell it that it needs memory one
gigabyte and sbatch time equals 10 minutes.
And we could add whatever else here.
OK.
And should we add then the thing that we want to run?
Yeah, so now we get to the actual shell.
And we'll enter basically the same thing
we typed ourselves there.
So ngrams count.py, words, and then Gutenberg fiction.
Actually, do you know the file name of the thing?
Yeah, it's below there, down there.
Yeah, you can copy from the note down below.
Should we try to do two grams, actually, like now that I think of it, should we do two grams?
Yeah.
So, if we add here, what's it does in, we can get two grams, I think.
Yes, dash lowercase n.
So, now we count word pairs, right?
Like how many word pairs we can get.
So let's save this file.
And actually.
And saving with Control-X and then pushing Y.
Yeah.
And actually, I'll rename it to 2grams.sh.
That's so now it's save under a different name.
Yes.
It's a better name for the file.
So.
OK.
And now we actually do the running.
So this is it.
We run the command sbatch, and we give it the script file.
And with luck, there won't be any errors,
and it will start running.
Yeah.
I'll try to be fast here.
So [name] will push, enter, and immediately run slurm history.
No, it already finished.
Actually, maybe slurm queue.
Yeah.
So now this is sort of a wide thing here.
And maybe I'll push it.
Yeah.
So there's several key Slurm commands
that you will need to know.
One, well, actually, so this Slurm
is only available on our cluster.
So on other clusters.
I think it's also on some other clusters.
But it's not part of the Slurm installation,
but it's present in many clusters.
Yeah.
I'm writing some stuff in the notes here.
So sbatch.
But you can, there's other commands like squeue.
Yeah.
You can use as well.
But OK, so what's the general thing?
We basically, we made our food order
and we handed it off to the manager, so the Slurm.
And now Slurm has a queue of everything there.
And when you type Slurm queue, that tells you what's queued.
And we see the second command.
Now it's done running.
So we can type the command Slurm history
and see the status of how it ran.
So Slurm history needs to be 8 by 12.
It's OK if it scrolls off the screen some.
Yeah, that's good.
So we see here in the history, there's
three jobs with IDs that end in 10, 43, and 30.
So it tells us the job name.
And we see for the last one, it's count2grams.sh.
So that's the file name we submitted.
When it started running, it said it
requested one gigabyte of memory.
And it used 602 megabytes of memory.
So 2 grams took a lot more memory
to compute than 1 grams.
That's good to know.
It says it took 22 seconds of CPU time.
And towards the end, we see the state
is COMP, which means completed.
Yeah.
And at the end we can also see what was the name of the computer, like the nodes where it ran.
So you can see that some of these other programs run on this pe78 and this run on pe8. This is not
usually important unless you run into problems or something and then if the computer breaks or
something and you need to contact us that hey my code didn't work but usually like
the queue manager can decide which computer can fill your things fill your requests and it will
decide the best computer to run it on yeah um yeah and that's basically it so with this
as you learn more and more shell scripting, or not, if you don't need much more, you can start
making these programs that will do more and more for what you do. Yes, and also an important thing
with the script, when we now run the stuff, we run it non-interactively. So when we submitted
the job, but we immediately didn't see any output or anything. What good is that if I don't see
anything? The reason is that Slurm will divert the output to files. If we look at the count
n-grams again, over here we have the output of the Python code itself, or the count.py.
We use this to divert the output of the counting program to this file, but Slurm will also
record everything that the program prints out, and that will be saved into an output
file.
You can change the name of this output file as well, but the default is that its name
is slurm, then dash, and then the job ID.
So the job that we run, the job ID discount n-grams, we get an output file out of here.
So we can later use pager less to view what was the output over here.
So we can see that this is what the code program printed.
So it's the same as we would have run it interactively.
We get the output over there.
So often in your program, you might have program write some output into the disk, but you also
want to print out, okay, what it is doing and if it's encountering problems and whatever.
And you can later see them in these output files.
Yeah.
Okay.
Should we give people time to work themselves now?
Yes.
Let's see.
I will info add.
When should we come back?
we come back five minutes before the end time,
and we can briefly wrap up.
Yes. I will add, yeah.
It may be a little bit short on time to do this,
but if so, it's okay.
The course will be over and then you'll have
time to work on it yourself before tomorrow.
We'll keep answering questions afterwards.
And did we mention how in the Slurm history command,
it showed what Slurm tracked as the resource usage, which is?
We can talk about it tomorrow in the monitoring.
Right, yeah.
While we're talking about the other monitoring as well.
Yeah.
And I guess we will, in the notes,
will add the commands that we ran,
so that way you can copy from there.
Yeah.
OK.
Well, good luck.
See you in about 20 minutes.
And yeah, have fun, and be happy with your first Slurm jobs.
This is an important day for you.
Maybe I shouldn't be so philosophical.
Okay, see you later then.
Okay, bye.
you
Hello and welcome back.
So sure, a lot has happened here in these notes.
In the bottom, there's a place you can respond if you finished the things. That would be good
to figure out. Also, we've started adding some feedback at the bottom. So, just like before,
this is a poll. You can add the O's in order to say if it's too fast, slow, basic, advanced,
whatever, and any other feedback for us. So I had several things from the questions I'd like to
bring up, but it might take a bit too long to go and actually find them through the material,
so I'll just say it. First, one important thing to note, once you have the batch script file to
run things, now your work is reproducible. So if you save the batch scripts that you run
and you come back in a month or six months or a year and need to run the same things again,
you can basically figure out what arguments you gave and how things should work. And that's really
important and shouldn't be underestimated. When you're doing this scientific work,
you have to remember things for a long period of time. And if, for example, a year from now,
you have to try to do something again for paper revisions or to verify the work,
having these batch grips will help you quite a lot.
Next up, many of the clusters are different. So we saw something down here, for example,
on the CSC computers, you need to specify the account and partition for every job you run.
So on some clusters, it sort of automatically does it because the time isn't tracked by project.
So this is another case where you need to find the reference for the cluster you're using and then
well, you know, copy that and translate it to what your work is doing now.
Next up, there was some point a question about the output files.
else. Where does it save the output? Okay. Maybe like this here. So there's different
types of output that a script can have. One is the output files that the code itself makes.
And the second is what the code is printing to the screen, which is what in the Unix world
is called standard output or standard error.
And this standard output and standard error
gets captured by Slurm and then saved
to a file for your reference.
So basically, there's two kinds of things that happen.
So your program runs, it saves the main results,
and then the information about how the program itself ran.
And usually, it's the second one that you
would look at to figure out what happened
if it didn't work correctly.
So, yeah, these dot out files like this are very,
okay, I can't select,
very important to look at when things go wrong.
And even when things go right,
just to make sure that it's going right the way you expect.
Yeah, and maybe we didn't emphasize enough
in the, when we wanted to get to the exercise
as quickly as possible,
why are we even doing this script?
So the important part is that you want to program to the computer what you want it to do.
You want to tell it what to do. And in the case of Slurm, you want to tell the Slurm that, hey,
I want you to do this thing for me, and I want you to give me the resources and do it somewhere
when I'm not watching. Basically, in the kitchen metaphor, you're just asking
basically you're ordering food from a restaurant, like you want somebody else to prepare it
to you at a later date and you will get it done later. So you want to be able to tell
the instructions to the computer in a way that it understands what commands it should run
when it goes to the compute node. And the output is basically the way that you can then monitor
what it actually did. So in your code, you can have print statements and stuff like that,
that will tell, okay, I am now doing this, I'm doing that. And especially if you're running a
job in the queue, you might want to monitor what it is doing. But if you submit it to the queue,
you don't have an interactive session there, which is a benefit because you can then close
a laptop and closer connection, nothing will break. It will run remotely there, but you want
to monitor the output and that's why you have the output files. Yeah, okay. And the last one I wanted
to note, which can I find it from here, is the difference between sbatch and srun and bash directly.
So sbatch will take a script file and hand it off to slurm to run it sometime later non-interactively.
srun when used directly from the command line will try to run something through slurm but right now
attached to your terminal and it doesn't read the different sbatch comments that are inside of a
shell script. And finally if you run something with bash only it doesn't know anything about
slurm and will just run it where you are directly. So this is something that
well you don't have time to go much more into depth than this now but if you read a little
bit more, you'll see us discuss this a bit more in the notes. Also, I mean, we're out of time now,
and there is, like, this was very fast. Like we said at the beginning, it's impossible to give
a course that will teach you everything about the cluster, about Linux, about the shell,
about version control, about the data storage within 10 hours.
So we aren't even trying to do that.
Instead, we're trying to give the broad overview
and show some demos and have good materials for you
to follow up on just the parts you need later.
Because also, everyone needs different parts
for their own work in the future.
So not everyone can sit through weeks of courses
to learn all the details.
So don't feel overwhelmed if it's overwhelming. I mean, yes, it is overwhelming. We know that,
but that doesn't mean that you personally need to feel overwhelmed. It just means that you are
learning things. With that being said, is there anything else we should talk about,
[name], before I go to the final notes of the day?
Yeah, I'll add that there was a good question of, like, is it not possible to write the
commands directly on the command line instead of writing them as scripts?
And yeah, like that's of course an option, but that requires then you to have the terminal
open and writing them and remembering to write them in the correct order.
And that's like extra effort that I don't personally want to do.
So that's why usually you write the scripts because they tell exactly what to do.
They tell the computer exactly what you want the computer to do.
And then you can tell the computer that, hey, do this for me.
And it will run those for you, run the commands that you specify for you.
And you can later see that, okay, these were the commands I used to run my code.
was the actual, like, what was needed to run my code. And you don't have to be there typing
the commands, because the computer basically, the queue basically types those commands for you.
Like, when it gets the job reservation, it will type those commands in the Slurm script into
the terminal, and it will run those. Yeah, like, for example, there have been
times I needed to use the cluster. I had one thing I needed to run that uses 200 megabyte,
or 200 gigabytes of memory.
So there, I'll go and I'll run it direct from the terminal.
I'll load the data, do a quick calculation,
and be done with it, because it's only a single thing.
But when I need to do something 100 times,
because I have 100 different data files,
then I want to make scripts for it.
So yeah, it's what's it called?
Spectrum of ways you use things.
Yeah, so for tomorrow we covered what was on the schedule and if you look on the schedule
there's the same stuff, links to it, in tutorial format that has more information.
Yeah, so you can read that and catch up, learn more, whatever.
we know you might need more time for the exercises,
so keep working on it later
or for the rest of the day today, tomorrow, whatever.
Maybe we can even make a Zoom session in the morning
to review things for those in Finland.
Or ask your colleagues, your friends, whoever for help.
I mean, a lot of the things here,
it's hard to do by yourself,
but if you have another pair of eyes
who knows things looking at it with you,
they can help you quite a bit.
So find that person who will help you.
And what we did today is needed
in order to continue tomorrow.
But also that means what we do tomorrow
will help to review what we did today.
So if it doesn't completely make sense now, it's okay.
Take it for the day, digest it a bit, think about it.
When you come back tomorrow,
we'll start again from the beginning.
Well, beginning like, you know, what's it called?
You'll see new examples starting from the beginning.
and that may help to put things into perspective
and understand the power of what we do here.
For example, we'll take the Gutenberg books
and run it for every book in parallel,
and it will be really easy and very fast.
And please do fill out the feedback poll here.
There is, if you don't tell us what went wrong,
it's hard to improve it for later.
I'm glad that things are mostly looking okay here.
And yeah, we realized that we need better instructions
for what we do before the lecture.
So we've recently created a new example.
Before our example was calculating pi, now it's Gutenberg,
and all the written material isn't updated for it.
So that makes it just a little bit, well.
Yeah, we didn't have a good thing to point you to.
conundrum with this course is that if the example is way too of a toy example, it doesn't reflect
the real situation. And if it's closer to the real situation, it can become more complicated.
And we try to adapt everything all the time. But yeah, sometimes, especially when we are doing
doing a switch from one example to another,
the material doesn't necessarily follow immediately.
So yeah, that's unfortunate.
We'll definitely improve that in the next iteration.
Yeah.
Should we just end now?
We will keep, there's a question somewhere up above.
Do we have homework for tomorrow?
the homework is just to try what we did, read stuff. I mean, basically the homework is to
keep reading and trying stuff until you feel comfortable with it. There's no strict homework
like, you know, you're not going to be graded or whatever. You're only here for your own benefit.
And don't forget, if you're not coming back a future day,
Once you're done with this course, come to our garage if you're at Alto and ask for help.
We're here to help you to see you through all of these steps.
You're not alone.
Yeah, okay.
Should we go then?
Yeah.
Okay.
See you tomorrow.
Same time.
I just heard Saul in chat that yes, we can have a Zoom session before the day starts
tomorrow.
So if you're one of the Finland people that has access to the Zoom, stay tuned for an
email to come and get help then.
Okay, now let's go for real.
Okay, bye.
Bye.
you