CodeRefinery.org
you
Now, I hope you can hear us.
Anyone out there?
So let's scroll down in the notes,
which if you're just joining today,
this is the shared document we use to communicate.
It's sent to registered participants only.
If we scroll down, we can get to day two,
and we already see some icebreakers here.
So icebreaking questions are, what programming languages
do you use?
how long have you used computers, and favorite ice cream?
Should we discuss these questions ourselves?
Yeah, I guess we could.
My favorite ice cream is already on the list.
It would be Strassetella at the moment, at least, because you can't really get it in
Finland.
Well, not a lot, at least.
Yeah.
But, yeah. I think saying what the first computer was that I used might tell my age. Might be
a bit embarrassing. It's been a long time.
Back when I first used computers, I didn't even know to ask what kind of thing it was.
was just something that was there. So, I mean, I wasn't that young. I just didn't know this was a
thing to be interested in until a lot longer. So, yeah.
Yeah. I think my first use of actual computers was playing Pac-Man.
And that was at a friend's house, so it wasn't really my computer.
Yeah.
Computers, other computers back then were for, well, for the company, by my parents'
dentists.
So they had a computer system for their patients, and that's one of the first ones that was
available back then.
Yeah.
What about programming languages?
your special interest there. For me, it's probably, well, Python and Shell as the
main ones. Probably more Python. And I've messed with C a bit.
I mean, some are a long time ago, but not really anymore.
Yeah. C. C is a long time ago. And C-sharp, if anyone still knows what that is.
That was, was that a Microsoft thing?
Yeah. Yeah. It was the C++ variant that Microsoft sort of used.
And then, yeah, I wouldn't say I've got a special interest. I'll have their uses. I've
I've used at least the top 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
8.
In school, I actually use basic, so yeah.
Does using count as claiming to know anything
or have barely made modifications to something in that language
and managed to somehow rebuild it and run it?
Because I've done that for a few of them.
That was at grade six or something.
And we had a pre-made environment
where we could write a few instructions.
And that's basically my knowledge of BASIC.
Okay, yeah. Actually, yeah. So BASIC was my first language. Somehow, that's the first
thing I was aware of. And then C.
I actually properly started programming with Java. Well, no, actually I properly started
programming with Dr. Scheme, which is a Lisp dialect. But I don't ever want to see that
again.
Yeah. So, by the way, there's a place you can ask follow-up questions from day one,
stuff you would like us to keep responding to. Yeah, and we can talk now. But is there any
decompression from yesterday you'd like to talk about? I guess, did you follow all the course
yesterday for most of it. Well, I was there for the morning. I didn't have time in the
afternoon to follow it, so I don't know much about what happened in the afternoon. I mean,
I read the core script, but... Yeah. But overall, I mean, it was... So it was sort of trying
to be a combination of what we did last year, which is following the written material in
the tutorials with the pie example, and doing the new Gutenberg example like we did a few
months ago without any materials itself. So we sort of tried to follow the page and have
people do stuff, but most of what we were doing wasn't on there. So it was a bit chaotic
hell. But since we know the strategy works, I guess we can improve it for next time.
And I guess from what I noticed from yesterday is that there were
lots and lots of discussions in the notes document, which I think was really good.
Yeah, yeah.
So I think it went quite nicely, what I saw.
Yeah. Okay, that's good. I mean, the feedback, yeah, there were some things that said
it was a bit, how would you say, chaotic or whatever, but most feedback seemed good,
so that's good. Oh, I was thinking last night, whenever you're not happy with something,
do tell us in the feedback preferably nicely and constructively but if even if we know
something can be improved if we don't if we see more people saying it worked really well then it
didn't work well or you couldn't do the exercises whatever then we'll think okay well I guess this
is the right balance so it really is important to fill out these feedback things not for this
year, but for the people that come next year. Yeah. So anyway, what's today? So we continue
with these examples. So we continue with the Gutenberg example. We show how to do things
in parallel with it.
Yeah, Parallel Gutenberg.
And also, actually, Parallel Gutenberg
covers several different things.
And then some other stuff about how
to use different applications on the cluster,
including Conda that lets you install Python and R
and more types of software, and more general application
stuff, and so on.
So hopefully, today's not as difficult as yesterday.
But we'll see.
I think it won't be as bad.
Oh, I guess I already answered this question down here.
Yes, we continue working on Gutenberg Fiction.
Did you like this example?
I'm really happy with coming up with it.
It's compared to the Pi example, which was a bit,
yeah, it's this typical problem of tutorials
that you have that one minimal effort example
that works and it's easy.
And then if you've got a real problem,
Well, there's quite a big step up from the exam,
so I think it's better in that respect.
It's a bit more complex than the Pi example
used to be in Kickstarts before.
I guess it's like the two different sides.
One is the Pi example was easy and you could run
without any data there,
but that made it not realistic.
Now you have to transfer the data and
the code and make them work together,
which makes it a lot more complex
and more things that can go wrong
and more things that are different
on all the different clusters
because you have to actually care about data paths
and stuff like that.
But on the other hand,
that was sort of the point to make an example
that's like realistic.
Yes, yes.
Like what's the value of teaching something
that's that simple that anyone can just read the code
or read one page of text about it
and then understand what it's doing and do it.
Yeah.
Whereas when you have a real-world problem,
there's so many more problems
that you never got taught in the course, basically.
Because the course example was the most simple one
that anyone could think of.
Well, probably not the most simple one
anyone can think of, but I will probably be saying Hello World, which is, well, it's been
annoying me when reading tutorials that everyone starts with a Hello World and it's so, so simple
all that. Yeah. What's the point? Yeah. But anyway, now it's time to begin.
Right. Let's see, what do I do? I scroll down. So
we already have some questions here that people are answering. So welcome to day two of the
course. We start with something we've done for a few years, which is a quick, I guess
I guess you could call it an interview, but it's not really.
I guess it is, technically.
So we talk to different people that
work on our team or similar teams
and hear about their careers, how they got where they are,
and you can ask questions and see some examples.
So today, right now, we have [name] here,
who actually, I think, is the newest member of our team, technically?
Yeah. It's been nearly a year now, but technically, I'm the newest member.
Yeah. So anyway, what's your background? How did you end up here? What did you study?
Yeah, I think it's maybe a bit of a sort of winding garden path. So I started as, well,
I started studying, originally I started studying Japanese and computer science as a side, then
switched that to studying bioinformatics, which is computer science with a focus on
some biological science. And I picked neuroimaging for that. So then I, I studied
further to do neuroimaging. And that's what I did there was mostly analyzing lots of neuroimaging
data. And yeah, I continued doing that for a little while, did my PhD, did a postdoc.
And yeah, I came to Aalto as a postdoc. And then at Aalto, I met, it must have been around
the Corona time, I met people from SciComp. So did you come here in 2019? Yes, I came to Finland in
2019, November 2019. And then, I don't know, I was in Finland like four or five months when the
the Corona lockdown started,
and everyone went basically working from home.
And my research group sort of didn't really have
a good on staying online presence.
So the psychon chat and partly the code refinery chat
sort of became my coworkers, my office.
Yeah.
And yeah, then I kept working as a postdoc for quite some time still.
Right.
For, I guess, five-ish years.
Yeah.
Ish.
Okay.
And then in the meantime, my husband had gotten to work as an RSE, and then at some point
I applied and got a position here. Okay, nice. Yeah. So was there, well, the next question I
have written, what led for the transition from science, like the direct academic science to
research support? And I guess the obvious answer is it was a job, but is there anything?
No, actually, it's not so much it was a job. Because for me, I've been always more interested
in doing the computation and not so much in getting the results and not so much in interpreting
them and writing them up. So to be honest, if I were on an academic career path still,
I would probably be failing right now because I'm rubbish at writing papers. So that's
one reason. And then there was also, so when I was still a postdoc, I started actually
trying to chat with a colleague who's also sort of into computing a lot, talking about
about that in NeuroImaging, there's a lot of code being written, but many people don't
know how to structure code, what to look for to make code reusable and readable in 10 years
time or even in two years time.
So we then decided we're going to do a little workshop, just for newer ending.
And that was something that I really, really liked, teaching people about how to do programming
really.
And yeah, that was one more reason why I wanted to do more of the teaching to code and less
of the actual science interpretation.
Yeah, yeah. Okay, well, then that's perfect, then. Yeah.
That's where I really wanted, I really, really wanted to go get that kind of position.
And would you say that's what you're doing now?
Yeah, I guess. I mean, there's the kickstart. And there's also a lot of other sort of
of small things. When people come to the garage and they've got a problem with their code,
we had a few people coming just lately that said, oh, it's running so slowly, we need
some help here. And then that sort of turned into a slightly bigger, let's help you restructure
the project and get it into a bit better shape so we can actually get started with improving
the how fast it runs. And that kind of thing. And then there's lots of other projects that
aren't really teaching that are more like trying to get the code done, but that's fine as well.
I do like coding. So I'm quite happy, actually.
Okay. So before, let's say when you were offered the job, were you worried about making the
transition anyhow, and how did it turn out?
Well, I wasn't so worried because I knew the team quite well. I've been in contact with
it through, well, since 2020, I guess, with the one or the other person. So I kind of
knew what I was getting into, and I'm still sort of on a retainer for my old postdoc project.
So I do still work a little bit on the science side.
Yeah. Okay. Right. Yeah. Yeah. So it's like a slow transition.
It is really.
I also had the same, like, I kept working into other things for a while.
What do you know now that you wish someone else had taught you when you first started as a researcher or like your first
I wish I had known when I started my PhD that use version control and use it regularly.
Like, it doesn't really matter whether it's Git, which is the thing that people use most at the
moment now, or I had come into contact with Subversion before that, which is a bit
bit more complicated and less featured, I would say, than Git, but it works. Anything
is better than having files by date with the code or having final, final.1, final.2, and
kind of thing is because it's a mess. Any sort of version control is better
than what you can come up on your own. And you will need it.
How often have you had something where you've edited some code and it's somehow broken and
you've spent days trying to undo the breakage because you can't figure out what it was?
Because that's happened to me many times.
Yeah, well, I don't know how many times, I remember a few, I mean, it's always something
breaks and then there's the, especially in science, if you've already sort of written
up a paper or presented a poster, and then you notice there's a mistake in the code,
you don't know, has it, does it affect my results? That's, I think, the worst kind of thing
that you can ever, that happens and it happens. Yeah, yeah. I know the feeling.
Okay, so next up, what would you say to someone who might be interested in careers outside of
tenure track. Well, already it's great that you're thinking out of the box, basically,
and interested in this. For me, it was mostly sort of talking to people to get to know what
is out there and it doesn't even have to be someone outside academia. A lot of the stuff
how I got into the RSE bit was talking to my colleagues who had heard about this and who
had heard about that. And then there was the CodeRefinery Coffee Hour. Actually, that's
quite a friendly place to go to, or it was when I was going there. And you can just chat to people.
No one bites. Even if it looks a bit intimidating, no one's going to bite you.
And I guess you could say like all the people at Aalto that are helping you,
if you ever want to chat about other stuff. Yeah, I mean, we're here for that. You can
chat in the process of other stuff or whatever. Actually, I think a few times I just went to
Garage because I didn't really have a problem, but I wanted some company of people who
know how to code, I guess, and have a similar mindset.
Your department here was Neuroscience and Biomedical Engineering, so were you sort of
the coder, computer person of the research group?
Well, strictly speaking, that would have been [name], because I wasn't the only one. I was
more or less the junior one. But yes, I was one of the people who knew how to code in
a field where not everyone knows how to code.
Yeah, yeah. And I guess that sort of leads to the next question. So what would you recommend
or what do you think someone could do to prepare for, you know, some more diversity of careers
after they're done with their degrees or postdocs or whatever?
Well, I think just realize that it's not as clean cut as it sometimes sounds.
And to not stress about, if something doesn't go, you do your bachelor, you do your master,
you do your PhD, and then you get a postdoc, and then after two years you get a professorship
or whatever.
That's not how it goes.
When I was still a student, I met a postdoc at the Max Planck Institute, which is a very
high-profile research organization in Germany, if people don't know.
And he, I think he started out as a gardener, and he said, yeah, don't bother.
Don't bother with the pre-set path.
Don't worry about it.
Everyone finds their niche.
If you just want to find something, you will.
It might take a while.
It might be frustrating, and yeah, it's going to be frustrating, but don't stop believing,
basically.
Yeah, okay.
And that sort of, yeah, that gave me some, I guess it gave me some peace of mind, because
my path isn't the straightest of them all.
Yeah.
And it hadn't been back then already, because I had changed degrees and changed universities
a few times.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, last question, and we can...
Yeah.
Go ahead.
Last question.
We can look at some of the notes.
you want to continue learning and what comes next?
I continue learning all the time about things that I didn't know about. So I can't say
what I'm going to be learning next time. I don't know who's going to come into Garage
tomorrow and say, hey, I've got a problem with this and then I'm going to learn about
it. Because that's something that happens quite often that I don't really know in-depth,
but I know where to look.
Yeah. Okay. So there's some interesting questions in the notes. Do you use ChatGPT or similar?
Well, me personally, I do not, at least not really regularly. I've used it a few times
to just get like a bit of a code snippet or just an answer that I didn't want to Google
about, or just to try it out. I could have just as well Googled it and found it out myself.
And I'm a bit, well, I'm a bit worried about everyone using ChatGPT because people then
tend to forget that it has a lot of downfalls and it starts hallucinating things.
You can't actually really trust it.
So you need to check it anyway and then some other source.
Yeah.
Okay.
But I know that a few people use it for things that are easy to check and you can see the
answers there.
Yeah, we can see what people have written there.
What's the most exciting thing you've worked on?
Well, the most exciting for me is the teaching.
I guess you're relatively don't have that many projects yet, but yeah.
I don't have that many projects, but yeah, I think for me, the teaching is the most exciting
thing.
Yeah.
The thing that I'm nervous about before and then sort of elected after.
Yeah, next one, what's the most important skill you look for when hiring RSEs like people
for our team?
Yeah, I guess that would be your question to answer.
That's more, yeah. But my answer is there, like, it's easy to find people that have good
technical skills, but harder to find the people that want to use those skills to help other
people instead of just only developing the skills for themselves. And that's sort of
main thing there, if you ask me. There's a question recommendation for someone in neuroscience,
but maybe you can answer that by writing afterwards. Here's an interesting one.
Most common easy-to-learn fixed mistake people work with high-performance computing make?
what's the most challenging part. This is a good one. We should actually discuss this all
as instructors at the end of the day or end of the course. Do you have any thoughts now?
Or should I try to answer? I think you've got much more experience than I do.
So once someone was talking about how hard it is to learn, how to teach people how to use a cluster,
And my comment was, if you know sort of the Linux operating system, like command line,
how files are stored, the Linux fire hierarchy, and stuff like that, then it's relatively easy
to add in the extra bit to the cluster. But when you're learning to cluster, most people tend to
be learning how to submit jobs. At the same time, they're learning how to write shell scripts,
how to ssh there, how to use the command line. All these things at the same time,
everything depends on everything else. So it's quite overwhelming, even though if you
knew everything except one thing, that one thing would be relatively easy and make sense.
So that's my take on it.
I think the first bit of the first comment is quite something important there.
How to look for parallelism, because if you really want to use the power of the cluster,
you want to run things in parallel.
And getting into that sort of mindset of identifying what can I run while I'm doing something else
and not doing it step by step by step.
Like usually when we're teaching, a lot of the time it's like you do this first and then you do this
and then you do this and then you do this.
this, and then taking this, what you've learned about the flow, and then trying to think what
can I actually do out of order? That's something that's somewhat hard to grasp, I guess.
So unfortunately, it's time to go on. I guess we can keep answering questions about this
later or find us, talk to us later. Next up is a session that's about Conda. I guess the
instructors seem like they're here in the room, so you can start appearing. So this session,
So, you may know of Conda as a way to install Python packages.
But it's a lot more than that.
It's also a way to install R packages and other compiled code kind of stuff.
And we have a running joke in our Garage session.
It's day's-
Okay, now you're just doing my intro.
Okay.
Go ahead.
I'll let you do your intro to that.
I mean, yeah, we have the running joke. Days since there was a Conda question in the garage.
Okay, how was I going to go? Yeah, it is always zero.
But that means two things. One, Conda's pretty important for installing software because it's
the best way to manage Python and compile the scientific software on a cluster.
And two, it's harder than it should be.
Or maybe it's as hard as it needs to be.
It's just that it's actually a hard problem.
So us as cluster admins before the RSE things started,
the software installation probably
took up most of our time.
Took up most of our time.
And yeah, so where was this going?
Yeah, software installation is quite a difficult thing.
And now, lucky you, you get to learn one way of handling it.
So maybe I'll just go and let Jarno and you
do their introduction.
So see you later.
All right.
Bye.
Yeah.
So I mean, my starting intro was going
to be that joke specifically.
So yeah, day since we've had a question about Conda
is always zero because Conda is very useful
and you also run into complicated problems.
But if you then include the kinds of questions
where it's about installing some software
or problems installing some software
and the solution is Conda,
well, you get even more of those questions.
It's basically like a half of the questions
or something like that.
So yeah, what is Conda?
I can be honest.
The name of this page that I'm sharing
is Python environments with Conda.
And that's also linked to in the notes page.
But Conda is not just about Python installations.
It's a very general dependency manager.
So to install a specific piece of software,
you have a bunch of dependencies
that need to be installed as well.
So this could be a system,
or what would normally on your own desktop laptop
be system libraries
and specific versions of those system libraries.
You can install those with Conda
and then get the software to work.
And it's also useful for separating between projects
because different projects
might need a different version of some library. Often they're not designed to exist at the same
time, but Conda takes care of that as well. So it is very useful. It also does have some problems,
especially when used with Python on some HPC systems. So we'll come to that later.
But yeah, I guess one important point about HPC specifically is that it's always a shared system.
So installing all the software that everybody using it needs on the system level would get very complicated very quickly.
And that's where conda helps. It allows you to install software that you need that maybe not everybody else needs.
Okay. I mean, I did not introduce myself or you. Do you want to introduce yourself?
Yeah, my name is [name]. I'm also one of the RSEs. I'm very happy to be here today.
And I'm [name]. I'm also an RSE here in Aalto.
Okay. So, let's get started. So, yeah, I mean, Conda is actually language agnostic. There's
nothing specific to Python. We use it often to handle Python environments. An environment
is, so an environment is when you have this certain set of dependencies for a specific
project and you can have a different environment for a different project.
So you can have a completely different set of libraries for a different project.
So it's a very general solution for handling software environments.
And actually yeah we use Mamba most of the time. Mamba is a replacement for Conda that's just
faster. It uses a different algorithm on the background. But it's essentially the same thing,
a very small difference. So let's actually go to the terminal and get started. And there's some,
well, we load a module called Mamba. Module is its own kind of, it's a system level way of handling
the fact that people need different software. There will be a separate section on the module
system later in this course, so I will not explain that much of it, except that I will show you.
If I try to run Mamba, it does not exist. I am on Triton, we do have Mamba,
but I do need to run module load Mamba in order to get access to it.
And now I have Mamba. Oh, it printed a long, long list of commands you can run.
but it did work, so the command is found.
And then we have this initial setup.
This is very much Aalto-specific.
It's something you probably should not run on other systems,
but it's here in the documentation.
And if you are on Triton, you should run it.
So if you're not on Triton, ask,
and probably don't just take our Aldo instruction
or Triton instructions directly.
Okay, and that's the first time set up.
Oh, there was one thing I was going to talk about
before going to an example here.
So about conda channels.
Channels are where conda pulls the software.
So they store a bunch of these libraries, binary packages,
and allow you to install them into your environment.
So there are many options.
conda-forge is probably the biggest one
and you almost always want to include it.
It has a lot of packages and it's,
well, the licensing is good for research.
It's mostly open source
and the channel itself is open source.
So it's very useful.
There's also the default channel, which is maintained by Anaconda Inc., who also maintains the conda command itself.
There's licensing issues though, so you mostly want to exclude it.
And if you do want to include it, it's a specific case and you know what you're doing.
Okay, there's also Bioconda, for example, okay, Bioconda has specifically bioinformatics
packages.
It's a separate place for those and if you are in bioinformatics, then you will often
end up using it.
PyTorch, the channel doesn't exist anymore and I should have deleted that line, but I
didn't notice that it was there.
So we will demonstrate installing PyTorch for machine learning later from CondaForge.
Okay.
So I will do a quick example of creating an environment with R. This page is about Python,
but you can also install R and R packages there.
Or any questions?
Anything before we delve in?
I have a question, actually.
Yeah.
How to exclude the defaults from the channel,
from the conda config or from the YAML file?
I always use the YAML files,
And I guess, well, let's make a YAML file.
I mean, so yeah, I always use the YAML files instead
of the config, because the file, essentially,
you can have it with the code and with the whatever version
that you've been running that has produced a specific result,
specific.
You can include it with your paper, basically.
So everybody can reproduce the same thing.
So if you push it to a GitHub repo, it will be there?
Yeah.
Then everyone can reproduce?
That's good.
Yeah.
Was there anything else about environments and managing software in general?
I guess we can come back to any questions if there's there.
there. Left side of my terminal is slightly off screen. So now it should be on the screen,
I think. Okay. Okay. So in order to create an environment, my workflow and workflow I
generally recommend is to create a YAML file. So let's make, I use a Vim to edit the file.
can use nano or whichever you want. I'm creating a file called tidyverse.yml or yaml and this will
describe the entire software environment for my project. So first name for the environment
and I will call it tidyverse. Tidyverse is an R package or an R, well it is a single package
but it contains a lot of useful things.
Then I will describe the channels. So this is a list of channels that
Mamba or Conda is allowed to use to construct this environment.
I will say Conda Forge. That's the only one I need for this one.
Okay and then dependencies. So this is the list of software we actually need
and I will only specify one, r-tidyverse. So because this r-tidyverse depends on r,
we will also get r, the entire programming language ecosystem, into this environment
and it will automatically have a version that supports whatever version of r-tidyverse it
pulls up. You could specify a specific version. I don't actually know what versions
exist though so let me not just do that.
Okay and then I'm saving the file so have it on the screen. Let's cat it.
So this is what the file looks like although very quickly
it will actually disappear off the screen when I run
the next command. So we can do mamba. I actually did not write down the
command. So let's see if I get it right. Mamba env for environment, create,
minus f, f stands for file, and tidyverse. Okay, so now it's looking for first tidyverse
in ContaForge and then it looks for possible dependencies. It's
It's taking a while before printing again.
OK, here we go.
So it found a bunch of stuff.
If I had one more character width on the display,
it wouldn't break the lines, but that's fine.
So yeah, it takes a while to download all of this.
Tidyverse is relatively small, so it doesn't take that long.
That's why I chose it.
But it takes a while to get all of the system libraries,
like X-Org, the window manager, graphics manager,
display manager for Linux, and a lot of other stuff.
FontConfig and GNU, C libraries, all sorts of stuff.
OK.
So it is essentially constructing an entire software
environment.
me oh okay it's done then i will not yet take a look at the um the chat uh the notes
okay yeah there's a question uh asking us to clean the terminal so that they can see the
commands on top so maybe move the terminal a bit upper or clean the terminal so um i guess
does it mean that they cannot see the lowest line? Yes, I think that's the problem. Okay,
you can move it up a little bit. Maybe that's it. Maybe run clear.
So, I want to comment on the text that is showing here. So, because in a lot of systems,
you actually do not want to run this command. On Triton, you do not want to run this command.
So, instead, we use source activate tidyverse.
But okay, let me clear the terminal first.
The reason that we don't want to run this command is that it requires you to modify
the shell environment in some way.
You need to run this mamba init command.
will tell you to run it if you run this mamba activate. So we want to avoid that to avoid
complicating things even more. So instead we run not mamba activate but source activate tidyverse.
Okay, so now it's showing that this particular environment is active and since I have it
active now, I have for example the R script command.
So let's make a HelloTidy.r, an R script.
If I was using a graphical system,
I could also run RStudio, for example.
OK, I'm not going to explain that much about what
is happening in this script.
But maybe I should say it will check
if I actually have Tidyverse.
and then it will tell me and it will say tidyverse could not be loaded or dplyr could not be loaded.
So I can use our script to run hello tidy
and it should report that the tidyverse library is available.
Okay, and there were some conflicts that became errors.
It loaded successfully, though.
I do not know enough about R to actually know if this is a problem or not.
Probably not a huge problem.
Okay.
So, yeah, that's the point of this demonstration, though, is to show you how to
to record the dependencies in a YAML file,
and also to show you that this is not just for Python,
that you can install a lot of other things as well.
The next thing, though, will be Python,
because it will be how to set up an environment
for a large language model.
How are we doing on time?
Not bad.
Okay, so
next
I have a section
about why you should track
dependencies, which we actually
did touch on a little bit.
So maybe
at this point, do we have any questions
in the notes?
Or do you have
have other questions just in general? There's a question about how do I exit the environment
tab? I think that's asking about the deactivation. Yes, so now I still have the tidyverse environment
active and that means I do have for example rscript. Version of rscript is yes. So to exit I
could run source deactivate.
Okay. It will complain about the source activate, source deactivate
thing but I do not want to like change the environment to run mamba
activate and mamba deactivate so this is fine.
Now if I try to run our script
version. It will not find R script. So now I'm outside the environment. I don't have
R anymore and I don't have the libraries. Okay.
Okay, there's another question about, it's kind of like a Python 3.0, I suppose it's
asking the Python's own virtualenv and how it's different from Conda.
Yeah, so, oh, so I guess like venv or venv comes with Python 3.
Yeah.
So, yeah, there's plenty of different environment managers.
The Python 3 venv thing is designed for Python specifically.
It can install Python packages.
So it cannot install system level packages.
it cannot install R for you.
So Conda is more general.
It's not just for Python, and it can install
some system-level things.
So for example, we'll soon install an environment
that has CUDA in it without you needing
to set it up for your system in the same way.
Yeah, I think maybe it's the time to go to the next question.
But there is also a question about the CSC thing.
The background of this is that Conda creates a lot of files in the environment, especially
if you install Python packages, it can be millions of files.
And this is often bad on an HPC system.
So if you want to use Conda to manage environments,
there is this solution from CSC called
Tykky, the container wrapper.
So it can create something very much like a Conda environment
for you.
It is actually a Conda environment,
but wrapped into a single file that is a container.
So you can read up about it in here.
And yes, there is a link to it already in the notes.
So most of the things I say apply,
but the commands are different.
And this is probably true on a lot of systems.
So yeah, if you're using a different system,
you do need to figure out how to do this in your system.
Maybe there is even a different manager.
OK.
But yeah, so let's move on.
Okay, so we already mentioned,
talked about how using a Conda environment,
so using a file like this inside your code
makes your code and your research more reproducible.
reproducible. So you can track the entire environment, your entire coding environment,
in a single file. And then you can include it either with your code or with your data,
for example. So if you publish a bunch of data, you can include some software to
to analyze the data and you can include a file that describes the entire environment
that you use to analyze the data so that it is way more reproducible.
People can install your environment and run your code and get the results from your data.
It also helps with debugging, so you will get a lot less of the it works on my machine
problem when other people can reproduce the same environment that you have and it allows version
controlling so if you are doing some heavy software development you are probably hopefully
using version control with your software and you can also conversion your environments so you can
create different versions for different versions of the software so it is it's very useful in for
yourself it also it is very useful for helping your teammates your people in your research group
set up the same environment and run the same code so you can give them the file and give them these
two three commands and they will be able to they will have the same software environment as you do
it also works across different operating systems
with some caveats.
So Windows might require different versions
of system libraries,
but if you don't specify exact versions,
they will mostly figure out to you
how to use the correct ones.
Yes.
So it also helps with a lot of this Python dependency
problems and especially problems
where you need multiple different versions
of the same package for different versions
of your software, different projects.
So those are the main points
for why to use conda in general,
or why to use software environments in general.
It becomes very,
it becomes an especially useful thing
if you have multiple projects running
at the same time with different code.
Okay.
So there's one more thing that I want to mention about practically how to use this.
So we have it somewhere. There are some
a list of useful commands that I could also demonstrate while we go.
So I still have mamba and now that I have an environment I can run.
one more. I was not in an environment. I exited the main. So, okay. If you're in an environment,
you can list. So, let's activate the environment. High diverse. Source activate high diverse.
And let's try. So, you can list all of the packages that are in the environment for additional
reproducibility to make it extra clear what's in,
and then to check to do some debugging
on what is installed in your system, in your environment.
Okay, you can also remove an environment,
but really with this,
which is necessary and useful occasionally,
cleaning the cache is necessary
if you run out of disk space.
But the main thing that I want to highlight
is how to update an environment.
So you can install a package directly into the environment that already exists,
but what I would do essentially always is I have this idverse.yaml file
is to edit the file. So what should I add?
I have R already but I can add it explicitly as a dependency and I could specify a version
for example. So let's see. So now I can run mamba-env-update and then use
minus-f or minus-minus-file and the environment file.
So let's see if it works when I specify the R. I did not specify a R version, I just specified
that I want R. It did install some new packages, which is interesting. Maybe I didn't have the
R command specifically before I just had R script.
Okay, so you can update the environment,
you can add new packages to the environment
and keep track of them in the file as you go, which makes it
makes the file more useful in the long run.
Okay, so here's about setting default channels and like I said I
always use the yaml file to track the channels but you can set default channels in your
conda rc file or in your conda configuration and that can also be useful
okay and that's the motivation for using conda section which essentially we already talked about
So yes. And a section about how to set up environment with CUDA, which we'll be talking
about next. But essentially, I will do this by not that much looking at the documentation,
which you can read yourself, but rather by just creating a new environment. So let's see how it
goes. So, let's create a new environment file. And this time, I want to develop some
language models, large language models with Python and PyTorch.
So, to do that, I will create a new environment. Let's call it PyTorch.yml.
And, again, the environment needs a name.
So I'll call it PyTorch and we'll need to list some channels.
So now we want NVIDIA as one of the channels because this environment will depend on CUDA
and that comes from the NVIDIA channel or some CUDA-related packages come from there.
We'll also want to use CoinderForge. That is almost always there.
And then list the dependencies. Dependencies. It is correct, I think. Yes. Okay.
We will definitely need Python, and I want to specify the version of Python,
because if you  it's actually missing a dash here, a minus sign there.
So if you don't specify, it will probably  well, it will first of all try to check all different
Python versions or possible PyTorch packages. And that will take a long time. Not as long as
installing PyTorch, but still. So that's one reason. But also, it will probably actually try
Python 3.13 and then just fail because I think some of the packages don't exist for Python 3.13.
I'm not sure why it doesn't figure it out before it tries to install, but there's something there,
some configuration issue somewhere there in the packages.
Might actually be useful to just demonstrate what a failure looks like, right?
Okay, well, actually, that will come, so let's see.
So we want PyTorch GPU, and I'll just specify larger than 2.6, less than 2.7, mostly just
to show the syntax, but also because I don't remember the exact version.
I didn't write it down in the notes on purpose.
So TorchVision, this is often useful if you are dealing with image models.
Let's do TorchAudio as well.
Just commonly installed in the PyTorch environment, although if I'm using large language models,
maybe I don't need them.
But I do need definitely these transformers.
Okay.
So there's some useful packages for machine learning stuff.
And let's save this file and show what's in there.
Okay.
And then let's see how long it takes to construct the environment.
So mambaenv create and use the PyTorch file.
The first thing it does is it recognizes that I'm on a Linux system. It can also use no-arch
version, so no architecture or system-independent packages, and then it's looking for specifically
system packages and dependencies that work on Linux to get all of these dependencies.
Okay, so we have a critical issue.
I almost transitioned to the nodes, but not quite.
So the problem here is that it doesn't find CUDA.
And it doesn't find CUDA because we don't actually have any GPUs
on the login node.
So there are nodes on Triton that have GPUs,
but on almost any HPC system,
you're not gonna have GPUs on the login node.
So that is confusing, Mamba, yeah.
And it's thinking that you're trying to install
some GPU dependent stuff on a system that doesn't have them.
I mean, technically it is correct about that,
But I still do want to install this environment that
depends on GPUs existing in the system.
So we can override the CUDA version
and just tell it that we have CUDA 12.6.
So that is also mentioned here in the notes here.
So we export that, and then we try again.
So mamba and create pytorch.yaml.
Okay, so this version of the command worked yesterday,
so we'll see.
It's always possible that some library got updated
and broken somehow.
But while we wait, let's see if there's any
other interesting questions in the notes
or important questions.
What are the channels?
So yeah, I guess we went over this maybe a bit too quickly.
But yeah, channels are repositories of packages.
So they are servers somewhere that store all the packages
that you might need.
Well, all the packages that somebody has added to them.
So conda-forge is one of them.
And it says, it contains a lot of different packages
that most things depend on.
So conda-forge includes torch-vision here.
I think `transformers` also comes from conda-forge.
Does anything actually, there's also
the NVIDIA channel that we included.
Does anything actually come from there?
Yes. Some libraries that have to do with CUDA and
with NVIDIA GPU specifically are coming from the NVIDIA channel.
So conda-forge is the big channel that has a lot of open source packages and most stuff comes from
there. But Nvidia has things that Nvidia maintains. So this is a channel where Nvidia provides a
bunch of packages and it's necessary for this environment. Okay, so let's run this to install
the environment and this will take a while. It should succeed but the main point though is how
to create the environment and how to use it and not actually finishing this download process
where it gets all of the PyTorch and all of the system stuff. But yeah so it is actually now
downloading this from the
channel is where it's actually pulling all of these dependencies.
If you have something cached, will it be faster?
Yes, definitely. If you have a similar environment
installed before, then it will be faster, right?
And I think it will even slightly prefer cached versions if they exist, but also
quite often when you create one environment and then you create another one with almost the same
requirement, it will still end up using slightly different versions and redownload stuff.
But yeah, in principle it does cache the packages.
I think it also done some fancy system or fancy linking where it actually uses the same
files in different environments if it just has the same exact same version of the package.
Okay. I think it's almost done. And so is also our time. So, unless there's anything
else, I guess we could move on to a break. I mean, showing that it works is kind of fun,
but not necessarily worth the wait. So, what is next on the schedule?
I think it's a break, or?
Yes.
Yeah, we have a short break.
And then we get back to hands-on with, I think,
it's Array Jobs, which is the start of Parallelism
and the Power of the Cluster.
OK, so I'll stick around and answer questions, of course.
There's a number of questions coming up, so just keep them coming.
So I guess, I guess we have a break until two minutes past the hour.
So yes, there it is.
See you later.
Bye.
See you.
you
Hello.
Welcome back.
I hope you can hear us out there.
Hello, hello.
So, where are we now?
What's going on?
So, [name], can you let us know what's upcoming?
Yeah, so we had great talks in the morning with [name] and [name] and [name], and now we
are jumping back to where we left off yesterday.
So yesterday we were writing stuff, we were running stuff in the queue, like we were testing
stuff in the queue and we were testing out the submission scripts. So, we were trying out
how we can write scripts that can be run in the queue. So, they can be run like we can submit
them to the queue and the queue will run them later on. So, that was the thing that we were
doing yesterday. And now we are going to get further in our users of the cluster because
we don't only want to do one thing usually, we want to do a lot of things. So that's why we want
to make it so that we can run a lot of stuff. So that involves parallelism. And the parallel
is like the whole thing about this day.
So we'll first talk a bit about different ways
of doing stuff in parallel in cluster,
because we have a lot of computers in the cluster
and we want to use as much as we can
to get all of our stuff done.
And we'll talk about the different ways you can do it.
And then we'll tackle three of those four ways today.
So we'll talk about array jobs,
then we'll talk about a shared memory parallelism and then
MPI jobs.
And that's about it.
And we'll do some exercises on those.
OK, great.
So I guess I'll switch to my screen.
And so what now?
Where do we start?
So let's first look at, if you want
Let's just show the serial jobs, what we were doing previously.
Let's look at a diagram that might refresh us.
So previously, we were writing these scripts, and we were doing also interactive runs, where
we were running something in the compute nodes.
And we were currently using only one computer, only one processor.
And these are called serial jobs, because they do the commands in order.
They run like a series of commands.
Like we write one script and then we execute that in the cluster and it executes everything
in order, like it does everything.
And it uses one CPU currently.
So we're taking only a small slice of the whole cluster.
Like we are taking one CPU in one node and the whole cluster is a big thing.
So we want to use more.
And the first and the easiest way of doing this is usually to split up your job, what
you're basically doing, split up what you're doing and do an array job.
So maybe we could talk about the different parallelism modes and let's, we could maybe
show a picture of an array job.
Yeah.
So I'm opening this, the parallel one from the schedule.
I guess we're looking at these things.
So let's go down.
This is an Array Job.
So what's the characteristic here?
So the idea behind Array Job is basically like, let's say you have a script that describes
what you want to do, but you want to do it with multiple data sets, or you want to do
it with multiple different random numbers, or you want to do it with different options,
different startup options.
You want to have different parameters for your model or something.
But they're basically the same thing, but there's something that changes.
And you want to do the same thing.
So we take the big problem, you make it a bunch of small problems, and each small problem
is only slightly different.
And you can basically load up every small available place on the cluster.
You get independent jobs, and it's often called embarrassingly parallel, not because it's
not embarrassing to use it, but it's because it's so easy to parallelize.
Previously, we had the HPC kitchen metaphor, and we talked about CPUs being like stove top
burners. So if you put two kettles in two different burners, they're independent of each
other. They're not interacting, but you can cook two pasta varieties in different pots,
And they work independently of each other in independent learners. So this is basically
the idea. So the array jobs are spread out throughout the cluster. And there's this nice
syntax that you can use to easily create even a large array job of, let's say, 100 jobs running
at the same time. And each of them works independently. Okay. So we're not doing it now,
but should we preview the things we'll do? Is it the end of the day?
Yes. So the other methods that we're going to be talking about are a bit more involved. And the
first one of these is shared memory parallelism. And this is basically what your laptop is doing
right now, or your computer. You have multiple processors in your computer, but it's all inside
this one computer, right? Like you don't have other computer there like connected to that.
You only have one computer, but it has multiple processors. So you can, if you have a problem
that way, it suits the problem. You can use multiple processors in the same machine
to calculate something faster. So this is like, this just usually makes calculations faster if
if your program supports it.
Yeah, and I guess this is relatively easy to do.
Yeah, so your job ends up in one of the computers
and then you can have multiple processors
working together to solve a bigger problem.
And this is like, it's of course limited
by the size of the computer
that you're going to be using or getting,
but this is something that we'll be talking
in more detail later on.
Yeah.
Okay.
And finally we have the shared or
We have MPI jobs.
Message passing.
Yeah. So message passing jobs.
So, so this is like the traditional
high performance computing, like supercomputing.
If you think about like big weather models or whatever
they often use, or most often use
this message passing interface,
which is like this standard that has been created
since the 90s or something like that,
that makes it possible for a lot of different processors
in different computers to know about each other
and talk with each other to solve a really big problem.
So it can, you can utilize multiple computers
at the same time, and you need to, you can, you can,
like each of these can communicate with each other,
but this is a bit more involved
and it's specific for programs that use this.
So we'll talk about this later,
but nowadays I think vast majority of problems
are Array Jobs or like vast majority of parallelism
is nowadays Array Jobs or shared memory,
but in the big clusters, the MPI is still a very big thing.
Right, yeah.
Okay, so should we get started with Array Jobs then?
Yeah.
I'll close this window and let's go pin array jobs.
Yes. We're going to be demoing few of the array jobs,
and we're going to contrast them
with the serial job that we did yesterday.
If you didn't manage to do it yesterday or if you weren't here,
There's instructions in the notes on how you can bring yourself up to speed.
So basically how you can download the example data set and the examples repository.
And there's an example like solution script for the CDL job script, so that we can like
then compare the results.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, since I didn't do the typing yesterday, I've set up where I've walked into the cluster
and I've copied the data to my personal work directory
in a Gutenberg Fiction folder, just like before.
So hopefully, it will be pretty similar to what
we did yesterday.
We're in a fairly similar place.
Yeah, so I guess the first thing I'll do when I've logged in,
I want to see where we are.
So I type `pwd`, and I'm in my home directory.
And I know I need to go to the same place I was yesterday,
which is the HPC examples directory. So I'll change there.
Yeah. It's always a good idea to go to the work directory whenever you go to the cluster.
Yeah. And verify where you are before you start running commands.
Yeah. It's a small but important thing.
OK, so here we are.
So do we have the do you have the previous script there?
The previous?
No.
Maybe let's go over.
Well, let's.
Well, then.
Yeah, let's.
We can.
I can copy it from the notes here.
If you'd like.
Yeah, let's.
Yeah, let's do that.
So nano.
What was it called?
count-ngrams-2.sh
Yes.
Yes. And I'll just put it in this directory, I guess.
So, do you want to remind us what these things are as I type them?
Yes. So, there's the first line is the is the shebang or that tells which like it's the magic
that runs everything with the terminal. I think our pictures are a bit cutting off the terminals.
Yes, and then we need to tell the queue system what were the requirements that we want, what
memory we want, what time we want, and then we need to tell what we want to actually run.
In this case, it was the n-grams.
We took the two grams, so every two-word pair, and we wanted to get those calculated.
And we gave it the folder of where we had the dataset downloaded and part of the dataset
that we wanted to analyze.
And you can use, [name] is using this backslash syntax.
So if you put, as the last character, you put this backslash, you can continue from
the next line.
So basically, it means that just continue, combine these together so that you can fit
more stuff into the, without wrapping.
And make sure it's the very last line.
Should I run this just to make sure that it actually works?
Yeah, let's do that.
So I do Control-X to exit.
Y, yes.
Yeah.
So now [name] is checking that it's in the queue.
So it is running.
It's the last one over there.
Yeah.
So it is running, and then it probably finishes quite quickly.
Yeah, it takes a minute to run.
But now the question is that, okay, like this is quite a simple program, but let's imagine
that our data would be a lot bigger.
So let's imagine that we would have a lot bigger of a data set.
So in that case, we might want to do these calculations of these n-grams in, or like
we would want to do it in pieces, right?
Like, we don't necessarily want to have one job that does everything.
We could do it so that, like, every job, like, we could split it up, the program, so that
every, we could split it up to, let's say, ten programs, that each program would do
one-tenth of the analysis.
So are you roughly saying we have 100 books in this sample data?
So we'll have one program do 10 books, the next do 10 more books, and so on.
We can run 10 things at the same time, and then I guess that means we get 10 different
output files?
Yes.
That have to be combined?
But it can in theory run 10 times as fast.
Yes.
And that's very, very well put.
And for this, we can use like the program, the ngrams program, it supports these start
and step functions.
So you can decide, you can tell it that, hey, I want you to take every 10th book.
I want you to start from a certain number.
So we can modify the count ngrams to code.
So if we make a copy of it into, let's call it an array, count n-grams, and not the output,
but the count n-grams.
Oh, yeah, not the output.
SH.
So this is not good.
Oh, yeah.
Wait.
Yeah, yeah.
Yes.
So let's modify the code a bit, and let's try to like split it up, split it up the work
to multiple workers.
So if you look at now the array script.
Yeah, OK.
So we can do small additions here.
Yeah, so we can do small additions here
that make it so that we can split it up.
So the first important thing about the array thing
is that when you want to submit an array job,
you add this `sbatch` and then `--array`, and then let's say it's from zero to nine [`--array=0-9`].
And what this syntax, this looks a bit interesting, but what this syntax tells
the queue system, like the queue system will read this comment and it will recognize that,
Hey, the user wants me to create 10 copies basically from zero to nine.
Right.
And it wants me to create 10 copies of the same job.
All of those jobs are independent and all of those get the same requirements.
So it's not like additive, you don't get like 10 gigabytes, so you don't need
to modify the requirements in a way.
Of course, like in this case, like, like some of, like if we split up a big
program. Each of those might have less requirements to do, but that's not necessarily
something we need to think about. We're not thinking about that now.
Basically, we're running 10 identical copies here, but if we don't do any modifications to the
running part of the code, like the Python call, we are going to be running the same thing 10 times,
and that's no fun. That's a waste of resources. Hopefully it's exactly the same ten times. Yes.
But instead what we can do is we can like this program supports a different starting point.
So we can use a different starting point for like which book we want to analyze.
So, if we add here, that's the start, and then we put there a magical environment variable.
So, in Terminal, you can have these environment variables that are like something that will
be filled later.
It's just a variable that will be filled later.
And for the array, it's called `$SLURM_ARRAY_TASK_ID` with underscores and all capital letters.
So it's very important that it's written correctly.
Exactly like this, I guess.
Yeah, exactly like that.
But once you have written it out loud a few times,
you will remember it and it will become more natural.
And what this...
Like for me, even every time I do that,
I almost always look at a reference
just to make sure I'm spelling it right.
So don't be afraid there.
Okay, so this means it starts and `$SLURM_ARRAY_TASK_ID` becomes the numbers 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9,
I guess. Yes. So, when we submit the array job, we will get a number for each of these
these array tasks. So, we get a number. So, the number, well, that's a task ID running
based on what are the numbers we are giving in the array, like lying over there, the Sbatch
array. And each of them gets a different one. So, what we do with those numbers is
up to us. And that's the beauty and the complexity of the array jobs, that we can map this number
to any sort of like parameter values, we can map it into datasets. You can do whatever you want
with this number, as long as you map it to something different for each job. There's many
examples in the ArrayJobs tutorial page of different kinds of structures you can use
to map this into different things. Yeah, and I guess if the program didn't support the start
option, it wouldn't be easy to do this with arrays. You'd have to somehow add it yourself.
Yes, quite often you want to implement this sort of functionality in your code. Like,
if you know that you are planning on using the code for, let's say, running a hundred different
things, you might want to implement in your code functionality where it can take a number and,
based on that number do something different. Yeah, but so is there anything else we need to do
for this then? So we need to like currently we are setting up a starting point but we are not
setting up a stepping like stride. So if we would only have the starting point we would
like everyone would start at a different number that but then they would analyze all of the rest
as normal. So, we need to set this step over here to be 10. So, everyone takes, or in every 10th
book. So, zero, yeah, like Riks is writing, we get numbers like that. And then 1, 11.
1, 11, 21, and so forth, 91, I guess.
Yes.
And this, so when we made this program,
this is basically like the Python array slicing.
So you give a start and a step.
And I think you could also give a stop there.
So it's, well, if you know the Python syntax,
it looks familiar.
If not, well, that doesn't really matter.
And yeah, but we could try out submitting this
and see what happens.
Should we adjust the output?
Because it looks like it will be writing.
Yes, great point.
I almost forgot.
So if we wouldn't change the output,
everyone would be writing into the same file. So, instead, let's call it `ngrams2` and then
then `-array` and then `_$SLURM_ARRAY_TASK_ID` [so `ngrams2-array_$SLURM_ARRAY_TASK_ID`].
So now, because all of these programs will run independently, all of them need to have
an independent output as well.
So yes, we want them to write to different files.
And again, the SlurmArrayTaskID will be filled when the code is actually running.
So it's based on the array number that it gets.
Now I think we are ready.
Okay.
Yeah.
So I exit and save.
Do we trust it works?
I think it's going to be fine.
It looks good to me.
So let's hope.
Yeah, `sbatch count-ngams-2-array.sh. And if you now look at the queue, what does this queue say?
So, we see, yeah, we see that we have now this weird job ID for the job. So, what that means
is that, maybe you can try running it again and trying it again with the scheme.
But this structure means that we get the same job, but with basically 10 copies of it.
And we have only one ID for the whole average.
And this makes it easier for the queue system to also understand, okay, now we have the
same thing, but 10 times.
And now we see like how it looks actually in the queue.
So once the resources are, yeah, once the resources are reserved, we get these array
jobs running and each one gets a different ID.
And you notice that some of them are running in completely different machines, or most
of them are running in completely different machines because they are independent, right?
all of these are independent and they would be running independently of each other. So let's
look at the output. Did it crash or did we get anything in the output files? Oh, there's a lot
of output. I see this output is doubled here. Should we look at what should we look at? Let's
look at the ngrams output first. Let's verify that it worked correctly. So we get a lot of
output over here. Yeah, and it looks 7000. So, that's about one tenth of what was there before,
I think. If we look at number one. Sure. Yeah, okay. Yeah. So, what we get is we get independent
outputs from all of these, but we also get this slurm outputs as well. And by default, when you have
this array structure, you have the slurm, it's called slurm, and then you have the job ID and
the array task ID after that. And again, it captures all of the output from each array job.
So let's say you need to do some analysis a hundred times, and each one takes an hour or
something, and one of them crashes. You can look at the outputs and see that, okay, that one crashed,
what was the problem with that one, and then you can figure out that, okay, maybe there's
like a corrupted data or something. But each one is independent, and each one gets an independent
output. Yeah. Maybe we should almost go to an exercise. Yes. Let's look at one of the outputs,
and let's then check the combined data, like what did we actually get what we wanted. So,
So if we look at one of the SLAM outputs.
The output of 0.
It says it found 100 files.
It didn't say which files it's processing.
Yeah.
Yes.
But it looks like it ran in about three seconds.
So each of these was very fast because now we're
splitting it into 10 parts.
But let's try combining the data together.
How do we do that?
So we do it by running combine counts.
Yes.
I'll run help first, and let's see what it says.
So it needs the output count files,
and then it has an output file.
Yeah.
So we combine counts.
And don't worry, we'll post all of the commands that we're going to be running into the notes
in a second, so that you can try them out in the exercise.
So I guess this is how I'll run it, Python 3, the program name, and I can use an asterisk
to glob and capture everything that starts with this, which I know will be the 10 files
that are needed.
Yes.
And then you specify the output.
I saved it somewhere.
Yeah, you have the out and the ngrams.
Yeah, to array out.
That looks good.
Dot out.
Yeah, OK.
Takes a while to combine them.
Yeah.
So this is kind of like, yeah, this
is the kind of map-reduce kind of situation
where we map a lot of map the same functionality
onto different data, and then we reduce the results
into together.
So if you look at the output.
I can look.
Should we see if it looks the same as the non-array one?
So like 62,000.
Top number is 62,3.
And if we do array ngrams2.out, exactly the same,
at least the first number.
So this is a bit of, again, like a toy example.
But if we would have, let's say, the data would be a lot bigger,
then this would really speed up the execution.
And to use an imaging example, if we
have 100 brain images to process and they each take a few hours to do, we can do them in
parallel, even 100 times in parallel. Okay. And now let's go to exercises. So the exercises,
we'll post the commands that we just ran into the notes and you can create your own
ArrayScript, or you can already start writing it if you feel like doing that. And after that,
in the array examples, there are many examples. They use this py example, but there's many
examples of different ways you can choose the different array IDs in different ways.
And if you have more time, check out a few of those
and run a few of those examples and see what they do.
But yeah, let's go to the exercises.
And should we have about 20 minutes?
I guess that will start getting into the lunchtime a little
bit.
OK.
I guess we can go some people.
Or should we just combine the exercises with lunchtime
And then people can beat the cues of the places or whatever.
Maybe we'll have 50 minutes of exercise,
and then we'll talk about a few of the questions,
and then we'll return to it after lunch.
OK.
So 40, no, 50.
Well, yeah.
Let's go 55.
55, yeah.
And you can try some Ask Questions,
And there's more time during the lunch break.
So yeah.
OK.
And the task of people will be to do basically
what we've done here.
Yeah.
Is that the case?
OK.
And I think Sima will be pasting in commands and more detailed
instructions to the notes.
OK, great.
So see you in about 11 or 12 minutes.
OK, bye.
Yep. Bye.
you
Hello, we are back.
So, our plan now, I believe, is to go over some of the questions and stuff and then we
go to the lunch break and we can do one more array example after lunch.
So, which questions were most relevant here? There's some on best practices, like, oh,
Oh, yes, please, even for a reference or a future,
please let us know if you did the exercise,
weren't trying, or had some problems,
because this will help us plan for future years.
So yeah, so this is a good question here.
So if someone goes and makes an array job,
Like you run 1 million array jobs that each take 10 seconds.
That's not a very good thing, because it's
a lot of scheduling overhead to constantly be
finding these spaces, planning it, running it, stopping it,
and restarting it.
So that's sort of an extreme example.
But what's our rule of thumb?
Try to make the jobs at least 15 minutes, but if it can be longer.
Yeah, like usually we talk about half an hour or an hour
is better.
But yeah, it depends how in a hurry are you.
If you want to get most done, you usually want it to be, let's say, an hour.
If you want the results now, less than 15 minutes is fine.
But if you do, let's say, 100 jobs in less than 15 minutes, that's going to...
At some point, somebody will send you a mail of like, why like this?
Because it's not good for the queue.
The queue system doesn't like if there's a huge number of jobs happening that are very
small.
It doesn't usually like that.
And there was also a question in the chat, why not just use a bash script that submits
jobs or something like that.
And the reason behind that is the array structure is much better handled by the queue.
been designed for this sort of workflow. If you have a bash script that just submits stuff,
then each of these are independent and the queue cannot reuse the same information it gets from
all of the array types. So, it's not as good. So, please use the array structure instead.
And a good benefit with the array structure is that it's reproducible because you then know what
is the mapping between the array indices and the different things. And it's very easy to then look
at it later on and see that, okay, I run it with these array indices, so I get these results.
And there was also a question...
One of them fails, they don't all fail or something.
Yeah, yeah. There's also questions of more complex parameters. So after the lunch,
we'll talk about an example of how you can map out different combinations of
parameters. If you have multiple parameters you want to do, you can use array to map to those.
You can map one number to multiple things. That's possible. And if you have a situation
where you have very small things that you need to do a lot, what you can do is you can have an
array job where inside each job you have a for loop that does 10 things or 20 things. If you
If you have something that only takes 10 seconds, but you need to do it like 100,000 times,
you can split it up so that you have, let's say, 10,000 or 1,000 10-second things running
in each average job.
And then you can set up what is the run time, basically how many iterations you want inside
one job.
But usually it's this kind of like, okay, you can think of it a bit like you can have
either like a really thin rectangle with the same surface area as like a very wide one.
And as long as you keep the number of things that aren't needed to be done the same, you
can rearrange it in a way that you can do it in like, you can do a small number of jobs
that do a lot of things, or you can have a large number of jobs that do a few things.
Yeah. So I guess most of the people asking these questions, like, can I do x with array jobs,
the answer is always yes, if you write the code, whether it's in Python or Shell or whatever else,
to do the splitting up, and if it doesn't make it too short. And this is why we have other courses
on shell scripting and stuff like that. Knowing a little bit of bash can save you a lot of time
doing other stuff. Yeah, and if you have problems figuring out, okay, that's my program. Can I
split it up? How do I split it up? What would be the best way? Again, asking for help is a
good thing because for different projects, you might have a different thing you want to split
it up by, and all tasks are individual. So it depends on the task at hand. How do you want to
split it up? But yeah, maybe we should go. Anyway, I guess it's lunchtime. So should we
head there? See you in an hour.
Yeah, and when we come back, we'll
talk a bit more about arrays, about more complex array
things, and then we'll jump into applications and other things
in the cluster, monitoring jobs and that sort of stuff.
So a little example and some more philosophical stuff
before parallel.
OK.
Yeah.
Great.
As always, you can keep asking questions.
So talk to you later then.
Bye
you
Hello, are we back?
I think so.
I hope you had a good lunch break.
I think we did here.
So what comes next?
So my understanding, we have another quick demo
of Array Jobs, and we talk about monitoring and applications.
Any other notes and stuff to review from, or questions from the notes to review?
I think, yeah, there's plenty of good discussion there. And I recommend reading up on it later on
if you feel like it. But I think we can move forward. And let's do, like, many of the topics
in there touched the subject of, okay, what is, like, what can you do with the array jobs? And
Let's look at one of the more complex examples. Let's run one of these from the
examples in the course material. [name], if you want to run the case example.
Yes. So, what do I type? So, this is a new thing. This is with calculating pi.
So, in the parallel part, when we are going to switch into another example, which is much more
like computational example, and it was already mentioned in the beginning of the day, and it's
a bit of a toy example, where it calculates or estimates the number of Pi using a stochastic
test. Basically, it's like throwing a dart at a dartboard and whether it hits the dartboard,
it will calculate how many hits do you get and estimate Pi by that. It's very like a toy model,
but it's very easy to pack analyze for multiple CPUs and stuff like that, or relatively easy to
optimize for that. And here I see we have five array tasks, 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
Yes. And for that, we want to test out a different kind of way of
of choosing the parameters.
In this case, we might want to choose a seed number
for the random process that we're going to be doing,
so we can decide which number we want to use.
And in Bash, it's a whole programming language,
the terminal, so you can do, for example,
this case statement that [name] has written.
So, basically, based on the number of the Slurm array  it's mistyped, actually.
So, based on the number in the Slurm array task ID,
a different value will be set to this variable seed. So, let's say you want to test different
If a parameter is out, it's very easy to test it with this kind of like a syntax.
Then there's more complex syntax that you can use in the other examples.
You can take the parameters from a file or you can do all sorts of things.
But this is like very easy way of testing out.
So over here, we try...
So I guess, yeah, there's the seed.
Yes.
we try out what we get from the slurm/pi.py.
And you notice also in the #SBATCH statement,
we have changed the output file name
of where the output of the,
up in the top, like in the #SBATCH statements,
we have changed the output file name.
And you can use these test wildcards.
are documented in the documentation sections. You can use this %a to denote the Slurm Array Task ID.
So, if you want to create your own output file for the Slurm output, then you can use this
sort of a syntax for that. But let's... I guess everything's configurable.
Yeah. Okay. So, what this will do is that it will do two and a half million iterations
slurms with different seed values, and it will print out the outputs into pi underscore
and the seed number, and then it will print out the slurm outputs into the pi array hardcoded
with the array index. So, let's try it out.
Exit, save, yes.
And there's, like I said, there's multiple of these different things that, different
ways that you can do this array kind of like expansion.
So first, I make sure I'm where I expect to be after the break.
pi-array.sh.
If we do `slurm queue`, it's already running.
So four things.
And it's done.
If you want to look at one of the outputs and.
Okay, now this is a lot of files here.
Yeah.
So, what are the new ones?
The pyarray hardcode.
These are the output files.
Yeah.
Should we look at the first one?
So, this is the output that the code, yeah, what the code runs.
But the actual output of the code is going into the py underscore and then.
1, 2, 3.
OK, yeah, and it's a JSON structure that says stuff.
So I guess this is a way where if you
have different file names that aren't predictably named,
you can sort of hard code what the inputs are
or what the hyperparameters are or whatever like that.
Yeah, and there's a lot of flexibility
in the array chops for this.
But OK, I think you probably get the idea that you can
Yeah.
You can check this out later.
We'll check out the different examples.
So maybe we should jump into the next section,
which is about monitoring.
Yeah.
So should I come back here?
Where is it?
Monitoring.
Yeah.
So throughout this, we have already
started to use some of the tools for monitoring and, of course, one big monitoring thing is
the output itself. The code produces output. You can check the output and see if it's correct.
That's one way of monitoring it. But when we talk about monitoring, we often think about
how does the queue perceive things and what happened when the job run, like what happened
in the queue. And for that, we have used the Slurm queue to check when we have submitted
a job, what happens there. That's the first thing. When you submit a job, you usually
want to check, is it running? Is it queuing? When does it start?
Will it finish today of the 2,000 things I submitted yesterday? When is it done? And
so on.
clusters that don't have the Slurm script that we are using, which is this kind of helper script,
you can use the sq-user mentioned in the documentation, but we'll also put it into the
notes to check the... I guess that's here. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. What other kinds of monitoring are
So the other one and the major one is the history like we want to see what is the like what happened like if the job has finished what has happened did it finish correctly and so forth and for that we use the slam history so when we use the slam history we can we can check okay what was the did it complete correctly did it
like, what resources actually used, how long did it take, that sort of stuff, like, basic
stuff.
There's also, like, if you don't have the Slurm command, you can use this s-act-u user.
We'll put it into the notes as well, or we'll, yeah, there's many of these Slurm commands
that you can use to monitor.
But usually it's a good idea to, yeah, something like that.
Yeah, you can figure out what information you want from the job and you can get a lot
of information from the Slurm itself.
So basically, yeah, Slurm keeps a huge database of all the parameters of everything that's
run.
What the commands are, who ran it, where it was run, but then also things like all the
resources that were requested and the resources that were actually used.
So you can go and submit all your stuff,
and then you can return later and then
see what finished, what didn't finish, what had errors,
how much resources did it use,
do I need to adjust any of these things?
Stuff like that. That's this.
Okay.
Maybe we could jump into the terminal now and view a few of the monitoring outputs.
So there's another like this kind of wrapper script that is usually like added with Slurm
called `seff`.
And we have a few example job IDs that we can show in the notes, in our own notes.
we could try out that you put there.
Yes.
I see.
Okay.
Yes.
So let's look at-
These commands will work on Triton, but not other places.
Yeah, these are jobs I have run in the past, and let's look at something like that.
So once you have a job that has run, you get the job ID.
And if you give that job ID to this command sf, it will print out various efficiency information
about that.
So you will see, for example, here, like, okay, did it complete, what was the status?
Then you see that, okay, how many CPUs did it use?
And then it tells how much time it used with those CPUs, like the CPU time.
And then it will tell what is the CPU efficiency.
So that just means that how much of those reserved CPUs were utilized.
So what is the time?
Is 97% considered good?
Yes.
Like 100% would be that it's using all of the time.
So 97% is great.
And the wall clock time is again like the time that you would see on the wall.
So it's like the time in real time.
So if you use multiple CPUs, the CPU time can be bigger than the wall time because you
have multiple CPUs running the stuff.
And then, yes, next, but let's look at first the memory utilization.
So you can see what was the memory consumption and what was the memory efficiency.
So not very good.
I do note that many of these numbers are not necessarily the true numbers, they're sampled
numbers.
So what Slurm does is that it samples what the process is doing every now and then.
I think it's 30 seconds by default that it samples what the program is doing.
So if your program has a huge spike of memory consumption or something, it might not be shown
in this data, or if the job crashes immediately or something, it might not show correct numbers.
So these are sampled numbers over the whole runtime.
So if there's something weird happening that happens quickly, it might not be reflected
here.
But you can get the overall big picture.
So let's look at one of the jobs that uses multiple CPUs.
So the output here is pretty similar.
The only difference is that now we see that there's cores per node is four.
So we're using four cores per node.
And we noticed that the CPU utilized is actually the same, basically.
We are doing the same calculation.
We're doing the same exact amount of CPU time utilizing, but now it's divided for four CPUs,
basically.
And the CPU efficiency is still very good, but the wall clock has dropped, like, dramatically.
Yeah, so instead of taking 41 seconds with one CPU, it's 11 seconds for four CPUs.
But this also came with a bit more of an increased memory utilization, but at the same time,
We can't really say if that's correct, because the sample time is so small, like it's 11
seconds.
So it's not that big.
And quite recently in Triton, we've added also GPU stats here.
So if we take one GPU job, so this was a very simple test PyTorch model, it ran for three
minutes so it's not very big. So you can see here at the bottom there's now like GPU stats also.
So these are again sampled on the compute nodes so you can see what GPU was utilized,
what was the GPU utilization and what was the memory utilization. So the GPU utilization
basically here means that how much of the time the GPU was doing calculations.
It doesn't say that whether calculations are efficient or whatever. It just means that how
much the GPU was just doing calculations. And in this case, the model is so small that
basically the GPU finishes it immediately when it gets it. So
it doesn't utilize the GPU very efficiently. But in other clusters, there might be other
ways of monitoring the GPUs. A common way is that once you get a job running, you can usually
take an SSH connection to the node where the job is running and use this tool called NVIDIA SMI
to print out information. There's more information in the documentation about that.
So you can go to the GPU node and monitor the GPU utilization.
So while it's running, this is what you can do.
OK, yeah.
There is a good question in the notes.
Considering that we have profilers
as part of our code, which may be very detailed,
how can we benefit from the short summary?
So how would you balance the profilers
with this kind of reporting?
And that's a good question.
I think if you know how to use a profiler
or if you know how to profile or get the information from your code itself,
it's of course great, because then you get much more detailed information.
But in a lot of cases, you might be using a program that you don't control what it's doing.
And if you want to add profiling to it, it might be an extra effort.
So with these, you get numbers from the source.
You get the numbers based from the queue system
and the hardware itself.
So it's like these numbers are free and automatic.
So it's like the big picture.
And if you see these numbers are low,
then you go to your profilers, and you can understand why
and make it better or understand that it's as good as it can be.
Something like that.
So is it kind of like, you know, like the, like, have you tried turning it on and off
again, kind of a situation where like, like you first do the simple things and then you
like, if it's still like you first do the, you try out the simple things and then you
try the more, more complicated things usually.
So if you want to profile your code, the easiest way is usually just look at these numbers
and see like, okay, what are these numbers saying?
And then if you want more fine-grained information,
you use a profile or something.
We can post some good profiling tools into the notes soonish
that can do it for you with minimal hassle.
But yeah, they are not one or the other.
But this is something you get for free, like Richard said.
Yeah.
OK, what else?
There is an interesting question.
Is there a way to have it write this efficiency information
to the job output files automatically instead
of only being in the database?
And that's a good question, I guess.
So when it appeared there automatically
in the Gutenberg stuff, that's because the code
itself was written to do that.
Yeah, I'm not certain. In principle, yes, probably. But I think, because it's hard to
put it into the job script itself, because the stats are not recorded until the job finishes,
or if they're not finalized. So it's like you're bootstrapping yourself, basically pulling
yourself out with your own bootstraps. And it becomes quite complicated. But I can imagine
that you could do some sort of like a script you can do
after the job has run?
Or you can wrap it in a profiler or something
that will track this.
Like, for example, one trick that I sometimes
do, user bin time dash v.
And it has to be the full path, because otherwise it's
a bash built in.
And then if you run something like y.py,
that's 2 and 1 1,000,000.
So this will run.
And it automatically, so this is from time.
So time prints out all of this other stuff, which will
tell you some basic summary.
So the user time in seconds, what percentage
of a CPU was used during this time period
and some other interesting technical stats there.
So this doesn't tell you the overall efficiency of memory
efficiency and so on, because time
doesn't know how much memory was allocated to the job and so on.
But it has stuff.
But yeah, like you can do various.
I think it's.
I do it with two threads.
It's coarse.
Yeah.
Let's run it with help.
But maybe we should move forward.
Yeah, I guess we should go on.
It's nprox.
Yeah.
And here we see it says 190% of a CPU, which means it's using almost two CPUs.
But there's plenty of these kind of programs that you can use to do the monitoring.
Yeah.
Yeah, so we'll note, put into the notes, our favorite profilers.
And if you have your favorite tools that you can use to profile, do add them there as well
so that other people can benefit from knowing about them.
But basically this is like usually when you run something in the queue and if you think
that the job is using like four CPUs, you think you reserve four CPUs and you think
that the job is using four CPUs.
And then you usually want to look at the SF or whatever
to verify that it actually used the four CPUs
because otherwise it's wasted resources, right?
So usually you want to use quickly SF or something
to verify that what is the memory usage,
what is the time usage, what is the processor usage
in order to set the requirements of your job
match more closely to what it actually needs.
Yeah. And if you tried this and you can't figure out what it is, I'd say always, if you're using
resources, always check, see the efficiency. If it doesn't look like what you expect,
spend a little time, see if you can understand why. But if not, come talk to us and we can help
do that. If everyone would do this, it would make the cluster go much faster because there's
a lot less wasted stuff there. Anyway, yeah. Should we go on then?
Yeah, let's go. And next we have a talk. Yeah, next we are going to go through some applications.
Yeah, so.
So yes.
Well, I guess the purpose here isn't
to talk about specific applications.
But if you're using a cluster, you want to run something.
And it's either an application someone else has installed,
or it's something that you need to install yourself.
Or for example, you need to install Python or something
and then run your own code.
And this is just a very broad overview of what's available.
Since everyone needs different stuff, we're not going to take the time to go into any detail
here because most people would be bored and you will need to find it again when you need it anyway.
But this is the general idea. So some people come to the cluster and say, why can't I do
sudo apt-get install something, which is the command you would use on a Linux computer to
install something. And there's several reasons, but the most important of the reasons is that
this is a shared cluster. And if you can install something or change the version of something,
then it will break it for everyone else. And even if us as admins do stuff,
any little change we do has the possibility of breaking someone else's code.
So it's very conservative what's installed as part of the operating system.
So if we go down, that's us.
So yeah, there's a few things we install that way.
But for the most part,
anything you need is not just available by default.
Yeah. Maybe demo in the terminal a few of these applications.
So many, at least here in Aalto,
The computing cluster, all of the computers are very minimal installations, so they don't
have a lot of software installed, because they're not installed into any disk or anything
when the computer is booted up.
Everything is in memory, and this is quite common in many clusters, so the whole operating
system is in memory, and the more you have in the memory, the less.
The more stuff you have in the operating system, the less you have memory available for the
users.
So that's why usually the image is very small.
But there's some programs there.
So if we, for example, look which Python 3, so which is this tool that checks, like if
I would run Python 3, what is the actual application that will run?
So we noticed that this is, it comes from user bin.
So this is like, Linux has this file systems through the operating system.
Yeah.
Linux has this file system hierarchy where like user is the applications, the operating
system applications there and bin is usually like the executable binaries.
So it's part of the operating system, but we want to still run multiple things in the cluster.
So often, we admins install stuff into the cluster
and make it available for many of the users.
Yes.
And we do that with, well, the most common one
is called the module system.
And this is a way you can run a command,
and it makes other software available by manipulating
the paths it looks at for software.
And we don't need to go into depth about exactly where this
comes from and how it works.
But can you give one example, then?
Yeah, let's check if we have MATLAB available.
So if we run this module spider MATLAB,
yeah, we can first check if we have it.
And it says there's no MATLAB anywhere.
OK, yeah.
So if we now run module spider matlab,
so this module spider is a tool that it checks like,
is there, like, can you find matlab in the modules?
You can just run module spider to run you
all of the available modules.
But you notice that now we see that there's multiple
versions of matlab available over here.
Yes.
You see that there's matlab
and then there's like multiple versions.
So let's pick one of those versions.
So let's pick the latest one.
Maybe that one.
Maybe the latest one.
And we can press Q to quit, and then module load,
and then give that name.
So I paste it once.
And what happens?
Looks like nothing.
Well, yeah.
But we still, if you are on module list,
yeah, module list shows what modules are loaded.
So we can see that there's now the MATLAB module is loaded.
There's also this kind of like environment module.
So many of, many clusters have this kind of like
overall yearly installations or something
and we have them now too.
So it makes a lot of software available for you.
And it makes it possible to install a lot of other software.
But let's now check which MATLAB, did we actually get MATLAB, so okay, now we see.
Manual installation software MATLAB, yeah, okay.
So there's now like a system installed MATLAB.
So this is the most common way that we provide software or the system providers provide software
for you.
Maybe we can start the MATLAB and test it.
let's try that. Let's see, I hope it doesn't do something weird.
Yeah, we started with the no JDM so that we don't want the graphical interface. But yeah,
you can see that this is the muscle. It returns. Yeah, okay, so that worked.
Okay, and what's available in the module system? What kind of stuff do we have there?
Well, a huge bunch of software. There's many libraries, many finished software installations
and all sorts of stuff. So you can find it in the applications page and running module
spider will give you more information on that. But we also have some very specific software.
So this might be, again, like some of this
is also only auto-specific.
You want to check your cluster's stuff, how they are doing.
But one for whatever, is it safe to say
what every cluster you have, the first thing to do
is read the documentation for what you need
and see if it's already installed
or there's special instructions, because it
will be different for everyone.
Yeah, especially for the very complex programs,
there might be a specific reason why
installed the way they are. And the admins have used a lot of effort trying to get the most
like performant version and most stable version installed to the system. And doing it manually
by yourself can be quite tricky sometimes. Yeah. Okay.
Should we demo? We could demo a few more software. So we have in our
So in our cluster, we also have these containers available.
So there was, yesterday at least,
there was a question about like what,
can you run Docker containers in the cluster?
So containers, for those who don't know,
is this basically like an operating system
paired with the software, like everything is there.
Like everything is contained in the same package.
And we use these apptainer containers,
or they used to be called singularity containers.
They are called, in some sites, singularity containers
to have these kind of very complex software
that wouldn't install into the operating system
that we're using.
So, but these can be run in the cluster,
and we have a few of these available.
They need usually a bit more manual work to get working,
But in the notes, we'll link a course page with Code Refinery that we did on creating
these containers. So if you are interested in this, please check that material.
And on Triton, at least we do have some software already installed in containers.
So it's not just, despite what it says here, it's not just under install it yourself.
So yeah.
But should we give a demo of running stuff,
something with a container?
Yeah.
Yeah, let's look at it.
So one example is this FreeSurfer,
which is this Neo4j imaging suite, which
is they provide existing containers.
So it's easiest to install using that.
So for that, we have this module,
apptainer-freesurfer.
So if you load that, it will tell you
how to get more information on how to run it.
But we have read it, so [name] can maybe execute the command.
And is this a typo here?
Should that be a curly bracket?
Oh, that's true.
Yes, good point.
We need to fix that.
So now we run it with aptainer execute,
and I guess the path to it?
Yeah, the mesh path.
And then we execute some program inside of it.
So this is running.
So if I can unpack this command, apptainer's the container
program.
Exec means we want to run some command in a container.
Image path has been defined by the module that tells me
this is where the container is.
And if you make a container yourself,
you would just give it the path there directly.
Yeah.
And FreeSurfer is now a thing that will run inside of there.
So it's like it's starting up this other, almost
like an operating system that's self-contained with all
the stuff, and then says, hey, you, this box I just made,
run FreeSurfer.
And it connects it to what's outside.
Yes.
Yes, very well.
And I guess we can run it with the Help option
to verify that it does something in there.
And it sure looked like it gives us help from it.
And I guess if we do FreeSurfer outside the container,
there's nothing.
So yeah, OK.
Are there any other big, major ways of software?
I guess there's Conda that we already
went over in the morning.
So actually, what is the most common way of doing things?
Yeah, well, that's, at least in the Python world,
it's quite common.
But for many people who don't necessarily
like who want to use Python, but they don't necessarily
want to do stuff themselves or install their own environment,
we provide existing environments that
are like handcrafted to have a huge bunch of packages
available, at least here in Alta.
So we have this SciComp Python environment
that has a lot of packages already installed.
But of course, you can create your own environments.
So maybe we should demo that quickly, loading that.
Demo, ah, so the pre-made content things, yes, OK.
Yes.
And I have a visitor here.
So let's see how much I could type.
So module load.
And I know from my experience that it is called `scicomp-python-env`.
And what's in this environment?
A huge bunch of Python packages he installed already.
So now we can see that the Python has changed.
Like, what is the Python version that we're using?
It comes from our installation.
But like, yeah, these are something that we provide,
but there's a lot of stuff you can, of course, install yourself.
And if you encounter any problems, it's always a good idea to ask help
from the admins, or if you know a software
that other people might be interested in using,
it might be good to let us know, then we can install it for everybody.
in the cluster because that's that makes it life easier for everybody.
Yeah, and even if you aren't sure about it, you can ask. So there'll be sometimes we'll say,
okay, yeah, I mean, we haven't had many requests from this. It seems easier to install yourself
and we'll help you install it yourself. But as we see the patterns, we might add it to one of the
existing environments, especially if it's a Python or R thing, install it within one of these. If it's
it's LLM-related, install it to our standard LLM environment.
Yeah.
So, and depending on your, yeah,
but usually like as a good rule of thumb,
go check out module spider in the cluster
that you're running in and check what's there
and it's your program that you're planning on running there.
That's a good starting point usually.
and check the application page for the program.
But I think now is a good time to switch gears,
to talk about, like we have a talk by [name and [name].
And I think the cat is getting pretty hungry,
so it's a great time to switch.
Yeah.
There is this interesting question about using Python 2 on Triton.
So that's one of the cases where we'd say it's not installed in any default environment,
but you can install it yourself with Conda.
And then we point you that way and give you any help you might need.
And that's that basically.
Yeah. But also, I would say that if you have to run some Python 2 code, that's the least
of your worries. It's been deprecated for so long that transitioning to Python 3 in
that code might be... Asking people supporting you, can they help with the transition process
from Python 2 to Python 3 might be a good worthwhile investment.
Yeah, but I mean, if it's some code that they haven't made
and someone else is like, yeah, you just
aren't going to update that.
But yeah, OK, so with that said, let's close this out.
There's a lot more to read about applications.
We've just prepared you to do your own reading.
So by all means, go do that.
And if you have questions about the application of your choice,
put them into the notes, and we can try to answer, like,
well, how it should go about installing.
Keep writing there.
And now we're switching gears for the second to last session
of the day, which is a more philosophical discussion,
I guess.
So it's more about how you use stuff.
Or no, not how you use stuff, about how
you do the science itself.
And this is with [name], who's one of our, well,
I want to say one of the reproducibility people.
But really, we all care about reproducibility in science.
So anyway.
Yes.
Yeah, have a good one.
Thanks.
Can you switch to my share?
Screen share, please.
There you go.
And Thomas is also with me.
So, basically what we covered so far, you are now able to run so-called embarrassingly
parallel programs on a HPC cluster, and you understood how to manage the data, move the
data into the cluster, out from the cluster.
So I would say, well, I don't know if it's the majority of workflows, but a good portion
of the typical use of these systems is basically already covered.
The rest of the course will go more into parallelization, which is the so-called non-embarrassing parallelization
and this type of specific nodes that are called GPUs, but I don't want to spoil the fun so
you will hear later about this.
So to have a little break and consider if what you're doing is worth doing and I don't
want to, you know, depress anyone here, it's good to also consider and be aware of the
responsible conduct of research and specifically in the case of computation one could talk
about responsible computational research and you can write if you want in the notes document
what type of ethical or moral or legal issues that you might not even know that you have
or maybe you think that you have but they're not issues at all but in general what is making
you doubtful about your research. I wrote there, for example, that reproducibility,
which we have mentioned many times, is something that kind of I feel that often in my past
as a researcher that I had issues of reproducibility. What about you, [name]? What is your kind
of...
I completely agree. Either other people's stuff that I wanted to replicate or my own
stuff. In both cases, I had issues with getting things to run again.
Yeah. And you actually mentioned really well my own stuff, because one could think that
reproducibility is something, you know, I'm trying to figure out the universal law of
whatever. And, you know, it's good that other people repeat my experiment. But sometimes
the issue is really that I was doing six months ago something, and I was able to obtain some
results and I'm not able to rerun the same code anymore. Was it that the library has changed?
The operating system has changed? So this is very common. I've seen it many times with my work,
with other people's work. So a few of the topics that I will mention now, they cover or they show
you ways on how to deal with reproducibility issues. And you kind of already got a glimpse
of this when earlier we talked about Conda and the Conda environments and now someone was just
asking about Python 2 which is like traveling back in time and trying to reproduce or replicate
something from the past. So it's impossible to cover everything exhaustively when it comes to
research ethics and responsible conduct of research so I will try to give you a very
short five minutes intro but this page has lots of links that ideally every researcher should check
and read and be aware. The kind of conceptual framework that you can think of is the so-called
normative cascade which is how basically society works. You can understand that or you maybe feel
that there are these general ethics principles that can drive basically the creation of laws.
In the ideal case, ethics, all the good ethical principles would overlap completely with the laws
but in practice it is not like that, so there is never a full overlap between ethics and law.
And then of course laws will cause the creation or will influence so-called research policies,
so how the legislations stemming from the ethical principle will actually be applied in the work you
need to do with research. And then at the end of course it's the actual researchers that are
affected by the cascade. On the other hand, if the researchers notice that there are new
issues that the core ethical principle needs to be revised, they can together influence
the cascade and go back at the beginning and change the ethical principles.
So if we talk about the ethical principle, I'm not going to talk about as many ethical
principles. The Universal Declaration of Human Rights is one example. But in the context
of Research, I hope that everyone here, if you are in Europe, you should all read this
very short book which is the ALLEA European Code of Conduct for Research Integrity. Basically
there's everything there. If you know that book by heart, you just need to apply that
book whether you do computational science, I don't know, artistic research or whatever
type of research activities that you are doing. The four principles of the ALLEA Code of Conduct
are reliability, ensuring basically the quality of your of your research. Honesty, that what you
develop and what you do can be basically audited by others. So again, we're kind of covering this
type of reproducibility and transparency. And of course, respect is very important,
respect towards your colleagues, respect towards the administrator of your cluster, respect towards
the people that you will encounter on your career, others, authors in other universities
and more in general respects towards society and the ecosystem and so on.
And finally, accountability, given that, you know, from the accountability for the research
from the idea stage, the publication stage, and all its type of management and organisation,
which also requires you know this type of relationship between supervisor and mentors
and let's say junior researchers who are supervised and so on.
So that is kind of the general level and then from this core ethical principle there are
many legislations that apply to research where I will not go into the detail of any of these
But the typical case, maybe I can ask this actually to Thomas,
have you ever experienced in your work
that some researcher thinks
that they're not working with personal data,
but actually they were processing personal data?
Almost the other way around,
is there anything that's not personal data?
Exactly.
Yeah, I think the biggest issue with respect to personal data
is that it's really, really difficult to define what exactly personal data is, or rather what
does not constitute personal data anymore.
Yeah, I totally agree.
It's very difficult to anonymize data and we see this, you know, very often with people
who come and ask for help that they think that they're not presenting personal data
because whatever direct identifiers are missing.
But if it's a data about an individual, then let's just agree that it's personal data rather
than trying to mathematically demonstrate that the probability of re-identifying this
person is whatever is your favorite threshold.
But in general, again, here we don't have time and maybe we don't even have the energy
to go through legislations, but at least this list that is mentioned here is something that
you should be aware if your research kind of you know applies in this with this type of data.
And then of course from the core ethical principle to the legislation and regulations we have the
kind of national policies or even university level policies. So in the page you find some
links related to Aalto University but if you're from other university most likely you have the
similar policy whether it's about the ethical review if that's what you need in your research
or open science policies, open data policies, code of conduct and things like that.
So then at the end it's you the researchers who will depending on the case need to consider
these policies and this legislation and maybe these core ethical principles and trying to do
the best you can. I want to stress here that sometimes the best practices are some,
how can I say, state that it will never be reached and I really like that in this paper
by Wilson 2017 that is linked here, they mention good enough computational practices in this case
because sometimes it's trying to avoid that type of sloppy practices so that by adopting good
enough practices you can, you know, do the best you can and maybe slowly adopt more good enough
practices until you reach the best practices. I would like to add that one problem with
best practices is that very often to actually achieve best practices you need multiple people
working on the same thing and one person doesn't have all the knowledge and very often also not the
capabilities to do all things that would be best practice because it's just getting too much.
So this concept of good enough practices is something that is quite important in my opinion.
I totally agree. In this figure here, I tried to represent this is not exhaustive. I'm sure
there's more best practices in computational science and there's more, how should we call
them, worst practices. But in this continuum, so basically in the green side, we would have,
you know, that all the data is archived with the DOI, there is data versioning, we have protocols,
register protocols for data collection, version control for the code, so full reproducibility,
unit tests, you can add you know all the things that also we have mentioned today earlier,
and on the other end you really have this case that there are no backups, there's no documentation,
no readme file, no idea how to rerun things, no dependencies listed, no history log on which
script was from before the other. So I'm not asking you now, Thomas, to disclose something
sensitive, but if you put yourself in this type of continuum, or maybe let's rephrase this. Have
you had experience of some worst practices, actually? Okay, I have myself been in the
situation that I had code that was not documented well enough and that where I then two years later
was trying to think okay how did I do this, where did I put the configuration files, where did I do
this and that and needed to go back and not completely reinvent but it took me quite some
some time to set this up again. I have seen enough kind of bad things online from others
where it's like, you're providing the data, but informants that are completely unusable
and that essentially it would feel kind of more honest
to just not provide the data.
And I hope that I'm nowadays somewhere
on the yellow to greenish border there,
because yeah, I also won't be always able
to go through all the different things
that should be on the list.
Because it's also quite a bit of things
come with a lot of administrative work,
which essentially means
while you're doing the administrative work
on a couple of things,
you're not actually doing anything
to progress the project that you have.
And that's getting frustrating very quickly.
I agree. And the administrative work is sometimes not even valued, meaning that, for example,
I wrote this here, this single folder for all projects where all the researchers from
the same group have read and write. And, you know, basically I've seen myself, I was part
of this type of, you know, gigantic research folders where things, I don't know, more
or less self-organized, but never really, you know, nobody had the time to do this type
of administrative work, even though the policies, whether they come from EU horizon or whether
they come from Academy of Finland, they kind of stress the importance of managing the data
and managing the software. But, you know, maybe you get a very good point earlier that
when it's not anymore this type of single person job that needs to do everything from
inventing the idea, collecting the data, writing the code, if it becomes a teamwork that then
you have the data steward, the research software engineer, and then it's the researchers,
the expert can focus on their expertise. And then in the end, best practices and even
administrative tasks can be taken care of. Just along those lines, I often see the problem that
that I would like to follow best practices,
but the best practices are written down so vaguely that,
yeah, like I just said,
they stress that you should care about data management,
but how?
What should you actually do?
These kind of really concrete guidelines,
they are, at least to me, very often lacking.
Just to mention it again,
with the administrative stuff that is undervalued,
especially as a researcher
that does something with personal data,
you fill in the same data into 20 different forms
to submit to 20 different places for approval.
And it gets really frustrating.
Why can't you just do this once?
and everyone who wants to know something can extract from what you just submitted.
So these are the kind of things that then lead to people not following protocol, not, yeah.
Yeah.
But I would say in general, I feel that things are much better.
I don't know if it's because I've been involved in dealing with these issues,
but maybe there is more awareness in general among researchers.
It is getting better. Also because higher levels are enforcing it more.
That's too good. All right, but basically to conclude, this page also has this little mention
of cyber security and again the point here, you know, it's not to give a course on cyber
security and most likely your organization has a mandatory course on cyber security.
What is very important that I often try to remind to our researchers is that they need to understand
the classification of information, meaning that they need to understand whether it's a script,
whether it's a piece of data, whether it's your internal note or the picture for the summer trip
of the department. You need to understand is it public data, is it internal data,
is it confidential or is it secret. In general you could assume that most of the work we do
goes between the confidential or internal if you are for example drafting a paper or
still working on something that you're not ready to fully make public.
But then of course there's also lots of public work that we do whether it's our open source
code projects web pages and things like that.
Maybe I would say that a minority of us need to work with secret data but of course there
There are legislations, for example,
when you need to reuse health data,
so data that was collected for medical purposes.
There are legislation that forces to be secret.
Then in this last three minutes, we
were discussing a few days ago that it's
important to maybe mention what could be the issues,
whether they are ethical or legal.
It's a blurt of using generative AI in your daily work.
Now here, I try to think of many types of issues,
but to keep it short without,
you can read the whole thing yourself.
In general, I see when it comes to computational science
as to write code, that there could be
this type of unwanted plagiarism issues
that I might be, that the generative AI
might synthesize some code that is verbatim,
some excerpt from a library,
but then I might not realize this,
most likely I would not start searching
if that code is verbatim from a library.
And then the issues becomes that maybe that library
had a specific type of software license
that wouldn't allow me to reuse it
unless I also adopt the same license.
There's no point here to go down to these details,
but you can understand that there are multiple risks
of using this type of generative AI
without carefully considering basically the output.
So again, if you are so-called vibe coding afternoon project
because you just want to make some funny cat pictures
through some code, maybe it's OK.
But if you're writing the core functions for your research
analysis, and you are not sure if the output
from this generative AI system is the actual output
that you would need, you need to reconsider or maybe
ask for help from other experts for doing code review
things like that. Maybe one that I like to mention is recently they noticed that
when you work for example with Python you might need to import some NumPy or Pandas or whatever
and if you don't have them in your system you need to pip install NumPy, Pandas and so on.
And recently there are some consistent hallucinations of packages and then in the Python
ecosystem but also in many other languages there is this type of typosquatting so that
malicious people actually have created packages with a similar name and then you do a typo when
you or the generative AI does a typo and then suddenly you have basically you know some
malware installed in your system. I would like to add something that also recently came up
when it comes to tools allowing the LLM to collect and process additional data or additional
public data, and particularly if that same thing also allows the model to access some
private information, because there have been recent attacks where essentially the public
data that was consumed by the LLM contained instructions to the LLM, at which point it
generated content that, when you looked at it, had image links or things in there that
essentially were leaking private information.
So essentially my recommendation is assume that the LLM is just another human, just another
random human and think about whether you want to give it access to whatever you are currently
giving it access to and that includes the whole conversation that you're currently having with it.
I had to quote this, it's not [name]'s quote but [name] often says this that there is no cloud
computing it's just someone else's computer and in my opinion it's the whole point because unless
you run these LLMs locally and truly locally in your machine you're just sending data to
somebody else's computer and even if they promise don't worry we will never give this data to anyone
you know it's exactly yeah all right but hopefully this was motivational enough to think if what
you're doing is good, is right, is moral, is ethical, is legal and so on. Feel free to
write something in the chat of this type of philosophical thoughts but I guess it's time
for a break and then later we can go back to code and computing. Thank you Thomas for
the nice conversation and I guess see you in 10 minutes
I don't see any clock now so 12 p.m. bye
you
Oh, hello.
We are back.
Hello, hello.
So I see a shadow moving under the table.
I wonder if my feet are about to be attacked.
OK.
Yes, so we're back for the last session of the day.
Go ahead, [name].
Yeah, I was going to say the exact same thing.
Yeah, you go right ahead.
OK, last session of the day.
And this is something which you need a little bit
of an introduction to.
But like many things, you'll probably
come back to it in more depth whenever you actually need it.
We're not telling you how to write code in parallel,
but how if you have a code which should run in parallel,
how you can actually use it and run it on the cluster.
Yeah.
Maybe.
So let's look at, maybe we should
start with the picture of the Shared Memory Parallelism.
OK.
So I'm opening this page.
Yes.
I need to go to the right screen.
There we go.
Yes.
So yeah, we talked previously about the Embarrassingly Parallel and the
like array jobs and how to run it. Lots of individual jobs basically in the cluster and
that's already like very good, like you can get a lot of stuff. But there's of course a lot more
available left on the table when it comes to the parallelism in the cluster because the
the computing nodes, like these computers,
they are basically, the CPUs are pretty similar
to what you would have in your laptop or in your computer,
but there's just usually more of them.
They're like server CPUs,
and they usually have much more resources.
They have more memory, more CPUs.
So if it's possible for your code
to utilize all of those resources,
you can, in theory, get a lot of speed up to your code.
And you can get your code done faster.
And that's basically this part of the parallel.
So the array jobs are more like maximum throughput
kind of parallel.
You get maximum amount of jobs through the system
and maximum amount of stuff done.
And they're very good if you have this kind of problem
that you can split into chunks.
But if you have like, let's say a big simulation
something and it just takes a long time. It takes a long time and it would benefit from
having multiple CPUs to run on. Then, yeah, let's look how you can do that in the cluster.
Okay. Should I go to the terminal for a demo? Yeah. So, there's two things you need to
think about. So, the first thing, of course, is that does your program work in parallel? Can it
do stuff in Parallel? That's a big question. Many programs can nowadays because many normal
computers have multiple CPUs. They are nowadays written to be able to utilize those CPUs. For
example, if you use Python, libraries like NumPy, Scikit-learn or whatever, they allow you to use
parallel CPUs natively, or MATLAB does. Or if you use R, you can use parallel in R to do it.
And there's various ways you can run without many code changes utilized. But of course,
like the efficiency, whether you get best efficiency, that is up to the air. But at
at least in principle, they could utilize multiple CPUs.
And to test it out in the cluster right now,
maybe [name], if you were on module purge
to verify that there's no like previous modules loaded.
Yes.
So we can start by testing out an example code that we have,
by testing out an example code that we have,
which is the Pi code that we mentioned previously
in the example.
So we have this in the Slurm folder,
that is Pi code.
And if you give it like a thousand or whatever,
like a number of thousands,
and if you run it like here in the login node,
okay, you see that.
That's very fast.
Yes, it's very fast,
but of course it's only like a thousand tries.
And this is like a very simple code,
but because it only does calculations,
it's quite easy to parallelize.
And that's why we can use it as an example
of how do you reserve resources with multiple CPUs.
So let's try running this in the queue
with a bit more requirements.
So if you add the normal stuff at the front there,
like srun meme.
what does this dash dash pty mean yes so we didn't think i'm copying yeah yeah we didn't
mention it before but you can add this that's a pty and it means like zelda terminal so
uh what it means that it will uh without spaces origin yeah i'm just verifying i'm doing it right
Yeah, like the PTY, it will allocate like the input and output for the terminal. So, basically,
if your code would have like interactive stuff and that sort of things, like it would ask for
input or something, it will work. It prints, yeah, okay.
Yeah, it will print everything automatically. It looks just like the normal shell. Okay, yeah.
Yeah, if you're running with this interactive SRUN, you might sometimes want to add the PTY there.
Yeah. But yeah, so let's add a bit more numbers here. So we have now, what's, is it 50 million?
It's 50 million. Yeah. Yes. So let's run it. It takes a bit longer. So this is about,
I think, maybe 40 seconds or something, if I remember correctly.
vc srun says it's queued. And now this is doing what we learned in the interactive job part
yesterday. And this is the kind of a program that, okay, like this could use multiple CPUs and it
could run faster with multiple CPUs. So let's get first a benchmark. What often you want to do is
that you want to, if you have this sort of like a program, you first want to try running it out
without any bells and whistles like with single CPU and then see how long does it take. If you're
running it already on your own computer you can look at the process manager usually and see how
many processors it's using and then try using the same sort of requirements in Triton for that.
So it shouldn't take that much more longer.
Yeah, let's see.
But we can see that, like, yeah, it takes, okay, now we can, yeah.
So it took some time.
Maybe if you run quickly the seff to check what is the, how long did it take?
On the job ID, and it says 95% efficiency for 40 seconds
and 42 real-time seconds.
So if we now want to allocate more CPUs for this job,
what we need to do is tell Slurm that we want more CPUs.
That's done with this CPUs per task flag. We just say CPUs per task, and let's put four
equals four. This would allocate four CPUs for that. We'll talk about tasks later. You don't have
I can't worry about that too much right now, but that is just a Slurm internal thing.
But basically, you just specify how many CPUs you want to get.
And we need, of course, the code to understand this as well.
The code needs to be able to utilize those, because otherwise, it might run with a single
CPU.
So in this case, we use this nprox, dash dash nprox, and we give the same number.
And it's important that the numbers match, because otherwise you might run into a situation
where you reserve more CPUs than you use, or you use more CPUs than you reserve.
And in both cases, like in the case where you reserve too many, you underutilize the
CPUs.
So you basically underutilize the resources.
And if you use too many CPUs, they can get crowded.
So they compete on who gets to use the CPUs, and then the code runs slower.
So sometimes if you run some code in the cluster, you might encounter a situation where it runs
slower.
And the reason might be that it tries to use, let's say, all of the CPUs, but it's only
getting one, and suddenly it's slow.
you need to tell the code to actually use the CPUs you want it to use. So let's try this out.
And I guess this is a hard problem. I've often seen codes that say it can use multiple
processors, but it doesn't tell you how it actually works. So you don't know if it's doing
the right thing. The most annoying one is when you run something and it says,
Oh, I'm running on a computer node that has 40 processors.
So I'll try to use 40.
But it's actually only been allocated four.
And it's just a huge slow down then.
OK, it's done.
Should be seff.
Yeah.
Yes, if we check the efficiency of that.
So compared to my other nodes, this
says 83% efficiency, compared to 95.
And we ran the same 40 seconds of CPU utilization,
because that's how long it takes to run.
But now it took a shorter amount of time in real time.
Only 12 real time.
OK.
And so basically, it's nothing magical
about the reserving of CPUs in the submission scripts
Or in the command line, you can just
specify the CPUs per task to SLURM,
and that will give you more resources.
And there's a nice question in the notes.
Are you going to answer the same thing?
Yeah, go ahead.
I guess we're thinking the same thing.
You can say it.
Yeah.
So what I've just highlighted here,
This is the argument to srun and to slurm. So, the CPUs per task equals 4 is a slurm option
that says please give whatever I'm running for CPUs. And then that wraps this other command.
And the --nprocs=4 is a command that was programmed into the pi.py file, which tells it I have four
processors available, I can try to use them. And you can tell if these don't match up,
then stuff can go wrong. Should we demonstrate what happens if you don't get it right?
Or is that just maybe people can do that themselves? Yeah, I would say probably.
But yeah, so maybe we should just jump into exercises. If the exercise is basically
do the same thing. Okay. Yeah, I see it's already appearing in the notes there.
Oops, I copied the wrong one. Sorry. Check the right one.
But yeah, the question is, how do you tell the program what you want it to get?
Yeah. How do you tell the program what resources it should use? In many cases, this is something
like nprocs. Many programs use this OMP_NUM_THREADS environment variable, and they use that. For
example, NumPy uses that to determine how many processes it should use. They are all
listed in the documentation. So, there's many environment variables that sometimes set these
numbers. And if you look at the documentation of a library that you're using, it might say
that, hey, give it the number of processes with n processes or nprocs or nthreads or whatever.
like there might be various flags for there's no like consistent language across the board
so you need to look at your your application and if it provides a possibility of using
multiple processors and if it does you need to give the information to it
yeah and there's a good question what's the limit of the number of CPUs a program can use
Yes, that's an excellent question. And the answer is that it depends on the hardware.
Like in many clusters, you have compute nodes that might have a number of CPUs that might
run from, let's say, 28 to 256 or something like that. It might be small or it might be
very large. But because you're all limited into this one computer, so it depends on the
hardware available in your cluster.
And of course, you might reach the parallelism maximum.
At some point, it doesn't run any faster
after you reach a certain number of processors.
Usually, quite often, magical numbers
might be something like 8 or 16 or something.
But there might be something that
works with 64 or 128 as well.
Yeah. I guess it really depends on what it is you're doing.
Yeah. But usually it's on that ballpark. So we're talking about tens to hundred
processors usually. Yeah. So how long should people have to try this themselves? And is there
anything else to try other than what we just did? Let's just do this. I think that's enough.
and you can run stuff in the examples and run more exercises as a bonus exercise after the courses.
I will also note that in the exercise, there's a submission script that you can test out,
and in that we're using an environment variable called slurm CPUs per task,
which is very useful if you want the job to find out the number of CPUs
automatically. So Slurm will set this number if you ask for more than one CPU. So you can
use that in your code to determine numbers. But try it out.
Okay. How much time do you have, people?
Like 35, maybe?
Still 35. So that's seven minutes or six. Well, seven minutes. Okay. Yeah. Okay.
Then see you in a little bit. Yeah. Bye. Bye.
you
We're back.
Hello.
So what now?
I think we'll go straight to the next parallel part
and take all the questions later.
Yeah, if you want to fill out, I'm
adding the poll to the exercise block.
Forgot to add it previously.
So if you want to feel there, if you
managed to do the exercises, sorry about there
being quite not that much time for these.
But hopefully, you got it done.
But yeah, asking to see this, it's basically one flag.
So hopefully, you got it done.
But yeah, now we are switching gears to,
so this is quite a quick explanation
of the overview of the MPI, like parallelism, what it is.
So there was already a question in the notes about,
OK, how can I parallelize across multiple CPUs?
So how can I analyze across multiple computers, basically?
And this is why MPI originally was created, like the MPI thing.
So MPI stands for Message Passing Interface.
And it's basically like this kind of library that allows you to do
message passing between computers and different processes running on different CPUs
through various network messes.
When writing for these supercomputers, there's a high-speed interconnect usually connecting
these CPU nodes.
If you want to have a really large program, so if you think about a weather model, if
you want to predict the weather, you need to have a very big simulation of the weather
happening at different places, at different times, and you integrate the physics equations
to get the next time step of, okay, what is the weather going to be tomorrow?
And for that, you need a big computer to calculate together.
You need the whole simulation to be able to be calculated together.
And for that, MPI has been constructed, basically.
it's still a standard in many of the supercomputers when it comes to this kind of big-scale programs.
It's important to remember about MPI is that either your code uses MPI or it doesn't.
If your code hasn't been constructed around MPI, if it hasn't been constructed in a way
that it will use message-passing interface, it won't use it. So it's very important to remember
that if it uses MPI, if you see in the documentation that there's an MPI build of this,
or you can add MPI support or whatever, then it uses MPI. Or if you build a program from the
ground up to use MPI, then it uses MPI. But if it doesn't, then it doesn't.
Making a new MPI program is a very big process.
Yeah, depending on the program, but yes, usually you need to figure out whether your program can use MPI.
But there's already lots of programs, especially physics programs and that sort of stuff, that use MPI on the background.
And for those users of those programs,
this is a very good way.
Like, you just install your program
with the MPI capabilities available,
and then you can utilize multiple computers
at the same time.
Yeah.
So should we do the example?
Yes.
Let's look at the example.
So we have the Pi version written with MPI support.
And because you need to bake it into the program,
so the Python version doesn't cut it.
There is this MPI for Python that you can use
to use Python and MPI together,
which is a nice library if you want to start,
if you just want to use Python,
but that requires additional libraries.
So for this example, we are going to use C,
like C compiled, like C version of a program
does the exact same calculation that the Python one did, but it does it in C and it uses MPI.
Okay, and so how do I start? So in order to, usually when you have an MPI program,
the first thing you need to do is you need to load up the MPI installed by the cluster
administrators, because the MPI is tied directly to the queue system and it's tied to the network
infrastructure. So it's very laborious usually to install the MPI. So that's why the system
administrators usually provide it and you install your code using that MPI.
This will be different for every cluster.
Yes, yes. So if you run module spider MPI, open MPI is one flavor of MPI. That might be
be something you want to use.
So then we can compile our program using MPI CC.
So if you type `mpicc -o pi-mpi slurm/pi-mpi.c`.
Yeah.
So what this does is, yeah.
What it does is it compiles this `pi.mpi` executable that is now MPI-capable.
You can check what the source code is if you want to.
But now, okay, we have this.
Maybe you should try running it with srun, with the normal stuff, and see how it goes.
Like, if we just put like 10 minutes and 500 megabytes of memory and just run it.
So without anything, it should run similarly.
How many steps should I do?
Let's put the same 50 million.
It shouldn't take that long because it's C code,
so it's faster than the Python code.
Let's see.
I bet it will be very fast.
Yeah.
So it's quite a bit faster.
Should we SF it?
Yeah, sure.
Yeah.
So it said it used one second of CPU and took one second.
So it's quite a bit faster than the Python version.
So that's how it usually goes if you use the lower level stuff instead of like higher level
languages.
Of course, Python can be fast if you use the correct libraries, but in this case.
Yeah.
I mean, that's why you write a C library and run it from Python.
Or you use NumPy and that's fast itself.
But in this case, let's try now adding some more MPI tasks.
You notice that in the output,
it said that what was the computer's name,
where it was running,
and then it says something about rank.
MPI has these MPI ranks,
so basically, every CPU in the MPI tasks,
it's this rank number.
It's similar to the array ID,
but in this case,
they are like a collective.
So in the MPI, everybody works as a collective,
and they get this number.
So we can ask for more of these tasks.
So previously, when we saw the CPUs per task kind
of a situation, so these are now the tasks
that we are requesting.
So if you give the SRUN n tasks, yeah, nodes 1 and n tasks.
Let's go with 4, yeah.
Yeah, okay.
And let's add at least one zero at the end, so we get some like reasonable, like 10 times,
make it 10 times harder.
So maybe it runs for a few seconds.
Okay.
So, in this case, what we are asking the queue system, we are asking, okay, give me one computer
and give me four, on one computer, give me four of these MPI tasks.
So we didn't mention the CPUs per task here.
We are asking these MPI tasks.
And what it does basically is that when the program starts, it starts the individual programs
and then each of these connects into a collective that then solves the problem together.
But if you use the end tasks without an MPI program, you run into all sorts of problems
and the same program might run multiple times and overlap.
don't use the end tasks if you don't have an MPI program. Okay. Yeah. And I guess the pi-mpi,
we didn't tell it how many tasks there were, so it sort of automatically knows what's available.
Yes. It creates this communication world where everybody knows about each other and then they
can do the work together. And you might see here that the output is a bit scrambled because
everybody works independently and they might print out stuff in different orders. Some might
print out stuff before the other tasks. It's like one starting zero, it's done,
and then two and three report they're starting. But that's pretty typical when
you're trying to do this stuff. Anyway, should we SF it? Yes, let's do that.
It used nine seconds of CPU and the efficiency wasn't three seconds.
Yeah, because the efficiency wasn't that good because it's still so short.
So if we would have increased the.
Yeah, like these numbers are so short, it's not good statistics.
So, yeah.
It's clearly taking those times four and dividing nine by that.
Yeah.
Okay.
And in the notes, we have a good question of like, does it mean that the end tasks for
that we run for independent tasks and they are not independent.
They are a collective, like in MPI, everything is a collective.
So there's like four tasks running in the same collective, which is the whole program.
So let's say you would run with 30 computers, if you run in Mahti or if you run in Lumi
or somewhere like a really big machine, you might run with, let's say, a thousand processors.
And in those cases, you need to run with, let's say, 20 computers.
So you might ask for a thousand tasks and then get that from the queue system.
technically, it's not threads here, but it's independent processes that communicate between
each other. But if that doesn't make any sense to you, it really doesn't matter.
Yeah. But yes, so this MPI is still, for many bigger things, it's still very
like very heavily utilized.
But it's like many of the smaller programs,
it's usually better to use the array structure in addition
with the shared memory parallelism to run your stuff.
Because this requires your program
to support this from the ground up, basically.
OK, so what now?
We've got 12 minutes left.
Should we give people time to try it themselves and then come for a wrap-up?
Yes.
Okay.
Yeah, I will copy the commands we run.
In here also there's the SBatch script that you can use to run this in the queue.
And do note that if you're running this in the queue with the script, you will want to
add the srun before you run the program.
And the reason, well, it depends on the cluster, but in most clusters, you want to do this.
And the reason for that is that the srun basically ties the program to the queue system that
then tells each program that they're part of the collective.
If you don't run it with the `srun`,
they don't necessarily understand
that they're supposed to know about the other ones.
Because basically, Slurm starts multiple processes
at the same time.
And all of those call home and ask, who am I?
And then they start working as a collective.
So if you don't add the `srun`, then the program
doesn't necessarily work as intended.
Yeah.
OK, there's the exercise stuff.
So should we return at what time?
Maybe, again, five minutes and then have a wrap up.
Yeah, OK.
We'll take a short bit of time, see what you can do.
See you in five minutes.
and bye for now.
you
Hello, we're back, all four of us.
So yeah, what's the wrap up here?
From the notes, there's some good questions.
a question like, what does nodes and what does tasks mean?
The different MPI implementations.
This can get really deep really fast.
And I guess we're not even trying to go into it that deep.
Yeah.
So I highly suggest looking at our documentation
and other sites documentation if you plan
on using any of these frameworks.
Like the problem with, I would say,
like there was a great feedback that there
be more exercises, and I completely agree. But especially for these topics, it's very hard to
have exercises because they depend so heavily on the application. But the main thing to remember,
I would say, is to remember that these are the paradigms that are usable in the systems.
If you have a program that mentions something about threads or workers or whatever,
it usually means that you can use multiple CPUs.
And if you have something that mentions MPI,
then it usually can use MPI.
And remembering these words and these connections
allows you to then ask the queue
to provide you those resources.
But those exact flags you want to use
and exact implementations you want to use
differ based on the cluster.
And then it's good to look at the documentation.
But basically, in order to make the connection
okay, now we are talking about this sort of approach is very good, because then you can
make certain that your code uses all the resources it can use.
Yeah. And I see in the notes here, there's two questions about weird internal MPI errors,
which are caused by who knows what. And yeah, this is what I think of when I think of MPI. So,
So having to figure out the cluster thing,
get your code working, get all the problems solved,
it can make stuff run faster, but it takes some time
to figure it out.
And at least if you're at Aalto, come ask us
rather than digging into it, unless you just
want to dig into it, in which case, by all means, go ahead.
And I don't think we can really answer these here.
Who knows what it is?
I guess you've probably seen there's feedback of the day here.
You can start filling that in.
Is there anything about parallel or any other general questions we should answer before
we leave for the day?
I guess if so, write them down.
Any other general questions we may have missed from before or you'd like us to talk more.
So what's the expectations for day three now?
We covered what was in the schedule.
Are there many exercises and hands-on things tomorrow?
Does anyone know?
Well, at least in the GPU part, we
will be doing some small examples.
But again, it depends on the application you're using.
So it's quite a hard thing to say.
And in the LLM session, in the example,
we will definitely show you how you can do stuff, at least
here in Aalto.
And we show code that you can use to run local LLMs.
But yeah, we will have hands-on exercises, but of course, yeah.
Depends on how involved you want to be.
And we also have two philosophical sessions, one about how to ask for help with supercomputers,
which is a talk written by one of our collaborators in Norway, but I'll be
presenting. It sort of gives you some insight for, you know, when and how and what it's like
to ask for support. And then there's a wrap-up session at the end of the day which has 20
minutes budgeted. And what's usually happened other years, sort of all the instructors come
here and you can ask us all the questions about anything at all. So all the big broad things,
putting stuff together and we can see what happens there. So, yeah.
Yeah, so do stay for that. And I guess there's nothing special to prepare. If you have access
to the cluster, you can probably run the stuff we do tomorrow. The GPU stuff may be different
on different clusters. So it would be good to review the GPU info for whatever cluster you have
and then come prepared with that tomorrow to see if you can get it working.
Or even see if you can get it working over the night. If you are hungry for more exercises,
like all of the tutorial pages linked in the material, they have at the end multiple exercises.
Because if you want to do them, and even better, if you want to give feedback on if you had
done them, like how could they be improved, or which one would you want to see in the
course, let us know, that would be great.
But no worries, there's no homework, we don't force you to do something if you don't want
to do it.
But if you feel like you still have the hunger to write some Slurm scripts, do go and check
the tutorial, basically.
Yeah, OK.
Great.
Should we wrap up for now?
And I guess see you tomorrow at the same time.
Yeah.
Come prepared for all your stuff.
Yeah, OK, great.
Have a good, or wait, was there any other feedback questions?
No, no questions.
Lots of love for the cat.
Yeah, thanks for all the stuff.
Hopefully cats will come back tomorrow.
It's only morning, so it might be sleeping.
OK, great, see you later.
See you.
Bye.
you