CodeRefinery.org
you
____________________________________________________________________________________________________________
the course or not using what's in the course and what you would do otherwise.
I got stun locked in the fruit section, wondering about the avocado. Is that a fruit?
Like for me it goes into the vegetable family, but maybe it's a fruit like technically. Maybe
there's seeds inside of it or something. I don't know like what's the definition, but
But yeah, that's an interesting one.
But avocados are really cool.
OK, well, Wikipedia says it's a botanical fruit.
OK, well, the more you know, the more you know.
Wait, no, I searched the wrong thing.
I opened the fruit page instead of the avocado page.
Evergreen tree.
It was prized for its large, unusually oily fruit.
Yeah, I think maybe the fruit is part of the plant
or something.
But yeah.
Only mention of vegetables in vegetable salad.
So OK.
Have to go for a Wikipedia deep dive again in the afternoon.
OK.
So [name] and [name], will you get to do much computing stuff
next week.
Yeah, hopefully.
Hopefully, there's customers who have computing problems like for us, it's quite often like
we are often the people who help people with the tools.
We don't necessarily use the tools like by ourselves if like, because we often help the
researchers with their problems, not so often that we do the research ourselves.
So it depends on what the researchers are doing.
So maybe some people from this course will drop by the garage and we get to do some fancy
computation stuff.
Yeah.
Cool.
Yeah, that's a good answer.
It's like really depends on the customers.
So hopefully we would get new customers and it would do a lot of computations.
But at the moment, I have something to do as well.
Yeah.
It's not related.
It's more like a Kunda environment thing than the computational stuff, but yeah.
Yeah.
Okay.
Do you want to know how long it takes to make videos?
So [name] and [name], how long do you think is worth making videos?
Like if you're doing it on the same day as you have taught the whole day, like I would
say zero hours.
I think that you should like leave them for another day, but let's say, I guess it takes like
two hours, let's say. But how long is it worth taking? Oh, but you guessed, yeah.
Zane, quick guess. I would say less than one, but I don't think it takes that long. I think
it's like five. But yeah. So my guess is it takes between two and three hours each day.
The most annoying part is revising the subtitles, which maybe I should ask
[name] to write an AI-related thing that will do that for me automatically. But yeah.
Yeah.
OK, let's go on.
So if we go to the schedule, which here, what do we have for?
We have How to ask for help with supercomputers
So I start with this How to Ask for Help, which is a talk.
Actually, I'll add it later.
Then we have two talks, which are basically
about GPU-related things, for which [name] and [name] and you
do, and then an end time where you can basically
ask us questions about anything.
And we'll answer that.
Also, I guess it serves as a bit of a buffer.
So with that being said, let's go to this.
I will, [name], I need to share my screen here.
Hmm, let's see, oh wait, there's too many buttons to click.
Okay, yeah, some fun with the streaming stuff there. Okay, so welcome.
The first talk is this,
How to ask for help with supercomputers.
This is actually not my talk,
not my slides, though I've contributed a bit to it.
It's by one of our colleagues,
[name], who worked in Norway,
basically doing a lot of the same stuff that we do.
What's the point of this talk?
To give you a perspective of whenever you come to us,
when should you come to us and how to come with us,
and ask us things.
So yeah, what kind of help is available? When to ask? Especially this like how to write a message
that looks good and we can answer quickly because we probably both want to be able to
for you to be able to answer stuff or to have good messages so we can answer quickly
and a little bit more advice on getting started. So yeah, here's the credits.
There's some people you know there. Okay, so when you need help with something,
what are the different places or ways you can ask for the help? So there's
different things available. So often a good place to start is asking your
colleague. So it's really simple to ask someone who sits at a desk next to you, hey, have you had
this problem? If they say yes, then that helps you. If they say no, then you can keep working
on it yourself before asking again. There's these official, like, live help sessions,
garage office hours, stuff like that, search engines, chat, the real information.
One interesting place is that you can search, if you're at Aalto, the issue tracker we have.
So we ask people to make their issues there in public, so that way you can help all the
next generation of things. That also encourages us to give better answers, because we know that
it won't be helping just you, but all the people in the future. Anyway, people sometimes wonder
when do you ask for help? So should you work on it forever? Are you going to get bitten if you go
ask for help? Is that seen as a bad thing? So my philosophy is that computers are way too complex
these days and no one can possibly tend to know everything they need to know about it. It's just
too much. Even within our team here, we have a policy that if you don't know something, ask
someone with a really low threshold because it's just not worth spending time trying to
solve a problem that's already been solved. Unless, of course, you want to
do an exercise to solve it. But, you know, your exercises are probably the actual research or
other work you're doing and not some solved computer problem. But do at least try a little
bit yourself, do your googling, start at the lower levels, and then work up as you see it's needed.
You know, basically do enough that you learn something so next time maybe you can
solve it yourself or know where to look for the future.
So this is an advice I got when I asked someone what do you wish you knew now that
what do you know now that you wish someone had told you? They had this philosophy. So,
for every problem they had, they set an internal limit in their mind. So, they might say, okay,
I'm trying to get Python to run on the cluster. I think it's reasonable that it should take me
an hour to do that. So, I'll work on it for an hour, and then I'll go to the
Science IT Garage and ask for help because that's the reasonable thing. If it's
not done within an hour, then there's clearly something wrong here that is taking much longer
than it should. When you ask for help, if you come especially to our live thing, you can ask,
can you do this for me? Can we do it together? Or you could ask, should this be a hard problem?
am I looking the right direction and should I keep going with where I am?
And at least if you come to us and you say, is this the right direction? Like, can you help
point me in the right documentation? Am I looking at the right page? We're happy to say, yeah, it
looks like the right page. And then you can keep working and come back the next day if you need to.
So, I guess if you're seeing this talk, you've already seen a lot of the people that are on
the other side here. But the people answering are also humans and we're also not great at
everything. We're not superheroes or something. We just try to be as good as we can.
So this says something for the other side. So we do a lot of work in our team to try to
teach, like remind people that we need to be nice when people are coming to us. So we have
people at all sorts of different levels of education, or not education, but different
points in their careers, knowing more or less who are studying computers or are not studying
computers and it's just some sort of tool, and we need to be respectful and understanding of
all these different types of things. And on the other hand, realize that, yeah, like it says,
Because we don't know everything either.
We're also really busy with possibly too many problems.
So this is an example from the author of these slides.
So someone wrote a super long message saying something, and it was actually hard for the
person who was reading it to figure out what you even needed.
So they responded with this one-line email saying,
oh, I guess you want to get the code.
Sure, here it is.
So it could have been a much quicker request there.
It's good to have a good email subject and things like that.
So of course, you don't know what the actual problem is,
but try to give a little bit of clarity of what it is.
Because when someone goes to the issue tracker,
they see a bunch of titles.
and they'll start at looking at the stuff that they think there's the highest chance of them
knowing and answering first. So that is something like my job is crashing today but not tomorrow
or yesterday. Then we know, okay, so this might be something that has changed in the last day.
we can look in there more quickly.
It's good to have all this different context.
So the more we know about what happened better.
Sometimes someone will send a request saying,
hey, my job isn't working.
But they don't say what cluster they're on.
So if you send it to the Alto people, that's obvious.
But if you send it to, for example, CSE people,
that's not obvious at all.
And that just makes more time that has
to be spent to figure that out.
Or we have to send something back saying,
can you please tell us what you actually did?
And that's not fun.
And we don't want to just say, reply always with,
well, we don't really like your request, so just tell us more
so we don't have to do anything.
The more initial stuff, the better.
So anything special that might be here?
Is there anything special about the environment?
Are we allowed to look at your files directly?
And so on.
OK, and this is something that I had thought up.
So there, as soon as you see these lists of how to ask
questions, and it's a long multi pages of do this, and this,
and this, and this.
And that's basically saying, we don't
want you to ask questions because we
I want you to have done all this other stuff first.
So I tried to narrow it down to like a really simple thing.
What are the most important things for us to know to answer
without making it seem too overwhelming?
And this is what it is.
So has it ever worked?
So if you're trying to run your first job on the cluster,
that's a lot different than the jobs works yesterday,
but not today.
If it's never worked at all,
that means we need to start with a much broader perspective.
If something worked yesterday, but not today,
and you know it's the same, we know to immediately ask the person that's been working on the cluster
recently and, hey, have you changed anything? Did we just break something there?
And what are you trying to accomplish? So not just like I'm trying to run this job on the cluster,
but I'm trying to run, what's the program? I'm trying to run PyTorch on the cluster to do
inference or whatever. So we'll see a little bit more about this later, but having the big picture
of what you're trying to do is important, because if we don't have the big picture,
we might give a too specific or too general answer somehow. Actually, no, I'll come back to this
later. So what did you do? So what have you actually typed and done there? If you say,
my job doesn't work, but you don't give the job script, well, we'll be like,
please tell us the job script or whatever.
The more you can copy and paste, the better.
I recommend don't use screenshots because we
can't copy and paste text from screenshots.
Also, it doesn't appear in
the e-mail messages we get and so on.
But go to the terminal,
copy, paste it into the message.
It doesn't matter if it looks bad,
we can dig through it.
And this is like the exact commands you ran, the files,
stuff like that.
It's usually better to give more stuff rather than too few
stuff, because we're quick at scanning through all this text
and seeing what we need.
And it doesn't take you very long
to copy and paste relative to trying to describe it.
And finally, what do you need?
So are you looking for a complete solution to someone
to solve the problem for you and give it back to you?
Or are you looking for, hey, is this expected?
Should I keep working on it?
If you say, I just need help with this one little bit,
that's OK.
If you say, hey, I'm completely overwhelmed with what this is,
can we look in more depth and do it from the beginning?
Then we can start reserving time and doing it that way.
Especially if you need something small,
say that you need something small.
That helps a lot.
Yeah, this is the tell us what you tried.
So have you tried narrowing it down?
Is it failing in only one way or multiple ways?
There's different ways to tell us
how you've done the narrowing.
And this is something that has been called the XY problem.
There's some website around it.
I don't know where it came from.
But the problem is that someone has a problem.
They try to do some solution to the problem.
The solution doesn't work, so they ask
about what the solution is.
Like, I can't run this or that script.
We go, we help them with that solution,
and then it turns out that they were
trying to do the original problem that wasn't actually
a good solution to the problem.
So we could have said, hey, you're
trying to get a content environment solved,
do you know we already have an environment
that's designed for LM usage
and it probably has what you need,
so why don't you use that instead?
So basically this big picture is quite important
so we can see, do we need to take a step back
and go down a different way?
Also, if you don't do this,
there's a problem that the staff will answer
the one exact question you answer
then say okay it's done and close the issue because they get measured by how quickly they
close issues and how few issues there are so yeah
I guess this is more advice for us that are here but if you're ever helping people
think of these kind of things so it's important that we the staff answering make the person
realize or think that they're valued and we want to actually help them. The worst thing to do is
send back different links saying have you read these pages first what you need is in here and
then like a two sentence answer or something like that. So we try to consider this and do well
but if we're ever not perfect we're sorry and it's okay to let us know.
So when you send requests, I guess
this is perhaps more from other people.
I guess it basically applied to us.
So when you send a request in written format,
it goes to a issue tracker.
And then there's a bunch of issues there.
And the people coming have to find what's available.
So at least within Aalto, we sort of all
try to look at it and ask the right person
to answer it no matter what time it is. But at some point, in some organizations, there's like
one person that's answering for one week and then they have multiple weeks when they're off
and doing other work. So there can be very different types of people answering these questions.
And if something takes too long and you don't get an answer, then consider asking a different way.
if you're at Alto, then come to our daily garage
and ask questions.
Because if we get a written message
and it's not clear what the question really is,
people are always going to first work
on the ones that are more clear.
And if you come talk to us live,
then it is much easier to do this quick back and forth
and narrow things down and that works better.
OK, we're a bit running out of time,
so let's not go into this too much.
But example request, I'm this username.
I'm trying to do something.
I can log into the other clusters.
I can't log into this cluster and the exact message
that's there.
This is a pretty good request.
So it gives the context.
It gives what does work.
And then it gives exactly what doesn't work.
And from us, at least me as a cluster admin, if I see this,
I immediately know what to look at.
And I will check something.
Here's another request.
So it says, I'm not sure this is the right support.
I'd like to do this and that.
They're asking for a web server and a database.
But then they say, this is the kind of thing,
like this is what the big problem is.
So we look at this and can say, hey, for 2,000 records,
that's really not much.
Maybe you don't need a full database.
And here's a much easier way to do things.
And we save you and us time.
So it was very important that they
gave this extra piece of information
about sort of the size of the problem and the usage.
Okay, maybe I'll just stop here.
You can read here a little bit later
or maybe I'll summarize.
Yeah, so the summary here is that
when you go to a new computer for the first time,
don't immediately start with the biggest thing possible.
Start with the smallest job.
Like we started with an interactive job on one core
and then a serial job, a batch job on one core.
and then a few multi-processing. So start small and slowly work up so you can tell at exactly what
point it stops working and it stops being efficient. And then that helps you to figure
out only one thing at a time and it helps us to know where the problem is. Okay, and with that
being said, I will shrink the screen. When you are with us,
we have this thing called the Scientific Computing Garage. This is an Aalto University thing.
I think some other people might be trying it some. But the basic idea is that
that every workday at 1 o'clock, we, as in a lot of us,
instructors and more, are in Zoom.
And you can drop by and ask us any questions.
This is a time you can join and share screen and sort of show
us what's going on.
You can ask, oh, is this a real problem?
Should I do this?
Should I file a issue request about this?
And so on.
And well, that's basically it. So it tells a lot about stuff here.
Join us and ask for help with a low threshold. We have multiple people coming per day.
And yeah. Oh, and finally, I'm running out of time here, but if you're new and you're at
Alta University, we have people that have time in the next few weeks specifically to help with
new problems and new questions. So, by all means, if you're new, okay, basically everyone that's
starting new projects as a summer intern, we're trying to have time for you to come and spend
an hour, half an hour, whatever, talking with someone live about how you're doing the problem.
And we can't do everything in one garage next week, but we'd like for all of you to try to find the time to come by and have a quick chat with us.
And we think we can probably do it in the next month.
So, who knows how this will work, maybe we'll send an email with more instructions for reserving time or something like that.
But, um, yes, please do.
So OK, with that being said, I'm done.
Hopefully this was a sort of useful starting point.
And next we have GPUs, I believe.
That's [name] and [name].
Yeah, thanks, [name].
Yeah, with that being said, I guess I'll go.
See you later.
Bye.
we'll jump from how to ask questions into a topic that raises a lot of questions.
So GPUs are the kind of stuff that often, like nowadays they are very popular,
so they introduce a lot of questions to our users. So let's maybe start by talking about
what is a GPU? Maybe we could look at quickly into this sort of a diagram and maybe use that
as a starting point for the GPU. It's a bit small. [name], how would you describe a GPU?
I think GPU is also a component of a computer that does the calculation
but in a faster way. It's very good for parallelism. If you have small calculations,
it's very good for it. But otherwise, the CPU is the way to go.
Yeah. So, GPUs are, like [name] said, they're like a specific kind of an extra hardware component
in the computer. And usually GPUs, they are like special cards or pieces in the computer
that have this graphical processing unit that has multiple computing cores inside of it.
So basically, I hope the font isn't too small here, but basically there's usually like,
like you transfer your program and your data into the GPU,
it has its own memory
and it has a lot of these parallel computing cores
and you can run various kinds of calculations on the GPU
in parallel using all of these cores.
But because it's a separate thing to the CPU,
the central processing unit,
it means that the code needs to specifically be written to utilize these cards because
otherwise it won't use it. You cannot run normal code on a GPU, it needs to be a GPU code or needs
to be using libraries that use GPUs in order to be able to access all of the power inside the GPU.
Yeah.
So how do you, like, nowadays there's lots of different GPUs available.
So [name], how would you choose between, like, how would you know what is inside your
GPU or what kind of GPUs are available nowadays?
So I can talk about Triton, but in general, when you're talking about the GPU, you can
see the model of the GPU but the beside the model and like that the specifics
about the watt and energy usage and everything, the most important thing
that you have to consider is the memory available for the GPU because as [name]
mentioned the GPU memory is different than the normal RAM memory of the
computer and the reason is they have a specific memory inside the GPU component
and it's like very faster to write and read from. So if you go to the bottom of
this page, [name], we have a list here that shows the different GPU types that we have,
and also it shows the memory as well.
It's a bit narrow, but if you can scroll...
Yeah, I'll try to change the size a bit.
Yes.
Okay.
If you go to the left a bit, yes.
So now, for example, you can see that different GPUs have different number of, amount of memory
that they have.
For example, one have 616, one have 81, the advanced ones that we have, and at the moment
the state of the art of the industry is 141 gigabytes.
So it depends what you are choosing.
You also have another thing that's called the architecture of a GPU, which I would say
you are not an advanced user and you haven't heard of architecture of the GPU, you don't have to be
worried about that. But just to have an idea, if you are compiling your program for a specific
architecture, it doesn't run on another architecture. You can think of it as like
ARM, like in a CPU world, ARM versus Intel, or like in the old days like 32 bits versus 64 bits.
So if your program is compiled for another architecture, it doesn't run another architecture.
Nowadays in the AI world, some of the advanced techniques like flash attention and these kind of
things that we were going to talk about in the LLM part are actually
compiled for a specific architecture, so you cannot use it in the old ones.
But if you haven't heard of it, you don't have to worry about it and you can just
go ahead and learn your program. Yeah, like in most cases, when you are going to be using the
GPUs, you're going to use them through some, like in vast majority of cases, you're going to be
using them through some libraries that are compiled with various backends of this architecture,
so they can run on different versions of the GPUs. So the question usually arises that when we
talked about, let's say the memory and the architecture and stuff like that, is that
the GPU you choose, especially in case of Triton, where we have so many different
packagings of these GPUs, is that it depends quite a bit on the problem that you have.
If you have a very small problem, like you try to do some, let's say the first MNIST
data set, PyTorch model or whatever, you try to do a quick AI test thing, it won't require
any much resources. So it will run basically in the same time with any of these GPUs because
the model is so small, it cannot use all of the compute capability in the card and it doesn't use
all of the memory in the card. So it doesn't matter which thing you use. But if you're going to be
doing the LLMs that we'll be talking about later. You might have heard a lot of talk about the
parameters, like how many parameters these models have and stuff like that. The number of parameters
means also the amount of memory consumed by storing those parameters in memory increases.
If you have these big LLM models or stuff like that, they require a lot of memory. In those
cases you're usually forced to use the GPUs in the higher end that have more memory available.
But you notice that the total amount of GPUs, we have a lot of these V100 cards, so we have
plenty of these smaller cards that you can use for smaller projects. And it's not bad to use
GPUs, like different kinds of GPUs. But maybe we should quickly show how you can see, how
you can differentiate or choose between these. And how do you do it in many clusters in Aalto
as well is by setting up in your code which partition you want to use. So you can, there's
other ways as well, but the easiest way is to set up the different partitions. So, when you submit
a Slurm job, you want to give it that, hey, I want the card from this partition. Or you can
put multiple partitions over there, and you can use slurm-e in your terminal to view all of the
available partitions. It will print a lot of information over here, but what you see is that
you can get the partition names and you can of course look at the reference as well. But if you
want to use a certain kind of a GPU, you usually need to provide the partition that I want to use
this sort of GPU. That is true. I guess in our cluster you can also make the constraint for the
architecture as well, but the GPU partition is the easier way to go. And if you don't specify
a partition, but you request for a GPU, the Slurm would automatically assign to all of the
partitions available, except for the one that you have to specifically ask for, the advanced ones
that we have, which you specifically have to ask for it to be assigned to that specific partition.
Yes, and usually when you're working with these cards, quite often, like I mentioned
previously, you are going to be using them through some libraries. You're not actually
going to be using them directly because all of these cars, they utilize something called CUDA.
You might have heard about it. CUDA is this computing stack that NVIDIA provides. AMD has
its own called ROCm, but basically they are the same kind of idea. And in there, there's usually
you have the GPU, which is the hardware part, and then you have this driver library that is
installed on the GPU nodes, and then you have some CUDA library that your code uses to actually do
the calculations. So in the case of most cases that you see, you need to have some CUDA library
installed into your environment or you need to use a module with a CUDA in order to actually
use the GPUs. And in most cases, you probably will use something like you install PyTorch with
GPU capability and it will bring you the corresponding CUDA toolkit that you need.
So that's about installation or setup that we forgot to mention.
Usually you want to have the specific CUDA toolkit for your program that will then use the GPUs.
But, okay, maybe we should mention also other ways you can use these, maybe interactive
usage.
Yeah, that's actually a good part because GPUs and GPU computing can be a bit tricky
and when you have a large program, as [name] mentioned, and if you have a large pipeline
of training or doing simulations. It's very hard to and if it doesn't work it's very hard to
understand why it's not working. So it's very good to start small at the beginning and when you are
when you you know that your code works then you can jump to the higher end of GPUs if you need them.
So in the SLURM that the partitions that [name] is showing we have a partition called the
gpu debug partition if you jump back to the yeah it's i don't think we have it here but
yeah it's probably yeah i think it's mentioned somewhere there but uh yeah i think it's mentioned
here yes yes uh so we have a partition called gpu debug and the limitation is you have only 30
minutes of the time uh so it's like very good for testing your program or start uh running your
program at the beginning for one run or one epoch if you're training a neural network and then see
if it works then you can request for a large node. The reason is sometimes if your code doesn't work
it's not your fault but like there are a lot of things that you have to be considerate about
and it's good to start small because if you request for a large one, one it's harder to debug
Second, you have to wait probably longer time in the queue,
so then your program would run and then it would fail.
Yeah, if it fails, you can run
the partition with the debug and see what is going on.
It's hard to work with the terminal.
There are some ways you can
connect with the VS Code and everything,
but come and ask us in the garage.
It's a bit complicated to talk about it here.
But since the beginning of this year,
we also have the GPU debug available with some conditions on the Jupyter on demand.
Should we show that, [name]?
Maybe we could show the interactive uses from the terminal.
If we want to reserve a GPU, like if we go to the, like how do we get a GPU?
Let's first take one from a GPU debug partition.
So what we do is we would run the exact same things that we would do normally.
Like we run the srun, we would add all of the things we want to have here.
So let's say like 10-minute job.
And I'm going to run a program called NVIDIA SMI.
This was mentioned in the monitoring part that this NVIDIA SMI is a program that shows what
the GPU is doing. Basically, it shows what the GPU is doing. But currently, I haven't requested
any GPUs here. I haven't actually added any GPU requests here. I can add that by first adding the
partition I wanted to use. So I want from the GPU debug and then I can say GPUs one.
So that's the only thing you need and GPUs equal one. And now if I submit this to the queue,
it's allocated resources and let me make this a bit
And you can see over here, it prints out the output of the nvidia-smi, so now it only runs this
one command in the node and then it returns back.
And you can see that I have a GPU called Tesla V100, 16 gigabytes.
So I got the 16 gigabyte V100 card.
So, yeah, as you can see, like the GPU debug is almost instantly allocate the resources
because it has the limitation of 30 minutes.
So usually there are like free GPUs for you to get allocated.
And then you don't have to wait a long time for that for the slurm queue to get your resources.
But at the same time, the topic that I want to mention is that when we are talking about
GPUs because they are more expensive at the moment as well because of the demand and everything.
If you look at the stock of the NVIDIA, you would notice this.
But be more careful and be more responsible about the GPU usage because we don't have a lot,
we have much, but we don't have enough, I would say.
So when you are requesting, try to not be, like, make it idle or, like, don't actually utilize it.
So if you notice that you are not utilizing the GPU, the utilization is not high or you are not,
I don't know, like, your program is not as fast as possible, please come to us and we will try to
help you with optimizing your code. So your simulation or your training will run faster and
also, we would make the computation that is available as much as we can.
Yeah, especially the interactive usage, it can get quite quickly. You could use the GPU,
but whenever you're not actually running GPU code, the GPU isn't doing anything.
So, it's just waiting there. So, it can quite quickly just underutilize all of the GPUs and
because the demand is heavy, it's a good idea to utilize them as much as possible.
What we usually recommend is that if you, let's say, want to do a training or something,
like a deep learning training, if you can do it one batch, basically, if you can train it for one
batch or one epoch, you can train it for a thousand epochs, basically, because you can do it, just
continue doing what you're doing previously. So just run it longer, basically. So it's quite
easy to run them usually in the debug partition. You can just run the GPUs in the debug partition
like a small job. And once you have run the code, you notice that, okay, now it has run.
And now, basically, I can start coding again without preserving the GPU for the whole of my
coding session. But let's quickly look at what the GPUs can actually do. So, this is again,
like, unfortunately, a bit of a toy model. So, what we're going to be doing is from the
the documentation we're, whoops, clicked the wrong link.
We are going to be running this Pi example again,
our friend Pi, and what we're going to be doing
is that we are going to be building our own GPU code.
So let's first check which folder am I in.
I can get, sorry, terminal, I'm hiding, yes.
I'm currently at the wrong folder, so let me go to the work directory and then I'm going
to go to the hpc-examples.
What we are going to be doing is now building a GPU program, basically.
For that, we need a compiler and a CUDA toolkit.
This is basically, if you don't use a program that is pre-built, and most of them nowadays
are, but some aren't.
And if you don't use that sort of program, you need to give this massive, usually these
flags when you're compiling in order to make it so that it works with different architectures,
the code works with different GPUs.
And now we have a program called pi-gpu.c.
So you can try this in your own cluster in a minute.
You can try it out.
And let's run this pi-gpu in the queue.
So let's add the GPU.
So this is the exact same kind of a Py calculating code, but this time it's written so that it
gives us the GPUs.
So I will add all of the Slurm flags.
So we want the interactive terminal,
and then 10 minutes, 500 megabytes of memory, one GPU,
and we run in the debug partition.
And then the pi-gpu.
And let's give it some nice numbers.
So let's say, because this is so much faster than the CPU one,
So let's say like, is it a hundred million?
Yes.
So previously we run, yeah, yeah.
It's, it's way too low.
Uh, so this is like billion.
So previously we run with the CPU.
It took 40 seconds to run 50 million and it's basically instantaneous
to run a billion with the GPU.
So it's, they, they are for this sort of calculations.
GPUs are much, much faster, so in order to actually utilize the GPU, we need to, well,
even add more zeros there. They are way too fast for this sort of a program.
So, you can see already the power compared to the CPU. And this is, of course, just a toy example.
But now we can of course write a script that would do the same exact thing.
So here's an example script that would run the same thing in the queue.
But maybe it would be a good time to have some exercises.
So you can try out the demo that I just posted here.
Yeah, of course, the major caveat is that in your cluster,
the modules might be different.
So in order to get the CUDA module,
you probably need to maybe load a different compiler
or different module.
So they might be different
and the partitions might be different.
So now it's a good time to also look at the documentation
and check in your cluster, what are the GPU partitions,
what GPUs are available
and what CUDA modules, for example, are available.
I just want to add one more thing that although GPUs are very powerful to use, but it doesn't
mean that it's for every code.
So every code is different and if your code knows how to do depolarization and you have
a small task to do, I would say, they are very good, but it's not for everyone.
It's not for every computation.
For this Pi example, it's a very, very good match and it can be run a lot faster than the CPU
because you can do all of the calculations in parallel.
Let's have the exercises. We'll probably answer a few of the questions in the notes.
like we'll answer them through the exercises and we'll probably answer a few of those and
then we'll have a break. So try out the demo that I posted here. I'll post this into the
notes as well.
Yeah.
Is it supposed to be exercise now? Time now? Should I go to the break or?
Yes, let's have exercise until 45, sorry, 55.
Yeah.
Okay, then I will say bye.
you
And hello, we are back.
So I hope you had a possibility to attend the exercise, it was quite a short amount
of time, sorry about that.
There was a lot of good questions or good discussion in the notes.
So there was a question about the GPU RAM, and what is the rule of thumb for requesting
RAM and GPU?
So the RAM in the computer and the VRAM, like the RAM in the GPU, they are different.
they often are different when you're doing all sorts of calculations. So as an example,
like if you're doing machine learning or kind of a thing, you usually need to reserve the VRAM for
the model that you're going to be training and the data that the model is going to be taking in and
the data that the model is going to be putting out. But you often don't need to reserve data
for the whole data set, unless you load the whole data set into the GPU memory.
But quite often, the data set doesn't even fit into the GPU memory.
So you have a situation where you might request more RAM, like the normal RAM,
and then you have a GPU with a different amount of VRAM.
But sometimes, of course, like so often the situation is something like you might request
the same amount of RAM as the GPU RAM or a bit more, but it depends on how your data is going
to be loaded into the GPU. But they're different, and you cannot request a different amount of
VRAM unless you choose a different GPU. You cannot partition or split up that VRAM in any way.
you will either get the card or you won't get the card.
It is also true about the computation as well, right? When you are requesting the GPU,
the whole GPU is for you, the whole RAM of the GPU and also the whole compute nodes.
Yes. And there was also a question about what is the difference between the GPUs, so
the different numbers here. So they are like the technical numbers, what is the brand of the GPU,
basically. And the newer the brand, they are usually faster, they have more memory,
they are faster, they have also some more advanced specialized computing units for
certain kinds of calculations that we don't have time to go through here. But basically,
that's sort of a situation happening there. But usually it's like the newer is more powerful
and bigger. That's the situation.
Yeah, and there's lots of great questions here that we'll answer, but we need to go to break,
I think, at this point. We'll return to the questions here, and we'll talk a lot.
we'll answer all of them here and we can after the LLM session we have the panel discussion where we
can probably raise some of these questions there as well but in the LLM section you will hear more
about like what is the actual use like how do you actually use the GPUs like how do how does it
actually look like when you use the GPUs but yeah in order to get to there we first need to take a
bit of a break. So, we'll be back at 11.10. Is that good?
That's good, yeah.
Yeah, we'll be back at 11.10. Bye.
See you.
you
Hello again, hello everyone, we're back, I guess we can skip
introduction. You have seen me and [name] before. This section will be about the LMs and generative
AI tools. Please let me shortly overview the generative AI services available in Aalto.
So we have a public service as a web service. It's similar as ChatGPT, but it's under
agreement between Aalto and the company.
We call it Ardor GPT or Aalto AI Assistant.
It's similar as Chat GPT and based on the same models.
Secondly, you can use some remote APIs to run models.
Aalto also has institutional agreement with Azure OpenAI API,
so you can request that.
It has a better data security.
In addition to that,
we have hosted some local models
on entirely on our own infrastructure.
Those APIs are based on open source models,
so they have very good data privacy.
So basically, you can use them and
maybe request for different models.
This job is in developing.
Of course, if you want to run models locally on
your computer or on a cluster to get higher performance,
it's also good. Actually, that will be our main focus today.
But usually, your computer doesn't have enough resource.
so Triton or the other cluster you're working on will be a good option.
But in addition to these general AI tools, we also have a dedicated tool for speech-to-text.
[name] knows better about this. Yeah, but just to add something about the API that is provided by
ITS. If I'm not mistaken you can use it with confidential data as well but it has this cluster
structure and you have to go and like fill a form and everything but if you host your model locally
you don't have to be worried about the cost and everything all except for the GPU time that you
are you are getting for that for the cluster. So yeah in the project. But yeah but we have also
another service called Speech-to-Text. It's based on the OpenAI Whisper and it's very good for
transcribing your videos or audios or interviews that you have. We would show how to run it on,
or maybe we don't have time, I don't know, but if you go to the docs and click on the link
there is a very good documentation that you can follow both on on-demand on the web service and
also on the terminal if you prefer that. All of the processing is done on Triton so you can process
confidential data as well, and it supports multiple languages. It's at the moment very
fast because it utilizes on the GPUs. I guess that's it.
Is there anything else that you want to add? I think that's it. Let's go to our main focus
today, which is running LLMs on the cluster. So we know that LLMs, LLMs models, they are very big
and they usually need quite a lot of disk space to store the models. So we pre-downloaded
the popular models on Triton. So you can access them and you can use them. It's in a shared
the folder so it won't occupy your own disk space.
But there's some tricks to use the models.
We will talk about the coding part later.
But firstly, maybe you want to know which models are available.
So simply run this command on Triton, of course.
you will see all the models listed there.
You can request more models if you need,
and we will also be keeping
our eyes on the latest models and download them for you.
The most common way to use the models
is by using Transformers Python library.
It's developed by Hugging Face,
and it also provides a lot of tools and models,
of course, to use it has a very good interfaces to use the models. We will demonstrate some
examples later. But after you know that where to find the model, the next thing to consider is to
how much resources to request to use the model. You have just listened to the wonderful talk from
similar and the whole thing about GPU computing.
So when it comes to LLMs,
GPU is where most of the time needed.
So you needed to request the GPUs.
The thing is, what kind of GPUs to request?
That depends on the model,
which model you're using.
Meanwhile, you needed to request
some number of CPUs and system memories.
You have just listened to this,
that the system memory is
something separated from the GPU memory.
Let's first talk a bit about the GPU memory.
When you request a GPU,
you get the whole GPU,
so all the memory belongs to you.
but different GPUs have different amount of memory.
On Triton, we can use it as infer.
I think [name] also showed that
to get a list of partitions available.
Partition names can reflect the GPU type.
For example, GPU V100 with 32 gigabytes memory,
There are also some other newer GPUs like A100 or H100 and H200.
But the thing is,
how much memory do you need?
It depends on the model size.
We have a table here as a reference that usually,
when you find a model on Hugging Face,
there will be a model card.
The model card will tell you how many parameters the model has,
and also from the model name,
you can also know the number of parameters.
For example, it's a Mistral 7-billion model,
then it has seven billion parameters.
But it depends on the data type used by the model.
it could be like 28 gigabytes or 14 gigabytes,
or if you quantize the model,
then it will be even like a half the memory.
So this table can be roughly telling you
that how much GPU memory you need
and then which kind of GPU you can request.
But there's some other tricky things here
Because AI is developing very fast,
some models, they use different operators.
And some operators or model layers
may need a different GPU computing capacity.
So it's a bit tricky that maybe the model can fit in the GPU,
but the GPU doesn't support the model
or the software you use to run the model.
So you may also face this kind of errors.
Don't be very worried.
You can come to us.
We can help you to do the troubleshooting.
And you can also try out, generally speaking,
try out newer GPUs.
So that's about the GPU memory.
Let's go back to this again.
And there's the system memory.
The system memory, well, like [name] mentioned before,
it depends on how your program was written
and how the data will be loaded.
So usually we will request a bit more memory,
system memory than GPU memory.
For example, here, the GPU memory is 32 gigabytes.
I put 80 gigabytes here,
but it's probably a bit too much, I would say.
But roughly speaking,
the system memory is less expensive,
so I would use a slightly higher number.
For example, maybe 40 gigabytes is enough here.
And then the CPUs, a number of CPUs.
Sometimes you need multiple CPUs to run the models.
Some framework can use multi-processes to do
some data pre-processing or even some intermediate steps,
many more CPUs.
So in general, I would put a few more CPUs here
And again, it's less expensive than GPUs.
So what do you think, [name]?
Do you have anything to add here?
I was trying to answer a question.
But no, I think it's fine.
But the thing that you were mentioning
about the architecture of the model
is also an important thing.
And again, if you don't know what is happening,
I guess you don't have to worry about.
But sometimes, some part of the model
or like some part of the calculation needs
and a specific kind of architecture like flash attention
that it's like very popular nowadays.
But if you run it on a normal GPU
that doesn't support the flash attention,
it would just raise an error.
So it's like very likely, especially at the beginning
when you're working with these huge models
to care to face a lot of issues
and then don't get worried, come and ask us
and we would try to help you.
Or ask GPT in that case, but we prefer human interaction.
Yes.
OK.
Yeah, I mentioned that we have downloaded a lot of models
for you and put them in a shared folder.
The thing is Hugging Face Transformers
doesn't look for the models by default.
There is an environment variable called hifhome.
By default, it's pointing to your home folder.
As you have learned on the first day,
I guess, your home folder is kind of small.
It has only 20 gigabytes disk space.
So what you should do essentially
is to change the Hugging Face home to the shared folder
we have.
But again, as you have learned before on Triton,
or I would say most of the clusters,
a lot of softwares and tools will be managed by modules.
So here we also use a module to manage
the access to the models.
So you need to module load the model hacking face.
What this does is basically setting the hacking face home
to the correct location, the correct directory,
which is this one here, yeah.
And by doing this,
transformers will know where to find the models.
But after that, you need to have a proper conda environment
to use the models.
We have created a model, sorry,
we have created a conda environment,
which is called scicomp-llm-env.
This is managed by us.
It has most of the popular frameworks,
like Transformers, like llama.cpp and the stuff like that.
But if you need your own ones,
you can make a customized conda info
by using the knowledge you learned from yesterday, I think.
But anyway, for this demo, we can use this one.
And most of the times, this one would work, I would say.
So that's the Python environment.
But after that, we needed to do something else
to let Transformer to use the local model instead
of downloading models from HuggingFace.
So we needed to set up two environment variables.
Here is transformers offline, kind of set it to true,
and then export another one.
It's also for transformers to load the local models,
and then run your Python script.
We will show the example later.
I will skip this Python script.
We will see it in the demo.
Yeah. I think that's all from here.
We can start to the demo now.
Maybe we can show a real example.
Sorry?
Yeah, we can show a real example.
It can be a bit overwhelming to hear all of this in a 30-minute session,
but once you understand a bit of it and then get your hands dirty,
you would, don't worry, you will get it.
But at the beginning, it can be really overwhelming with
all of the environments and different parameters
that you have to set.
Yeah.
Okay, let me go to the,
I'll use the on-demand Jupyter Notebook to do the demo.
This is my work directory.
I haven't downloaded the examples.
I will go to the repo.
Okay.
The LLM examples report, yeah.
Yes, it's in the note.
You can see we have a few different examples here.
Today we will focus on the hacking face models.
We also have models for VLLM and
also a small example for like a chat with your PDF.
It's a kind of AI application example,
but we will focus to HuggingFace.
So basically, we have a minimal example here.
I have the Summator script.
So this is the one.
This is a batch script you have seen from the previous days.
Basically, I have the time here and the number of CPUs and the memory.
Okay, I have 40 gigabytes here.
It's more reasonable.
I request one GPU.
Of course, you can request the two GPUs if
the model is large and couldn't fit in one GPU.
But that's a little bit advanced.
Maybe we can look at that later.
If you need help, come to our help session.
Then the partition, I will use this V100.
I would say this is a bit old GPU,
but the model I'm going to run is also not a very new one.
As I mentioned before,
load the necessary modules and run the script.
I will submit the job firstly because it will take a while.
Yes. But what does it do, the script?
Can you also show the script and we can see?
The Python script.
I will show that later after I submit the job.
Now it's submitted and let's
check out if it can start immediately.
It's pending. Let's go to the script.
This is the script I submitted by using
the shell script.
It's an example to use the model.
This is the model I'm using here.
HuggingFace provides basically
two different ways to run the model.
The first one is a little bit complex.
You can see it has multiple steps.
Firstly, you need to load the model,
like initialize the model and specify the data type.
I use auto here.
By using this, it will automatically choose
the best data type or
the default data type when the model was released.
I also did some memory usage reduction by quantization.
I will load the model with 8-bit instead of float 32 or float 16.
I set the device map to auto to let it automatically find the GPUs available.
Maybe I shouldn't go to that detailed stuff.
We have the tokenizer and the tokenizer will be initialized under the messages.
You want to pass to the model and then use the tokenizer to do some preprocessing for the text, like apply some chat template.
But again, we won't go to the details. This is necessary for some models.
And then the inputs after the preprocessing, the inputs will be passed to the model.
The model has a generate method and then we will see the generated stuff.
But this is a slightly complex procedure to use HuggingFace models.
There's a higher level help API from Transformers or from HuggingFace.
It's easier, but before that, maybe let's go back to the terminal to see if it's running.
Okay, it's done, I think.
Okay, it's done.
Actually, I want to show you the GPU usage.
Maybe I should submit it again.
But we can also look at the seff data as well.
Yeah, yeah, of course.
And let me see if it's still running.
Okay, it's running.
Anyway, let's go back to this one.
So a easier way to use the transformers
is by using the pipeline API provided by Hugging Face.
You don't need to specify the tokenizers
and like initialize the model separately.
You just put all the stuff to the pipeline,
the name of the model, sorry, the task,
name of the model and the device, the GPU, and some other parameters, some generation parameters
or model arguments and all the configuration stuff here. Then the message, then it's...
The job is running, so if you want to show that... Yes, let's see.
It's quite, I hope it won't be stop.
Okay, now we can see the usage of GPU.
So, I gave it 32 gigabytes of memory GPU,
GPU, but it used only half of the memory.
GPU utilization is also lower than 50%.
Well, this is something you can see yearly.
OK, now I think the calculation has started.
The usage of the memory is increasing to 24.
Okay, yeah, so basically, you can have a look at the GPU memory usage and the computation
usage in real time, but as [name] mentioned that after the job is done, we have the other
tools to show the resource usage.
Okay, now, maybe let's have a look at the output.
We have two, the first one.
Yeah, the output, well, it's not something very exciting.
I just give it a message and it will apply a chat template,
it will apply a chat template,
kind of give the model some reminders.
Okay, this is the starting point of the prompt,
this is the end,
and this is the starting point of your message.
Sorry, so firstly is the system prompt
like you are helpful assistant thing,
and then it's the starting point of your message,
your question.
And then it will also add the starting point
for the assistant, kind of telling it,
now it's your turn to continue the generation
to answer the questions.
Yeah, we can see.
Yeah, then the pipeline, by using the pipeline,
we kind of skip the intermediate steps
and get the response.
By default, it will give you the prompts and the answers.
You can do post-processing for this.
Do we have any questions?
I was trying to answer the questions.
We have a user who faced an error.
with the CUDA, I guess, but I'm not sure. But I just want to ask a question. When we're
looking at the utilization, the utilization was like around 20 or 30 percent.
How can we try to increase that or why is the utilization low, I would say?
I think the utilization is low mainly telling us that the GPU is waiting for CPU doing stuff.
or sometimes it's the input to output things going on,
and the GPU is waiting for that.
But in our case, I think it's mainly GPU waiting for CPU to do stuff.
But our example is quite small.
We don't have very large input data,
and also we requested,
I think we do some quantization of the model.
Yes, we did. We used this to do some quantization.
It will also make the computation lower,
and the usage lower.
But if you are running something very big,
you would definitely need to optimize the usage of GPUs.
But don't worry about that.
It's a bit complex or tricky sometimes,
so don't hesitate to talk to us.
What essentially it means that load utilization,
it means that your GPU can do much more computation,
and because we are only answering simple questions here in this example,
it means there are not enough data
or not enough computation for the GPU to be done.
If you have load utilization,
And one of the things that you can try is like feed it more data or more complex data to a more complex
model in this case. And as you mentioned, because the model is not complex, it only
has eight bits of each parameter. It means every calculation is like done very fast.
So yeah, there are like some techniques to make that GPU more useful or like make it more work.
But yeah, it can be very complicated, so come and ask us and we will try to help you with that.
Yes. Yeah, so anything else that you want to add here?
I don't have too much from my side. I mean, we only give a very simple demo. There are
too many the other details. Yeah, unfortunately we don't have enough time for the exercise today,
but we will be there. So what I would recommend is to try to run the LLM example by yourself.
I would look at the example again and see if we can find the error that the user was
facing and would reply in the in the notes but try to rerun the example and
see if you are facing an error and if you can do that of course you can do
like much more you can like request multiple GPUs with like larger amount of
like larger model so to divide the model and everything but it's more complicated
it doesn't fit in that 30 minute session so yeah if you want to learn more or if
you have any questions come and ask us and yeah I think it was good and we are
are all right on time.
So what is next?
I guess we have a, no, we don't have a short break.
So we have the wrap-up and summary.
So maybe [name], again.
Now you can hear me.
Yeah, I'll switch to the notes.
And so as usual, at the very bottom,
there's the feedback of the day.
And not just the day, I guess, this
should be for the whole course.
Do we have two feedbacks, one for the day
and one for the course?
If someone wants to duplicate it twice, you can.
But usually it's just one.
No, let's go with one.
At least for this part.
But then now for general Q&A. So now's
the time when we can all be here,
and we'll just reflect on the course itself.
Yeah, so who remembers at the beginning
when we said that it was impossible to teach everything
that was needed in a, what's it called, in a 10-hour course?
HPC system?
Yeah, so I still think that's true. I mean, here in this course, we've only had time to give you
a summary, do some examples, and so on. But by no means do we think that this course is the end of
what you need. It's just a starting point. It basically, hopefully, lets you realize what's
possible and have had the initial experience with stuff. And now, you will know when and
how to go read for what comes next. What do the other instructors think? Was it?
Yeah, I think, I don't remember, when was the first time I was doing this course back
in 2016 or something, and the ecosystem has changed dramatically from those times.
Don't be afraid of thinking that, okay, this is a lot of stuff happening, because it's
There's a lot of stuff happening for everybody.
Back then, it was basically like we wouldn't have even, let's say, the GPU day at all basically
because the GPUs weren't being utilized, but not in this sort of a level.
Many of the concepts like AI and whatever, they weren't things that are happening constantly.
a lot of stuff currently happening in the space, like the computational space is getting
very complex. But at the same time, I would say that it's good to differentiate.
If you have certain things that you need and you want, it's good to know that, okay,
I don't need to necessarily know everything about everything. You can focus on learning
those things that you need for your work and then learning the rest later.
Yeah, so some of these questions. The first question is about
COMSOL and how to get started. What would you all think?
Depends on your time limitations. I would suggest coming in on one of the COMSOL focus
days that we have in Garage, because then there are plenty of experts here that have a lot of
knowledge of Comsol and also a lot of detailed knowledge on how Comsol exactly works.
While if you come in on another day, we do have a few people that do know about CompSort,
but you might be unlucky and, well, not get the right person on that day.
But it doesn't hurt to show up any other day, and you're welcome to, but it's just possible that
we might not be able to help you on the spot. And I would say that Comsol is one of
these kinds of programs that once you get it sorted out and it works, it works.
It's the kind of a program that, because it has this, you can submit it straight from
the graphical user interface and then it just runs stuff on the background and you don't need
to think about it. But to get it working, that's the problem. And that's usually like,
yeah, it's a good idea to ask for help because it's not fun doing it by yourself based on
just looking at the manuals. Yeah. And it's the kind of thing that you'll always find people
that know about the cluster itself but might not know all the buttons Comsol. So if you can get
it most of the way there and show us an error message that comes from the cluster,
you can probably get help almost any day. But if it's not that, then no.
Next question is also pretty good. So a custom library which is not written for Triton,
and not available, and the default instructions
don't work on Triton.
So yeah, what would people do there?
I guess, what's the name of the library?
Like, is there a public link or something?
Is it a common library?
So if it's.
So I would say, in general, I would say, yeah,
come to Garage and let us have a look at it together.
I would say it really depends on what kind of library it is.
If this is something that is, for example,
or is a Python library, then you can normally
just do it yourself if you know enough about Python
so that you can just run the code
from a customally installed library.
If you don't, also, come to Garage.
We can try to help you there.
And if there are no really strange things happening,
normally we get the things running.
But yeah.
Yeah, quite often, especially for scientific coding
and scientific programs, for the whole ecosystem,
like the Linux ecosystem and stuff like that,
like the GNU ecosystem and everything related to that,
There's standards that are very engineer focused, but they follow them very well.
So they have, usually if you have a code, you have certain configurations or configure
flags or whatever, and you can spot the pattern and use that.
But the unfortunate thing is that because it's so engineering focused is that I remember
one CMake manual, a tutorial from those people was like 500 pages. So it was insanely long,
like all of the tutorials, but it's very strict and very regimented and everything is where it's
supposed to be. But when it comes to scientific programs, nobody has time to read those 500 pages.
So you might end up that the scientific program, it doesn't follow those standards completely.
So it becomes kind of like a translation problem where you have like, okay, this is what the
creators of the program intended to be done, but they use different names for the flags or
whatever. And now suddenly you need to do this kind of translation. Okay, what did they, like
this XY problem kind of situation, what did they want to do and what things that the installation
thing need and it becomes this kind of guessing game. You need to go through the source usually
and check what it actually tries to do. And sometimes getting outside feedback on this,
it can be really helpful. Like somebody else who has done enough of the pattern recognition
to see that, okay, like, hey, they're probably trying to do this kind of thing and they mean
these and these things. And sometimes that can happen with many libraries.
Or even just knowing where in the error message you actually have to look for what the actual
error message is, because you get like three pages of outputs. And if you don't, or if
haven't done this before. Okay, this is so much stuff. I don't even know where to look
for things. And there's a thousand different warnings, errors and stuff. And yeah, we kind
of have seen these things and we know which things are important and need to be considered
and which ones are, yeah, this is just standard output that it always prints.
But I would also say that I wouldn't discourage you to try checking out the pattern recognition
yourself.
But the problem, the important thing to realize is that the problem often necessarily isn't
in you.
It might be that somebody misheard something five years ago and now it's in the code.
Now it's like this game of telephone that happens with programs and sometimes somebody
doesn't follow a standard or something, and then it gets baked into the code and everybody
uses the code already, and now it's like a standard in the code, but you need to know
about it.
And it's like hidden in a readme five pages deep, and it's not necessarily your fault
that you didn't recognize the pattern, or you didn't know about this, or you didn't
know about the thing.
But what you can try, like at least I do, is that if I see something, I'll usually go
back to the source and check, like, okay, how is this supposed to be written?
Like, let's say, like, how are they expected these flags to be given?
And why aren't they given like they are and what flags they want to give them and that
sort of stuff.
But it becomes this kind of like, it's very hard to say, how do you recognize these things?
Like what [name] said about the error messages, it's very hard to say how you spot the right
line in the error message.
It only comes through time, but it's not the problem that you're wrong because you didn't
understand it.
The message always can be bad, like the error message can always be bad, but you just plow
through it.
At a certain point, you just know to look for a certain place after you encountered
it more and more times.
It's like, unfortunately, it's sometimes like that.
But so I would encourage everybody
to just also try it out.
Like, just try reading it and try googling as well.
Because after a certain time, you
get accustomed to seeing those patterns.
And just where you mentioned this
has become standard in the code, or there is
something that is happening.
It might also be good if this is a project that
is hosted on GitHub to just look for something
similar or something where you think this could
be related in the issues.
Because often enough, there is an issue from five years back
that, why the heck is this the default?
This is completely unintuitive and not documented anywhere.
And could this place be changed?
And yeah, it just never was.
Yeah, and I have a personal example for that
just from a Microsoft library.
Yeah.
And my comment on this question,
when I see there's an install.py file,
that's not the standard name of a package project thing.
So if it was setup.py or pyproject.toml,
I'd think, OK, most likely, I can
make a virtual environment or content environment
and run a command.
And it will install it and mostly do all the stuff
automatically.
I might need to tune some, but not.
But install.py makes me think someone
has written a custom script that tries to install it.
Who knows where it installs?
And if I need to do it myself, it's
probably going to be a lot of manual work
in figuring out how they did it.
Of course, if you're using this, there's nothing you can do now, but this is a lesson for the
future. When you're releasing something, it's worth taking a little bit of time to understand
how the project, how Python stuff is supposed to be packaged, and so on, and then do that if you
want people to use it. We actually have other courses in the Python for Scientific Computing
course that's usually in the autumns. There's a session where we very briefly talk about the
packaging standards and it's not that hard. And I want to add on that, also to consider
what should be happening in an installation script in Python and what should not. Like
things where Python assumes that underlying system libraries are installed. So your installation
script should not try to install system libraries, because that is always operating system dependent
and Python says, no, I don't want to do this. This is something that the user has to take care of
in a different way. Conda, for example, does a lot of wrapping around that and adds
some things that are system libraries in the environments, but don't try to do this in a
the custom installation script, you will just most likely make it extremely complicated
for someone else to actually install it.
Yeah.
But like, like, again, like, yeah, I will quickly mention that the, like, again, like,
but it's often, like, also high burden, like, to, like, think that, okay, this needs to
be perfect and whatever first time. If you want to do something and you want to publish it,
don't worry if it's bad the first time. It's the continuous process of improvement that matters
more. I have published code that is really bad, and I have made repos that I still look back and
think that these are bad, but they were bad because I didn't know better at that time.
You will go through the process and that will happen for everybody. Everybody will publish
code that is not using the standards. It's missing something that you realize later that,
hey, I should have used this and that. Don't put too high of a burden on yourself.
But in the next iteration, know that, OK, maybe I
shouldn't use the previous one.
Maybe I should try improving it in the next iteration.
Yeah.
Yeah, I sort of say something similar.
So you don't have to be perfect, because perfect is always
too far away.
Just try to do a little bit better
each time you do something.
And then once you, like, if you do something often,
you'll get better at it and reach the level you need.
So what, I mean, OK, so for the feedback parts here,
it looks pretty similar to other days.
Yeah, so what should we recommend people do next?
So what we covered was in the schedule.
There's a lot more written material to review.
Yeah, like at least I would recommend just trying out whatever you are planning on working
on.
Like it's like if you have a bunch of cookbooks in your bookshelf, but you never go to the
kitchen, you will never learn how to do like cook food.
Like you really need to go to the place and start cooking and tasting the food for yourself.
And then of course, use the cookbooks as this kind of like reference point that, okay, it
should look like this, but why does it, why my food doesn't look like this?
And then you're like, you can do the improvement procedure, but like, I would highly recommend
that you pick a program or a thing that you want to do in the cluster.
And first, let's say you have a program that you run currently on your laptop, and let's
say it heats up your laptop and you can't have it in your lab anymore, it's too hot
because it's constantly running some program.
Can you move that to the cluster and what does it require from you to do that?
And try out, would it be possible that it heats up the computer in a machine room somewhere
so that your computer isn't overheating?
So try some program, move it into the cluster,
and get accustomed to the workflow
that you basically put something running somewhere else,
and you don't have to worry about it anymore.
Yeah, that's a good way to do it.
What courses would you recommend people to follow up next with?
Well, on the autumn, we have the Python for Scientific Computing coming up again, like
that's our course.
And there's also the Code Refinery course coming at some point.
They are good ones, of course.
I think Code Refinery is mid-September now.
So I guess you'll get links to this in your email
if you've registered.
And Code Refinery and Python for SciComp
are a lot of these same kind of instructors
and the same teaching style, where
it's live stream with the notes to ask stuff
and lots of exercises and so on.
Yeah, the focus is more on the workflows and how to use Git and that sort of stuff.
Improving your productivity, basically.
Yeah.
Should we discuss any feedback?
I think the feedback is good and honest.
And it's always complicated with this course, and especially with the time frame, how to
get everything into that.
Yeah. And there's this thing we struggle with for every course. So if you make it
advanced enough to be useful, then it excludes most of the people that could benefit from it,
and is basically saying, do all these other more basic courses before you can get to what you need.
But with today's academics and so on, like the academic system and the time pressures people
have, people just don't have time to do a ton of prerequisite courses before they start getting
stuff done. And that's why we emphasize the big courses that sort of set the basic level,
ways for people to study what they need themselves, and then also our help so we can
help you with the specific parts that you need help for. And, you know, sort of like one-on-one
working together. So time's up. Are there any final things to say? So I propose
that we paste in the student, the Zoom room here, and then all of us instructors
and anyone who wants can join there for a live, well this is live, a meeting style
feedback and you can briefly talk with us and tell us what went well and not well and so on.
Would anyone want to do that?
Well, I guess we can paste the link here and see.
Let's see.
see. So actually, I don't have the right Zoom link. Can someone put it here?
Oh, this Zoom link?
Not the broadcast studio, but the student Zoom room, which at least [name] has, I think.
Wait, for this one?
No, the student one.
The student one.
I have it now.
I have it.
You have it.
Okay.
And where to post?
In the notes in the News for Day 3.
Okay.
But if.
Yeah.
[name], are you going to post it or?
No.
You can put it.
Yeah.
Okay.
But anyway, let's wrap up now.
So, thanks for attending.
Um, we, at least I enjoyed all the feedback.
It's nice to have all these chats going on at the same time.
And I think we all hope that you have the document now.
OK.
And I'll be heading over there.
We all, that you all have a good career in computing,
however much you would like.
More or less, everyone will be unique.
OK, bye then.
Bye.
Bye-bye.
you