Okay, let's get started. It's already 12 o'clock.
So welcome everyone to this second part of the Linux shell course.
It's called Linux shell scripting.
My name is [name].
I'm at Aalto University working for the Aalto scientific computing.
And so the practical aspects of this course, a few notes.
There will be a couple of documents which we will be using.
So one of them is the material itself.
It's the, you should have received already an email
from [name].
So there were a couple of links, including this Zoom link.
And on top of that, there were also a link
to this AaltoSciComp at GitHub.
So here we have our Linux shell course.
So that's already the course continuation.
The first part was given already in the autumn,
but no worries, we will come back to this.
I will tell you shortly what we expected.
So let's continue with the documents.
There will be feedback form for yourself and for ourselves.
So this is the HedgeDoc, pretty much like HackMD, just the branch of this.
And so here will be your questions, here will be our comments, our references,
and we will keep it up to date and updated all the three days.
So the second part of this course, I mean this part of this course,
it's gonna be the three hours each, three times,
today, tomorrow, and after tomorrow.
We will start precisely at 12,
but then actually the Zoom sessions
will be open already a bit in advance.
So if you have any question,
or if you need some kind of issues to resolve,
so you can also join the Zoom session a bit earlier,
and we will take a look at your issue.
So what is my expectation from your side?
I expect that you already somewhat
spend some time to get your terminal open
so that you have access to Linux.
I'm not talking about that you have full type
of Linux installation.
It's full enough if you have some exercise connection
to your, be it interactive server at your university
or maybe your workstation.
That's enough if you have your own Linux laptop,
that's even better.
So you can do it locally.
So pretty much anything which will give you
a Bash session open for you.
So that's regarding this one.
So what you can expect from this course is that
we will go through all the scripting abilities of the Bash.
abilities of the bash. So what you expect by the end of the course you should be
able to write already your own scripts and we will start with very simple ones
like hello bash and then we will continue to keep the increase in the
level of complexity and then by the end of the day you should be able to create
something which is more or less suitable for your CV and something which you will
be able to put finally on the github if you have an account over there. So regarding these notes,
notes on the code refinery.org. So if you go there you can easily go to the edit mode
or you can have them both and you can see what you are typing in. So just make sure that
well if you have any question then you can click the help button and so you
will see more or less the references about the syntax of this code and then
don't hesitate to ask the questions over here. So we streamed this
lecture and that's streaming we're also recording it so you're muted and you do
appear on the recording so that's the point why we actually want these
questions to be answered to be asked to be answered in this kind of text mode
so but feel free it's anonymous you don't need to have any kind of account
just go there my setup my setup is going to be as next so our sandbox our
working horse will be here the terminal so this is what I have so I have a
prompt and I have the blinking cursor which will be waiting for me to start typing the commands.
Because of the commands they sometimes provide quite long outputs. So what we've done also,
I have another one terminal over here which will automatically output what I'm typing here.
So if I'm typing the command like echo test it will appear over here. You will find it useful
later when the screen will go off and the will be polluted already by the output of the different
and or I will clear the screen somehow of my terminal and so you can still look at these
commands over here. That's not it. I have also done this my demo space in my home directory on
my local computer as part of my university page. So I have on my university page a directory called
shell. If you go to this https users auto.fi my username and shell so you should have this link
actually over here on the code refinery so you don't need to type it on your own just click it
over there so here you will get first here we'll get all the scripts that we will be preparing
they will be automatically added over here to the web page and then also you will hear the whole
you will here see the whole bash history it's easy to take it out from here and copy paste it to your
on terminal. Okay, by saying that I think I'm pretty much done with it.
So this is a hands-on tutorial. So my target over here is to be more or less 50-50. If I'm saying
something like for 10 minutes then I expect that we will spend 10 minutes on actually doing
something. So there will be lots of doing over here and so it does really make sense that you
have your terminal open and you have all the setup ready to go.
I think this is pretty much what I had to say about
the initial part. If any question is left then please go and type it over here.
I'm not alone on this course. I'm the speaking
kind of head but there will be several of our team guys
helping you and me to answer these questions so if you type the question be sure there will be
someone to reply you pretty much immediately so there is will be work done in the background
but let's get back to the material so this linux shell basics has been given as i told you already
in autumn so now we will be working on the linux shell scripting the material is quite
It's comprehensive.
This is the one which is online.
I will not read you from the slides.
I don't have actually any slide over here.
I will use its material.
And everything what I will be saying,
it's more or less somewhere here,
but I don't really follow directly the material itself.
And the exercises which are part of this material
and actually written fully by our team,
they will appear over here.
So I have an example of first exercise
and so that you, when we will come to this,
you will see how it will go full.
Okay, so the first icebreaker and the starter.
So you're told already, if you haven't answered yet
the question, please try to do it also over here.
So that will give us some picture of what we are doing
and who is taking the course.
and let's get your hands dirty so my first touch will be actually writing the script