and let's get your hands dirty so my first touch will be actually writing the script
so that's the what we are here all together so my first script will be
let it be the hello bash but before we go actually for writing the script we have to decide or you
you have to decide which editor you will use
to write your scripts.
So you have a number of options over here.
There is a very popular, like Emacs.
If you're familiar with the Emacs, go with it.
There is very popular another one, Vim.
It's also the text editor,
which is used by many people on Linux.
But both of them and Emacs,
well, let me put it this way.
So it's the Emacs and VIM.
They are quite complicated
and they require some kind of passion and experience.
So when you are becoming the experienced users
of Linux Shell, you will definitely,
you will pick up one of them.
For less experienced people, we suggest Nano.
Let me run it and let me show how it works.
I would suggest if you are not really experienced
with any kind of text editor on the Linux shell,
then use that one.
It will be the most intuitive, I would say.
So when you type here something,
type something, and then you want to exit the code.
Then you just press Control X.
It will ask you, do you want to save it?
yes and then it will ask you where you want to save it and for instance I want to save it to the
hello bash. Okay and I'm now in my demo space and I've got this hello bash dot shell. So that's the
first script I have created. It's not really a script. I have demonstrated how to use nano.
it's up to you which one do you prefer I prefer VIM and during this course I
will use mostly VIM simply because it have it has really good highlightings it
has and I'm just way more experienced with this one so let's try to I will
delete this line and then let's try to write your first script your first
script ever will come with this cryptic line. What it stands for? It's called the shebang.
Shebang is nothing else than the... it says to the program which runs it which
interpreter is supposed to be used. So #!/bin/bash is path to the binary which will run the code
which comes after and so and this number sign and exclamation mark is a special two special
characters which are widely used on linux especially for the which are used on linux
for the shebang mark so in the same way when you'll be writing some python script you will
be putting this shebang (#!) with the /usr/bin/python if you will be writing some tcl or some other
something which is just normal text so that will come into use as well in the
next let's actually output something which is the hello bash
let it be even correct way so now I'm done I'm also able to put here
some comment so
let me say that it prints hello bash that's that much you're supposed to know
so then another one about syntax so this is the comment this is the
shebang that's the comment which comes and
which outputs the hello bash and then
you can continue the string for instance to another line so just put the backslash like this one
if the line is pretty long and you want to make it more or less compact and readable you can use it
we don't need it right now but just this part of the syntax and then also the indentation if you are
a python user so that you know that you need to all these strings especially all these blocks
they're supposed to be indented but in case of bash it doesn't really matter so you can put
another one command over here like this hello bash again
okay typings hello bash again
and that will be completely okay you can do it even more compact you can do the
with the delimiter it will be also okay you can do it this way it will be also okay from the bash
syntax point of view so bash will not tell you anything about your syntax about all these lines
so the empty lines that will not be that will be just omitted as usually
and this is pretty much everything else this pretty much it that you should supposed to know
about the syntax so we will come later to the blocks we will come later to the if statements
and this for loops etc and the other stuff and you will see that the actually i will use
indentation over there, but it's only for the sake of readability. So let's try to
run the script. If I do it like this
first command not found. Okay, so what happens over here? You can see that
actually from the Linux perspective you can check out what kind of permissions
this script has. So even if it's already something with the .sh
actually the .sh is nothing else than just the
extension. So extension can be any. Bash script is not supposed to use .sh
I'm just using .sh because I want to make sure for myself
that I know that that's the shell script and it's written by myself
so but only because it's text it's supposed to be executable this execution bit over here
it's missing so there should be x you remember from the previous course there should be it's
readable it's writable but it's not executable so what first i need to do is i need to change mode
and say that my script is going to be executable hello bash plus X so now you
see I've got this plus X fine it's already executable if I still try to do
it like this hello bash nothing is found
Why? It's because the bash is actually to not pick up your local files by default.
So it expects that your binaries, even including the scripts,
they are somewhere in the directory. So you have to call them explicitly. And calling explicitly
saying that I need to put the path. In my case it's just enough if I put dot and the slash. That
means that in current directory take the hello bash and execute this. So now it has happened.
Well this is powerful step. And now what's next? Next I would like to use the good practice
and create a directory where I will be putting all my stuff
and I'm not only will be keeping all my stuff in there,
I will also make it this way that bash will actually look
at my directory when I want to execute something
and will be executed, the script will be executed
without this dot slash.
So how to do that?
I suggest that you run make dir in your directory
where you are been we will come to this during the exercise so I have already
been directory so but when you will need to run it just like this so I have
already been directory I have even couple of scripts over there which we
will be later use no just one but then let me move that bash no hello bash only
hello bash over here. So now I have it in bin
and it's not yet enough. So what next I need to do? I need to modify the environment variable
called path. So if you look at the echo path there should be some directories
is where your bash will be looking at
to find the binary that you are trying to run.
So even the bash itself, it's somewhere in the directory.
So in our case, it's /bin/bash, yeah?
But you see that this bin-bash
has been already added by default.
So it's already part of the default.
so it's bash user, bin bash, et cetera.
So it's part of the default and it's always there.
But our local bin has never been added to the path.
Path is modifiable, so you can edit this
and let me do it this way.
So I can use the command export.
So now don't go deeply into this,
just type, you will just use it as is
when we will be doing the exercise.
Export, and I will say that,
export my path and do the changes.
So add to my path something which is called ~/demospace/bin.
What will happen after?
Let's see.
If I take a look at the bash, at the path once again,
you will see that actually my directory
where I have my scripts has been added to that path.
And now it's executable.
Now, if I run something like hello bash,
it will immediately be executed as next.
And I can tell you even more,
this command type -a,
this is the utility within the Linux
which can always ready to tell you
which binary will be run when you type with with no absolute path
so in this case it tells me exactly that hello bash is like this
okay then what else i was about to tell you
so the execution summary a kind of executive summary is that you create the file
you make sure that shibank is there,
then you don't really care much about syntax.
That's a takeaway message.
Then if case, that should be enough already
to get you running,
but then in case if you want to be efficient and productive,
so you will organize your own bin directory
and you will add it and export later to the path variable.
so that information should be pretty much enough to go for the exercise
to go for the exercise
let it be test exercise because you are still will be playing with the editor so let us say
that it's going to be 10 minutes yeah and now it's 12:22 so that we will go till
till till till where was the exercise down we will go the first exercise till
32 of your local time so i put here xx because i'm expected some people are not from Finland
so some people are from somewhere else so it's not uh no sorry the vice verse 30 or let it be
three so now it's your time you try it you may succeed you may not not a big trouble just ask
your question online and when you're done please put something like this over here or if you see
that it's come time is coming so press it over here like this or if you still don't really care
you're just listening uh write it over here okay so not 10 minutes is yours and let's go
I'll mute myself for a second.
Okay, I guess most of the people. I will continue. Can you hear me?
Hopefully yes. I mean if you can't hear me
then just tell me.
Okay, so the first exercise has been already done,
has been already over.
So your hands already dirty,
which is good for me and good for you.
So welcome to the world of the bash,
even though that some of you
have already written some scripts.
Actually, I wanna,
even if this hello world is not so practical,
but let me write another script.
let me go back to the prompt so if you are a python user for instance then you may think okay
I'm writing Python and I have a kind of sandbox where you can test it easily with just
writing the command and then for instance you do something like that and you just quite yeah
That's fairly easy. And you can think about how to do that with the bash.
Well, you're already actually there. So this command line that you have, it is already the
kind of ready to go prompt for you. You don't need to put bash, you don't need to put anything else,
you just put your commands and everything what you want, you can put over here.
so in this way bash is adapted for the interactive usage so scripting is just
the kind of fancy addition and the kind of value added to the bash but bash
itself is mostly about prompt and most of the commands you can run as is just
from the prompt and this is what we will use also over here so some of the
statements, some of the expressions, I will just test it from the command line before actually
adding them to the script. So scripts are made mostly for the sake of automation.
Scripts are made mostly for the sake of if you have a long list of commands, you don't remember
all these parameters and you want to make out of this complex construct of some utilities,
you want to make out of them some kind of one single command.
So this is what for you are using the scripts.
Again, and see that for instance,
one example that I will show you.
So for instance, I will be doing this archive
in time to time of my demo space
and saying that I want to compress it.
and my file name which I want to my archive name will be like demospace.tar.gz
so it's the quite common in linux tar utility and the gz compression and then I'm saying that
actually my directory which I want to compress that's the demo space
so I can just put one single dot but for the sake of readability let me put it this way demo space
so I'm doing the compression so these are warnings there just you can skip them so now
you see that I have got the file over here I'm not exactly kind of I'm not exactly
Actually, it's my colleague over here.
So I'm not exactly, maybe wants to do it time to time.
So what I want to make over here,
that I want to put it to the bin
and make it one single command,
shorter one and easier to one,
and which will serve us for the whole course.
So we will do the modification to that.
So let me call it tarme.sh, for instance.
My shell script will be starting once again
with the #!/bin/bash, with the shebang.
And then I'm putting here my command over here.
And as a good practice, remember to have some kind
of comments and some kind of revision, a history.
So what you've done and when you have done.
So I'm saying yet nothing to you about the Git over here,
but I'm encouraging you in your entire life after all,
use Git for a kind of versioning.
Here, we'll just skip this part
and make it kind of more simple
and the Git part will be covered already
by the CodeRefinery when you will be there.
So, but here I archive my directory.
So that's the easy way.
And then let's try once again, chmod +x.
And what's good about this, because the,
if you put tarme.sh, you will see that actually
it's immediately found from my bin directory
my bin directory has been already added to the path and I don't need to do anything else if I
decide to go and make another archive. I just run tarme and that's it.
We will use this further to develop a bigger script. So this will be part of our exercises,
it will be part of our demonstrations overall. So this is why I did this right over here.
okay sorry variables so definitely what you want to know about the uh when you start programming
something how to use the variables within your code so the variables is nothing really specific
so let me uh start doing this uh in the prompt and then we will move these variables to the file
so variables it can be any it can be just the letters and digits and then
minus that could be hashed so there is quite a quite a number of the there is
some special characters if you go to the variables a section of this of this
material so you will see there were somewhere a list of special characters
yeah sure it's here it's coordinate substitution so you these characters
cannot be really used in the variables because they are part of the other
syntax but then everything else can be used as a variable and so let's see what
else so variables for instance assigning the variables you just put the equals
sign and say my first bash variable it will be like this it's already there so in order to call
that variable it's enough if you put the dollar sign in the front of the name and so you can see
echo will give you the output of that variable in the same way you can use this dollar sign variable
name within any commands or within any part of your script. It just will be calling and it will
be returning you the value of that variable. Variable, there is no kind of definition, there is
no points, there is no strings, booleans, integers, etc. So all the variables inside of the bash,
they will be used as is. If you are doing this as a string, they will be interpreted as a string.
if you are doing something else that there will be if you make the integer summation within the
integer expressions then it will be interpreted as an integer etc so bash is really flexible in
terms of variables so even if you are not defined it but you still call it it will just return you
the empty variable and not the error so be careful about this and this is actually quite
common error is that you are misprinting or mistyping the variable and you call it later
and then you are surprised that okay nothing comes out. Actually bash doesn't really take
care about it. It relies on you and it still thinks that you are making your scripts
pretty much robust and checking whether the variable is empty or does it exist at all.
so where here it comes the place where the quotation also matters
let me open once again the hello script
and i will use it as a sandbox for this kind of situation so for instance i want to assign a
a variable and let it be some text
and then if I go to the echo and want to output that variable that should be enough but then if
if my syntax or if my sentence is more or less complex.
So if I wanna say that var is,
okay, I have to use already,
well, not exactly have to use with echo,
but let's assume that we have to also with echo.
So I have to use the quotations.
And here where comes the difference between the quotes.
So the echo with the single quotes
will produce you exactly the sentence you have it within the single quotes it will not open for you
the variables but the double quote quotation will do it for you so here take a note, quotation
matters so then there are a few other things for instance
less complicated cases
so let's try it out so now we will actually we can use it we can comment this
once just we don't need it and use it as a sandbox
so it has been already added to the bin it's executable by default so and now you can see
the difference the first line has been using the single quotes and the second line was using the
double quotes so yes take it take it into account along with the variables which you
kind of create yourself and define yourself there is a bunch of other variables which
have been already created for you by the environments, by the bash itself and by
Linux itself. You will be surprised if you type this printenv, you will see a
long list of all kind of predefined variables. Some of them read-only, some of
them are changeable, but most of them you don't really need to touch, except
with something which is kind of, I don't know
well, I don't know even the exact example when you need to change the
variables, well sometimes you end up changing this for instance I've been
doing this for the script which is over here but anyway
Anyway, so, and a few examples that you may find useful.
The first one was already mentioned, that's the path.
That gives you the list of the directories where Bash will be looking for the binaries
when you type it without absolute path.
Then home, it's exactly your home directory.
for instance, shell, that's exactly your bash shell which is defined for you. So I
said nothing about the other shells but that's probably the good point to do
that. So bash is just one of the shells. We were talking about this on
the first part of the course. And there are other ones which are perfectly fine
to use like zshell or something else like cornshell, it's up to you. But
this course is focused on the bash mainly because bash is the most popular nowadays
so and this is also the shell number one for us because we are running the big cluster installation
triton and so on triton we expect everyone used to bash so this is one and because I'm part of
the team so we pushing people to use bash and the whole course is about bash how to change your shell
it's the change shell command if you want to do it on your local desktop it's easy to do
you do the change shell and you just put the /bin/bash and your next session will be started
with the /bin/bash okay said that i think we can now jump to the
exercise number two so I call it variables and i will give you another 10 minutes
to do what first you need to adapt your hello bash shell and assign the hello bash to a variable
and print the variable to the output so i've done it already for you during the demo so now try to
use your memory don't look yet at my hello bash but try to use your memory and try it out then
the next one which haven't been done yet but now you have to implement it on your own so your script
which will be placed also in the bin and call it whatever you want i call it here print vars
which will print for us the home shell and path one per line so now time is yours and we're 48
so let's say that already 49 so that let's go this way we will have both
and the how to call it break let's call it joint break and exercise sessions so we will come back
to the screen at 13.09 but so 10 minutes for the break 10 minutes for the exercise and you decide
how you use in which order. I mute myself and I will add it to the
Okay, let's get back to the material. So my next stop was actually tell you even more
about the variables. This is something which is very specific to the bash. This is what
you probably will not see in most of the languages. So when you can do something with the
variables on the fly, the construction looks like
this curly brackets column and then some kind of cryptic syntax which will do something
to the variable as a string so what can be done with the string so you can make it for instance
all capital all small you can replace some part of the some part of the variable value
then you can for instance check whether this variable exists or not you can redesign it
it, redefine it with some default value.
So there are quite a number of things that can be done.
So I'm not really put everything to this material.
So, but the selected of them over here,
so you can check them out.
And then on top of that,
you can also actually forgot to sell.
So if you're ever thinking about syntax,
if you're ever thinking about some particular commands
which have been used within this bash scripting.
So all the internal logic is written in the bash manual.
If you go for the man bash, you will see the very long,
I mean, it's at least 100 pages
if you will print it out in a normal font size,
but you will see all the details about what else
and what kind of options, what kind of arguments
given by every single command which I use internally and then what all these magics,
all these extensions, all these practical aspects of the bash programming.
So the magic I was thinking about is that, for instance,
I know that the echo var already exists because I have it designed.
Actually, let me tell you one thing, you can unset the variable.
so if you don't really want this variable to exist anymore it will exist there as long as
your session is there but if you don't want to exist it anymore you just can do it with the
unset var and now if you see that I'm trying to address var it doesn't exist anymore bash is not
complaining anything about calling the undefined variable but it just returned the empty line
which is fine, which is not an error, that's just a feature. So let me say that I want still to
define it somehow and for instance it's still undefined but I want to check it out. So my
approach would be here checking out for instance
this
one is pretty simple for the sake of checking out the existence of this variable so you see
what will happen so echo or bash on behind of echo it will check that variable exists or not
and then give this error message which comes after the question mark so here i'm saying that bash
var not defined. So if you use it within the script or within your function it's perfectly
enough to make your script more or less robust. There is another one option if you instead of
exclamation mark you put something like equal that would check that variable and if it does not exist
it will assign some special value or some default value it could be anything
then just put default value oh it's up to you what do you decide to do this but then if you see from
now on echo var even has it has been defined undefined over here you see you remember that
now it already has the value. And the thing to remember with all these
major constructions, with all these curly brackets, this do column and the equal
sign is the only operator which actually does something to the variable. It
changes it. It assigns the default value or another value which you just put it
over here all the rest all the rest which are listed here as a selected operators they do
really nothing to the variable they just simply extract it or they modify it on the fly and put
it to the line to the online give it to the output print it to the output but then they actually do
nothing with the variable itself so a variable stays as is so let me let me
do the example for instance here i'm grabbing the f path so i'm saying that that's my path
to the file and i'm naming that variable accordingly so if you take a look at the f path
it's pretty much like that yeah so what I want to say that I want to first get
the path
for instance here this cryptic says that okay return me everything what is what is
before the last slash, or actually everything except what is after the last slash. So now I'm
getting the name of the file actually. So you see that I've got rid of this one while the file
itself, I mean the fpath, has not been modified. It's only the modification which has happened on
the fly and it has been outputted to the script. In order to make it modified actually you have to
reassign it to another variable. So if I assign it to another variable and say let's call it fpath2
now it's gonna be already something which will be
remember it, which will be saved to the memory and which will be part of your global space.
And then, for instance, another example, if I want to keep running this fpath thing
and want to return only the path. So that's the another approach. So I'm not going any more deeply
into this. I want you actually to go this deeper into this thing. So learn this section and let's
try it. Let's say that we go for another 10 minutes playing with this variable magix. So
what I want you to try I wanted to try in this construct where you have the variable name
and then the curly brackets and then something after the variable name late on your own or
actually if you will be ready
here is my or did I put it over here already
So, here is my suggestion for you. So you pick up once again your "Hello Bash"
and you change it in such a way that this variable HelloBash will be printed in capitals.
that's the first and the second one is that you will wrap once again that
fpath variable in the way you want to but I mean you just copy paste from the
course material and make your script to return file name only without the full
path and extension so the hint over here is that I have said you previously over
here is that you will not be able to do it with one single iteration. You will have to do it with
two iterations and for that you will have to save one variable to another. So let's see how you will
manage this to do. You will have now 10 maybe even 15 minutes because it's gonna be quite
quite a challenge for you especially for the first time but then let's go so we
will finish when at 1325
Okay, we're gonna keep going.
So let me demonstrate with you techniques over here.
So the first, I will also put it to the answers to this, both exercises, to both tasks of this
exercise will be on the notes, but then first let me go with demo.
So quick demo for the first one, echo, and then we were expecting some modifications
the var so we need the curly brackets and then we need to say what we want
so we put two hats over here that should be enough let's see what we get out of this
so yeah so you can see that actually the first one was the
from the previous version of the script and the second one was already the first
they say the other one so regarding the fpath plane so there was a request to do the
get the only the archive that was somewhat complicated and complex and I do hope that
that place some of you have got already some of this so let me grab this one and say that I
go to the bin and I will create my new script. I will call it some kind of fpath
and I will play with that and I will say that it's gonna be bash once again
and let's see what can be done. So I actually can use pretty much the variables
modifications this magic from the
from the
learning material, but here
what I'm getting, I would get it only on the fly
I don't really want it on
the fly, I want
it to be another
variable, but here
I don't really care about the
original fpath, I can
simply reassign it
in order to make the
modification
not on the fly, but
save them to the variable I can simply unsign it this way and you will see later that actually
so let's say that I want to put the fpath
and I can say here that's the phase one
it's going to be the fpath
part which will be, I will take off everything which is behind this one, this slash.
So the only thing which will be left to me, that's this one. Okay, and now that's the moment
where I can already, if I don't care about what's the final result of leftPath, this is where the
moment where I can't put something like this but modify it a little bit so let's say that here
I put the comments
just to simply here we get
archive for the extensions. Okay, you can check it out from the command line. I know that it's
going to be like this already because I already checked, so I just put it to my script already
directly. So now,
so this block is over here, now the next step
getArchive out of
so now we have to get rid of this
two so how to do that is that we can say that okay we don't need dots
and we don't need anything out of these dots
now the tricky thing because of this syntax so this will allow me to get rid of the only the last one
content of which comes after the dot but what i want i want the everything after the after the
after the dot so in this case i will have to use the two percentages so that was the complication
over here and that was kind of thing that you had to had to find it out from the
from the manual page or just to try it to fit with that
okay now let's see what's going on change mode let it be okay okay it should be plus x
and now I'm ready to run fpath and so in the phase one we got archive.z and
after the second one we got the archive so take a look once again it's nowadays
looking like this so let me put it to the
to the solution part where my 15 minutes functions that's going to be the next one here is the
so here's for everyone who wants to take a look at this later on
okay now we can if any question please ask
if something is yet unclear so i can take rid of this one and we just
have actually the part which we need. So saying that, I think I'm done with the variables
and you know already pretty much a lot. So you know already how to use the variables, you know
how to define them, how to call them. You should now by now know that the variable can be undefined
and then you also know this matrix of this bash variables which you can do with the curly brackets
and do some modifications on the fly in case you want to do this so if you want to substitute this
modified modify variable and put it to the command line so that's the way to do
with the curly brackets so now the next one i wanted to try is functions
Functions are everywhere, it's just a piece of code, which you can use repeatedly.
Usually, I mean, if you know that within the same code, you will use the same snippets,
so you can just put them somewhere else to the function and then use them all the time within the code.
this is quite normal, this is quite usual, and this is not an exclusion in terms of bash.
Functions are there, the only difference, the functionality of the functions is nothing really
extraordinary. It's just a piece of the code which will work in the normally global space.
So, basically, you will have access to all the variables that you use within the script,
You will have access to all the variables, the global space, that would mean that you have access to all the variables that you have assigned within the script itself.
And then on top of that, every single modification of that variable that you do within the function will be seen to the end of the script.
So just remember this. And this differs this function's functionality from the other languages.
On top of that, the function does not really return the result of the modification of this
variable with the return command.
It does have a return command, but the return command does nothing except returning the exit
code.
The exit code, this is something which is, I already mentioned it once, and so every
Every time when you run some command, for instance, if I run something like echo test,
you can expect that this command has returned some exit code.
The exit code is saved in the variable called $ and then the question mark.
in case of bash if it's zero that means that the action has succeeded and if it's non-zero
one two three any other digit so it means that the action actually has failed
so this thing to remember and to take a note if you are doing so
let me get back to the functions what i suggest to do is that i suggest to organize the file
which I would call functions surprise surprise you don't need to put dot shell or anything like this
it can be just functions another one surprise that within these functions those the file where
you want to define it you don't really need to push the put the shebang I will tell you
I will show you how to call the functions later on but just for now it's enough if you just
do it without it. So my first example will be for you is the usage of your
space. So let me first get out of this and copy-paste the command from the
material. You can do it on the same way. So what the command does, it shows you
the files in this current directory and sort them out by their size. So in my
situation I'm trying to look at the all the files including the hidden ones. So
the hidden ones as you remember from the previous course material that's the one
which start with a dot. So by default if you don't address them specifically
no one of the commands neither ls nor other commands will see them. So this is why they
are called hidden even if they are not really hidden in such a way. But you must say explicitly
and this is the expression how to address all the hidden files in the current directory.
So because no one of the hidden files is found this usage gives me the warning that
nothing can be accessed it's completely okay it can be ignored but the other files are over here
so I have tested this command and now I want to make a space usage out of this one
so let me write a function
or did I have a functions okay I probably haven't functions
haven't yeah that was empty so now let me go into that function and put the body
of my function and then put the actually name etc around so the way you write the
function you open the curly brackets so you put the name of the function it
should have this brackets, round brackets, and then you put the curly brackets and then you
put actually the name of the command itself. So now it has been defined.
Now it's in the file and the function file does not need even the execution bit.
so if you look at the ls -l functions you will see that it's nothing
else than just normal text file how to source it so you can go to you can just
grab that file functions and type source and you will have these functions part of
your environment how to check it again you can use type minus a and see that what kind of
function is behind the space usage and you will get the list so there are two signs here first
space usage is part of your environment by now and second sign that you can see that actually
it's supposed to work right away so by now because it's your part of your environment
you can run it pretty much like any other binary so now you can see that after running space usage
there will be this kind of list exactly that I would have get out of this command but this
comment is now has a kind of a nickname space usage the name you come with is just up to you
and actually bash doesn't really care as except that you are if you are not trying to rename some
real some real binaries and even for that there is medicine I don't tell you yet anything about
this but for this there is a medicine as well so let me say that i'm pretty happy with this
already one, but there is something else that can be used with the functions. Functions can accept
the input parameters. And input parameters, so if let me say that if I call space usage like this
and then if I say some argument number one, argument number two, argument number three,
and so on, they will immediately be within my function, they will be immediately
recognize as $1, $2, $3, etc. And we can use it.
Okay, so let's say that we expecting some input arguments, input parameters. And let's say that
my space function will be actually expecting a directory so that I don't really go and check
the current one but I can check any one
now what to do now I know that my directory is going to be like this yeah and so what kind of
what kind of thing I can implement over here. So I can say that everything within
this directory like this or even more I can say that everything within this
directory will be checked. It's already a good progress so we've got already
something to solve but in case in case I want to make sure that actually this
directory is provided how to check it and here where we can use our magic
variables and so we can implement it in a way that okay I keep it like this but
I put my curly brackets and I use this operator which will say if it's equal if this one is not
defined then let it be my current directory current directory in the bash notations is dot
so in the same way I can do it over here if one is not defined then I want to say
that to let it be dot now we are good enough to go with the new space usage so
now we already have created pretty robust
code let me check it once again was it the minus or was it the
yeah okay so here i'm doing one thing so i don't want to reassign it but i want
to return it so i'm using the minus operator you see
what's the difference with the equal with the equal i would
reassign it so I don't really want to change and I
will not be able to change this special variable $1 but with the '-' I will be able to return
the dot without changing the variable itself that's the difference
okay now we are pretty much robust and now we can even put again
return the space usage
well, return the space usage with disk usage command. Now let's try. Now we need to
source it once again, functions. Now let's try type once again. Now you see that my
script function which is now part of my environment has been modified and now
let's see how it works. First, I will use it with some variable. So, I want to, for instance, check
my demo space. Okay, let's see if it works. So, once again, this warning is just about the
dot files. You can simply ignore this. And then, if I put no parameter, what it do for me?
Okay, now I can see that actually it's trying to do it the same way
like this. So which is pretty much what I have expected out of this function.
Say it again.
Now you have written the first function which can be used then within the code. So how to do that?
Let's say that I want to...
I will demonstrate it for the sake of demonstration over here. So now let me do the
kind of dummy file. Let me copy functions to some
space, whatever, space.shell. So I do it only for the sake of demonstration how to call the
function within the code. So I'm now looking at the space. Here I already need this shebang
because I'm doing the actual scripting and so again in the previous file which was called
functions I was only defining the function, was not executing them. In this situation I want to
define it first and execute it after so and that's the way
to space usage and then even if I put some arguments I
can put the argument right away space usage and then for instance
let it be my home yeah like that
let's see what it gives us oh I can do it with the
more readable format so I can give it with the home so let's see what we will get again we will
have to add the execution bit and then because we are already in the bin we don't need anything else
space shell so yeah pretty much works okay so now you've got also the idea of how to call
the function within the script and again if you are kind of lost and you you still can go to the
bin and you can check it from here and see what's going on so I don't really steal all this
this of course from you so you have access to them
so what else i wanted to tell you about the
there are also options how to use the space within these functions how to use them
with the local variables we don't really want to check it out
one thing that i wanted to introduce you another one
beneficial being part of the syntax which is called the command substitution. So let me
say that I want to define a function. I want to call this function
me.
So what I'm doing right here, while defining this function, I'm actually putting to the
command line, not the command itself, but the
outputs of this command into one single line.
So command line substitution means that
you actually want to substitute the output
output of that command into some part of the code, into some part of the other command that you're
typing. It's quite useful. You will see it in the further examples that we will run. And now just
one single to show you how it works. So I have created it. So I have it added to the functions
and now I can once again with the type minus a see that my function has been
added and if I run it you can now see okay host name is not found I didn't
check it host name
Well, whatever.
So okay, actually, I know the problem over here.
So it's good that we've got this error message.
So what has happened just now?
Again, this construction, where you have the round brackets and the sign, dollar sign at
the very beginning, it gives you the output of the command and it just prints it to the prompt.
So, for instance, I want to check id. Yeah, and I want to check id with the
-un, so I'm just checking my username, basically. If I do it like this, it's completely fine.
it will return me the actual output of the command. But if I will try to do it like that
without substituting it to the code, without substituting it to the prompt, so I'm getting
the error message. Why? Because bash and the ground, it will execute this command substitution,
it will put the output of the command substitution to the prompt and it will expect that it's going
to be a name of the command, which is not correct. And so this is why you are getting the error.
Let me fix that functions and say that actually what I'm looking for is the echo. So what I need,
I need to put them all together and then output it to the screen. So let's see what will happen.
I have to source it once again. Now I expect that it has been fixed. Yes, now you see that
I've got the perfect information about myself. Who am I, what's my group number, what's my
group and then also what's my machine name.
Cool, so once again now you have at least two functions defined. You know how to do it,
you know how to call it you know how to call it function both from the prompt and from the from
within the script and then on top of that you also got some impression how to use the command line
substitutions.
I think we are
we are done but
not yet fully. I still wanted to add you something
with the script because I touched the command substitution
and so what I wanted to do I have to I wanted to demonstrate you some other
commands. So let me introduce you
some practical usage. Well, the me function was also practical, but this is even more practical
than it is. So you remember the tar command, which I used just with the
explicit, saying explicitly what's the name of the tar archive is going to be, and then saying
explicitly which exactly directory I wanted to archive. So here what I'm doing
in this command let me explain that so let me make it more readable
here what I'm doing I'm using the command substitution
for a [?] so first of all I'm using date let me say that I save this command for you without
executing right away so i know what date will provide to me this format of the date will give me
me a year, a month, and a day.
Okay, that's what I want.
Then what I want else, I want the current directory,
but I want to have a current directory
only the actual name one.
So you remember we've done it with the variables.
Now I introduce you another one way to do that.
You can use the built-in utility called base name,
Oh, maybe it's not built-in, maybe external, but anyway, it's part of the system.
So now you see that I'm getting the bean. So out of this one, out of this nested command
substitution, so first of all the command substitution can be nested and bash understands
this kind of syntax. It's quite clever. So you will get bean, here you will get date,
And the rest will be just as normal.
Okay, let's try it, and let's see what will happen.
That's correct, so we have created some files inside the directory that we're
archiving, so tar was given this warning.
And now you can see that actually we've got the tar archive, which is named bin,
and then the date, which is dynamically perfectly generated name,
which can be used for the scripts.
so my suggestion that we will use it right away and actually we will go to
this what was that something tell me and we will use it actually not as a
function but we will use it
as a command okay so so
pretty good we're already on the functions and i think we are ready yet for another 10 minutes
exercise so let me see it's there or maybe even 15 minutes simply because
it may take you 15 minutes. So now what I want you, this is the simple one, you can copy paste
it as is, just create the bin functions and make sure that space usage in me both are there.
And then on top of that what I want you to ask is add yet another one function to that functions
files and test it. So let it be called fast find function, just the ff, and what it's supposed to
be? You provide with the fast find any search word, any, and it must return all the files and
directories in the current folder which name contains this word. And I suggest let it be case
insensitive so in case of find you just put this minus i name so basically just use this one
put the search word the word i mean if you are not familiar with the find you still have some
time to try man find or you can take a look at the course material from the
reverse part so you can find some examples of find usage over here and yeah let's say that we get 15
minutes because this is I expected that you're back to the functions and you will write something
maybe more and then you'll write your first function and make it to work so 15 minutes so
so that means that we are back to the at 14.22.
so we have left now already less than 30 minutes to go
it's almost 32 so i see that less and less people are actually
in time with doing the exercises so we will have a short also questionnaire at the end
don't run away we will ask how complicated was the material so on you will actually your opinion
will have an impact. So if you think that we are pretty decent for the intermediate level
your replies are more than welcome. If you think that it's too complicated or too intensive or etc
your replies even more welcome. So I will try to adapt by tomorrow the
material if we decide to do so. So let's get back to the functions. So the space usage and me
actually the easiest probably was just to go to this demo space which I have
posted on my web page copy it from there and there you would get the ready to go
functions so please do it if you haven't done yet so or if you were typing on
your own, then just consult these functions that this syntax is correct. So one question was
why that was returning the error message that the command does not exist. So this was explained in
a way that command substitution will print to the prompt the result of the executed command
and that result will be already interpreted as a command.
And so if you just put your login name on the prompt,
then of course there is no command with that name.
And so basically you will get the error message
that the command doesn't exist.
Just a second, I close the room.
oops back online uh the other one uh fast found so what i was trying to what i was trying to
make it to do so find function where where was it find name so that should be already
good enough to get started
the only thing that you need to substitute is search word
like for instance if i would like to be some kind of word
i don't know let's say that i
what kind of stuff i have here do we need store bin
okay let me find for instance the bash history
so now I want to iname and then I want to find something which has bash in name
that wouldn't be enough because it will be looking explicitly for something which is named bash
but we are looking for something which has bash in the name so we need to put this
stars just to make sure that actually we are looking for something which has bash
now that should be good enough and we found already bash history which is in
the current directory and we also have found the hello bash which is somewhere
down there okay now we need to create a function we have already ready to go
command we have it tested from the prompt and we are ready to put it to the
functions so let me call it
fastfound I open this this way and I close it this way and
I put my name over here so I also was told that this should pick up
any search word not only bash okay so we can
remove it from here and then we need to specify what we want. The good practice if we actually use
some specific variable over here. Even if you can use this $1 and you expect that variable exists
we usually and the the best practice I usually suggest well I'm not sure about we
I usually suggest that you use the you reassign this $1 to some other variable
it's made in the way that you do not occasionally actually would try to edit
this or modify and otherwise you would get error message so in this case that
should work perfectly yeah I guess so but let me see the only error over here is
that I don't want to use the quotes single quotes I need to use this double
quotes. Why? Because I did the explanation at the very beginning of this session. Double quotes
make the bash to actually open the variables and substitute the variables. Single quotes will just
take the word as is with the dollar sign and nothing would happen. So this is already something
and let's say that I want to source it once again and I want to see that
type -a ff and see it's there and if i want to try this again with a bash see whether it works
it works if I want to try without bash does it work it does work because find will find you everything
even if you provide empty uh string so basically it just we're using this
they start to tell you that it has lots of file inside. Okay, we don't really want this kind of
situation. So we really want to make sure that actually this word is not empty. What to do in
this case? We can use once again a logic, a magic of this variable exchange and then what we do here
is that we are supposed to actually give out either the variable itself or the
error message and so that we can say here that what was a directory or search
word so sorry we are so short is missing does it work for us yeah i'm pretty sure this would be
already good enough for us but one thing to remember uh we still don't want that this find
will be executed how to do that and this where we come with another one thing uh which i didn't tell
you yet but i will tell you on the next session but i will already use it over here just to make
this kind of function complete so let's say that i will execute it like this and let's see what's
going on. So, source
and then if I run ff search word is missing
so it's already completely correct and so we have just exited the bash so we
don't really need anything over there but then
if you want to be completely sure what's going on actually
let's don't go that far and let's go to the next session
and then I will do the explanation and do the modification to this code already right away
so to have
to have it on the line and go in line with the traditional thing I can put it as a replace
okay here you go
brush
so here you go and let's make it more compact
like this
Good. So let's get back to the material. So my next step was actually touch a little bit the
redirections. So I'm not going to the conditionals yet. So I wanted to tell you something about
redirections because I want to touch a few other things within these subjects. Redirections have
have been actually pretty much covered, I think,
files, directories, command line utilities.
I think they have been, yeah,
redirections have been covered pretty much in the same,
in the previous ones.
And then also we have, it's quite a lot of things
covered also within this material.
So that's a kind of advanced one.
But let me say a few words,
because it's important, even if you know this,
it's still important.
So every time, every time when you are running
some kind of any command,
when you're running any script, whatever program,
lots of happens actually under the hood.
And one of the thing which has happened
is that you are getting along with your running file,
several file descriptors open for you.
some of them are reserved and even enumerated.
So that's the zero, one and two.
And they stands for the standard input,
standard output and standard error output.
And all of those guys there actually can be controlled.
So you can control where by default,
if you type something like echo,
or if you type any commands and hit output something,
goes to your standard output and the standard output is the screen the terminal of your terminal
so you just see it on your on your display basically but you can control where it goes
and one thing to do is to actually do the redirection and you can redefine actually all
of them but let's say that I want to do the redirection of something which I don't want to
see. I can use as an example ping command. So ping one of the google dns servers. What it tells me
that if ping goes through that means I am online. So I don't want this to be interactive. I want to
to just one single packet,
which will be sent and then exited.
But I still don't want this one go to the screen.
I want only the exit code.
And we were talking with you already,
the exit code, even if you don't get any output
of the command, you can always take a look
that what kind of exit code was given by that command.
And if it has succeeded, then the exit code will be zero.
If it's not succeeded, it will be something else than zero.
One, usually one, or it could be two.
It could be even two, five, six.
So that's kind of exit code.
So I think maximum is 256.
That's the maximum, but can be wrong.
So not really sure.
Usually from the programmer perspective,
can, by the number of this output, you can say what exactly has happened and what went wrong.
Okay, but in this case, what I am saying here, I've used the redirection sign.
This says me that I want to redirect the standard output to some other place. So,
you can do it and redirect it to a file and that would be part of the exercise. But you can also
do something else and you can use the special device called null. On Linux that means that
everything what goes to the def null will disappear, it will not be seen anywhere.
So let's see what will happen over here. Pink is okay and then if you see that I can actually check
the status which has been returned. It's zero, so it's correct.
Let's emulate somehow the situation that we didn't reach the ping. So I will not be
disconnecting myself from here, but let me just come with something which does not exist and
which will generate the error message. So in this situation ping actually has returned the error
message it still came to the screen and you see that actually the status the exit code of this
command was something which is not zero which is already from the point of view if you want to for
instance run some kind of if or conditional statement so this will be already good enough
to say that okay it's if it's not succeeded then do that and that okay but we still have
one other problem if there is an error it's still on the screen so what we do by default
this redirection pipe this redirection sign will redirect everything which goes to the standard
output. But we also want to redirect everything which will go to the standard error output.
So how to do that? And we can say explicitly here that please redirect the file descriptor number
two, and here we put the redirection sign, to the one. So what will happen over here?
So, from the bash point of view, both standard output and standard error output will be joined
together and redirected to the standard output, which means they will go directly to def null.
What will happen here is that no error message will appear on the screen and this exit status
is the only one we get because we are just requesting it explicitly.
it's correct, but in the modern version of... so this is the most common syntax for this kind of
notation, but in the modern version of the bash you can also use the compact way
so you can do it the same, but
but probably the other way around.
Yeah, that was the problem, not this one.
Yeah, so here you go.
you actually, you get the output, only the exit output. And what else I wanted to introduce you,
but actually not the introduction, but the kind of remembering from the previous course,
is that this exit status can be used with the logical operands.
That's operands in the bash syntax. That's the logical end and logical or.
So basically end says that if the exit code of the previous command was not zero, was zero,
so if it succeeded then do next and we can say that echo we are online like this yeah
let's put the quotes just to be more readable
essentially we are not uh i mean we are getting the error message we are not getting the error
much we are online and in the same way that if something went wrong we can always say that echo
we are down
okay at the moment we are online but then if something went wrong
whatever so we will be getting the message that we are down so this is my touch on the
redirections and then this logical or logical and and logical or you can use
it within the script easily you can use it from the command line and this is the
most often used how it's most often used on the command line but nothing stops
you from using this on the screen then another one thing which I was about to
tell you is that actually usage of the pipe this is something which stands for this one
so basically output of this command will be redirected from the standard output
of one command to the standard input of the another command and so let's see how it works
so we have had kind of couple of examples like for instance
actually we have had already this disk usage so let's try it once again
okay
what I did so what's happening over here
is that we are redirecting everything what we've got from the disk usage command to the sort
and the tricky thing that if you want to redirect also the
error from the from the command number first you will also do it this way okay
maybe it's the other way around so I was yeah that's the other way around but
actually if I want to get rid of if I want to get rid of for instance this
message you can do it from this exactly situation so I don't really want to get
everything what comes as an error I only want to get something which comes to the
standard output and so you can see that our output is way more clear even if it's harmless
it's still if you want to make your code robust you can do it this way and also I have demonstrated
you how to do that the other way around and I think we're pretty much
what I was thinking about. So we have eight minutes left but if you're up for
the yet another one exercise I was actually planning to finish right on
this exercise so we can try to do it right now and then we will come back to
this on on Wednesday tomorrow at 12 I'll do the explanation so let's say that the
rest of the time you spent playing with the redirection and piping this exercise
do as much as you want as much as you can I'll be here probably for the next 15
minutes at least and we will continue otherwise tomorrow at 12 and [name] if
you want to get something like how complicated material is that's also a
good chance to do it right now but otherwise let's say that our last
exercise for today is this one
redirection and piping so try to do it that should be fairly easy but except
the last one last one will probably take you some time to get to the point but
it's also doable there should be no something
no much of the troubles
okay let's try to do this and then i will get back to the screen
we will be about three minutes late running today but let's hope that's okay