Okay, welcome back, day two.
For those who didn't participate the previous day,
so once again, the overview of the setup.
So you can ask your questions
and you can be interactive on the notes.
You should have received already email
from [name] with all the links over there.
Then I will use my own sandbox.
Here, it's my own laptop.
And then on top of that, there is another one screen,
which just echoes what I'm typing over here
so that you see the exact commands and their syntax.
On top of that, again, there will be all the commands
on my webpage with the directory shell.
So you can go there and see pretty much everything
what happens in this demo space.
So it's kind of exact copy of the demo space.
So all this
binary is ready to go over there.
And then the bash history.
Bash history for today is 17th.
So basically you click over here
and if you want to get the command out of here,
so you will get it out anyway so let's get started uh short overview of tomorrow's of yesterday's
no not tomorrow's yes of yesterday so we went through the basics how to create a hello
kind of hello world scripts so you know how to make those scripts we went through the functions
we now know what's the variables and what's this uh magical functions if you put the variables
inside the curly brackets and what you can do with them.
So we also touched a little bit redirections in piping
and we did quite a lot of exercises to go through all these subjects.
For today's target we will go through the conditionals
and we will also go through the loops. So it's my plan but let's see how we
go through and how intensive it will be so if any question please keep asking on the notes
there will be someone also replying to you online while i'm speaking i'm a kind of speaking head
over here but then there is a team which is behind the scene doing the
the work on the nodes as well. So, conditionals. As we told you already, scripting language
can be considered as a programming language and it has actually
all the features of the programming language in this sense. And one of them, of course,
how you do the if-else etc and how you go for the conditionals. Even if if-else is presented
and we will now touch it just in a few minutes, I have to say that the driven force of this
checking and verifying something from the command line it's this double square brackets
expression. So importantly here you put the double square brackets on top, on the left,
on the right and then you have the expression and importantly you have the spaces in between.
Otherwise if no space bash will not recognize the syntax and will be given as an error.
So everything what happens within the expressions, if it's executed and the exit code is true or
success then from bash perspective it's zero and if it's something which is not
one which is not zero it could be one two three or etc to 256 it's considered to be false
so uh bash and shell and diff
bash's speciality with respect to the conditionals is that it has a number of operators
that you can use for instance for easy checking file existence, directory
existence, whether the variables is empty or not alike. So I have several selected
examples over here but in order to proceed so I want to go to the demo
right away. So I go to my bin directory and let me demonstrate you, let me show
you, for instance, that was our previous file
which was the archiving stuff. Now I want to go further and I want to actually
create something which will be doing the
more complicated stuff so what I want to check I have the file already so if you want to check
this out please do and the file is called no it's not that one the file is called tar.it
and here is a little bit more than one single line and let me explain through
line by line what that means. So now you know that we are picking up here the
the argument which is given as the argument from the prompt when you execute the script.
So I assign this argument to the variable dir and then I will start using if. So if and else
is there and actually if and else very practical and very normal if you have
been using some other languages so the only difference over here that every
single if block need to be closed with the fi that ends that's just the norm of
the syntax but otherwise if you are using if you can use l if and then you
can use else so the thing about this syntax over here
is that this then it could go to the other line
or it could just stay on the same line but then you need to have the
delimiter because from the syntax from bash syntax perspective it's
considered to be two different commands and if you omit
this semicolon then you will get the syntax error
Okay, so let me use it right away in this noise and this. And again, this expression
in the double square brackets, it will give you either zero or non-zero output. So it's
either succeeded or not. And so what happens after, it's up to you. So what do you put
this within this block of this if conditionals. But condition over here, we will come to this
a bit later, can be basically anything. Anything what returns an exit code or anything what gives
you some kind of, if it's even an empty command, can give you something which is kind of from the
bash perspective can be considered as a condition. But first of all, let me go with the example of
combination if, else if, else, and then these operators that you can use within the double
square brackets. So my first example, if I'm trying that whether the directory which is given here
exists it's essentially for me it's if and then the operator within this double square brackets
minus d and the directory name and then I delimit it because it's a standalone
command and then then comes another command you can easily put it like this
it's just a matter of of your choice I prefer more compact way so I put them on the same line
and in my opinion it's also more readable. So what I'm doing next, my final target is to actually
make the tar as far as I remember. And so what I need for the tar, first I need the archive name
we already went through this tomorrow, so I'm using here a number of common substitutions
so I'm doing the base name, I'm checking, I'm getting out of the dir the
name of the directory itself and then I'm getting also the date. So my kind of new name which I'm
will be exploring over here is unique more or less. Next what I'm checking. Okay if this given
to me directory does not exist. So it's not actually checking whether the directory itself
exist or not. It's only checking whether this variable is empty or not. So if you go back to the
back to the online material, so this -z and then something, usually it comes the variable,
it doesn't really check whether the variable is defined or not. It's only checking whether this
zero or it has some kind of length so let me show you I will show you just in a
second actually when we come back to this examples but here you see what's
happening so if this argument is not given at all from the bar perspective
perspective if no argument is giving this dollar one is does not exist it's
not defined and dir will be just simply empty and emptiness from the bash logic that also means that
directory that this variable does not exist and so here i'm checking if it's that does not exist
then what i'm doing then i'm saying that actually dir supposed to be my current directory so dot
from the bash expression that means that it's the that stands for the current directory and then
I'm already forming the base name the archive name based on the my pwd command so pwd it's the
one which gives you the your current working directory and so I'm taking the name of my
current work in directory and then I'm taking the date again and here is just extension for the
for the for the archive name
finally my final conditional logic would say that if no one of this true so directory is either
argument is either given by directory does not exist or it has never been given
Then what will happen? It will happen that actually I should say that this directory
does not exist or it's simply empty.
Actually, it's not yet correct. We will come to this just in a second.
And then I'm introducing you another one command which you can use within the script. It's called
exit. What will happen if you run exit within the script is that you just leave the script.
whatever comes after exit
doesn't matter from the dash perspective
so you will exit the code and nothing happens after
so that's enough for you it's a kind of just
quite in python or I don't know it's when you just don't want to be
you want to just close the execution of your
of your script and another one important thing is that you put the exit code exit code as I told
you it could be zero if you want to say that the exit code is successful so it's important for
from the point of view that if you want to be
if your programming part also want to be sophisticated and you want to be able to use
your script for the for instance for something else and then you want to be able that you want
to make sure that actually script fails then the if it piped to something else then the other
command would know that okay this has failed and then actually could react accordingly so
here you are providing the exit code exit code can be as i told you zero then that would mean
it succeeded but then in our case actually I wouldn't consider that this has succeeded so
that I provide the exit code one it's just normal that means that actually something went wrong
and it has failed you can provide 206 if you want to and usually people will do is that they have
a number of exit codes somewhere documented if it's complicated and really huge scripts
then for every single code there is a description that what has happened and how this can be
interpreted from the debugging point of view. And then when I'm done with my if condition
then I just close the whole statement. Again, the indentation is not important over here.
I do it simply because I want to be code readable, but this is not an error at all from the bash
syntax point of view. So it's just for the sake of clarity in this case. And then finally
if I came down to this line, that means that something has happened already.
so and I'm expecting by coming to this line that at least archive is defined and dir is defined
and what will happen is that my directory will have the name which is will be the this variable
archive and the directory that will be compressed and archived and that's going to be the one
so that's the logic and now let's try it
Now let's try it. So I am in the bin directory. tarit has the x bit. So in my
case I can easily run it as is. You remember I've told you already
previously is that because we have bin in the path. Yeah, this is the last one
this demo space bin. So in this situation I don't need to put anything. I can run
the script just like that. It's executable, it's part of the path and Bash will find it for me and
run it. So let me see what I will get over here. So now I should have get something which is called
bin and this is exactly the directory of mine, I mean the archive directory of this my current one.
Okay, I don't want this but say I want to try it out in the root of my workspace and
then if I want to run something like tar.it and provide a directory name so let it be
that another one. Story, what will happen?
Actually, it happened exactly what's supposed to happen. So I've got the archive of that story.
Okay, so it seems that it works. I don't need, of course, the archive of that directory,
so I just remove it clean up after myself but here is what we've got already
so my next step would be going through the back to the actual
actual square brackets and let me do it on the online so you see like that it's pretty much
working syntax so if I even have this like that so that's going to be a syntax error but then if I
I don't know if I'm putting here checking var yeah whatever so it's executed and something has
happened in the background what has happened let's try to realize so we can always try to see what
what was the exit code of the last command.
And in our case, this double square brackets,
it's actually in kind of a command execution.
The only thing that this execution,
it comes down to the checking
whether this condition is true or false.
And so let's see what has happened.
Var, is it defined or not?
Let us check.
echo $var
there is some value over there
but let's start it from the very beginning
so I'm unsetting this
one, so
no value behind this
so var does not exist
and so let's see what the
-z $var will tell us in this case
so it's 0
so it does not exist, it's exactly
what -z is expecting
so it's true if the
length of the string is zero. So non-existing, non-defined variable and empty variable are the
same from the from the from the bash perspective. So I'm assigning for instance to kind of proof of
concept. So I'm assigning a variable itself but it's empty and it's still going to be zero and
only after I'm saying some value over here it's going to be said that okay it has actually failed
so this directory this variable has been defined and it has some value. Be careful because in other
language if you would say that var is equal zero from the bash point of view the length of this
variable is non-zero it's at least one byte so that means that this minus z will give you false
and again it doesn't matter what you put over here it will be still considered only the length
of this variable so if you want to make sure that you are kind of follow the logic of this
operators then just just take this into account so you're working with the
not with the definition of the variable, but actually the content of the variable itself.
Saying that, let me go further and see how complicated this kind of expression could be.
So you have a number of the things. So I have demonstrated here already minus d. In the same
way, if you are checking the file, you can check minus f and say that does this file exist or not.
take a note on this because they're going to be the exercise
right on this then if you want to check this is it readable for you I express
here it's for you so it's not readable in general but it's readable by you so
you can post this -r and then what else so all these kind of comparisons
including integers and just normal lexic, so you can use them within this
double square brackets, but regarding the integers, let's say that we will come
back to this yet today, so when we will be considering the arithmetics, so I
will definitely say that please use for the integers some other, so you can see
within the loops subject there will be the arithmetic and there will be introduced the
other expression so just the normal round brackets over here and so that is way more powerful
and so coming back to the conditionals I would say that square brackets is mainly for the strings
even though you can put the integers over there and even though from the historical point of view
actually and for the sake of compatibility even those double square brackets they have
implemented all this equal not equal less than less or equal greater than and greater or equal
etc but again don't get confused so you can use them both but I would suggest that you
actually from now on you would start distinguish them and so these ones for the strings and then
the round ones for the integers. Again, a few examples. We can use the examples with the logical
AND and logical OR and then we will use negation and we will at some point may use also the grouping.
So you can have a list of here of working examples. It's up to you how you use them.
we use them, I mean those who are writing the scripts they are using quite often
and then
to demonstrate you that actually something may happen and be quite more
complex so I am going back to the tarit.sh and see that for instance if I would
like to implement and say that check that directory it's not only existing
but it's also not empty so what I'm saying here is that I need another one
condition so if actually can be nested so let me show you one the way to do
that so you can also do it like this if and then put another condition and say
that here I'm testing that it's not empty so how to do that you can use
known to you, command substitution, and you can say here ls -lA. So what ls -lA
gives you, it gives you a list of all the files and directories including the
hidden ones in the current directory. And if it happens that this directory
empty then ls -lA will return you empty list which from the
from the f and expression perspective that would mean that it's just the
falsing so what i'm saying here that okay let's put it like that
let's put it like that and let's see the logic so if it's if directory exists and if it's not empty
then we already do the setup for the archive and then we have to close this internal if condition
in the same way it's probably more readable but in the same way if you're already good enough
in programming with bash you can actually join those two conditions into one and using the
logical end you are saying pretty much the same thing but just within one line
like that it will work as well it's your choice i mean if you want to make readable if you have
some colleagues which are not really capable of reading this scripting syntax it probably
make sense to do it as a nested but if you do it for yourself and you are experienced enough then
that should go this way. Okay, you can test it out if you want to or you can just trust me that
this one will work. It's the how to use the complication of this operator and then
negation so negation would say that okay if you put the exclamation mark let's be
let's make it more noisy so -n would give you that directory variable
is defined its success but if I want to still negate it even a half -z so I
would put the exclamation mark over here this will work also at some point you
may want to use this exclamation mark, for instance,
will be, I don't know, in the same way if you put it
before the condition, then that means
from the conditional expression point of view.
So give me the value of that which is negated.
So if it succeeded, if this -d operator has succeeded,
then we put it that it has failed.
or
Okay, I think you've got the idea so sometimes you need this
So now we have this done
and I think
uh, I think
I should be ready now to go for the first
exercise
So my first exercise of this day, there will be conditionals and I will ask you to do next
so I am actually asking you to work with the data.it so if you think about it
where to get it you just go over here and you click it and you just download
it to your own directory for sake of playing with that but anyway so here
what I want you to try so first of all try to check
whether any argument is giving so even though it's a little bit pointless from
this programming point of view for this kind of script but
it's not pointless from the studying point of view so you will learn how to
check the number of the arguments I have it in the material or you can say that
if you remember this variable it's a system wide variable it's existing by
default when you run any kind of program any script in bash and it gives
you just exactly the number of the the number of the or the number of the given
arguments so basically if you say that it's if it's equal zero yeah
then you should already come out and decide what to happen
and before doing that
so i'm cleaning it up before doing that actually i wanted to demonstrate you
something which was
say that if you want to compact view of this test operator so what will happen
over here I mean the what will happen over here that if this exists you can
use you can use this logical and and logical operator on the command line and
because bash is mostly about command line and mostly about prompt so on the
prompt you will not probably using something like if etc even if you can if then and even if you can
do doing all these kind of things over here the most popular way to use the if to use these
conditional operators on the command line directly is to using them with the
bitwise operator so with the booleans and in my case if I'm checking that if it exists echo
okay let's see if it doesn't I'm using negation it does not exist so now you know now you can
use also this kind of technique if you want to make it compact but within the script I would
say if is correct way to do that so it's more it gives more readability but when you do it from
the command line you can simply do it and simplify it and simply do it like this so that's another
one hint for the conditionals so let's say and then the last one that i'm expecting you to check
that this archive which we're trying to make it does exist okay uh let's go and say that yes xx:45
it's something that we will come back to this and i will show you how to
how to actually this can could be implemented
okay several replies already there so let me let me demonstrate what actually you are supposed to be
doing so i copy my tarit to the
the tarit, let it be version one.
So I'm not using git here,
otherwise that I would just make the comment
that would keep adding,
but here just for the sake of clarity
so that we can have both versions and open up all of them.
So I'm now let's me make out of this original tarit
something which was requested to do.
So this dummy check for the command line argument.
So what I'm saying here is that I'm assigning the variable
to the dir and now what I need to,
I need to make a check that this directory is not,
is given to me.
So it's once again, minus that dir over here.
And what happens then?
if it's not correct so then we are archiving or let's say that we are putting minus n
and so we're checking if it actually exists does it actually exist is it existing so yes I can say
that the directory exists archiving it
Okay, in the other situation, if this guy is not there, then what I'm saying is that
I'm carving the current directory and then there was also a request to put the name of
that directory.
easiest would be to put the pwd and pwd so my current directory or if we want to have just the
name in case we can do the thing with the base name like this that should work for the
how do we call it, arguments check,
arguments check, and then the other one was to check whether the file does exist.
So what will happen over here? My point was that I don't really want to overwrite
already exist in archive and so I need somehow to check this I need somehow to
check the the archive itself and luckily we have this archive as a variable so
there is nothing else to do than just putting this minus F and see whether
this exists or not and so we can do this in exactly the same way the only
operator will be here -f which says that check please that this file exists
and now one hint for you so I always suggest that you put actually these
variables which you put into the test conditional test operator so put them
quoted. Why? Sometimes those variables may have some special characters, even the space is considered
to be special characters and so if you omit this kind of double quotes then what will happen that
archive will put on this line for instance a string which would have which will have a space
and it will be considered as a kind of additional variable or additional check or whatever
and most probably bash will just tell you about the syntax error. So this is why
just get started with the good practices and so use the double quotes within this
test construct so and then what I'm doing here that if archive if it exists I'm saying echo
archive
already exists
okay and then important thing before I actually close in the whole block I need to exit because
I don't want the whole script go down to that line so I'm saying here exit and I can put some
exit parameter like two and now if you run this within some script and you are getting this kind
of errors you already can get around with the exit code and say that okay this exit two is about
this existence of the archive and so that we don't overwrite this so let's see if it works
we need to check what we need to check tar i team shell so let's see first
the archive the current directory demo space okay that's correct demo space is there
so we assume that at least this part is working
and now what we need to check we need to check whether the directory is existing or not so
basically if we are trying to oh sorry now i did the wrong thing so let it exit let it create
recreate it and now i'm trying to do the same thing and trying to overwrite exactly the same
demo space dot blah blah blah so now let's see what will happen now it actually has checked that
this directory is already there this file this archive is already there and nothing has happened
so it has not been overwritten it's exactly what we were up for and so let me clean up after myself
once again and so that one is there. I will also add the right answers to the
to this node guy so that afterwards should be able to
to come back to them
okay they're there okay so on the show we should be good to go further
now we are back to the back to the conditionals but now i want to tell you about something
special which is called the matching operator so you have here a long text so but basically
imagine operator this is the functionality which will work only within the only within the
double square brackets so there are some historical notations also for the test operators like single
square brackets so but this will work only with this model one way and what it does it's supposed
to it can allow you to use the basically the in the most basic concept you will find whether the
part of the string that you are looking for it's a kind of search word is actually part of the
string which you are trying to match against and in the worst case you can go with the regular
expressions. Let's see what you can do. So there are a number of selected operators over here,
we call it operators, but actually from the regular expressions point of view it's a mini
language. I mean if you ever met this, if you ever tried this with Python for instance, or if you
were tried it with the grep so every single setup it has somewhat special syntax but most of the
things more or less are the same so the most of these operators most of these characters or most
of these special characters that you use inside the regular expressions more or less the same
I will not go deeply into this, so it's a subject for the book, it's a subject for the different
lecture. My only point here is that matching operators is existing and my point here is that
I will show you how you can use it within the bash with several examples. My first example would be,
for instance, let's say that I want to verify that the email which is given to me by somebody
so I go to my stream email is given to me by somebody is actually an email so
now I have a variable and now let me check it so what will happen I first I
need to create some kind of regular expression okay so let me put first these
guys round brackets down so that should be perfectly enough if there is
something before hat and then there is something after hat. So this is the very simplest way to
check whether this given one is the actual example. So let's say that I am satisfied with
this kind of verification, so I'm not checking the domain names, I'm not checking that the user
existence etc. That's already too complicated, it's not for the script. But then let's see what
will happen whether this will be executed correctly or not so in my case yes it succeeded
so the email was correct but then if i'm trying to something which is
not looking which is not looking like a email then let me try it once again now it's not succeeded
so that's the way to use this kind of regular expressions in the same way the easiest way
if for instance i still want to have this email in the previous format and i just want to check
whether this variable has for instance auto inside for me would be enough if i just put
the auto name so my string which I'm matching against will be compared with this auto and
this operator will try to find me every single entries of auto in the email
so now it says that okay correct it has been found and so you've got the idea
it's how to use this matching operator and let me show you one thing for instance you remember
where we're playing with the append with the how to make the path
how to make the additions to the path variable so let me go to the bin
functions and I will add another one function over here which we can use later we can make
it more generic and we can later make it to work with any variable but at this point let it be path
so my point is okay I can expand the path variable as many times as I want to
but what I don't want to happen if that for instance I want to add yet another path to the
bin directory but if it already exists there then we should skip it somehow so my point if I wouldn't
be using the matching operator I wouldn't be using for instance something like echo grep okay
Okay, that would work.
Let me check it out.
So for instance, if I know that my path is demo space bin,
yeah, path something like demo space bin.
Oh, I can't put it even in such a sophisticated way,
so I know it's home demo space bin.
bin. This is what I have added on the very first day. Okay, and now what I'm doing is that I want
to check that this demo space bin is part of my variable. Without the matching operator I would
use grep. So what I would do, I would echo
echo original path and I would say that please grep for me
that one that I have designed just recently. Okay and grep will tell me exactly this guy is there
this guy exists and you can see that actually we can even say that even if we get rid of the
uh output we can still get this
output the exit code so the exit code in our case was succeeded okay nice
but then how to do the same thing with the matching operator so let me do it the way
we do it with the functions so that would be as simple as that so i need only the path itself
then I need that
matching operator over here and then I need the actual string which I'm
comparing against. That's it. And the function will pretty much
work only with the bash functionality
so we don't need any external program like
grep or not even echo so we just do the like this so that's one of the demo how to use it already
right away and that's also the way to show you that actually there are some there are different
approaches how to solve it and you can find them also when you google differently for the all kind
of bash solutions so you will find these different approaches just just be aware that all of them
work and maybe the question of compatibility it's but also the question if if you want to
implement everything with a bash or if you wanna use these utilities which are around
and then we come back to one thing to my first example uh email let me do it in such a way that
I actually email is the one which is supposed to be correct but let me check my regular expression
which I have used for the email and remember at the very beginning there were the round brackets
in the regular expression round brackets would mean grouping so what that mean from the
from perspective when you start using the matching operator.
Matching operator will have such an array
which is called bash rematch.
So we don't know yet anything about arrays.
They are coming only on the study day number three,
so it's gonna be tomorrow.
But let me say that they are in the bash.
And so here is the first touch of this one.
So what will happen over here?
when we assign this to email and regular expressions and then if we go and check it
like this so what this matching operator will do for us it will find this one and this one
and actually it will be able to distinguish them and it put the them to the to the array
and so we will have number of elements in this array elements zero of this bash rematch it's
going to be the whole sentence and then element one is going to be the content of the first group
and the element two is going to be the content of the second group and vice versa i mean it
will be as many elements as many groups you have over here let me show you what i mean
so what I actually exactly want to do here is that I want to output the bash
so the easiest way to output the array is using this syntax so by now don't go deeply into this
just copy paste it when you will be playing with that so let's see what will happen and now you
will see that actually this has been done and those variables have been assigned and now you see that
I've got three different fields over here and I can use for instance if I want to use the
only the first one so I can say that okay give me not everything but only for instance the
name of the guy so that's going to be and then if I want only domain that's going to be like that
it's fantastic that it works actually so you definitely wouldn't expect this kind of from
the bash functionality and if you are familiar with the regular expressions so that's the
that's the basically that means that you're good very that you've got a very kind of
efficient tool in your hands
I wanted to mention also one thing with them if and else what this thing is is
that reminder to you when we are talking about condition which comes over here
when we are talking about condition which comes over here
this condition can be basically anything what can bring you true of else in this
the same way, like I'm using, for instance, test operator over here, in this
exactly the same way I can use I can use pink command or any other command and if
result of that command will bring me something then will be do if it's
succeeded. Right after this if it's not succeeded then it will be an Elsa. So
take away message that basically any condition, anything which will bring you
as a condition we will also we will use it later on for the for the for instance for the
for the arithmetic operators so we will also use if and arithmetic operators and you will
see that actually yes if can accept anything what you want so but here i think it's now time for the
exercise session and now we will take this conditional operator and play with
that. Now what I want from your side is that you will spend your next 15 minutes
building a regular expression. It's not easy, not at all. Please use the slides
over here and check the examples and check the examples that we have
used also from the online and then try it out and even if it looks like it's very simple it
may actually start bringing you the errors and it's maybe even painful because actually playing
with the regular expression it has never been easy it's the thing itself so it's a kind of
media language and understanding how that works
is the
integral. Okay, so now we will have joint break and exercise
so remember to stretch your legs or stretch something whatever you want to
and then we go back to the at 13.32 so let's say that 15 minutes plus 10
minutes break 13.32 and then the exercise is coming over here otherwise you can start doing already
this one so i'm talking about the start id that we keep developing with you
okay now the floor is yours i am muting myself
and if any question please don't hesitate to shoot them
Hopefully the break is over. If you can't hear me, then just let me know that you can hear me somehow.
It shut me on the notes or somewhere. So let's get back to this validation. So now
what was the problem? The problem was that you had to make some kind of regular expression,
which would take, which would make the validation of the directory path. So I know that for the
for the bash scripting it's usually not that this validation is not really that often.
Having some people they really don't really care about this, but as a former for instance
have been developing for the web quite a lot in some recent times so you can see that actually
there are everything what comes out from the from the outside somehow it could be the argument it
could be the giving the input on the interactively I would suggest that you definitely do check
because you never know which who will use the script where and how it will be used so whenever
something comes to the hand especially if you want to remove something if you want to rename
something if you want to move something then definitely makes sense to check that is it
actually the valid the valid path or the valid name or is it the valid thing at all so what we
are doing here is one we need to create a regular expression so that wasn't easy at all so i must
say that definitely if you have never played with the regular expression then
having this layer something like this would definitely go
with
would will take some time over here so my example over here
ready to go that i have just put to the data
so my regular expression is looking like
this one and let me explain what's happening over here
within the regular expression I'm saying that
within these brackets that what comes that should be either a digit
a letter a capital letter it could be a dot
it could be underscore it could be slash so
that's the kind of and these square brackets
in this case they will just indicate that that's the
any combination of these characters and then on top of that I'm saying that it should be plus
so it should be at least one or many and then I'm limiting it so I'm saying that hat at very beginning
that means that it should start with this and the dollar sign at very end that means that
it should end with this so there should be nothing else except those ones okay that should be good
enough already for checking out that that's the valid path and then how implement this so this
what you do usually if you do the implementation something like this so we can of course increment
it into some some of this checking right here but then we can do a separate also so for instance
let me do it actually let me just increment it into the incorporate it
into the existing one so here I'm checking that directory existing but
actually before the thing I have to check that directory is correct so this
can be taken off and then off
then so here is my consequence of checking list so I'm checking that
directory given to me is actually a valid directory path so second I'm
checking that the directory itself exists and third one I'm checking that
directory is not empty so that should go like this and the regular expression over there
so that was the that was the whole thing so let me let me copy paste it to you
over here and so next time you know how to use it where am i
on the arithmetics. So the next will be for us the, while I'm doing this I'm speaking also,
the next will be for us the arithmetics. Strictly speaking bash is not really,
can't be really proud of arithmetics. So when you are talking with the arithmetics
so like this yeah so let it be there for the sake of documentation so when we
are speaking about arithmetics in general we are speaking only about
integers so these are good for all kind of indexing it's good for making all
kind of counters but nothing else so if you are looking something to work with a
float point then you definitely should go for some specific math applications
or at least look for the libraries for the Python, PySQP and other, NumPy and others.
But with respect to this plus one plus one, one plus two, or 100
multiplied by something, so that should be good enough to do at least this one. If you want to
count the line numbers, if you want to count the character numbers, if you want to make the indexing
within the array so this bash is capable of doing and there is a special expression over here
these are round brackets round brackets like this and everything what happens within the round
brackets it's gonna be interpreted as the arithmetic expression so when i'm saying that
n plus m bash would expect that there is a variable called n and there is the variable called m
and i want to see the sum of those two variables okay and as comparing to the for instance this
square brackets double there is no need for the space over here and also as comparing to the
square brackets there is no need for the dollar sign you can put it it's not a syntax error
but it's not a syntax error either if you omit them so just remember everything what is later
over here it will be interpreted as a variable and then what will happen so let's say that i
want to assign n equal to and m equal i don't know five if i do it like this
you will see nothing. Why? Yes, the arithmetic action actually has been done,
it has been counted, but it has not been saved to any variable, or it has not been
printed to the output. So if you want to print the output of this action, so you
have to put the dollar sign and then do something, like for instance echo, and
and this way you get the output or if you want to assign another one variable
like I don't know variable p or variable sum summation so that's going to be also like this
then your echo s and you will see echo not ego it's going to be like that
and here is a number of selected operators what you can do so take a look at them and we will
start using them right away and one of the particular examples so you can do the incrementation
plus minus exponent and then multiplication truncating and so if you're dividing for instance
two numbers yeah so you will get the integer still so if you even think that okay and m is five and
n is two then i can divide them so i can still see that actually there's gonna be the integer
so they will be rounded to that or another direction so but you can also get the reminder
over here this is that much about logic about this arithmetics inside the bash so i don't
really think we still we need to tell way more because what we need to what we need to do is that
we need to be ready to go for the upcoming loops. But before that I would
like to use this section to introduce you something which is called read
command. So let me do it in this way like I have a prepared command in the
bin which is called read sh let me try it out with you so what i'm doing here i'm saying that please
read for me something which comes from the keyboard from you essentially into the variable e int1
and I'm also saying that my prompt before this int1 should be this one
okay and then i'm just using that variable to echo this this is that simple but that's
demonstration how to use it so it has nothing yet to do with the integer but but you will see shortly
that it is useful because we will start doing now the exercises soon
so what will happen over here give me an integer please so i give something like
hmm give me another integer okay still integer oh no so too early so you see something like that
in a sense read is nothing specific i mean if you go to the manual page and see the read it
has very few options so it has a time limit for instance you can say that there's something like
like -r, in order to avoid some special characters,
you can put the minus T and say that the time limit
for the waiting would be 10 seconds, or let it be even four.
And then if you can even say that you can hide
everything what's been typed, if you are kind of curious
and you want to request for some secrets.
So let's see what will happen if I do it like this.
give me an integer please so if I type there will be nothing and actually the timeout has been now
has been now gone and so nothing has happened so read again so that was your integer is like that
fine and then if I wait for four seconds it will just break me out and I'm done so
We're pretty much now ready, I think, to go for the actually next example.
Ah, I want to make one demo for you.
I have a demo called Gaussian.
There is a story behind that.
So the Gaussian, you know, this famous mathematician.
And he was a genius, and so at some point in his classroom,
when he was kind of quick enough to answer all the questions
the teacher was giving.
So the teacher told him that please count me
all the numbers, a summation of all the,
to give me a sum of all the numbers from one to 100.
And the teacher was quite surprised
that when the kind of 10 years old boy
was in a couple of seconds saying the right answer.
So the problem over here is that
Gaussian actually find out how to make the summation and his method was that he was taking the
1 and 99, 2 and 98, 3 and 97 etc and he have realized that actually there are 50 pairs that
would give you 100 and then there is 50 which is just in the middle and so you easily can count
that actually. Summing 1 to 100 will give you 5050. But that's just the history. But then actually
we will use it for the sake of trying the arithmetics within the bash. So what I'm doing here,
I'm starting to use the arithmetics right away in this script. So first I'm checking that actually
this variable which stands for the number of arguments so this is the special variable and
i think we were talking about this already earlier and here i was mentioned this already so that's a
number of selected variables and one of them is special one when you give this number of input
parameters. Okay, and so what I'm saying here if this is exactly one then we take the n from the
command line and if it's not the case if no argument is given or if more than one argument
is given or if not equal to one or whatever so what I'm saying here that please read this number
from the prompt and let's make it interactive and then when it's done we already do the actual
summation and you can see that actual summation happens within one line I'm printing and counting
it just like that so in my case using this Gaussian approach I just using this formula
so n and plus one divided by two and you can see that i can even use within this
double round brackets the round brackets themselves so this is made to put the priorities to grouping
so that this actually arithmetic action arithmetics will happen first and then after
that will happen the the rest so there will be multiplication and and division
this is to tell you to show you that actually something still works and so let me try the gauss
you can try it on your own as well if you just copy it from the web page so give a positive
number and let it be hundred and so so you are getting actually correct answer saying that a
gaussian boy was pretty genius yes at that time at his age
and the same way that if I put the first to the line so or let it be 101 whatever
so you can see that actually I'm still getting the correct answer so now what I was about to
demonstrate here along with the read command along with this check for the input parameters
for the number of input parameters. I'm also actually demonstrated you quite nice techniques,
so you can both check the input parameters, and if nothing has happened over there,
then you go and ask interactively. Okay, so that's the demo. Nicely looking, hopefully.
another one thing which I was thinking to tell you
actually I was just met it tomorrow because I was developing one script and
then realized that okay I never told the
course participants how to check the syntax there is this
-n with bash so if you want just to check the syntax but do not execute the
code so please make a note for yourself so
use the bash minus n so let me for instance
break it somehow yeah that's our own syntax and see what will happen with the binary somewhere
so you will get the error without actually executing the code which is just nice and you
even get the line number where the code has been where code is failing so you can already see
what exactly is happening over here on the line seven okay so just to make a note for yourself
bash minus n that will probably save your time somehow, somewhere, when you're doing these
things already for the production. Now it's next session, interactive session, so let's
try to look at the arithmetics. I don't think we really need that much time over here, but I still
give you 15 minutes or let it be 10 actually because
it's happening
so the only thing that's
again if you are quick enough with the read command and you should be probably quick enough
because you just use this read and do what it's supposed to do then if you are quick enough
a kind of advanced task for you would be check that given input is an integer
so it's the continuation of my previous exercise so if you want to play with the regular expression
then you can find out the way how to check that actually input which you get from the prompt
is what you're expecting okay now the time is yours and now let's say that we give it
10 minutes and then we continue at 14
in 0.1 I guess, yeah
yes and we probably need a second break so let's continue then at 14.10
or, no, let it be 10, or...
I'm muting myself, but yes,
you know where to ask the questions if you want,
if you have any.
Okay, coming back online.
So I think the simplest would be just if I will show you how I have done it, I will just
copy-paste it directly to the notes and they will be there.
the script to implement this kind of arithmetics is pretty much straightforward. I mean
from the programming point of view and the point was here just to find out how to
use the right syntax for the for the bash specifically. So what I'm doing here I'm
go through the asking for the read ones so if I am asking with the read command the two variables so
one is integer one another is an integer two so you can name it the way you want to it's just the
for the sake of convenience and then I do the comparison using the if else if and else statements
and inside of this I'm using the arithmetic expressions.
So here basically logic is pretty simple.
The more
kind of advanced it was to check that the number is actually a number
or the given input is actually a number. So what I've done here
is that I have prepared the regular expression and was comparing that is what I receive from
the user something which is contains all the digits or it could be also the negative one
just to make sure and be more complete on this one and so I'm using this one condition so this
would go somewhere right after the read and if it's okay then I will just continue to the rest
of the code or if it's not okay I would just make the exit in the previous examples that was already
there so these are two or two these last ones now let's get to the one another one real part I mean
taking if I count like conditionals like one essential part of any language then the loops
is another essential part of any language and bash has several implementations of for loop
it also has this while until loop and again remember that for loop in bash is something
specific it's not what you expect in the c style even if the c style is also there but since the
the bash has been initially a kind of scripting thing
for the administrators and for the advanced users.
So what it can do the best,
it can work with the files and the directories,
and you will see the example why this way,
and then it can also work directly
with the input parameters.
So what I think I will just jump directly
the four examples so my first example will be
go through the every single parameter on the line so if I
tell you that for instance if I'm creating some file
any file for example
yeah i'm starting it pretty much with the same way like you would start any other
any other bash file and then says for instance i want to go through the loop if i say for
some index variable in the list and here i am having a list list could be for instance item
item1, item2, etc.
And then I'm saying, please do that.
And then when it's do, when it's done, then just done.
For the sake of compactness, I'm usually putting the do as well here.
It's in the same way like with the if statement, so I put the then over there.
And here you do with the variable i, so basically it becomes item1, item2, etc.
by one but in case of bash you can simply omit this list one what will happen over here you
remember we're telling you that this dollar sign and the number sign is the number
of the arguments given from the command line and then those arguments are like
one, two, three, etc and there is another one variable which is called
dollar sign and hat, where do I have hat, it's here.
So which actually a list of all of those variables at once.
So these are the only three,
or these are the only the range of variables
which you're supposed to know
when you're working with the input parameters.
And what will happen actually here in this construct
that this for loop and bash by default
will simply go through all these,
through the variable, this one.
So it simply go through one, through two,
through three, et cetera.
And so every single item over here will be like this.
So we have ready-to-go script.
Let's try it.
So I say that we can even make it more
for the sake of clarity.
So let's say that this
and no we can't really say anything else so let it be like that so what's happening here so I have
so once again chmod +x and i'm not in the bin so i have to put the essential explicitly
path and let's see what will happen if no arguments then no output but if there is some argument
two, three, one, two, three, for instance. You see, I will get the arguments back. A, B, C, D. I will
get the arguments back in the same way if it's A, B, B, B. A, B, D, F, G, C, R, T, Y, D, Y, blah, blah, blah.
So I will get these arguments back to my line. So that's already something. So now you've got
the proof that actually, by default,
4 will go through all these items
and will do something which you think is reasonable.
So I have, I think I have one example forsh.sh.
So what am I doing here?
I'm pretending I'm somewhere in the directory
where there are lots of shell files.
And so, my next step will be actually to work with those files.
You saw in the previous step that if I omit complete this part in and list, then it gonna
be the input arguments given to the file, given to the script which is running currently.
But in other case, if you give the argument, if you give null the argument, or actually
even if you give the argument, but then if you put the list explicitly, then what will
happen over here?
Bash will consider that these are the file names.
So if you want to expand, for instance, and take this with the star and the wildcard and
see that actually all the names, all the files with the extension .sh shell will be listed
over here.
So if they are not found, you will get a message that nothing has been found.
But if they are found, they will be proceeded one by one.
So what will happen next?
It will pick up the first file with the extension .sh and will go through it.
this small script does nothing except that it's just the grip out the the empty lines like that
and then it what will does further so it will just uh grip also the shebangs so basically
what i'm trying to grab out of this sh files it's only the comments so let's see what will happen
if I go to bin, well if I will try it from here, I will get the error message
and now that was
interesting
so if I go to the bin
yeah so actually I had one sh file so this is why I didn't get the error message so that was the
just the recently created example but if I go to the bin and if I will run exactly the same file
so you can see that actually my list of shell files is already about a dozen of them
so you can see that I've got all the comments except the shebangs and then the something
which has real comments but all this stuff which comes from there just one by one
so that was a proof for you that yes by default
bash will recognize this kind of list as a list of files. It doesn't mean that their for loop
will end like here, like here, like this, like here, so you can still work with the items
and put the list to this for loop in any way. So anything that can produce a list
can be used with this notation.
So quite often you can use, for instance, bind command.
So you will find the files or directories
and then you will do with them something.
Quite often you can also use something
like brace expansions.
I never mentioned this, but there is a brace expansion.
So for instance, if I want a list from one to 10,
yeah, what will happen over here?
so bash will automatically generate me a list from one to 10.
If I want a list from A to zeta node like this,
so bash will automatically generate the list of zeta.
So if I want to make something with this list,
for instance, four items in the list,
and then do, you can see that actually I can type also
the four from the command line,
and it's just normal techniques,
people do this do and then I will do something nothing specific so I still just echo them
and I can say that even for instance
the item is and then I put down so just remember if you put everything in one line just remember
this command delimiters, so you need the semicolon at the very end of every command,
but at the end of every command. So here you see that I have listed every single element
separately. If you want to do something else with those elements, just do it, it's up to you.
So in the same way this list can be a, a, d, d, r, d, y, and blah, blah, blah. So everything what you
want to be on the list or it happened to be on the list, it's gonna be on the list and you can
proceed with that. So that's the easiest part of this for loop. Then, as I promised you, there was
another one approach to the for loops and this is called the C-style approach. C-style is known to
you, so I'm pretty sure that if you've been working with the other languages, you know what this
stands for so this one is not that often actually used in bash it's there and actually i'm pretty
much sure that even the advanced users maybe have never used that or have never heard about this
system loop in bash but i mean if you at some point need this then just feel free to use it
the usage is pretty simple so there is the starting point first of all it's known to you
arithmetic expression, round brackets. Then you start with the 1. When you put the condition when
1 till 1 is less or equal n, and you have to define the n or you have to say it explicitly over here,
and then you do the normal incrementation. And actually this is what will happen if you do the
normal math and the c-style loop has appeared also as part of bash when this double round
brackets notation has appeared in the bash so we i don't think i want to tell you
any more on this i would rather prefer that you go to do the
to do the
exercises. Yeah, one node. So, for just a normal command.
In a sense, this one, this construct is nothing else, not just a command.
Yeah? And so, I want to do everything what I want. If I want to redirect
the output of for loop, I do it like that. So, if I want to
redirect to a file, file for loop be there like that
it's gonna be there so now I can take a look like output of my for loop has
been redirected over there. In the same way if I want to send it
as a pipe to another command then we can do as well this way
in the same way you can work with the what I mean if you want to put back something to the loop
so that's going to be like that so pretty much normal command operators that can be used for
any other command can be also applied to the for loops and then the other loops but now let's
Let's get back to the for loop and now let me print for you the next exercise.
So what I'm expecting from you right now is that you do a number of dummy files, a number
of dummy files and then actually rename them.
So the issue here is more or less copy-pasted from one of the examples in the material,
so you can find it out somewhere here, I guess, yes.
So I've done this for the conversion and actually there is the move as well.
So what I want you to start running is that I want to create those files and then implement
the script that will go through all these files one by one and make a renaming.
So the original name should remain the same.
What only needs to be done that this extension, which is originally in the capitals, should
become the small ones.
should be quite simple so but still I don't think we need actually even 15
minutes just copy paste the example and play with that I think even the 10
minutes should be pretty much good stuff for that and then we will be well on
time so let's say that we are back to the stuff 14:38
yeah coming back already to the
so that what we've been doing I guess it was rather quite simple or should be I expect that
that should be already quite simple for you. So let me put the right answer
and a little bit of explanation. So what has happened here?
You see that I'm from the command line, I'm just running touch, so I'm creating the number of files.
So from the bash perspective, this brace condition, brace expression
will just give me files from 1 to 5, try it on the all, and then the bash script itself. So,
what I'm saying here is that go through all the files with the extension with the capital TXT,
assign it to the f, and do it one at a time. So, we move all the variables, every single file name,
and here we are using already the bash syntax for the variables, where I can easily remove
one extension with another one. Done. You can use it anytime, anywhere, from command line,
or making scripts, etc. Very useful when we are working, for instance, with the jpeg files,
and very useful when you are working with the, well, especially with the graphics. I found that
when I'm using this display or convert commands, when I can just go through all the
all the directories, all of those files, and do all of them at once, easily.
Okay, so my next stop would be the while loop.
It's interesting. I mean, it's while, it's unpeel,
and the same thing that it's while the condition is
returning zero status so while it's succeeded then we use while and this loop will continue
and until is the same way but when the condition returns non-zero status so basically when it fails
and one of the example for instance let me try the gauss but I say gauss.realone.sh
in a sense that I'm just making for you pretty much the same situation like we did with the
original gauss simulation but except we don't really use the numbers we don't really use the
formula by gauss but we are using the straightforward direct summation so what
I'm doing here is that I'm expecting the n variable from the command line so I'm saying
that my original one will be one so beginning and so I'm going through the loop with the arithmetics
so to you my variable my counter I mean is less than the the this one number given to me
from the prompt do the summation so here this formula says that s is actually well we can assign
s equal zero and so we can say that from very beginning we just start the summation every
single iteration of this loop what I'm doing is that I'm adding this i to the s and then I
do the incrementation and this way I am getting from n from 1 to n so that should be very simple
the only thing that I have done something new here you can see that actually assigning the
variables can be done within one line and even with no telemeters from the syntax
point of view it's completely fine so let's see what's going on
change mode plus X it's in the bin so it's there and I want to see the 100
okay I want to see something like 1 million and now let's see that how much
time it takes in Linux there is this utility called time which can tell you
what's the execution time of the command.
So you can see that if we go down to the million
or something, it's already 10 millions.
It will already quite take a lot of time.
I mean, well, I can't really wait for that.
So let it be just 1 million.
I'm saying you here that actually different approaches
and let me run exactly the same,
you remember where we were using the formula by Gaussian and it's way faster. What's the
so what's the takeaway message from here that actually the algorithm that you are using
really matters so the exactly the answer is exactly the same it's correct but then the
execution time is way more different. So, one other thing that can be done with the while,
and this is where the while is used quite often, here you see, it's when you're working with the
files. So, what usually is being done, you send the file to the standard input of the while loop,
and then it comes the read command in action and with the read you can do lots
of things I mean you can read it from the prompt as one integer as one single
variable but you can also do the read the whole line or even make the line
division so read is quite powerful and when you start working with the files
and when you start implementing some kind of real programming stuff with the while
you will realize it pretty much. So what else I'm introducing here in this script
it's the IFS. IFS is nothing more than just the default telemeter. It's installed
it's used everywhere so by default it's just the backslash n so which means
let me see can I even see it somehow yeah that means that in my case it's
just the new line but you can redefine it and redefinition of this one will
give you actually lots of abilities so let me see that I have
prepared the file for you which is quite real these are the students okay so let
me see what's there. That's the list of students I picked up just for a start
.fi and so that's the list of students from 2018 per university so you see the
number of universities and number of students male and female students so if
I want to for instance do something with every single line but not only with
every single line I can I want also to do something with every single field
separately. So, what I do in this case? I know that separator over here, semicolon,
it's the standard syntax of CSV files. In your case, that could be something else,
but here I'm using it just as an example. So, I'm redefining this
variable and say here that actually my telemeter is going to be the semicolon. And
And what happens over here, if I don't skip this backslash,
then syntax would be broken
and will be interpreted by bash at the end of the line.
And so that's gonna be the error.
So this is why I have to use this backslash
and this works as a quote.
In the same way, you can put, of course,
the quotes over there, but in most examples,
you will see this backslash and then the quote.
So I'm just backslashing, but actually the character
when it comes to the IFS, IFS would be this semicolon.
And now it comes the turn of the read command.
And the read command, what it does?
Saying that this one is telemeter,
it grabs every single line
and divide them one by one according to this telemeter.
And so we say here that this F1,
going to be the field one so in this case it's going to be this one actually this one
including the quotes so the whole field the f2 is going to be this one then f3 is going to be
this one f4 is going to be because no f5 here f4 is going to be the rest of this file
so whatever comes after f3 will be the f4 so that means that you have to know the format
of your file and if you want to work with the format of your file then be specific and be
precise actually check well in advance that all these fields are marked in the order and all
these fields are actually the way you want and then after all you can use those variables separately
one by one and you can skip some of them you can use some of them for the sake of
summation etc so here i'm just printing them out and so one more touch here so please welcome the
printf command so the printf command is nothing else than the c style printf
So if you know how to program in the... it's in Python in the same way except that in Python you
have to put it in the brackets. But C style is working like this. So you are defining the
format of the outputted variable and then you define another one format, I mean some text
then format of that variable,
another text and format of that variable, et cetera.
And then basically you just make the formatted string
the way exactly you want.
It's really powerful.
I would say that most of the people all the time
are using this echo, which is completely for okay.
And it does the job for you probably nine times of 10,
but sometimes you want to make it
real nicely formatted output.
so I go to the bin file and I was thinking that I still have some wild example to show you
so this wild was actually from here except that I have added this f5 and so let's see what will
happen so I'm expecting the file from the command line this says you this $1 and then that will be
submitted over here and given to the student input. So let's see that this students
students file is here. So what I'm saying that please use while shell in my case and then
then this one students and let's see what has happened so you see that I have
actually got the fields and but also there came some stuff which was
originally in the file but I don't really wanted this because these are the
These are the just normal command for the CSV file, and these are the empty line, and these are the header.
And so there are several ways to get rid of them.
And now you will have 10 minutes to actually try to do that.
Well, I will stay here longer, but we have official 10 minutes of the left of the exercise.
And so my exercise for you, the last one for this day, will be pick up my file while.sh.
and use it so that to count the total number of students.
So the total number of students, if you can see,
that's the field number three.
So basically what I want you, I want you to two steps.
Get rid of this one, empty line and the header
somehow the way you want.
I have introduced several approaches over here on the line.
and then grab this one and make the summation so now basically you already have the gauss you have
the while sh so you know more or less where to grab this piece of programming and get them together
and so let's say that the next one is for the 10 maybe 15 minutes but i will stay here for a
a bit longer so if you are still curious and still want to continue so i'll be here
to give the answer otherwise i will just put the output the right answer just in 15 minutes
online and so you will see the result okay the floor is yours and let's say
we are running a little bit late but we will be but let's say xx:07 that's the end of this exercise
and basically the end of the whole day and then we will continue tomorrow at the same time
Okay the final remark to anyone who has yet stand so if any question please ask but here
I'm going to put the answers for the last exercise and otherwise I'll see you hopefully tomorrow
so if you need an explanation here you go
So, what I've done, I've used this while script that I have already explained.
The only thing that I've done, that I have got rid of the thing which I didn't like.
So basically, I've checked that if the field 1 is not looking like this, so I was expecting
that there are only numbers and only the quotes, double quote, what, what, what could be there.
everything else I was just making summation actually this is not correct so that should
be in the field number three okay not five and then when it's done I have just print it out
I have also introduced here the another approach using the process substitution but actually just
remember that I have never told you about this so you can just keep it or I keep it over here
for those who are you as advanced but actually it's yet another way to do the the same thing
okay otherwise thank you for participating today if you have any feedback please leave it
back there and then otherwise tomorrow at 12 o'clock we will continue with the
how to work with the inputs how to work with the
traps then I probably will have chance to tell you about the arrays and how to put the here
documents. But anyways, see you tomorrow.