CodeRefinery.org
you
Test one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17,
Test one, two. Can anyone hear us? Yes. Okay. Good. So, welcome, everyone. We're in the
the 10 minutes of icebreaker time, so we're just here to chat while we're getting ready.
So my name is [name]. I'm here to, well, I'm one of the instructors and organizers
of the course. And with me here, would you all like to introduce yourselves? So [name]
is next on my screen.
Did [name]'s internet.
Oh, there.
Hello.
Sorry, I was just switching to a wired connection.
Good idea.
So hello, I'm [name].
I'm also one of the instructors
and a research software engineer at Aalto University.
Hi, I'm [name]. I'm an application expert at UPPMAX, Uppsala University in Sweden,
and I will also be teaching during this workshop. Hi, everyone.
Okay, so what I'm screen-sharing here is what we call the notes.
So, right here.
You can't see the cursor.
So, this is only for registered participants.
So if you would, if you're watching and you're not registered, if you register, I think you'll get an auto-reply that has this information here.
So how does it work? So at the top it has all the important links, and down below we see, well it's like Google Docs, so it's a collaborative writing thing.
So, I think the microphones might be wrong here.
[name] or [name], can you say something?
Hello, one, two, three.
One, two.
Okay. It seems... Oh, wait.
Okay, now I think it's better. Yeah. I know what the problem was. If there was an echo,
that was me.
So there's a question in Twitch chat which is asking, is this recorded? So the answer
is yes. So Twitch has the videos available immediately. And on YouTube, by the same night,
it should already be there.
And we can talk about the video processing later.
But OK, so back to the notes that we're talking about.
So if you go to the top, you can switch to an edit mode,
and then back to view mode.
You can even do the split mode.
But we used this like a chat.
So any time you would be asking something in a chat,
instead come here and write it somewhere. So you see at the bottom there's a Q&A part,
so someone could demonstrate writing the question. Let's practice writing the question.
Is this recorded?
And then we have a whole bunch of people who are also course instructors, and we're watching and
and answering it in real time.
So it's like a synchronous parallel chat Q&A kind
of thing.
So with this, we can have so many different questions
and answers at the same time and actually keep track of it.
And then we can archive it later.
But for now, we have icebreakers.
So if you scroll up, you see some questions
from registrations and so on, but then down here
to icebreaker questions.
So everyone that's registered, please take this, open it,
and scroll down to this point, and write down where
or write down the answers to the questions.
And let's see.
So you can also answer plus one for anything
that you're agreeing with.
And this is also a common thing.
So if you see something that you'd especially like answered
or you agree with, you can plus one it.
So where's everyone?
Where are we from?
So right now, I'm from a small office
at Aalto University in Finland.
And I guess [name] is teaching from home today?
Yeah, from somewhere in Espoo, Finland.
Yeah, and I'm in my office in Uppsala.
Yeah.
Oh, OK.
So we see a big variety of people from mostly European
countries, but not only.
So that's good.
We're glad that people can join us from all over.
And how much do people use Python?
Fair amount, quite a bit.
How much have the instructors used Python?
So, I don't know, what was your intro to Python and how long have you been using it?
I don't remember.
Which is, I guess, for a long time.
Yeah.
So, at least six, seven years ago.
So, I don't remember the first thing I did with Python.
But yeah, I do most things with Python these days.
Okay.
And before Python, what did you use?
C, C++ mostly, so I was doing very different kinds of things, so those were appropriate
languages for what I was doing, yeah.
And [name]?
Yeah, I had started with C, some C++ and Fortran, and it's mostly during the, I don't know,
maybe five years, past five years
that I've been using Python.
OK, yeah.
And as for me, I remember, so at first, I
was doing some stuff in C. And I had this friend saying
I needed to learn Python some.
But I didn't for a while until I did.
And well, I've been using it as my main language.
ever since.
So yeah.
And let's see.
So our audience here, how much have we used Python?
Yeah.
So I'd say this whole course, it's
designed for people that know a little bit about Python,
like the basic programming, but not the details
of using it for science.
And we're especially going into these libraries.
But if you're more advanced than that,
you'll probably still learn some tricks,
although the first few days may be a bit slow.
Just come back for the later days.
And if you haven't done any Python at all,
well, we're not covering that.
But by watching, you'll probably learn about, well,
learn some good things to help when you do start using Python.
OK, using Jupyter before, almost nothing.
So Jupyter is something that we talk a little bit more about.
And I believe, who's the first instructors here
for the Jupyter part?
It's me and [name].
OK, yeah, so Jarna and [name] will talk about that.
Oh, these JupyterLab extensions.
So maybe I should give some background on why we ask this question.
So some of our participants are working on hearing what those are, but we won't really
have time during the course.
And it's also great to hear from you all.
But if you do not know what those are, don't worry.
Yeah.
Okay.
So it's time to start the main part.
I saw a comment in chat that our audio might not be balanced.
So should we do our standard test first?
So the order is me, [name], [name].
We say 1, 1, 1, 2, 2, 2.
1.
2.
OK, how's our audio balance?
So, I guess I'm a little bit lower than [name].
I'm slightly louder.
I can handle that.
I can slightly increase my volume.
Okay.
I don't know how slightly.
Maybe slightly.
Okay.
Okay, well, people say audio is okay.
Let's go on. So okay,
I will go to an introduction.
So as another example of the notes here,
you see when we go to a part at the bottom,
we will add introduction,
and then someone will add
the link to where we're talking about now,
and then someone will start adding more places for questions here.
With that being said, I will try to go to
my screen share and hope that this works.
It's trying to work, but it's blank.
So zoom.
Oh, OK.
So here we go.
So this is the course web page.
This is the course web page.
And if you scroll down, you find the schedule.
And right now, here we are at intro.
So I open that.
So hi, welcome to Python for Scientific Computing.
So we've already introduced ourselves
in the little icebreaker session.
So let's go right past that.
Maybe we can talk about our organization some.
So [name] and I work at Aalto University in Finland.
And [name], who, what, where do you work right now?
I'm working at Uppsala University in Sweden.
Yes.
And as you may have noticed from the webpage,
there's a lot of different partners here.
So we have instructors from Finland, Norway, and Sweden,
at least.
And people all around have been advertising the course.
So the basic course contents.
So day one starts off with some basic tools.
So if you've used Python for science a little bit,
you probably know these.
But we have to cover them to make
sure everyone's on the same page and has a good foundation.
On day two, it's still fairly basic,
but we start going to more interesting things,
such as the visualization and data formats.
And then days three and four gets
to even more specialized tools, which,
unless you've done a lot of stuff,
this is probably still new to you.
And we can adjust the schedule as needed.
So what you see on the website might be adjusted some.
Also, on the last day, we have this panel discussion.
And in the panel discussion,
we have all the instructors together
and you can ask us any questions.
And that's usually a lot of fun.
Okay, so how to attend.
So obviously you figured out this is a live stream.
So you're watching on Twitch.
You're free to share the link
to anyone you may want in the world.
That's completely fine and intended.
But there can be different pathways beyond that.
So some people will pay close attention,
do all the exercises, try to learn everything.
Other people may watch,
you may follow along with some of the examples and solutions,
but you might be a little bit less active.
Some people might be watching passively,
seeing what's there, and then come back
later whenever it becomes more relevant to you.
These are all OK ways of attending.
And we support them all.
Practicalities.
So live streaming is different.
So whenever we would do these workshops in person,
we might have a few tens of people there.
Right now, according to my Twitch description,
there's 209 people following us.
And there are more than 400 people registered.
So how does this work?
So we're like a TV production, something like that.
Anyone can watch.
There's pauses for exercises, like considerate,
like commercial breaks or something like that.
And we will say, OK, now it's time for an exercise.
We mute the stream.
Us instructors come and plan what
to do next in the background.
And then you have time to work on things.
We keep watching the notes and let's see.
So we watch the notes.
answer questions there during the exercises and we come back and based on what the questions were
and what people are interested in, we can go over the exercises and the solutions or go straight on.
In some places there may be other in-person or online meetings where people are working together.
For example, some people might be
with their friends in a conference room.
You're watching together, and during the breaks
you're working there.
This is also completely fine, and actually we'd recommend it.
So some years we've organized these Zoom sessions ourselves,
but this time it's all on our partners to organize those.
Within the workshop, we have different parts.
So we have the part where we're talking, the live stream.
we have type along where we're typing and you can try to type along with us. There's exercises.
So this is where you do your own thing. And then we have breaks. So at least 10 minutes per hour,
sometime between the 50 and the 10 of the hour. Chat and communication. So some of us are
watching the Twitch chat, but it's not where you recommend the questions go because we can't follow
it. Instead, we recommend that you ask an answer in the notes document, which you get if you
register. It's the benefit for registering. So like this, so this is from a different course,
but you see there's sections, there's things, people ask questions in bullet points, and answer
in other bullet points. And we have people that are always watching this, so you'll usually get
an answer very quickly. Always write at the very bottom because that's the only part we're
actively monitoring. Every so often we copy all the old questions away and put them in an archive
notes document and that's findable from the top. You can also use this to figure out where we are
are in the lesson.
We update the section, stuff like that.
Yeah, here's the way you switch between view and edit modes
and so on.
Yeah.
So one thing or two things to be aware of.
So there's going to be a lot of stuff written here,
so don't get overloaded.
So the point is that you can come back and follow this later.
So during the course, I'd recommend if you're bored,
look at it.
you're actively focusing on what we're saying, focus on that and leave the notes alone. And also,
please never include any identifiers or names or things in the notes because it's archived and
anyone may see it. So from the course website, you can find these forever. They're not going away.
So if you haven't done it yet, please open the notes and answer the icebreaker there.
there. We've already been doing that some, but now really do it.
Okay, screen arrangement. So you may notice we're broadcasting in this weird little vertical
arrangement. There's a very specific reason for this. So you can arrange the screen like
this, where Twitch with the vertical arrangement is taking half, and the other half is for
you. So you can have the lesson and notes in the web browser, your workspace where you're
doing work. I guess in this case, your workspace might be a Jupyter, JupyterLab or something
like that. Whatever the case. And yes. And we found this works pretty well, even for
small screens. Okay. I've already talked a little bit about this, but just to emphasize.
So we recommend first you focus on the screen sharing lecture when we're talking.
And that's your first priority.
Then is your own type of longer exercises.
And then only after that, you focus on the notes, your own exercise group if you have
one, and the lesson webpage.
And we have plenty of breaks where you can follow up and catch up later.
I mean, everything we say is written down somewhere,
so you're not really losing information.
This year, we don't have the Zoom,
but we will explicitly tell you when you go to exercises,
and when you come back to the main lecture.
If you're trying to work like that,
you don't have any worries.
What can go wrong, or should I say will go wrong?
Some of these variation will always be,
will happen in every one of our courses.
So for some people, the lessons are too simple.
So it's OK.
The later lessons will become interesting.
You're in your home or office or wherever,
so just do something else and listen passively.
The lessons are too advanced.
Well, you can keep watching passively
and learn and come back later.
All our material is open and will stay open forever.
However, if the instructors make a mistake, well, actually, that's by design.
So you'll learn by seeing when things don't work and how we debug it.
If the nodes stop responding.
So if we have 200 people editing this document at the same time, it might get a little bit
slow.
So in that case, people will wait a little bit and hopefully it will pass.
also keep trying to keep it short to avoid this by moving to the archive notes. And you can find
that link at the top. If the stream dies. So if the computer I'm on, well, if one of them dies,
then all the broadcasting gets lost. And in that case, well, you'll get a message from Twitch.
So just wait around some, I'll restart everything, and we'll get back as soon as we can.
It's happened only very rarely, but be aware.
Internet dies. Actually, during one of our courses,
the Fastly CDN had a problem,
and then people couldn't rejoin the stream,
and that was lots of fun.
But in that case, just wait around and we'll be back eventually.
Oh wait, this isn't a problem.
So if I was at home,
which hopefully I will be,
my cat might come and visit us,
and that's always one of the joys of the workshop.
So, hang around and maybe you get to see us get distracted that way.
Okay, videos.
So yes, it is recorded.
Twitch saves them for seven days directly there, the raw video, and usually on YouTube
by the same night, we have them processed and released.
If you want to follow this process or help us, please get in touch.
Okay.
It should be respectful and helpful to everyone.
So here's four main pieces of advice, and you probably heard more later.
But be aware, everyone here is at different levels, and that's just expected.
So people focus on different things.
Passive learning is okay, so be kind to each other.
Everyone is both a teacher and a learner, even us.
So I think all of us, when preparing for this course, we've learned a few new things about
the different stuff we're teaching.
As a learner yourself,
you're a teacher to other people you're interacting with.
Yes, keep this in mind.
Take the time to check it.
Ask the other people you're with,
and we'll be asking you, how's it going?
Are you able to follow?
Do you need us to go faster or slower?
Then finally, when something isn't right,
let us know immediately.
So the classic case here is that the sound is too low,
or you can't see the screen, or I've
forgotten to adjust the broadcast
to include what's needed.
Write in the notes or Twitch chat or somewhere immediately,
and we'll see, even if you think it's
only a minor inconvenience, like our audio is imbalanced.
OK, final notes.
So we have information on credits on the web page.
You can read it there as much as you want.
You can keep in touch with us these ways.
We're always happy to have new people taking part,
especially if you would like to co-teach or become
a partner in this workshop later.
So basically advertise and run own workshop sessions.
This date is not out of date, but we
have other workshops which are going on.
We recommend you sign up for the Code Refinery newsletter
to get those announcements.
And Code Refinery, that newsletter
is findable from here.
OK, that's all.
I'm not too over time.
So I will switch back to the notes
to see if there's any questions.
These are all being answered here.
So yes, whoever is sharing screen next, please grab it and we can get going.
Okay, that would be me.
I had a couple of times when the internet connection somehow wasn't great and your voice broke.
So I hope it doesn't happen again. I closed Twitch stream and all of that.
Okay.
So, yeah, pay attention to what's happening instead of me, which, you know, and I will
concentrate on what I'm sharing.
Okay.
So, so the first lesson is Jupyter.
And I guess one main reason, one big reason to talk about Jupyter is that we will use
it a lot.
It's a convenient way of teaching and showing things.
[name], do you want to say anything about why Jupyter is good to learn before we start?
I think it's great at the very beginning when you are starting to write your Python
scripts.
It's easier to, it's more readable.
I find it easier to debug as well, but I would say, I mean, if you're used to IPython or
just running it from the command line, that is great as well.
So it's really a matter of preference.
If you are used to Python and you have a favorite way of using it, then just go ahead and use
that instead.
So getting started with Jupyter.
So let's just show one way of opening it.
is how I will use it.
And just to note, so in the installation
instructions that you hopefully did take a look at
before the course, if you didn't just ask questions, but
if you did, there is also instructions for how to open Jupyter for
whatever method of installing it you chose.
So, I will activate a conda environment in my terminal.
And while [name] is doing this, I will mention that you can also open it from the Anaconda
navigator. So, if you prefer that, that's perfectly okay. And if you're using Anaconda
and did not create a special environment, then you don't need to activate anything. You just run
on this command, jupyter lab.
And this opens a new browser window or a new tab in the browser.
And there's a lot of stuff here.
That's probably not the most useful information at this point.
So oh, I'm running it in my main folder.
Is there a way of easily going to another folder here, or should I just restart?
Maybe I'll just go to Python for SciComp.
Okay, that works.
Also, there is a file browser here.
You can clearly go to into folders, I will use it to delete my previous version of this
session.
Okay, so now I have no files in the folder.
And if you have nothing open, it will automatically open this launcher, which will show you what
kinds of programming languages you can use in Jupyter, basically.
So this is a Python 3 kernel, and it's the only one I have.
So I can open a Python 3 notebook here.
If you don't see this, you can open this view by pressing this plus button here.
Okay. So, I will open a new one and immediately I will rename it. So, right-clicking here
and rename. I will call it demo.
Yeah. That's always a good practice. Although I have a lot of untitled documents as well.
Yeah. So, it will automatically – oh, it's showing like it didn't save it. Okay. Well,
I mean that blue dot – that dot in my mind means it didn't save it, but maybe it's because
it's empty. Okay so we have this notebook and what we can do here we can write Python code and run it
and it will show the output immediately or we can use markdown to write a narrative so you can
essentially you can make this a document where you write some description and then you write the code
code, and then you write some more description and then some more code and so on.
So that makes it nicer for sharing your code or sharing your workflow with other people.
They can immediately see what you've done and see the code actually in the document.
So it says code here.
It refers to this one, well, they could have multiple cells here.
It's a plus button, so now you have multiple cells.
So this code refers to this particular cell that I have selected.
I will change it into Markdown.
Markdown is the language that we use in the collaborative document, in the notes.
So it should look relatively straightforward.
If it doesn't, that's fine.
The point is not to learn Markdown, but you can do formatting in addition to text with
Markdown.
this one hash means title this is like the biggest title available so this is a title
and make sure that it's the same markdown that we are using for the notes document yeah and you
don't have to be great at it to to use it i mean i think you can just learn a few syntaxes and
that's okay so this is some text i'll just write that and maybe i'll do like we do the questions
so a bullet point.
So it actually does some, just like the notes, it does some
syntax highlighting here so that you see there's a title and the bullets
they're different. But now if I press play here it will
actually run this markdown code which means
generate a formatted text area here.
Okay, now I can also do Python code. So this is just markdown, code, or raw text. Code in this
case means Python code because this was a Python notebook. So let's just do a simple one, one plus
one. Run that. And if you install a different kernel, let's say you work with Julia instead,
then the kernel is going to interpret what they said that you are marking as code will
be interpreted by the kernel that you have chosen. Yeah, actually I will steal this
notes from here for a while. Okay, so what else should we try? So just a quick intro to Python,
I suppose. So we can do a for loop and if we do for loop for starting from the value of i
starts from 0 and goes up to 2, we use the range function and actually write the number 3. So it's
0, 1, 2. That's three different numbers. So that's kind of the logic. And let's just print
the number and run this cell. So I should print the numbers 0, 1, and 2.
Or you can do sum of range from 0 to 5.
So now I'm not using print, but it will still print the last thing that happens, the output
of the last line.
So just like here in 1 plus 1 it printed 2, it prints 10 here.
Okay, so this is essentially most of Jupyter.
Let's quickly also show a magic function.
So there are a few commands that don't exist in Python, but are very useful in Jupyter.
And they start with a percentage.
So we can print the directory we are at.
So this stands for print working directory.
And if you use a Unix terminal in Linux or in Mac OS, this will be a familiar command.
So this is where we are right now in my file system.
But not all Unix commands exist here.
So there's another command called bash, which will run.
So bash is essentially a terminal.
So you can run any terminal command here
to host name, for example.
So this will print the name of my computer,
which is some string of numbers and characters.
But I guess the thing I want to demonstrate
is that even though this doesn't exist as a magic command,
so this is what an error looks like,
it does exist inside this bash command.
Also, everything now in this cell is this magic command
because it starts with two percentage signs.
So that changes how the cell works in general.
Yeah, exactly. So for one line, it's one percentage for the whole cell, you should use two percentages
followed by the magic. And maybe I could add that, I mean, using this magic commands is
a great way of integrating Bash and running other programs that you have compiled within
your Jupyter notebook. So you could integrate, for example, R or C or Fortran and run it
from the cell. But you just need to make sure that you do have the correct environment when
you're trying to do that. But yeah. One command which I think is very nice as well is the ls
magic one. If you could show it. And that will print all the magic commands that are available.
Oh, is it just one word?
ls magic one word. It's always one word for the command. And then you may have options
following. And then if you, yes, expand, then you can see everything that is available as
line magic or cell magic. I think that line magic is with one percentage sign and cell magic is for
two. Exactly. Yeah. And this may not be so instructive, but you could use, for example,
magic or quick breath one word to know more about them or you can just Google for them
or check in there. Yes, exactly. In the documentation. So that's that's okay. It's like find it quite
but very long cheat sheet. But was there a magic command called pip? Let's see. So I
I mean, sometimes it is very useful to be able to also install packages from, so yeah,
there is.
There is.
And there is Conda as well, as a magical.
Okay.
Should we demonstrate the sort of the biggest problem that people were running to or should
we just go to the exercises first?
We have one minute.
Okay.
Okay, well, let's just show one thing that might, this is something you might run into that might
be a problem. So we have here, we have run a for loop that sets a value for the variable i.
So here I can run an i equals 2. Okay, what if I add a cell here
here and run this. What do you think should happen? What do you think will happen? Well,
the way Jupyter works is that it just runs the cells in the order that you run them in.
It doesn't care about what order they're written in. So this will still be equal to 2, this
i here. What did I do? Okay. So that might be a problem if somebody else now gets your
notebook. If you take your notebook and send it to someone else and they try to run it so
there is this very convenient button here that will run all the restart the kernel just forget
everything and run all the cells from the beginning. So this is basically what will
happen when you give your notebook to someone else. They will run it every cell from the beginning.
So, now it ran this cell correctly, but this cell I doesn't mean anything, so it just failed
and gave an error.
It's a very useful error.
Name i is not defined, so you know what's happening.
So I will just delete this cell, because this is a problem.
It shouldn't be there, it should be here.
And let's try again.
So it's always useful to do this restart kernel
and rerun all the cells in order before sending your notebook
to anyone.
Oh, host name not found.
That's interesting.
OK, right, because that was it.
Actually, I was showing you that it doesn't exist.
OK, let's remove that error as well.
OK, now everything worked.
All the cells worked correctly.
OK, so I guess we'll go to the exercises
then. So let's do exercise one is almost at the top. So starting
and exploring Jupyter. And if you are new to Jupyter, it's
very much enough to just do that. There are some I mean,
it's good if you get to this first one, which is run some
code in Jupyter. The rest are some a bit more slightly more complicated exercises and if you
get all the way to the end, I mean I don't really expect you to get all the way to the end
necessarily, if you do then go on to exercise three. It's an optional discussion exercise so
you can write things into the notes or you can discuss with people close to you if they are also
done with all the exercises. So we'll give you 15 minutes and then we'll do a quick wrap-up. So go ahead.
Should we write some information in the notes about the exercise time?
Yes, I just...
you
Okay, welcome back. I hope you had a good time with the exercises and got Jupyter running.
So we had a couple of questions and I think the biggest issue is that bash indeed doesn't
work on Windows. It's an operating system specific thing. So there is a magic command,
how was the percentage sign there called CMD that should work on Windows
so you can use that one instead it will not work on my system so
you can try running it but yeah it does not exist. Yeah but sorry yes we missed that so
but bash equivalent in windows should be cmd so whatever we tried in the bash magic
in the bash cell then you could try that with cmd
okay so that's everything about jupyter for now we will be using it for the
a lot of the course so you will get used to it
it. Is there any other notable questions to bring up? There's a lot of questions and a
lot of answers which is great. Yes I think most of them are answered so maybe we can
just wrap up with when to use Jupyter and when is it not so great.
Yeah, so do you use Jupyter a lot?
It's actually mostly for teaching and for visualizing plots.
Yeah, it's really useful for visualizing because you can, it can display the plots or any images
inside the notebook. So, it's kind of inlining it. So, that's useful. It's good for quickly
changing a single cell. You don't have to rerun the whole thing. So, if you have a really – if
you have a processor that takes a few minutes to run and you want to work on the very last
10 seconds of it, you may not want to run the whole thing every time you're testing it. So,
just run the last couple of cells. And why should you not use Jupyter?
There's a few actually, a few good reasons to not use Jupyter as well.
I think the main most important one is the top most one here, so they don't promote modularity.
So yeah, writing functions in Jupyter notebooks or moving things into
to importable files is, I mean, it doesn't happen automatically. It's something you need
to think about when you're writing the notebooks.
Yes. And one thing I would mention here, it's also written in the material is that the nbdime
extension. That's really great if you are versioning and controlling your notebooks
and you should do that. So that will allow you to see differences between different notebooks,
which is not straightforward. Or rather, version controls the tool.
Okay and yeah there's some other things written down here but so you can read on your own time.
Now it's time for a break so do take a break you can come back to the exercises or any part of this
later but it is it's actually very useful for or very important for learning that you also
take breaks if you were really working on this one then take some time off to take your hands
off your keyboard and walk around and then come back. So we'll take nine minutes and then we'll
come back at the short. Let's come back two minutes past. And we'll continue with NumPy.
Alright, so see you after the break. Bye
you
So, welcome back, everyone, after the break.
Hello, should we say something about ourselves?
Yes, we should. So my name is [name]. I work at the PDC Center for High Performance
Computing in Stockholm. And with me here is [name].
Hi, I'm [name]. I'm a staff scientist at Aalto and I work with [name] and others at Aalto
scientific computing and I'm sure you will receive some emails from me regarding links
and other details for the course. So, nice to see so many of you here. So, [name], numpy.
Yes. So, as you can see here, we have opened here a Jupyter notebook. So, we will continue
this tool that you were introduced to in the previous lesson. And we see that you have
been posting, continue to post questions in the HackMD, and we will answer them continuously.
So [name], why would we need something, we do have support of lists and various data
types in regular Python from the beginning.
So why would we need a library like NumPy?
Yeah, I think that the issue with Python list,
with the kind of basic supported Python list,
is that they, as you can see here in this example,
there is one, 2.5, some string, some Boolean.
So it's a bit of a mixed bag of different types.
you can guess already that maybe this is not the most efficient way to deal with data,
especially if you need to do fast computation with it. So I think that the NumPy,
is it a NumPy? I think that it stands for numerical Python, isn't it?
Yes, indeed. And NumPy is a library used for scientific computing and it's something that
that we will use a lot here now in the course, and often it's so that even if you don't explicitly
work with NumPy, you might have it under the hood. So it will, for instance, come in under
the hood when we look on the Matplotlib visualization tomorrow.
So one of the core objects in NumPy are the arrays, which is a construction that can work
with a regular set of values. You can call them a grid. And all of the elements have
the same data type. This data type have indices, which are non-negative numbers. And these
indices can be in one or more dimension that is natively supported. If you look on the
The properties that the array elements have, or the arrays have, they have a dtype, and
an intrinsic property they have is that they have a shape. So, for instance, you can have
a two-dimensional array, three times two. You can have a three-dimensional array, three
times two, type 500. There's also the corner case of having a zero-dimensional array indexed
here by square brackets.
An important aspect is that we have
the data stored as raw memory, and it
can be passed to C and Fortran code
for efficient calculations.
So is it, [name], can you, do you
have some examples of when you combine C and Python?
Well, I mean, this is, NumPy is maybe the greatest example
of having so much sea power under the hood.
But what do you think,
should we show the power of NumPy?
Yes, yes.
So I'm gonna type so that also you,
whoever wants to type can do the same.
So basically we are creating a list
and this is range and it's 10,000.
All right. And that's the first list. And then we have another list. It's called B.
And this is now in regular Pythons. This is still not NumPy.
Yep. All right.
Yes. So let's see here what happens if you take the elements of the list A and you square
them and assign the value to B. It's a long list.
Yeah, it's a long list. So in this small example here, we basically
need to build a for loop, right? So that it will go through each of the elements of A
and assign them to b and then we use this magic time it which is very useful for basically
telling us the performance of the piece of code in the cell that we see here so we said
that we do a for loop in the range of the length of the list a and then we want to
do that the ith element of b is equal to the ith element of a square i think it's correct right
should we check that that was correct so what's the timing for this so it's saying 2.68 milliseconds
per loop so well one could think that it's even you know relatively fast 2.8 millisecond
Now, should we try the NumPy version?
Yes.
So there's now a new command that we have not used yet, which is import.
This is practically saying to Python that now I'm importing a library.
And often we even nickname that instead of using `numpy`, often it is nicknamed as `np` for brevity.
So you can save typing time.
and now we basically redo what we did earlier but this time we use this function so np.arange
with 10 000 and for the b we initialize it to zeros
and again 10 000 so basically we have recreated what we were doing earlier
with this but now they're not lists anymore now they are NumPy arrays and
now we can do you can already see how compact is the NumPy version of it so
we want to time it again and then we want to make sure that the array B will
contain the square the element y square of array A and let's see how long it
it takes. Okay, this was 3.42 microns [microseconds]. So I'm not good with math, but we are talking
at order of magnitude, three order of magnitudes of difference. So it's...
Yeah, yeah. This is quite a bit faster.
It's quite a bit different. So we showed some functions like this np.arange and np.zeros.
or are these related to this creating arrays, [name]?
Yes, exactly.
So there are a few different ways that one can create arrays.
So the arange, here we had as an argument 10,000
and so perhaps we can look at `a`.
So what does it start with?
Does it start with one or does it start with zero?
In this `a` here?
Yeah.
So, it starts with zero.
It starts with zero, yeah.
And also, I mean, the first element also has the index of zero.
Yeah.
So, this is then compatible with C, but it's then another convention than what is used
in, for instance, in Fortran.
So we could also have that we assign a distinct set of elements. So perhaps if you would like
to have just numbering up to six, but have it in a three-dimensional array, in a two-dimensional
array.
Yeah.
I think you have an example there for `b`.
So yep, so mparray and now I'm passing like in this example here I'm actually passing
a matrix basically row one and row two so I need many square brackets now this is the
first row and then there's a comma and then there's the second row four five and six all
All right, let's have a look at `b also.
All right, yeah, this is now like a square matrix
or not square, but two-dimensional.
Rectangular, yeah.
Now we have these attributes
that we can inspect the array with.
So yeah, b.shape, okay.
Pings back then that the shape of the object
is two rows and three columns.
And the size will give us the number of elements.
I see.
So, there are many alternatives to how to create arrays. So, we have here, for instance,
you can create all zeros. You can create all ones. Or assign all elements to some arbitrary
amounts. For instance, this np.full, 2, 2, and then 7, which then will assign all elements
to 7. You will see here soon in the exercises that you can manipulate the elements. So we
can yeah perhaps you can first show that how one can save and then read in again
yeah so let's see if we have something stored maybe a can be this
Yes, now we want to save it and be don't say I call it a.npy just because so that's the
a native format. Let's give it file.npy and the variable a this is actually like I'm coming
from a MATLAB past this is very similar to the save MATLAB where you have the name of
the file and then the variable and then of course I guess we can load things back. So
now I'm loading to a different variables called x and p dot load and the name of the
the file, which was file.mpy and let's see if it works.
Yeah, no, the same way.
So we would, should we already go to the,
or do we need, do you want to mention something
about this data type?
Yes, so one can change the data type.
change the data type. So, the data types here are dynamic. So, if you assign an element
or elements to be integers, then the array will be an array of integers. But you can
cast it into something else.
So, I'm making now an array of booleans just for the fun and let's see if it looks okay.
Yeah, so this is basically true and now we want to cast this. So, casting meaning that
we don't want to treat this as booleans anymore but we want to see them as integers. Let's
see if this works. Yes, so now there are 1s. Of course, we didn't actually modify D because
we didn't. So, D still has the, you know, we didn't store the output of D.
Yeah, exactly. Okay. So, now it's time for you to start exploring this on your own. So,
We are coming here to exercise one, where you get four tasks and you will explore how
to create with arrays and also how to create arrays that fill random numbers, how arrays
can be reshaped and also how arrays can be written to file and read from file.
And for this exercise, we will give you 15 minutes to work on it.
So that means that they will reconvene at 31 past the hour.
Okay.
And feel free, of course, to write on the notes document if you have any blockers.
And for those who want more advanced things, you can already jump to the next exercises
if this is too simple for you.
OK, I'll see you all in 15 minutes.
you
Hello, welcome back, hopefully you had enough time to do these exercises.
You must have noticed already that there's a solution box there so that, you know, if
you are not sure if you are, it's good to learn also from the answer so you can click
the box and it will expand. I'll just briefly comment on one exercise because at least looking
at the notes document maybe it wasn't clear that the output of np.arange is a little bit
different than the output of np.linspace and the difference as you might have noticed is
on the type so in practice one can set you know like we did earlier here with this casting
or if you look at the linspace function there's also a way to pass the type into as a argument
for the linspace so we will not cover all the exercises because hopefully the solutions
are good for you. So, should we talk about array maths and vectorization, [name]?
Yes, indeed. And first we can point out is that NumPy is fast as the backend of it is
done in C or in Fortran. That it has in common with other high level languages such as R
and MATLAB. So one important notion is that by default basic arithmetic such as plus minus
multiply and division is element by element. So this is something that we already saw this
when we calculated the square of a and assigned it to the variable b. So the default is that
it will perform the operation for each element in the array
and you don't need to explicitly write a loop.
And if you have run other languages such as MATLAB,
you might then notice that in MATLAB,
if you have the star for multiplication symbol,
that means matrix multiplication.
So this is then different in NumPy
because the star then means that you do it element-wise.
So NumPy, instead we are using the at symbol
to perform multiplication.
So perhaps we can have a look on some examples.
So if you create two arrays, A and B.
So the first array is a square matrix.
First row.
And then the second row.
and then I close the row and let's sure that it's like it should be okay then we
do or be five and six seven and eight
okay so now we can for example sum the two arrays just with a plus oh yes no
need to write any for loop a plus b and let's have a look at the output yes that
seems to be as intended yes so each element in the respective position has
been added to each other so is there some other way you can write this
instead of using the plus operator yeah there is this add function in practice
it's kind of the same but the advantage of having a function is that there will be more
parameters and more options but yes now we store it in the output D and we can have a
look at D and yes it's the same.
So how then if you want to perform the matrix multiplication of A and B?
So we said that it's this at,
or maybe I used the function notation,
at B dot dot, A and B.
And now it will store in E.
And it's been a few years,
I haven't done matrix multiplication,
but this looks like one, two, five and seven.
Yes, it is five plus 14, so 19.
Yeah, that's correct.
Good, so here you can see there's an exercise tool here, but we will, for now, we will move
on and look on indices and slicing. So this is core functionality when working with arrays.
So there are a few modalities how you can extract values. So you can extract single
elements that you then put in brackets. You can select rows or columns, or you could actually
take subvolumes of the array. So, for instance, if you have a two-dimensional array, you can
take out a rectangle that is within the full two-dimensional data range. So, I think we
can see how this goes in practice. So, I already started typing.
Yes, exactly.
I couldn't wait. So, with this np.arange. So, this will create an array with 16 elements.
And now we append the other function reshape. So, that instead of having, you know, kind
of a one dimensional 16 elements array, it will be a matrix. And so, and yes, it's a
times 4 matrix and now we can slice it we can take out whatever we need so the very first element
will be the first row because it works for wise which is also something that is a bit different
than matlab matlab prefers column wise so at least for me something that i had to remember
at the beginning but of course we can also get the first column yes and let's see if we get it
yes it's the first column
then there's another example here that we want to take kind of the middle two times two array
yeah so let me type it without errors from 1 to 3 in the rows and from 1 to 3
in the columns and then here how many element did we extract here so you had
the in this specified 1:3 and we see here that what we for the row and
And for the columns, we were picking out from index one,
but then up and until two.
So three is in the upper range,
but you don't include that in the selected elements.
Yeah.
Which again, I mentioned MATLAB again,
because there were many people
also in the registration asking.
So it's different, very different behavior than in MATLAB,
which instead it would have an indexes
would be 1, 2 and 3. All right, what else do we have here? We also have Boolean indexing.
So, what are these Boolean indexing? Let's see the first line and hopefully it will be clear.
So, now I'm basically saying a larger than 0 and a actually has one element that is 0.
Yeah, so then we can expect that this relation will come out as true, yes, for all of them
apart from the first one, the first element, yeah.
And now we can use this Boolean matrix as indexes, isn't it? So this is a good way
of filtering based on a value. So, a of idx, yeah, now it doesn't have the first element
anymore.
Ah, yeah, yeah, this is very, this is very neat, yeah.
So we basically filtered, maybe we could have, to make it clear, let's say a bigger than seven,
right and now let's see what is this filter and you see we only have those elements that
are bigger than seven so we are quite good with our timings is it now time for some more
exercises yes indeed so the idea is now if you scroll up so we will do exercise number
number 2 on matrix multiplication. And you will also do the exercise 3 which is on view
versus copy. And for this we intend to have 10 minutes exercises and then we will cover
the last sections of the lesson after this exercise.
Yeah.
Or should we give a bit more than 10 minutes if there's three exercises?
I think we can do it in 10 minutes.
Okay.
Yeah.
All right.
So we will be back at 52 past the hour.
Okay.
So good luck with the exercises and see you in 10 minutes.
Bye.
you
Hello, nice to see that you had time to try the exercises.
Something that was a bit puzzling, and I can totally understand if you come from other
programming languages like Matlab or R, is this view versus copy.
I will cover it a little bit later when I'll show you about other materials that we have
that we will not cover it today but in practice you can think it that B is like a pointer to
the memory allocated by A so hopefully I didn't use too much jargon in this maybe those familiar
with C and C++ they can understand what I mean but in it is actually useful to only
edit some elements of the same original array.
Instead, when you need the full copy,
there is actually a common call np.copy
that would basically clone the array A
into a new part of the memory to store a copy.
But yes, we have a few minutes to wrap up everything
and show you some future paths for you for self-learning.
Maybe something that is important to talk about NumPy
are the so-called universal functions.
Fancy names to basically saying that these are functions,
these are operations that can happen element-wise.
And we already tested them when we were doing A plus B,
you know, we didn't need to write a for loop
like we would have done with standard Python lists
because basically the function add
was one of these universal function
going through all the elements of the arrays.
Another very interesting thing that maybe if you're, you know, I sometimes never think
about this just because I'm a NumPy user without knowing, without really paying too much attention
what's going on under the hood, but we have something called like broadcasting which becomes
really practical when, for example, you need to sum things that are not exactly of the
same shape so it's not just a simple element wise but numpy is clever enough for example you see
in here that given the size of the array of b numpy understands that you want to kind of broadcast
it so that you want that each of the row of the vector of the array a of the matrix a actually
is summed with the matrix B.
This is something I would say that this is by no way obvious that you will have this behavior.
So before you feel confident in using it then I mean
be very careful and verify that you actually get the intended behavior.
Yeah this is maybe one good thing one positive thing about Jupyter notebooks is that
that you can actually you know when you are building your code when you are when you are
developing your method you can easily test that it's doing what you're expecting and
then maybe even write a test for what you are actually building.
So what else. Well we will leave exercise for you because our time is out for NumPy
today. In general, NumPy is under the hood on so many Python libraries, so that if your
needs are more into, you know, mathematics, signal processing, another thing, there are
lots of linear algebra functions already in NumPy, but another good library is SciPy,
which has all these type of functions for doing, you know, signal processing and other
more advanced numerical things in general for this last minutes that we have there's additional
exercises that if you have time of course and if you want to learn you could do them and if you
don't want to do them it's also interesting to just look at the solution and try to understand
what's going on and maybe get curious and try to run them try to run them yourself also last year
we cover this other lesson here that you see now where I'm here in the bottom and I click next
and so we have the recording from last year of this advanced NumPy for those who want to
understand for example like in this exercise 3 what is going on under the hood when we have a
view of the array A into something called B and actually here if you spend time going through this
lesson by yourself or watching the video from last year we are actually covering exactly this case of
the exercise 3 where let me find the picture yeah so you see that basically in the definition of
array A the memory a part of memory is allocated for A but in the moment where we take a view a
different view for another array B it was it's basically just a pointer to a subset of the
of the memory allocated by A. And this has the benefit then of being more efficient in two
regards so both that you're reusing actually memory so that's economic and also that you
don't need to in this case you don't need to make the copy. Yeah especially if you have a very big
matrix copy can be very very expensive even just the copy itself might take lots of seconds yeah
precisely so i think we cover everything and please keep on writing more questions or doubts
that you have in our share notes we could maybe start already the break right now and so we will
come back in about 10 minutes to continue with Bandas. So, thank you for listening.
Thank you, [name], for being here with me.
Yeah, thank you, [name].
And we will see you later. Bye.
Bye.
you
Wait, why is it not in gallery view?
Can one other instructor please join the Zoom room?
Because Zoom on this computer is acting weird.
Okay, hello. Welcome back. So, we will continue with pandas. So, yes, pandas. So, it's a Python
package that builds on NumPy and allows us to do many more fancy operations that are
basically involving tabular data. That'll involve tabular data. So we will see this
has lots of different built-in functions and things like that.
So Pandas is one of these things that, at least for me,
I know the basics of Pandas.
But for almost everything I do, I will do a web search
and then figure out, OK, how do I
do this particular thing to find the functions I need to do it?
And yeah, that's the same for me.
Yeah.
I'm sure there's some people that know it really well
and do things.
But yeah.
In fact, I wanted to add an exercise here,
which was specifically about doing this web
search to learn more.
So what's the point?
So the point is, be aware, this is the starting point
for this lesson.
So there's three exercises.
We do two exercises today, hopefully in about 20 minutes,
and then one tomorrow, where we'll continue.
So yes, let's get started.
Here you should see my screen, yes.
There's a lot of different getting started guides here.
And really, I'd say we have an overview,
But you're going to have to be reading these quick start
guides and so on things anyway.
Can someone add a pandas section to the notes?
I can't do that right now because I'm talking.
OK.
Yeah, so the pandas overview.
It's conventionally imported by `import pandas as pd`,
as a shorthand.
And then it provides lots of functions.
Like, for example, reading from CSV,
which I think NumPy also provides CSV reading.
But it actually does a lot more and provides lots of summary
information and things like this.
But now, [name] will be the one doing typing.
So let's switch to [name]'s screen.
Yeah.
So I guess the main difference between or in terms
a greeting CSV file. In NumPy, an array will always have all the data in the array will
be the same type. If there's one integer, it's all integers. If it's one floating-word
number, it's all floating-word numbers. And Pandas has different kinds of columns, so
it reads the column header and has a lot more information about different types of data.
So let's show this.
So we've got a...
I guess, yeah, first things first.
So I guess I'll start by importing it.
And we'll be going relatively fast here, so you can try to follow along, but at some point
we'll probably get ahead of you.
And then stop, watch what we're doing, and come back to it during the exercises.
Okay, so then there is this address in the notes, which I will mostly copy, although
I think I missed .csv.
So I'm just setting this string to a variable, and this contains a CSV file.
And then, again, I didn't create it, okay.
So this could be also a file on your computer just as well.
So what we're seeing here is loading the data directly
from the web.
Yeah.
So I will call the data frame Titanic
because it is about passengers on Titanic.
And let's just read CSV function to read it.
The mouse is hovering over the text.
OK.
And the URL is, I think, set here.
And I will also tell it to use an index column.
What is an index column?
So well, let's show the next line, the Titanic.head,
and we can see.
So every pandas array has columns and rows.
But notice the first row here is an index.
It's bold.
And the first column, this one's the name column here.
Yeah.
So basically, in NumPy, we'd access these rows
by rows 0, 1, 2, and so on.
In Pandas, we can also access it by these names
here, which we will see a little bit later.
Yeah, OK.
Let's do another one.
So another very useful function to start with
is describe with describe yes that's spelled correctly yeah okay so we see there's summary
statistics here so how much data actually exists and um i guess the um yeah these are the um
Percentile, 25%, 50%, 75%.
They're not that useful for passenger ID,
but let's say if you look at age, for example,
then it makes some sense.
Yeah.
So let's go on.
There's two more things here.
We will show them, but not explain what they do.
So these two commands show how you can
do some pretty fancy things.
So the group by means if they survived or not.
We separate them to two groups and then
take the age of those groups.
And then we find the average age of these people.
OK, so group by survived, take the age,
and take the mean of the age.
There we go.
OK, so we see the average ages for survived 1
and didn't survive 0 is pretty similar.
And let's do the next one.
So this histogram.
OK, that's slightly so titanic.
Which I think basically probably needs to be.
OK, yeah.
So age column.
So this is going to make a histogram of the ages.
And there'll be two groups, the passengers who survived
and didn't survive, and then some other parameters,
like the number of bins, the layout, and so on.
I wonder how important these parameters
are for this example.
I'll just copy.
Yeah, I would say just copy.
So figure size, layout, some ordering, shared x-axis.
Let's just go on.
At this point, we aren't knowing what these things mean.
OK, so positional argument follows keyword argument.
There's by equals survived there.
Oh, this needs to have an equal sign.
OK, yes, OK.
And we see these two figures.
So 0 didn't survive, and 1 did survive.
And this is showing the histogram of age.
So we're not going into the details here now,
because this is just a preview.
But now let's go to the actual details of what just happened.
OK.
So what's in the data frame?
Maybe start with the info function, I guess.
Can you go to the screen or the lesson again?
Yes.
There's a picture there.
Yeah, OK, yeah, so this is what a data frame looks like.
So we see it consists of rows and columns with column names
instead of just numbers at the top
and an index column on the left side.
So each of these columns themselves
is a pandas.series object.
And the data itself inside of these series objects
is stored as NumPy arrays.
OK.
So should we go back to the Jupyter
and let's run Titanic.info?
The head looks a lot like the picture,
although a little bit different.
Yes.
It's also the info function, which
tells you what columns exist and what types those are.
So these are the series that exist in this data frame.
And these data types are, in fact,
the NumPy data types there, at least in 64 and Float64.
So once we have this, we can do things,
like we can extract out single columns.
For example, we can do Titanic and then slice the age.
And then take the age.
And we can index it now by the name, the column name.
Yes.
Yeah, the column name, age.
Age is useful.
And we see, so notice it's pulled out
both the names and the ages, because this index got
preserved in the series itself.
And then we can, there's another shorthand here,
titanic.age with the column name.
So this doesn't work when age is also
an attribute of the data frame, but it's
convenient for shorthands.
So this is the same thing, basically?
Yeah.
OK.
We can list all the columns with titanic.columns.
So now it returns a list.
Otherwise, this is the same information
as in the .info function.
But it's a list, so you can, for example,
do a for loop over it.
Yeah.
I guess it doesn't contain the index.
So we have the name as an index, so you can also
take the index.
Yes.
Although this will now be a list of the names.
Yeah.
The name of the index column is name.
This is, in fact, a NumPy array inside of it also.
Yeah.
So we can get a single individual values
different ways.
So for example, this .loc method,
titanic.loc, we can give it a position by the index
and then column name.
So now I'm, so the index is the name again,
so I'm typing a name in.
And then column name is age.
It's easy to make a spelling mistake here,
so it might actually be good to, OK, key error.
I think lamb is capitalized.
Yeah.
OK.
None.
Well, that was the age is not recorded in the data frame.
So there is a little bit more here.
I think we don't have time to go into all these details.
But we can do things like using at.
we can set a value so okay let's do that yes
um okay well i'm not going to use the index method here so i'll just copy the name
yes should we set the age of age it says set age to 42
Well, I mean, I said it's 40 instead of 42, but that's fine.
We don't actually know the age.
So one thing that's taken me some time to get used to is you can use this loc and add
method to get values based on the names in the indexes.
But you can use the iloc and iat functions
to get values based on first row, second row, first column,
second column, and so on.
And these both have different uses in different cases.
For example, if there's a big time series,
then it makes sense to extract what happened on this day.
But if you're iterating through, maybe it
makes sense to get the first row, then second row,
and so on okay so basically it depends on if you're doing something for all the columns
then or splitting it in some way by numbers then just use the numbers otherwise it's more
readable to use the names usually yeah okay um we can do the boolean indexing just like numpy
raised. So for example, let's get the... So I guess I'll do it in a couple of steps.
So did you want to get any something other than this age thing? Let's go. So let's extract the
passengers that are older than age 70. So this returns a boolean thing, which is mostly false.
most people are not over 70 years old. But I can use that as an index for the array and just take
the passengers who are older than 70 years old. Yes, five of them.
So this is just now all passengers older than 70.
Okay, and this looks a lot like the NumPy syntax because it's designed around that.
Yeah, it's good that things work in a similar way.
So there's a lot more things to demonstrate here.
For example, we can get all the NA values.
We can remove the NA values.
we can replace the missing data with other things.
Which one would you like to demonstrate?
Maybe let's.
So, OK, what you would mostly need to do
is often you just need to drop the none values.
This doesn't create a new data frame.
This does not override the data frame.
It creates a new one and returns that.
So we don't actually change this Titanic data frame now.
Yeah.
But it's often useful to get the data frame that
only contains non-defined values.
Of course, you can also, you might
want to first take a set of columns
and then drop the values, or drop the rows
where those columns are not defined.
Because this is dropping everything
where even any value in any column is none.
This is dropping it.
Okay, so we are going a little bit fast here, but that's by design to give you more time
for exercises.
So again, we're just summarizing the biggest high level things.
Okay, the next section, so now there's exercises, but instead we're going to cover the next
little section, well not so little, but then have you do two exercises at once.
So now there's tidy data. So this is not purely panda stuff itself, but also
it's about how you arrange the data itself. So in tidy data the idea is that every column
is a variable and each variable has its own column and each observation is a row.
So for example down here we're making a sample thing about runners and if [name] creates that.
Yes let's go back to demonstrating. So I will again just copy this data in
But it contains three runners and some values for, I guess, run times.
And now runners is a data frame.
Okay, so distances and times for those distances run.
So is this tidy data?
No.
So there's multiple measurements per row here.
It's measuring run times for four different, possibly different runs, but at least in four
different places in the same run, possibly.
But in any case, four different measurements.
So basically, yes, every row contains the results from four different races.
So what's next?
this melt function.
OK, so maybe it's better to comment while I write it.
So we'll replace the runners data frame.
pandas.melt is the function.
And we put the current runners data frame in.
And then we have to define a set of variables that, well,
I mean, these are kept in the rows, in every row.
So this is something that identifies the runner
or the experiment or the subject,
experimental subject, something you want to keep.
And this is not a measure.
This is not something you measure.
This is something that identifies the measurement.
So the name of the runner is not something you measure.
it's something that identifies the measurement and then I guess value variables and those
are then the numbers so these are the columns that contain actual measured values
so these we want to split into separate rows and these we do not
I guess then we need a name for this new variable.
So we split this into multiple rows so that creates a new column.
We want a name for that column.
So what is the name for these numbers?
I guess distance run.
And what is the name for the thing that we're measuring here?
That's time.
Okay, hopefully, oh, not quite right.
It's not present.
These variables are not present in the data frame.
400, 800, okay, maybe they are strings.
Maybe.
Can you so I'll give you coffee from the lesson.
Let's see.
Yeah.
I think we should try to go well, it did work now.
Okay. So it was some spelling error somewhere. Okay. So what did it do? It took all of these
numbers and made a row for each of them. And then we have identifying information. So this
run a name, and this column title
go here as identifying information
for that measurement.
Yeah.
OK.
And this is now tidy data.
And the reason is that each row is only one observation.
An observation is the amount of time it took on a race.
And this lets us do things like the group by we saw before.
So basically, by using the other operations,
we can do cool stuff on this.
But we need to carry on now.
So again, this is a thing that there's a linked article
that you should probably read.
It has a lot more and really convinced me
why this is a good idea.
Okay, working with data frames. So there's a lot of other stuff we can do with them.
And I propose that you all can read this as well as we can say it right here.
Um, is there anything to comment on? Um, there's
is, yeah, there's an example of making a data frame that
has a date range index where all the index values are
a certain date.
And then ones with other things, and shows
how we can combine them, merge them, and so on.
Yeah, I propose we go to the exercises now
and leave the 20 minutes for them.
So we'll come back at 52.
And we can go into more details about things tomorrow
and after we get back.
Does that sound good?
Yeah, that sounds good.
Okay, great.
Alright, so let's go to the exercises, until 52, and see you then.
Okay, bye.
you
Hello, we are back.
We have a little bit of wrap-up for the day,
and we know this was a rather rough lesson,
So, like I tried to motivate when we started,
pandas is the kind of thing that even we are always going through
and reading about it to figure out how to do things.
So this is sort of an impossible lesson to teach.
So we can either go so slow that we don't show anything interesting,
or show some cool stuff,
But you need to go back and read to figure out how it works
yourself later and
we tried to have a little mix in here and
Well, it didn't work that well
That's um
Well, it's unfortunate, but we'll try to do better next time but it's sort of how it is
So, by the way, at the bottom of the notes here, you have a place you can vote about
what you thought of the lesson.
So use this poll to say what you thought of it, and please give us comments.
And we'll go look at those quickly.
So, any comments from the exercises or what we can do?
Let's take a look.
So this thing here, so the problem with this we see, and the solution here.
So the difference is these are in parentheses here.
So basically Python gets this order of operations wrong, where it would try to do the ampersand
first and then the comparison.
I know this has tripped me a lot, many times in the past.
It's so much in fact that I just, nowadays if I type a number and I also type the parenthesis
around both sides, just automatically, because otherwise it will usually fail.
Yeah.
OK.
And yeah, so there's this convention in Python
that when you're slicing things, the first index is included,
and the second one is not included.
And that's, well, Python or Pandas
follows the Python convention.
And you can read there the debate on which one is better or worse.
Well, it's an interesting question, and let's not get into that.
We can write by chat.
Are there any other questions or comments here?
So [name], what's your overall summary of Pandas?
what should someone have gotten from this lesson?
Well one thing is just that it exists that the
how the data frames work also there is a python library that's really good at
this sort of table like data and you can do kind of magical things
with it.
Well I guess that last part of the sentence was the second one so
You don't need to remember how to do this, all of these things. It's mostly you will look through,
do a web search for what you want to do and look through the documentation.
But yeah, so it is, it can do kind of similar things to what a spreadsheet can do,
but a lot faster and you can save it as script.
Maybe my summary would be if you're making things that have a bunch of numpy arrays,
one for each effective column, or you have these deeply recursive dictionaries of list
or list of dictionaries or things like that, then maybe pandas with all this extra structure,
Like the indexes, the names, the way you can slice different things can do it better.
And we'll see another example of this tomorrow.
But as of now, we have this feedback of the day.
So please, please comment here.
It's the only way we have to improve things.
So, there will be videos produced for tomorrow, hopefully.
If you would like to help with that, please let us know.
There is, yeah, and if you can do the stuff of today, then tomorrow should be okay.
more important to have JupyterLab or similar because we do visualization and we need to show
these graphics in the notebooks. And if there are any problems with the software today,
you should make sure you install this for tomorrow.
Yes, not this. Any positive feedback kinds of things.
So yeah, I mean, this is, if you're completely new to Python now, like, you're still using the Python syntax a little bit.
today will have been really hard. But don't let that discourage you, because I mean this is a
medium, like an intermediate kind of course. But hopefully you can stop, take a step back,
and watch and see what we're doing, and use this as inspiration when you're learning on your own
later on.
Any other comments?
A lot of this is an overview of
a lot of stuff
that
will probably be
useful at some point in the future.
So there is one comment that there
is a lot of material and that
can stress
you out.
But the idea is not that we cover or that you learn all of the material. It's a selection. You can go for what you're interested in.
And yeah, not everything will be useful immediately. You will not learn everything immediately, but you can always come back.
Yeah, okay, so, um, well, it's time to stop, so let's go with that.
See you all tomorrow, same time, a little bit early for icebreakers and initial discussion,
And thank you for attending.
Bye.
you