CodeRefinery.org
you
Test 1, 2, can anyone out there
Okay, I hear an echo.
Where is my audio?
I think it's better now.
Okay.
Hi.
So, welcome to day two.
We see the notes here, as usual.
So, should we talk a little bit about yesterday?
many people were here yesterday or not? How about we add a poll? I'm writing it now.
So yeah, you see right here. If you were here, then add an oh yes or on the no part or partly
and let's see. Are there any other cool questions we can ask for starting off?
Yes, today's topic is Matplotlib and mainly that's the big one and the data formats,
Good morning, are we already streaming?
Yes we are live.
Hello everyone.
Good morning, everybody.
Yes.
OK.
OK, so there I added a poll about how big of data use
was Python, which relates to several things today.
Yeah, so any other questions and follow-ups from yesterday?
Let's see.
Someone asked anything special to know from Tuesday.
So if you ask me, the Tuesday session was a pretty, like it really was covering basic
kind of things.
So the first lessons were about Jupiter and NumPy, which was sort of setting everyone
at the same starting level.
If they're new to you, it's worth reviewing them, but if you use them a little bit, it's
probably okay.
And also, it's okay—I mean, it's always worth learning more about numpy and pandas,
but you're probably okay for the rest of the lesson.
The last lesson from yesterday was pandas, and we continue with pandas in a few minutes
now.
So for that, we really had this high-level overview, because we had to talk both quickly
and also rather it was a bad combination of speaking quickly
and giving a high and low level overview at the same time.
But that's because there is so much to talk about there.
So all we hope to give was a starting point
and then motivating you to read more yourself.
And if Pandas seems like the kind of thing you need,
I'd really recommend reading these tutorials, like 10 minutes to pandas and so on.
So today we'll basically start from scratch and do something else, so it's not that necessary
to look through yesterday if you want to see today's thing, because it is the first thing,
so you have four minutes.
It's fine.
Did anyone notice the videos are published?
So I've slightly refined the video making system.
So it's a little bit quicker for us now, which is good.
There's a good question here.
In part of the course, so this is on the course page or the lesson page, Python is strongly
and dynamically typed.
means roughly it's not possible to circumvent the type system. Is there any language that
behaves the opposite? Does anyone have any answers to that?
Well, there's
there's plenty of ways of circumventing the type system in C and C++
because they're so low level. So I guess they are not as strongly typed.
Yeah, so that means, like, reinterpret the memory as a different kind of pointer or something
like that.
Basically, yes.
Okay.
I'm casting to a different subclass of a class.
Okay, okay.
Yeah.
Really, I don't think there's anything that's weakly and statically typed, because that,
I don't know.
I mean, that never makes sense.
But there are weakly typed languages where there just are no types, like JavaScript is
rather weakly typed.
And then there are statically tied, where you have to declare all the types, like C
and C++.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's the kind of thing that I haven't really gone that much into the theory of different
types of programming paradigms and so on.
Anyway, any other questions we should discuss?
No comments from the audience.
Yeah, I don't see anything.
It's also one minute, too.
How's our volume level doing?
Should we do our standard test?
So one, one, two, two, three, three.
Okay.
What do you think?
If there's no comments on audio, I guess.
Okay.
Audio levels are good.
So yeah, so the big picture of today,
first we start with a little bit more of Pandas.
So we'll show about time series stuff
and an overview of something from last time.
And then we have a big, long lesson
on matplotlib, which is the core plotting library.
And that's sort of the basis of all the other plotting stuff.
And then there is a quick summary of data formats,
and then a slightly longer description of productivity
tools for Python, things like linters and stuff like that.
OK, but with that being said, let's start.
So I will switch to Yarno's screen.
Where's all my pointers. So, there we go. Okay. So, we are continuing with pandas. So,
I'd recommend at the first, for now, you watch us as we type. And then, when it comes time
to exercise your work, because we're going to be typing fast.
And I don't think you can keep up
where this is more a demo than a type log right now.
So with that being said, where's our starting point?
So we first wanted to demonstrate some extra data
frame properties, which was the merging of data frames.
Is that correct?
Yeah.
OK, so a merge, if you know the concept from SQL or things
like that, it will make sense.
But let's show what it is visually.
So we're using the runner examples.
So import pandas.
So this is from yesterday just.
And this is the runner ranking.
Yes.
And if we run this, what do we see?
It's also printed.
So we see runners with distance and time.
So if we scroll down a little bit
under the working with data frames,
we see an age data frame, which has different.
For each runner, it has the age.
So notice the runner column is the same among both of them.
So we want to match up these datas and connect.
Aljarno, can you close the sidebar?
Yes.
OK, there we go.
OK, so what happens when we merge them?
So we take the parent data frame,
and what we want to add to it is age.
we say we connect age to it and the runner column is the thing that matches up and if we run this
we see uh does it return it directly yes it does okay so this returns it directly it probably
doesn't modify the original data frames but we see now age has been connected to the runners
everywhere it should be
And yeah, that's that's the idea of merge. And there's all kinds of these tools that you can
find in pandas to do almost everything you can. I mean, it's the same kind of tools you'd find in
other things like SQL and so on. But if you ever find yourself going in manually, doing this kind
of data processing thing, connecting tabular or tidy data, then maybe take a step back and see
see, should we be doing it with pandas instead.
So our next demo is about time series.
So what does this mean?
So a time series is something where
there is data which occurs periodically over time.
And this is one of the original major use cases of pandas.
So it has pretty good support there.
So first, we will load this CSV file
from the web, which has information on all the Nobel
Prize winners.
So when we run this, we can see something.
And we see there's, well, like we expect, first name, names,
born, died, born, country, all these kinds of things.
So the thing is that these born and died columns,
it looks like dates to us,
but the computer doesn't interpret them as dates.
So we can tell pandas this should be a date time column.
So there's this next little bit here we can copy.
There we go.
And if we run this and then do a head of the Nobel Prize,
Nobel Prize, again. So it looks pretty similar. But if we do an info now, nobel.info.
So notice that born, died, and year, they're all now DateTime64 objects. Which means,
so before they were object like the other ones. So that means Pandas knows that these are actually
DateTime objects. And under the hood, these are actually NumPy types.
So we can do some extra things now. So for example, if we do for each of these DateTime
columns, there's a .dt attribute, which means interpret this as a Python DateTime.
And we can do things like day. Let's see. And it tells us, oh,
It's the day of the month.
It's the integer of the day out of there.
We can do year.
Yeah, that looks OK.
And even things like weekday, which
this comes from the Python date time object.
And I guess that will also define what it actually
means in there.
So it's like, it's Sunday, Monday, Tuesday, and so on.
Yeah.
But represented as a number.
So since these are date times, we can do things like arithmetic on them.
So the next thing down here is how we can subtract them.
So we're subtracting the born and died years, converting it to days, dividing that by 365
to make years, and then rounding it by one.
So I guess we want to run nopal.head or something
like that.
OK, yeah.
Because this just added a lifespan column.
And somewhere there, there's probably lifespan.
It's the last one.
That seems pretty reasonable looking.
So what do we do with this lifespan now?
So we have an integer lifespan.
So we can do things like plot, like make plots out of it.
So for example, let's make this histogram.
So column lifespan, we specify some bin size and so on.
And OK, yeah, looks like reasonable ages
for relatively well-off people from the last century.
Next off, let's do something else.
Since we have a column that
specifies what category or price they've got,
there's all kinds of things built in like
plotting the lifespan split up by category.
So how does this look?
Yeah, I mean, seems pretty reasonable.
Yeah, the statistics are not that great, so I don't think you can actually draw inferences,
but you see some interesting data.
Okay, so we're about to go to exercises here, these exercises three.
And what have we learned then?
So basically, by using Pandas the way it's made, by converting things to the right data
types and aligning all the columns and making them tidy, there's all these different powerful
things we can take and use, which let us do things very quickly.
But remember what I said back at the beginning.
So almost every time I do something medium level in Pandas, I do a web search to figure
out how I do it.
Because I can't keep it all in my mind.
I know the basics like slicing stuff and so on.
So just keep that in mind.
If it seems hard, just take the time, read about it, and the more you use it, the better
you'll get at it. Okay. What do you think? Should we go straight there?
Yeah. Let's just go to ‑‑ I mean, I don't have anything special to add. It's the
same for me. I'm always checking how to do things in pandas rather than remembering.
And this goes for basically any library in Python. Usually you don't remember how to
do any complicated operations, you check.
There's so many things you can do with these libraries.
OK, yeah.
There's a good question coming up.
Can we say something about the difference between pandas
and R's tidyverse?
So Jarno, do you know much about R's tidyverse?
Not that much.
I mean, it's a few more.
I propose we go to the exercises. Maybe we can have someone comment a little bit more after the exercises.
So, yeah. Okay, let's go. So how long were the exercises supposed to be? 20 minutes or 15 minutes?
15 minutes. Okay. 25, and then we come back. Okay, I switch to the notes, and see you soon. Bye.
you
Hello, we're back.
So yes, if we look here, we see some good questions in the notes.
There's this one about the difference between pandas and R's tidyverse.
When us instructors talking, we thought a good metaphor is that pandas is like what
R does itself, and tidyverse is a collection of many things around that, like a consistent
ecosystem of stuff that works together, and that's sort of like SciPy in Python.
But really, the philosophy is very similar of a bunch of stuff
consistently trying to work together.
There's some compatibility between them,
like in the data formats, which we might talk
about a little bit later today.
Okay. There is various.
So one thing maybe to raise is because there are these two functions for accessing columns
and rows, lock and add, which we did mention yesterday really quickly, but lock gets you
data but it doesn't allow you to set data and at allows you to set the data so that
so if you try to say database.log and then equals something it will give you an error
and then you should I guess the error message doesn't tell you to use at
so you need to remember to use at just a little bit you know annoying it's something you need
need to remember yeah okay so there is a little bit more in pandas down at the
bottom beyond the basics it's probably not worth us trying to go into the
details here but basically the idea is you can do a whole lot here there's
Sometimes depending on what you want, you can either get more power, or you can get
more optimized, like faster, and so on.
And yeah, maybe that's all we've got.
And remember, if this seems remotely useful to you, read the 10 minute introductions to
pandas and get this perspective.
Um, yes, okay. Should we call it good and go to
the next part then?
Yeah, let's move on.
Okay, so here we've got our other instructors.
There is [name] and [Name].
And I guess Jarno and I will head out for a bit.
See you.
Thanks a lot.
Bye.
And good morning, everybody.
Maybe we should, what I'm unsure about
is whether my microphone volume level is all right.
but so give us feedback somewhere on one of these chats.
But let's start with an introduction.
So my name is [name].
I'm super excited that I will teach
data visualization here with [Name].
We will talk about data visualization and Map.lib,
two topics I really like to talk about.
I work in Norway, in Tromso.
I do research software engineering
and I like to help researchers with improving their code.
And I like to teach Python and different things. And with me is [Name].
Yeah, good morning, everyone. My name is [Name]. I work at the PDC Center for
High Performance Computing in Stockholm. But right now I'm sitting here from Uppsala.
And I realized that I should take the screen and arrange it. Let me do that.
Just a sec, he, no, that's not right.
Almost double range.
And while I opened the sharing window,
I will close my physical window.
All right.
Good.
We will talk about data visualization.
And let me first tell you how the best way to participate.
So what to expect.
It's good if you have your JupyterLab open,
and I understand you have that already
if you were following the Pandas episode,
but if you joined later,
it's a good moment to open up your JupyterLab.
We will be using it.
So we will be doing data visualization inside Jupyter.
And we will also explain why that is such a good fit.
And we also, you can open up this episode,
the data visualization with WebHotLib,
which is also linked in our collaborative notes.
And [Name] and me, we will look at these notes.
So that's a good place to ask us questions.
And in a different window on my screen, I have them open,
and we will try to react to questions live.
So please keep the questions coming.
We plan to do a bit of introduction
for the first 15 minutes.
We will then do an exercise block.
So you will get 20 minutes to try this on your own.
We will then do a break.
And after the break, we will do something,
we will talk about how to make plots even prettier.
And then we will have another exercise block.
And now the question is, should you, should you, as we, as we show you how this works
in a notebook, you can, you can either try that with us.
So if I add something to the notebook, you can do it as well.
If that is cognitively a bit too much to listen and also go into a different window and type
something it's also totally fine to just watch what we do and you will have enough time in
the exercise box to try it yourself good so let's first motivate why we do this and why
we chose matplotlib and why we do that in a jupyter notebook let me just arrange the
to Windows here on my side so that I can see your questions.
Let me also zoom in here a bit.
Data visualization with Matplotlib.
So our goal is not becoming experts
and knowing everything that can be done with Matplotlib,
but we want to give you a really good overview
of how to find help, how do we use it,
and what are good starting points,
and how does it connect to the previous episodes
like pandas?
So that's our goal.
In total, we will spend one and a half hours on this topic.
So not only being able to start,
we also want to show you how can you tweak,
how can you improve plots without remembering
all the options and the commands
because we don't remember them either.
The application interface of Matplotlib is, is really big.
And it's also so that, so Radaman, is Matplotlib the only Python packet for visualization or
are there more?
No.
Opportunities?
So there are many.
Here are the ones that we know, that we know.
So there are probably even more.
I have tested most of them and I use them in different contexts.
So there is Mapplotlib.
This is the one that we will show you.
There is also, and it is probably the most popular one, but there is Seaborn, which builds
on top of Mapplotlib.
There is Vega out there, Plotly, ggplot, and then there are different libraries for more
special use cases.
I would consider the top four here or the top five really general.
So there are many libraries and also Python is not the only language that can do plotting.
So why do, why do we do matplotlib?
So I would say one, one very, very good thing with matplotlib is that, I mean, as Python
is a completely free ecosystem, it is transferable.
So if you write the plotting scripts in Map.lib,
you can share them with your colleagues
and also with the community at large.
This can be done a little bit in contrast
with some commercial packages for plotting
where you might have a lock-in effect
that you prepare your scripting and then you share it
and others cannot, perhaps they can read the script file,
but they cannot make use of it
because they do not have the program.
Yeah.
And it may even be the same person or you
in a different job in future.
And so the fact that it is free,
that both Python is free and open source
and that MapleClip is free and open source
is really important.
And it's really important for reusability
and reproducibility.
And I like to, so when I talk about data visualization,
I like to start with this quote,
which I took from this fantastic book
by Klaus Wilke, Fundamentals of Data Visualization,
which you can browse, the book is online.
And it is this quote here,
that one thing I have learned over the years
is that automation is our friend.
I think figures should be auto-generated
as part of a data analysis pipeline,
and they should come out of the pipeline
ready to be sent to the printer with,
and here I paraphrase, with minimal post-processing needed.
And this is because when we generate plots for posters
or publications or theses, at least in my experience,
I never do it only once.
I do it at least twice.
I do it once and then I do it again
one day before the deadline because something changed.
I want to modify the color or I get new data
or I realized that there was a tiny mistake
and I need to change the figure.
And if this is not automated, it's hard.
Might need different versions of your figures.
So the precise size and shape of a figure
that you have in a manuscript might be different
from what you then need to go on a poster
or on slides for presentation.
Then if you have that in script form,
you can then tune to the appropriate format
and then reuse your work.
Yeah. Or new data comes in and you want to update the figure.
And we will see that if we use tools like Matplotlib
in combination with tools like Jupyter Notebook, this becomes a really nice combination.
So we will now focus on Matplotlib, but you can browse, of course, all the other ones as well.
Well, at the end of the session, we might also have a look at one of the other libraries.
Why did we start with Matlab? We motivated a little bit. It's also, so it is the most
popular library. It is, if you come from Matlab, it will feel familiar because it, it takes
a lot of inspiration from how plotting is in MATLAB.
Even if you choose to not use Matplotlib, maybe you prefer Seaborn.
Many of these libraries build on top of Matplotlib.
And then if you want to tweak it, improve it, it helps to have an understanding of Matplotlib
to be able to improve your plots.
But it is relatively low level, low level in terms of we can really modify everything.
So in terms of abstraction, it doesn't provide statistical functions.
Some of the some of the other libraries do.
But the advantage of my book is that you can adjust everything, you can really make things
publication ready.
and can be configured and modified.
And speaking of statistics,
which is not containing matplotlib,
I mean, you can naturally combine the matplotlib scripting
that you do with other Python packages,
such as numpy, scipy, and then mostly pandas
that we have been talking about earlier.
And I'm having just a quick look on the questions.
Thanks for coming, raising them.
For instance, question nine,
when should I use X and when should I use PLT?
This is something that confused me a lot
when learning and using maplotlib.
And we will comment on that.
So we will clarify that.
This is something I realized maybe 10 years into using it,
that there were these different interfaces.
So we will comment on it.
Also, another really good question is,
how is matplotlib built on top, built using,
so how does it connect to pandas?
And also this is something we will discuss.
Some of the plotting libraries interface with pandas
in a more nice way or less,
but also with matplotlib it is possible
to use pandas data frames.
we will come back to that.
But I think we are ready to open up the notebook
and start creating our first plot.
At this moment, you can either do it as well
if you have enough screen space
and enough cognitive management,
but you can also watch what we do.
You will have the chance to test it out
in the exercise block.
I will open up a new notebook.
So let's start with a new notebook.
Let's not continue from one from before.
I will open up a new one and also good first reflex is to rename it.
I don't want to have my notebooks untitled, untitled 1, untitled 2.
I want to give it a good name.
I will rename it.
Right click, rename notebook.
Let's call it plotting.
And back to the material.
I will copy paste the code here from this block.
I will run it in a notebook,
but let's also explain then what is happening.
Let me copy.
So I copied the whole block.
Let's see whether this works at all.
Yeah, you're in the Python for SciComp
Python environment, I guess.
Yes.
or anaconda environment yes yes so at this moment all we import is a library called matplotlib
which is part of the python for scicomp it is also part of an anaconda base environment
so if you get here an error that matplotlib not found then you are probably in a different
environment. And I ran this code, I got a first plot, which shows some dots. I have
an x axis, I have a y axis and a title, they are not very concrete yet. And now let's inspect
the corresponding code. What did what did we do, we imported the functionality. I am
I defined two lists of numbers x values y values
and these values take they are part of the so-called arms come squatted which is a really
important data set
because it is used to motivate why we even do data visualization because it's it's for
data sets which
really look very different when we plot them.
But when you look at the statistical values,
like the mean, the sample variance, the correlation,
the regression, the statistical values are the same.
So if I didn't plot these,
if I would only look at the numbers at the table,
I would maybe have less insight.
But back to the example, what else can we discuss here?
This is the important part. These two lines, we, we set up a figure and we set up axes.
These are objects, which we then can use to, for instance, do a scatter plot. And here
I sent the data X into, I said, these are the X values. These are the Y values. And
I define a color, which in a really weird format here,
but I will later comment on why we do this.
Instead, I could also use a named color.
I could say red.
And if I run that, then the dots will be red.
And this is self-descriptive here.
Just having a look at the questions.
using just import matplotlib instead of matplotlib.pyplot.
So why I do this here? Because there is more in matplotlib than the pyplot. Pyplot is one
of the interfaces that Matplotlib provides.
I could also import Matplotlib and then here I would have matplotlib.pyplot.plt.
I could do that as well and it would also work.
It wouldn't be on any noticeable penalty, maybe a little bit more typing.
I chose this way because this is often what people do and this is often what you find
when you look for examples on the internet or if you ask one of these AI chat solutions.
Just looking at the other, so question 15, is it better to use this way of doing it rather
than the PLT?
We will comment on that.
So we will come to this.
recommend to do it this way. So we show you the more robust way and but we need
to then also explain why this is possibly more robust. I think we will do
that after the exercise.
To go into the first exercise, so should we perhaps present it? Yes, so now you
you have all the tools ready to do the first exercise block.
Your goal, I mean, here it says 15 minutes,
but we really want to give you 20
until five minutes past the hour,
but I need to explain also clearly.
Your goal will be to do what we did here with [Name].
Open a notebook, copy the block, get it to run.
But once you get the image that we got here,
you are asked to extend it, you should add a second data set
and then yet another data set which is this one multiplied by two. And here we wanted to show you
also that this is a way to multiply all numbers. This is one of the many ways in Python to multiply
a list by a factor. Then you will get a plot that looks like this. And another thing that
you can try to do is browse the documentation, find out, so you can have a look at the quick
start guide and try to find out how can you get a label, sorry, a legend into the plot
that we can then link to the data values.
And at the end, it should look like this.
You can also experiment changing, modifying the colors.
And if you get stuck, there is a solution here.
So if I would open this up,
but I will do it only very quickly
because we don't want to have a spoiler,
but you find a solution for this exercise.
And then we can come back five minutes after the hour.
And after that, we will send you into a break.
And if you are curious about
why did we choose these particular colors,
here is an explanation.
Do we have everything we need for the exercise block?
So your goal is this exercise number matplotlib one.
And I will add instructions into the document
And we will be back five minutes after the hour.
All right, good luck and see you in a bit.
Bye.
So, do we do it until five past?
Yeah, which is less than 20 minutes, but I think that's fine.
Yeah, that's fine.
Yes, ma'am.
Great.
So I'm thinking for the, when we do the customization thingy,
I think I will do the.
I had to step out.
Are we off now?
Yes, we are in, or hopefully, we are an exercise block.
you
And we are back from the exercise.
So sorry that we were talking through the exercise.
It took us a little bit to notice
that we were still on air,
but nothing bad happened, hopefully.
Thanks for doing the exercise.
Thanks for so many questions.
We will be continuing answering them,
but we want to give you a break.
So please take 10 minutes break.
We will meet again 15 minutes past the hour
and I will continue answering the questions.
So see you in 10 minutes, 15 past.
All right, bye.
you
And welcome back from the break.
We will continue with Matplotlib.
I wanted to also show you the result of the exercise session.
So hopefully you get the result that looks like this.
You also find this in the solution.
So here we have plotted three sets of X and Y values with different colors.
I want to save the notebook.
I just wanted to remind a really good practice that I find very useful is that before I save
a notebook and before I share a notebook with other people, I like to run all cells from
top to bottom.
If the notebook is not too long, I would recommend to do the restart kernel.
Yeah.
This is even better because this will reset and run everything from top to bottom because
this is exactly what the next person will do.
Because the next person opening the notebook will not have anything in memory.
It will...
They will run the notebook from top to bottom and I want to make sure that it still produces
the results that I want it.
This will prevent me from having to run the notebook
in a very particular order that nobody will remember.
And now I can save.
Super.
And before I hand over to [Name],
and before we talk about now, how can we improve a plot?
How can we customize it?
I wanted to comment on the question
that we got a couple of times,
which is which of the two possible ways
that one can use Matplotlib should we use?
and why. And I admit, sorry I need to zoom in here, I admit that although I was using
Matplotlib for quite a while, it wasn't clear to me that there were actually two different interfaces.
And I got really confused because every time I was asking the internet for how do I do something in
Matplotlib, I saw an answer but it always looked different than what I remembered. And I was
doubting myself for a long while until I learned that there are actually two ways to run Matplotlib.
One way is the so-called object oriented way, or also called the explicit interface.
And in this explicit interface, we create these objects.
And then we use them.
This is the method that we use in this lesson.
This is also the method that we recommend.
There is another method, which is the so-called pi plot way of doing things, or the so-called
implicit interface, which looks shorter. So there is less to type. I don't have to create
the figure object. I don't have to create the axis object. I can do this directly. So
it looks easier. The downside is that now that we start customizing. So if I now change
the the line width and the format and colors and settings. I will affect
the settings for all my plots that come later in the notebook or in my Python code. And
sometimes this is not what you want. So this will be more practical. If you
Once you start putting this into a function, because then when you change settings, you
change settings only for the for the function that you want and for the plots that you wanted
instead of changing it implicitly for everything.
So that's why we recommend this way, but we show you both ways because so that again,
You know, if you then search Stack Overflow
or you ask chat GPT for,
how do I do something with my potlip?
You might get, you might see this kind of an answer.
And then you know why this is different
than what we have just learned.
Here's also an explanation why we even spent
now a couple of minutes emphasizing this.
And with this, [Name] will now take over and guide us through styling and customizing plots.
And we continue watching the collaborative notes.
And please continue asking questions, we really appreciate it.
Yes, thank you, Ranaan. So, we will now touch upon the topic of styling and customization
plots. And a starting notion here is this, that this is also an aspect of reproducibility.
Because I used myself earlier in the days to often do plots with, yeah, often with MATLAB.
And I would then get a certain feel and look of the figures, and perhaps do something which
needed to be tuned a little bit, and I might then do it in a drawing program.
That's fine if you do it once or twice, but if you need to do it for 10 figures, it's
a lot of extra work.
So matplotlib and other libraries, they allow to customize almost every aspect of a plot.
And it's going to be good to know what are the different matplotlib parts of a figure
so that we know what we can search for when to customize things. So we open up this. And
This is here for a two-dimensional figure.
So you can see here that in the object-oriented modality,
we have all of these variables.
So you have the axis set minor locator.
You have a major tick label.
You have the markers that you can change.
And you have a legend.
And one thing that can be very convenient,
which you can show later in the notebook,
is that in order to see what are the different properties
that are available, you can use the help command.
Yes, and it's also nice to know how is this even called?
Like if I want to web search for something,
I really like this figure because then I know
that I need to search for something called
Minotic or Legend.
Yes, yeah, good point.
There's also, yeah, below here on the same webpage,
you also have an extensive listing
on what are these properties in web format.
So, from this paragraph here,
we also have a resource here,
which is, this is a Tor Github repository
with Mac.lib cheat sheets.
So this is something that you can explore later.
There is also a number of predefined style sheets that you can activate with the use
command. We can show some of these. So these are with the different collections of colors
and marker styles and line styles that you then can choose from. And these are designed
so that they have a good, good collection of colors, which is something that is very
important because it is not uncommon that a reader or a viewer of your figures might
have a limited capability to be colorblind, red, green colorblind, or other vision impairments.
And then it's good to have a color palette that works also when you are working in a
gray in gray scale so that you have light. You have that the color range ranges from
lighter up until the darker yeah one like during my PhD one recommendation was always
to print print your plot in black and white on a printer to see how it looks then if somebody
later prints the paper on a black and white printer then later I thought well that doesn't
make any sense anymore because I think nobody's reading papers anymore in paper, people read
it on in a computer. But now again, I know that it does make sense because it can help
us identify any sort of color problems for color vision deficiencies.
So we will now have an hands on example of exercises and styling and I will do it as
as a demo, you will also have time to do
the UND exercise session.
So what we'll do here is that we'll import a data set
from using pandas.
So the exercise is this one,
customization one, log scale in map.lib.
And I will now switch over to do it in the,
in the notebook. So, I start with copying this text snippet here.
And please remind me because I was so distracting answering something. Should we now all do
the same thing as you or should we watch? You can watch.
Okay. Yeah. So, this is now imported a data set. This
is about the statistics of countries. It's the gapminder dataset. And we will then use
a plot command that we go into the plot. It's, we can maybe reconnect to the previous lesson
about pandas. So what people see here is that we load a CSV file from the internet, but then
is this read CSV command,
which we have seen in the previous episode.
And at the same time, there is dot query.
So we filter out and we are only interested
in the data for the year 2007.
And here we have four different countries.
We have the life expectancy,
and we are interested in GDP, the gross domestic product.
So roughly how wealthy the country is.
So, I now take this snippet here and I paste it in here and execute it and what we get
here is that what we choose to work with here is the life expect. We will visualize life
expectancy as a function of the GDP per capita in terms of perching parity. The PPP, what's
Yeah, so it's some like inflation adjusted US dollars that are also adjusted to have
a more fair comparison. So it's not US dollars, but for our purposes, we can think of like
inflation adjusted US dollars.
Yes. And what we note here is that the data is here and distributed so that it's seen here.
a lot of it is along the vertical, along the vertical line here, and then around this horizontal
line here, horizontal region here in uppermost in the plot. So the question is here, how
can we make better use of the visualization to highlight the data here? So do you have
When you suggest another one, what could be?
Yeah, so one step that we can do
is we can try a logarithmic axis, which will then,
because we have such a big difference
in orders of magnitude on the x-axis.
So by switching to, from a linear to a log axis,
it will, we will probably see the trend hopefully clear.
Exactly, so we need then to set the axis scale
to a logarithmic one. And this will do by setting this attribute, the setXScale to log.
that line. And I go to the notebook. And add it there. Set X dot set scale underscore X
scale log. Yes. And now we have the logarithmic scale on the X axis here. And yeah, what we
have here is much more much more evenly distributed within the canvas. There's
also here one attribute, the alpha attribute, that we can play around with
here. So the alpha attribute is at first it's a half. You can see what happens if
If you change it to 0.8, yeah, then you can see that this affects the, the, the transparency
of points.
So by using this higher value, we have a more dense visualization of all the thoughts.
Great.
And a question to both of us.
So do, do you remember all of these things like how to set a log axis, how to, what,
how to do the trust, how to set the transparency? Like I admit that I don't, so I almost never
remember this. I always have to look it up. Yes, that's a good point. And one can then,
so we have here, if you see here, what, what, what are the objects that they've created?
They've created the handle fig and they've created the handle X and the logarithmic scale
is something that is set by working with the axe object.
And let's see what attributes do we have here for this object. So, we can type help and axe.
And then we can see that we have a very lengthy listing. Here's a description of what the object
these, what class it is. And then you can see that we have all of these listings. And
among these listings here, we will have then the logarithmic scale. Or the opportunity
to set a logarithmic scale.
That's neat.
Good.
We will now have,
we will,
not now, so we'll let you go into the exercise session
where you will play around with
customization of figures. And yeah, should we perhaps introduce the exercises. Here it's
working with the same datasets. Your task is that you will make the ticks marks and the
axis labels fonts larger. And you need you can search on the web for what are these attributes
that you need to work with. And the target that you're aiming for is to arrive to a figure
which is looking like this. So this is one of the exercise that you can do. And the second
exercise that you could, oh, we should hide the solution there. The third exercise that
you can work with here is that you can adopt a gallery example. And here we have some links
to some of the other resources that are, yeah, like Seaborn, which is based on Matlocklib.
And then there's also Vega Altair, which is a standalone Python package for visualization.
So people will choose exercise two or three.
And the exercise three is really close to at least how I work in real life.
So in real life, I don't remember all of these commands.
I often look through the gallery examples for something that looks similar to what I
have in mind.
And here you will try to first, I often take the example and I'll try to run it on my computer.
And then once I get it to work, then I try to change the data.
And then I try to put in my data, and then I tweak.
So that can that can be a really fun exploration, which is at least close to how I work.
I don't know about you, Juan, but I can't remember on almost anything.
I always start from something that already works
that somebody else created.
That's also how I do it.
So looking at this galleries
is a very good source of inspiration.
And that's also where you then get exposed
to what are the different functions and attributes
that you can work with.
So is there anything that we can bring up from the HackMD?
For now, I'm looking.
So most questions are answered
and they are relatively detailed.
One bigger picture question was
whether we will talk about interactive plots.
So plots where you can, you don't get just an image
but you get something that you can interact with
like with a slider.
And I believe that we will not do it in this course
but I will link to a lesson where this is demonstrated.
But I think we are almost ready for exercise session.
It will be customization two or three.
Until what time, like when we will be back?
We will take 20 minutes for this exercise.
All right, so we'll be back at 55 past
and then we will summarize,
we will connect this a bit with pandas data frames
and then hand over to the next episode.
So exercise customization two or three starting now,
see you again in 20 minutes.
Bye.
you
All right, we are back.
more minutes of matplotlib. So we want to wrap up the session and then we will go into
a break and then we will go into something else. And we thought that in the five minutes
we could try to do this exploration together on an example. And I also realized now during
the exercise session that the solution that we have listed here doesn't match anymore
perfectly the gallery of seaborne because they changed their examples anyway let's try this
together i will now take seaborne which is something that builds on top of matplotlib
and i will i will take that for a specific reason that i will come back to before the hour is over
so this is often how i start i open up one of these libraries i go to the gallery and i look
look for an example that looks close to what I have in mind.
And here I will, I will take,
I will try to be somehow close to the exercise.
I will, I want to do a violin plot,
which is a way to show distribution of points
and a statistical spread.
And so this is something,
I want to have something like this.
Here, this is what it looks, and there is an example code.
And the way I start often is I take what they have
and I try to run it on my computer first.
Let's try that.
Seaborn is a library that should be in your environment.
It is in the Python for Sarcomp.
It is also a part of Anaconda base environment.
And now I'm crossing fingers and running the cell.
and I get a plot that looks like what they have.
So that's already a big success story.
I don't fully understand what's going on here,
but my next step often is to,
I want to get an insight into the data
because I want to replace it with my own data.
And here I have a feeling that,
so load the example tips data set.
This is some data set about some bird.
No, it's about some smoking and not smoking.
But what I do, because I don't know this data set,
I would often, I would actually split,
split the cell into two.
And here I would print, I can do either this,
or if I'm in a notebook, I can do this directly tips.
I want to see how it looks.
Let's run all cells.
And this turns out to be, we already recognize this.
This is a pandas data frame with columns and rows.
And I think this data set shows
the different tipping behavior of smokers and non-smokers.
And now I also maybe understand that what this library is able to do is that we load
the data set and then we can map X values to a certain column and we can map the Y values
to a different column and we can map the color to a yet different column.
And now I would go in and instead of using this data set, I would try to put in my own
pandas data frame and I will try to plot that and only then I would start tweaking and adjusting
and customizing and here I wanted to show you that Seaborn is a library that is able
to really use pandas data frames directly and map columns to visual channels x y color
Can we do the same thing in map.lib?
And back to our lesson.
And I learned very recently that you can do almost the same thing in map.lib.
So instead of what we were doing, that we were sending a slice, a column of data into
defined as X or as Y, we can use this instead.
I can say the data is a data frame.
And then I can map X values to particular column,
Y values to a different column.
So that's very nice.
If you then try to do a bit more,
like if you try to map color to continent,
then it becomes a little bit harder.
And these are, so we wanted you to know
that there are libraries in Python
that make this easier and this is also for those of you who come from R and ggplot2
you can do the same things in Python with in libraries like Seaborn, Altair, Vega
but I see now that we are out of time
we will continue answering the questions so please keep asking questions about plotting
about Matplotlib and we will continue answering but I don't want to eat into the future sessions
So, thanks from my side, [Name], any concluding words here?
You covered it all.
And as I said, we will continue to answer questions on the HackMD.
Yeah.
More details there, I will answer there.
Thanks so much, everybody, for listening.
Thanks to [Name] for co-teaching and looking forward to the next sessions.
And I think now we go into a break, into a 10-minute break, if I understand correctly.
Yeah, break to 11 past the hour.
Yep.
Bye.
you
Hello, we are back.
So yes, so now for the rest of the day, we have two lessons, one on data formats, which we're not actually going to much detail. We give this really high level summary that addresses some of the questions which people have been asking yesterday and today, and then we go on to productivity tools.
But we did teach this course, or this lesson, in full last year, and you can find it from
the playlist of the course last year, linked from the main page.
So [Name], where do we start with...
Yeah.
So maybe I'll introduce myself.
My name is [name].
I'm from Aalto Scientific Computing, and I've been working with Python for, well, 15 years
at this point or something, so a long time.
So in the chat, in the HackMD, there
were lots of good questions about NumPy and Pandas.
And what it means, like what are the columns in Pandas?
And there were questions about tidy format also,
which is popular in RxTidyBuzz.
And we'll quickly explain these concepts.
But like [Name] said, we had a longer dive on this last year.
So if you want to see that, you should check the video.
but let's teach the main concepts.
So when we're talking about data frames,
like data frames are like,
like I figure out this analog of like a hardware store.
So if you go to a hardware store,
you have like hammers in one aisle,
you have nails in one aisle,
you have nuts and bolts at one aisle
and wrenches in one aisle.
So you have different aisles of different things
and lawnmowers in like,
you can have completely different things in one aisle
and another aisle can have a completely different thing.
This is basically what a data frame is.
So data frame is organized in columns.
So each column has one type of a thing.
So it has integers or it has timestamps or it has strings.
So in the code example there, you don't have to write it.
We have an example data frame that has like strings
and timestamps and integers and floating point numbers.
And all of these can be like
some sort of a correspondence, of course, so you can have like temperature or pressure or something,
or you can, like if we go to the hardware store analogy, if you go down one aisle and you find
a certain kind of a nut and you know that, okay, I need a corresponding wrench to tighten this nut,
then you go to the wrench aisle and you go to that place. In pandas, you usually have the
corresponding things in the same place. So, in the same row, you would have the nuts that
correspond to a certain branch, and then you can easily find the things you're looking for.
And this is basically what a data frame is. So, you have multiple of these columns that
are collected together, and they are collected into this tidy data format. So, below in the
[Name]'s share, we have this view of this tidy data format. So, you have each column
is a variable. So, temperature, pressure, time, I don't know, like it can be whatever.
And in each row, you have an observation. So, at a certain time, the pressure and temperature was
this. And the idea behind this is that if you keep this format, it's easy to write tools
that you work with this format. So you can easily calculate an average. You don't usually
want to calculate average of time, pressure, and temperature. I mean, you don't want to calculate
because that doesn't make any sense. But you want to calculate an average of, let's say,
one column. You want to calculate temperature over time or something. You want to calculate
an average of that. So some operations are written for columns and some operations are
written for rows. And because everybody keeps the same format, it's very easy to manage these tools.
And this is why pandas and similar kinds of things like tidyverse are popular. And this is
important. Even though you might have a table where you just have a table and what does it
matter? Is it organized in what way? It's organized in a certain way because people
expect it to be in that way because all of the tools have been written that way. So, you should
just do it like the other people do. And this is basically how data frames are organized.
And NumPy arrays are a bit different. So, all of the columns are usually NumPy arrays.
NumPy arrays can be multidimensional. They're always one data type, so you might have one
dimensional array like a column, or you might have a two-dimensional array like a matrix
or just an array of numbers or multiple things. But usually you have, let's say, a temperature
in x and y directions or something like that. Or you might have a three-dimensional array
of like pressure at different altitudes and different places in the world.
So in NumPy, you have this one big blob of same kind of data, so organized in this one
blob.
And what does this mean is that, yeah, so [Name].
And like you would do the same kind of operations across every row, column, and rank, I guess.
Yes. So what you would usually do is like you would do, let's say you calculate, you
take a matrix or take an array and then you multiply it by some constant and then you
do it, apply for it, all of them, or you calculate the sum of certain rows or certain columns
or something like that. But, okay, so you have these two different formats and they
are different. They're fundamentally different, but in some sense they are the same, but they
are different. It's very hard to explain, maybe. But the main thing is that for all of these
different things... Sorry? Well, go ahead. Yeah. But for both of these things, they are tools
that are designed around these formats. So, for example, you don't do matrix multiplications in
Pandas. You do matrix multiplications from NumPy arrays because for tables, it doesn't make any
sense to do matrix multiplication. But for array, it makes sense. And there are tools for these,
and then there are ways of storing this data that are designed for these things.
And for pandas, there are many, many tools that are designed, many formats, like file formats,
that are designed for certain kind of data, and for NumPy as well. And usually,
the situation goes like this. You might have seen this XKCD comic, that they are competing
standards, and then somebody's like, okay, let's just write a new standard that fixes all of the
This is not perfect. Let's do something that does what both of these does.
Yeah. And then you have one more. And this is how it always goes. So, you have a huge
amount of competing standards. So, there were people asking about ARDA. If you want to move
data from ARDA to Python, either you can use CSV, for example, or you can use Parquet or Feather.
There's mentions in the article about these different formats. If you want to use Matlab,
you can use math files, which are like these HDF5 files. If you want to use Python and,
let's say, Fortran code, you might need to use HDF5 or use the Fortran file. There's a million
file formats. And, yeah, we don't want to give too long to talk about it. So, let's just say
that they are. And if you want to see more about these formats, there's a huge list here. And more
will be added here as well. And use the formats that your tools use, basically. Choose the file
formats that your tools use and your data is optimized for. Yeah. And I guess you could say,
I mean, talk to people. Like, I guess our main message here isn't use this or don't use that,
but actually do take a little bit of time to think about it before you go too deep into your work.
work.
Yeah.
Yeah, basically.
And do some searching, do some thinking.
The pandas and NumPy, they already have good interfaces for all of these different data
formats.
So, check the documentation, like in this page, there's mentions about it, but check
the documentation on pandas and NumPy.
Don't write your own data reader, because somebody has written it already.
Like somebody has written a CSV reader.
don't need to open a CSV file in Python yourself. You can use NumPy or Pandas to read it based
on what sort of data you have in the CSV file. There's also a question in the chat why Excel
isn't good human readable. Excel is a binary format. Have you opened it with an editor?
But it's a good point, like many of these arguments are complicated.
And what human-negatable means is, yeah, it's a complicated thing.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, maybe we can keep answering these questions by the text, and we can go on.
And if you want more, watch the video from last year.
someone could link it here. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Yeah. We ask questions in the chat. We'll try
to answer as many of them. There's some really good questions there and we'll happily answer them.
So what's next? It's productivity tools. So I will open that.
So [Name], what do we mean by productivity tools? What kind of productivity?
Yeah, so throughout the day you have run many of the exercises already and examples
and you have encountered probably many errors and you have encountered many like when you
have a wrong code you get an error or something in your code and of course when we are talking
about, for example, exercises in this course, these are small programs that you run. But when
you start to write your own program, we'll talk about scripts tomorrow, so a bit more about how
do you write, and also about modules and libraries, how do you write bigger programs. And when it comes
to these, for writing these bigger programs, you usually have the situation where it's a big thing
and you can have errors in multiple places. And we are all humans, so we don't write perfect code.
Nobody writes perfect code and that's completely normal. And for that, programmers and people who
write programs, they have written things that help with the tool, help with dealing these
problems. And well, the most common is like if you have an editor that has syntax highlighting,
like Jupyter has. So if you have...
So it's basically, it's tools that make your human effort more effective.
Yes, so let's say you have a VS code or something and it can give you auto-completion or something.
These are already productivity tools, they improve your productivity when you code.
But there's different colors of productivity tools or different types of productivity
tools and these are the most common ones, of course.
But then there's other tools that are specifically designed to fix certain things about your
programs, or help you fix certain things about your programs.
So for example, let's think about what the Python language is.
So if you want to give a terminal, or Python terminal, and run the first example that
we have there in the code.
So if you try to run what we have in the...
A terminal or Jupyter Notebook?
You can take a notebook as well.
Okay.
Sure.
Yeah.
So...
I have to set a name.
This is a follow along.
You don't need to type in this, by the way.
So each language has a syntax.
So like program language has a syntax.
And sometimes you might do something that is not permitted in that language.
So for example, here you cannot assign true to be one because you're not allowed to change
the true value.
So you have to get a syntax error.
So you have a problem in the syntax of what you have been writing.
Like the programming language doesn't understand what they're doing.
Of course, in this case, it's like a trivial problem.
But if you have a big program and you forget to write one extra bracket or one extra comma
somewhere or something, you get the same syntax error, and it can be really tedious to find
out this, especially if it's at the end of your program.
I guess it's better to know right away rather than have to save it.
And for this reason, people have written these linters.
So they remove lint.
I think that's the name why they have been written.
So they remove extra stuff and bad stuff from the code.
And they can spot these syntax errors.
So some popular linters are this rough i-lint and flake-8.
But for this example, let's try with i-lint, which should be installed in the example.
For example, yeah.
OK, so I'll type.
So in order to open the script, so we'll
talk more about this tomorrow.
Here's what I can do.
I can right click and copy the link.
And in JupyterLab, go to File, open from URL,
and paste the link.
OK, I have to use Control-V. And click Open.
And here it is. So it's both saved the file and has opened it in the JupyterLab here.
Yeah. And this program, usually when you get programs on the internet, when you use code by
other people, or if you write the code, you might write it as a script. Like in this case, it's an
example script. And by quick glance, it looks like Python code. So what's the problem? But let's try
to use PyLint to check if there's any problems here. So, the examples here use the command line.
So, there is possibility of getting these linters working in JupyterLab, but unfortunately,
well, you need to install specific packages for that. And for this example, let's try with the
terminal. So, we're showing from the command line. We think we've made this where if you're using
the Anaconda that should work on all operating systems.
But if not, then take a step back, watch us,
and don't worry.
Yeah, you don't need to run these examples while we are.
So I've made a new terminal here.
And I can scoot this down here.
So it shows I'm in.
Oh, I wanted this to open in the terminal.
If I click plus here, OK, so opening it this way
has put me at the right place where my Python stuff is.
OK, so what do I do?
I try running the lint.
Yeah, let's try running pylint and run the example.
Pylint, lint example.
So I push tab, it filled out the name.
I push enter, and okay, error.
So now we get an error.
So we see that there's first the name of the file, lintExample.py, then we get a line number
4, and then we get a 31.
I'm not certain what the 31 actually is.
I think it's called column 31.
And then we get an error code, like E something, like an error, 0001, parsing failed, unmatched
bracket. So if we now look at line four of the code and scroll down, we notice that there's
an extra bracket there. Well, actually, the JupyterLab highlights it for us. It marks
it as read already, which is nice, and which probably would help you not make this error.
But it's easy to see that, okay, now that we see it, we can remove it.
So let's remove that and save the file.
I remove that.
I save.
How do I save here?
File, save all, I guess works.
And then we rerun the linter?
Yeah, let's rerun it and see what happens.
So here in this terminal, I can push the up arrow key instead
of typing the whole thing again.
Yeah.
So now it's running again.
Why is it so slow?
Yeah, I don't know.
And we got plenty of other errors.
And let's look at these one by one.
So maybe if you can close the tab on the left.
Yes, OK.
So at the top, we see that, okay, on the line one,
we get this C something, missing module doc string.
So, okay, now this is like a code style warning
that you should have in your module,
you should have a documentation string there,
but okay, this is not an error, it's just good practice.
So let's not look at that too much.
On line four, we see, and also on line four,
column 4, line 4, column 19, and line 5, column 4, which is undefined variable np.
So the linter doesn't understand what np is, it hasn't been defined yet.
And this is explained by the last line in the error message, which is that on line 1
we have an unused import NumPy. So we imported NumPy, just import NumPy instead of import
NumPy as NP. So that's why we got this error, but it was hard to spot because it was valid code.
Like it looked valid, but we had a mistake in the code because we did the import wrong.
Should I fix it?
Yes, let's fix it. If you look at also the end of the output for the PyLinter, you see that
it gave a code rating. And the code rating was zero because it knows that, okay, this code won't
run. So, let's give it a zero rating. Like, it's zero out of ten bad code. And now that we have
fixed it, let's try running the linter again. Okay. I save all and push up arrow key again.
So, now we see that it shows that it's still missing the module doc string, so it gives
a code warning on it, but the other problems have been solved, so now it grades it as 8.33
out of 10, and it shows the previous run, so what was the improvement.
And this is, to me, the most fun part of Linter, because it gamifies the coding, like how high
can your score go?
Can you get the 10 out of 10 for the Linter?
And basically, the idea behind the Linter is that it allows you to spot the errors and
fix this kind of coding style and coding problems that you might have in your code before you
even run the code.
So you get coding done faster and you get a better result out of it.
So should we go to the first exercise already maybe, or do we have any questions in there?
There's a good question.
Why can't the linter show all errors to begin with?
So why does it only show the syntax error first?
Yeah, so that's a good question. And I think that is related to,
like, yeah, that's a good question. That's probably how the linter has been designed
internally. There's different kinds of syntax errors. There's egregious ones, for example,
the true equals one, or the brackets. If it doesn't know how to parse the input.
Basically, in the first example, we had the extra bracket there.
So the linter didn't know that, okay, how should I pass this, even this text?
Because I don't understand what's happening here, because suddenly we get an extra bracket
and I don't understand, is this valid code?
It doesn't understand the input.
And in the second example, there's something wrong in the input.
So it's like there's a first kind of an error, which is like, okay, yeah, yeah, it doesn't
understand what, like in the context of the language, it doesn't understand that, okay,
what is NumPy?
Like this hasn't been said before to me.
But of course, like Linter doesn't capture all errors because like we said at the beginning
of the day, Python is strongly typed, but not like not enforced.
So you might modify the things when the program is running in a way that the linter doesn't
know about, and it might not spot those errors, but it will spot a lot of errors.
Like the most annoying ones, the trivial errors, the ones that you are like, okay, I should
have noticed this, it will spot those.
So for our time progress, so we've got 25 minutes left.
recombine two exercises together?
Or?
Yeah.
Yeah, maybe we can.
Or the second exercise is more of a demo, I would say,
anyways.
So maybe we should go to exercise one
and then go to the format.
OK.
So exercise one, and how long do we have?
So should we, yeah, should we take 10 minutes?
It's not that long of a nexus.
45.
Okay.
Yeah.
Great.
So see you in 10 minutes.
Okay.
Bye.
you
.
if you show the exercise code. This is, by design, an example of an error that the linter
doesn't spot. If you look at the code here, it's fairly normal code, but it's so complex
that it's hard to say where the errors are. But the error that the linter doesn't spot
is in the axe scatter, where you have one T instead of two Ts in that line. The reason
why the linter doesn't spot this error is that the linter doesn't actually import anything
when it runs. Like, when it runs, it just checks the code. It doesn't actually, like,
import pandas. It doesn't import matplotlib or anything like that. So, it doesn't spot
that, okay, there's this object that has this attribute that is wrongly named.
So, it's, yeah.
It doesn't import anything or doesn't go fully deep?
Well, yeah. It usually checks like module level stuff. But usually it doesn't go that deep. So,
of course, there's other linters that might spot this, but there are various tools that you can use.
But this is like an example. Linters are no means perfect, but the thing is that they spot
spot a vast majority of the kind of things that humans might not spot, like these kind
of like KVL things.
I guess it's just...
Yeah.
Go ahead.
I was going to say, it's like, it's, it works well with a human.
Like you spot some things easily, but not others.
And the computer spots some things that you don't see well.
Yeah.
And it's a tool. It's a tool that you can use or not use. If you don't like linters,
you don't have to, but then you might encounter errors a bit more.
Yeah.
Okay. But let's move forward to another kind of productivity tool that you can use.
And this is about style enforcement. So Python is very flexible when it comes to
what sort of programming styles should you use? What sort of naming should you use? So
Here's a few examples. You can use different variable naming styles. These are all valid
Python, but they are for the reason that it's flexible. It doesn't enforce it,
but at the same time, it recommends certain standards, Python developers, because then it
makes coding easier to read for other people as well. These major standards are these Python
Enhancement protocols. I don't know what these are called. These PEP.
**JASON LENGSTORF** Yeah, I think it's Enhancement protocols.
**JASON LENGSTORF** Yeah, they're like recommendations for the community.
And the PEP 8 is one of the most popular ones, which is like set standards of how,
like, okay, your code should look like this. And then there's a docstring standard of how
the documentation strings should be written. And different people have different standards.
For example, for the documentation strings, NumPy has its own standard.
and Google has its own standard and different places have their own standards. But what is
usually nice is that you can use these different kinds of formatters and linters to enforce a
certain standard for your code. So I personally, I don't have that many opinions on my code.
I would rather my code be readable than something like, there's this joke about why don't people,
people, if they are in a courtroom and they are asked to tell in your own words what happened
in the situation, nobody just invents their own words, they use the same words that everybody
else uses.
They don't just start gobbling up random words, they use the words that other people
use.
And it's the same thing.
standards that other people use, it makes other people easier to read your code and easier to
write your code. And it's much easier to let a formatter or linter determine the standard than
fix it yourself. So, in the example, let's do the example here. So, we'll use this.
Oh. So, do right here.
Yeah. So, if you download the code here. So, this code looks pretty awful, right?
it's by design, it's supposed to look awful. It works. It's completely working code, but
I don't like it. It doesn't look pretty to me.
It's spacing weird.
Yeah, there's weird spacing, weird variable names, and all sorts of things. It's not pretty.
So let's do it.
Yeah.
copy the link, go to file, open from URL, paste the link, and open. I'm going to move
this to the top here.
Yeah. So, yeah, it works and it calculates this pi estimate using this target method,
but it's...
Yeah.
And it gives like examples there, but it looks pretty awful.
Should I try to run it?
Yeah, you can try to run it. Maybe try it from the command line.
Yeah, so here's Flake.
We'll see more how these scripts work tomorrow, so if this doesn't make sense, don't worry.
Yeah, but the main thing is how can we make it better?
So let's try first running PyLint on it.
Sorry, Flake 8 on it.
Flake 8 is this kind of like linter and code syntax, like checker.
And if you look at what sort of things it gives, it gives various of these, like, okay,
you should fix this and yeah.
And what we can do, of course, is we can manually fix these and it makes the code better.
But we can also use a formatter.
So one of the most common formatters is this black by Python Software Foundation, which
is like this opinionated formatter.
So it has its own style and it wants to enforce that style.
So it's a play on the Henry Ford's, like, you can have the Model T, the car.
Oh, that's where the name comes from.
In any color, as long as it's black, like that famous quote.
So it tries to enforce its own style.
So let's try to run black on this code example.
Okay, so, and I have been black, but it's in the, in the environment, in the, it's in
the code environment.
If you have, if you have installed them, yeah, okay.
Yeah.
Oh, so now it's reformatted it.
So you probably need to open the file again or reload it or.
Is there a reload Python file from disk?
So now we see that things happened.
So if we compare what's at the bottom and what's here, suddenly, for example, between
the brackets, all of the extra spacing is gone.
Some of the spacings are gone and things have been organized in a bit better way.
If you now run the Flake 8 again, Hoyt, let's ask it what it says about this.
So, I just pushed the up arrow key twice there.
Okay.
So, one line too long.
Yeah.
So, it.
Line.
Yeah.
Line five.
So, it says that, okay, usually there's this character limit of 80 characters so that it
can fit into a terminal. You don't have to enforce any standard, but that's common. In
your environment, you probably don't have this pep8 naming package that is in the example
and in the example environments, but it doesn't really matter. But it would give, if you scroll
a bit up.
It's up.
like, there. It would give those warnings. So, the name of the package is a bit above.
But those are warnings. It would give those warnings. So, you can install into Flake 8
these additional style guides. There's a huge amount of these extensions. And one of these
extensions gives warnings about variable names that don't abide by the pet8 convention. So,
example, it would say that the function name should be lowercase and the variable should
be lowercase. So those PI numbers there, because those are basically the standards.
But it doesn't really matter. You can go by the standards that you want to. All of these tools
are meant for you to enforce what you think is good code. But of course, they're also to
to, like, help others read your code, but you don't have to use any of these tools.
But usually, like, at least for me, it, like, gives me a peace of mind that, like, I haven't
written, like, code that looks bad for other people to read, because, like, then it makes
harder for them to use the code that I've written, because it's a collaborative effort,
and that's why people use these formatters and linters.
So here, well, do we have more or should I ask a philosophical question?
Shoot.
So my problem with things like code formatters, so for example this 4.11 here.
To me, how it is now with these spaces.
I would, if I was writing this myself, to me this is clearly easier to read.
Yes.
And, like, the way that things...
So, like, I like the idea, but the implementation...
If I'm running Black on my own code, it's usually making it easier to read in places I don't care about and harder to read other places.
So what I think, and I tend to use this white space a lot
to group things so I can mentally
understand what's going on or align things vertically.
But my proposed solution to this dilemma
is if it's a small issue of my own project,
I know I'm formatting it well myself anyway.
But whenever it's someone else's project,
or if it's a big project, a random contribution coming in
is probably worse than I would want.
So there it's better to make it uniform,
even if the uniform is not exactly what I would want.
Do you have any thoughts on this?
Yeah, yeah, I completely agree.
And I will also mention that there's like,
like what I usually myself do is that I usually pick
the tools I want to use,
like the linters or formaters I want to use.
And then you can, all of these tools,
you can specify different things that they want to do. There's different flags and configuration
parameters. And usually they're like black RC or some configuration file that you can specify that,
okay, don't care about these things. I want you to worry about these things and not these things.
And then you can enforce throughout the project a consistent style, but leaving your own things
there. There's also alternative linters that, for example, fix... Google has its own linter that
fixes these multiplication things. But I agree. The code, the formatters, it's the same with
ChatGPT or something like that. The ChatGPT has seen code and it writes code, but of course,
it doesn't understand code in the sense that humans do. So for us, we might have a different
kind of perception of the code and see some code to be better than the other one,
and more visually pleasing or something. The pattern looks nicer or something.
I don't know how much more time we have, but there's a really good question, number 71,
do linter spot type mismatches. Should we go to the notes now? Are we done with the lesson?
Yeah, I think we're done with the lesson. This is just a quick demo. In the lesson,
there's also mentioned about how you can automatically integrate into this to Git
so that whenever you run a commit, it will automatically run these linters and it will
say to you that, okay, like you have a problem in your commit or something. But, yeah, let's go to
the we can go to the, like, the cool down of that. But the idea behind this, there's huge
amount of these linters and huge amount of these productivity tools. But they are these tools. Like,
that's the most important things. And, like, if you don't know if you feel unsure about your code
And if you don't know how you should write your code and that sort of things,
the formatters and linters can make you write better code because they can help you with
the hard decisions of how should I write my code. And you don't have to worry about the code style
that you're using. You just follow what the linter says. And I personally do that a lot,
because I don't want to think about... I don't have that many opinions, so I would rather...
Like, somebody else has decided the thing already, so it's better to follow their lead.
They probably have good reasons for it. I usually follow that sort of paradigm.
Yeah. Okay. Sorry, I was looking at other things and adding the feedback to the notes.
Did we already answer that do linters detect type mismatches?
Yes. I'll mention that. So, like Python, for example, it's not strongly typed. So,
the types can change throughout the code runtime. But they are like type hints that you can put
into your code. And various programs, for example, or various libraries like NumPy and
Matplotlib and everything, they do this in the code. So then you can, if you write your type
into your code, you can run the static code checkers that basically go through your code,
they run the code, and then they check if the type suddenly changes or if they're incompatible
types or whatever. There are tools for this, and it just depends on how production code you want
to write. Normally, when we write scientific code, it's not necessarily like
you don't have to worry about types that much. But if you write a core library,
if you want to write a library that other people are using, then it might be a good
idea to add a type in. It becomes more easy for other people to use that.
But yeah, like on a normal small program, I don't know if it's necessary to use the type
hints.
Yeah.
It depends on the size of the program and the amount of collaborators as well.
Like if you have thousands, like I think somewhere in Black's website, they said that
there's 20 million lines of code formatted with Black.
20 million?
Yeah.
Formatted?
Formatted, yeah.
In the form?
Yeah.
So there are so many big projects that are using it, like no human would want to do that
code formatting for that job, basically.
I wouldn't want to do it.
I wouldn't want to be a type checker in a big company
checking, is the code looking good?
But there's tools for that.
OK.
Any other comments or things to discuss here?
So, this question 73, I think you can configure many of the linters for own preferences, like
what to ignore, and so on.
Also, [Name], I think you hinted at this, can black be configured to not do certain formats?
Or is it only one?
I think all of them have a huge amount of flags, so usually what you do is you start
But start from the basic configuration
and then you drop out certain things.
So yeah, it's usually like you can skip various things.
OK.
And this question 74, is it possible to use x with tool y?
The answer is usually yes.
but the person you ask usually won't know because there's so many combinations.
So do your own web searches and probably you can figure out how to.
But if you're using any of the popular things like in the question list PyCharm,
but if you're using VS Code, Veeam or whatever, there's like a million extensions that combine,
like [Name] said, tool X with tool Y. And usually you get like a button that
But like, if you press this button, it will run this linter or whatever for your code.
And usually many IDEs, they already come with some of these tools.
Like they will automatically flag you syntax errors and that sort of thing.
But it's important to know that like these tools exist and you can utilize them.
And it's not like cheating, like who cares?
Not like, yeah, it isn't like you did it the hard way.
OK, now you won a medal.
Like coding isn't like a competitive video game
or something.
Like it's like coding is, yeah, you can go the easy route.
Your main work isn't a homework assignment
where if you don't do it yourself, it's plagiarism.
your real work is.
Yeah.
Like, for example, one would think that, for example, like.
We're past the time now.
So if we are done with everything for today,
we might still hang out talking for a little bit.
But thank you for coming.
And if you have more, please fill out
this feedback for today.
it is very important and we always look at it before preparing the next year.
Okay, so what were you saying before? Yeah, I was just saying that if you think about,
the fresco on Sistine Chapel or something, Michelangelo didn't paint the whole thing.
he had a huge amount of helpers planning and doing that painting. Or like David, he had people
helping with the initial steps of the work, like applying a low-layer paint and that sort of
stuff. So coding is a similar kind of thing. The hard things are what you really want to do with
with the code, the easier things of, okay, how do I write this?
You can use chat GPT or whatever, like linters and formatters to help you with
that, getting the idea across and the, you can, you can get the art out of the
marble block, but like, yeah, it's not cheating to use like helper tools.
It's, it's just a way of improving the productivity.
Yeah.
Okay.
Hello, [name].
Any comments on today before we hang up?
I really like this productivity tool session.
It was good to edit.
So I learned new things.
And these are tools I use.
Yeah, the only thing I would want to, like next year,
we have to figure out how do we add it into the Jupyter.
Because, yeah, like just we maybe
need to make the environment so it's already there
something because it's possible to add these into Jupyter as well. So the exercise will be easier to
run without scripts. Yeah, but it's also a good preview for tomorrow since tomorrow we need to do
the script stuff. Yeah, tomorrow we'll have a lot of talk about like scripts and also libraries and
that sort of stuff. And also there was mentioned about software architecture in the chat. So we'll
be talking about that as well. And these productivity tools are, yeah, like [Name] said,
tied to that. But yeah, so should we close out the day? Great. Let's close up. See you tomorrow.
So remember to prepare for day three. There's some news here, which you probably already read.
Remember to give feedback. This session, for example, was a new session, so it would be nice
to hear what can we improve and what would you like to hear more in the upcoming years.
Yeah. Okay. Thanks a lot. See you tomorrow. Same time. Bye.
you