CodeRefinery.org
you
Hello, test 1-2. Can anyone hear us?
Yes.
Well, people on stream, can they hear us?
So, as usual we've got some icebreakers here.
Today, we do a bit more than usual with a command line interface, so you can answer
the size breaker.
This question, I didn't write it very well.
How do you run the same things over and over again, but with slightly different parameters?
So this is like you have 10 different datasets, and you want to run the same code on all of
of them, or you have one data set
and you need to run with 10 different values
of some parameter.
So how would you do that?
OK, there's these other questions here,
which we can try to answer in a bit.
But we have a special guest with us.
So [name], can you introduce yourself?
Yeah, sure.
Yeah, so I'm [name].
I'm based in Finland.
And at the moment, I'm finishing my PhD in computer science.
And I'm also working in industry as a Julia software developer
in a startup for AI.
So yeah, I'm Julia Enthusiast.
And in Finland, I organized this Julia Users Helsinki.
It is a small community of people in Helsinki area, or even outside the Helsinki area,
who want to come together and talk about Julia.
Yeah. And you may wonder, why do we have a Julia visitor here in a Python course?
Yeah. And indeed, I brought the white flag because, you know,
I come in peace and also want to live in one piece.
But I mean, my answer to that is that, why not?
I mean, it's not like one language is better than another
for everything.
But there's all these different things here.
And knowing more about different languages
would have helped me in the future some, or in the past.
But also, the idea is to have role models
of different kinds of career paths.
So [name], can you tell us a little bit about how
you got to where you are now?
Like, what's your background, and how did you like?
Yeah, so my background is more like computer science, signal
process, statistical signal processing, that kind of stuff.
And I was like, when I think when I started doing my master
thesis, I had like the traditional story that I was
doing a lot of coding at the beginning, I was doing in a very
like painful way, like moving files around, and that felt
wrong. So I started like getting more into proper way and got
like more into proper scientific computing, and so on. And
And also, I heard about open source communities, and I was interested in that.
And at some point, Julia came under my radar.
So I heard about this Julia language that was meant for scientific computing and researchers.
And I was pretty interested in it.
But what really sparkled my enthusiasm about Julia wasn't even the technical features of
Julia.
Because at the beginning, I didn't know anything about it.
I didn't know why it was good.
I didn't know about internals or multiple dispatch or metaprogramming or whatever.
What was cool is that it was beginning 2020.
I had started my PhD and as you probably remember, COVID had also started, so I was stuck in
my room and I joined the Julia Slack.
And then it was pretty cool to see how everybody was very friendly, how everybody was very
active.
And I was seeing famous people, like people of popular Julia packages, who were sitting
there answering my dumb questions and getting me step-by-step, so it was more this community
feeling that really got me into open source, so I sticked to Julia.
Then I actually started writing documentation, so I was in this Google Summer of Docs for
writing documentation, and I started building a web page for a couple of libraries, and
writing documentation for libraries. And then I was twice in this Google Summer of Code
program, like doing more Julia programming. And after that, I also found a job as a software
developer, Julian, like a startup through like people I knew in the Julia community.
And I have, of course, like been using Julia in my research also for like for my PhD and
for my own research. And yeah,
Julian is a pretty new language, right?
Yeah, we celebrated the last year's 10 years of Julia
There was this a heck MD kind of a yearbook where you could design your experience of 10 years of Julia
so it was I think the first commit was from 2009 and the first
Public release was from 2012 and it achieved the version 1.0 at the 2018
it was developed at MIT and
And the goal of Julia was to solve this so-called two-language problem.
So, you know, you encounter this problem that you start writing in Python,
and then you hit some performance bottlenecks, because Python is an interpreted language,
and then you needed to rewrite it in C.
Or also, people who use Python, actually, under the hood, TensorFlow is written in C.
Or a lot of libraries are written in C or Python.
Sorry, in Cython, I meant, not Python.
So whereas in Julia, the power about Julia is that it allows to prototype and achieve
performance in the same language. So the magic word here is multiple dispatch,
and there's a very inspiring talk like the unreasonable effectiveness of multiple dispatch
from JuliaCon 2019, which explains how it achieves both dynamicity and performance.
Okay. Interesting. Okay, so we're almost where we need to begin the next lesson.
Anyone have any questions for [name]? If you do, please write down there.
there. So [name], there's something I always ask people. So what do you know now that you
wish someone had told you at the start of your career?
Yeah. So what for like more like my open source career, like being involved in the Julia community,
like one thing that I really wished people like told me before, which I learned kind
of my experience is that you really don't need to be scared to start and you don't need
to ask permission. That's a good thing about open source. Also, at the beginning, when
I started, I was a bit shy. I was like, okay, maybe a first prototype in closed repository.
Should I open it? Will people just say it's dumb or will people steal my job or stuff
like that, but this doesn't happen in open source, at least not in Julia communities,
like a reasonable size for it not to happen.
So just put your code out there and don't be afraid.
The best way to get the answer is not to ask the question, it's to post the wrong answer.
So just put your code out there, put your work out there, and people will help you.
You don't need to be afraid of that.
And actually, similarly applies to research, at least like in my field, I don't need to
worry that much about scooping.
So it's pretty cool that also research
I can put my code and my work out there publicly
and I just meet new people.
So that, and maybe other quick thing about
is that open source is not about code, it's about community.
So we have already a lot of people coding in open source
and of course the more the merrier,
but we also need the non-technical people in open source,
people helping with writing documentation,
people helping with bringing people together,
people helping with improving diversity
inclusion. So open source is really not about code, but it's more about community. And as I mentioned,
like, I got, like, sparkled from truly not because of multiple dispatch, which I didn't know what it
was, but because of people friendliness. So, yeah. Yeah. Okay. Great. Thanks. And I can also
say about what [name] said about putting your code out there. If you want to be hired somewhere,
like whenever I'm looking to hire people, having public code and saying that,
like being able to see things, that's a huge benefit there.
Okay, but now we need to get started.
Thanks for visiting.
Yeah, last thing, if you are in Finland, we have every month in Helsinki,
this Julia Helsinki meetup, except not this month,
but the next one is going to be on the 13th of December,
and it's gonna be especially for beginners about Julia, so we're gonna be like intro about Julia
and about how to use Julia research and teaching. I also put in the notes, so 13th of December. It's
not official, it's not even on the website yet, but I can give you the spoiler of this. Congrats
and hope to see you there. Yeah, okay, great, thank you. Yeah, thank you for having me. Bye.
Okay, bye.
So, with that said, I guess we should get started for the day.
Yes, so the first lesson is [name] and I.
Hello, [name], have you already introduced yourself? I think so.
I don't think so. I think this is my first appearance this year.
So yeah, I'm a research software engineer at Arthur University, working in [Name]'s group
and in general interested in programming.
In general. Okay, so what's our first lesson of today?
The first lesson of today will be scripts, so going from the
Jupyter Notebooks more into a command line area, and kind of
the very, very first step to make code really reusable without
modifying the code itself.
And that's related to this first icebreaker or second icebreaker
question here.
How do you run the same thing over and over, but with slightly
different parameters, like the same code with different data.
So should I share my screen and we
can get straight to the lesson?
Yep.
Sounds like a plan.
I will push a button here.
And it transfers.
I adjust that.
OK, so as a reminder for the schedule
Coming to scripts here, I open this.
So what does the word script even mean?
To me, script means a kind of self-contained, very small
program that doesn't have a lot of interactions yet,
but that's just some very small thing.
It can call additional libraries, but in itself,
it doesn't provide a lot of code.
That's what I think of when I'm talking about a script.
When it gets more complex, I would rather
talk about a program.
So is this lesson really about scripts or programs or?
I think both.
Yeah.
I guess how it's about the transition
from different systems of using code.
Yes.
And exactly.
So the point is, this lesson, so far we've
been showing things in Jupyter.
So basically, you can click and run things
in whatever order you want.
So now that we have scripts here,
we'll be able to plug our code into other things
a little bit better.
Yeah, or at least we will be able to rerun our code
with different parameter sets without actually modifying
the code.
Because if you're modifying a Python script or the Jupyter
notebook by editing your initial conditions or the source
files or whatever.
You're always modifying the code.
Yeah.
OK.
So up here, there's the section on why scripts.
So if you had to convince the people listening here
that you should consider making a script or a program out
of your code.
Well, the main reason, I would say,
It very often comes down to, I have a certain pipeline
that I've developed for one example.
And now people want to use this pipeline
for multiple different data sets.
Of course, if I have that in a Jupyter Notebook,
I can, every time, change the Jupyter Notebook,
change the input variables, and run it for their data set.
But that needs me to do it again, and again, and again.
And I will likely do typos and whatnot in there.
So I'd rather have some kind of folder
where I have the data sets, and I
want to go through all the files in that folder.
And potentially, I want to run this on a cluster or something.
Yeah, that's a good way to say it.
Some people come and want to use our cluster to run tens.
They have hundreds of input data sets.
Let's say I have this Jupyter Notebook.
How do I run it on 100 different things in parallel?
That's sort of hard.
But if you make a script out of it, then we can make a thing that
extremely easy to just run it with 100 different input
parameters.
Yeah.
And that's where scripts or the transition to Python scripts
from a Python notebook comes in.
So we have two exercises prepared for today.
The first one is coming up shortly.
So it's just about converting a Python notebook or a Jupyter
notebook to a Python script.
Yeah.
I guess here's our short-term road map.
So I will do a demonstration of converting a notebook
to a Python script.
And then you'll have five minutes to try this yourself.
Then we'll come back, talk, demonstrate more,
and then there'll be a much longer exercise
where you can finish up number one and try some more things.
Does that sound good?
Yeah, at least to me.
because that's what we're going to do.
OK, so I'll show my JupyterLab here.
So yeah, essentially, it should be.
So this is the instructions here.
Should we go to the exercise and show?
Yeah, you can also just download it now.
Okay, so I'll use the same trick I used before. I will right click here and do copy link
and come into JupyterLab and do file open from URL and paste it here.
And it both downloads it as you see on the side here and it's opened it in JupyterLab.
Should I try running it to show that it works?
Yes.
Okay, there we go.
Okay, and now you essentially want to export this into a Python file.
The easiest is just going to File, Save and Export Notebook as.
So, this will download it to my computer?
Yep.
And not save file as, save and export.
File...
Further down. Save and export.
As executable script.
Executable script.
Okay.
But this is downloaded, and where is it now?
Yeah.
Okay.
So, another, I suppose we also do, we try it from the command line here.
So I think that what I'm about to show will work for more people.
I'll go to file.
Or at least it's easier that way.
launcher and from the new launcher I start the terminal and I see this is the directory where
I'm doing course things. So this may be the first introduction to command line for some people.
So for some people this may seem impossibly hard and for some people will be impossibly easy.
That's just sort of how it goes unfortunately. So if it's too hard take this lesson as a demo
and work slowly and come back to it later now that you're inspired.
That's all I can recommend. So I'm copying this line here and I will paste it.
And for me ctrl shift v works. I think just ctrl v might do something.
Ctrl v actually does work.
Anyway, so if I run this, then it converts it.
So it says it's writing data to weatherObservations.py.
You can try if it works.
If I open the file browser, I see weatherObservations.py here.
if we come here, we can try running it this way. Python.
Oh, it looks like it ran. Yeah, and if you now type ls or dir, depending on the operating system,
you see that there is a weather.png being created. It wasn't there before. Let's come
come back to the file browser, and we see weather.png.
And if I click on this, I see it.
The same image that was generated before.
The same.
OK, so it showed it.
It was also generated from the notebook,
but it was updated, as you can see.
It was created seconds ago.
OK.
It actually works.
So, let's give our, sorry for the videos hiding, well I would say let's give our viewers
five minutes to just repeat this again and see that that works on their machine.
So we'll give you five minutes, yeah, if things go horribly wrong then
Then, well, we're sorry,
something's gone wrong and sit back and do this as a demo.
Thanks. Five minutes. See you shortly. Bye.
you
And there we should be back on track.
And now coming more to what the actual use is of doing this
and putting it in a script.
Yeah.
So reading through the notes, there's
some different problems here.
And this is sort of, I mean, this is expected.
So of course, we don't want problems.
But there's always some places where
like someone's own computer is different,
or with different operating systems,
or I have a feeling that there is some cloud service which
is not working and doesn't provide shell access.
And this is, well, yeah, in that case.
Not much we can do about that, especially
if Jupyter is run on a web service,
then it's mostly out of our control, unfortunately.
Yeah. So if it doesn't work, just watch.
Okay.
Or if it doesn't work, what I would suggest is you download the file,
copy the data from the file into
a new file that you call .py
because it mainly is exactly the same.
But that Jupyter Notebook is mainly Python code.
And doesn't contain a lot of other stuff.
Yeah.
OK.
So let's continue.
Yeah.
So the nice thing with having this as a script
is that we now have access to command line arguments.
So if you run this from the command line like [Name] just
did when he was in the terminal, we
can add additional information in.
And that information is accessible inside the code
via the sys.argv, or via the sys object and via sys.argv.
And it's interesting to know that the first value,
so this argv stands for argument values.
The first argument value is always the program,
or the script name that you're calling,
because it's actually the arguments to Python
that you're getting there.
Yeah.
So basically, I could run something
like Python weather observations, as an example.
Hello.
Hello.png.
And the code can figure out that this hello.png is
where I should save the figure.
Needs to be modified accordingly, but yes.
So from the command line, we have a and b arguments.
And from the code, we have it accessible as ARCv1 and ARCv2.
So should I do it?
Yes.
The example I'll go also adds the time range,
because we are looking for something
with weather observations that maybe we
want to change what times we actually want to look at.
But yeah, we can also first just change it
so that it just changes the output name.
So I will come, I will open the script itself.
So here, the icon is a Python script thing.
So I double click this, and I've opened now weather.py.
And I see the script.
So it looks a lot like the Python code in 1,
in 2, where the cells were.
So what do I change?
So if you want to change that, the first input argument
is the we will depart from the code that's
in here a little bit at the moment,
just to make people aware of that.
So if we want to have the first input argument as the output
file name, then we would need to go to, essentially,
to the end of the script, where it says fig.savefig.
Well, let's do what it shows here in the screen share.
So OK, then, the first thing we need to do
is we need to actually import the system information.
And that's just to know that, OK, now
we can access this system information.
It's a package that's always available in Python
because it's a basic package.
But we still need to import it so that we
can access the information.
And so now, if you're watching, if you're still
working on the exercise, stop and just listen to us.
So that's what I'd recommend.
We will change it so that we can set the start and end
for always the first and second argument.
Arguments are always,
command line arguments are always separated by spaces.
So the first in that instance actually is number one
because zero, as we said before, is the script name.
So that's sysargv1.
And the second and the end date would be sysargv2.
And then we want to have the third argument
being the output file name.
And we can either directly say here, sys.arcv3,
or we can create a variable in between that indicates
the output file name.
OK, here we go.
I've saved it.
And if you now go back to the terminal.
Terminal.
So Python weather observations from the 1st of March, 2021,
the end of May.
Let's see.
Did it work?
Let's come back to the file browser.
And I see there's an image now called Spring in Tapiola.
And it looks different, for sure.
And it's still quite cold and dirty water.
It doesn't look that bad, though.
Actually, there's something odd here.
Might be that the data actually doesn't contain the March part,
because it only starts at somewhere beginning of May.
OK, so yeah.
OK, so now what do we get from this?
Well, we get the option that we can now essentially modify
or call the same code, but use different input variables
without going back into the code and modifying the script.
So you can run this script multiple times
with different input parameters.
That has the advantage that you can essentially
call it from some other tool, or you
can call it in another script and can automatically
call it with a list of things, making it a bit more
robust to potential changes.
Yeah.
So now, before we go to the exercise,
there's a little bit more.
So here, what we've done in this code is very basic.
So we're just using the system directly.
But there's more advanced modules to do this.
So what can you tell us about that?
Well, there are a lot of so-called command-line argument
parses.
All of them have their advantages and disadvantages.
Essentially, the more complex stuff you want to do,
the more complex code you have to write in the end.
For simple programs, I think ArcParse
is quite efficient, because it doesn't need a lot of details.
But it's not as flexible.
So if you have some requirements where, yeah,
you can have requirements that just are not
achievable with ArcPars.
All of these parsers commonly give some kind of positional arguments or named arguments.
Named arguments help you to, if you have multiple arguments and you have some default values,
you don't want to have to make sure that, okay, position one is always that, position
2 is always that and always have to check okay is it the right thing but you can essentially write
okay in the end or you can in the end write um whether observations by minus minus
start date and give the start date minus minus end date give the end date minus minus
um output file or output file name or something and the output file name um making the
the command line arguments or the command line call
that you give a lot more readable and a lot less prone
to, oh, that was the wrong position.
Yeah.
So I believe the next exercise is
having you try to modify this weather script to do
what we just demonstrated and also use ArcParse.
Let's see.
Yes.
So there's some, well, it's up to you what you work on.
So you can keep working on the first part if needed.
You can try to do what we just did.
You can use ArcParse if you want and have extra time.
Then there's another exercise at the very bottom which we won't talk about but you can try working on it now.
Okay, should we go to the exercise now?
I think so, and when we come back we'll quickly discuss a few more details.
Yes, so this is 15 minutes, so a relatively long amount of time.
Okay, great.
So see you at 45.
Okay, bye.
you
Hello, we're back.
So let's see.
So from the note, it was clear there were lots of different problems in here.
that's sort of that's unfortunate but I mean it's this really is a pretty
interesting and difficult thing because this is the first time we're going from pure Python
to going and connecting to the bigger operating system you're running on and there's so many
different variations there there's things like can't access pandas for example so that means
your Python on the command line is running in a different environment from that on the
the... Python on the program, yeah.
So if you're having really big problems here, don't give up. So take it and basically
Basically, go to one of your colleagues who can sit there with your screen and ask, okay,
so I'm trying to do this lesson.
Can you tell me what's going on here?
And you can get some help that way, and it will work much better.
As long as you sort of understand the general idea of what we've done here, and why these
scripts should be used, then you've gotten to the main points.
So with that being said, what have we learned here in the end?
Well, I hope we have learned that you can,
by changing the notebook into a script or into pure Python,
use command line arguments to modify
what your program does without modifying the program's code.
And yeah, I think I would call it program, because in the end,
this is exactly what kind of distinguishes things.
Here, if you have command line arguments,
that's something that you kind of always
have to call a program with.
Because any other part is self-contained,
but a program you can call with different arguments.
Yeah.
So if someone comes to us and wants
to run some code with a program on our cluster
on many different input files, how would we approach that?
That depends a little bit.
So if the input files have a certain naming convention
or are just numbered, then it's relatively simple
because you can essentially just go through the numbers
and have a for loop in a batch script
where you, with that for loop, call the individual files
or call your script with the individual files as file names.
If they are not ordered in a specific way,
you probably need to either provide
a file that contains the file names
and you read those in or you might go into well either write an additional python script or you
or you provide a or you change your your script so that it reads in a certain file and if
or a certain folder and goes through the folder but if each each of the computations is quite
expensive so you can't just do this in one python script or it would take ages but you want to
parallelize the computation, you will likely
write some additional script that
loops through those files, and then provides them
as inputs for your script at the end.
And those inputs are then run individually,
and each use one job on the cluster.
Yeah, so there is no clear this and that because it depends a lot on your situation.
But one thing that happens quite regularly is that people have input parameters and want
to go through, let's say, a thousand different input parameters that they have more or less
predefined.
have them predefined, they can, in the script, define them once.
And then the input parameter, or the command line argument,
would be the position of that parameter
in the list of parameters that they have defined.
And each run will take one input parameter set, for example.
Okay. So with that being said, should we go to a break?
I would
give a few more words about
additional options like using configuration files
because I think the problem with
command line arguments is that at some point the command line string gets
It's really long.
And even if you have an argument parser or something,
it becomes not really well-readable anymore,
the individual call.
So we are running out of time.
So please continue, but let's try to be quick.
And I just want to mention that there are then
methods that you can have a look at later on
to write the configurations for your program
into a configuration file and use that as and just be given a configuration file as input argument
that is then parsed. That's just what I wanted to mention. Yeah, so like here for example we've
defined all the parameters for the plot and it can be generated. Okay, great. So let's take a break
until two minutes past the hour and we'll see you back for the next episode. Thanks and bye for now.
Bye-bye!
you
Hello, welcome back from the breaks.
So we'll now move on to something about the library ecosystem, how the Python libraries
are set up.
And also after that, we'll move on to dependency management.
[name], have you introduced yourself already?
Yeah, I introduced myself yesterday.
Have you?
Yes, so my name is [Name].
So disclaimer, I'm not a Python programmer,
but I support users on our high-performance computer
systems.
My current job is as the manager of the Norwegian AI Cloud.
But I also contribute to Code Refinery and Alto
and all the partners when I can.
So this library ecosystem, [Name], is
that when you want to achieve a certain task,
somebody might have already made some code
that you can achieve the thing you want to do.
So instead of you try to write it again,
you could reuse others' work.
In the first introduction, there was this interview
with the student.
So when we study, it seems people tell you
not to take others' work.
You have to do everything yourself.
But when you come to the real research,
practically, you can't do, quote, everything you want.
For example, if you want some matrix transformation
or Fourier transformation, some array sorting kind of thing,
it's already there out there.
So you have to use them.
So we will talk about how to reuse work.
So this is not like stealing other people's work.
This is actually reusing and collaboration.
Do you use a lot of libraries, [Name]?
Yes, all the time. So I would say that why Python is so popular, especially in scientific
context, is because of this library ecosystem. Python is not the perfect language for scientific
computation, like what, for example, [name] said at the Icebreaker session this morning, that
there are languages that are designed for scientific computing. Python is not one of them.
But Python is a very general language. It has all kinds of things. And the library ecosystem
makes it possible to have various things. So, like [name] said, in a job interview or something,
you might be asked to do a quicksort algorithm or something. But I would never trust my own
algorithm compared to something that is in a library ecosystem that has been validated by
hundreds or thousands of users. So yes, I use a lot of libraries all the time. I don't want to
reinvent the wheel if somebody already has perfected it. Correct. So if you were there
in the first day when [Name] and [Name] were introducing some beautiful introduction to the
course. So [Name] asked from [Name], when did you start using Python? And I know for a fact that
Yano is a very heavy user of this Python.
But he has to think a little bit.
When did I actually use Python?
So that's a very important thing that you mentioned, [Name].
That means Python itself is not a very useful part of it.
It is just what people made out of Python.
So earlier, if you remember that,
I don't know when you were young how you learned programming.
they taught us pseudocode, you know,
and you had to learn how the programming tactics
in order to actually write a big,
by the time you end up writing some code,
you have learned about a semester of,
you know, what programming is.
So this Python made it more democratic.
It doesn't matter where you come from.
We have come from biology, mathematics,
space science, or whatever it is.
You can just start achieving something.
So that achievement comes from the library ecosystem, as you said.
Yes.
And also I would add here that, like, for example, my first start in Python,
when I started working on it, I was in a summer job in Aalto University, actually.
And I had to convert a code that was using Python numeric, which was
this really old library, to NumPy.
So I had to convert this code that used this old library to a new library.
And the reason behind is that NumPy, like we have spoken already, underneath it, it's
C and Fortran, like underneath it.
But nobody wants to touch that part.
Like nobody wants to see that part because it's harder to write and more laborious to
write.
It's much easier to work with the NumPy.
And that's why like Python is so popular.
You can write these like other things on top of other things.
So at the bottom, you can have the C stuff and the Fortran stuff and that sort of thing,
but you don't ever have to necessarily touch it.
You can just interact with Python things and that's fine.
And that still gives you most of the speed that C and Fortran would give, but much more
usability.
Correct.
So it is not the time you first tried the Hello World, you know, it's not the Python
usage.
People actually use Python when they use a library and do something.
So that's why people think a little bit,
when did I actually use Python?
So it's not the Python hello world print,
it's actually the libraries ecosystem.
And then it is very nice that we have placed
all these terms in the same screen
because taking them alone,
libraries, packages, and dependencies,
sometimes it's hard to sort of comprehend
what this is about.
So I like to think of libraries as like a screwdriver.
you can it's it's not like well documented or well sort of made for like there's no big description
of how to do it but people who know how to use it they know how to use it but the package is more
like a tool set with a set of screwdrivers and there are some instruction and there are different
different gauges, different lengths. So you have this difference. So is that a good way
to look at it, these libraries and packages? So how do you look at it?
Yeah, like libraries, when we talk about libraries, we can often mean multiple things. So for
example, like library can be, like usually everything in Python is a module also. Like
I'm not completely certain what module means in the context of Python, because it's used
so many places so that it becomes a bit more like, like it's used so often that it loses
the meaning.
Like if you say a certain word enough, you don't know what it means anymore.
But usually like libraries are like, libraries and modules, they can be a bit like all over
the place, unless they have been like packaged together and made into like a complete set
of like tools.
and like usually when we talk about packages, we mean that there's like a bunch of code and
you don't want to look what necessarily what's inside of it if it works correctly. But you want
to interact with that code with certain like functions or objects or certain things that it
presents you. So, for example, like you NumPy arrays have a lot of like hidden things inside
of the hidden attributes and that sort of thing. But you don't want to work with those because they
are inside the package. You want to work with the functions that the arrays present you or what the
developers of the package present you. So, you want to only deal with the outermost layer of
the package because that's what the developers of the package want to give you. And that's how it
usually goes, that you have an outermost layer of nice things that you can use and inside there's
a whole mess of stuff. But you don't necessarily need to worry about that because that's the
the packet manager's problem, or developer's problem.
Yeah, you are presented with an easier interface
for what you want to achieve.
And when it becomes dependencies,
it's also like libraries and packages.
If you are building something, let's
say if you were to build a table,
you need nails and bolts.
So these nails and bolts are sort of like dependencies.
So the table could not be made without those things.
And then these nails, they are specific length, type,
and gurge, you know, not all nails will fit all joints.
So there are, when it comes to dependencies,
it's about other things that you need to,
for your code to work.
And also there are some specifications
that we will go on later on.
And then we talk about this sci-fi,
scientific Python ecosystem.
This is maybe the ecosystem most of the research community,
they get, they would think that they start using Python, you know, when they start using this.
So we have this NumPy, SciFi, Matplotlib, Panda for data structures, you know, Panda could,
when people work, researchers work with data, it could do wonders, they get, you know, really amazed
how Panda could help them, you know, they could scrape web pages for tables, they could create
data frames and then you have the NumPy with all the optimized array functions and all the
mathematical functions there. So this is kind of the ecosystem that people start actually
interacting, not all people, but researchers that we interact with. And yes, [Name]?
Yeah, and I'll just mention quickly that also this ecosystem is highly influential to other
packages. Yesterday, there was questions in the chat, for example, about Bollars or Dusk, which
are built upon pandas, but do pandas more efficiently or more in parallel or something like
that? But they usually build upon the syntax and the ideas behind these packages. So there are
lots of packages that do the same thing again, but they try to reuse as much of the language that
NumPy and Pandas and Matplotlib. They do similar kinds of things, but they might do it a bit
differently or better or something like that, or efficiently or in parallel. But they usually
reuse the language. They reuse the same kinds of concepts. So if you learn these core concepts
around the NumPy ecosystem, you can then transfer them to other things or in other ecosystems
or in other tools that use this?
Yes. So in addition, there are other packages like scikit-learn.
This is not like an exhaustive list here.
So this is a part of it.
So if you're doing some classification machine learning,
even scikit-learn is using these packages.
And if you extend things like PyTorch has an optimized version of NumPy
by manipulations for machine learning related operations.
And the rest is really similar.
This is for people to read about the packages.
So I would not spend time on reading through this
because I think the next lesson of dependency
we can talk a little bit more.
Only thing before I give it to you, I want to mention
is this connected to Python to other languages,
because we'll talk about Conda, for example, next.
So connected to other languages, the library
that we were talking about, NumPy, is a good example.
So there are certain things Python, they could do it,
but there are other programming languages like C
could do it better.
For initially, when the code you write,
it could write on your laptop, run on laptop.
But if you want to go to a high-performance computer
system, or a bigger server, or to achieve bigger things,
you have to use the resources optimally,
and also to understand the underlying hardware.
For example, how wide is your processor's registry width,
for example.
That kind of things we don't worry about when
you do Python programming.
So Python provides these libraries.
Behind the scenes, they use C or Fortran or other languages.
For example, [Name] slightly mentioned
that you have this one data, one program that you want
to introduce different data sets.
So we call this the SIMD, single instruction multiple data
kind of work.
So those are better done in other languages than Python.
But you don't have to learn all those things.
You only need to learn how to call those.
So if you want to do some vectorization, for example,
if you have a loop that goes through 10 things,
you could do Python loop.
But if the loop is going through 100,000 things,
you don't want to go through the 100,000 steps one by one.
You want to go 100 steps at a time or 1,000 steps at a time.
So those kind of things we call loop vectorization
could be handled by this code, but you could still use them inside your Python environment.
Is there anything else that you want to mention here before I give it to you?
Yeah, I'll quickly mention this last chapter about evaluating Python packages.
So how do you know what is good? If you go to GitHub, there's like a million packages.
And there is no single way of determining what is good or something is bad. What I usually do
is like, let's say our user wants to solve a certain problem and they wonder if they should
re-implement an algorithm or if there already exists an algorithm that does it. I try to find
with the corresponding keywords, like a git repository or something in GitHub that would
provide such a package. And then I look for various factors, like is there a community around
this package? Has it been validated scientifically? Is there papers published from the package?
Are there lots of stars? When was the last commit? These sort of things. You need to usually check
what is the community around it? Is it a trustworthy source? Is it some random guy
somewhere? Can I actually myself validate it? Of course, I cannot validate, let's say, NumPy. I
I don't have time to read the whole source code,
but if it's like one page long,
maybe I can see what it does.
And these sort of things, there's various factors.
And here's some questions that you can ask yourself
when you're trying to validate.
And I would say that it's always a good idea
to first look if somebody else has done it
and maybe check if you can extend upon it.
Like, for example, many frameworks,
like, for example, Scikit-learn,
they provide a very comprehensive way
of extending their own things so that you can,
like if you write the way they write,
they're like models and that sort of thing,
you can reuse all of the other tools that they provide.
And then you don't have to like figure out
how to do like a cross-validation
or something like that yourself,
because you can use the algorithm
that they use for cross-validation
for your model or something like that.
So it's usually a good idea to check
what the packages provide, how to extend.
Usually there's like a development document somewhere
where they say that, okay, how to extend these packets.
And then they provide like guide
on how to write my own stuff
on top of already existing library.
And it's usually not that hard.
It's usually much harder to start something from scratch.
And of course, sometimes it's needed,
but a lot of times you can build upon
what other people have done.
Yes, so I will only comment about the security part
because you mentioned the list,
there could be malicious packages as well.
So there is trust, so research is based on trust actually.
So when you use a library,
especially if the library concerns like web security,
for example, you can't just use a,
just because it's doing the thing what you do,
you need to have a proper understanding
of what it actually do.
And also there could be malicious libraries,
misspelled malicious libraries.
you have NumPy and you like NumDy or something,
just to elude you.
So you have to be a little cautious as well.
Then I think we should go to the next lesson
about how we manage dependencies.
Yeah, yeah, let's jump to that.
So I'll take the screen share.
If [Name] can then switch to mine.
I'm working on it, something.
Yeah.
No worries.
So, the question here is, like, we've talked about library ecosystem, and libraries are
all fine and dandy, but quite often you have a case where you want to install certain libraries
for your code.
Like, you want certain kind of a situation, and the ecosystem is so big, like the whole
Python ecosystem, there's probably hundreds of thousands of packages available for different
Python versions and different kinds of different installations, different dependencies and
different things.
And they are not compatible all at the same time.
You cannot install Python, I mean, the whole Python.
It's impossible.
There's so many packages.
You cannot have everything in one installation.
So that brings to mind that, okay, how do you manage installing multiple things at the
same time for different projects?
How do you manage that you get the correct dependencies for certain projects?
And there are two major players in this thing, and they are the Python Packaging Index and
Anaconda.
So they are the major things.
So here's a big list of what is the difference between Python Packaging Index and Anaconda.
I can try to say it in short form.
So Python Packaging Index is this community-like project that basically provides Python packages
as these so-called wheels, like wheels of cheese, because everything in Python is a
multi-python joke, but it provides packages as these, like you have Python package as
one file that you can download from this Python packaging index. These are often used in conjunction
with these virtual environments. They don't have to be installed into virtual environments,
but they're quite often used so that you can have your own small Python world where you
install only the packages you need from the Python pip package. And this is very good.
And it was originally developed for sharing Python code. So, Python code written in Python.
But like we talked already, much of the Python code is not written in Python. There's underlying
layers that are written in C. There might be dependencies. So, for example, NumPy uses these
plus linear algebra libraries to run the matrix operations and that sort of stuff.
So it uses underlying libraries that are not part of Python.
They are not written in Python, they're written in Fortran and C.
Providing these is a bit of a complicated thing for the
for the 2T packaging index.
So what they do is that they basically
put everything into these wheels,
and then they provide everything with you,
which can result in very big installations quite often.
And it's a bit complicated there.
How do you share non-Python code?
There is a lot of packages that provide that,
but it's a bit complicated.
Writing these packages is pretty simple.
Like you can easily write your own bit packages.
We'll talk about it tomorrow.
There will be a session on packaging your code.
So writing these is pretty simple.
Like how do you write them?
And then you can publish them
in the packaging index yourself.
And if you're writing Python code
that depends on other Python code.
So for example, you write your own thing
that depends on other Python things
or other libraries like NumPy and that sort of thing.
it's very easy to share it in Python Packaging Index
and use pip to install it.
So pip is the installer tool
for Python Packaging Index packages.
The other major player is conda.
And conda is basically like a solution to the question of,
okay, like we have so many of these different dependencies
or different packages and they might not work together.
So how do we like, how do we make certain
that we get like a consistent working environment.
And the Anaconda Incorporated,
which used to be Continuum Analytics,
now it's Anaconda Incorporated,
they developed this tool called Konda,
which basically is a packaging installer.
And then they provide it in this Anaconda installation.
So they provide like a wide bunch of already existing tools
in one installation, which is this Anaconda installation.
Many of you probably already use it,
which contains, like, it was basically designed
for data science people or people in banks
or something like that.
Like, you get one installation that contains
a lot of already good stuff,
but it has moved beyond that.
Like, the project has moved beyond that
because the community thought that,
okay, like, we want more packages there.
We want more packages.
We want more things.
like we don't want to be all dependent on the Anaconda Incorporated. So what happened is that
Anaconda also provides their own Anaconda.org, which is this packaging index for Conda packages.
And you can have your own channels there where you can provide your own packages.
And some of these channels are now bigger, like the CondaForge, which is this open source channel,
is a lot bigger than the channels provided by the Anaconda Incorporated.
But basically, it's a different world. And what Conda does is that it can manage all of these
low-level dependencies as well. So it can install you compilers and tools and different kinds of
linear algebra libraries. And especially when it comes to CUDA, like GPU programming,
it can install you the correct CUDA toolkits, which are these GPU libraries that your code needs.
So it can try to manage this dependency thing. But of course, it's very complicated because
there's a huge bunch of these libraries and different combinations.
Is it correct to say that the Python package index, PPI index, the things you install in Python
with PIP is more or less Python packages and Python APIs.
You know, Python packages and other C and Fortran
and other code that's called from Python.
But we need to come to Conda.
In addition to that,
you can also rely on system level libraries
and also additional tools.
For example, the bioinformatics,
there are tools like SAM tools.
So if you want to analyze something,
Conda will also get these tools
which are not Python interfaces,
but all tools on their own.
In addition to that, in PIP, when you install this,
they also distribute the source code.
For example, a unique system.
For Windows and Mac, mostly you have the binaries.
In the PIP, if the source code is there,
and if you are Ubuntu computer, for example,
when you download it, the PIP expects that your computer,
your system to have the compiler.
But Conta could also bring down the compiler
and set up everything.
But mostly, maybe all the time,
Conda is pre-compiled binaries.
You know, they're compiled, so they're ready to be used.
Yes, yes.
And of course you can combine these.
So you can install P packages in Conda.
Like Conda creates its own environments,
which are similar to the virtual environments
I've already mentioned, but they're managed by Conda.
So there's, to the whole ecosystem,
I'll quickly mention this over here.
There's this kind of like glossary of different terms.
So when we talk about Anaconda and Konda,
like you can get headache from just hearing
about all of these different terms
because there's so many of them.
So I'll try to quickly like go through
the whole Konda thing.
Like what are the different partners
basically in the ecosystem?
So there's the Anaconda cloud.
So this is the place where people store the packages.
Then there's CondaForge, which is the largest open source
community channel.
And Anaconda Cloud also contains like packages
by the Anaconda Incorporated,
which are in so-called defaults channel
or base channel and R channel and those kinds of channels.
But they are incompatible usually with CondaForge
because CondaForge is basically like a completely
different world in the same ecosystem.
So Anaconda Cloud contains like two worlds.
There's this like open source world with CondaForge
And then there's the default world,
which is like curated by the company, Anaconda Incorporated.
You can use both, but usually you don't want to mix
and match them because you can get problems.
Then there's the package managers.
So peep is the package manager for Python packaging index.
So if you install from Peepy,
you install it with peep usually.
But then there's conda,
which is like the package manager for conda environments
and Anaconda stuff and that sort of things.
And there's a newer version that we usually recommend
to our customers called Mamba,
which is like a open source,
like Konda is open source project as well,
but there's a C++ implementation of this.
So because like, again, like Konda is written in Python,
so it's slow.
So when you create this huge environment,
sometimes it can take like minutes to figure out
how do I match these different packages
into the same environment?
And that's why people usually use this Mamba,
which can do it much faster, this solving.
So inside it, it's a mess,
but there's like a SAT solver inside the condan.
It tries to figure out the correct packages
that you need in the environment,
because it wants like a working consistent environment.
Maybe we will just like,
it will just install stuff into the environment.
Then there's like the package manager deployments.
So basically you can get already existing
like a good set of packages if you install the Anaconda.
So the Anaconda is like a distribution of lots of packages
by Anaconda Incorporated.
And it's free for academic and non-commercial use,
but for companies it's face money,
like the license is not covered,
it doesn't cover companies.
Then there's Miniconda, which is basically,
it's provided by Anaconda Incorporated
and it uses default channel by default,
like the Anaconda packages,
it comes, by default it tries to install them from there
and it's like, it only contains the conda installer.
So you can use that as like a starting point
if you want to like create your own environments
or something, you don't have to install
the whole Anaconda installation.
Then there's also this mini-forge,
which is like a Konda Forge version of the whole thing,
where it basically, it uses the Konda Forge by default.
So it's an open source version of mini Konda basically.
And it has Mamba as well installed.
So these are some of the words you might hear
when you look at webpages and look at installations.
So you need to basically choose what you want to use.
Usually when people are using, let's say Windows,
the Anaconda Navigator is so good
that like using that is a good idea.
And you can manage packages with that as well.
Like you don't have to use these command line tools
or anything, you can use the Anaconda Navigator
to manage your package installations.
If you're using Linux,
you often either maybe get the Anaconda installation
and just use that and maybe create your own environments
that doesn't have the packages you need,
or you just take like, let's say MiniForge
and then you use that to create your environments.
But that's like a more like command line,
let's do it like ourselves kind of a way.
So there's different ways of installing the packages.
Yeah, it's correct to say that regardless
of you have installed Anaconda or Miniconda
or some packages to get Conda,
you can use any of the other package managers,
you know, conda to install packets from any source. For example, you know, anaconda and
miniconda both could be used to install the same source, but miniconda is lightweight.
But when you, wouldn't you recommend that when you distribute the code that need conda,
that you'd recommend miniconda to be the requirements. And then you provide the package list other
than rather than asking the user to install anaconda and use your package.
Yes, usually it's a good idea to provide the minimal example.
So usually if you go to a web page and you see like,
okay, pip install this, if you have a library or something.
What they mean is that this is the minimum needed for the installation,
but usually you can have it installed in various other ways.
You might install it via conda packets or something.
or what they really are saying that, okay, like, create your own environment and then run this bp
install command. Because like, if you just run the bp install command, you usually install to whatever
environment you currently have. And that's not a good idea. So usually, it's a good idea to choose.
Yeah. For the sake of time, shall we show this best practice you are talking about?
Yes. What is this environment and why do we have to isolate?
So, when we're talking about environments, usually when you start, for example, if you
now have started JupyterLab, you might have started it in the base environment of your
Anaconda installation, or maybe you have installed the environment that we have provided in the
webpage.
But the environment, what we mean is that wherever your Python interpreter basically
is like what is your Python interpreter that you're running? That determines like Python,
based on where it is, it will try to find packages near that. Basically, it goes one
folder up and then one folder down and tries to find packages that are present in the system.
If the Python is the system Python, it will try to find it from the system libraries.
And if it's installed into a completely different place, it will try to find packages from there.
So what this environment means is that we create a folder, basically, we get some Python there,
and then we install packages relative to that Python. And then they are installed into this
own world where they won't interact with others, and we don't have it loaded all the time,
but we can load it per case. If we need to do one kind of a thing with certain packages,
we can activate this environment. So we basically go into this world of this Python and then we run
whatever we want there. And if we are doing a different project, we can activate a different
environment. And this is a good idea because it makes it possible to reproduce your code much
more and you run into less problems. Because as we mentioned previously, there's so many packages.
you cannot get them all working at the same time. So it's better to just have a small world
where there's not that many problems that has only the things you need, basically.
And that's in the environment. I always start with a new environment whenever there's a problem with
Python. You start from scratch and you start building up the environment that you need.
need. And you can create an environment by running some commands yourself. But nowadays,
and that is often recommended somewhere, but that is like we will, you will find in the
exercise, exercise two, you can run it after the course and run the environment yourself.
But we don't recommend that way of installing packages in general. So let's jump straight
to the correct solution basically, or the better solution.
So what you're saying is that, let's say if I want NumPy 1.24 and NumPy 1.23, both versions
of NumPy in my same system, rather than just installing pip install NumPy, that there's
a better way to do this, which will help me to reproduce this later?
Yes.
And this is by recording the dependencies into this environment file, because the problem
with, like, if you, for example, with that, of course, you can, like, install NumPy some
version. And then you realize, okay, my other code needs another version. So, you can basically
install the other version. But now you lost the other one. So, basically, either you need
to constantly reinstall stuff. And maybe when you do a reinstall, suddenly some dependency
of that package gets reinstalled. And suddenly you're in this mess where, like, the route
took to get to the current state of the environment is depending on what commands you run in what
order. And then you cannot reproduce it. You cannot anymore. You don't know how you got there.
So it's usually better to just create a world where everything is correct at the correct time.
And how you do that is that you record the dependencies into either the requirements.txt
or environment.yaml. Does it matter what you call this, [Name]?
Does it matter what you call these files? Yes. You can, of course, record them. You can
name them anything you want. But the thing is that if other people are trying to find them,
find, they will look at these files and they think that, okay, these are the files.
And these are the ones that the tools will, by default, try to search for.
If you try to install via people, for example, it will try to find the requirements.txt.
But these are basically like the conventions, so you should abide by the conventions.
Of course, if you don't, then let the users know or the other people know that, okay,
requirements are in foobar.txt or something, but that's not a good thing.
If I visit the GitHub page or GitLab page, if the requirement.txt is there,
I know what it is. So it's better that you follow this.
Yes, yes, exactly. So you can always look at these. And what the requirements.txt,
so the requirements.txt is meant for PEEP installations. And what it contains is just
a list of packages. Usually it can have, we'll talk about versioning a bit later,
but it's usually just a list of packages, a text file. And when you tell a peep to install
an environment, it will just install these packages. Condor environments are a bit more
complicated. Not in a bad way, but they have more information in them. And they're usually
called these environment YAML. There's a typo. It's environment.yaml, not environments.yaml
usually. So, and they contain like the name of the environment, usually, what environment you want
to use. And then where do you want the packages to come from? I talked about defaults and CondaForge,
the channels. So you usually define like, okay, I want the packages for in this case, for example,
to come from defaults channel. So the Anaconda incorporated packages. And then you have a list
of dependencies that are the packages. And you can usually convert, like you can notice from
syntax that you can easily convert PIP packages, PIP requirements txt to environment.yaml and
other way around. If you just take these and put them into requirements.txt, you can get
basically a PIP installation. And the other way around, if you take these, you can convert them
quite easily. So which version of NumPy would this install?
So in this case, because we haven't specified any versions, like the both tools, they try
to get the newest one.
Like if there's some other packets that of course creates like a requirement that, okay,
I need a lower version, then you might get that lower version.
But the point is here is that you let the tools do its job.
That like, if you don't know what version you need, if you don't have a specific need
for a version, it's usually a good idea to let the tool decide what versions to get.
Because if you don't have any specific requirement, it's a good idea to let the solvers figure
out what is compatible and what is needed.
Because you mentioned that it is easily interchangeable, so I want to mention one thing.
So if you have some packages, depending on the channel you select, there might be different
versions.
pip, it's always the latest version, you know, it might pick up. But depending on the channels you
specify, maybe some different versions can be installed. So you also need to, that's why it's
important that you specify the channel in your environmental file, rather than depending on what
defaults you have. Yes. And also in Conda environment, you can also, let's say, specify
the Python version you want to use, and that sort of, you can get more complicated with those.
But so why is this important to have the requirements file? Because it makes it
possible to recreate the environment quickly. So you can recreate the whole thing. You can
remove it and you can recreate it and you should get basically the same kind of situation.
Of course, in some cases you want to lock down some versions. So if you need to
to reproduce it. Let's say you run something for your paper and you want the collaborators
or reviewers or whoever, you want them to be able to reproduce the thing. So then you
might want to lock down the versions or pin the versions that you are currently using
because you know that those work. And in that case, you can give these versioning numbers.
So there's various logic you can give, like larger than, smaller than, that kind of stuff.
You can give all kinds of, but you can basically lock down certain versions of packages.
So let's say you want these exact versions of numpy, matplotlib, pandas, and scipy.
And same with the conda and with the added Python 3.10 here, so that you want it with
a certain Python version.
So as a best practice, wouldn't you recommend instead of having these exact versions, you
would say that something bigger than this version, but less than this, give us some
range being very specific?
Yes.
The versioning, how it goes usually in these packages, if the people abide by it, is so-called
semantic versioning.
So the first version is usually the major release.
So between two major releases, nothing usually works.
the number goes from one to two, the first number, it basically means that it's no longer compatible
and you should do major changes to it. In the minor version, the second number there,
it basically means that they can introduce new features and they can deprecate old features,
but they usually give a few versions of leeway where you see these deprecation warnings and
and that sort of things. These will go away in the next version or something like that.
So, usually, the second version will basically mean that, okay, we are doing some changes between
the versions, and some things might not work anymore. But usually, the main things are the
same. And the third version is basically a patch version. So, that shouldn't ever affect.
Like, if they have done their job correctly, it should never affect your code. It's like fixes
for bugs and that sort of thing. But that means that you can usually give quite a bit of a leeway.
You can say that it needs to be higher than version one, but less than version two or something. It
needs to be version one, but that's all. Or version something, some range of versions.
So all the advice you gave, we also need to take care when we distribute packages to stick to
those rules, because people expect that. Yes. And it's usually a good idea not to pin yourself
too hard to the packages, especially if you're developing something. Because if you're pinning
yourself to a certain version, you're basically locked in time. You're at that time moment.
And then the world will move onwards, but you are stuck in that time when you created an environment
and when you pinned the versions. And in two years, in three years, in four years,
Yes, most likely nobody else can recreate that environment anymore.
And that's a bad thing.
So your code will be stuck in that time.
So it's usually not a good idea to do that too often.
Yeah.
Sometimes we go on sort of bypassing these practices and say, if I have created an environment,
is it possible to create this file from an existing environment that I can give to other
people?
Yes.
In this exercise, there's an example how you can freeze an environment, so you can use this
conda env export. There's also an additional flag here that you can put
dashdash from history, if you want to freeze it based on the commands that you have run previously.
And you can also run this pip freeze. But what I usually recommend, if you don't
know how you created your environment. I personally start from completely blank slate
and then I run the code until I no longer get import errors. Because if you really don't know
what the environment has eaten, it's very hard to reproduce it. But you can freeze it
if you want to have an environment for posterity or publication or something like that.
Should we just show one example while learners could also follow or what do you recommend?
Let's do an example. So this will, of course, be dependent on what system you're running.
So like in my case, I'm running Linux, so I can use the terminal, for example, in JupyterLab
if I start, well, I can start a new one, let's say here.
I'll, oops, I'll start a new terminal.
If you're running in, let's say, Anaconda Navigator,
you can basically, like, point it to the environment file
and you can let it work on that.
But you can have various different user interfaces.
But because I'm using command line,
I'll create the environment in this way.
So let's say I have an environment YAML.
So in this case, it's basically the one over here
with the NumPy and Matplotlib and whatever.
So I'll run the exercise 4.
You can probably run it yourself, but because, yeah.
Or you can run it yourself, and I recommend trying it.
But because there's differences in environments,
it might be complicated if you get it working,
but do try if you feel like it.
So what I'm going to do,
I'm going to create this environment
using this conda-env-create,
and then I'm going to point it to the environment YAML
that I have.
Can you show us that file,
how it looks like in your-
Yes, yes.
So the environment, it's just a .yaml file.
So yaml syntax.
So it has this list of packages over here.
Or following, it's the teaching material.
Oh, yeah.
It's a CMS.
Yeah.
I've already have it, so I'm going to remove it.
So you can remove the environments with this command.
with this command and why it's also very important to do this environment.
I usually remove all of my environments every two months or something, and the reason behind
is that I'm secure in the knowledge that I can recreate it from the environment files
that I have.
I don't fear losing my system that I have set up is so fragile that I'm worried that
I mess it up, and now I cannot recreate it anymore. And that's a terrible fear to have
as a programmer, that you cannot recreate the environment you already have. And that's why
it's very important to create the environment file, because then you can let go of that fear.
You don't have to worry about that anymore. So typing, installing one by one would be easier.
That is the easy way out. But the robust way is that what you're doing. Slightly more work,
but you will thank your past self at some point. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yeah. And if you want to like,
let's say you want to recreate, like you want to add a new package there. What I usually do is
that if I run, let's say the install command in the environment myself, or in the documentation,
there's also this, you can update the environment based on an updated environment YAML. You can
and instant new packets there,
but they always record it into the environment anyway.
Because like eventually you mess up the environment anyway.
Like everybody does that.
Like everybody does a wrong installation or something
and then it's broken the environment.
And this is unfortunately the side effect
of having so many different choices of libraries.
But at the same time, you can fix it
by having a consistent way of recreating where you are.
are. And that is either the environment YAML or the requirements TXT. Of course, the requirements
TXT, it works very well if you're only using Python packages and stuff in the pip world.
But if you're using GPUs, if you're using more complex things, I recommend checking the conda
because it makes it possible to install much more complex environments where everything
works together. So it is thinking now, the Konda is thinking and it's solving the environment. You
see this timer going on. So when you work on a system and when you create environments like
this in the requirement file, the waiting time is also less rather than you add more and more
to an existing environment. Because Konda needs to figure out all the matching files. And the
other thing is when you work on a system for a long time, it might create a big cache,
the packages you don't want will get accumulated. So in addition to being reproducible, there are
so many other benefits by following the procedure that you are doing now.
Yes. And I'll also mention that if you want to share the environment or reproduce it in
another system. Usually, the environments are not easy to transfer. There are tools to do this,
but it's very finicky. Usually, it's better to just move the environment YAML to a different
place and recreate the environments there. It's just one text file, and it's very easy to copy
that and then recreate it in another place. Because the environments, if you're doing
work with like deep learning or something. The environments can get to like, I don't know,
like four gigabytes. You don't want to like move four gigabytes when you can move a text file.
That's not usually a good idea. So moving around things on different systems,
it would create issues as well because these are pre-compiled binaries. If you want to move
something from Windows to a Unix computer, almost it will never work. But if you can move this
environmental file and recreate it according to their system, according to your target system.
And also you could easily version control this environment file because it's text file,
you could have Git and other ways of version control. You can have multiple snapshots.
So yeah, that's an important thing. And I should mention that in the Python packaging index,
and also in the conduct channels, there's huge amounts of variety based on what operating system
you're running. So for example, some packages, usually the packages are built for Mac OS X,
they're built for Windows, they're built for Linux, different variants of Linux,
different dependencies, and you can have a huge amount of different combinations of the same
package. The same package, but it's built in different ways based on where it's going to be
installed. These tools make it possible to install it. Of course, this is a bit of a demo
effect, but the environment solving takes a long time. This is why the Mamba is so popular.
If we have time, I can show you how long it takes with Mamba, but I'm pretty certain it
doesn't take this long. But this can also happen in Anaconda Navigator, for example. It's pretty
annoying sometimes that it doesn't produce output that often. Like what's it doing?
Like it's trying to solve the environment and yeah, it takes a while and it doesn't
necessarily produce output so you can think that it's crashed. But yeah, sometimes the
solving just takes a long time. Let's see if there's any good questions in the chat.
Yeah. So I will also try on my terminal. Let's see. Yes. The one reason could be that you
have a lot of, we could, there are ways to clear conda cache, for example, to check less
things and also your base environment where this JupyterLab is installed. It might have
a certain libraries already installed. So what conda trying to do is it's trying to
sort of not to redo things and maybe reuse things and also be compatible.
Yeah, and also maybe it's because of the share and that sort of thing.
There's other things running on my laptop at this point.
Yeah, let's see. Are there any good questions? So where should it be stored? So usually a
good idea to, if you're using version control or something, you should usually store the
environments and requirements with the code, so that it's easy to reproduce.
There's a good question there, honda-update-or, this is a good thing to
mention, that updating already existing environments can sometimes be really
complicated, like it's, well, for pip it's less complicated because pip usually
It just downloads stuff and it doesn't care necessarily.
It just will install them.
It doesn't look...
It just goes YOLO and it just installs packages, which is good in many cases, but it sometimes
gets you environments that don't work anymore.
What Conda does is the complete opposite.
So it tries to make certain that everything works.
And if you have like, basically, if you have, let's say, if you have ever been to like a
tour or something, like a tourist tour or something, and there's one person who walks
slowly, then the whole group needs to walk slowly.
And that's basically what can happen with the conda packages, is that there's one package
that is basically like, I don't want to update, like I don't like updating, I don't want
to like be updated.
And then it can hold the whole environment back.
And it can create this kind of a situation where, like, the content goes on a tangent
and it tries to, like, create an environment which doesn't want to update anymore.
So for all of these situations, usually the solution is to just create a new environment.
For fun's sake, I created a new environment here. Let's try with Mamba. I'm running it
now from my terminal, and it's the same command, exact same command, but this time I'm running it
with Mamba. Mamba is much faster, so I'm pretty certain that this will finish before this
And it gives more output as well, it tells where it tries to find the packages and what does it download, like what packages and that sort of stuff.
Yeah.
So now it tells what we are looking for.
we are looking for, and soon it should probably give you the answer to what it's, yeah.
So now it's already doing the installation.
So this is why we usually recommend people to use Mamba when they create environments.
So it's already done when the conda is still wondering about, and this is why this is maybe
a good demo on why certain tools have been reinvented.
But the user interface is basically the same.
But maybe we should have, like, do we have anything for this session?
Do you want to show something more?
Yeah, maybe I'll quickly show how to activate the environment.
So, when we often, often in places, we recommend you don't necessarily run this conda init.
You can run it.
So if you see, let's say you have a terminal
and you see, let's say the space over here,
it means that your conda is active now
and the Python will always be found from that environment.
And then this can cause problems in many systems.
Like if you want to,
if you don't want to always have it active,
like if you have a program that tries to use Python,
but suddenly it wants to use the Python
from the activated conda, that can cause problems.
So, we usually recommend that people don't run this conda in it, but you can, of course,
run it.
And if you run it, you can use this conda activate to activate the environment.
And now you have an environment here.
But if you, yeah, usually we don't recommend you run it all the time, because then other
programs that want to use Python as well, they might find this wrong Python instead
of the Python that you want to use.
So here in this file that you activated, we didn't mention which version of Python we
need.
So, we can check what is the version of the Python, so we got 3.12, so in this environment
I didn't specify what Python to use, so yeah, I just got the newest Python in this case,
if I run which Python, this is like Linux specific command, but you can see that it shows Python from
my newly created environment. So in an environment, does it always include a Python as well?
Not necessarily. Even if you don't have it, mention it in your requirement file,
does it always include a Python? No, no. If there's nothing that requires Python,
it doesn't always contain Python. So usually when you create an environment, it might be sometimes
a good idea to add, let's say, pip and Python always there so that you always get pip and
Python into the environment. But sometimes, like most of the time, you install NumPy or something,
and then that has a dependency to Python. So it will bring Python with it. But it's always like
this kind of a question of who are the major players? What are the major packages that you
want to get. And those are the ones that bring everybody with them. So they're basically like
the Taylor Swift going into a restaurant. Other people come because Taylor Swift is at the
restaurant. And those are the stars of the environment. Let's say PyTorch or something.
PyTorch will bring its friends with it. But nobody's really caring about the friends. They
are caring about the PyTorch. And this is usually how you want to think about the environment. So
there's usually the major players that you want to, these are the major things that they want
the conda to focus on. So to sort of, sort of investigate that, what you said, you know,
there might be other packages that pandas needed. Is it possible for you to rephrase this
environment and show how that would look like, you know, after creating? Yes, let's, let's,
Let's run the conda-env-export.
And you notice here that I get this pretty horrible looking environment file, where suddenly
there's a huge bunch of stuff here.
And this is basically the exact versions I got.
And most of these are packages that come as dependencies to, let's say, NumPy.
But you don't want to give other people these as an installation instruction, unless they
want the exact same environment.
But usually you don't want it.
You want to give them the actual instructions that you need.
The one you use.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So, in fact, this will break in most systems because if you see the hash, like the third,
like you have two equal signs, the third hash actually is very unique to the system you
are in now.
So, there's very likely that it will break on a different system.
Yes.
So, many of the things here are like, you can read it as you have a package, then you
have a package version, and then you have a specific build of that package.
For example, in this case, it's for Python 3.12. But yeah, it's very specific. And that's why you
usually want to give the broad outline of the environment instead of the exact requirements.
Of course, if you want to create the exact same cake that somebody else has created,
you can give the exact grams of what flour to get, exact brand of the flour, exact date of the flour
when it was made, like exact amount of the flour that is needed. But most of the time,
you want to give a generic recipe that says that, okay, just get me flour this amount.
So it's like similar, you don't want, you want to give a general recipe, you don't want to give,
and the Konda is like the cook that can then manage this.
Yeah. Then also the file you used, the environment file, you should also give the
the others to build upon your package. For example, if they
need a, let's say, PyTorch in their program, in addition to
what you install, it's easier for them to add PyTorch instead
of editing this file. So this is sort of overwhelming. And this
is not something you want to show. And it's also very
simple.
Should we now go to a break before?
We have two minutes. I think one minute you can have a look at
questions? Yeah, let's look at the questions quickly and then go to a break.
So let's see. If you have any more questions, please go and ask them. I will try to answer
them. Do you want me to share the questions? Yes, maybe. Yeah, that would be great. Okay, here we go.
You can only see on the stream how this goes.
I can see the questions on the stream.
There's some questions about things like, how do you make the stuff in the environment
file?
Do you have to do it manually?
I think you might have answered that.
It usually is a good idea to write it yourself.
Where do you store the environment file?
Yeah.
So I think we have some Mamba installation instructions somewhere as well.
So we had to find that and place it.
So under question 44, we'll place it
as soon as I find the link for the mobile installation.
Yes.
So about the question, I often think of environments
like if you go camping or if you go to a hotel,
like you go on a trip, you always
pack the usual suspects.
like you pack your toothbrush and you pack your shampoo and whatever,
like this kind of stuff.
And that's basically what most of the environments are.
You always get numpies and matplotlibs and scipies and python and beef.
And like most of the stuff is like, it rolls off your tongue.
Like you know that, okay, I will need these anyway.
Like I always want these stuff.
And then there's all like, usually like maybe two, three packages that are the
actual like meat of the whole thing and they are the special like let's say you need a certain
kind of like clothing when you go to a like a trip you need clothing for warm weather or
something like that and that's the actual thing there. Yes although it's very interesting our
discussion [Name] that we have to stop now. On question number 46 I'll slightly mention something
about it especially we see this if it says access denied when you try to install especially on
shared HPC systems for example it's always like that you are not allowed to modify the central
environment and actually you should not do that try to do that you can use with dash as user
as mentioned answer but you should go for this environment what [name] was promoting so create
isolated silos where you can add things and have different versions and also delete them
if they don't want. So don't try to install it centrally.
Yes. So if you install like Anaconda Navigator or something, usually like in that example,
you install it into program files and you install it as root or something like that.
And you don't have maybe right access to that folder. And that's a good thing because then
you cannot mess up the installation. But what you want to do is create a separate realm,
separate world, virtual environment, or conda environment, where you then install the stuff.
Because if you run, for example, the pip install, it will install into folders where
they will always be present. So if some other environment uses the same Python version,
it will find the same packages, and then all hell breaks loose, and suddenly nothing works anymore.
So, you want to keep the packages that you want in the environment, you want to keep
it in a separate silo, like [Name] said, a separate world, and you want to first create
the world for it, like the environment.
You want to create the world, and you want the packages to that world.
And [Name] will take the rest of the questions and the community, and thank you very much
Thank you so much for your this great introduction. I think it will be very useful for most of us. [Name], can you please take on.
Yes. So, yeah, I guess, um, we will have a break until 23 past hour.
So, see you then.
you
There we go, we are in gallery.
Hi, so welcome back.
We've got a last exercise here,
So you may see on the notes,
there's this initial discussion question,
which we will talk about shortly.
But we'll get back there in a minute.
So I will switch to [name]'s screen.
We are now on the Binder lesson here.
So, yeah, so the question is,
when is sharing code alone not sufficient?
So let's reflect on what just happened in
the first two lessons of today.
So we had scripts which worked roughly okay for many people,
but there were many different problems there.
And once we start having these dependencies, everyone's computer is different. So we have
people running via Anaconda Navigator, Anaconda Cloud, making own environments, maybe some people
on clusters, and multiply this all by three different operating systems. So basically,
even if someone has the code, it really doesn't work that well. So look at this picture here.
So what looks really simple, so there's we say okay there's this code it says
Python import pandas. There's all these things underneath and it can all go
wrong some different ways. But what happens if we want to make our code a
little bit more reusable? So we want to find a way to have code and have someone
else to easily be able to try it out even if we aren't giving them all the resources directly.
And that leads to this question, which is being shown here. So Leia is a PhD student in
computation biology, and after two years of work, she's ready to publish her first paper.
The code used for analyzing data is available on GitHub, but the supervisor is an advocate
open science and says just sharing this code is not sufficient. So if this code is just on GitHub,
what kind of problems could happen? And by the way, GitHub is a version control platform. It's a way
to share code and control changes to it. So this course is definitely not about Git and GitHub.
Our other big course, Code Refinery, is about this. So don't worry about that name.
But what kind of things can go wrong? Please write in notes, and I will flip back there.
So what can go wrong?
The easiest is probably we miss requirements. We miss dependencies.
case.
Okay.
So, so basically the NumPy or pandas that worked five years ago doesn't work anymore
because something has changed.
That or we don't even know that it is there or that we need it initially.
Yeah.
So if there's code that shared but doesn't have this environment file or requirements
file, then there's really hardly any chance there.
documentation it can be really hard to use. So what about the whole version of Python changes?
So for example, a lot of my old codes were written with Python 2 and I never updated them because
I'm not doing that anymore. That code is probably effectively dead by now.
Very likely, except if someone, well, it's, okay, I would make a distinction. It's dead for current development.
It might still work if someone has a Python 2 and their respective dependencies to run it.
So the code might still work if you get the right dependencies, if you know which versions are needed for it.
But it's probably dead for further development.
And then what about the practical difficulties of someone installing these?
Let's say you're sharing it with someone that's not an expert in Python and doesn't
use environment files and all these things. Is there any way that they can
explore this code and do anything with it at all?
Well, yeah, there are tools like binders, which essentially provide a virtual environment
that is independent of your machine.
And if they don't want to care about it, this kind of, yeah, more or less virtual machine
for a virtual interpreter can help you there.
I wouldn't know of anything else that you could really
do if they don't want to install anything.
Yeah.
So well, anyway, that leads to what
our lesson is now, which is sharing computational
environments with Binder.
So back to [name]'s screen.
So this is something where you can try to follow along
and do it with us if you want.
But for most people I would say don't just watch us and ask questions. And why is that?
It requires knowledge of git and the github account and for a later part is the nodo account.
And these things are definitely not prerequisites of this course. So we don't expect everyone to be
able to do this. So try if you want, but try to get the point of what we're doing and ask questions
and get inspired to do this later. So let's see. Let's get started then.
and how I'm arranging my screen so I
can see what [name] is doing.
So we start off with this example
we used from a previous lesson.
Which lesson was it?
The data visualization.
So it's a little plot.
So we see the code here.
It's in a notebook.
Can you run it?
I hope it works and I didn't do anything wrong, but yeah.
Yes, okay, so there's a plot.
So we need to... we want to make this reusable by other people.
So to do that, the first step is to make a git repository.
So we would probably do this from a command line, but instead we're doing it
from GitHub. So here we are on github.com.
[name] is logged in, and we'll click New.
And this allows us to make a new repository. We can call it Binder Demo.
Okay, and there's no description needed. Public.
It's relatively important that it is public, otherwise Binder might get into problems.
Yes, and click Create Repository.
So, so far, what we've done is a pretty standard way of using GitHub.
And next up, we will find on this page, upload existing file.
So we can do everything here.
It's right around there.
Yes.
Okay.
Did you save it in JupyterLab?
And give it a title?
Yes.
Or rename the file?
It is. I just try navigating there or actually choose your files.
So this is a bit.
Word finder teaching.
There. Called it plotting.
So it's been added and we give a git command message.
So this is this provides a history and explains what we're doing. So we commit changes.
And there we go. There's a notebook. Can we click on it and see what it looks like when we open it?
Yep. GitHub has a preview. Okay. Yeah that looks like what we just did.
So now in fact maybe someone can copy the link and put it
in the notes, but this is something that anyone can see.
OK, [name] is doing it.
Yeah, just need to find the notes again.
OK, there we go.
Okay. Okay. Let's go back. So now here we are. So what what's the first minimum step in order
for anyone to be able to run this code? Telling what requirements there are. So what other
what dependencies it has. Yeah so exactly what we just covered in the lesson. So we'll create a new
file. We will call it, we'll copy this,
and we paste it and call it requirements.txt.
So now we've just made another file in this repository
from the github web interface, and we paste it in
the requirements.txt version of dependencies.
So we can click Commit Changes.
It gives us some standard message to create the files.
We can do it, and we click Commit Changes.
And now if we look at our code, we
have plotting.ipynb and requirements.
So there we go.
So now, OK, so what is Binder?
If we go to mybinder.org, which is listed, it's a way where we can...
So it's a cloud service that starts Jupyter
in the environment specified in the repository. So Binder will read the requirements
and make an environment and then start Jupyter in there for anyone online.
So, if we copy this URL, yeah, let's copy, actually no, we can copy it from there, and
then paste.
So, what it tells us to do is not to click launch, but to click the little arrow down
below, lower, there.
And this gives us a launch binder button, just like we see up there.
So copy that, and let's go back to the GitHub repository, and let's make a new README file.
And oh, there's this nice button there to do it.
So it's called Binder Demo.
We can paste this.
Maybe we can put it below the title.
Okay, yeah.
So we see Binder.
And if we commit the changes, commit directly.
Yes, OK.
So now our repository is described.
And this readme file would be, like it would say,
this is my example code for such and such a project.
Here's my citation, stuff like that.
And if you're following along online, you will see this there also.
And now you can click LaunchBinder, this button.
Maybe open it in a new tab.
But it's okay.
Yeah. So we see a preview of it,
and we see it's running some stuff here.
So this is building the environment.
And can you zoom in a little bit?
So we see it's running a bunch of code looking stuff,
but it looks like it's trying to install from the requirements.txt
file.
And it might take a little while.
Um, I'm not sure why it took me a long time yesterday.
Um, maybe we can take a short break and ask, did you
No, I just went over.
You went to a new...
Okay.
Yeah, it's not.
So we're just open the git repository again.
So if there's any questions, please write in the notes because I'm sure there's all
kinds of things here.
So yeah, it's still going.
Building, let's hope that gets done soonish.
Yeah, it took a few minutes for me.
So while we're waiting, in what cases
is this especially useful?
I would say for a relatively well for for research code that you want people
to be able to explore and that does not depend too much on particular data sets
that you have so as soon as you depend as your code depends on really large
data sets it might not be the easiest or best approach yeah because they need to
to be stored somewhere and you only
have limited resources on Binder.
Yeah.
So in Code Refinery, we gave an example
or we showed a demo, I think.
There's a scientific project that
was analyzing some data and making
some interesting pictures.
And they created a Binder repository out of this.
So basically anyone else with a little bit of knowledge with Python could start this up and regenerate the figures and see how little changes would affect what the results are.
And this was really good for science because the more people that can use your work, the more likely you are to get citations about it.
And that is presumably one of your goals here.
I mean, of course, it's also good for science if other people can explore and reuse things
and stuff like that.
There's a good question coming up.
So would Binder be suitable for projects where the same project folder has the raw data files
used by the study?
So yes, I mean, if the data is small, then this makes sense.
So you could have the data within the Git repository.
I would say it makes sense up to like a few megabytes of data size or something like that.
Otherwise, GitHub and Binder Hub might not be very happy because it's basically using their
resources to host data. But one thing that can be done is the data is put somewhere else
And your notebook itself is made so that it downloads the data
whenever it runs.
So the code would say, OK, does the data already
exist if .downloaded?
And then it uses a downloaded file in that directory.
Does Binder run on your local machine,
Or does the Binder instance run remotely?
This is running remotely.
So Binder is run by some nonprofit group,
which gets donations of the computing resources
from Google and other kinds of places.
Is it running?
It's running.
It's installing things.
Yeah, so they get donations of these resources, and basically BinderHub is a modified JupyterHub.
And it, um, yeah, so it's running in the cloud.
So it provides resources for a short time, like after 15 or 30 minutes it would time
out and remove everything. So it's not suitable for storing things online for a long period
of time. Like not suitable for long term work or doing your main work. You know, if we do
this again, maybe we could have a break while the binder is launching.
That sounds very reasonable.
While we're waiting, we can preview
what would happen next.
Or actually, maybe we could do it at the same time even.
So the next section is about how can I get a DOI from Zenodo.
So DOI is Digital Object Identifier.
and basically it is what is used to cite papers and other things.
So the idea here is that let's say you have a project and you make some code
and you want your code to be cited. So Zenodo is a publicly funded data repository.
It's funded by the EU for open science purposes. It's run by CERN. But people can upload data
there and it gets permanently archived. And then you can refer to this, you can cite it,
you don't have to worry about storing it yourself, things like that.
And what we will do is we will connect GitHub to this. So basically Zenodo has GitHub integration.
So, whenever you go to Zenodo, you can tell it, okay, you can log in with, well, log in
with GitHub, and it requests permission to connect there
so we can authorize.
Firefox is managing the passwords.
I am multi-factor authentications.
Yes.
Okay.
And here we are.
So this is making the account on Zenodo,
complete registration, or whatever.
Yeah.
This is for the sandbox, so yeah.
Yes, so we wouldn't want to do a demo for a course using
primary Zenodo because it's permanently archived.
But this sandbox.zenodo.org is just for testing purposes
and teaching.
So OK.
As you can see in the recent uploads,
big stuff for more downloading.
So yeah.
Yeah.
OK, so if we go to the three line menu at the top right,
There is GitHub down below.
That's it.
So we choose our repository, which would be Binder Demo.
We would flip this to on.
And it goes and tells GitHub to set up this repository.
OK, and now that's all we need to do on the Binder side.
Can we go check Binder?
OK, that's still running.
And I really wonder why this is taking.
Actually, I bet it's because we gave it
these exact requirements.
So maybe it's actually taking a long time
to figure out what packages are even
compatible with pandas 1.2.3 and matplotlib 3.4.2.
Possible.
Actually, I bet that's it.
Well, it's building the wheel, so it
doesn't know what it wants.
So it's not at that stage anymore.
a compiling pandas or something. Yeah. Well, anyway, we don't know. Okay, so let's go back to GitHub.
So here we are. And now in order to make this code appear on GitHub, we have to do
what's called a release. So if you look on the right side under releases,
there's create a new release.
And we would, our first release, we need to choose, yeah.
Yeah, there's a good question.
How big of datasets can be shared on the Zenodo?
And the default limit is 50, but I have a feeling that if you ask, they can allow more.
the default has to be small because otherwise it gets filled up with random stuff. Okay,
so we can choose a tag towards the top. We would do create a new tag. We have to push the
plus button. Yeah, okay, there we go. First release. We can do publish release.
Okay, so it has this archive here. It has a zip file and tar.gz of the stuff. And if
If we go to Zenodo again, and let's see, if you click on profile, maybe, no, you go to,
maybe click there.
We have a DOI for this.
So after you first release a DOI batch that you can include in GitHub, right, we will appear
next to your repository below.
So this is our badge.
Yeah.
Do you want to add this to there?
We can copy this.
Wait.
Which is a bit funny that we do a release
and then add the Zenodo badge, which is kind of, yeah, OK,
so we are changing the release.
But yeah.
I mean, the release has the Zenodo thing in there, so anyway, okay.
And there we go. So let's click there. Maybe open in new tab. This works. So we see here on Zenodo,
the sandbox. We see the thing, we see the files that were there, we can download it,
we see the citation for it, we can see it can track different versions when we
make more releases. This actually looks a bit more organized than it looked
when I was checking before.
Anyway. That's the citation.
Do you know if this citation updates if you have multiple contributors?
That's a good question. I don't know. Maybe someone can answer
in the notes. Or someone else can join for our wrap-up.
Or someone wants to make a pull request for...
Yeah.
But yeah.
OK.
Has Binder finished building yet?
One second.
Binder.
Building wheels for map.
OK.
So I guess it really is just.
Slow today.
I also remember that this used to be faster.
Yeah.
So I propose we go back to our notes and we can have a final discussion of today.
I will switch to my note screen again and if you see this is built we can switch back to it.
Okay here we are.
So, yeah, um, we've got plenty of time for a wrap-up today, so what would you all like
to discuss?
Is there any news for Day 4 before people start leaving?
So, I think we go back to...
So there is one thing
which uses the command line and this other environment
a little bit more.
But there are two
things which can purely be done in JupyterLab.
Oh, hello [Name].
I heard a bad signal basically with the requirements thing.
So what I think is happening is that because you see that it's building wheels, it means
that it didn't find the correct versions of matplotlib straight up from pip.
So it starts to build it itself from source code.
And because the version numbers, I think they are locked down to a previous version.
So because you're running like, it's probably running most recent Python, Python 3.12 or
something.
And because you have an older version, it probably has to rebuild it from scratch.
So that might be the reason why you're encountering this.
So essentially what it means is we need to update the requirements, the versions that
want that or we just remove the version deployments. But now it seems to be finishing,
so maybe you don't want to do it at this point. But yeah, this is the kind of stuff,
like if you see something like building wheel, it might be a situation where it's like
like it actually is doing something from a source code
instead of installing from it.
But yeah, I have.
Yeah, so we're showing [name]'s screen again.
And it's pushing.
And oh, look, it.
Starts the Jupyter.
Just started.
Yeah, there we go.
And we see along the side, there is the plotting notebook.
So I guess [name] can click that to open it and then probably
run it.
And there we go.
Yep.
Yeah.
So, do you want to try the thing without, if you, okay, lack stack requirements, what happens?
Yeah, well, we can try that later. Yeah, we can try it later.
Yeah, I agree that is very likely the case. Yep.
Switched back here.
So, what's the summary of today? So, this course, the started alph on days one and two,
which is just about using Python. And that works in JupyterLab in the cloud wherever.
But as we're going on we're moving further and further towards how Python interacts with the
operating system itself. So basically we're seeing how you would break out of the Jupyter notebooks
and be able to run these other, like run things on your computer, run it without Jupyter, run it
more times, be able to share your code, things like this. And these are the kind of things which
are needed to go to the next level. So someone, like there is plenty of work that can be done
only within the Jupyter web interface, but many of you probably need to at least know of these
concepts of how to go out, even if it's someone else you're working with that's managing these
kinds of things. So there's feedback which is coming here. Please answer. I see right now
there's 86 people who are still on the stream and this is not many answers. So please vote
for what you think.
Okay. So the news for tomorrow. So there's one lesson tomorrow which uses the command line
and it's actually about packaging. So it's basically how you can make
a package which can itself go on the pip or conda repositories and then other people can use it.
But it doesn't have to go that far. I oftentimes make things into packages but I install it
directly from github because the use isn't really that much and I'm just using it internally myself.
So, the topics are more advanced, but also you can do things, there's the first lesson
can be done only through JupyterLab and the third one.
So these have good exercises which other people can do also.
Also at the end, we have a panel discussion where you can basically ask all of us instructors
anything you may want, like, what do you recommend for this case or that case, and so on.
And in fact, you can ask some good questions and, you know, try to get us debating each
other about what's the right answer.
Or maybe there is no clear right answer.
Yes, sometimes programs are a bit like lawyers.
It depends.
Yeah, and often like I think it happens
quite often in the Python ecosystem that it's basically like
Once you start your studies and you start your bachelor's and that sort of thing,
you have your friends in the same courses and you're all working on the same courses
and you do the same things because those are the basics. And basically the NumPy and Pandas and
those sort of things, Matplotlib, they are the basics when it comes to scientific computing
with Python. Those are where everybody goes. But then it quite quickly diverges into different
fields. Different fields have different needs and different tools they use. Neuroimaging,
they need to do 3D plotting of MRI slices or something like that. If you do deep learning,
you do completely different tools. Of course, the ecosystem is still the same and everybody's
working the same kind of things, but the problems become more specialized and specific for the field.
And that makes it, of course, hard to give a general answer, what is good.
But what we can hopefully provide is some semblance of like, there are these kinds of tools that go across all of these different fields.
They are tools that are like ecosystem tools and these kinds of things that help you or processes, like packaging in a certain way,
or that help you maybe even if you're working in a very specific field. But of course like every
field has their own special cases that might be complicated or certain kinds of like plotting
or certain kind of thing and you need to like yeah it's a different like specific question
at that field, of course. Yeah, there's some good comments here about today being advanced
and getting stuck. And yeah, I mean, this is unfortunately something that happens sometimes.
We have such a broad audience here, we tried to do something that's a little bit interesting
for advanced people, and for people who get stuck, you can still watch it and take it
as a demo, and then learn more yourself later.
I think that's the only way to manage such a wide audience.
Yeah, and there are different ways of working in different systems. So, for example, many of
the things might be that we go to a terminal and in Windows you don't usually work with a terminal
that often. You don't necessarily use that much of it. The working environment might be different.
But in Windows, let's say you use VS Code or something, you might have OpiCharm or something,
and they can replicate. With an IDE, you can get an even better working environment than with a
terminal, in many cases, like you would do maybe in a Linux system. So there are different ways of
working. So there's no right answer. It is only answer that you want to choose from.
So if you encounter problems with, let's say, environment creation or some of the
command line things or scripting or these kind of things, like PyCharm and VS Code,
you can give arguments to run. When you run, press the green button to run a code,
you can give it arguments to run like it would run as a script. So you can basically demo
how it would behave as a script, even when you're not using terminal. And this is quite common
in the IDE world. So there's different ways of working with the same things. But of course,
when we present it, we present it with the way that we most commonly see in our users,
which is using the command lines or scripts and that sort of thing. But the same things can apply
to different workflows as well. Yeah, so we're over time. If there's no more comments from
anyone, maybe I'd wrap up with this one comment at the bottom. I like this course. It gives a good
overview of good coding practices, but the course requires weeks of hands-on practice to learn.
And I'd say that's absolutely true. And for a 12-hour course, I think any one of the lessons
we teach could easily become a 12-hour course just on their own. And our goal here is to show
you what's possible and give you a little bit of hands-on practice of what's there,
but to inspire you to go learn these later on. And you can learn them by
doing yourself reading more, or probably more likely working with other people that do things
and finding it together. If you're at any of the universities that have partners, you can try
asking the people that are advertising the course and see if they can provide support in these
things. At Aalto University we do plenty of this and I know the people in Sweden and Norway are
very happy to help you with these kinds of things. So with that being said, should we
Should we wrap up?
I think so.
Okay, great. Thank you so much.
See you tomorrow, same time.
Yes, thank you. Bye.
you