CodeRefinery.org
you
I think you should be able to hear us on the stream.
I can hear us on the stream, which I will now mute because the echo is, of course, annoying.
So we put two icebreakers in here.
What's the most surprising thing you've learned so far in this course and most surprising
thing you've learned so far in your career?
And if anyone has any other icebreaker ideas, please, well, you can also propose your own
questions there.
I'm trying to think of something specifically related to today's materials, which is a bit,
we have a wide range of topics.
Yeah, so what's our summary so far?
Where have we come from and where did we go?
We started with day 1, and it seemed like it was pretty normal Python stuff.
Like Jupyter, NumPy, Pandas, I mean, doing Python code.
Day 2 did we start getting exciting.
So day 2 started pretty normal with Pandas and Matplotlib.
again using normal Python code. Towards the end, we start seeing more interactions with the rest
of the world. So the data formats emphasizing how it's not just about the code, but how you
mess with this other, how you read and write data outside of Python can matter.
And then, of course, the things like the linters and so on, which is user interface.
But then yesterday, I mean, yesterday's the kind of stuff which is really important for
using Python, but you wouldn't see in a typical course.
So things like making the scripts, well, you might see that in a Python course, not a purely
theoretical programming course.
But yeah, the introduction to programming with Python
might not even use Jupyter.
It might use just scripts.
And the library ecosystem independency management,
well, that is, I mean, that's really
getting to the kind of stuff which we use
and we support people with on a daily basis.
So my estimate has been that about half of our
total support requests are helping to install software on the cluster,
a lot of which is in Python and could, in theory, be done independently.
But it's so confusing and hard.
Dependencies are a complicated topic and a big unsolved problem.
Um, it's also the reason, like all of these libraries, the fact that they
exist is the reason why Python is good.
I mean, the language itself is good, but the main reason people actually use it
is because there are already all of these libraries available.
Hello from my side as well.
Yeah.
Like I was just thinking myself at that, like, uh, quite often when, when using
Python, it's more about reading what some other person has done like a package and then reading
how they want you to use it and then just using it. And it's like, is this, can you call this
even like coding when you're like calling functions from other libraries and that sort of
stuff? But of course you are coding, but like, yeah. And, and, and, and using, using like, it
would be wasteful to not use the capabilities provided by the other people.
And it's usually the thing you find is not exactly the thing you want, but you can
coax your data to fit into that and kind of use it or modify it slightly to make it what you want.
Yeah. And it's like buying Lego blocks. You buy Lego blocks and then you have a world that you can
create with them and you can of course like just follow the instructions and do the set that you
have bought or whatever or you can go wild and do whatever you want with them like combine the blocks
in an unexpected way and create something new and that's what like usually happens but you don't
start molding the lego blocks yourself like that would be waste of time like getting like a 3d
printer to mold them. Of course, if you want to, you can go to Python libraries and start
writing C code and that sort of stuff, but then you're coding C code and you're not coding Python.
So I think we need to do a volume check.
So, well, let's start with an order, me, Simo, Yarno.
1.
2.
3.
Three.
So, I think Simo is too loud.
I can also drop it here.
I'm actually not at 100%.
Is it better now?
You still seem pretty loud.
Better?
One.
Two.
Sorry.
Oh, yeah.
One, one, one.
Two.
Okay.
Is this better?
Might be just my enthusiasm rubbing off on you.
Yeah.
Might be just my enthusiasm rubbing off.
So I'm liking these icebreaker answers here.
I just thought of these last minute,
but it's good to see what's surprising in the course.
And also, I like these career lessons also.
So, last time there were some problems with a blurry screen, and one part might have been
Twitch, but also it might have been so people are sharing by Zoom, and then I render it
on the screen, and then capture it, and then it gets rebroadcasted.
So there might be a little bit of blur that comes here.
So if you see a problem, let me know, is it really bad or like a little bit of anti-aliasing
around the letters and let us know right away and we'll try to fix that.
Yeah.
On your side, I recommend in the Twitch, there's like this cog icon at the bottom right of
video where you can click the video quality and you can make it to appear as source quality,
because otherwise it's automatic and then it might degrade it based on the network performance that
you have. So you might like get suddenly a blurry flash because it's buffering or something like
that. So setting it to force it to be the highest quality might mitigate some of the problems.
Okay. Well, it's 10.01. Any comments from these surprising things or should we just
go on? Should us instructors say the most surprising stuff? Maybe we should just go
on. We can answer this in the panel discussion.
Okay.
In the wheel getting reinvented. But yeah, we'll talk about it. Well, at least we will
talk about how to package your own stuff so that other people
don't need to necessarily write it themselves later.
But first, we have some parallel processing.
OK, so I'll head out.
Can you share the screen?
Yeah, I can take the share if you capture it from my screen.
Okay.
I see it.
I will head off.
All right.
See you.
After.
Okay.
Are we ready?
Yeah.
So okay.
So the first thing I want to do is I want to run this.
Okay.
Okay, are we ready?
Yeah.
So, okay.
So, the first topic is parallel programming and that's kind of an interesting topic to
talk about in Python and I mean, well, you'll see in a moment, but the main thing, I guess,
in Python is that you are using, you're often using Python to connect packages written for
you or written by someone else, and possibly written in other languages.
The first thing when you start considering making your program faster, or especially
if you start thinking about making it parallel, is to check if the libraries you're using
already are parallel or not.
That's probably the most important point of this lesson.
If you come away with just one thing, that's it.
But we will talk a bit about how parallel programming actually works, what it actually
does and how it can or maybe cannot make your code faster.
Sorry, I interrupted you, do you have something?
No, no, no, go ahead.
So maybe we can ask, I could ask, what do we mean when we talk about parallel?
we mean when we talk about parallel programming? Is it like two people on a keyboard?
Yeah, right. So that's called pair coding, I guess. That's a slightly different thing.
Although that is actually a good, I think that's a pretty good metaphor for what the computer does
or what the program does when you run it in parallel. So if you are writing some code
code, and you want to do it twice as fast, hiring two programmers will make it faster,
I guess, but it might not make it twice as fast.
But yeah, so basically, the starting point, if you're thinking about making your code
parallel, is that you want to make it run faster.
It's taking too much time for one reason or another.
Otherwise, you can just run it on a single processor and it will be done.
So that's the starting point.
We want to make it faster.
If your program is fast enough, you don't need to make it parallel.
Would you say that the speedup would come from utilizing multiple processors in one
computer?
Yes, so parallelization specifically, yeah.
So you try to make it faster by essentially using multiple computers.
There are multiple processors on most computers these days.
Basically, if you have a laptop, desktop, you're watching this.
It has 4, 6, 8, 12, maybe around 12 processors that are on the same chip,
but are essentially running calculations independent of each other at the same time.
So, yeah, so making your program parallel basically means all of those processes are
doing something at the same time, so in parallel.
Okay.
So the first thing, though, if your code is too slow, you kind of want to do some, before
going into parallel programming, because it can quickly become a complicated thing, is
check why your code actually is slow, where are the slow spots, use some profiling tools
and then think about can you use existing libraries or somehow make that part faster
and then profile it again and see what part is slow now and so on and then when you get to the
point where that's no longer helping you may think about parallel programming and then
Then there are essentially two different modes of parallelism that people generally use
and you can think about whether one or both of those will work actually in your program.
So the first thing to check is if there is something that really needs to be running
sequentially like you have to know the result of a previous computation to go to the next
one, then you can't do those two things at the same time.
So it's not really parallelizable.
And then you just have to think of something else.
Um, so there will be those parts in the code, but there will also be probably
some parts in the code that were two calculations can be done at the same
time, and then you can parallelize it.
So, okay.
So then like, and what do you say that like in some cases, like, let's say you
have, you want to run the same code or multiple data sets or
something like that you want.
Yeah, so that's one example. So maybe you just want to run the
same code for multiple different parameter values. So
you have a bunch of files that you want to process. So that's
an example of something embarrassingly parallel. Which
is like, I mean, it's an interesting expression, but
that's kind of the official term these days. So it's, the reason
embarrassing is because you don't need to do anything to make it parallel. It just means
you run multiple copies of the program on those different processors, on those different
computers. You can do that by running the command multiple times or you can program it in some
more fancy way to start multiple copies of the program. We will see ways of doing that,
but I mean, there's many ways. Many languages do that.
I would say that the embarrassingly parallel is usually like, if you notice that in your code,
you happen to have a for loop at the outermost layer and inside the for loop, you have something
that run a model or something. You know that you can basically take that for loop and run it
outside of the program. So basically run multiple copies of that program. And that's why it's
barely called parallelism. It's like, so embarrassingly parallel, you don't need any
fancy structures to make it happen. So the main thing about this embarrassingly
parallel category is that the different processes, the different copies of your program don't need
to communicate at all. They just do their own thing. And when they finish, they finish,
the others do not care. That's embarrassingly parallel. And that is the most common situation,
I think that's that's what you will usually end up doing. I just run the same thing many times
but if that's not possible then there's two other options. There's multi-threading.
Multi-threading means that they are running on the same computer but on different
processors on that computer so essentially the thing is that they can share memory.
when you have a variable in the program's memory, the other copies, so-called copies,
or which are called threads really, they have access to that memory.
So that makes things a bit easier. That makes sharing information between the processes a bit
easier. And then there is message passing or MPI, message passing interface is a
common term people use. And a common framework for this. So that means you have a bunch of
independent processes that can be running on different computers and then they send messages
to each other. They communicate over some kind of network. Or in Python you also have this
multi-processing and what it basically means is that Python launches multiple processes and then
they communicate by writing small files into memory, and then each process reads the files.
But basically, it launches multiple Python interpreters that each run stuff.
Yeah, so that's a Python-specific thing that is important, and we'll talk about
multiprocessing in a moment. I'm kind of, well, we'll come back to it because I'm kind of struggling
with a way of going in. Check the first example of Parallel. Yeah, okay. So if you go down a bit,
there's the multithreading example. So this is still like relatively straightforward,
especially in Python because essentially Python doesn't do multithreading, but the libraries that
are written for Python can do multi-threading. So if you're using NumPy, SciPy, Pandas, and so on,
they will be using libraries in the back end that are already multi-threaded.
So basically, you don't need to do all that much. Just make sure you're not running a for loop in
Python, but rather you are using a NumPy operation if you can. There are complicated enough NumPy
operations that you can do most things without a Python for loop. For the technical side,
people who want to know how it works, basically NumPy inside it has lots of libraries or it uses
lots of libraries like this linear algebra libraries. Also, if you think about a for
loop. It's like sum all values in this array or something like that. There's a for loop
in many of the NumPy functions, and those for loops have been threaded in NumPy itself.
If you just tell NumPy to use multiple processors, whenever you use the NumPy functions,
it will try to run these for loops in parallel. It works behind the scenes, so the only thing
you need to tell it is this OMP number of threads, which is a pretty cryptic variable,
but basically what it tells is that use multiple processors.
And this is also MKL and a third possible option. Usually, those are already set so that you don't
need to set them. Usually, NumPy will just use multiple threads. You will see that by
if you run NumPy and check what your processor load is, that Python process will be using something
like 400 or 800 percent of a CPU. So that means it's already running on multiple processors.
Threading is also common for web applications and that sort of thing, but because they're not,
well, for scientific computing they are not so relevant. We won't be going to that, but
But there's like Python has lots of these async things, but they are not relevant.
So I'll just mention it, but if you see parallel using that, they are basically mainly for
web applications and that sort of thing.
So one big thing kind of worth mentioning, like if you are trying to do multi-threading
on your own, I said Python doesn't do it.
So it's, in fact, something that was kind of a choice that
was made when the Python language was developed
or is being developed.
So there's something called a global interpreter lock.
And basically, that means that there can only ever
be one thread, one process running Python code.
So if you want to run Python code,
like have multiple processes running your Python code,
you actually need to start multiple Python interpreters,
which is exactly what the next thing will do.
So this is a way around.
Multiprocessing is a Python library,
and it's a way around this issue.
So if you actually find that whatever libraries
you are using are not multitreaded,
so you're not doing calculations in NumPy,
or you are doing something a bit more complicated in Python
and you know that you need to kind of split it
into multiple processes,
multiprocessing is a way to do it.
There's a bunch of nice libraries built upon multiprocessing that might be more useful,
but well, I guess we'll write a list into the notes in a moment, but here we'll just
try to use multiprocessing.
Yeah, let's check on, like, I can run the demo here and see what happens.
So here we have an example.
So we have a function.
So we have a function that – well, maybe you can explain and I can write.
Well, yeah.
If you type – I mean, this is a very simple function.
It just calculates the square of the number that you put in.
But this is a Python function on purpose, so we're assuming that it's somehow something
we cannot do in NumPy directly.
And then map will run that function on every number in the list that you give it.
So you notice it gives you the squares of every number.
So one squared is one, two squared is four, and so on, six squared is 36.
That was really fast because it's a small list, but it was running pure Python code,
If it was a big list, it would be a lot slower than, say, numpy.
I'll mention here that this might look, for those people who haven't used functional programming
kind of things, this might look a bit strange, but it's basically like a for loop in a small space.
It is running the same function to every element in the list.
Yeah, you might see a more Pythonic version might be something like this.
Yeah, okay, that's the same.
Yeah, this is basically like a map function.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's a good example.
Yeah, but basically it's the same thing, but using these maps makes sense when we go to the
The reason we use the map function there, demonstrated, is because multiprocessing comes
with its own version of the map function.
So if you now import pool from multiprocessing and then pool contains the map function.
Oh, okay.
It's from multiprocessing input pool, not with.
Oops.
Yeah.
My mistake.
Was looking ahead already.
Yeah.
And then, yeah, then you need to get a pool or yeah, create a pool.
So, so what we have, there's a great way of, of, or a great
explanation of why this is called pool, but it's essentially a set of like.
So it gives you a set of processors that you can use to run stuff.
So you can run this square function with multiple processes.
Um, it didn't actually return anything.
I guess you have to probably need to store it somewhere.
Yeah.
Okay.
So yeah, this does the same thing and you didn't see the
speed up of course because it's so fast.
Anyway, we could have a much bigger list and then you would
see it.
But so what the multiprocessing pool does it it takes the
list it splits it up between all the processors available.
and then runs this function on all of those processes to some part of the work, basically.
Yeah, and in general, I would say, here we give a list to it, but map basically works on any kind
of iterable thing. So in Python, you see a lot of these iterable things, like something that
at least is an iterable thing, but you can have other things as well, like iterators.
And what map does is basically take something from the iterator and it runs a function on it.
And if you use the normal map function in Python, you do it one by one in one processor,
basically. But here we have a processor pool. So, we have multiple processors.
Usually the number is decided to be the number of processors in your computer. Of course,
you can set it yourself. But you have a number of processors, and we read from the iterator,
and then we give each processor one at a time.
Send those one by one to the different processors.
Yeah.
Or really, actually, many at a time, because sending one number is not efficient.
Yes, many at a time. Of course, the multiprocessing library then collects the
results in the same order back so that you get the same kind of correspondence between the input
and the output but but basically now you do the mapping in parallel. Okay so let's now go to the
exercise so there's an exercise one where you use multiprocessing and then you can also move
on to exercise two which is more of a discussion about running on a cluster. So a cluster is a
a supercomputer. It's a system with a lot of computers in a fast network. But yeah,
mainly do exercise one, and then if you have extra time, take a look at exercise two.
So we'll have 15 minutes for it.
During the exercise we'll try to answer any unanswered questions in the notes and we'll
bring them up after the if there's anything interesting or any especially good questions
we'll raise them up. Okay, so that's it for now. See you in 15 minutes. Bye. Bye.
you
Hey welcome back. So yeah there was one more thing we wanted to mention before MPI.
Which is that a lot of the libraries, like we mentioned in the beginning, a lot of the libraries have some sort of parallelism built in, usually multi-threading.
And often it just works out of the box.
But also there are ways of setting the number of workers and using parallelism through some settings.
So, yeah, it's usually usually a good idea to use this like the developers of the packages they have most likely tested that this parallelism actually speeds up the code.
So, instead of like making some parallelism outside of what the developers have intended, using their method is most likely the most efficient way of getting parallelism.
So, for example, like just like an example library that you might encounter is like a
ski kit learn.
If you're doing like machine learning or data analysis and that sort of stuff, putting models
there.
And let's say we are in the user guide, we just go to the user guide.
Like this is what, like when people ask about parallelism, this is what I usually do.
I open the packet space and then I press control F to search and then I search for parallel
And there's like a page on parallelism here.
And if we look at here, they mentioned that they're using this job lib library,
which is similar to, or it's built upon multi-processing.
It's a nice library.
We'll mention other tools like this in the notes after the MPI session.
But basically it says that there's this end jobs parameter, like on estimators
that you can like, you can put it there and then it uses parallelism basically.
And then you can, you also use this, uh, this higher level
parallelism and these open MP stuff.
And they have various ways they explain, like, uh, how do you get the best performance?
So it's usually a good idea to check, check the guide, whether it's parallel
mentioned anything parallel is the magic world, uh, word usually, uh, that, that
can be found in various documentations.
And you can then use that.
Another thing that in the notes, I think it's good to mention.
So at least one person got an error that from multiprocessing,
that it cannot pickle the object something.
something. And that happens because, like we mentioned, Python actually doesn't allow
multiple processes, so they cannot actually just read memory or read the same memory.
So what multiprocessing does to get around this is that it essentially writes the function
and everything it needs to run that function to disk, starts another Python process, and
And then that Python process reads it from the disk or if it's like if the disk can be
on RAM.
So the file can be in fast memory, but still it needs to be possible to write it to disk.
And that the main thing is that that causes some restrictions.
So sometimes things just don't work and there's ways of getting around this.
You can read the instructions or try to ask people, but it gets a bit complicated.
And in general, let's say you have a function that does really complex things and that sort of
thing. If you want to run it in parallel, all of the different parallel processes need to know
about that function and what the function has eaten. If it uses global variables or whatever,
all of that needs to be transferred to that other process. So the more complex your parallel thing
is, the harder it is usually to parallelize. So usually it's a good idea to parallelize.
Yeah, keep it simple. Have a simple function that will be executed in Parallel and then
return to a bigger program or something like that.
So basically, if it's a method of a class, it needs the entire class. If it uses a global
variable, it needs the entire file. And if you're calling multiprocessing from that same
file, it will just fail. So one way around this often is to just move the function that
you're running into a different file and often that will help but sometimes not.
So just be aware of that.
It gets complicated and try to use parallelism from inside the existing libraries rather
than writing your own if possible.
Now MPI though is usually not built into the libraries for a very important reason which
is that it always needs to be run with this MPI run program, basically, that sets up an
environment for.
So what MPI does, it runs completely separate processes and then tells them some information
about the other processes so that they can communicate.
So these can be running on completely different parts of completely different computers as
As long as they know the IP address to the other computer and there's an Ethernet cable
or Wi-Fi connection or something, so that they can communicate.
Of course, that would be quite slow if you send a lot of information back and forth.
In principle, that is something you can do.
So MPI is a very different paradigm because you just run copies of the program.
All the copies run everything from the beginning.
All the copies run all of your code, basically.
the main difference. Whereas in multiprocessing, it just takes the function and tries to put it in
a file and read that file and run it. With MPI, all of the copies will run everything unless you
tell them specifically to not do that. There are other frameworks as well that work in a similar way
that they basically set up some network configuration and they do their own configuration.
For example, PyTorch has a Torch run, and there's Ray, which is this parallel library as well.
But there's many frameworks that do this. Everybody starts, and then they just know
about where the others are. They communicate in some way. In MPI's case, the MPI will handle this,
okay, who are you? Where are you? But in many other cases, you might have master processes
and clients connecting to the server.
So for MPI, I mean, MPI is kind of the lowest level.
It's kind of the basis, again, like multiprocessing
is the basis of a lot of libraries.
MPI also is the basis for a lot of stuff.
So, okay, so we'll just show a quick example,
but this is something you may not be able to run
because it requires that you install
not just the Python library,
but also you need to install,
like MPI as a system-level library. It's not written in Python. So it's possible to do it in
Conda, but we don't assume that you have done that. You can try. Maybe you have the functions
or not. Okay, so what Simo is doing here is first importing MPI for Pi, and then there's some magic
stuff that, I mean, yeah, I could explain what those things are doing. But the main thing is that
that, you get the size, which is the number of processors that are running this program.
And then you get the rank, which is the unique identifier for this particular copy. It's
a number from zero to size, basically. So that's what you have to work with, really.
have a single number that identifies this particular copy and then there are MPI functions
that allow you to send information to other copies. You have to know the number of the
other copy. So from these building blocks, you can build a lot of stuff, of course, but
it takes a bit of work.
Yeah.
Okay, so let's just try this. So this is just printing the rank, the identifier number and
the number of processes.
And to run an MPI program, you need to use MPI run.
And you can give it a number.
Okay.
Well, I gave it the wrong name.
Oh, yes.
You need to give it the correct program, it will run better.
If you try to run the wrong program, it will not run as well.
Yeah, yeah.
That's a good hint.
Okay, so yeah.
So it ran two copies of the program,
one of them has identifier 1
and the other one has identifier 0.
So if you were, for example,
doing what we were doing previously,
where you split
this list into
two multiple processes,
you would need to have
perhaps just, usually you just
set it up with
process number 0 and then you
send a part of you. You actually have to write manually write the code to send the part
of the list to the other process. We'll do a different example. Let's just let's just
run the example in the notes. It has all of the stuff that we just ran, but it's also
yeah, like the different so yeah, okay. So the different identify the different processes
are now doing a different thing, and in the end, it's being collected.
Yeah, so all of this code, what's important in the code basically, we have the function
that all of them will run independently and all of them will do their own part of the
whole thing, but the important part is here in the line 39, where we have this communication
gather so basically we gather everything and then we have this root so we gather all of that
information to the processor zero so you can have this kind of like collective everybody
send the information to the process zero and the process zero will then print. So that's an example
of one of these functions that allow the processes to communicate with each other.
There's also a send, for example, that just means one process sends information to one
other process.
Okay.
I guess we probably don't want to go too much into detail about this because we also
want to spend some time on all the rest of the material.
Yeah.
I'll quickly mention that the MPI is commonly used in scientific codes and that sort of
where you might have a grid or collective, like you can't solve some problem in a big grid or
something like that, where everybody talks to their neighbors. But the communication,
how do you communicate? It depends heavily on the problem. So you need to usually provide the
communication. Who tells who what information? Based on your problem, you usually need to
to decide yourself how to do it.
So there's one big rule of thumb
when it comes to multi-threading or multi-processing
and MPI, which is because multi-threading
and multi-processing usually run a very small path,
like a single for loop in parallel,
whereas MPI will run all of the code in parallel.
So in MPI, you want to split at the highest level possible.
So as much as possible get split between the processes and then they're just like occasionally sending messages to each other.
In multi-threading, basically you want to parallelize the smallest loop or one loop at a time.
So they tend to be used quite differently and that's also the reason why often the libraries are parallelized with this multi-threading,
multiprocessing things and not with MPI, but if you're using MPI then you usually have to do it
yourself or use something that's specifically intended with MPI. Okay, so another thing is,
like we said, a lot of libraries are using multithreading and the reason they can do
it efficiently is because they're not written in Python. Python needs to use a multi-processing
approach because one process can only run at a time. But in C, C++, Fortran, whatever,
in all of these fast compiled languages, you can run multiple threads at a time.
Multiple threads can run code at the same time. Almost everything is written, has a back end
that runs the fast parts using libraries written in these languages.
So if you ended up in a situation where you need to kind of extend those libraries a bit,
there's multiple ways of writing C, C++ code for Rust and then calling that from Python
to get the thing done.
Yeah, there are also...
You can just call your library from Python.
There are also like Python libraries
such as Numba and Jax nowadays
that can do stuff like
just-in-time compilation
where they like take your Python function
and then they compile it
into a faster C++ function
without you ever leaving Python.
But they are...
They need additional things usually
things usually. Your code needs to be written in a way that it can be compiled, not be like
generic Python code. It doesn't exactly support general Python. It's a subset of Python that you
have to use, but it allows you to write the program, write the function in Python and then
run it as if it was written in C, which is really convenient and usually actually the
first thing you would want to do or try. Yeah. And before we leave for a break,
we can mention Dusk as well. So if you're dealing with big pandas data frames,
if you have a lot of data that you need to process, Dusk is this kind of
of like improvement on pandas or more parallelizable version
of pandas that allows the probe, like what it does basically
is that when you set in your pandas code or whatever,
you select certain rows here, calculate average of them,
and whatever, you have some operations that you do.
Dusk can create this kind of like a computational graph
of it and then it can execute it in parallel. So let's say it will run like the data in pieces
or something like that and it can handle the parallelism on the back end. And if you're
dealing with large data sets like big data sets of data frames, it's a very useful tool and it's
used in like banks and that sort of stuff because it makes it possible to analyze like huge amounts
of, let's say, customer data or something.
So I started a list of useful libraries for parallel Python libraries, and I wrote that
the task is useful for large data sets.
There's also JobLabel, which is, I guess, an easier way of doing maps with multiprocessing.
I guess it probably does other things as well.
Yes, so we'll continue adding more stuff there, and if you have any more questions, just put them in the notes.
Yeah, and please add any library you know of or you use that we may not know of yet, because that's always good to keep up to date.
Yeah, and also if you, at the end of the day, if you have some certain cases that you would
want us to present or certain libraries you would want us to present in the coming years,
let us know, because there's so many of these nowadays, so it's hard to say what are the
most important ones for our users.
But what sort of use cases you want us to demonstrate.
Otherwise, so we intentionally left a good amount of time for discussion here.
So I'm looking for questions in the notes that we might want to bring up.
There's a good question there, how can I install OpenMPI?
Well, Conda has an OpenMPI installation package there in it.
So you can just Conda install OpenMPI, at least from Conda Forge, and MPF API as well.
that's, I would highly recommend using that compared to like
installing an MPI by yourself, unless you're using it in a very
large scenario in a computational cluster or
something. But if you want to work in in like one machine or
something like that, the MPI in the in Conda is good, good
enough in most cases, like, or if you have a, if you're working
in a computational cluster, the maintenance of that cluster
will usually provide you with an MPI already,
because it needs extra stuff to be able to do it.
There will probably be multiple versions you can choose from.
Another one, so this is answered in the notes,
but benchmarking libraries,
because we talked a good bit in the beginning
about how before thinking about parallelizing,
you should do benchmarking and try to just make the code
faster with the existing libraries,
which is usually enough.
So if you have one specific function you know you want to benchmark,
then timeit is a really good library.
And if you have an entire code,
or when you're starting you basically just have one entire code,
you want to figure out what is the slow part in that code,
then scalene is a good option.
So, that's on this question, mark this question number nine, but should we, is it easy to
find in notes?
Yeah, I added to the libraries list.
Okay, good.
So, it's benchmarking and yeah.
Yeah.
Guidelines for deciding knowing in what way I should parallelize my code.
I would say like the first thing is like check out the embarrassingly parallel.
That's usually the most efficient way of parallelization because it's like if you have a natural thing in your code.
code that is embarrassingly parallelizable. For example, you run it with multiple parameters,
multiple datasets, and that is usually the way to go because that scales infinitely, basically,
because you can always launch more processes. As long as you have more data, right?
Yeah, as long as you have more data. Yeah. And after that, I would say probably check
the libraries that you're using, whether they support parallelization.
But yeah, so then if a single case just takes too long to run, like several days,
so if you're running on a cluster or on a supercomputer, you can usually reserve it
for a few days. But then if something breaks, you might lose everything. So it's important to
build in some checkpointing. So write everything to disk so that if you have to restart it,
it can continue from where it was. That's already very useful. It's not parallelization exactly,
but it just allows you to run for longer. Then if it still takes way too long,
then you just need to make it faster and you might need to parallelize in some way.
And then, if there's a way of splitting the data, like if you're running a simulation with a grid of points, you can split those points and run independently for each of those points.
That's a good case for MPI, possibly.
if you have big loops over a lot of small things inside those you might be able to parallelize with multi-threading options.
So basically though, well the multi-threading thing basically means use libraries that are multi-threaded,
multithreaded, which means NumPy, SciPy, Torch, TensorFlow, whatever. It depends on what you're
doing, but almost everything is multithreaded if it does a lot of calculations. So just
try to combine calls to NumPy, for example. If you have multiple calls to NumPy with the
same data, try to make it one call so that it doesn't get split.
One thing also, there's a few questions in the chat about the multiprocessing example,
like locking up. It might be due to the Jupyter locking the GL, the global interpreter lock,
what we were talking about. Because if you have a Jupyter, you have a JupyterLab running
Python interpreter, and then you try to run multiprocessing there, it might be that the
Jupyter and how it processes the sales and that sort of thing, it should work, but there
might be a situation where it somehow locks the global interpreter lock.
So that might happen, but it's hard to say.
We will check the examples and we will verify that.
There's at least two questions about this.
Yeah.
So we'll verify.
solution, like if you take the solution from the web page and it doesn't work, then it
might be, yeah, you might want to check compared to the solution.
Okay. We are out of time though. So let's take a break and then we'll move on to packaging.
Yeah. I'll quickly mention that there was also like a question about pooling, like
pool one getting bad results or like using pool was worse than not using pool. And this is
exactly what might happen in a case where you parallelize a thing that actually doesn't benefit
from parallelization. So the example of course is like a trivial example that we have. So it's a
very low, like the processor will just go through it in an instant anyways. Like it's going to be
like nanoseconds or microseconds or something to calculate it. So adding the constructions of,
okay, we'll construct a parallel pool and then we'll give everyone their own process to run,
it's a huge amount of overhead. But the thing happens is that when we are getting to the
runtimes of seconds or minutes, then suddenly the overhead isn't that big. But usually you need to
figure out what is the part in the code that requires me to parallelize it.
And usually, also, I'll mention that, for example, the map thing, writing it as a NumPy array and
just squaring the NumPy array would be much faster than any pooling because NumPy already
does the parallelization inside. So, not using Python objects, but using NumPy arrays would be
always faster than doing the pooling thing. So it's a trivial example, but it's just to
demonstrate how to use the tools. Okay. But yeah, so we are out of time. So
do take a break and walk around a bit. Let's come back in 10 minutes. All right. Bye.
Bye.
you
Hello.
Hello. I hope everyone had a good break and is refreshed after 10 minutes. So, let's go
to packaging.
And yeah, we talked about all the different libraries
in the Python ecosystem.
Now we are going to add one, or at least add one
into the test thing, but show you
how to create your own package and how
to publish your own code, or at least make it easy for you
to use across all of your projects.
So should we do some talking first or just jump directly in?
I would jump in.
Or why are we doing it?
Yeah, I guess the main thing is to make it easy for you
to use your code.
If you have a piece of code that you
want to use in multiple projects,
make it easy for you to do that.
And just have it all in one place
where you can maintain that bit.
well, you can just maintain it in one place.
Or even to get it to the point
where other people can use your code
and only one person still has to maintain it,
which is, it saves time.
Other people might even be maintaining your code
at some point.
I'd actually say that is probably the most important point
for packaging in the end,
that you make it easy for other people to use it.
Yeah.
So that it is actually used.
Yes.
So, what do we need to make a Python package?
Well, we need some structure.
Well, yeah. There needs to be some structure that everybody knows is going to be there.
And that's basically kind of predefined.
There will be modules because a Python file is called a module so you will have code in
Python files and then we collect related modules into packages and in here we will
show how to collect them into a package. Then if you want other people to be able to use your code
you need a license. That's also if you want to accept contributions from anyone else you
need a license because they need to give you the access to use the code and that the license file
is usually in the root of the project the root folder of the project. You need a readme file
because you need to tell people what the code is and what it does. It's also good to have
other documentation but often in a small project or when you're starting readme is enough
documentation but it's also good to have other documentation and automated testing is great
because it allows you to check that everything works well at least like the things you are
testing work by just running one command. And it helps you a lot in staying backward
compatible so that what you're changing doesn't change for earlier results. Yeah,
Yeah, that's very important, very useful.
Okay, so those are the things we'll cover.
I'm actually not sure if we cover testing.
Well, let's see.
But first we'll start with creating a package.
So we'll assume that we have some useful functions
we have written that we want to use in other projects.
So the first of them is add.
Yeah, imagine that this is a useful function.
So this will add two numbers together.
Here we are.
OK, great.
Let's also write a subtract.pi, or subtracting.pi,
which will subtract two numbers from each other.
Okay, and finally, one thing that's slightly more complicated, which will do a numerical
integral.
You are cheating a bit, we don't really write the code, we just use a library.
Well, yes, but you should not write the code
for a numerical integral.
You should use SciPy.
So there's one question.
Can you do this packaging in JupyterLab?
So you can write the code in JupyterLab.
You can create the files in JupyterLab.
So almost everything we do, you can do in JupyterLab.
But it is, at least for me, we're
dealing with the file system more than with Python code.
So it's kind of more natural to do it here.
You can also, so, okay.
So the point is Jupyter is more made for, I guess, notebooks
and the packaging part,
like it's about creating Python files
and running commands in terminal.
So you can do it in Jupyter.
It's fine, but it's not using notebooks.
Sorry, Richard.
Thomas, can you make your fonts bigger?
Is that big enough?
Well, probably good.
We can see what people say.
I think it's probably good.
I probably can't change them in the editor, at least not quickly.
Yeah, the editor will probably follow the terminal font.
Let's see.
Can you run ls just to see what's in the current directory now?
So yeah, we have some Python modules that are useful and we want to use in other places.
I think for now, if you scroll down in the notes a little bit, you'll see a general structure
for a package or what the folder could look like.
I think the first thing we want to do is to create a folder where we put all the modules.
So this will essentially be like, this is the Python stuff.
This is the thing that's called a package.
So this is where all the Python code goes.
And it's a folder.
It's just a normal folder, and we just move all of the .py files there.
So do you want us to start here with the project?
So is this what we're currently looking at, the project folder for our example?
example?
I mean, OK, so you created a folder that
will be the project rules.
OK.
OK, so let's just go there.
And then there we create another folder that's the package.
I'll just push all of this over so that we.
So this is a very common structure in Q.
We are back in here, but.
Yeah, so now let's create another folder.
So basically, the reason for this
is we want to have one thing we can import.
Like, when you import NumPy, you import all of NumPy.
We want to import calculator and be
able to import all of these functions at once.
But now, actually, we can't quite do that yet.
What we can do now is run from calculator import adding,
for example.
But we need to tell what Python needs to do when
we want to import calculator.
And we do that by adding this __init__.py.
That's something that it's kind of predefined in Python.
And it is what turns a folder into a Python package.
So here you can import things that you
want to be imported when you import this package.
And this is just normal Python code, really.
So actually, what happens is when you import calculator,
when you import this folder or this package,
it will run this code that Umesh is now typing.
And everything that's then defined in this Python code,
all of that will appear as calculator.something.
So there will be calculator.add, calculator.subtract,
and calculator.integral, and also calculator.version
with the underscores.
OK, so this looks good.
Should we now try importing it just to see?
Or, well, yeah, let's import it first,
and then we'll add a license and readme.
I hope I started the environment.
Let's see.
Well, right now, it's all in this folder, so you don't actually need to be in the environment.
SciPy isn't, potentially.
Oh, SciPy might not be there. That's true.
Well, if you try to import Calculator, if there's no SciPy, can you run...
run so okay you just run from calculator can you run import calculator
no module name calculator is it yeah it has an init file oh uh wait
i'm not entirely sure but i think well okay let's see
Okay.
Nope.
Interesting.
Did you actually move to the folder?
Can you type ls?
Okay.
I'm in the wrong folder.
Yes.
You are in the wrong folder.
Okay.
So now you can import calculator and you have SciPy.
Yep.
So it didn't actually, it didn't fail.
All right.
So yeah, that's why we add this init.py and that's why we have all of these files in a
single folder.
You can, of course, you can have a more nested structure with multiple folders, but the init.py
makes this a package.
And then, well, you can also try, you can do from calculator import add.
This actually, actually this does require an input.py, yeah, okay.
Seems to work.
Yeah, seems to be doing things.
So let's exit this interpreter, or if you
want to try something else, fine.
Try an integral or something.
OK, yeah, let's exit the interpreter.
And now we don't have a license file or a readme file.
So we don't need to decide on a license for this test case,
but let's just create the file and a readme file as well.
Let's just create them for now.
Yeah.
They are empty.
Okay.
So, yeah.
Now we have two empty files.
If you don't, press again to show what we have.
Okay.
So, we have calculator, we have license, and readme.
Now, the next thing to make this a package, oh, what is the time?
22.
22 passed.
Okay.
So, yeah, so the next thing we need to add to make this package installable is this piproject.toml.
And yeah, just create a file and we'll just copy the stuff from the example.
And this is what I do anyway.
Like when I start a project, I copy a piproject.toml from somewhere and then I modify it according
to like my needs.
So you probably want to change my name because,
so the reason is we will actually be uploading this
to the Python package index,
which means you can install it with pip.
And that means, yeah, so you don't want,
you want a unique name.
If you have, if you try with a name that already exists
in PyPi, that's already a Python package,
then it will not work.
So let's just identify it as the package for Python SciComm 2023.
That's a good idea.
Okay, otherwise everything is okay.
It depends on SciPy.
There's a quick example, a quick description and readme file.
Yeah, so you can also add your name and email if you want to.
We could add additional ones.
Yeah, you can add multiple authors. You can add more dependencies. That's all. And, yeah,
there is something called a long description.
I'll leave that at example.org.
Okay. Yeah. So, this is it. And what this does, it makes your package installable with
pip. So, now we can run pip install. And, well, it's not yet on PyPI. It's not yet in
index, so we need to point it by pointing to this folder if we want to install. But let's just
demonstrate it quickly. So pip install dot. Dot is the current folder. Okay. You don't have pip.
Oh, okay. Okay, we will fix this. But that should have worked.
And if you are in the Anaconda environment, base environment, I think this should work.
I would just pip.
So the next thing we do is we go to the exercise which is essentially creating the package
we just created and testing that you can install it locally.
So we will give you, now we're running a bit late, we'll give you 15 minutes anyway because
This is the important part and that means we'll be back at 11.40.
All right, so, yeah, good luck and see you in 15 minutes. Bye.
you
Hello. So, yeah, let's go straight into PyPy. This will not take that long. So, we do this
as a demonstration, but you can also follow along and upload your package to test PyPy
preferably, because unless you have an actual package you're going to want to upload.
So yeah, we will be uploading to testpypy. I guess I should explain what pypy is, right?
So pypy stands for Python Package Index.
And when you type pip install and just the package name instead of a folder, for example,
then it will look for that package in PyPy in the Python package index and yeah you can push
your packages there and then people can install them with just pip install the name. So it's a
very useful thing to have. So yeah we'll show you how to use it and you can follow along if you want
to and you can upload something to test PyPy with these instructions. And yeah test PyPy is
kind of what it says so it's for testing and your packages will get removed rather quickly.
I don't remember how quickly exactly but it's not meant for actual packages. I have the impression
it's not that quickly I just found that there's still one that I probably put on there a year ago.
Okay I'm kind of surprised but okay well fine. Anyway so it is meant for testing
So yeah, so let's just go through the steps on how to get this package into PyPy.
So yeah, first you run build.
This doesn't work.
Okay.
Build is a package and cannot be directly executed, but that's kind of the point, isn't it?
Should be.
Okay, so maybe we need to update the instructions a bit. Let's see.
What about twine.build, maybe?
OK, that could be.
Or, well, OK, let's install twine.
Yeah, OK, that's the next step.
So Python packaging guide tells you to, oh, come on.
And we are using setup tools.
Okay.
Well, it tells you to install build using Python, using pip.
Let's try that.
This is a relatively new site, right?
PyPi instructions.
Can you try running pip install, or did you try installing Twine and it didn't work?
I tried installing Twine and it didn't want to do, so I'm going back to the base environment
to see.
Oh, okay.
This, well, we'll try for another two minutes, say, but.
Actually, Twine might just be the uploader.
No, pip install Twine.
Okay.
Okay, and then pip install build.
Okay, now let's try Python 3 minus m build.
The tree is in the wrong place.
Yeah.
So there has been a relatively recent change in.
OK, that did something.
Good?
Yeah, that looks correct.
OK.
And then we'll try Twine upload.
So Twine is a Python package that
uploads things into the Python package index.
here we are specifying to put it into the test index. You do need a username and a password,
you need to create an account to upload anything and it will of course be associated with your
account. Okay there we are and now we can try installing it. So normally if you put
something into PyPy, it's just pip install package name, but in this case we need to
tell it to use the test PyPy instead. What was the name? It was underscore after four, I think.
I tried like this because it seems like it changed the underscores.
Oh, okay. All right, so yeah.
underscore is not allowed now it's installing our package yeah and now we should have it
so is it now called calculator for pi sc 2023 or is it just called calculator we will see
oh well they are definitely not with minus signs it changes minus signs to underscores
Okay, well, we did run into a couple of problems here, but okay, fine.
So we need to update this example a little bit to use SciPy correctly and to, well, I
guess the instructions for uploading the PyPy were correct, but somehow it didn't work in
that one environment.
So something called build was already installed,
but it wasn't.
Oh, no, no, maybe it just wasn't installed
and it was just a folder.
In any case, it worked.
I have an impression that the SciPy version that
is being used here is not really what we want.
Could be.
Yeah, the SciPy 0.1.
0.1 is not what we want. Why would it – oh, because it's from test.py. It got SciPy from
test.py. So, it didn't get the latest version. It got whatever they used for testing a long time
ago when they tested uploading SciPy last time. All right. In any case, that is how you upload
packages to scipy and also to pypy to the python package index and that makes installing them a lot
more straightforward for your friends and collaborators. All right so there's one thing
I quickly want to point out this question about what the license and readme files should say.
So in the exercise description we added a lot of details about well essentially we just added
links to Code Refinery materials which you can read up on your own time or come to the
Code Refinery course. We would love to have you there. There's something about documentation
in general, so that also tells you some ways of writing README files. In social coding,
is a part about software licensing the general instruction the most important thing is use an
existing license don't write your own because it's legal language and yeah it's better to leave
that for the lawyers and then there's a section on testing automated testing which we mentioned
it's nice thing to have in a package but we didn't actually show you how to do it so there
is a section on that. Otherwise we are right on time for a break. Anything else?
I think not really. All right, so let's take a 10-minute break and then come back for web APIs.
All right, bye.
you
Thank you very much.
We are back.
So the last real lesson of the day is now web APIs.
So Enrico, how do we start?
Yes, so maybe it's good to start with understanding
what do we mean with web API.
And I don't know if everybody knows what API means,
but most likely everybody knows what UI means, user interface.
So for example, most, let's say they want to search something with the browser, with
the window, which is your user interface, you go to a website like google.com and that's
the interface that you work with.
You type something and you get an answer, the search results.
So API, the interface now is application program interface.
So it's like that the interface is not designed anymore for humans who can, you know, use the
mouse and type and do things like that.
that we can basically use machines.
So basically this kind of goes down
to the concept of server.
I don't think we need to go into the details
what is a server, but in general,
we are all using these servers,
meaning these softwares that when we ask for a page
or when we ask for some information,
whether it's with our smartphones or with our computers,
we get an answer, so we are served with an answer.
So what we are gonna cover here is that sometimes
in some cases, it's very useful to interact
with these sources of data that are not physically stored
on the same machine where you are.
Like the example that I gave that you might wanna query
something from Google, but instead of looking
at the answer yourself, you can have Python
look at the at the answer. And then of course there are other more advanced uses of the so-called
APIs, meaning that there are companies who might give you access to a specific API to do something.
I guess you all have heard about OpenAI and ChatGPT. That's another example that, you know,
it would have been possible to store this huge GPT model on your local machine so you can,
for example via Python, send the query or like the prompt that you would send to the remote
computer and then get an answer back. The most simple way of doing this programmatically with
Python is with this package called requests. So request is a Python library that makes
requests to web servers as I just gave you some example. You see here in the bottom there is this
Basically, the web page for this request is embedded there, and they label it as HTTP
for humans.
Maybe I could ask Richard, what does HTTP mean, even though we type it almost every
day?
Yeah.
So, HTTP means Hypertext Transfer Protocol, and it's basically the way everything communicates
with the web server.
you send the request saying, I would like to see this web page,
and it sends back saying, OK, here's the data you requested.
And you can give other parameters,
like what languages my web browser is configured to show,
or things like that.
And for humans, means that request
is trying to make it a way that's well that's
easily easy to use by humans so they really
care about the user interface of this.
Exactly, which basically simplifies your work.
As usual, maybe one of the biggest lesson
here in this course is that often there's
no need to reinvent any wheels.
There are already very good packages
that can do the heavy lifting for you.
So here in this retrieve data from API,
the introduction text there is basically telling you
that there is a list of many
of these application program interfaces
that can be used without a key.
So this is something that if you will start working
with external API, sometimes you need to have a key.
For example, in the OpenAI chat GPT example
that I was giving you earlier,
if you want to query the remote model,
you need to basically show that it's you through a key,
through a token.
But in this case, we're gonna use an API called cat fact,
which is basically it's going to return
some random fact about cats.
And so maybe, you know, enough with the talking,
should we just get started with some Python?
Sure.
Okay, I'm arranging things.
Yep.
So I guess I will make a new notebook in my place
and rename it to, OK.
So how should I start?
Yeah, so if you scroll a bit down,
and you can also do the same for those who are watching,
there's a section a little bit more down in the materials
where we basically start with the import for this library.
And then the code will also have this URL.
So URL, it means Uniform Resource Locator.
It's basically, again, what we normally type daily.
It's the address of this,
in this case of this remote server API.
And then we can use this library,
this request library by getting this URL.
So what happens?
So now there should be something inside this response.
So it's a response object.
So with objects, you know that with dot and name of the name
of the field, you can actually get some content.
And here we see basically a string that starts with the B
and lots of stuff.
So, the string looks like JSON, but it has a B in front.
What does the B stand for, Richard?
That's a thing I like talking about.
So, it looks like a string, but the B in front means Python is interpreting this as binary data.
So basically, it's not assuming it has a text encoding.
In Python, all the things that look like strings are either unicode strings, meaning they should
contain text and can have any unicode character, like each index is a character, or B, which
means each position in the string is raw, like a raw byte from 0 to 255.
But I think we probably shouldn't go too much into that.
It's something you can get deep into later.
But then the rest of the whatever comes after the B
looks like JSON.
Did we introduce before what do we
mean with JSON, the JSON format?
I don't know.
Did we?
Maybe I should say again anyway.
Yeah.
So JSON is a way to turn objects into strings.
So this looks like it would be a Python dictionary,
but actually, it's all encoded in a string.
And basically, JSON is a way to do
that encoding in a way that's standardized and shareable
among different computers.
And many, many APIs that basically will return strings,
they will actually give you the answer in JSON.
And this is why this response library also has a dot JSON function.
So what if we tried the, um, exactly that part of the, so now basically is
this like, like, um, dictionary basically, let's see, yes, it is a dictionary.
So then we could know easily access, for example, using the keys, the
different elements yeah all right instead this this what you did earlier now it's listed
as bytes because it's it has to be the yeah
so now basically you are you're yeah you're putting the this dictionary into a variable
corresponds underscore json and then you're getting the key fact yeah all right so so far so good we
saw basically that we can basically get some data and get is one of these terms using this
http protocol but sometimes we also want to maybe send or at least tell the remote server that you
know maybe we don't want to just get the page like in this specific case but we want to filter
according to what the remote API is allowing us.
So often you might, again, have seen this
when you browse the internet,
you might see a URL and then a question mark
followed by various values or like key equal values.
So these are basically,
these are called parameters for the GET query.
And in this specific case, for example,
we use a remote API that is called
universities.hypolabs.com, which is basically
providing a list of all the universities in the planet.
But you see here that now this URL
has a parameter as a question mark, country equal Finland.
So if we run this code and we get the request from this URL,
Will it most likely give us basically a list
of the universities in Finland?
And as you can see already, indeed, it does.
In this case, why did you put like,
can we remind people what is this column 2?
And this says it's giving the first two elements
of the array.
So if I remove it, then it will be a log response.
Exactly. And we will see all the list. But then this is the thing. So now we were passing this
parameter through this question mark, followed by key, name of the parameter and the value.
But this library, the response library is actually,
with the response library is also possible to pass the parameters via the Python request.
So, should we try this bit of code, Richa, where now, instead of, so the URL now is different,
it's just a general URL for the API.
But now we pass the parameter country equal to Finland, basically.
So I've just copied the whole thing.
Yeah.
I guess the key point here is this parameters equals parameters, which is a dictionary.
Exactly.
And now it will give the same results, but you can try, for example, with your own country,
you can put Sweden, you can put Norway, and then you can get programmatically, you can
get the list of all the universities that are at least listed in this remote API.
So this is basically the main idea behind this remote APIs.
rather than talking we could let people try exercise one it's an exercise where in this
case you don't have to how can I say think the solution the solution is actually following
after the exercise so it's an opportunity for you to test another API so even copy pasting
is fine and exploring the output and when it gives we could assign 10 minutes if these
are too short for exercise 1 you can also start with exercise 2 and then later we will
comment on what is going on with exercise 2. Does this sound like a good plan, Richard?
Yes, it is. Yes, very good.
So let's have until 12.23 start with exercise 1 and if you have time do exercise 2 and then
we will come back and do a recap and more stuff.
OK, sounds good.
See you later.
Bye.
you
There was a nice interesting question in our notes document, are there any best practices
or general guidelines, but when it comes to the coding, the examples that we gave you
with this request library, it's a good starting point for working with web APIs.
But then one should also consider maybe the ethical and sometimes even the legal aspect.
Ethical, it can be in the sense that, you know, are you allowed to use this data?
Is it ethical to scrape this data?
we do this for research purposes, so we can do these things, we don't break any law.
But then there's also the ethics of the fact that you are sending many queries to some
remote computer that maybe you don't want to overload the remote server, I don't know,
with 1,000 queries every second. So then often if you, let's say that you need to scrape
many many web pages and we will soon show briefly a little example on that maybe you
don't wanna you know maybe you wanna have a break between every every page so that your
Python code could scrape one page wait for a few minutes scrape another page and so on.
So there's no comments related to the exercises so most likely they were easy and understandable
Maybe regarding exercise two, Richard, exercise two talks about something that we didn't really
cover before, the headers. In practice, if I understand it correctly, it's like what
we tell to the remote server, like I'm on this computer with this operating system and
this browser, but do we need to sometimes change these headers?
I've done it occasionally. So sometimes the headers can be used for, for example, passing
authentication information. So the API knows who you are and that you have permission to access it,
but oftentimes there's other things in requests that can handle this for you.
Sometimes the headers would say things like what format you want the data in, or things like that.
And I can't remember an exact time, but I've probably done it once or twice.
Exactly. In the learning materials, there is an example where there are some example
of these headers that according to what you need to pass to the server, you need to modify
eventually. But often, if your goal is, for example, to scrape materials from the internet,
it's okay to use the default headers of the request API, of the request library.
And when it comes to scraping exercise three, we don't have time to go through it. So please
go, please do it if you have time. So the code that we see here is basically an example
where we wanna download the full HTML of a remote server.
So now it does not an API in the sense
that there's some software that even the parameters
that we pass is going to return an answer
like we had earlier JSON.
But now what is returned is basically
the so-called HTML code, which is this structure
which is the language of the web pages that you see.
So, in practice, with the example that you see here,
you request the HTML of some page,
in this case, example.com,
and then there's another library that is used.
If you scroll a little bit more down after this HTML,
there is this beautiful soup,
which is one package that allows you
to basically parse the HTML so that, again,
you don't need to invent new wheels
to extract the information that you need here basically it creates a structure of all the
tags that are contained in this HTML file and for example one can look at the title
of the page or look for all the links the links are marked with this tag A and so this
is why there you see find all A there so that will search for all the links in this case
there was just one link in this web page but it's time to wrap up maybe there's also something
else interesting in this web page which is saving the data the example there it's a useful
example there's nothing too difficult there but it's a nice example of doing multiple
queries one after the other like I mentioned earlier and and you see at the very last line
there is this sleep.
If you scroll up a bit, yeah.
So this is exactly the thing.
So we put one second between the multiple queries.
In this case, there are three queries to this cat fact API.
And then what's happening,
this code that this JSON replies from the APIs,
they're stored, they're appended to the same text file.
And this is a useful way to deal with kind of
to basically building a data set.
So at the end, you will have a big JSON file
that everywhere, every line is a JSON string.
And then most likely from this type of data,
from this format, maybe you want to move it
into a pandas data frame to basically continue
your analysis.
I think we are done.
Richard, do you have any comments on this data storage
from API?
Yes, I would say so how this data storage relates to what we talked about yesterday or two days ago.
So you might have different ways of storing data for different purposes.
So for example when it's downloading you want a file format where you can easily append
expedited to, and it won't get broken, like it can't really get corrupted. So for that,
downloading and storing in a giant text file with one line per thing, that's easy and relatively
foolproof. But when you're analyzing, then you might convert this to some other format,
which is more efficient for your other analysis. There's a comment there, like,
what a good way to be to store it in an SQL server of some sort. I mean, it could be done
if you have that set up. Many of our researchers have access to a big file system, but not an SQL
server. But another thing like saving it to disk first, just so you have it, because the file
system is more reliable than SQL server for, well, not getting corrupted.
Yeah.
I guess SQL would be a useful solution if these files, you know, if one is planning
to store 1 million JSON files, maybe that's not the best, but, you know.
Yeah.
I mean, it really depends on the site.
So even if you're scraping whole internet-level things,
you have to really think about this
and try to do it really well.
And that's not easy.
OK, with that being said, I guess
next is our panel discussion.
I'll switch to the notes here.
Yes.
Unfortunately, not all instructors from the first two days were available, but at least
we have some Alto people here.
Yeah.
So it's basically like our team here is answering questions.
OK.
So yeah, this is something that we tried a year or two ago
and worked really well.
So basically, yeah, think of what you'd like to discuss
and send it.
Someone's typing at Jupyter.
Question.
Do you use Jupyter training?
AI?
Machine learning image analysis algorithm.
I mean, I would start with Jupyter for most, like, for training a relatively simple model,
I would start with Jupyter, but then at some point when I'm writing the model, I would
probably take the model definition part, for example, and move it into a Python file, a
module.
Yeah, what a problem can happen with Jupyter is that it's, by design, interactive.
And interactive is all fun and dandy if you're actually watching the screen and actually typing
commands. And that is, of course, when you're prototyping a model or something like that,
you're actually doing it. But when we're talking about longer AI training,
usually interactive doesn't cut it. Like if Facebook is writing a llama or something,
there's no one guy running Jupyter cells. They have a non-interactive script that they run on
a compute cluster. For example, for Lama, they were using two compute clusters with huge amounts
of GPU resources. If you're doing a big AI training, you usually don't run it in an interactive mode.
You run it non-interactively and then you store the model checkpoints and that sort of stuff.
and store results maybe in a TensorBoard or 1 DB or something like that to monitor the training progress.
But of course for prototyping and that sort of thing, running Jupyter is good.
But then you usually need to have access to a GPU card.
And especially in compute clusters, the GPUs are usually demanded by these longer term jobs.
term jobs, these jobs that run for days and interactive usage basically means
that it's idling, the GPU is idling most of the time.
So usually what we recommend is that people who are actively doing
modern development, they get a cheap gaming GPU to prototype on with
Jupyter or something like that.
And then they move on to compute cluster to run the actual
training that takes days or even longer.
There's one question about benefits or disadvantages of Python versus other scientific or other
programming languages.
The example given here is Matlab.
My personal take would be one big advantage of Python is that it's open source, mostly.
There might be some packages where it's a bit more difficult that rely on the proprietary
software. But overall, it being open source is a big benefit. I have the impression, at least,
that Python is better when it comes to backward compatibility than, for example, Matlab.
I think Matlab has a good track record on that. But I'd say that Matlab is basically like,
You get what you buy because it's a commercial product. There are many
answers and many programs that are designed for doing some coding or calculations or running
some simulations. For example, MATLAB is very popular with signal processing people,
electrical people and that sort of stuff because it has good support for that in the toolboxes.
but it's like if you want to do MATLAB or web scraping that's not like it doesn't have the
connections that Python have to other things but it's very good at those things that it's
been designed to do and what the developers provide but it's not like a generalist programming language
what Python is as well. Well nowadays MATLAB does have a lot of interfaces with other languages
So, in the end, it's a bit of a style question.
And one clear thing is that if you use MATLAB, whoever you think might want to use your code
also has to have MATLAB.
And that means they have to pay for it.
So, I would assume at least that Python code is more widely used just because there is no financial barrier to using it.
I remember once when I was starting in a previous research group, everyone that comes in says, okay, who has the bootleg MATLAB copy.
But, you know, I never did that because I use Python and it's free already.
So, you know, even though it is available, the fact that you have to deal with licenses
and all that makes it harder and your work less reusable.
the best way to export plots if you need them as vector graphics. I think Matplotlib does support
vector graphics, right? Yeah, like probably most of the plotting libraries you could find a way
to export to SVG or PDF or something. So basically, yeah.
Let's see. Now we're getting lots of questions here.
Are you planning to run a Python course on AI and ML? I had answered that up above a little bit,
and my general thought was there's so many courses about AI and machine learning out there that
that's not our main target. There's a similar question right below about parallel programming
which we I mean we covered a lot of things really quickly and didn't go very deep in a
lot of things. There are a lot of courses out there and materials out there and
And so, yeah, I'm not sure if we can actually get 500 people or even 100 people in a course
about MPI or parallel programming in general, but you can study it and then, like, talk
about it with your local IT people, hopefully it will help.
Yeah.
In both cases, like, I think there's this kind of, like, in the industry as a whole,
is kind of a situation where the examples and small courses on how to write an MPI Hello World
or how to write a Keras or PyTorch machine learning thing that analyzes the MNIST numbers
or something. There's lots of material on the first part of the thing. Then there's usually
how do you scale it up? How do you scale MPI up? Or how do you get a big machine learning pipeline
or deep learning pipeline, training pipeline working? Then it goes super technical, super
quickly. And then it gets into this kind of a valley where usually you cross that valley only
by having engineers or somebody, a support person, who actually constructs a huge scaffolding that
you can cross the valley. And of course, big companies like Google and Facebook and those
kinds of companies, they have engineers who do that kind of scaffolding. But teaching that
that scaffolding is very hard, usually.
The biggest issue is that teaching that in a general way
is often not possible.
Because what you need to do depends
on your particular field or particular problem.
So we can teach basics of MPI, how MPI works with our ranks,
what functions are available to you.
Then we can talk specifically about your problem, your research field or the program you're writing
and talk about how to apply that framework. We can teach how to do MNIST with PyTorch
or do image recognition with PyTorch but then you will have a specific case
and most of what we – those are – we can give you the basics, but then from there it's
too specific, so it really only applies to you and a small group of people.
And then we talk with three people in the room and that's fine, but it's not a course.
It's a garage session, which is a very useful thing to have.
Yeah, many of these things which we're talking about, or these other courses requested, they
already exist, or you can find a good tutorial online.
And we very carefully targeted this course to things that are important for a junior
scientist but are not really taught other places.
you might not know about because of course you have to go follow up for most of these things.
Can we talk about a little bit about what our daily jobs are?
So how do we relate to researchers?
Well, I think most of us mainly help researchers with a variety of questions when it comes to
programming, but we are mostly, I think we are not solving the scientific question, we are solving
the implementation of whatever they come up with, with their solution or enable them to
use that solution or make it available to others.
Exactly, so that to me at least is one of the issues with specific questions for specific
software where I would commonly say, ask an expert in your field, they have a much better
chance of having in-depth knowledge of, okay, these are the tools that are currently state
of the art when it comes to analyzing tools or analyzing data.
We can of course also search things, but we are not commonly using these tools ourselves
most of the time.
There might be projects where we get in connection and see things, and yeah, if we see that that
works well or is well documented or something we can sometimes make suggestions but in a general
principle they are specialized highly specialized software where we can help you get into it or
if you tell us that you need something or if people tell us that they need something to
to something done with a certain software or so,
we can probably set up a system that they can use,
a kind of building a small prototype
that they can then expand.
But as, yeah, on a more general level,
we are not the experts in the software, I would say.
Any other opinions?
Yeah, I'd say that throughout this course, you might get this impression that you start
with the coding, which is NumPy and Pandas and that, and it quite quickly goes into actually
what you're doing is doing library management and installing dependencies.
And that's, of course, where we usually help our users.
like, if you know about the scientific subject, you know, about the context of like context of
the functions you're calling, what, what does it mean to do a Markov chain or whatever?
Like, you know, a context of where, where do I use this? Like, I don't know, like,
genome splitting function or whatever, like, you, you know, the context of the function,
the mathematical context and the subject context. But we usually help with that annoying part,
which is like, okay, how can I get this working? And this is unfortunately a big part of the whole
field because there's so much available. And of course, everybody wants to utilize the tools
because if you've ever tried writing, for example, Fortran code, and then you get some solutions
out of it and you store it, then you have to think about, okay, how do I even visualize this?
How do I plot this? Because it's like a Fortran binary format or something. Nobody wants to do
that. Nobody wants to write their own data readers or CSV readers or that sort of stuff.
nobody wants to waste time on that. So you want to use already existing tools. But of course,
if you want to use the already existing tools, you encounter a lot of hiccups with those tools.
And that's where we usually jump in and help the users. We understand enough of the context
to understand what the tools, how are the tools are supposed to be used and that sort of stuff,
and what the user wants to do with the tools.
But usually, we don't know about the field that much.
We mainly know the general idea about it.
And then we can figure out how to apply those tools
to that specific case.
Yeah.
I like question 42.
Do you think Python will ever become outdated, replaced
by a different language, since some people seem to say that R
might not be used anymore in the near future.
I've put an answer in there.
I think it's possible, sure.
I don't think it's likely anywhere
in the foreseeable future, since the ecosystem has kind of
achieved a critical mass, provides
so much possibilities and has addressed the issues that the language has.
So all these bridging to other languages where you have a lot more efficient ways to do certain
and things, make the disadvantages somewhat less.
So like, let's say Python seems to have this really good balance
between power and user interface,
and also a way that it moves slow enough
they really think about how the language is developing.
It is being actively developed, so yeah, that obviously helps a lot.
So there is that one little design choice that it can't do multi-threading, but I mean
we make this ways to get around that and multi-threading happens in the libraries anyway, so it's not
really a big problem.
But yeah, the way I could see any language gets replaced is by the design issues becoming
problematic, or by a completely new paradigm becoming problematic.
Yeah.
Python has this kind of like a tendency of whatever, like people say, like if people
say that, okay, they don't like a feature in Python, like suddenly there's like a package
that somebody like implements that, like for example, like Python doesn't do static typing,
but nowadays people have written extensions that basically like for static typing wherever,
or they try to do type hints and they try to do typing as much as possible in Python.
Python is object-oriented and it's functional at the same time. There's people who like the
functional side and they write functional programming only and they try to implement
their stuff as functional programming and they find extensions that provide that. Then there's
people who like the object-oriented style and they write extensions that make that easier.
And then it's like, is it even the same language anymore? It's like a completely different dialect
of the same thing. And it's very hard to say like, yeah, what is the core language in Python
is so adaptable. And I think that's the main thing why it's so popular, that you can do all
kinds of stuff with them. There are libraries like, I mean, I guess TensorFlow is a great example.
It is essentially declarative. So Python is written to be, if you know, there are different
programming paradigms and Python is not written as a declarative language, but there are libraries
that actually make it declarative. So it can actually, depending on what library you use,
it can use a completely different programming paradigm. It's extensible enough.
And also the question about when people are asking there about R, I like R in many cases.
For statistics, I think R is a wonderful language. I wouldn't, again, do web scraping in R
necessarily or web servers or something like that. But again, it's not the forte of the language,
but it's very good at what it does. And I think the thing with the languages is same as
with natural languages? Are people actually using it in their everyday speech, basically?
Are people writing new stuff using that language? Are they creating new things or are they like
songs that some old person, like a hundred year old person remembers and that's the only
recollection that we have of a language and then we record it on a tape and then we remember that
we used to have this sort of a language, like languages are only alive when people use them.
Like in a normal, normal case, I think maybe some linguistics might be, might have a different
definition, but, but I think for programming language, the main thing is like who are,
who other people are using it? Not, not whether I'm using it correctly. If I have nobody to speak
with that language, it's not really helping me in any way. It's, it's about the whole like
community and ecosystem. And I think Python currently has a very healthy ecosystem. Of course,
there might be new things coming, but it's hard to tell. The timelines are so long.
Some questions about what to learn next. So there's not just the programming language,
but you might have seen a lot of what we're doing here is about how the programming language
interacts with the operating system, the data, things like that. And that's another good thing
to think about and follow up on, no matter what language you're using.
Question 45. If you want to learn Python or any other language, it's good to have a
problem and a deadline, and then you should try Advent of Code, just advertising Advent of Code.
But it's fun if you have time.
Should I do a little bit of wrap up of the course?
Yeah.
So there's an outro linked from the web page,
but it's not very up to date.
Maybe I'll share it anyway.
There, this is my screen.
So, there's many people that have helped made this part, not just the instructors, but others, and you can see the credits on the web page.
So, about organizations. Code Refinery is a publicly funded project by the Nordic e-Infrastructure Collaboration, which supports computational research, teaching, and software tools.
Our organization at Aalto University supports computational research here,
and a lot of the other instructors you saw from other institutions, they're very similar to us.
So basically, the idea is, like oftentimes in academia, you think, okay, I need to learn
everything myself. But in the real world, it's good to have other people you can work with as a team.
And if you don't have these kinds of computational experts
in your own group, you can come to people like us
and ask for help and advice.
So wherever you are, I'd recommend
you finding if there's these type of people there.
There are other future events.
So this is not updated since last year.
But actually, if you update the years,
it's actually pretty accurate.
So Code Refinery is a workshop on, basically,
version control and other software development practices.
So not about Python, but it's taught like this
and really good to take also.
Workflows course, this is written
we wanted to give it in 2022, and then we
wanted to give it in 2023, and we still haven't given it.
But maybe we should get on that.
I'm not sure if high performance data analysis will
be taught again.
And then also in June of 2023, in our university,
we have a course which is a kickstart
to scientific computing and high-performance computing.
And these courses, Code Refinery and this one,
are all taught just like we are here,
with the livestream format, code teaching,
and basically should be of this quality.
For announcements for many of these things,
subscribe to a Code Refinery newsletter. How to stay in touch? Well, you can find some social
media here. If you think that the kind of things we're talking about are what you're interested in,
possibly more interesting than the scientific side of things you do, or you like the science
but you also like the software more than you can do there, a research software engineer is the name
of the kind of people we are. So we do research, we do software, and we connect them.
If you would like to meet with more like-minded people like this, there's research software
engineer associations, which are of the people like us. In Nordics there is this one, but you
can find more in other places. Are there things to talk about working together?
So in the future,
these are some ideas for what to do.
Basically, you can join
the Code Refinery organization and
help us to put on courses like this.
So we really think we have
a pretty good teaching style here.
That's both accessible to a very large audience.
It's our information is reusable
since we have the videos and all of that.
It's also very interactive and fun to listen to.
If you would like to support this kind of thing,
please get in touch,
join Code Refinery, and at the very least,
tell people that we have this good way of teaching,
so we can try to spread it to other people.
With that being said, in the past,
we've had an after-party in Zoom,
So we would share the Zoom link that we are in right now
and allow everyone in the audience to join.
So I won't give it yet, but it's a possibility.
Should we put the feedback for today?
Oh, yes.
I forgot that.
And I will also send you a feedback, a more general anonymous feedback for the whole course
so that you could tell, for example, you know, what worked best, what needs improving or
what was missing.
And I was writing something in the notes that I forgot.
Oh yeah, that we also have a form where you can request future courses.
So I'm now I'm going to paste it there on it's coming so that you know if there is enough
volume of requests we can do all sorts of things I have to say that many of you when
you register, maybe 75% actually tick the box, please let me know about future courses.
So you will definitely receive more emails from me. And of course, you can always unsubscribe
Please give feedback if you hear this is important.
Is there any more?
Or should we call it the end?
Maybe we should call it the day and let people
join the Zoom after the streaming is over.
Yes.
Thank you, everyone.
Thank you to all.
You were a great audience.
And I think this was one of the best courses we've put on yet.
So thank you.
Bye.
you