the 10 minutes of icebreaker time, so we're just here to chat while we're getting ready.
So my name is [name]. I'm here to, well, I'm one of the instructors and organizers
of the course. And with me here, would you all like to introduce yourselves? So [name]
is next on my screen.
Did [name]'s internet.
Oh, there.
Hello.
Sorry, I was just switching to a wired connection.
Good idea.
So hello, I'm [name].
I'm also one of the instructors
and a research software engineer at Aalto University.
Hi, I'm [name]. I'm an application expert at UPPMAX, Uppsala University in Sweden,
and I will also be teaching during this workshop. Hi, everyone.
Okay, so what I'm screen-sharing here is what we call the notes.
So, right here.
You can't see the cursor.
So, this is only for registered participants.
So if you would, if you're watching and you're not registered, if you register, I think you'll get an auto-reply that has this information here.
So how does it work? So at the top it has all the important links, and down below we see, well it's like Google Docs, so it's a collaborative writing thing.
So, I think the microphones might be wrong here.
[name] or [name], can you say something?
Hello, one, two, three.
One, two.
Okay. It seems... Oh, wait.
Okay, now I think it's better. Yeah. I know what the problem was. If there was an echo,
that was me.
So there's a question in Twitch chat which is asking, is this recorded? So the answer
is yes. So Twitch has the videos available immediately. And on YouTube, by the same night,
it should already be there.
And we can talk about the video processing later.
But OK, so back to the notes that we're talking about.
So if you go to the top, you can switch to an edit mode,
and then back to view mode.
You can even do the split mode.
But we used this like a chat.
So any time you would be asking something in a chat,
instead come here and write it somewhere. So you see at the bottom there's a Q&A part,
so someone could demonstrate writing the question. Let's practice writing the question.
Is this recorded?
And then we have a whole bunch of people who are also course instructors, and we're watching and
and answering it in real time.
So it's like a synchronous parallel chat Q&A kind
of thing.
So with this, we can have so many different questions
and answers at the same time and actually keep track of it.
And then we can archive it later.
But for now, we have icebreakers.
So if you scroll up, you see some questions
from registrations and so on, but then down here
to icebreaker questions.
So everyone that's registered, please take this, open it,
and scroll down to this point, and write down where
or write down the answers to the questions.
And let's see.
So you can also answer plus one for anything
that you're agreeing with.
And this is also a common thing.
So if you see something that you'd especially like answered
or you agree with, you can plus one it.
So where's everyone?
Where are we from?
So right now, I'm from a small office
at Aalto University in Finland.
And I guess [name] is teaching from home today?
Yeah, from somewhere in Espoo, Finland.
Yeah, and I'm in my office in Uppsala.
Yeah.
Oh, OK.
So we see a big variety of people from mostly European
countries, but not only.
So that's good.
We're glad that people can join us from all over.
And how much do people use Python?
Fair amount, quite a bit.
How much have the instructors used Python?
So, I don't know, what was your intro to Python and how long have you been using it?
I don't remember.
Which is, I guess, for a long time.
Yeah.
So, at least six, seven years ago.
So, I don't remember the first thing I did with Python.
But yeah, I do most things with Python these days.
Okay.
And before Python, what did you use?
C, C++ mostly, so I was doing very different kinds of things, so those were appropriate
languages for what I was doing, yeah.
And [name]?
Yeah, I had started with C, some C++ and Fortran, and it's mostly during the, I don't know,
maybe five years, past five years
that I've been using Python.
OK, yeah.
And as for me, I remember, so at first, I
was doing some stuff in C. And I had this friend saying
I needed to learn Python some.
But I didn't for a while until I did.
And well, I've been using it as my main language.
ever since.
So yeah.
And let's see.
So our audience here, how much have we used Python?
Yeah.
So I'd say this whole course, it's
designed for people that know a little bit about Python,
like the basic programming, but not the details
of using it for science.
And we're especially going into these libraries.
But if you're more advanced than that,
you'll probably still learn some tricks,
although the first few days may be a bit slow.
Just come back for the later days.
And if you haven't done any Python at all,
well, we're not covering that.
But by watching, you'll probably learn about, well,
learn some good things to help when you do start using Python.
OK, using Jupyter before, almost nothing.
So Jupyter is something that we talk a little bit more about.
And I believe, who's the first instructors here
for the Jupyter part?
It's me and [name].
OK, yeah, so Jarna and [name] will talk about that.
Oh, these JupyterLab extensions.
So maybe I should give some background on why we ask this question.
So some of our participants are working on hearing what those are, but we won't really
have time during the course.
And it's also great to hear from you all.
But if you do not know what those are, don't worry.
Yeah.
Okay.
So it's time to start the main part.
I saw a comment in chat that our audio might not be balanced.