So, so the first lesson is Jupyter.
And I guess one main reason, one big reason to talk about Jupyter is that we will use
it a lot.
It's a convenient way of teaching and showing things.
[name], do you want to say anything about why Jupyter is good to learn before we start?
I think it's great at the very beginning when you are starting to write your Python
scripts.
It's easier to, it's more readable.
I find it easier to debug as well, but I would say, I mean, if you're used to IPython or
just running it from the command line, that is great as well.
So it's really a matter of preference.
If you are used to Python and you have a favorite way of using it, then just go ahead and use
that instead.
So getting started with Jupyter.
So let's just show one way of opening it.
is how I will use it.
And just to note, so in the installation
instructions that you hopefully did take a look at
before the course, if you didn't just ask questions, but
if you did, there is also instructions for how to open Jupyter for
whatever method of installing it you chose.
So, I will activate a conda environment in my terminal.
And while [name] is doing this, I will mention that you can also open it from the Anaconda
navigator. So, if you prefer that, that's perfectly okay. And if you're using Anaconda
and did not create a special environment, then you don't need to activate anything. You just run
on this command, jupyter lab.
And this opens a new browser window or a new tab in the browser.
And there's a lot of stuff here.
That's probably not the most useful information at this point.
So oh, I'm running it in my main folder.
Is there a way of easily going to another folder here, or should I just restart?
Maybe I'll just go to Python for SciComp.
Okay, that works.
Also, there is a file browser here.
You can clearly go to into folders, I will use it to delete my previous version of this
session.
Okay, so now I have no files in the folder.
And if you have nothing open, it will automatically open this launcher, which will show you what
kinds of programming languages you can use in Jupyter, basically.
So this is a Python 3 kernel, and it's the only one I have.
So I can open a Python 3 notebook here.
If you don't see this, you can open this view by pressing this plus button here.
Okay. So, I will open a new one and immediately I will rename it. So, right-clicking here
and rename. I will call it demo.
Yeah. That's always a good practice. Although I have a lot of untitled documents as well.
Yeah. So, it will automatically – oh, it's showing like it didn't save it. Okay. Well,
I mean that blue dot – that dot in my mind means it didn't save it, but maybe it's because
it's empty. Okay so we have this notebook and what we can do here we can write Python code and run it
and it will show the output immediately or we can use markdown to write a narrative so you can
essentially you can make this a document where you write some description and then you write the code
code, and then you write some more description and then some more code and so on.
So that makes it nicer for sharing your code or sharing your workflow with other people.
They can immediately see what you've done and see the code actually in the document.
So it says code here.
It refers to this one, well, they could have multiple cells here.
It's a plus button, so now you have multiple cells.
So this code refers to this particular cell that I have selected.
I will change it into Markdown.
Markdown is the language that we use in the collaborative document, in the notes.
So it should look relatively straightforward.
If it doesn't, that's fine.
The point is not to learn Markdown, but you can do formatting in addition to text with
Markdown.
this one hash means title this is like the biggest title available so this is a title
and make sure that it's the same markdown that we are using for the notes document yeah and you
don't have to be great at it to to use it i mean i think you can just learn a few syntaxes and
that's okay so this is some text i'll just write that and maybe i'll do like we do the questions
so a bullet point.
So it actually does some, just like the notes, it does some
syntax highlighting here so that you see there's a title and the bullets
they're different. But now if I press play here it will
actually run this markdown code which means
generate a formatted text area here.
Okay, now I can also do Python code. So this is just markdown, code, or raw text. Code in this
case means Python code because this was a Python notebook. So let's just do a simple one, one plus
one. Run that. And if you install a different kernel, let's say you work with Julia instead,
then the kernel is going to interpret what they said that you are marking as code will
be interpreted by the kernel that you have chosen. Yeah, actually I will steal this
notes from here for a while. Okay, so what else should we try? So just a quick intro to Python,
I suppose. So we can do a for loop and if we do for loop for starting from the value of i
starts from 0 and goes up to 2, we use the range function and actually write the number 3. So it's
0, 1, 2. That's three different numbers. So that's kind of the logic. And let's just print
the number and run this cell. So I should print the numbers 0, 1, and 2.
Or you can do sum of range from 0 to 5.
So now I'm not using print, but it will still print the last thing that happens, the output
of the last line.
So just like here in 1 plus 1 it printed 2, it prints 10 here.
Okay, so this is essentially most of Jupyter.
Let's quickly also show a magic function.
So there are a few commands that don't exist in Python, but are very useful in Jupyter.
And they start with a percentage.
So we can print the directory we are at.
So this stands for print working directory.
And if you use a Unix terminal in Linux or in Mac OS, this will be a familiar command.
So this is where we are right now in my file system.
But not all Unix commands exist here.
So there's another command called bash, which will run.
So bash is essentially a terminal.
So you can run any terminal command here
to host name, for example.
So this will print the name of my computer,
which is some string of numbers and characters.
But I guess the thing I want to demonstrate
is that even though this doesn't exist as a magic command,
so this is what an error looks like,
it does exist inside this bash command.
Also, everything now in this cell is this magic command
because it starts with two percentage signs.
So that changes how the cell works in general.
Yeah, exactly. So for one line, it's one percentage for the whole cell, you should use two percentages
followed by the magic. And maybe I could add that, I mean, using this magic commands is
a great way of integrating Bash and running other programs that you have compiled within
your Jupyter notebook. So you could integrate, for example, R or C or Fortran and run it
from the cell. But you just need to make sure that you do have the correct environment when
you're trying to do that. But yeah. One command which I think is very nice as well is the ls
magic one. If you could show it. And that will print all the magic commands that are available.
Oh, is it just one word?
ls magic one word. It's always one word for the command. And then you may have options
following. And then if you, yes, expand, then you can see everything that is available as
line magic or cell magic. I think that line magic is with one percentage sign and cell magic is for
two. Exactly. Yeah. And this may not be so instructive, but you could use, for example,
magic or quick breath one word to know more about them or you can just Google for them
or check in there. Yes, exactly. In the documentation. So that's that's okay. It's like find it quite
but very long cheat sheet. But was there a magic command called pip? Let's see. So I
I mean, sometimes it is very useful to be able to also install packages from, so yeah,
there is.
There is.
And there is Conda as well, as a magical.
Okay.
Should we demonstrate the sort of the biggest problem that people were running to or should
we just go to the exercises first?
We have one minute.
Okay.
Okay, well, let's just show one thing that might, this is something you might run into that might
be a problem. So we have here, we have run a for loop that sets a value for the variable i.
So here I can run an i equals 2. Okay, what if I add a cell here
here and run this. What do you think should happen? What do you think will happen? Well,
the way Jupyter works is that it just runs the cells in the order that you run them in.
It doesn't care about what order they're written in. So this will still be equal to 2, this
i here. What did I do? Okay. So that might be a problem if somebody else now gets your
notebook. If you take your notebook and send it to someone else and they try to run it so
there is this very convenient button here that will run all the restart the kernel just forget
everything and run all the cells from the beginning. So this is basically what will
happen when you give your notebook to someone else. They will run it every cell from the beginning.
So, now it ran this cell correctly, but this cell I doesn't mean anything, so it just failed
and gave an error.
It's a very useful error.
Name i is not defined, so you know what's happening.
So I will just delete this cell, because this is a problem.
It shouldn't be there, it should be here.
And let's try again.
So it's always useful to do this restart kernel
and rerun all the cells in order before sending your notebook
to anyone.
Oh, host name not found.
That's interesting.
OK, right, because that was it.
Actually, I was showing you that it doesn't exist.
OK, let's remove that error as well.
OK, now everything worked.
All the cells worked correctly.
OK, so I guess we'll go to the exercises
then. So let's do exercise one is almost at the top. So starting
and exploring Jupyter. And if you are new to Jupyter, it's
very much enough to just do that. There are some I mean,
it's good if you get to this first one, which is run some
code in Jupyter. The rest are some a bit more slightly more complicated exercises and if you
get all the way to the end, I mean I don't really expect you to get all the way to the end
necessarily, if you do then go on to exercise three. It's an optional discussion exercise so
you can write things into the notes or you can discuss with people close to you if they are also
done with all the exercises. So we'll give you 15 minutes and then we'll do a quick wrap-up. So go ahead.
Should we write some information in the notes about the exercise time?
Yes, I just...
Okay, welcome back. I hope you had a good time with the exercises and got Jupyter running.
So we had a couple of questions and I think the biggest issue is that bash indeed doesn't
work on Windows. It's an operating system specific thing. So there is a magic command,
how was the percentage sign there called CMD that should work on Windows
so you can use that one instead it will not work on my system so
you can try running it but yeah it does not exist. Yeah but sorry yes we missed that so
but bash equivalent in windows should be cmd so whatever we tried in the bash magic
in the bash cell then you could try that with cmd
okay so that's everything about jupyter for now we will be using it for the
a lot of the course so you will get used to it
it. Is there any other notable questions to bring up? There's a lot of questions and a
lot of answers which is great. Yes I think most of them are answered so maybe we can
just wrap up with when to use Jupyter and when is it not so great.
Yeah, so do you use Jupyter a lot?
It's actually mostly for teaching and for visualizing plots.
Yeah, it's really useful for visualizing because you can, it can display the plots or any images
inside the notebook. So, it's kind of inlining it. So, that's useful. It's good for quickly
changing a single cell. You don't have to rerun the whole thing. So, if you have a really – if
you have a processor that takes a few minutes to run and you want to work on the very last
10 seconds of it, you may not want to run the whole thing every time you're testing it. So,
just run the last couple of cells. And why should you not use Jupyter?
There's a few actually, a few good reasons to not use Jupyter as well.
I think the main most important one is the top most one here, so they don't promote modularity.
So yeah, writing functions in Jupyter notebooks or moving things into
to importable files is, I mean, it doesn't happen automatically. It's something you need
to think about when you're writing the notebooks.
Yes. And one thing I would mention here, it's also written in the material is that the nbdime
extension. That's really great if you are versioning and controlling your notebooks
and you should do that. So that will allow you to see differences between different notebooks,
which is not straightforward. Or rather, version controls the tool.
Okay and yeah there's some other things written down here but so you can read on your own time.
Now it's time for a break so do take a break you can come back to the exercises or any part of this
later but it is it's actually very useful for or very important for learning that you also
take breaks if you were really working on this one then take some time off to take your hands
off your keyboard and walk around and then come back. So we'll take nine minutes and then we'll
come back at the short. Let's come back two minutes past. And we'll continue with NumPy.
Alright, so see you after the break. Bye