So, welcome back, everyone, after the break.
Hello, should we say something about ourselves?
Yes, we should. So my name is [name]. I work at the PDC Center for High Performance
Computing in Stockholm. And with me here is [name].
Hi, I'm [name]. I'm a staff scientist at Aalto and I work with [name] and others at Aalto
scientific computing and I'm sure you will receive some emails from me regarding links
and other details for the course. So, nice to see so many of you here. So, [name], numpy.
Yes. So, as you can see here, we have opened here a Jupyter notebook. So, we will continue
this tool that you were introduced to in the previous lesson. And we see that you have
been posting, continue to post questions in the HackMD, and we will answer them continuously.
So [name], why would we need something, we do have support of lists and various data
types in regular Python from the beginning.
So why would we need a library like NumPy?
Yeah, I think that the issue with Python list,
with the kind of basic supported Python list,
is that they, as you can see here in this example,
there is one, 2.5, some string, some Boolean.
So it's a bit of a mixed bag of different types.
you can guess already that maybe this is not the most efficient way to deal with data,
especially if you need to do fast computation with it. So I think that the NumPy,
is it a NumPy? I think that it stands for numerical Python, isn't it?
Yes, indeed. And NumPy is a library used for scientific computing and it's something that
that we will use a lot here now in the course, and often it's so that even if you don't explicitly
work with NumPy, you might have it under the hood. So it will, for instance, come in under
the hood when we look on the Matplotlib visualization tomorrow.
So one of the core objects in NumPy are the arrays, which is a construction that can work
with a regular set of values. You can call them a grid. And all of the elements have
the same data type. This data type have indices, which are non-negative numbers. And these
indices can be in one or more dimension that is natively supported. If you look on the
The properties that the array elements have, or the arrays have, they have a dtype, and
an intrinsic property they have is that they have a shape. So, for instance, you can have
a two-dimensional array, three times two. You can have a three-dimensional array, three
times two, type 500. There's also the corner case of having a zero-dimensional array indexed
here by square brackets.
An important aspect is that we have
the data stored as raw memory, and it
can be passed to C and Fortran code
for efficient calculations.
So is it, [name], can you, do you
have some examples of when you combine C and Python?
Well, I mean, this is, NumPy is maybe the greatest example
of having so much sea power under the hood.
But what do you think,
should we show the power of NumPy?
Yes, yes.
So I'm gonna type so that also you,
whoever wants to type can do the same.
So basically we are creating a list
and this is range and it's 10,000.
All right. And that's the first list. And then we have another list. It's called B.
And this is now in regular Pythons. This is still not NumPy.
Yep. All right.
Yes. So let's see here what happens if you take the elements of the list A and you square
them and assign the value to B. It's a long list.
Yeah, it's a long list. So in this small example here, we basically
need to build a for loop, right? So that it will go through each of the elements of A
and assign them to b and then we use this magic time it which is very useful for basically
telling us the performance of the piece of code in the cell that we see here so we said
that we do a for loop in the range of the length of the list a and then we want to
do that the ith element of b is equal to the ith element of a square i think it's correct right
should we check that that was correct so what's the timing for this so it's saying 2.68 milliseconds
per loop so well one could think that it's even you know relatively fast 2.8 millisecond
Now, should we try the NumPy version?
Yes.
So there's now a new command that we have not used yet, which is import.
This is practically saying to Python that now I'm importing a library.
And often we even nickname that instead of using `numpy`, often it is nicknamed as `np` for brevity.
So you can save typing time.
and now we basically redo what we did earlier but this time we use this function so np.arange
with 10 000 and for the b we initialize it to zeros
and again 10 000 so basically we have recreated what we were doing earlier
with this but now they're not lists anymore now they are NumPy arrays and
now we can do you can already see how compact is the NumPy version of it so
we want to time it again and then we want to make sure that the array B will
contain the square the element y square of array A and let's see how long it
it takes. Okay, this was 3.42 microns [microseconds]. So I'm not good with math, but we are talking
at order of magnitude, three order of magnitudes of difference. So it's...
Yeah, yeah. This is quite a bit faster.
It's quite a bit different. So we showed some functions like this np.arange and np.zeros.
or are these related to this creating arrays, [name]?
Yes, exactly.
So there are a few different ways that one can create arrays.
So the arange, here we had as an argument 10,000
and so perhaps we can look at `a`.
So what does it start with?
Does it start with one or does it start with zero?
In this `a` here?
Yeah.
So, it starts with zero.
It starts with zero, yeah.
And also, I mean, the first element also has the index of zero.
Yeah.
So, this is then compatible with C, but it's then another convention than what is used
in, for instance, in Fortran.
So we could also have that we assign a distinct set of elements. So perhaps if you would like
to have just numbering up to six, but have it in a three-dimensional array, in a two-dimensional
array.
Yeah.
I think you have an example there for `b`.
So yep, so mparray and now I'm passing like in this example here I'm actually passing
a matrix basically row one and row two so I need many square brackets now this is the
first row and then there's a comma and then there's the second row four five and six all
All right, let's have a look at `b also.
All right, yeah, this is now like a square matrix
or not square, but two-dimensional.
Rectangular, yeah.
Now we have these attributes
that we can inspect the array with.
So yeah, b.shape, okay.
Pings back then that the shape of the object
is two rows and three columns.
And the size will give us the number of elements.
I see.
So, there are many alternatives to how to create arrays. So, we have here, for instance,
you can create all zeros. You can create all ones. Or assign all elements to some arbitrary
amounts. For instance, this np.full, 2, 2, and then 7, which then will assign all elements
to 7. You will see here soon in the exercises that you can manipulate the elements. So we
can yeah perhaps you can first show that how one can save and then read in again
yeah so let's see if we have something stored maybe a can be this
Yes, now we want to save it and be don't say I call it a.npy just because so that's the
a native format. Let's give it file.npy and the variable a this is actually like I'm coming
from a MATLAB past this is very similar to the save MATLAB where you have the name of
the file and then the variable and then of course I guess we can load things back. So
now I'm loading to a different variables called x and p dot load and the name of the
the file, which was file.mpy and let's see if it works.
Yeah, no, the same way.
So we would, should we already go to the,
or do we need, do you want to mention something
about this data type?
Yes, so one can change the data type.
change the data type. So, the data types here are dynamic. So, if you assign an element
or elements to be integers, then the array will be an array of integers. But you can
cast it into something else.
So, I'm making now an array of booleans just for the fun and let's see if it looks okay.
Yeah, so this is basically true and now we want to cast this. So, casting meaning that
we don't want to treat this as booleans anymore but we want to see them as integers. Let's
see if this works. Yes, so now there are 1s. Of course, we didn't actually modify D because
we didn't. So, D still has the, you know, we didn't store the output of D.
Yeah, exactly. Okay. So, now it's time for you to start exploring this on your own. So,
We are coming here to exercise one, where you get four tasks and you will explore how
to create with arrays and also how to create arrays that fill random numbers, how arrays
can be reshaped and also how arrays can be written to file and read from file.
And for this exercise, we will give you 15 minutes to work on it.
So that means that they will reconvene at 31 past the hour.
Okay.
And feel free, of course, to write on the notes document if you have any blockers.
And for those who want more advanced things, you can already jump to the next exercises
if this is too simple for you.
OK, I'll see you all in 15 minutes.
Hello, welcome back, hopefully you had enough time to do these exercises.
You must have noticed already that there's a solution box there so that, you know, if
you are not sure if you are, it's good to learn also from the answer so you can click
the box and it will expand. I'll just briefly comment on one exercise because at least looking
at the notes document maybe it wasn't clear that the output of np.arange is a little bit
different than the output of np.linspace and the difference as you might have noticed is
on the type so in practice one can set you know like we did earlier here with this casting
or if you look at the linspace function there's also a way to pass the type into as a argument
for the linspace so we will not cover all the exercises because hopefully the solutions
are good for you. So, should we talk about array maths and vectorization, [name]?
Yes, indeed. And first we can point out is that NumPy is fast as the backend of it is
done in C or in Fortran. That it has in common with other high level languages such as R
and MATLAB. So one important notion is that by default basic arithmetic such as plus minus
multiply and division is element by element. So this is something that we already saw this
when we calculated the square of a and assigned it to the variable b. So the default is that
it will perform the operation for each element in the array
and you don't need to explicitly write a loop.
And if you have run other languages such as MATLAB,
you might then notice that in MATLAB,
if you have the star for multiplication symbol,
that means matrix multiplication.
So this is then different in NumPy
because the star then means that you do it element-wise.
So NumPy, instead we are using the at symbol
to perform multiplication.
So perhaps we can have a look on some examples.
So if you create two arrays, A and B.
So the first array is a square matrix.
First row.
And then the second row.
and then I close the row and let's sure that it's like it should be okay then we
do or be five and six seven and eight
okay so now we can for example sum the two arrays just with a plus oh yes no
need to write any for loop a plus b and let's have a look at the output yes that
seems to be as intended yes so each element in the respective position has
been added to each other so is there some other way you can write this
instead of using the plus operator yeah there is this add function in practice
it's kind of the same but the advantage of having a function is that there will be more
parameters and more options but yes now we store it in the output D and we can have a
look at D and yes it's the same.
So how then if you want to perform the matrix multiplication of A and B?
So we said that it's this at,
or maybe I used the function notation,
at B dot dot, A and B.
And now it will store in E.
And it's been a few years,
I haven't done matrix multiplication,
but this looks like one, two, five and seven.
Yes, it is five plus 14, so 19.
Yeah, that's correct.
Good, so here you can see there's an exercise tool here, but we will, for now, we will move
on and look on indices and slicing. So this is core functionality when working with arrays.
So there are a few modalities how you can extract values. So you can extract single
elements that you then put in brackets. You can select rows or columns, or you could actually
take subvolumes of the array. So, for instance, if you have a two-dimensional array, you can
take out a rectangle that is within the full two-dimensional data range. So, I think we
can see how this goes in practice. So, I already started typing.
Yes, exactly.
I couldn't wait. So, with this np.arange. So, this will create an array with 16 elements.
And now we append the other function reshape. So, that instead of having, you know, kind
of a one dimensional 16 elements array, it will be a matrix. And so, and yes, it's a
times 4 matrix and now we can slice it we can take out whatever we need so the very first element
will be the first row because it works for wise which is also something that is a bit different
than matlab matlab prefers column wise so at least for me something that i had to remember
at the beginning but of course we can also get the first column yes and let's see if we get it
yes it's the first column
then there's another example here that we want to take kind of the middle two times two array
yeah so let me type it without errors from 1 to 3 in the rows and from 1 to 3
in the columns and then here how many element did we extract here so you had
the in this specified 1:3 and we see here that what we for the row and
And for the columns, we were picking out from index one,
but then up and until two.
So three is in the upper range,
but you don't include that in the selected elements.
Yeah.
Which again, I mentioned MATLAB again,
because there were many people
also in the registration asking.
So it's different, very different behavior than in MATLAB,
which instead it would have an indexes
would be 1, 2 and 3. All right, what else do we have here? We also have Boolean indexing.
So, what are these Boolean indexing? Let's see the first line and hopefully it will be clear.
So, now I'm basically saying a larger than 0 and a actually has one element that is 0.
Yeah, so then we can expect that this relation will come out as true, yes, for all of them
apart from the first one, the first element, yeah.
And now we can use this Boolean matrix as indexes, isn't it? So this is a good way
of filtering based on a value. So, a of idx, yeah, now it doesn't have the first element
anymore.
Ah, yeah, yeah, this is very, this is very neat, yeah.
So we basically filtered, maybe we could have, to make it clear, let's say a bigger than seven,
right and now let's see what is this filter and you see we only have those elements that
are bigger than seven so we are quite good with our timings is it now time for some more
exercises yes indeed so the idea is now if you scroll up so we will do exercise number
number 2 on matrix multiplication. And you will also do the exercise 3 which is on view
versus copy. And for this we intend to have 10 minutes exercises and then we will cover
the last sections of the lesson after this exercise.
Yeah.
Or should we give a bit more than 10 minutes if there's three exercises?
I think we can do it in 10 minutes.
Okay.
Yeah.
All right.
So we will be back at 52 past the hour.
Okay.
So good luck with the exercises and see you in 10 minutes.
Bye.
Hello, nice to see that you had time to try the exercises.
Something that was a bit puzzling, and I can totally understand if you come from other
programming languages like Matlab or R, is this view versus copy.
I will cover it a little bit later when I'll show you about other materials that we have
that we will not cover it today but in practice you can think it that B is like a pointer to
the memory allocated by A so hopefully I didn't use too much jargon in this maybe those familiar
with C and C++ they can understand what I mean but in it is actually useful to only
edit some elements of the same original array.
Instead, when you need the full copy,
there is actually a common call np.copy
that would basically clone the array A
into a new part of the memory to store a copy.
But yes, we have a few minutes to wrap up everything
and show you some future paths for you for self-learning.
Maybe something that is important to talk about NumPy
are the so-called universal functions.
Fancy names to basically saying that these are functions,
these are operations that can happen element-wise.
And we already tested them when we were doing A plus B,
you know, we didn't need to write a for loop
like we would have done with standard Python lists
because basically the function add
was one of these universal function
going through all the elements of the arrays.
Another very interesting thing that maybe if you're, you know, I sometimes never think
about this just because I'm a NumPy user without knowing, without really paying too much attention
what's going on under the hood, but we have something called like broadcasting which becomes
really practical when, for example, you need to sum things that are not exactly of the
same shape so it's not just a simple element wise but numpy is clever enough for example you see
in here that given the size of the array of b numpy understands that you want to kind of broadcast
it so that you want that each of the row of the vector of the array a of the matrix a actually
is summed with the matrix B.
This is something I would say that this is by no way obvious that you will have this behavior.
So before you feel confident in using it then I mean
be very careful and verify that you actually get the intended behavior.
Yeah this is maybe one good thing one positive thing about Jupyter notebooks is that
that you can actually you know when you are building your code when you are when you are
developing your method you can easily test that it's doing what you're expecting and
then maybe even write a test for what you are actually building.
So what else. Well we will leave exercise for you because our time is out for NumPy
today. In general, NumPy is under the hood on so many Python libraries, so that if your
needs are more into, you know, mathematics, signal processing, another thing, there are
lots of linear algebra functions already in NumPy, but another good library is SciPy,
which has all these type of functions for doing, you know, signal processing and other
more advanced numerical things in general for this last minutes that we have there's additional
exercises that if you have time of course and if you want to learn you could do them and if you
don't want to do them it's also interesting to just look at the solution and try to understand
what's going on and maybe get curious and try to run them try to run them yourself also last year
we cover this other lesson here that you see now where I'm here in the bottom and I click next
and so we have the recording from last year of this advanced NumPy for those who want to
understand for example like in this exercise 3 what is going on under the hood when we have a
view of the array A into something called B and actually here if you spend time going through this
lesson by yourself or watching the video from last year we are actually covering exactly this case of
the exercise 3 where let me find the picture yeah so you see that basically in the definition of
array A the memory a part of memory is allocated for A but in the moment where we take a view a
different view for another array B it was it's basically just a pointer to a subset of the
of the memory allocated by A. And this has the benefit then of being more efficient in two
regards so both that you're reusing actually memory so that's economic and also that you
don't need to in this case you don't need to make the copy. Yeah especially if you have a very big
matrix copy can be very very expensive even just the copy itself might take lots of seconds yeah
precisely so i think we cover everything and please keep on writing more questions or doubts
that you have in our share notes we could maybe start already the break right now and so we will
come back in about 10 minutes to continue with Bandas. So, thank you for listening.
Thank you, [name], for being here with me.
Yeah, thank you, [name].
And we will see you later. Bye.
Bye.