So [Name], what do we mean by productivity tools? What kind of productivity?
Yeah, so throughout the day you have run many of the exercises already and examples
and you have encountered probably many errors and you have encountered many like when you
have a wrong code you get an error or something in your code and of course when we are talking
about, for example, exercises in this course, these are small programs that you run. But when
you start to write your own program, we'll talk about scripts tomorrow, so a bit more about how
do you write, and also about modules and libraries, how do you write bigger programs. And when it comes
to these, for writing these bigger programs, you usually have the situation where it's a big thing
and you can have errors in multiple places. And we are all humans, so we don't write perfect code.
Nobody writes perfect code and that's completely normal. And for that, programmers and people who
write programs, they have written things that help with the tool, help with dealing these
problems. And well, the most common is like if you have an editor that has syntax highlighting,
like Jupyter has. So if you have...
So it's basically, it's tools that make your human effort more effective.
Yes, so let's say you have a VScode or something and it can give you auto-completion or something.
These are already productivity tools, they improve your productivity when you code.
But there's different colors of productivity tools or different types of productivity
tools and these are the most common ones, of course.
But then there's other tools that are specifically designed to fix certain things about your
programs, or help you fix certain things about your programs.
So for example, let's think about what the Python language is.
So if you want to give a terminal, or Python terminal, and run the first example that
we have there in the code.
So if you try to run what we have in the...
A terminal or Jupyter Notebook?
You can take a notebook as well.
Okay.
Sure.
Yeah.
So...
I have to set a name.
This is a follow along.
You don't need to type in this, by the way.
So each language has a syntax.
So like program language has a syntax.
And sometimes you might do something that is not permitted in that language.
So for example, here you cannot assign true to be one because you're not allowed to change
the true value.
So you have to get a syntax error.
So you have a problem in the syntax of what you have been writing.
Like the programming language doesn't understand what they're doing.
Of course, in this case, it's like a trivial problem.
But if you have a big program and you forget to write one extra bracket or one extra comma
somewhere or something, you get the same syntax error, and it can be really tedious to find
out this, especially if it's at the end of your program.
I guess it's better to know right away rather than have to save it.
And for this reason, people have written these linters.
So they remove lint.
I think that's the name why they have been written.
So they remove extra stuff and bad stuff from the code.
And they can spot these syntax errors.
So some popular linters are this rough i-lint and flake-8.
But for this example, let's try with pylint, which should be installed in the example.
For example, yeah.
OK, so I'll type.
So in order to open the script, so we'll
talk more about this tomorrow.
Here's what I can do.
I can right click and copy the link.
And in JupyterLab, go to File, open from URL,
and paste the link.
OK, I have to use Control-V. And click Open.
And here it is. So it's both saved the file and has opened it in the JupyterLab here.
Yeah. And this program, usually when you get programs on the internet, when you use code by
other people, or if you write the code, you might write it as a script. Like in this case, it's an
example script. And by quick glance, it looks like Python code. So what's the problem? But let's try
to use PyLint to check if there's any problems here. So, the examples here use the command line.
So, there is possibility of getting these linters working in JupyterLab, but unfortunately,
well, you need to install specific packages for that. And for this example, let's try with the
terminal. So, we're showing from the command line. We think we've made this where if you're using
the Anaconda that should work on all operating systems.
But if not, then take a step back, watch us,
and don't worry.
Yeah, you don't need to run these examples while we are.
So I've made a new terminal here.
And I can scoot this down here.
So it shows I'm in.
Oh, I wanted this to open in the terminal.
If I click plus here, OK, so opening it this way
has put me at the right place where my Python stuff is.
OK, so what do I do?
I try running the lint.
Yeah, let's try running pylint and run the example.
Pylint, lint example.
So I push tab, it filled out the name.
I push enter, and okay, error.
So now we get an error.
So we see that there's first the name of the file, lint_example.py, then we get a line number
4, and then we get a 31.
I'm not certain what the 31 actually is.
I think it's called column 31.
And then we get an error code, like E something, like an error 0001, parsing failed, unmatched
bracket. So if we now look at line four of the code and scroll down, we notice that there's
an extra bracket there. Well, actually, the JupyterLab highlights it for us. It marks
it as read already, which is nice, and which probably would help you not make this error.
But it's easy to see that, okay, now that we see it, we can remove it.
So let's remove that and save the file.
I remove that.
I save.
How do I save here?
File, save all, I guess works.
And then we rerun the linter?
Yeah, let's rerun it and see what happens.
So here in this terminal, I can push the up arrow key instead
of typing the whole thing again.
Yeah.
So now it's running again.
Why is it so slow?
Yeah, I don't know.
And we got plenty of other errors.
And let's look at these one by one.
So maybe if you can close the tab on the left.
Yes, OK.
So at the top, we see that, okay, on the line one,
we get this C something, missing module doc string.
So, okay, now this is like a code style warning
that you should have in your module,
you should have a documentation string there,
but okay, this is not an error, it's just good practice.
So let's not look at that too much.
On line four, we see, and also on line four,
column 4, line 4, column 19, and line 5, column 4, which is undefined variable np.
So the linter doesn't understand what np is, it hasn't been defined yet.
And this is explained by the last line in the error message, which is that on line 1
we have an unused import NumPy. So we imported NumPy, just import NumPy instead of import
NumPy as np. So that's why we got this error, but it was hard to spot because it was valid code.
Like it looked valid, but we had a mistake in the code because we did the import wrong.
Should I fix it?
Yes, let's fix it. If you look at also the end of the output for the pylint-er, you see that
it gave a code rating. And the code rating was zero because it knows that, okay, this code won't
run. So, let's give it a zero rating. Like, it's zero out of ten bad code. And now that we have
fixed it, let's try running the linter again. Okay. I save all and push up arrow key again.
So, now we see that it shows that it's still missing the module doc string, so it gives
a code warning on it, but the other problems have been solved, so now it grades it as 8.33
out of 10, and it shows the previous run, so what was the improvement.
And this is, to me, the most fun part of Linter, because it gamifies the coding, like how high
can your score go?
Can you get the 10 out of 10 for the Linter?
And basically, the idea behind the Linter is that it allows you to spot the errors and
fix this kind of coding style and coding problems that you might have in your code before you
even run the code.
So you get coding done faster and you get a better result out of it.
So should we go to the first exercise already maybe, or do we have any questions in there?
There's a good question.
Why can't the linter show all errors to begin with?
So why does it only show the syntax error first?
Yeah, so that's a good question. And I think that is related to,
like, yeah, that's a good question. That's probably how the linter has been designed
internally. There's different kinds of syntax errors. There's egregious ones, for example,
the true equals one, or the brackets. If it doesn't know how to parse the input.
Basically, in the first example, we had the extra bracket there.
So the linter didn't know that, okay, how should I pass this, even this text?
Because I don't understand what's happening here, because suddenly we get an extra bracket
and I don't understand, is this valid code?
It doesn't understand the input.
And in the second example, there's something wrong in the input.
So it's like there's a first kind of an error, which is like, okay, yeah, yeah, it doesn't
understand what, like in the context of the language, it doesn't understand that, okay,
what is NumPy?
Like this hasn't been said before to me.
But of course, like Linter doesn't capture all errors because like we said at the beginning
of the day, Python is strongly typed, but not like not enforced.
So you might modify the things when the program is running in a way that the linter doesn't
know about, and it might not spot those errors, but it will spot a lot of errors.
Like the most annoying ones, the trivial errors, the ones that you are like, okay, I should
have noticed this, it will spot those.
So for our time progress, so we've got 25 minutes left.
recombine two exercises together?
Or?
Yeah.
Yeah, maybe we can.
Or the second exercise is more of a demo, I would say,
anyways.
So maybe we should go to exercise one
and then go to the format.
OK.
So exercise one, and how long do we have?
So should we, yeah, should we take 10 minutes?
It's not that long of a nexus.
45.
Okay.
Yeah.
Great.
So see you in 10 minutes.
Okay.
Bye.
.
if you show the exercise code. This is, by design, an example of an error that the linter
doesn't spot. If you look at the code here, it's fairly normal code, but it's so complex
that it's hard to say where the errors are. But the error that the linter doesn't spot
is in the ax.scater, where you have one T instead of two Ts in that line. The reason
why the linter doesn't spot this error is that the linter doesn't actually import anything
when it runs. Like, when it runs, it just checks the code. It doesn't actually, like,
import pandas. It doesn't import matplotlib or anything like that. So, it doesn't spot
that, okay, there's this object that has this attribute that is wrongly named.
So, it's, yeah.
It doesn't import anything or doesn't go fully deep?
Well, yeah. It usually checks like module level stuff. But usually it doesn't go that deep. So,
of course, there's other linters that might spot this, but there are various tools that you can use.
But this is like an example. Linters are no means perfect, but the thing is that they spot
spot a vast majority of the kind of things that humans might not spot, like these kind
of like KVL things.
I guess it's just...
Yeah.
Go ahead.
I was going to say, it's like, it's, it works well with a human.
Like you spot some things easily, but not others.
And the computer spots some things that you don't see well.
Yeah.
And it's a tool. It's a tool that you can use or not use. If you don't like linters,
you don't have to, but then you might encounter errors a bit more.
Yeah.
Okay. But let's move forward to another kind of productivity tool that you can use.
And this is about style enforcement. So Python is very flexible when it comes to
what sort of programming styles should you use? What sort of naming should you use? So
Here's a few examples. You can use different variable naming styles. These are all valid
Python, but they are for the reason that it's flexible. It doesn't enforce it,
but at the same time, it recommends certain standards, Python developers, because then it
makes coding easier to read for other people as well. These major standards are these Python
Enhancement protocols. I don't know what these are called. These PEP.
Yeah, I think it's Python Enhancement protocols.
Yeah, they're like recommendations for the community.
And the PEP 8 is one of the most popular ones, which is like set standards of how,
like, okay, your code should look like this. And then there's a docstring standard of how
the documentation strings should be written. And different people have different standards.
For example, for the documentation strings, NumPy has its own standard.
and Google has its own standard and different places have their own standards. But what is
usually nice is that you can use these different kinds of formatters and linters to enforce a
certain standard for your code. So I personally, I don't have that many opinions on my code.
I would rather my code be readable than something like, there's this joke about why don't people,
people, if they are in a courtroom and they are asked to tell in your own words what happened
in the situation, nobody just invents their own words, they use the same words that everybody
else uses.
They don't just start gobbling up random words, they use the words that other people
use.
And it's the same thing.
standards that other people use, it makes other people easier to read your code and easier to
write your code. And it's much easier to let a formatter or linter determine the standard than
fix it yourself. So, in the example, let's do the example here. So, we'll use this.
Oh. So, do right here.
Yeah. So, if you download the code here. So, this code looks pretty awful, right?
it's by design, it's supposed to look awful. It works. It's completely working code, but
I don't like it. It doesn't look pretty to me.
It's spacing weird.
Yeah, there's weird spacing, weird variable names, and all sorts of things. It's not pretty.
So let's do it.
Yeah.
copy the link, go to file, open from URL, paste the link, and open. I'm going to move
this to the top here.
Yeah. So, yeah, it works and it calculates this pi estimate using this target method,
but it's...
Yeah.
And it gives like examples there, but it looks pretty awful.
Should I try to run it?
Yeah, you can try to run it. Maybe try it from the command line.
Yeah, so here's Flake.
We'll see more how these scripts work tomorrow, so if this doesn't make sense, don't worry.
Yeah, but the main thing is how can we make it better?
So let's try first running pylint on it.
Sorry, flake8 on it.
flake8 is this kind of like linter and code syntax, like checker.
And if you look at what sort of things it gives, it gives various of these, like, okay,
you should fix this and yeah.
And what we can do, of course, is we can manually fix these and it makes the code better.
But we can also use a formatter.
So one of the most common formatters is this black by Python Software Foundation, which
is like this opinionated formatter.
So it has its own style and it wants to enforce that style.
So it's a play on the Henry Ford's, like, you can have the Model T, the car.
Oh, that's where the name comes from.
In any color, as long as it's black, like that famous quote.
So it tries to enforce its own style.
So let's try to run black on this code example.
Okay, so, and I have been black, but it's in the, in the environment, in the, it's in
the code environment.
If you have, if you have installed them, yeah, okay.
Yeah.
Oh, so now it's reformatted it.
So you probably need to open the file again or reload it or.
Is there a reload Python file from disk?
So now we see that things happened.
So if we compare what's at the bottom and what's here, suddenly, for example, between
the brackets, all of the extra spacing is gone.
Some of the spacings are gone and things have been organized in a bit better way.
If you now run the Flake 8 again, Hoyt, let's ask it what it says about this.
So, I just pushed the up arrow key twice there.
Okay.
So, one line too long.
Yeah.
So, it.
Line.
Yeah.
Line five.
So, it says that, okay, usually there's this character limit of 80 characters so that it
can fit into a terminal. You don't have to enforce any standard, but that's common. In
your environment, you probably don't have this pep8 naming package that is in the example
and in the example environments, but it doesn't really matter. But it would give, if you scroll
a bit up.
It's up.
like, there. It would give those warnings. So, the name of the package is a bit above.
But those are warnings. It would give those warnings. So, you can install into Flake 8
these additional style guides. There's a huge amount of these extensions. And one of these
extensions gives warnings about variable names that don't abide by the pet8 convention. So,
example, it would say that the function name should be lowercase and the variable should
be lowercase. So those PI numbers there, because those are basically the standards.
But it doesn't really matter. You can go by the standards that you want to. All of these tools
are meant for you to enforce what you think is good code. But of course, they're also to
to, like, help others read your code, but you don't have to use any of these tools.
But usually, like, at least for me, it, like, gives me a peace of mind that, like, I haven't
written, like, code that looks bad for other people to read, because, like, then it makes
harder for them to use the code that I've written, because it's a collaborative effort,
and that's why people use these formatters and linters.
So here, well, do we have more or should I ask a philosophical question?
Shoot.
So my problem with things like code formatters, so for example this 4.11 here.
To me, how it is now with these spaces.
I would, if I was writing this myself, to me this is clearly easier to read.
Yes.
And, like, the way that things...
So, like, I like the idea, but the implementation...
If I'm running Black on my own code, it's usually making it easier to read in places I don't care about and harder to read other places.
So what I think, and I tend to use this white space a lot
to group things so I can mentally
understand what's going on or align things vertically.
But my proposed solution to this dilemma
is if it's a small issue of my own project,
I know I'm formatting it well myself anyway.
But whenever it's someone else's project,
or if it's a big project, a random contribution coming in
is probably worse than I would want.
So there it's better to make it uniform,
even if the uniform is not exactly what I would want.
Do you have any thoughts on this?
Yeah, yeah, I completely agree.
And I will also mention that there's like,
like what I usually myself do is that I usually pick
the tools I want to use,
like the linters or formaters I want to use.
And then you can, all of these tools,
you can specify different things that they want to do. There's different flags and configuration
parameters. And usually they're like .blackrc or some configuration file that you can specify that,
okay, don't care about these things. I want you to worry about these things and not these things.
And then you can enforce throughout the project a consistent style, but leaving your own things
there. There's also alternative linters that, for example, fix... Google has its own linter that
fixes these multiplication things. But I agree. The code, the formatters, it's the same with
ChatGPT or something like that. The ChatGPT has seen code and it writes code, but of course,
it doesn't understand code in the sense that humans do. So for us, we might have a different
kind of perception of the code and see some code to be better than the other one,
and more visually pleasing or something. The pattern looks nicer or something.
I don't know how much more time we have, but there's a really good question, number 71,
do linter spot type mismatches. Should we go to the notes now? Are we done with the lesson?
Yeah, I think we're done with the lesson. This is just a quick demo. In the lesson,
there's also mentioned about how you can automatically integrate into this to Git
so that whenever you run a commit, it will automatically run these linters and it will
say to you that, okay, like you have a problem in your commit or something. But, yeah, let's go to
the we can go to the, like, the cool down of that. But the idea behind this, there's huge
amount of these linters and huge amount of these productivity tools. But they are these tools. Like,
that's the most important things. And, like, if you don't know if you feel unsure about your code
And if you don't know how you should write your code and that sort of things,
the formatters and linters can make you write better code because they can help you with
the hard decisions of how should I write my code. And you don't have to worry about the code style
that you're using. You just follow what the linter says. And I personally do that a lot,
because I don't want to think about... I don't have that many opinions, so I would rather...
Like, somebody else has decided the thing already, so it's better to follow their lead.
They probably have good reasons for it. I usually follow that sort of paradigm.
Yeah. Okay. Sorry, I was looking at other things and adding the feedback to the notes.
Did we already answer that do linters detect type mismatches?
Yes. I'll mention that. So, like Python, for example, it's not strongly typed. So,
the types can change throughout the code runtime. But they are like type hints that you can put
into your code. And various programs, for example, or various libraries like NumPy and
Matplotlib and everything, they do this in the code. So then you can, if you write your type
into your code, you can run the static code checkers that basically go through your code,
they run the code, and then they check if the type suddenly changes or if they're incompatible
types or whatever. There are tools for this, and it just depends on how production code you want
to write. Normally, when we write scientific code, it's not necessarily like
you don't have to worry about types that much. But if you write a core library,
if you want to write a library that other people are using, then it might be a good
idea to add a type in. It becomes more easy for other people to use that.
But yeah, like on a normal small program, I don't know if it's necessary to use the type
hints.
Yeah.
It depends on the size of the program and the amount of collaborators as well.
Like if you have thousands, like I think somewhere in Black's website, they said that
there's 20 million lines of code formatted with Black.
20 million?
Yeah.
Formatted?
Formatted, yeah.
In the form?
Yeah.
So there are so many big projects that are using it, like no human would want to do that
code formatting for that job, basically.
I wouldn't want to do it.
I wouldn't want to be a type checker in a big company
checking, is the code looking good?
But there's tools for that.
OK.
Any other comments or things to discuss here?
So, this question 73, I think you can configure many of the linters for own preferences, like
what to ignore, and so on.
Also, [Name], I think you hinted at this, can black be configured to not do certain formats?
Or is it only one?
I think all of them have a huge amount of flags, so usually what you do is you start
But start from the basic configuration
and then you drop out certain things.
So yeah, it's usually like you can skip various things.
OK.
And this question 74, is it possible to use x with tool y?
The answer is usually yes.
but the person you ask usually won't know because there's so many combinations.
So do your own web searches and probably you can figure out how to.
But if you're using any of the popular things like in the question list PyCharm,
but if you're using VS Code, Veeam or whatever, there's like a million extensions that combine,
like [Name] said, tool X with tool Y. And usually you get like a button that
But like, if you press this button, it will run this linter or whatever for your code.
And usually many IDEs, they already come with some of these tools.
Like they will automatically flag you syntax errors and that sort of thing.
But it's important to know that like these tools exist and you can utilize them.
And it's not like cheating, like who cares?
Not like, yeah, it isn't like you did it the hard way.
OK, now you won a medal.
Like coding isn't like a competitive video game
or something.
Like it's like coding is, yeah, you can go the easy route.
Your main work isn't a homework assignment
where if you don't do it yourself, it's plagiarism.
your real work is.
Yeah.
Like, for example, one would think that, for example, like.
We're past the time now.
So if we are done with everything for today,
we might still hang out talking for a little bit.
But thank you for coming.
And if you have more, please fill out
this feedback for today.
it is very important and we always look at it before preparing the next year.
Okay, so what were you saying before? Yeah, I was just saying that if you think about,
the fresco on Sistine Chapel or something, Michelangelo didn't paint the whole thing.
he had a huge amount of helpers planning and doing that painting. Or like David, he had people
helping with the initial steps of the work, like applying a low-layer paint and that sort of
stuff. So coding is a similar kind of thing. The hard things are what you really want to do with
with the code, the easier things of, okay, how do I write this?
You can use chat GPT or whatever, like linters and formatters to help you with
that, getting the idea across and the, you can, you can get the art out of the
marble block, but like, yeah, it's not cheating to use like helper tools.
It's, it's just a way of improving the productivity.
Yeah.
Okay.
Hello, [name].
Any comments on today before we hang up?
I really like this productivity tool session.
It was good to edit.
So I learned new things.
And these are tools I use.
Yeah, the only thing I would want to, like next year,
we have to figure out how do we add it into the Jupyter.
Because, yeah, like just we maybe
need to make the environment so it's already there
something because it's possible to add these into Jupyter as well. So the exercise will be easier to
run without scripts. Yeah, but it's also a good preview for tomorrow since tomorrow we need to do
the script stuff. Yeah, tomorrow we'll have a lot of talk about like scripts and also libraries and
that sort of stuff. And also there was mentioned about software architecture in the chat. So we'll
be talking about that as well. And these productivity tools are, yeah, like [Name] said,
tied to that. But yeah, so should we close out the day? Great. Let's close up. See you tomorrow.
So remember to prepare for day three. There's some news here, which you probably already read.
Remember to give feedback. This session, for example, was a new session, so it would be nice
to hear what can we improve and what would you like to hear more in the upcoming years.
Yeah. Okay. Thanks a lot. See you tomorrow. Same time. Bye.