Hi.
So, welcome to day two.
We see the notes here, as usual.
So, should we talk a little bit about yesterday?
many people were here yesterday or not? How about we add a poll? I'm writing it now.
So yeah, you see right here. If you were here, then add an oh yes or on the no part or partly
and let's see. Are there any other cool questions we can ask for starting off?
Yes, today's topic is Matplotlib and mainly that's the big one and the data formats,
Good morning, are we already streaming?
Yes we are live.
Hello everyone.
Good morning, everybody.
Yes.
OK.
OK, so there I added a poll about how big of data use
was Python, which relates to several things today.
Yeah, so any other questions and follow-ups from yesterday?
Let's see.
Someone asked anything special to know from Tuesday.
So if you ask me, the Tuesday session was a pretty, like it really was covering basic
kind of things.
So the first lessons were about Jupiter and NumPy, which was sort of setting everyone
at the same starting level.
If they're new to you, it's worth reviewing them, but if you use them a little bit, it's
probably okay.
And also, it's okay—I mean, it's always worth learning more about numpy and pandas,
but you're probably okay for the rest of the lesson.
The last lesson from yesterday was pandas, and we continue with pandas in a few minutes
now.
So for that, we really had this high-level overview, because we had to talk both quickly
and also rather it was a bad combination of speaking quickly
and giving a high and low level overview at the same time.
But that's because there is so much to talk about there.
So all we hope to give was a starting point
and then motivating you to read more yourself.
And if Pandas seems like the kind of thing you need,
I'd really recommend reading these tutorials, like 10 minutes to pandas and so on.
So today we'll basically start from scratch and do something else, so it's not that necessary
to look through yesterday if you want to see today's thing, because it is the first thing,
so you have four minutes.
It's fine.
Did anyone notice the videos are published?
So I've slightly refined the video making system.
So it's a little bit quicker for us now, which is good.
There's a good question here.
In part of the course, so this is on the course page or the lesson page, Python is strongly
and dynamically typed.
means roughly it's not possible to circumvent the type system. Is there any language that
behaves the opposite? Does anyone have any answers to that?
Well, there's
there's plenty of ways of circumventing the type system in C and C++
because they're so low level. So I guess they are not as strongly typed.
Yeah, so that means, like, reinterpret the memory as a different kind of pointer or something
like that.
Basically, yes.
Okay.
I'm casting to a different subclass of a class.
Okay, okay.
Yeah.
Really, I don't think there's anything that's weakly and statically typed, because that,
I don't know.
I mean, that never makes sense.
But there are weakly typed languages where there just are no types, like JavaScript is
rather weakly typed.
And then there are statically tied, where you have to declare all the types, like C
and C++.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's the kind of thing that I haven't really gone that much into the theory of different
types of programming paradigms and so on.
Anyway, any other questions we should discuss?
No comments from the audience.
Yeah, I don't see anything.
It's also one minute, too.
How's our volume level doing?
Should we do our standard test?
So one, one, two, two, three, three.
Okay.
What do you think?
If there's no comments on audio, I guess.
Okay.
Audio levels are good.
So yeah, so the big picture of today,
first we start with a little bit more of Pandas.
So we'll show about time series stuff
and an overview of something from last time.
And then we have a big, long lesson
on matplotlib, which is the core plotting library.
And that's sort of the basis of all the other plotting stuff.
And then there is a quick summary of data formats,
and then a slightly longer description of productivity
tools for Python, things like linters and stuff like that.
OK, but with that being said, let's start.
So I will switch to [name]'s screen.
Where's all my pointers. So, there we go. Okay. So, we are continuing with pandas. So,