Where's all my pointers. So, there we go. Okay. So, we are continuing with pandas. So,
I'd recommend at the first, for now, you watch us as we type. And then, when it comes time
to exercise your work, because we're going to be typing fast.
And I don't think you can keep up
where this is more a demo than a type log right now.
So with that being said, where's our starting point?
So we first wanted to demonstrate some extra data
frame properties, which was the merging of data frames.
Is that correct?
Yeah.
OK, so a merge, if you know the concept from SQL or things
like that, it will make sense.
But let's show what it is visually.
So we're using the runner examples.
So import pandas.
So this is from yesterday just.
And this is the runner ranking.
Yes.
And if we run this, what do we see?
It's also printed.
So we see runners with distance and time.
So if we scroll down a little bit
under the working with data frames,
we see an age data frame, which has different.
For each runner, it has the age.
So notice the runner column is the same among both of them.
So we want to match up these datas and connect.
[name], can you close the sidebar?
Yes.
OK, there we go.
OK, so what happens when we merge them?
So we take the parent data frame,
and what we want to add to it is age.
we say we connect age to it and the runner column is the thing that matches up and if we run this
we see uh does it return it directly yes it does okay so this returns it directly it probably
doesn't modify the original data frames but we see now age has been connected to the runners
everywhere it should be
And yeah, that's that's the idea of merge. And there's all kinds of these tools that you can
find in pandas to do almost everything you can. I mean, it's the same kind of tools you'd find in
other things like SQL and so on. But if you ever find yourself going in manually, doing this kind
of data processing thing, connecting tabular or tidy data, then maybe take a step back and see
see, should we be doing it with pandas instead.
So our next demo is about time series.
So what does this mean?
So a time series is something where
there is data which occurs periodically over time.
And this is one of the original major use cases of pandas.
So it has pretty good support there.
So first, we will load this CSV file
from the web, which has information on all the Nobel
Prize winners.
So when we run this, we can see something.
And we see there's, well, like we expect, first name, names,
born, died, born, country, all these kinds of things.
So the thing is that these born and died columns,
it looks like dates to us,
but the computer doesn't interpret them as dates.
So we can tell pandas this should be a date time column.
So there's this next little bit here we can copy.
There we go.
And if we run this and then do a head of the Nobel Prize,
Nobel Prize, again. So it looks pretty similar. But if we do an info now, nobel.info.
So notice that born, died, and year, they're all now DateTime64 objects. Which means,
so before they were object like the other ones. So that means Pandas knows that these are actually
DateTime objects. And under the hood, these are actually NumPy types.
So we can do some extra things now. So for example, if we do for each of these DateTime
columns, there's a .dt attribute, which means interpret this as a Python DateTime.
And we can do things like day. Let's see. And it tells us, oh,
It's the day of the month.
It's the integer of the day out of there.
We can do year.
Yeah, that looks OK.
And even things like weekday, which
this comes from the Python date time object.
And I guess that will also define what it actually
means in there.
So it's like, it's Sunday, Monday, Tuesday, and so on.
Yeah.
But represented as a number.
So since these are date times, we can do things like arithmetic on them.
So the next thing down here is how we can subtract them.
So we're subtracting the born and died years, converting it to days, dividing that by 365
to make years, and then rounding it by one.
So I guess we want to run nopal.head or something
like that.
OK, yeah.
Because this just added a lifespan column.
And somewhere there, there's probably lifespan.
It's the last one.
That seems pretty reasonable looking.
So what do we do with this lifespan now?
So we have an integer lifespan.
So we can do things like plot, like make plots out of it.
So for example, let's make this histogram.
So column lifespan, we specify some bin size and so on.
And OK, yeah, looks like reasonable ages
for relatively well-off people from the last century.
Next off, let's do something else.
Since we have a column that
specifies what category or price they've got,
there's all kinds of things built in like
plotting the lifespan split up by category.
So how does this look?
Yeah, I mean, seems pretty reasonable.
Yeah, the statistics are not that great, so I don't think you can actually draw inferences,
but you see some interesting data.
Okay, so we're about to go to exercises here, these exercises three.
And what have we learned then?
So basically, by using Pandas the way it's made, by converting things to the right data
types and aligning all the columns and making them tidy, there's all these different powerful
things we can take and use, which let us do things very quickly.
But remember what I said back at the beginning.
So almost every time I do something medium level in Pandas, I do a web search to figure
out how I do it.
Because I can't keep it all in my mind.
I know the basics like slicing stuff and so on.
So just keep that in mind.
If it seems hard, just take the time, read about it, and the more you use it, the better
you'll get at it. Okay. What do you think? Should we go straight there?
Yeah. Let's just go to ‑‑ I mean, I don't have anything special to add. It's the
same for me. I'm always checking how to do things in pandas rather than remembering.
And this goes for basically any library in Python. Usually you don't remember how to
do any complicated operations, you check.
There's so many things you can do with these libraries.
OK, yeah.
There's a good question coming up.
Can we say something about the difference between pandas
and R's tidyverse?
So [name], do you know much about R's tidyverse?
Not that much.
I mean, it's a few more.
I propose we go to the exercises. Maybe we can have someone comment a little bit more after the exercises.
So, yeah. Okay, let's go. So how long were the exercises supposed to be? 20 minutes or 15 minutes?
15 minutes. Okay. 25, and then we come back. Okay, I switch to the notes, and see you soon. Bye.
Hello, we're back.
So yes, if we look here, we see some good questions in the notes.
There's this one about the difference between pandas and R's tidyverse.
When us instructors talking, we thought a good metaphor is that pandas is like what
R does itself, and tidyverse is a collection of many things around that, like a consistent
ecosystem of stuff that works together, and that's sort of like SciPy in Python.
But really, the philosophy is very similar of a bunch of stuff
consistently trying to work together.
There's some compatibility between them,
like in the data formats, which we might talk
about a little bit later today.
Okay. There is various.
So one thing maybe to raise is because there are these two functions for accessing columns
and rows, lock and add, which we did mention yesterday really quickly, but lock gets you
data but it doesn't allow you to set data and at allows you to set the data so that
so if you try to say database.log and then equals something it will give you an error
and then you should I guess the error message doesn't tell you to use at
so you need to remember to use at just a little bit you know annoying it's something you need
need to remember yeah okay so there is a little bit more in pandas down at the
bottom beyond the basics it's probably not worth us trying to go into the
details here but basically the idea is you can do a whole lot here there's
Sometimes depending on what you want, you can either get more power, or you can get
more optimized, like faster, and so on.
And yeah, maybe that's all we've got.
And remember, if this seems remotely useful to you, read the 10 minute introductions to
pandas and get this perspective.
Um, yes, okay. Should we call it good and go to
the next part then?
Yeah, let's move on.