Thanks a lot.
And good morning, everybody.
Maybe we should, what I'm unsure about
is whether my microphone volume level is all right.
but so give us feedback somewhere on one of these chats.
But let's start with an introduction.
So my name is [name].
I'm super excited that I will teach
data visualization here with [Name].
We will talk about data visualization and Map.lib,
two topics I really like to talk about.
I work in Norway, in Tromsø.
I do research software engineering
and I like to help researchers with improving their code.
And I like to teach Python and different things. And with me is [Name].
Yeah, good morning, everyone. My name is [Name]. I work at the PDC Center for
High Performance Computing in Stockholm. But right now I'm sitting here from Uppsala.
And I realized that I should take the screen and arrange it. Let me do that.
Just a sec, he, no, that's not right.
Almost double range.
And while I opened the sharing window,
I will close my physical window.
All right.
Good.
We will talk about data visualization.
And let me first tell you how the best way to participate.
So what to expect.
It's good if you have your JupyterLab open,
and I understand you have that already
if you were following the Pandas episode,
but if you joined later,
it's a good moment to open up your JupyterLab.
We will be using it.
So we will be doing data visualization inside Jupyter.
And we will also explain why that is such a good fit.
And we also, you can open up this episode,
the data visualization with matplotlib,
which is also linked in our collaborative notes.
And [Name] and me, we will look at these notes.
So that's a good place to ask us questions.
And in a different window on my screen, I have them open,
and we will try to react to questions live.
So please keep the questions coming.
We plan to do a bit of introduction
for the first 15 minutes.
We will then do an exercise block.
So you will get 20 minutes to try this on your own.
We will then do a break.
And after the break, we will do something,
we will talk about how to make plots even prettier.
And then we will have another exercise block.
And now the question is, should you, should you, as we, as we show you how this works
in a notebook, you can, you can either try that with us.
So if I add something to the notebook, you can do it as well.
If that is cognitively a bit too much to listen and also go into a different window and type
something it's also totally fine to just watch what we do and you will have enough time in
the exercise box to try it yourself good so let's first motivate why we do this and why
we chose matplotlib and why we do that in a jupyter notebook let me just arrange the
to Windows here on my side so that I can see your questions.
Let me also zoom in here a bit.
Data visualization with Matplotlib.
So our goal is not becoming experts
and knowing everything that can be done with Matplotlib,
but we want to give you a really good overview
of how to find help, how do we use it,
and what are good starting points,
and how does it connect to the previous episodes
like pandas?
So that's our goal.
In total, we will spend one and a half hours on this topic.
So not only being able to start,
we also want to show you how can you tweak,
how can you improve plots without remembering
all the options and the commands
because we don't remember them either.
The application interface of Matplotlib is, is really big.
And it's also so that, so [name], is Matplotlib the only Python package for visualization or
are there more?
No.
Opportunities?
So there are many.
Here are the ones that we know, that we know.
So there are probably even more.
I have tested most of them and I use them in different contexts.
So there is matplotlib.
This is the one that we will show you.
There is also, and it is probably the most popular one, but there is Seaborn, which builds
on top of matplotlib.
There is Vega out there, plotly, ggplot, and then there are different libraries for more
special use cases.
I would consider the top four here or the top five really general.
So there are many libraries and also Python is not the only language that can do plotting.
So why do, why do we do matplotlib?
So I would say one, one very, very good thing with matplotlib is that, I mean, as Python
is a completely free ecosystem, it is transferable.
So if you write the plotting scripts in matplotlib,
you can share them with your colleagues
and also with the community at large.
This can be done a little bit in contrast
with some commercial packages for plotting
where you might have a lock-in effect
that you prepare your scripting and then you share it
and others cannot, perhaps they can read the script file,
but they cannot make use of it
because they do not have the program.
Yeah.
And it may even be the same person or you
in a different job in future.
And so the fact that it is free,
that both Python is free and open source
and that matplotlib is free and open source
is really important.
And it's really important for reusability
and reproducibility.
And I like to, so when I talk about data visualization,
I like to start with this quote,
which I took from this fantastic book
by Claus Wilke, Fundamentals of Data Visualization,
which you can browse, the book is online.
And it is this quote here,
that one thing I have learned over the years
is that automation is our friend.
I think figures should be auto-generated
as part of a data analysis pipeline,
and they should come out of the pipeline
ready to be sent to the printer with,
and here I paraphrase, with minimal post-processing needed.
And this is because when we generate plots for posters
or publications or theses, at least in my experience,
I never do it only once.
I do it at least twice.
I do it once and then I do it again
one day before the deadline because something changed.
I want to modify the color or I get new data
or I realized that there was a tiny mistake
and I need to change the figure.
And if this is not automated, it's hard.
Might need different versions of your figures.
So the precise size and shape of a figure
that you have in a manuscript might be different
from what you then need to go on a poster
or on slides for presentation.
Then if you have that in script form,
you can then tune to the appropriate format
and then reuse your work.
Yeah. Or new data comes in and you want to update the figure.
And we will see that if we use tools like Matplotlib
in combination with tools like Jupyter Notebook, this becomes a really nice combination.
So we will now focus on Matplotlib, but you can browse, of course, all the other ones as well.
Well, at the end of the session, we might also have a look at one of the other libraries.
Why did we start with matplotlib? We motivated a little bit. It's also, so it is the most
popular library. It is, if you come from Matlab, it will feel familiar because it, it takes
a lot of inspiration from how plotting is in MATLAB.
Even if you choose to not use Matplotlib, maybe you prefer Seaborn.
Many of these libraries build on top of Matplotlib.
And then if you want to tweak it, improve it, it helps to have an understanding of Matplotlib
to be able to improve your plots.
But it is relatively low level, low level in terms of we can really modify everything.
So in terms of abstraction, it doesn't provide statistical functions.
Some of the some of the other libraries do.
But the advantage of my book is that you can adjust everything, you can really make things
publication ready.
and can be configured and modified.
And speaking of statistics,
which is not containing matplotlib,
I mean, you can naturally combine the matplotlib scripting
that you do with other Python packages,
such as numpy, scipy, and then mostly pandas
that we have been talking about earlier.
And I'm having just a quick look on the questions.
Thanks for coming, raising them.
For instance, question nine,
when should I use X and when should I use PLT?
This is something that confused me a lot
when learning and using maplotlib.
And we will comment on that.
So we will clarify that.
This is something I realized maybe 10 years into using it,
that there were these different interfaces.
So we will comment on it.
Also, another really good question is,
how is matplotlib built on top, built using,
so how does it connect to pandas?
And also this is something we will discuss.
Some of the plotting libraries interface with pandas
in a more nice way or less,
but also with matplotlib it is possible
to use pandas data frames.
we will come back to that.
But I think we are ready to open up the notebook
and start creating our first plot.
At this moment, you can either do it as well
if you have enough screen space
and enough cognitive management,
but you can also watch what we do.
You will have the chance to test it out
in the exercise block.
I will open up a new notebook.
So let's start with a new notebook.
Let's not continue from one from before.
I will open up a new one and also good first reflex is to rename it.
I don't want to have my notebooks untitled, untitled 1, untitled 2.
I want to give it a good name.
I will rename it.
Right click, rename notebook.
Let's call it plotting.
And back to the material.
I will copy paste the code here from this block.
I will run it in a notebook,
but let's also explain then what is happening.
Let me copy.
So I copied the whole block.
Let's see whether this works at all.
Yeah, you're in the Python for SciComp
Python environment, I guess.
Yes.
or anaconda environment yes yes so at this moment all we import is a library called matplotlib
which is part of the python for scicomp it is also part of an anaconda base environment
so if you get here an error that matplotlib not found then you are probably in a different
environment. And I ran this code, I got a first plot, which shows some dots. I have
an x axis, I have a y axis and a title, they are not very concrete yet. And now let's inspect
the corresponding code. What did what did we do, we imported the functionality. I am
I defined two lists of numbers x values y values
and these values take they are part of the so-called arms come squatted which is a really
important data set
because it is used to motivate why we even do data visualization because it's it's for
data sets which
really look very different when we plot them.
But when you look at the statistical values,
like the mean, the sample variance, the correlation,
the regression, the statistical values are the same.
So if I didn't plot these,
if I would only look at the numbers at the table,
I would maybe have less insight.
But back to the example, what else can we discuss here?
This is the important part. These two lines, we, we set up a figure and we set up axes.
These are objects, which we then can use to, for instance, do a scatter plot. And here
I sent the data X into, I said, these are the X values. These are the Y values. And
I define a color, which in a really weird format here,
but I will later comment on why we do this.
Instead, I could also use a named color.
I could say red.
And if I run that, then the dots will be red.
And this is self-descriptive here.
Just having a look at the questions.
using just import matplotlib instead of matplotlib.pyplot.
So why I do this here? Because there is more in matplotlib than the pyplot. Pyplot is one
of the interfaces that Matplotlib provides.
I could also import Matplotlib and then here I would have matplotlib.pyplot.plt.
I could do that as well and it would also work.
It wouldn't be on any noticeable penalty, maybe a little bit more typing.
I chose this way because this is often what people do and this is often what you find
when you look for examples on the internet or if you ask one of these AI chat solutions.
Just looking at the other, so question 15, is it better to use this way of doing it rather
than the PLT?
We will comment on that.
So we will come to this.
recommend to do it this way. So we show you the more robust way and but we need
to then also explain why this is possibly more robust. I think we will do
that after the exercise.
To go into the first exercise, so should we perhaps present it? Yes, so now you
you have all the tools ready to do the first exercise block.
Your goal, I mean, here it says 15 minutes,
but we really want to give you 20
until five minutes past the hour,
but I need to explain also clearly.
Your goal will be to do what we did here with [Name].
Open a notebook, copy the block, get it to run.
But once you get the image that we got here,
you are asked to extend it, you should add a second data set
and then yet another data set which is this one multiplied by two. And here we wanted to show you
also that this is a way to multiply all numbers. This is one of the many ways in Python to multiply
a list by a factor. Then you will get a plot that looks like this. And another thing that
you can try to do is browse the documentation, find out, so you can have a look at the quick
start guide and try to find out how can you get a label, sorry, a legend into the plot
that we can then link to the data values.
And at the end, it should look like this.
You can also experiment changing, modifying the colors.
And if you get stuck, there is a solution here.
So if I would open this up,
but I will do it only very quickly
because we don't want to have a spoiler,
but you find a solution for this exercise.
And then we can come back five minutes after the hour.
And after that, we will send you into a break.
And if you are curious about
why did we choose these particular colors,
here is an explanation.
Do we have everything we need for the exercise block?
So your goal is this exercise number matplotlib one.
And I will add instructions into the document
And we will be back five minutes after the hour.
All right, good luck and see you in a bit.
Bye.
And welcome back from the break.
We will continue with Matplotlib.
I wanted to also show you the result of the exercise session.
So hopefully you get the result that looks like this.
You also find this in the solution.
So here we have plotted three sets of X and Y values with different colors.
I want to save the notebook.
I just wanted to remind a really good practice that I find very useful is that before I save
a notebook and before I share a notebook with other people, I like to run all cells from
top to bottom.
If the notebook is not too long, I would recommend to do the restart kernel.
Yeah.
This is even better because this will reset and run everything from top to bottom because
this is exactly what the next person will do.
Because the next person opening the notebook will not have anything in memory.
It will...
They will run the notebook from top to bottom and I want to make sure that it still produces
the results that I want it.
This will prevent me from having to run the notebook
in a very particular order that nobody will remember.
And now I can save.
Super.
And before I hand over to [Name],
and before we talk about now, how can we improve a plot?
How can we customize it?
I wanted to comment on the question
that we got a couple of times,
which is which of the two possible ways
that one can use Matplotlib should we use?
and why. And I admit, sorry I need to zoom in here, I admit that although I was using
Matplotlib for quite a while, it wasn't clear to me that there were actually two different interfaces.
And I got really confused because every time I was asking the internet for how do I do something in
Matplotlib, I saw an answer but it always looked different than what I remembered. And I was
doubting myself for a long while until I learned that there are actually two ways to run Matplotlib.
One way is the so-called object oriented way, or also called the explicit interface.
And in this explicit interface, we create these objects.
And then we use them.
This is the method that we use in this lesson.
This is also the method that we recommend.
There is another method, which is the so-called pi plot way of doing things, or the so-called
implicit interface, which looks shorter. So there is less to type. I don't have to create
the figure object. I don't have to create the axis object. I can do this directly. So
it looks easier. The downside is that now that we start customizing. So if I now change
the the line width and the format and colors and settings. I will affect
the settings for all my plots that come later in the notebook or in my Python code. And
sometimes this is not what you want. So this will be more practical. If you
Once you start putting this into a function, because then when you change settings, you
change settings only for the for the function that you want and for the plots that you wanted
instead of changing it implicitly for everything.
So that's why we recommend this way, but we show you both ways because so that again,
You know, if you then search Stack Overflow
or you ask chat GPT for,
how do I do something with my potlip?
You might get, you might see this kind of an answer.
And then you know why this is different
than what we have just learned.
Here's also an explanation why we even spent
now a couple of minutes emphasizing this.
And with this, [Name] will now take over and guide us through styling and customizing plots.
And we continue watching the collaborative notes.
And please continue asking questions, we really appreciate it.
Yes, thank you, Ranaan. So, we will now touch upon the topic of styling and customization
plots. And a starting notion here is this, that this is also an aspect of reproducibility.
Because I used myself earlier in the days to often do plots with, yeah, often with MATLAB.
And I would then get a certain feel and look of the figures, and perhaps do something which
needed to be tuned a little bit, and I might then do it in a drawing program.
That's fine if you do it once or twice, but if you need to do it for 10 figures, it's
a lot of extra work.
So matplotlib and other libraries, they allow to customize almost every aspect of a plot.
And it's going to be good to know what are the different matplotlib parts of a figure
so that we know what we can search for when to customize things. So we open up this. And
This is here for a two-dimensional figure.
So you can see here that in the object-oriented modality,
we have all of these variables.
So you have the axis set minor locator.
You have a major tick label.
You have the markers that you can change.
And you have a legend.
And one thing that can be very convenient,
which you can show later in the notebook,
is that in order to see what are the different properties
that are available, you can use the help command.
Yes, and it's also nice to know how is this even called?
Like if I want to web search for something,
I really like this figure because then I know
that I need to search for something called
Minotic or Legend.
Yes, yeah, good point.
There's also, yeah, below here on the same webpage,
you also have an extensive listing
on what are these properties in web format.
So, from this paragraph here,
we also have a resource here,
which is, this is a to a Github repository
with matplotlib cheat sheets.
So this is something that you can explore later.
There is also a number of predefined style sheets that you can activate with the use
command. We can show some of these. So these are with the different collections of colors
and marker styles and line styles that you then can choose from. And these are designed
so that they have a good, good collection of colors, which is something that is very
important because it is not uncommon that a reader or a viewer of your figures might
have a limited capability to be colorblind, red, green colorblind, or other vision impairments.
And then it's good to have a color palette that works also when you are working in a
gray in gray scale so that you have light. You have that the color range ranges from
lighter up until the darker yeah one like during my PhD one recommendation was always
to print print your plot in black and white on a printer to see how it looks then if somebody
later prints the paper on a black and white printer then later I thought well that doesn't
make any sense anymore because I think nobody's reading papers anymore in paper, people read
it on in a computer. But now again, I know that it does make sense because it can help
us identify any sort of color problems for color vision deficiencies.
So we will now have an hands on example of exercises and styling and I will do it as
as a demo, you will also have time to do
the in the exercise session.
So what we'll do here is that we'll import a data set
from using pandas.
So the exercise is this one,
customization one, log scale in map.lib.
And I will now switch over to do it in the,
in the notebook. So, I start with copying this text snippet here.
And please remind me because I was so distracting answering something. Should we now all do
the same thing as you or should we watch? You can watch.
Okay. Yeah. So, this is now imported a data set. This
is about the statistics of countries. It's the gapminder dataset. And we will then use
a plot command that we go into the plot. It's, we can maybe reconnect to the previous lesson
about pandas. So what people see here is that we load a CSV file from the internet, but then
is this read CSV command,
which we have seen in the previous episode.
And at the same time, there is dot query.
So we filter out and we are only interested
in the data for the year 2007.
And here we have four different countries.
We have the life expectancy,
and we are interested in GDP, the gross domestic product.
So roughly how wealthy the country is.
So, I now take this snippet here and I paste it in here and execute it and what we get
here is that what we choose to work with here is the life expect. We will visualize life
expectancy as a function of the GDP per capita in terms of perching parity. The PPP, what's
Yeah, so it's some like inflation adjusted US dollars that are also adjusted to have
a more fair comparison. So it's not US dollars, but for our purposes, we can think of like
inflation adjusted US dollars.
Yes. And what we note here is that the data is here and distributed so that it's seen here.
a lot of it is along the vertical, along the vertical line here, and then around this horizontal
line here, horizontal region here in uppermost in the plot. So the question is here, how
can we make better use of the visualization to highlight the data here? So do you have
When you suggest another one, what could be?
Yeah, so one step that we can do
is we can try a logarithmic axis, which will then,
because we have such a big difference
in orders of magnitude on the x-axis.
So by switching to, from a linear to a log axis,
it will, we will probably see the trend hopefully clear.
Exactly, so we need then to set the axis scale
to a logarithmic one. And this will do by setting this attribute, the setXScale to log.
that line. And I go to the notebook. And add it there. Set X dot set scale underscore X
scale log. Yes. And now we have the logarithmic scale on the X axis here. And yeah, what we
have here is much more much more evenly distributed within the canvas. There's
also here one attribute, the alpha attribute, that we can play around with
here. So the alpha attribute is at first it's a half. You can see what happens if
If you change it to 0.8, yeah, then you can see that this affects the, the, the transparency
of points.
So by using this higher value, we have a more dense visualization of all the thoughts.
Great.
And a question to both of us.
So do, do you remember all of these things like how to set a log axis, how to, what,
how to do the trust, how to set the transparency? Like I admit that I don't, so I almost never
remember this. I always have to look it up. Yes, that's a good point. And one can then,
so we have here, if you see here, what, what, what are the objects that they've created?
They've created the handle fig and they've created the handle X and the logarithmic scale
is something that is set by working with the axe object.
And let's see what attributes do we have here for this object. So, we can type help and axe.
And then we can see that we have a very lengthy listing. Here's a description of what the object
these, what class it is. And then you can see that we have all of these listings. And
among these listings here, we will have then the logarithmic scale. Or the opportunity
to set a logarithmic scale.
That's neat.
Good.
We will now have,
we will,
not now, so we'll let you go into the exercise session
where you will play around with
customization of figures. And yeah, should we perhaps introduce the exercises. Here it's
working with the same datasets. Your task is that you will make the ticks marks and the
axis labels fonts larger. And you need you can search on the web for what are these attributes
that you need to work with. And the target that you're aiming for is to arrive to a figure
which is looking like this. So this is one of the exercise that you can do. And the second
exercise that you could, oh, we should hide the solution there. The third exercise that
you can work with here is that you can adopt a gallery example. And here we have some links
to some of the other resources that are, yeah, like Seaborn, which is based on Matlocklib.
And then there's also Vega Altair, which is a standalone Python package for visualization.
So people will choose exercise two or three.
And the exercise three is really close to at least how I work in real life.
So in real life, I don't remember all of these commands.
I often look through the gallery examples for something that looks similar to what I
have in mind.
And here you will try to first, I often take the example and I'll try to run it on my computer.
And then once I get it to work, then I try to change the data.
And then I try to put in my data, and then I tweak.
So that can that can be a really fun exploration, which is at least close to how I work.
I don't know about you, Juan, but I can't remember on almost anything.
I always start from something that already works
that somebody else created.
That's also how I do it.
So looking at this galleries
is a very good source of inspiration.
And that's also where you then get exposed
to what are the different functions and attributes
that you can work with.
So is there anything that we can bring up from the HackMD?
For now, I'm looking.
So most questions are answered
and they are relatively detailed.
One bigger picture question was
whether we will talk about interactive plots.
So plots where you can, you don't get just an image
but you get something that you can interact with
like with a slider.
And I believe that we will not do it in this course
but I will link to a lesson where this is demonstrated.
But I think we are almost ready for exercise session.
It will be customization two or three.
Until what time, like when we will be back?
We will take 20 minutes for this exercise.
All right, so we'll be back at 55 past
and then we will summarize,
we will connect this a bit with pandas data frames
and then hand over to the next episode.
So exercise customization two or three starting now,
see you again in 20 minutes.
Bye.
All right, we are back.
Five more minutes of matplotlib. So we want to wrap up the session and then we will go into
a break and then we will go into something else. And we thought that in the five minutes
we could try to do this exploration together on an example. And I also realized now during
the exercise session that the solution that we have listed here doesn't match anymore
perfectly the gallery of seaborne because they changed their examples anyway let's try this
together i will now take seaborne which is something that builds on top of matplotlib
and i will i will take that for a specific reason that i will come back to before the hour is over
so this is often how i start i open up one of these libraries i go to the gallery and i look
look for an example that looks close to what I have in mind.
And here I will, I will take,
I will try to be somehow close to the exercise.
I will, I want to do a violin plot,
which is a way to show distribution of points
and a statistical spread.
And so this is something,
I want to have something like this.
Here, this is what it looks, and there is an example code.
And the way I start often is I take what they have
and I try to run it on my computer first.
Let's try that.
Seaborn is a library that should be in your environment.
It is in the Python for SciComp.
It is also a part of Anaconda base environment.
And now I'm crossing fingers and running the cell.
and I get a plot that looks like what they have.
So that's already a big success story.
I don't fully understand what's going on here,
but my next step often is to,
I want to get an insight into the data
because I want to replace it with my own data.
And here I have a feeling that,
so load the example tips data set.
This is some data set about some bird.
No, it's about some smoking and not smoking.
But what I do, because I don't know this data set,
I would often, I would actually split,
split the cell into two.
And here I would print, I can do either this,
or if I'm in a notebook, I can do this directly tips.
I want to see how it looks.
Let's run all cells.
And this turns out to be, we already recognize this.
This is a pandas data frame with columns and rows.
And I think this data set shows
the different tipping behavior of smokers and non-smokers.
And now I also maybe understand that what this library is able to do is that we load
the data set and then we can map X values to a certain column and we can map the Y values
to a different column and we can map the color to a yet different column.
And now I would go in and instead of using this data set, I would try to put in my own
pandas data frame and I will try to plot that and only then I would start tweaking and adjusting
and customizing and here I wanted to show you that Seaborn is a library that is able
to really use pandas data frames directly and map columns to visual channels x y color
Can we do the same thing in map.lib?
And back to our lesson.
And I learned very recently that you can do almost the same thing in map.lib.
So instead of what we were doing, that we were sending a slice, a column of data into
defined as X or as Y, we can use this instead.
I can say the data is a data frame.
And then I can map X values to particular column,
Y values to a different column.
So that's very nice.
If you then try to do a bit more,
like if you try to map color to continent,
then it becomes a little bit harder.
And these are, so we wanted you to know
that there are libraries in Python
that make this easier and this is also for those of you who come from R and ggplot2
you can do the same things in Python with in libraries like Seaborn, Altair-Vega
but I see now that we are out of time
we will continue answering the questions so please keep asking questions about plotting
about Matplotlib and we will continue answering but I don't want to eat into the future sessions
So, thanks from my side, [Name], any concluding words here?
You covered it all.
And as I said, we will continue to answer questions on the HackMD.
Yeah.
More details there, I will answer there.
Thanks so much, everybody, for listening.
Thanks to [Name] for co-teaching and looking forward to the next sessions.
And I think now we go into a break, into a 10-minute break, if I understand correctly.
Yeah, break to 11 past the hour.
Yep.
Bye.