Hello, welcome back from the breaks.
So we'll now move on to something about the library ecosystem, how the Python libraries
are set up.
And also after that, we'll move on to dependency management.
[name], have you introduced yourself already?
Yeah, I introduced myself yesterday.
Have you?
Yes, so my name is [Name].
So disclaimer, I'm not a Python programmer,
but I support users on our high-performance computer
systems.
My current job is as the manager of the Norwegian AI Cloud.
But I also contribute to Code Refinery and Alto
and all the partners when I can.
So this library ecosystem, [Name], is
that when you want to achieve a certain task,
somebody might have already made some code
that you can achieve the thing you want to do.
So instead of you try to write it again,
you could reuse others' work.
In the first introduction, there was this interview
with the student.
So when we study, it seems people tell you
not to take others' work.
You have to do everything yourself.
But when you come to the real research,
practically, you can't do, quote, everything you want.
For example, if you want some matrix transformation
or Fourier transformation, some array sorting kind of thing,
it's already there out there.
So you have to use them.
So we will talk about how to reuse work.
So this is not like stealing other people's work.
This is actually reusing and collaboration.
Do you use a lot of libraries, [Name]?
Yes, all the time. So I would say that why Python is so popular, especially in scientific
context, is because of this library ecosystem. Python is not the perfect language for scientific
computation, like what, for example, [name] said at the Icebreaker session this morning, that
there are languages that are designed for scientific computing. Python is not one of them.
But Python is a very general language. It has all kinds of things. And the library ecosystem
makes it possible to have various things. So, like [name] said, in a job interview or something,
you might be asked to do a quicksort algorithm or something. But I would never trust my own
algorithm compared to something that is in a library ecosystem that has been validated by
hundreds or thousands of users. So yes, I use a lot of libraries all the time. I don't want to
reinvent the wheel if somebody already has perfected it. Correct. So if you were there
in the first day when [Name] and [Name] were introducing some beautiful introduction to the
course. So [Name] asked from [Name], when did you start using Python? And I know for a fact that
Yano is a very heavy user of this Python.
But he has to think a little bit.
When did I actually use Python?
So that's a very important thing that you mentioned, [Name].
That means Python itself is not a very useful part of it.
It is just what people made out of Python.
So earlier, if you remember that,
I don't know when you were young how you learned programming.
they taught us pseudocode, you know,
and you had to learn how the programming tactics
in order to actually write a big,
by the time you end up writing some code,
you have learned about a semester of,
you know, what programming is.
So this Python made it more democratic.
It doesn't matter where you come from.
We have come from biology, mathematics,
space science, or whatever it is.
You can just start achieving something.
So that achievement comes from the library ecosystem, as you said.
Yes.
And also I would add here that, like, for example, my first start in Python,
when I started working on it, I was in a summer job in Aalto University, actually.
And I had to convert a code that was using Python numeric, which was
this really old library, to NumPy.
So I had to convert this code that used this old library to a new library.
And the reason behind is that NumPy, like we have spoken already, underneath it, it's
C and Fortran, like underneath it.
But nobody wants to touch that part.
Like nobody wants to see that part because it's harder to write and more laborious to
write.
It's much easier to work with the NumPy.
And that's why like Python is so popular.
You can write these like other things on top of other things.
So at the bottom, you can have the C stuff and the Fortran stuff and that sort of thing,
but you don't ever have to necessarily touch it.
You can just interact with Python things and that's fine.
And that still gives you most of the speed that C and Fortran would give, but much more
usability.
Correct.
So it is not the time you first tried the Hello World, you know, it's not the Python
usage.
People actually use Python when they use a library and do something.
So that's why people think a little bit,
when did I actually use Python?
So it's not the Python hello world print,
it's actually the libraries ecosystem.
And then it is very nice that we have placed
all these terms in the same screen
because taking them alone,
libraries, packages, and dependencies,
sometimes it's hard to sort of comprehend
what this is about.
So I like to think of libraries as like a screwdriver.
you can it's it's not like well documented or well sort of made for like there's no big description
of how to do it but people who know how to use it they know how to use it but the package is more
like a tool set with a set of screwdrivers and there are some instruction and there are different
different gauges, different lengths. So you have this difference. So is that a good way
to look at it, these libraries and packages? So how do you look at it?
Yeah, like libraries, when we talk about libraries, we can often mean multiple things. So for
example, like library can be, like usually everything in Python is a module also. Like
I'm not completely certain what module means in the context of Python, because it's used
so many places so that it becomes a bit more like, like it's used so often that it loses
the meaning.
Like if you say a certain word enough, you don't know what it means anymore.
But usually like libraries are like, libraries and modules, they can be a bit like all over
the place, unless they have been like packaged together and made into like a complete set
of like tools.
and like usually when we talk about packages, we mean that there's like a bunch of code and
you don't want to look what necessarily what's inside of it if it works correctly. But you want
to interact with that code with certain like functions or objects or certain things that it
presents you. So, for example, like you NumPy arrays have a lot of like hidden things inside
of the hidden attributes and that sort of thing. But you don't want to work with those because they
are inside the package. You want to work with the functions that the arrays present you or what the
developers of the package present you. So, you want to only deal with the outermost layer of
the package because that's what the developers of the package want to give you. And that's how it
usually goes, that you have an outermost layer of nice things that you can use and inside there's
a whole mess of stuff. But you don't necessarily need to worry about that because that's the
the packet manager's problem, or developer's problem.
Yeah, you are presented with an easier interface
for what you want to achieve.
And when it becomes dependencies,
it's also like libraries and packages.
If you are building something, let's
say if you were to build a table,
you need nails and bolts.
So these nails and bolts are sort of like dependencies.
So the table could not be made without those things.
And then these nails, they are specific length, type,
and gurge, you know, not all nails will fit all joints.
So there are, when it comes to dependencies,
it's about other things that you need to,
for your code to work.
And also there are some specifications
that we will go on later on.
And then we talk about this sci-fi,
scientific Python ecosystem.
This is maybe the ecosystem most of the research community,
they get, they would think that they start using Python, you know, when they start using this.
So we have this NumPy, SciPi, Matplotlib, Pandas for data structures, you know, Pandas could,
when people work, researchers work with data, it could do wonders, they get, you know, really amazed
how Pandas could help them, you know, they could scrape web pages for tables, they could create
data frames and then you have the NumPy with all the optimized array functions and all the
mathematical functions there. So this is kind of the ecosystem that people start actually
interacting, not all people, but researchers that we interact with. And yes, [Name]?
Yeah, and I'll just mention quickly that also this ecosystem is highly influential to other
packages. Yesterday, there was questions in the chat, for example, about [?] or[?], which
are built upon pandas, but do pandas more efficiently or more in parallel or something like
that? But they usually build upon the syntax and the ideas behind these packages. So there are
lots of packages that do the same thing again, but they try to reuse as much of the language that
NumPy and Pandas and Matplotlib. They do similar kinds of things, but they might do it a bit
differently or better or something like that, or efficiently or in parallel. But they usually
reuse the language. They reuse the same kinds of concepts. So if you learn these core concepts
around the NumPy ecosystem, you can then transfer them to other things or in other ecosystems
or in other tools that use this?
Yes. So in addition, there are other packages like scikit-learn.
This is not like an exhaustive list here.
So this is a part of it.
So if you're doing some classification machine learning,
even scikit-learn is using these packages.
And if you extend things like PyTorch has an optimized version of NumPy
by manipulations for machine learning related operations.
And the rest is really similar.
This is for people to read about the packages.
So I would not spend time on reading through this
because I think the next lesson of dependency
we can talk a little bit more.
Only thing before I give it to you, I want to mention
is this connected to Python to other languages,
because we'll talk about Conda, for example, next.
So connected to other languages, the library
that we were talking about, NumPy, is a good example.
So there are certain things Python, they could do it,
but there are other programming languages like C
could do it better.
For initially, when the code you write,
it could write on your laptop, run on laptop.
But if you want to go to a high-performance computer
system, or a bigger server, or to achieve bigger things,
you have to use the resources optimally,
and also to understand the underlying hardware.
For example, how wide is your processor's registry width,
for example.
That kind of things we don't worry about when
you do Python programming.
So Python provides these libraries.
Behind the scenes, they use C or Fortran or other languages.
For example, [Name] slightly mentioned
that you have this one data, one program that you want
to introduce different data sets.
So we call this the SIMD, single instruction multiple data
kind of work.
So those are better done in other languages than Python.
But you don't have to learn all those things.
You only need to learn how to call those.
So if you want to do some vectorization, for example,
if you have a loop that goes through 10 things,
you could do Python loop.
But if the loop is going through 100,000 things,
you don't want to go through the 100,000 steps one by one.
You want to go 100 steps at a time or 1,000 steps at a time.
So those kind of things we call loop vectorization
could be handled by this code, but you could still use them inside your Python environment.
Is there anything else that you want to mention here before I give it to you?
Yeah, I'll quickly mention this last chapter about evaluating Python packages.
So how do you know what is good? If you go to GitHub, there's like a million packages.
And there is no single way of determining what is good or something is bad. What I usually do
is like, let's say our user wants to solve a certain problem and they wonder if they should
re-implement an algorithm or if there already exists an algorithm that does it. I try to find
with the corresponding keywords, like a git repository or something in GitHub that would
provide such a package. And then I look for various factors, like is there a community around
this package? Has it been validated scientifically? Is there papers published from the package?
Are there lots of stars? When was the last commit? These sort of things. You need to usually check
what is the community around it? Is it a trustworthy source? Is it some random guy
somewhere? Can I actually myself validate it? Of course, I cannot validate, let's say, NumPy. I
I don't have time to read the whole source code,
but if it's like one page long,
maybe I can see what it does.
And these sort of things, there's various factors.
And here's some questions that you can ask yourself
when you're trying to validate.
And I would say that it's always a good idea
to first look if somebody else has done it
and maybe check if you can extend upon it.
Like, for example, many frameworks,
like, for example, Scikit-learn,
they provide a very comprehensive way
of extending their own things so that you can,
like if you write the way they write,
they're like models and that sort of thing,
you can reuse all of the other tools that they provide.
And then you don't have to like figure out
how to do like a cross-validation
or something like that yourself,
because you can use the algorithm
that they use for cross-validation
for your model or something like that.
So it's usually a good idea to check
what the packages provide, how to extend.
Usually there's like a development document somewhere
where they say that, okay, how to extend these packets.
And then they provide like guide
on how to write my own stuff
on top of already existing library.
And it's usually not that hard.
It's usually much harder to start something from scratch.
And of course, sometimes it's needed,
but a lot of times you can build upon
what other people have done.
Yes, so I will only comment about the security part
because you mentioned the list,
there could be malicious packages as well.
So there is trust, so research is based on trust actually.
So when you use a library,
especially if the library concerns like web security,
for example, you can't just use a,
just because it's doing the thing what you do,
you need to have a proper understanding
of what it actually do.
And also there could be malicious libraries,
misspelled malicious libraries.
you have NumPy and you like NumDy or something,
just to elude you.
So you have to be a little cautious as well.
Then I think we should go to the next lesson
about how we manage dependencies.
Yeah, yeah, let's jump to that.
So I'll take the screen share.
If [Name] can then switch to mine.