Yeah, I agree that is very likely the case. Yep.
Switched back here.
So, what's the summary of today? So, this course, the started alph on days one and two,
which is just about using Python. And that works in JupyterLab in the cloud wherever.
But as we're going on we're moving further and further towards how Python interacts with the
operating system itself. So basically we're seeing how you would break out of the Jupyter notebooks
and be able to run these other, like run things on your computer, run it without Jupyter, run it
more times, be able to share your code, things like this. And these are the kind of things which
are needed to go to the next level. So someone, like there is plenty of work that can be done
only within the Jupyter web interface, but many of you probably need to at least know of these
concepts of how to go out, even if it's someone else you're working with that's managing these
kinds of things. So there's feedback which is coming here. Please answer. I see right now
there's 86 people who are still on the stream and this is not many answers. So please vote
for what you think.
Okay. So the news for tomorrow. So there's one lesson tomorrow which uses the command line
and it's actually about packaging. So it's basically how you can make
a package which can itself go on the pip or conda repositories and then other people can use it.
But it doesn't have to go that far. I oftentimes make things into packages but I install it
directly from github because the use isn't really that much and I'm just using it internally myself.
So, the topics are more advanced, but also you can do things, there's the first lesson
can be done only through JupyterLab and the third one.
So these have good exercises which other people can do also.
Also at the end, we have a panel discussion where you can basically ask all of us instructors
anything you may want, like, what do you recommend for this case or that case, and so on.
And in fact, you can ask some good questions and, you know, try to get us debating each
other about what's the right answer.
Or maybe there is no clear right answer.
Yes, sometimes programs are a bit like lawyers.
It depends.
Yeah, and often like I think it happens
quite often in the Python ecosystem that it's basically like
Once you start your studies and you start your bachelor's and that sort of thing,
you have your friends in the same courses and you're all working on the same courses
and you do the same things because those are the basics. And basically the NumPy and Pandas and
those sort of things, Matplotlib, they are the basics when it comes to scientific computing
with Python. Those are where everybody goes. But then it quite quickly diverges into different
fields. Different fields have different needs and different tools they use. Neuroimaging,
they need to do 3D plotting of MRI slices or something like that. If you do deep learning,
you do completely different tools. Of course, the ecosystem is still the same and everybody's
working the same kind of things, but the problems become more specialized and specific for the field.
And that makes it, of course, hard to give a general answer, what is good.
But what we can hopefully provide is some semblance of like, there are these kinds of tools that go across all of these different fields.
They are tools that are like ecosystem tools and these kinds of things that help you or processes, like packaging in a certain way,
or that help you maybe even if you're working in a very specific field. But of course like every
field has their own special cases that might be complicated or certain kinds of like plotting
or certain kind of thing and you need to like yeah it's a different like specific question
at that field, of course. Yeah, there's some good comments here about today being advanced
and getting stuck. And yeah, I mean, this is unfortunately something that happens sometimes.
We have such a broad audience here, we tried to do something that's a little bit interesting
for advanced people, and for people who get stuck, you can still watch it and take it
as a demo, and then learn more yourself later.
I think that's the only way to manage such a wide audience.
Yeah, and there are different ways of working in different systems. So, for example, many of
the things might be that we go to a terminal and in Windows you don't usually work with a terminal
that often. You don't necessarily use that much of it. The working environment might be different.
But in Windows, let's say you use VS Code or something, you might have or PyCharm or something,
and they can replicate. With an IDE, you can get an even better working environment than with a
terminal, in many cases, like you would do maybe in a Linux system. So there are different ways of
working. So there's no right answer. It is only answer that you want to choose from.
So if you encounter problems with, let's say, environment creation or some of the
command line things or scripting or these kind of things, like PyCharm and VSCode,
you can give arguments to run. When you run, press the green button to run a code,
you can give it arguments to run like it would run as a script. So you can basically demo
how it would behave as a script, even when you're not using terminal. And this is quite common
in the IDE world. So there's different ways of working with the same things. But of course,
when we present it, we present it with the way that we most commonly see in our users,
which is using the command lines or scripts and that sort of thing. But the same things can apply
to different workflows as well. Yeah, so we're over time. If there's no more comments from
anyone, maybe I'd wrap up with this one comment at the bottom. I like this course. It gives a good
overview of good coding practices, but the course requires weeks of hands-on practice to learn.
And I'd say that's absolutely true. And for a 12-hour course, I think any one of the lessons
we teach could easily become a 12-hour course just on their own. And our goal here is to show
you what's possible and give you a little bit of hands-on practice of what's there,
but to inspire you to go learn these later on. And you can learn them by
doing yourself reading more, or probably more likely working with other people that do things
and finding it together. If you're at any of the universities that have partners, you can try
asking the people that are advertising the course and see if they can provide support in these
things. At Aalto University we do plenty of this and I know the people in Sweden and Norway are
very happy to help you with these kinds of things. So with that being said, should we
Should we wrap up?
I think so.
Okay, great. Thank you so much.
See you tomorrow, same time.
Yes, thank you. Bye.