I'm working on it, something.
Yeah.
No worries.
So, the question here is, like, we've talked about library ecosystem, and libraries are
all fine and dandy, but quite often you have a case where you want to install certain libraries
for your code.
Like, you want certain kind of a situation, and the ecosystem is so big, like the whole
Python ecosystem, there's probably hundreds of thousands of packages available for different
Python versions and different kinds of different installations, different dependencies and
different things.
And they are not compatible all at the same time.
You cannot install Python, I mean, the whole Python.
It's impossible.
There's so many packages.
You cannot have everything in one installation.
So that brings to mind that, okay, how do you manage installing multiple things at the
same time for different projects?
How do you manage that you get the correct dependencies for certain projects?
And there are two major players in this thing, and they are the Python Packaging Index and
Anaconda.
So they are the major things.
So here's a big list of what is the difference between Python Packaging Index and Anaconda.
I can try to say it in short form.
So Python Packaging Index is this community-like project that basically provides Python packages
as these so-called wheels, like wheels of cheese, because everything in Python is a
multi-python joke, but it provides packages as these, like you have Python package as
one file that you can download from this Python packaging index. These are often used in conjunction
with these virtual environments. They don't have to be installed into virtual environments,
but they're quite often used so that you can have your own small Python world where you
install only the packages you need from the Python pip package. And this is very good.
And it was originally developed for sharing Python code. So, Python code written in Python.
But like we talked already, much of the Python code is not written in Python. There's underlying
layers that are written in C. There might be dependencies. So, for example, NumPy uses these
plus linear algebra libraries to run the matrix operations and that sort of stuff.
So it uses underlying libraries that are not part of Python.
They are not written in Python, they're written in Fortran and C.
Providing these is a bit of a complicated thing for the
for the PyPI packaging index.
So what they do is that they basically
put everything into these wheels,
and then they provide everything with you,
which can result in very big installations quite often.
And it's a bit complicated there.
How do you share non-Python code?
There is a lot of packages that provide that,
but it's a bit complicated.
Writing these packages is pretty simple.
Like you can easily write your own bit packages.
We'll talk about it tomorrow.
There will be a session on packaging your code.
So writing these is pretty simple.
Like how do you write them?
And then you can publish them
in the packaging index yourself.
And if you're writing Python code
that depends on other Python code.
So for example, you write your own thing
that depends on other Python things
or other libraries like NumPy and that sort of thing.
it's very easy to share it in Python Packaging Index
and use pip to install it.
So pip is the installer tool
for Python Packaging Index packages.
The other major player is conda.
And conda is basically like a solution to the question of,
okay, like we have so many of these different dependencies
or different packages and they might not work together.
So how do we like, how do we make certain
that we get like a consistent working environment.
And the Anaconda Incorporated,
which used to be Continuum Analytics,
now it's Anaconda Incorporated,
they developed this tool called Konda,
which basically is a packaging installer.
And then they provide it in this Anaconda installation.
So they provide like a wide bunch of already existing tools
in one installation, which is this Anaconda installation.
Many of you probably already use it,
which contains, like, it was basically designed
for data science people or people in banks
or something like that.
Like, you get one installation that contains
a lot of already good stuff,
but it has moved beyond that.
Like, the project has moved beyond that
because the community thought that,
okay, like, we want more packages there.
We want more packages.
We want more things.
like we don't want to be all dependent on the Anaconda Incorporated. So what happened is that
Anaconda also provides their own Anaconda.org, which is this packaging index for Conda packages.
And you can have your own channels there where you can provide your own packages.
And some of these channels are now bigger, like the CondaForge, which is this open source channel,
is a lot bigger than the channels provided by the Anaconda Incorporated.
But basically, it's a different world. And what Conda does is that it can manage all of these
low-level dependencies as well. So it can install you compilers and tools and different kinds of
linear algebra libraries. And especially when it comes to CUDA, like GPU programming,
it can install you the correct CUDA toolkits, which are these GPU libraries that your code needs.
So it can try to manage this dependency thing. But of course, it's very complicated because
there's a huge bunch of these libraries and different combinations.
Is it correct to say that the Python package index, PPI index, the things you install in Python
with PIP is more or less Python packages and Python APIs.
You know, Python packages and other C and Fortran
and other code that's called from Python.
But we need to come to Conda.
In addition to that,
you can also rely on system level libraries
and also additional tools.
For example, the bioinformatics,
there are tools like SAM tools.
So if you want to analyze something,
Conda will also get these tools
which are not Python interfaces,
but all tools on their own.
In addition to that, in PIP, when you install this,
they also distribute the source code.
For example, a unique system.
For Windows and Mac, mostly you have the binaries.
In the PIP, if the source code is there,
and if you are Ubuntu computer, for example,
when you download it, the PIP expects that your computer,
your system to have the compiler.
But Conta could also bring down the compiler
and set up everything.
But mostly, maybe all the time,
Conda is pre-compiled binaries.
You know, they're compiled, so they're ready to be used.
Yes, yes.
And of course you can combine these.
So you can install Pip packages in Conda.
Like Conda creates its own environments,
which are similar to the virtual environments
I've already mentioned, but they're managed by Conda.
So there's, to the whole ecosystem,
I'll quickly mention this over here.
There's this kind of like glossary of different terms.
So when we talk about Anaconda and Conda,
like you can get headache from just hearing
about all of these different terms
because there's so many of them.
So I'll try to quickly like go through
the whole Conda thing.
Like what are the different partners
basically in the ecosystem?
So there's the Anaconda cloud.
So this is the place where people store the packages.
Then there's CondaForge, which is the largest open source
community channel.
And Anaconda Cloud also contains like packages
by the Anaconda Incorporated,
which are in so-called defaults channel
or base channel and R channel and those kinds of channels.
But they are incompatible usually with CondaForge
because CondaForge is basically like a completely
different world in the same ecosystem.
So Anaconda Cloud contains like two worlds.
There's this like open source world with CondaForge
And then there's the default world,
which is like curated by the company, Anaconda Incorporated.
You can use both, but usually you don't want to mix
and match them because you can get problems.
Then there's the package managers.
So peep is the package manager for Python packaging index.
So if you install from PyPI,
you install it with pip usually.
But then there's conda,
which is like the package manager for conda environments
and Anaconda stuff and that sort of things.
And there's a newer version that we usually recommend
to our customers called Mamba,
which is like a open source,
like Konda is open source project as well,
but there's a C++ implementation of this.
So because like, again, like Conda is written in Python,
so it's slow.
So when you create this huge environment,
sometimes it can take like minutes to figure out
how do I match these different packages
into the same environment?
And that's why people usually use this Mamba,
which can do it much faster, this solving.
So inside it, it's a mess,
but there's like a SAT solver inside the conda.
It tries to figure out the correct packages
that you need in the environment,
because it wants like a working consistent environment.
Maybe we will just like,
it will just install stuff into the environment.
Then there's like the package manager deployments.
So basically you can get already existing
like a good set of packages if you install the Anaconda.
So the Anaconda is like a distribution of lots of packages
by Anaconda Incorporated.
And it's free for academic and non-commercial use,
but for companies it's face money,
like the license is not covered,
it doesn't cover companies.
Then there's Miniconda, which is basically,
it's provided by Anaconda Incorporated
and it uses default channel by default,
like the Anaconda packages,
it comes, by default it tries to install them from there
and it's like, it only contains the conda installer.
So you can use that as like a starting point
if you want to like create your own environments
or something, you don't have to install
the whole Anaconda installation.
Then there's also this mini-forge,
which is like a conda-forge version of the whole thing,
where it basically, it uses the conda-forge by default.
So it's an open source version of miniconda basically.
And it has Mamba as well installed.
So these are some of the words you might hear
when you look at webpages and look at installations.
So you need to basically choose what you want to use.
Usually when people are using, let's say Windows,
the Anaconda Navigator is so good
that like using that is a good idea.
And you can manage packages with that as well.
Like you don't have to use these command line tools
or anything, you can use the Anaconda Navigator
to manage your package installations.
If you're using Linux,
you often either maybe get the Anaconda installation
and just use that and maybe create your own environments
that doesn't have the packages you need,
or you just take like, let's say MiniForge
and then you use that to create your environments.
But that's like a more like command line,
let's do it like ourselves kind of a way.
So there's different ways of installing the packages.
Yeah, it's correct to say that regardless
of you have installed Anaconda or Miniconda
or some packages to get Conda,
you can use any of the other package managers,
you know, conda to install packets from any source. For example, you know, anaconda and
miniconda both could be used to install the same source, but miniconda is lightweight.
But when you, wouldn't you recommend that when you distribute the code that need conda,
that you'd recommend miniconda to be the requirements. And then you provide the package list other
than rather than asking the user to install anaconda and use your package.
Yes, usually it's a good idea to provide the minimal example.
So usually if you go to a web page and you see like,
okay, pip install this, if you have a library or something.
What they mean is that this is the minimum needed for the installation,
but usually you can have it installed in various other ways.
You might install it via conda packets or something.
or what they really are saying that, okay, like, create your own environment and then run this bp
install command. Because like, if you just run the bp install command, you usually install to whatever
environment you currently have. And that's not a good idea. So usually, it's a good idea to choose.
Yeah. For the sake of time, shall we show this best practice you are talking about?
Yes. What is this environment and why do we have to isolate?
So, when we're talking about environments, usually when you start, for example, if you
now have started JupyterLab, you might have started it in the base environment of your
Anaconda installation, or maybe you have installed the environment that we have provided in the
webpage.
But the environment, what we mean is that wherever your Python interpreter basically
is like what is your Python interpreter that you're running? That determines like Python,
based on where it is, it will try to find packages near that. Basically, it goes one
folder up and then one folder down and tries to find packages that are present in the system.
If the Python is the system Python, it will try to find it from the system libraries.
And if it's installed into a completely different place, it will try to find packages from there.
So what this environment means is that we create a folder, basically, we get some Python there,
and then we install packages relative to that Python. And then they are installed into this
own world where they won't interact with others, and we don't have it loaded all the time,
but we can load it per case. If we need to do one kind of a thing with certain packages,
we can activate this environment. So we basically go into this world of this Python and then we run
whatever we want there. And if we are doing a different project, we can activate a different
environment. And this is a good idea because it makes it possible to reproduce your code much
more and you run into less problems. Because as we mentioned previously, there's so many packages.
you cannot get them all working at the same time. So it's better to just have a small world
where there's not that many problems that has only the things you need, basically.
And that's in the environment. I always start with a new environment whenever there's a problem with
Python. You start from scratch and you start building up the environment that you need.
need. And you can create an environment by running some commands yourself. But nowadays,
and that is often recommended somewhere, but that is like we will, you will find in the
exercise, exercise two, you can run it after the course and run the environment yourself.
But we don't recommend that way of installing packages in general. So let's jump straight
to the correct solution basically, or the better solution.
So what you're saying is that, let's say if I want NumPy 1.24 and NumPy 1.23, both versions
of NumPy in my same system, rather than just installing pip install NumPy, that there's
a better way to do this, which will help me to reproduce this later?
Yes.
And this is by recording the dependencies into this environment file, because the problem
with, like, if you, for example, with that, of course, you can, like, install NumPy some
version. And then you realize, okay, my other code needs another version. So, you can basically
install the other version. But now you lost the other one. So, basically, either you need
to constantly reinstall stuff. And maybe when you do a reinstall, suddenly some dependency
of that package gets reinstalled. And suddenly you're in this mess where, like, the route
took to get to the current state of the environment is depending on what commands you run in what
order. And then you cannot reproduce it. You cannot anymore. You don't know how you got there.
So it's usually better to just create a world where everything is correct at the correct time.
And how you do that is that you record the dependencies into either the requirements.txt
or environment.yaml. Does it matter what you call this, [Name]?
Does it matter what you call these files? Yes. You can, of course, record them. You can
name them anything you want. But the thing is that if other people are trying to find them,
find, they will look at these files and they think that, okay, these are the files.
And these are the ones that the tools will, by default, try to search for.
If you try to install via people, for example, it will try to find the requirements.txt.
But these are basically like the conventions, so you should abide by the conventions.
Of course, if you don't, then let the users know or the other people know that, okay,
requirements are in foobar.txt or something, but that's not a good thing.
If I visit the GitHub page or GitLab page, if the requirement.txt is there,
I know what it is. So it's better that you follow this.
Yes, yes, exactly. So you can always look at these. And what the requirements.txt,
so the requirements.txt is meant for pip installations. And what it contains is just
a list of packages. Usually it can have, we'll talk about versioning a bit later,
but it's usually just a list of packages, a text file. And when you tell a peep to install
an environment, it will just install these packages. Condor environments are a bit more
complicated. Not in a bad way, but they have more information in them. And they're usually
called these environment.yml. There's a typo. It's environment.yml, not environments.yml
usually. So, and they contain like the name of the environment, usually, what environment you want
to use. And then where do you want the packages to come from? I talked about defaults and CondaForge,
the channels. So you usually define like, okay, I want the packages for in this case, for example,
to come from defaults channel. So the Anaconda incorporated packages. And then you have a list
of dependencies that are the packages. And you can usually convert, like you can notice from
syntax that you can easily convert PIP packages, PIP requirements txt to environment.yml and
other way around. If you just take these and put them into requirements.txt, you can get
basically a PIP installation. And the other way around, if you take these, you can convert them
quite easily. So which version of NumPy would this install?
So in this case, because we haven't specified any versions, like the both tools, they try
to get the newest one.
Like if there's some other packets that of course creates like a requirement that, okay,
I need a lower version, then you might get that lower version.
But the point is here is that you let the tools do its job.
That like, if you don't know what version you need, if you don't have a specific need
for a version, it's usually a good idea to let the tool decide what versions to get.
Because if you don't have any specific requirement, it's a good idea to let the solvers figure
out what is compatible and what is needed.
Because you mentioned that it is easily interchangeable, so I want to mention one thing.
So if you have some packages, depending on the channel you select, there might be different
versions.
pip, it's always the latest version, you know, it might pick up. But depending on the channels you
specify, maybe some different versions can be installed. So you also need to, that's why it's
important that you specify the channel in your environmental file, rather than depending on what
defaults you have. Yes. And also in Conda environment, you can also, let's say, specify
the Python version you want to use, and that sort of, you can get more complicated with those.
But so why is this important to have the requirements file? Because it makes it
possible to recreate the environment quickly. So you can recreate the whole thing. You can
remove it and you can recreate it and you should get basically the same kind of situation.
Of course, in some cases you want to lock down some versions. So if you need to
to reproduce it. Let's say you run something for your paper and you want the collaborators
or reviewers or whoever, you want them to be able to reproduce the thing. So then you
might want to lock down the versions or pin the versions that you are currently using
because you know that those work. And in that case, you can give these versioning numbers.
So there's various logic you can give, like larger than, smaller than, that kind of stuff.
You can give all kinds of, but you can basically lock down certain versions of packages.
So let's say you want these exact versions of numpy, matplotlib, pandas, and scipy.
And same with the conda and with the added Python 3.10 here, so that you want it with
a certain Python version.
So as a best practice, wouldn't you recommend instead of having these exact versions, you
would say that something bigger than this version, but less than this, give us some
range being very specific?
Yes.
The versioning, how it goes usually in these packages, if the people abide by it, is so-called
semantic versioning.
So the first version is usually the major release.
So between two major releases, nothing usually works.
the number goes from one to two, the first number, it basically means that it's no longer compatible
and you should do major changes to it. In the minor version, the second number there,
it basically means that they can introduce new features and they can deprecate old features,
but they usually give a few versions of leeway where you see these deprecation warnings and
and that sort of things. These will go away in the next version or something like that.
So, usually, the second version will basically mean that, okay, we are doing some changes between
the versions, and some things might not work anymore. But usually, the main things are the
same. And the third version is basically a patch version. So, that shouldn't ever affect.
Like, if they have done their job correctly, it should never affect your code. It's like fixes
for bugs and that sort of thing. But that means that you can usually give quite a bit of a leeway.
You can say that it needs to be higher than version one, but less than version two or something. It
needs to be version one, but that's all. Or version something, some range of versions.
So all the advice you gave, we also need to take care when we distribute packages to stick to
those rules, because people expect that. Yes. And it's usually a good idea not to pin yourself
too hard to the packages, especially if you're developing something. Because if you're pinning
yourself to a certain version, you're basically locked in time. You're at that time moment.
And then the world will move onwards, but you are stuck in that time when you created an environment
and when you pinned the versions. And in two years, in three years, in four years,
Yes, most likely nobody else can recreate that environment anymore.
And that's a bad thing.
So your code will be stuck in that time.
So it's usually not a good idea to do that too often.
Yeah.
Sometimes we go on sort of bypassing these practices and say, if I have created an environment,
is it possible to create this file from an existing environment that I can give to other
people?
Yes.
In this exercise, there's an example how you can freeze an environment, so you can use this
conda env export. There's also an additional flag here that you can put
dashdash from history, if you want to freeze it based on the commands that you have run previously.
And you can also run this pip freeze. But what I usually recommend, if you don't
know how you created your environment. I personally start from completely blank slate
and then I run the code until I no longer get import errors. Because if you really don't know
what the environment has eaten, it's very hard to reproduce it. But you can freeze it
if you want to have an environment for posterity or publication or something like that.
Should we just show one example while learners could also follow or what do you recommend?
Let's do an example. So this will, of course, be dependent on what system you're running.
So like in my case, I'm running Linux, so I can use the terminal, for example, in JupyterLab
if I start, well, I can start a new one, let's say here.
I'll, oops, I'll start a new terminal.
If you're running in, let's say, Anaconda Navigator,
you can basically, like, point it to the environment file
and you can let it work on that.
But you can have various different user interfaces.
But because I'm using command line,
I'll create the environment in this way.
So let's say I have an environment YAML.
So in this case, it's basically the one over here
with the NumPy and Matplotlib and whatever.
So I'll run the exercise 4.
You can probably run it yourself, but because, yeah.
Or you can run it yourself, and I recommend trying it.
But because there's differences in environments,
it might be complicated if you get it working,
but do try if you feel like it.
So what I'm going to do,
I'm going to create this environment
using this `conda env create`,
and then I'm going to point it to the environment.yml
that I have.
Can you show us that file,
how it looks like in your-
Yes, yes.
So the environment, it's just a .yml file.
So yaml syntax.
So it has this list of packages over here.
Or following, it's the teaching material.
Oh, yeah.
It's a same as.
Yeah.
I've already have it, so I'm going to remove it.
So you can remove the environments with this command.
with this command and why it's also very important to do this environment.
I usually remove all of my environments every two months or something, and the reason behind
is that I'm secure in the knowledge that I can recreate it from the environment files
that I have.
I don't fear losing my system that I have set up is so fragile that I'm worried that
I mess it up, and now I cannot recreate it anymore. And that's a terrible fear to have
as a programmer, that you cannot recreate the environment you already have. And that's why
it's very important to create the environment file, because then you can let go of that fear.
You don't have to worry about that anymore. So typing, installing one by one would be easier.
That is the easy way out. But the robust way is that what you're doing. Slightly more work,
but you will thank your past self at some point. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yeah. And if you want to like,
let's say you want to recreate, like you want to add a new package there. What I usually do is
that if I run, let's say the install command in the environment myself, or in the documentation,
there's also this, you can update the environment based on an updated environment YAML. You can
and instant new packets there,
but they always record it into the environment anyway.
Because like eventually you mess up the environment anyway.
Like everybody does that.
Like everybody does a wrong installation or something
and then it's broken the environment.
And this is unfortunately the side effect
of having so many different choices of libraries.
But at the same time, you can fix it
by having a consistent way of recreating where you are.
are. And that is either the environment.yml or the requirements.txt. Of course, the requirements.txt,
it works very well if you're only using Python packages and stuff in the pip world.
But if you're using GPUs, if you're using more complex things, I recommend checking the conda
because it makes it possible to install much more complex environments where everything
works together. So it is thinking now, the Konda is thinking and it's solving the environment. You
see this timer going on. So when you work on a system and when you create environments like
this in the requirement file, the waiting time is also less rather than you add more and more
to an existing environment. Because conda needs to figure out all the matching files. And the
other thing is when you work on a system for a long time, it might create a big cache,
the packages you don't want will get accumulated. So in addition to being reproducible, there are
so many other benefits by following the procedure that you are doing now.
Yes. And I'll also mention that if you want to share the environment or reproduce it in
another system. Usually, the environments are not easy to transfer. There are tools to do this,
but it's very finicky. Usually, it's better to just move the environment.yml to a different
place and recreate the environments there. It's just one text file, and it's very easy to copy
that and then recreate it in another place. Because the environments, if you're doing
work with like deep learning or something. The environments can get to like, I don't know,
like four gigabytes. You don't want to like move four gigabytes when you can move a text file.
That's not usually a good idea. So moving around things on different systems,
it would create issues as well because these are pre-compiled binaries. If you want to move
something from Windows to a Unix computer, almost it will never work. But if you can move this
environmental file and recreate it according to their system, according to your target system.
And also you could easily version control this environment file because it's text file,
you could have Git and other ways of version control. You can have multiple snapshots.
So yeah, that's an important thing. And I should mention that in the Python packaging index,
and also in the conduct channels, there's huge amounts of variety based on what operating system
you're running. So for example, some packages, usually the packages are built for Mac OS X,
they're built for Windows, they're built for Linux, different variants of Linux,
different dependencies, and you can have a huge amount of different combinations of the same
package. The same package, but it's built in different ways based on where it's going to be
installed. These tools make it possible to install it. Of course, this is a bit of a demo
effect, but the environment solving takes a long time. This is why the Mamba is so popular.
If we have time, I can show you how long it takes with Mamba, but I'm pretty certain it
doesn't take this long. But this can also happen in Anaconda Navigator, for example. It's pretty
annoying sometimes that it doesn't produce output that often. Like what's it doing?
Like it's trying to solve the environment and yeah, it takes a while and it doesn't
necessarily produce output so you can think that it's crashed. But yeah, sometimes the
solving just takes a long time. Let's see if there's any good questions in the chat.
Yeah. So I will also try on my terminal. Let's see. Yes. The one reason could be that you
have a lot of, we could, there are ways to clear conda cache, for example, to check less
things and also your base environment where this JupyterLab is installed. It might have
a certain libraries already installed. So what conda trying to do is it's trying to
sort of not to redo things and maybe reuse things and also be compatible.
Yeah, and also maybe it's because of the share and that sort of thing.
There's other things running on my laptop at this point.
Yeah, let's see. Are there any good questions? So where should it be stored? So usually a
good idea to, if you're using version control or something, you should usually store the
environments and requirements with the code, so that it's easy to reproduce.
There's a good question there, honda-update-or, this is a good thing to
mention, that updating already existing environments can sometimes be really
complicated, like it's, well, for pip it's less complicated because pip usually
It just downloads stuff and it doesn't care necessarily.
It just will install them.
It doesn't look...
It just goes YOLO and it just installs packages, which is good in many cases, but it sometimes
gets you environments that don't work anymore.
What Conda does is the complete opposite.
So it tries to make certain that everything works.
And if you have like, basically, if you have, let's say, if you have ever been to like a
tour or something, like a tourist tour or something, and there's one person who walks
slowly, then the whole group needs to walk slowly.
And that's basically what can happen with the conda packages, is that there's one package
that is basically like, I don't want to update, like I don't like updating, I don't want
to like be updated.
And then it can hold the whole environment back.
And it can create this kind of a situation where, like, the content goes on a tangent
and it tries to, like, create an environment which doesn't want to update anymore.
So for all of these situations, usually the solution is to just create a new environment.
For fun's sake, I created a new environment here. Let's try with Mamba. I'm running it
now from my terminal, and it's the same command, exact same command, but this time I'm running it
with Mamba. Mamba is much faster, so I'm pretty certain that this will finish before this
And it gives more output as well, it tells where it tries to find the packages and what does it download, like what packages and that sort of stuff.
Yeah.
So now it tells what we are looking for.
we are looking for, and soon it should probably give you the answer to what it's, yeah.
So now it's already doing the installation.
So this is why we usually recommend people to use Mamba when they create environments.
So it's already done when the conda is still wondering about, and this is why this is maybe
a good demo on why certain tools have been reinvented.
But the user interface is basically the same.
But maybe we should have, like, do we have anything for this session?
Do you want to show something more?
Yeah, maybe I'll quickly show how to activate the environment.
So, when we often, often in places, we recommend you don't necessarily run this conda init.
You can run it.
So if you see, let's say you have a terminal
and you see, let's say the space over here,
it means that your conda is active now
and the Python will always be found from that environment.
And then this can cause problems in many systems.
Like if you want to,
if you don't want to always have it active,
like if you have a program that tries to use Python,
but suddenly it wants to use the Python
from the activated conda, that can cause problems.
So, we usually recommend that people don't run this conda in it, but you can, of course,
run it.
And if you run it, you can use this conda activate to activate the environment.
And now you have an environment here.
But if you, yeah, usually we don't recommend you run it all the time, because then other
programs that want to use Python as well, they might find this wrong Python instead
of the Python that you want to use.
So here in this file that you activated, we didn't mention which version of Python we
need.
So, we can check what is the version of the Python, so we got 3.12, so in this environment
I didn't specify what Python to use, so yeah, I just got the newest Python in this case,
if I run which Python, this is like Linux specific command, but you can see that it shows Python from
my newly created environment. So in an environment, does it always include a Python as well?
Not necessarily. Even if you don't have it, mention it in your requirement file,
does it always include a Python? No, no. If there's nothing that requires Python,
it doesn't always contain Python. So usually when you create an environment, it might be sometimes
a good idea to add, let's say, pip and Python always there so that you always get pip and
Python into the environment. But sometimes, like most of the time, you install NumPy or something,
and then that has a dependency to Python. So it will bring Python with it. But it's always like
this kind of a question of who are the major players? What are the major packages that you
want to get. And those are the ones that bring everybody with them. So they're basically like
the Taylor Swift going into a restaurant. Other people come because Taylor Swift is at the
restaurant. And those are the stars of the environment. Let's say PyTorch or something.
PyTorch will bring its friends with it. But nobody's really caring about the friends. They
are caring about the PyTorch. And this is usually how you want to think about the environment. So
there's usually the major players that you want to, these are the major things that they want
the conda to focus on. So to sort of, sort of investigate that, what you said, you know,
there might be other packages that pandas needed. Is it possible for you to rephrase this
environment and show how that would look like, you know, after creating? Yes, let's, let's,
Let's run the conda-env-export.
And you notice here that I get this pretty horrible looking environment file, where suddenly
there's a huge bunch of stuff here.
And this is basically the exact versions I got.
And most of these are packages that come as dependencies to, let's say, NumPy.
But you don't want to give other people these as an installation instruction, unless they
want the exact same environment.
But usually you don't want it.
You want to give them the actual instructions that you need.
The one you use.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So, in fact, this will break in most systems because if you see the hash, like the third,
like you have two equal signs, the third hash actually is very unique to the system you
are in now.
So, there's very likely that it will break on a different system.
Yes.
So, many of the things here are like, you can read it as you have a package, then you
have a package version, and then you have a specific build of that package.
For example, in this case, it's for Python 3.12. But yeah, it's very specific. And that's why you
usually want to give the broad outline of the environment instead of the exact requirements.
Of course, if you want to create the exact same cake that somebody else has created,
you can give the exact grams of what flour to get, exact brand of the flour, exact date of the flour
when it was made, like exact amount of the flour that is needed. But most of the time,
you want to give a generic recipe that says that, okay, just get me flour this amount.
So it's like similar, you don't want, you want to give a general recipe, you don't want to give,
and the conda is like the cook that can then manage this.
Yeah. Then also the file you used, the environment file, you should also give the
the others to build upon your package. For example, if they
need a, let's say, PyTorch in their program, in addition to
what you install, it's easier for them to add PyTorch instead
of editing this file. So this is sort of overwhelming. And this
is not something you want to show. And it's also very
simple.
Should we now go to a break before?
We have two minutes. I think one minute you can have a look at
questions? Yeah, let's look at the questions quickly and then go to a break.
So let's see. If you have any more questions, please go and ask them. I will try to answer
them. Do you want me to share the questions? Yes, maybe. Yeah, that would be great. Okay, here we go.
You can only see on the stream how this goes.
I can see the questions on the stream.
There's some questions about things like, how do you make the stuff in the environment
file?
Do you have to do it manually?
I think you might have answered that.
It usually is a good idea to write it yourself.
Where do you store the environment file?
Yeah.
So I think we have some Mamba installation instructions somewhere as well.
So we had to find that and place it.
So under question 44, we'll place it
as soon as I find the link for the mobile installation.
Yes.
So about the question, I often think of environments
like if you go camping or if you go to a hotel,
like you go on a trip, you always
pack the usual suspects.
like you pack your toothbrush and you pack your shampoo and whatever,
like this kind of stuff.
And that's basically what most of the environments are.
You always get numpies and matplotlibs and scipies and python and beef.
And like most of the stuff is like, it rolls off your tongue.
Like you know that, okay, I will need these anyway.
Like I always want these stuff.
And then there's all like, usually like maybe two, three packages that are the
actual like meat of the whole thing and they are the special like let's say you need a certain
kind of like clothing when you go to a like a trip you need clothing for warm weather or
something like that and that's the actual thing there. Yes although it's very interesting our
discussion [Name] that we have to stop now. On question number 46 I'll slightly mention something
about it especially we see this if it says access denied when you try to install especially on
shared HPC systems for example it's always like that you are not allowed to modify the central
environment and actually you should not do that try to do that you can use with dash as user
as mentioned answer but you should go for this environment what [name] was promoting so create
isolated silos where you can add things and have different versions and also delete them
if they don't want. So don't try to install it centrally.
Yes. So if you install like Anaconda Navigator or something, usually like in that example,
you install it into program files and you install it as root or something like that.
And you don't have maybe right access to that folder. And that's a good thing because then
you cannot mess up the installation. But what you want to do is create a separate realm,
separate world, virtual environment, or conda environment, where you then install the stuff.
Because if you run, for example, the pip install, it will install into folders where
they will always be present. So if some other environment uses the same Python version,
it will find the same packages, and then all hell breaks loose, and suddenly nothing works anymore.
So, you want to keep the packages that you want in the environment, you want to keep
it in a separate silo, like [Name] said, a separate world, and you want to first create
the world for it, like the environment.
You want to create the world, and you want the packages to that world.
And [Name] will take the rest of the questions and the community, and thank you very much
Thank you so much for your this great introduction. I think it will be very useful for most of us. [Name], can you please take on.
Yes. So, yeah, I guess, um, we will have a break until 23 past hour.
So, see you then.
you