In general. Okay, so what's our first lesson of today?
The first lesson of today will be scripts, so going from the
Jupyter Notebooks more into a command line area, and kind of
the very, very first step to make code really reusable without
modifying the code itself.
And that's related to this first icebreaker or second icebreaker
question here.
How do you run the same thing over and over, but with slightly
different parameters, like the same code with different data.
So should I share my screen and we
can get straight to the lesson?
Yep.
Sounds like a plan.
I will push a button here.
And it transfers.
I adjust that.
OK, so as a reminder for the schedule
Coming to scripts here, I open this.
So what does the word script even mean?
To me, script means a kind of self-contained, very small
program that doesn't have a lot of interactions yet,
but that's just some very small thing.
It can call additional libraries, but in itself,
it doesn't provide a lot of code.
That's what I think of when I'm talking about a script.
When it gets more complex, I would rather
talk about a program.
So is this lesson really about scripts or programs or?
I think both.
Yeah.
I guess how it's about the transition
from different systems of using code.
Yes.
And exactly.
So the point is, this lesson, so far we've
been showing things in Jupyter.
So basically, you can click and run things
in whatever order you want.
So now that we have scripts here,
we'll be able to plug our code into other things
a little bit better.
Yeah, or at least we will be able to rerun our code
with different parameter sets without actually modifying
the code.
Because if you're modifying a Python script or the Jupyter
notebook by editing your initial conditions or the source
files or whatever.
You're always modifying the code.
Yeah.
OK.
So up here, there's the section on why scripts.
So if you had to convince the people listening here
that you should consider making a script or a program out
of your code.
Well, the main reason, I would say,
It very often comes down to, I have a certain pipeline
that I've developed for one example.
And now people want to use this pipeline
for multiple different data sets.
Of course, if I have that in a Jupyter Notebook,
I can, every time, change the Jupyter Notebook,
change the input variables, and run it for their data set.
But that needs me to do it again, and again, and again.
And I will likely do typos and whatnot in there.
So I'd rather have some kind of folder
where I have the data sets, and I
want to go through all the files in that folder.
And potentially, I want to run this on a cluster or something.
Yeah, that's a good way to say it.
Some people come and want to use our cluster to run tens.
They have hundreds of input data sets.
Let's say I have this Jupyter Notebook.
How do I run it on 100 different things in parallel?
That's sort of hard.
But if you make a script out of it, then we can make a thing that
extremely easy to just run it with 100 different input
parameters.
Yeah.
And that's where scripts or the transition to Python scripts
from a Python notebook comes in.
So we have two exercises prepared for today.
The first one is coming up shortly.
So it's just about converting a Python notebook or a Jupyter
notebook to a Python script.
Yeah.
I guess here's our short-term road map.
So I will do a demonstration of converting a notebook
to a Python script.
And then you'll have five minutes to try this yourself.
Then we'll come back, talk, demonstrate more,
and then there'll be a much longer exercise
where you can finish up number one and try some more things.
Does that sound good?
Yeah, at least to me.
because that's what we're going to do.
OK, so I'll show my JupyterLab here.
So yeah, essentially, it should be.
So this is the instructions here.
Should we go to the exercise and show?
Yeah, you can also just download it now.
Okay, so I'll use the same trick I used before. I will right click here and do copy link
and come into JupyterLab and do file open from URL and paste it here.
And it both downloads it as you see on the side here and it's opened it in JupyterLab.
Should I try running it to show that it works?
Yes.
Okay, there we go.
Okay, and now you essentially want to export this into a Python file.
The easiest is just going to File, Save and Export Notebook as.
So, this will download it to my computer?
Yep.
And not save file as, save and export.
File...
Further down. Save and export.
As executable script.
Executable script.
Okay.
But this is downloaded, and where is it now?
Yeah.
Okay.
So, another, I suppose we also do, we try it from the command line here.
So I think that what I'm about to show will work for more people.
I'll go to file.
Or at least it's easier that way.
launcher and from the new launcher I start the terminal and I see this is the directory where
I'm doing course things. So this may be the first introduction to command line for some people.
So for some people this may seem impossibly hard and for some people will be impossibly easy.
That's just sort of how it goes unfortunately. So if it's too hard take this lesson as a demo
and work slowly and come back to it later now that you're inspired.
That's all I can recommend. So I'm copying this line here and I will paste it.
And for me ctrl shift v works. I think just ctrl v might do something.
Ctrl v actually does work.
Anyway, so if I run this, then it converts it.
So it says it's writing data to weatherObservations.py.
You can try if it works.
If I open the file browser, I see weatherObservations.py here.
if we come here, we can try running it this way. Python.
Oh, it looks like it ran. Yeah, and if you now type ls or dir, depending on the operating system,
you see that there is a weather.png being created. It wasn't there before. Let's come
come back to the file browser, and we see weather.png.
And if I click on this, I see it.
The same image that was generated before.
The same.
OK, so it showed it.
It was also generated from the notebook,
but it was updated, as you can see.
It was created seconds ago.
OK.
It actually works.
So, let's give our, sorry for the videos hiding, well I would say let's give our viewers
five minutes to just repeat this again and see that that works on their machine.
So we'll give you five minutes, yeah, if things go horribly wrong then
Then, well, we're sorry,
something's gone wrong and sit back and do this as a demo.
Thanks. Five minutes. See you shortly. Bye.
And there we should be back on track.
And now coming more to what the actual use is of doing this
and putting it in a script.
Yeah.
So reading through the notes, there's
some different problems here.
And this is sort of, I mean, this is expected.
So of course, we don't want problems.
But there's always some places where
like someone's own computer is different,
or with different operating systems,
or I have a feeling that there is some cloud service which
is not working and doesn't provide shell access.
And this is, well, yeah, in that case.
Not much we can do about that, especially
if Jupyter is run on a web service,
then it's mostly out of our control, unfortunately.
Yeah. So if it doesn't work, just watch.
Okay.
Or if it doesn't work, what I would suggest is you download the file,
copy the data from the file into
a new file that you call .py
because it mainly is exactly the same.
But that Jupyter Notebook is mainly Python code.
And doesn't contain a lot of other stuff.
Yeah.
OK.
So let's continue.
Yeah.
So the nice thing with having this as a script
is that we now have access to command line arguments.
So if you run this from the command line like [Name] just
did when he was in the terminal, we
can add additional information in.
And that information is accessible inside the code
via the sys.argv, or via the sys object and via sys.argv.
And it's interesting to know that the first value,
so this argv stands for argument values.
The first argument value is always the program,
or the script name that you're calling,
because it's actually the arguments to Python
that you're getting there.
Yeah.
So basically, I could run something
like Python weather observations, as an example.
Hello.
Hello.png.
And the code can figure out that this hello.png is
where I should save the figure.
Needs to be modified accordingly, but yes.
So from the command line, we have a and b arguments.
And from the code, we have it accessible as sys.argv[1] and sys.argv[2].
So should I do it?
Yes.
The example I'll go also adds the time range,
because we are looking for something
with weather observations that maybe we
want to change what times we actually want to look at.
But yeah, we can also first just change it
so that it just changes the output name.
So I will come, I will open the script itself.
So here, the icon is a Python script thing.
So I double click this, and I've opened now weather.py.
And I see the script.
So it looks a lot like the Python code in 1,
in 2, where the cells were.
So what do I change?
So if you want to change that, the first input argument
is the we will depart from the code that's
in here a little bit at the moment,
just to make people aware of that.
So if we want to have the first input argument as the output
file name, then we would need to go to, essentially,
to the end of the script, where it says fig.savefig.
Well, let's do what it shows here in the screen share.
So OK, then, the first thing we need to do
is we need to actually import the system information.
And that's just to know that, OK, now
we can access this system information.
It's a package that's always available in Python
because it's a basic package.
But we still need to import it so that we
can access the information.
And so now, if you're watching, if you're still
working on the exercise, stop and just listen to us.
So that's what I'd recommend.
We will change it so that we can set the start and end
for always the first and second argument.
Arguments are always,
command line arguments are always separated by spaces.
So the first in that instance actually is number one
because zero, as we said before, is the script name.
So that's sys.argv[1].
And the second and the end date would be sys.argv[2].
And then we want to have the third argument
being the output file name.
And we can either directly say here, sys.argv[3],
or we can create a variable in between that indicates
the output file name.
OK, here we go.
I've saved it.
And if you now go back to the terminal.
Terminal.
So Python weather observations from the 1st of March, 2021,
the end of May.
Let's see.
Did it work?
Let's come back to the file browser.
And I see there's an image now called Spring in Tapiola.
And it looks different, for sure.
And it's still quite cold and dirty water.
It doesn't look that bad, though.
Actually, there's something odd here.
Might be that the data actually doesn't contain the March part,
because it only starts at somewhere beginning of May.
OK, so yeah.
OK, so now what do we get from this?
Well, we get the option that we can now essentially modify
or call the same code, but use different input variables
without going back into the code and modifying the script.
So you can run this script multiple times
with different input parameters.
That has the advantage that you can essentially
call it from some other tool, or you
can call it in another script and can automatically
call it with a list of things, making it a bit more
robust to potential changes.
Yeah.
So now, before we go to the exercise,
there's a little bit more.
So here, what we've done in this code is very basic.
So we're just using the system directly.
But there's more advanced modules to do this.
So what can you tell us about that?
Well, there are a lot of so-called command-line argument
parses.
All of them have their advantages and disadvantages.
Essentially, the more complex stuff you want to do,
the more complex code you have to write in the end.
For simple programs, I think argparse
is quite efficient, because it doesn't need a lot of details.
But it's not as flexible.
So if you have some requirements where, yeah,
you can have requirements that just are not
achievable with argparse.
All of these parsers commonly give some kind of positional arguments or named arguments.
Named arguments help you to, if you have multiple arguments and you have some default values,
you don't want to have to make sure that, okay, position one is always that, position
2 is always that and always have to check okay is it the right thing but you can essentially write
okay in the end or you can in the end write um whether observations by minus minus
start date and give the start date minus minus end date give the end date minus minus
um output file or output file name or something and the output file name um making the
the command line arguments or the command line call
that you give a lot more readable and a lot less prone
to, oh, that was the wrong position.
Yeah.
So I believe the next exercise is
having you try to modify this weather script to do
what we just demonstrated and also use argparse.
Let's see.
Yes.
So there's some, well, it's up to you what you work on.
So you can keep working on the first part if needed.
You can try to do what we just did.
You can use argparse if you want and have extra time.
Then there's another exercise at the very bottom which we won't talk about but you can try working on it now.
Okay, should we go to the exercise now?
I think so, and when we come back we'll quickly discuss a few more details.
Yes, so this is 15 minutes, so a relatively long amount of time.
Okay, great.
So see you at 45.
Okay, bye.
Hello, we're back.
So let's see.
So from the note, it was clear there were lots of different problems in here.
that's sort of that's unfortunate but I mean it's this really is a pretty
interesting and difficult thing because this is the first time we're going from pure Python
to going and connecting to the bigger operating system you're running on and there's so many
different variations there there's things like can't access pandas for example so that means
your Python on the command line is running in a different environment from that on the
the... Python on the program, yeah.
So if you're having really big problems here, don't give up. So take it and basically
Basically, go to one of your colleagues who can sit there with your screen and ask, okay,
so I'm trying to do this lesson.
Can you tell me what's going on here?
And you can get some help that way, and it will work much better.
As long as you sort of understand the general idea of what we've done here, and why these
scripts should be used, then you've gotten to the main points.
So with that being said, what have we learned here in the end?
Well, I hope we have learned that you can,
by changing the notebook into a script or into pure Python,
use command line arguments to modify
what your program does without modifying the program's code.
And yeah, I think I would call it program, because in the end,
this is exactly what kind of distinguishes things.
Here, if you have command line arguments,
that's something that you kind of always
have to call a program with.
Because any other part is self-contained,
but a program you can call with different arguments.
Yeah.
So if someone comes to us and wants
to run some code with a program on our cluster
on many different input files, how would we approach that?
That depends a little bit.
So if the input files have a certain naming convention
or are just numbered, then it's relatively simple
because you can essentially just go through the numbers
and have a for loop in a batch script
where you, with that for loop, call the individual files
or call your script with the individual files as file names.
If they are not ordered in a specific way,
you probably need to either provide
a file that contains the file names
and you read those in or you might go into well either write an additional python script or you
or you provide a or you change your your script so that it reads in a certain file and if
or a certain folder and goes through the folder but if each each of the computations is quite
expensive so you can't just do this in one python script or it would take ages but you want to
parallelize the computation, you will likely
write some additional script that
loops through those files, and then provides them
as inputs for your script at the end.
And those inputs are then run individually,
and each use one job on the cluster.
Yeah, so there is no clear this and that because it depends a lot on your situation.
But one thing that happens quite regularly is that people have input parameters and want
to go through, let's say, a thousand different input parameters that they have more or less
predefined.
have them predefined, they can, in the script, define them once.
And then the input parameter, or the command line argument,
would be the position of that parameter
in the list of parameters that they have defined.
And each run will take one input parameter set, for example.
Okay. So with that being said, should we go to a break?
I would
give a few more words about
additional options like using configuration files
because I think the problem with
command line arguments is that at some point the command line string gets
It's really long.
And even if you have an argument parser or something,
it becomes not really well-readable anymore,
the individual call.
So we are running out of time.
So please continue, but let's try to be quick.
And I just want to mention that there are then
methods that you can have a look at later on
to write the configurations for your program
into a configuration file and use that as and just be given a configuration file as input argument
that is then parsed. That's just what I wanted to mention. Yeah, so like here for example we've
defined all the parameters for the plot and it can be generated. Okay, great. So let's take a break
until two minutes past the hour and we'll see you back for the next episode. Thanks and bye for now.
Bye-bye!