So, as usual we've got some icebreakers here.
Today, we do a bit more than usual with a command line interface, so you can answer
the size breaker.
This question, I didn't write it very well.
How do you run the same things over and over again, but with slightly different parameters?
So this is like you have 10 different datasets, and you want to run the same code on all of
of them, or you have one data set
and you need to run with 10 different values
of some parameter.
So how would you do that?
OK, there's these other questions here,
which we can try to answer in a bit.
But we have a special guest with us.
So [name], can you introduce yourself?
Yeah, sure.
Yeah, so I'm [name].
I'm based in Finland.
And at the moment, I'm finishing my PhD in computer science.
And I'm also working in industry as a Julia software developer
in a startup for AI.
So yeah, I'm a Julia enthusiast.
And in Finland, I organized this Julia Users Helsinki.
It is a small community of people in Helsinki area, or even outside the Helsinki area,
who want to come together and talk about Julia.
Yeah. And you may wonder, why do we have a Julia visitor here in a Python course?
Yeah. And indeed, I brought the white flag because, you know,
I come in peace and also want to live in one piece.
But I mean, my answer to that is that, why not?
I mean, it's not like one language is better than another
for everything.
But there's all these different things here.
And knowing more about different languages
would have helped me in the future some, or in the past.
But also, the idea is to have role models
of different kinds of career paths.
So [name], can you tell us a little bit about how
you got to where you are now?
Like, what's your background, and how did you like?
Yeah, so my background is more like computer science, signal
process, statistical signal processing, that kind of stuff.
And I was like, when I think when I started doing my master
thesis, I had like the traditional story that I was
doing a lot of coding at the beginning, I was doing in a very
like painful way, like moving files around, and that felt
wrong. So I started like getting more into proper way and got
like more into proper scientific computing, and so on. And
And also, I heard about open source communities, and I was interested in that.
And at some point, Julia came under my radar.
So I heard about this Julia language that was meant for scientific computing and researchers.
And I was pretty interested in it.
But what really sparkled my enthusiasm about Julia wasn't even the technical features of
Julia.
Because at the beginning, I didn't know anything about it.
I didn't know why it was good.
I didn't know about internals or multiple dispatch or metaprogramming or whatever.
What was cool is that it was beginning 2020.
I had started my PhD and as you probably remember, COVID had also started, so I was stuck in
my room and I joined the Julia Slack.
And then it was pretty cool to see how everybody was very friendly, how everybody was very
active.
And I was seeing famous people, like people of popular Julia packages, who were sitting
there answering my dumb questions and getting me step-by-step, so it was more this community
feeling that really got me into open source, so I sticked to Julia.
Then I actually started writing documentation, so I was in this Google Summer of Docs for
writing documentation, and I started building a web page for a couple of libraries, and
writing documentation for libraries. And then I was twice in this Google Summer of Code
program, like doing more Julia programming. And after that, I also found a job as a software
developer, Julian, like a startup through like people I knew in the Julia community.
And I have, of course, like been using Julia in my research also for like for my PhD and
for my own research. And yeah,
Julian is a pretty new language, right?
Yeah, we celebrated the last year's 10 years of Julia
There was this a HackMD kind of a yearbook where you could design your experience of 10 years of Julia
so it was I think the first commit was from 2009 and the first
Public release was from 2012 and it achieved the version 1.0 at the 2018
it was developed at MIT and
And the goal of Julia was to solve this so-called two-language problem.
So, you know, you encounter this problem that you start writing in Python,
and then you hit some performance bottlenecks, because Python is an interpreted language,
and then you needed to rewrite it in C.
Or also, people who use Python, actually, under the hood, TensorFlow is written in C.
Or a lot of libraries are written in C or Python.
Sorry, in Cython, I meant, not Python.
So whereas in Julia, the power about Julia is that it allows to prototype and achieve
performance in the same language. So the magic word here is multiple dispatch,
and there's a very inspiring talk like the unreasonable effectiveness of multiple dispatch
from JuliaCon 2019, which explains how it achieves both dynamicity and performance.
Okay. Interesting. Okay, so we're almost where we need to begin the next lesson.
Anyone have any questions for [name]? If you do, please write down there.
there. So [name], there's something I always ask people. So what do you know now that you
wish someone had told you at the start of your career?
Yeah. So what for like more like my open source career, like being involved in the Julia community,
like one thing that I really wished people like told me before, which I learned kind
of my experience is that you really don't need to be scared to start and you don't need
to ask permission. That's a good thing about open source. Also, at the beginning, when
I started, I was a bit shy. I was like, okay, maybe a first prototype in closed repository.
Should I open it? Will people just say it's dumb or will people steal my job or stuff
like that, but this doesn't happen in open source, at least not in Julia communities,
like a reasonable size for it not to happen.
So just put your code out there and don't be afraid.
The best way to get the answer is not to ask the question, it's to post the wrong answer.
So just put your code out there, put your work out there, and people will help you.
You don't need to be afraid of that.
And actually, similarly applies to research, at least like in my field, I don't need to
worry that much about scooping.
So it's pretty cool that also research
I can put my code and my work out there publicly
and I just meet new people.
So that, and maybe other quick thing about
is that open source is not about code, it's about community.
So we have already a lot of people coding in open source
and of course the more the merrier,
but we also need the non-technical people in open source,
people helping with writing documentation,
people helping with bringing people together,
people helping with improving diversity
inclusion. So open source is really not about code, but it's more about community. And as I mentioned,
like, I got, like, sparkled from truly not because of multiple dispatch, which I didn't know what it
was, but because of people friendliness. So, yeah. Yeah. Okay. Great. Thanks. And I can also
say about what [name] said about putting your code out there. If you want to be hired somewhere,
like whenever I'm looking to hire people, having public code and saying that,
like being able to see things, that's a huge benefit there.
Okay, but now we need to get started.
Thanks for visiting.
Yeah, last thing, if you are in Finland, we have every month in Helsinki,
this Julia Helsinki meetup, except not this month,
but the next one is going to be on the 13th of December,
and it's gonna be especially for beginners about Julia, so we're gonna be like intro about Julia
and about how to use Julia research and teaching. I also put in the notes, so 13th of December. It's
not official, it's not even on the website yet, but I can give you the spoiler of this. Congrats
and hope to see you there. Yeah, okay, great, thank you. Yeah, thank you for having me. Bye.
Okay, bye.
So, with that said, I guess we should get started for the day.
Yes, so the first lesson is [name] and I.
Hello, [name], have you already introduced yourself? I think so.
I don't think so. I think this is my first appearance this year.
So yeah, I'm a research software engineer at Arthur University, working in [Name]'s group
and in general interested in programming.
In general. Okay, so what's our first lesson of today?