Okay, are we ready?
Yeah.
So, okay.
So, the first topic is parallel programming and that's kind of an interesting topic to
talk about in Python and I mean, well, you'll see in a moment, but the main thing, I guess,
in Python is that you are using, you're often using Python to connect packages written for
you or written by someone else, and possibly written in other languages.
The first thing when you start considering making your program faster, or especially
if you start thinking about making it parallel, is to check if the libraries you're using
already are parallel or not.
That's probably the most important point of this lesson.
If you come away with just one thing, that's it.
But we will talk a bit about how parallel programming actually works, what it actually
does and how it can or maybe cannot make your code faster.
Sorry, I interrupted you, do you have something?
No, no, no, go ahead.
So maybe we can ask, I could ask, what do we mean when we talk about parallel?
we mean when we talk about parallel programming? Is it like two people on a keyboard?
Yeah, right. So that's called pair coding, I guess. That's a slightly different thing.
Although that is actually a good, I think that's a pretty good metaphor for what the computer does
or what the program does when you run it in parallel. So if you are writing some code
code, and you want to do it twice as fast, hiring two programmers will make it faster,
I guess, but it might not make it twice as fast.
But yeah, so basically, the starting point, if you're thinking about making your code
parallel, is that you want to make it run faster.
It's taking too much time for one reason or another.
Otherwise, you can just run it on a single processor and it will be done.
So that's the starting point.
We want to make it faster.
If your program is fast enough, you don't need to make it parallel.
Would you say that the speedup would come from utilizing multiple processors in one
computer?
Yes, so parallelization specifically, yeah.
So you try to make it faster by essentially using multiple computers.
There are multiple processors on most computers these days.
Basically, if you have a laptop, desktop, you're watching this.
It has 4, 6, 8, 12, maybe around 12 processors that are on the same chip,
but are essentially running calculations independent of each other at the same time.
So, yeah, so making your program parallel basically means all of those processes are
doing something at the same time, so in parallel.
Okay.
So the first thing, though, if your code is too slow, you kind of want to do some, before
going into parallel programming, because it can quickly become a complicated thing, is
check why your code actually is slow, where are the slow spots, use some profiling tools
and then think about can you use existing libraries or somehow make that part faster
and then profile it again and see what part is slow now and so on and then when you get to the
point where that's no longer helping you may think about parallel programming and then
Then there are essentially two different modes of parallelism that people generally use
and you can think about whether one or both of those will work actually in your program.
So the first thing to check is if there is something that really needs to be running
sequentially like you have to know the result of a previous computation to go to the next
one, then you can't do those two things at the same time.
So it's not really parallelizable.
And then you just have to think of something else.
Um, so there will be those parts in the code, but there will also be probably
some parts in the code that were two calculations can be done at the same
time, and then you can parallelize it.
So, okay.
So then like, and what do you say that like in some cases, like, let's say you
have, you want to run the same code or multiple data sets or
something like that you want.
Yeah, so that's one example. So maybe you just want to run the
same code for multiple different parameter values. So
you have a bunch of files that you want to process. So that's
an example of something embarrassingly parallel. Which
is like, I mean, it's an interesting expression, but
that's kind of the official term these days. So it's, the reason
embarrassing is because you don't need to do anything to make it parallel. It just means
you run multiple copies of the program on those different processors, on those different
computers. You can do that by running the command multiple times or you can program it in some
more fancy way to start multiple copies of the program. We will see ways of doing that,
but I mean, there's many ways. Many languages do that.
I would say that the embarrassingly parallel is usually like, if you notice that in your code,
you happen to have a for loop at the outermost layer and inside the for loop, you have something
that run a model or something. You know that you can basically take that for loop and run it
outside of the program. So basically run multiple copies of that program. And that's why it's
barely called parallelism. It's like, so embarrassingly parallel, you don't need any
fancy structures to make it happen. So the main thing about this embarrassingly
parallel category is that the different processes, the different copies of your program don't need
to communicate at all. They just do their own thing. And when they finish, they finish,
the others do not care. That's embarrassingly parallel. And that is the most common situation,
I think that's that's what you will usually end up doing. I just run the same thing many times
but if that's not possible then there's two other options. There's multi-threading.
Multi-threading means that they are running on the same computer but on different
processors on that computer so essentially the thing is that they can share memory.
when you have a variable in the program's memory, the other copies, so-called copies,
or which are called threads really, they have access to that memory.
So that makes things a bit easier. That makes sharing information between the processes a bit
easier. And then there is message passing or MPI, message passing interface is a
common term people use. And a common framework for this. So that means you have a bunch of
independent processes that can be running on different computers and then they send messages
to each other. They communicate over some kind of network. Or in Python you also have this
multi-processing and what it basically means is that Python launches multiple processes and then
they communicate by writing small files into memory, and then each process reads the files.
But basically, it launches multiple Python interpreters that each run stuff.
Yeah, so that's a Python-specific thing that is important, and we'll talk about
multiprocessing in a moment. I'm kind of, well, we'll come back to it because I'm kind of struggling
with a way of going in. Check the first example of Parallel. Yeah, okay. So if you go down a bit,
there's the multithreading example. So this is still like relatively straightforward,
especially in Python because essentially Python doesn't do multithreading, but the libraries that
are written for Python can do multi-threading. So if you're using NumPy, SciPy, Pandas, and so on,
they will be using libraries in the back end that are already multi-threaded.
So basically, you don't need to do all that much. Just make sure you're not running a for loop in
Python, but rather you are using a NumPy operation if you can. There are complicated enough NumPy
operations that you can do most things without a Python for loop. For the technical side,
people who want to know how it works, basically NumPy inside it has lots of libraries or it uses
lots of libraries like this linear algebra libraries. Also, if you think about a for
loop. It's like sum all values in this array or something like that. There's a for loop
in many of the NumPy functions, and those for loops have been threaded in NumPy itself.
If you just tell NumPy to use multiple processors, whenever you use the NumPy functions,
it will try to run these for loops in parallel. It works behind the scenes, so the only thing
you need to tell it is this OMP number of threads, which is a pretty cryptic variable,
but basically what it tells is that use multiple processors.
And this is also MKL and a third possible option. Usually, those are already set so that you don't
need to set them. Usually, NumPy will just use multiple threads. You will see that by
if you run NumPy and check what your processor load is, that Python process will be using something
like 400 or 800 percent of a CPU. So that means it's already running on multiple processors.
Threading is also common for web applications and that sort of thing, but because they're not,
well, for scientific computing they are not so relevant. We won't be going to that, but
But there's like Python has lots of these async things, but they are not relevant.
So I'll just mention it, but if you see parallel using that, they are basically mainly for
web applications and that sort of thing.
So one big thing kind of worth mentioning, like if you are trying to do multi-threading
on your own, I said Python doesn't do it.
So it's, in fact, something that was kind of a choice that
was made when the Python language was developed
or is being developed.
So there's something called a global interpreter lock.
And basically, that means that there can only ever
be one thread, one process running Python code.
So if you want to run Python code,
like have multiple processes running your Python code,
you actually need to start multiple Python interpreters,
which is exactly what the next thing will do.
So this is a way around.
Multiprocessing is a Python library,
and it's a way around this issue.
So if you actually find that whatever libraries
you are using are not multithreaded,
so you're not doing calculations in NumPy,
or you are doing something a bit more complicated in Python
and you know that you need to kind of split it
into multiple processes,
multiprocessing is a way to do it.
There's a bunch of nice libraries built upon multiprocessing that might be more useful,
but well, I guess we'll write a list into the notes in a moment, but here we'll just
try to use multiprocessing.
Yeah, let's check on, like, I can run the demo here and see what happens.
So here we have an example.
So we have a function.
So we have a function that – well, maybe you can explain and I can write.
Well, yeah.
If you type – I mean, this is a very simple function.
It just calculates the square of the number that you put in.
But this is a Python function on purpose, so we're assuming that it's somehow something
we cannot do in NumPy directly.
And then map will run that function on every number in the list that you give it.
So you notice it gives you the squares of every number.
So one squared is one, two squared is four, and so on, six squared is 36.
That was really fast because it's a small list, but it was running pure Python code,
If it was a big list, it would be a lot slower than, say, numpy.
I'll mention here that this might look, for those people who haven't used functional programming
kind of things, this might look a bit strange, but it's basically like a for loop in a small space.
It is running the same function to every element in the list.
Yeah, you might see a more Pythonic version might be something like this.
Yeah, okay, that's the same.
Yeah, this is basically like a map function.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's a good example.
Yeah, but basically it's the same thing, but using these maps makes sense when we go to the
The reason we use the map function there, demonstrated, is because multiprocessing comes
with its own version of the map function.
So if you now import pool from multiprocessing and then pool contains the map function.
Oh, okay.
It's from multiprocessing input pool, not with.
Oops.
Yeah.
My mistake.
Was looking ahead already.
Yeah.
And then, yeah, then you need to get a pool or yeah, create a pool.
So, so what we have, there's a great way of, of, or a great
explanation of why this is called pool, but it's essentially a set of like.
So it gives you a set of processors that you can use to run stuff.
So you can run this square function with multiple processes.
Um, it didn't actually return anything.
I guess you have to probably need to store it somewhere.
Yeah.
Okay.
So yeah, this does the same thing and you didn't see the
speed up of course because it's so fast.
Anyway, we could have a much bigger list and then you would
see it.
But so what the multiprocessing pool does it it takes the
list it splits it up between all the processors available.
and then runs this function on all of those processes to some part of the work, basically.
Yeah, and in general, I would say, here we give a list to it, but map basically works on any kind
of iterable thing. So in Python, you see a lot of these iterable things, like something that
at least is an iterable thing, but you can have other things as well, like iterators.
And what map does is basically take something from the iterator and it runs a function on it.
And if you use the normal map function in Python, you do it one by one in one processor,
basically. But here we have a processor pool. So, we have multiple processors.
Usually the number is decided to be the number of processors in your computer. Of course,
you can set it yourself. But you have a number of processors, and we read from the iterator,
and then we give each processor one at a time.
Send those one by one to the different processors.
Yeah.
Or really, actually, many at a time, because sending one number is not efficient.
Yes, many at a time. Of course, the multiprocessing library then collects the
results in the same order back so that you get the same kind of correspondence between the input
and the output but but basically now you do the mapping in parallel. Okay so let's now go to the
exercise so there's an exercise one where you use multiprocessing and then you can also move
on to exercise two which is more of a discussion about running on a cluster. So a cluster is a
a supercomputer. It's a system with a lot of computers in a fast network. But yeah,
mainly do exercise one, and then if you have extra time, take a look at exercise two.
So we'll have 15 minutes for it.
During the exercise we'll try to answer any unanswered questions in the notes and we'll
bring them up after the if there's anything interesting or any especially good questions
we'll raise them up. Okay, so that's it for now. See you in 15 minutes. Bye. Bye.
Hey welcome back. So yeah there was one more thing we wanted to mention before MPI.
Which is that a lot of the libraries, like we mentioned in the beginning, a lot of the libraries have some sort of parallelism built in, usually multi-threading.
And often it just works out of the box.
But also there are ways of setting the number of workers and using parallelism through some settings.
So, yeah, it's usually usually a good idea to use this like the developers of the packages they have most likely tested that this parallelism actually speeds up the code.
So, instead of like making some parallelism outside of what the developers have intended, using their method is most likely the most efficient way of getting parallelism.
So, for example, like just like an example library that you might encounter is like a
ski kit learn.
If you're doing like machine learning or data analysis and that sort of stuff, putting models
there.
And let's say we are in the user guide, we just go to the user guide.
Like this is what, like when people ask about parallelism, this is what I usually do.
I open the packet space and then I press control F to search and then I search for parallel
And there's like a page on parallelism here.
And if we look at here, they mentioned that they're using this job lib library,
which is similar to, or it's built upon multi-processing.
It's a nice library.
We'll mention other tools like this in the notes after the MPI session.
But basically it says that there's this end jobs parameter, like on estimators
that you can like, you can put it there and then it uses parallelism basically.
And then you can, you also use this, uh, this higher level
parallelism and these open MP stuff.
And they have various ways they explain, like, uh, how do you get the best performance?
So it's usually a good idea to check, check the guide, whether it's parallel
mentioned anything parallel is the magic world, uh, word usually, uh, that, that
can be found in various documentations.
And you can then use that.
Another thing that in the notes, I think it's good to mention.
So at least one person got an error that from multiprocessing,
that it cannot pickle the object something.
something. And that happens because, like we mentioned, Python actually doesn't allow
multiple processes, so they cannot actually just read memory or read the same memory.
So what multiprocessing does to get around this is that it essentially writes the function
and everything it needs to run that function to disk, starts another Python process, and
And then that Python process reads it from the disk or if it's like if the disk can be
on RAM.
So the file can be in fast memory, but still it needs to be possible to write it to disk.
And that the main thing is that that causes some restrictions.
So sometimes things just don't work and there's ways of getting around this.
You can read the instructions or try to ask people, but it gets a bit complicated.
And in general, let's say you have a function that does really complex things and that sort of
thing. If you want to run it in parallel, all of the different parallel processes need to know
about that function and what the function has eaten. If it uses global variables or whatever,
all of that needs to be transferred to that other process. So the more complex your parallel thing
is, the harder it is usually to parallelize. So usually it's a good idea to parallelize.
Yeah, keep it simple. Have a simple function that will be executed in Parallel and then
return to a bigger program or something like that.
So basically, if it's a method of a class, it needs the entire class. If it uses a global
variable, it needs the entire file. And if you're calling multiprocessing from that same
file, it will just fail. So one way around this often is to just move the function that
you're running into a different file and often that will help but sometimes not.
So just be aware of that.
It gets complicated and try to use parallelism from inside the existing libraries rather
than writing your own if possible.
Now MPI though is usually not built into the libraries for a very important reason which
is that it always needs to be run with this MPI run program, basically, that sets up an
environment for.
So what MPI does, it runs completely separate processes and then tells them some information
about the other processes so that they can communicate.
So these can be running on completely different parts of completely different computers as
As long as they know the IP address to the other computer and there's an Ethernet cable
or Wi-Fi connection or something, so that they can communicate.
Of course, that would be quite slow if you send a lot of information back and forth.
In principle, that is something you can do.
So MPI is a very different paradigm because you just run copies of the program.
All the copies run everything from the beginning.
All the copies run all of your code, basically.
the main difference. Whereas in multiprocessing, it just takes the function and tries to put it in
a file and read that file and run it. With MPI, all of the copies will run everything unless you
tell them specifically to not do that. There are other frameworks as well that work in a similar way
that they basically set up some network configuration and they do their own configuration.
For example, PyTorch has a Torch run, and there's Ray, which is this parallel library as well.
But there's many frameworks that do this. Everybody starts, and then they just know
about where the others are. They communicate in some way. In MPI's case, the MPI will handle this,
okay, who are you? Where are you? But in many other cases, you might have master processes
and clients connecting to the server.
So for MPI, I mean, MPI is kind of the lowest level.
It's kind of the basis, again, like multiprocessing
is the basis of a lot of libraries.
MPI also is the basis for a lot of stuff.
So, okay, so we'll just show a quick example,
but this is something you may not be able to run
because it requires that you install
not just the Python library,
but also you need to install,
like MPI as a system-level library. It's not written in Python. So it's possible to do it in
Conda, but we don't assume that you have done that. You can try. Maybe you have the functions
or not. Okay, so what [name] is doing here is first importing MPI for Pi, and then there's some magic
stuff that, I mean, yeah, I could explain what those things are doing. But the main thing is that
that, you get the size, which is the number of processors that are running this program.
And then you get the rank, which is the unique identifier for this particular copy. It's
a number from zero to size, basically. So that's what you have to work with, really.
have a single number that identifies this particular copy and then there are MPI functions
that allow you to send information to other copies. You have to know the number of the
other copy. So from these building blocks, you can build a lot of stuff, of course, but
it takes a bit of work.
Yeah.
Okay, so let's just try this. So this is just printing the rank, the identifier number and
the number of processes.
And to run an MPI program, you need to use MPI run.
And you can give it a number.
Okay.
Well, I gave it the wrong name.
Oh, yes.
You need to give it the correct program, it will run better.
If you try to run the wrong program, it will not run as well.
Yeah, yeah.
That's a good hint.
Okay, so yeah.
So it ran two copies of the program,
one of them has identifier 1
and the other one has identifier 0.
So if you were, for example,
doing what we were doing previously,
where you split
this list into
two multiple processes,
you would need to have
perhaps just, usually you just
set it up with
process number 0 and then you
send a part of you. You actually have to write manually write the code to send the part
of the list to the other process. We'll do a different example. Let's just let's just
run the example in the notes. It has all of the stuff that we just ran, but it's also
yeah, like the different so yeah, okay. So the different identify the different processes
are now doing a different thing, and in the end, it's being collected.
Yeah, so all of this code, what's important in the code basically, we have the function
that all of them will run independently and all of them will do their own part of the
whole thing, but the important part is here in the line 39, where we have this communication
gather so basically we gather everything and then we have this root so we gather all of that
information to the processor zero so you can have this kind of like collective everybody
send the information to the process zero and the process zero will then print. So that's an example
of one of these functions that allow the processes to communicate with each other.
There's also a send, for example, that just means one process sends information to one
other process.
Okay.
I guess we probably don't want to go too much into detail about this because we also
want to spend some time on all the rest of the material.
Yeah.
I'll quickly mention that the MPI is commonly used in scientific codes and that sort of
where you might have a grid or collective, like you can't solve some problem in a big grid or
something like that, where everybody talks to their neighbors. But the communication,
how do you communicate? It depends heavily on the problem. So you need to usually provide the
communication. Who tells who what information? Based on your problem, you usually need to
to decide yourself how to do it.
So there's one big rule of thumb
when it comes to multi-threading or multi-processing
and MPI, which is because multi-threading
and multi-processing usually run a very small path,
like a single for loop in parallel,
whereas MPI will run all of the code in parallel.
So in MPI, you want to split at the highest level possible.
So as much as possible get split between the processes and then they're just like occasionally sending messages to each other.
In multi-threading, basically you want to parallelize the smallest loop or one loop at a time.
So they tend to be used quite differently and that's also the reason why often the libraries are parallelized with this multi-threading,
multiprocessing things and not with MPI, but if you're using MPI then you usually have to do it
yourself or use something that's specifically intended with MPI. Okay, so another thing is,
like we said, a lot of libraries are using multithreading and the reason they can do
it efficiently is because they're not written in Python. Python needs to use a multi-processing
approach because one process can only run at a time. But in C, C++, Fortran, whatever,
in all of these fast compiled languages, you can run multiple threads at a time.
Multiple threads can run code at the same time. Almost everything is written, has a back end
that runs the fast parts using libraries written in these languages.
So if you ended up in a situation where you need to kind of extend those libraries a bit,
there's multiple ways of writing C, C++ code for Rust and then calling that from Python
to get the thing done.
Yeah, there are also...
You can just call your library from Python.
There are also like Python libraries
such as Numba and Jax nowadays
that can do stuff like
just-in-time compilation
where they like take your Python function
and then they compile it
into a faster C++ function
without you ever leaving Python.
But they are...
They need additional things usually
things usually. Your code needs to be written in a way that it can be compiled, not be like
generic Python code. It doesn't exactly support general Python. It's a subset of Python that you
have to use, but it allows you to write the program, write the function in Python and then
run it as if it was written in C, which is really convenient and usually actually the
first thing you would want to do or try. Yeah. And before we leave for a break,
we can mention Dask as well. So if you're dealing with big pandas data frames,
if you have a lot of data that you need to process, Dask is this kind of
of like improvement on pandas or more parallelizable version
of pandas that allows the probe, like what it does basically
is that when you set in your pandas code or whatever,
you select certain rows here, calculate average of them,
and whatever, you have some operations that you do.
Dask can create this kind of like a computational graph
of it and then it can execute it in parallel. So let's say it will run like the data in pieces
or something like that and it can handle the parallelism on the back end. And if you're
dealing with large data sets like big data sets of data frames, it's a very useful tool and it's
used in like banks and that sort of stuff because it makes it possible to analyze like huge amounts
of, let's say, customer data or something.
So I started a list of useful libraries for parallel Python libraries, and I wrote that
the task is useful for large data sets.
There's also JobLabel, which is, I guess, an easier way of doing maps with multiprocessing.
I guess it probably does other things as well.
Yes, so we'll continue adding more stuff there, and if you have any more questions, just put them in the notes.
Yeah, and please add any library you know of or you use that we may not know of yet, because that's always good to keep up to date.
Yeah, and also if you, at the end of the day, if you have some certain cases that you would
want us to present or certain libraries you would want us to present in the coming years,
let us know, because there's so many of these nowadays, so it's hard to say what are the
most important ones for our users.
But what sort of use cases you want us to demonstrate.
Otherwise, so we intentionally left a good amount of time for discussion here.
So I'm looking for questions in the notes that we might want to bring up.
There's a good question there, how can I install OpenMPI?
Well, Conda has an OpenMPI installation package there in it.
So you can just Conda install OpenMPI, at least from Conda Forge, and MPF API as well.
that's, I would highly recommend using that compared to like
installing an MPI by yourself, unless you're using it in a very
large scenario in a computational cluster or
something. But if you want to work in in like one machine or
something like that, the MPI in the in Conda is good, good
enough in most cases, like, or if you have a, if you're working
in a computational cluster, the maintenance of that cluster
will usually provide you with an MPI already,
because it needs extra stuff to be able to do it.
There will probably be multiple versions you can choose from.
Another one, so this is answered in the notes,
but benchmarking libraries,
because we talked a good bit in the beginning
about how before thinking about parallelizing,
you should do benchmarking and try to just make the code
faster with the existing libraries,
which is usually enough.
So if you have one specific function you know you want to benchmark,
then timeit is a really good library.
And if you have an entire code,
or when you're starting you basically just have one entire code,
you want to figure out what is the slow part in that code,
then scalene is a good option.
So, that's on this question, mark this question number nine, but should we, is it easy to
find in notes?
Yeah, I added to the libraries list.
Okay, good.
So, it's benchmarking and yeah.
Yeah.
Guidelines for deciding knowing in what way I should parallelize my code.
I would say like the first thing is like check out the embarrassingly parallel.
That's usually the most efficient way of parallelization because it's like if you have a natural thing in your code.
code that is embarrassingly parallelizable. For example, you run it with multiple parameters,
multiple datasets, and that is usually the way to go because that scales infinitely, basically,
because you can always launch more processes. As long as you have more data, right?
Yeah, as long as you have more data. Yeah. And after that, I would say probably check
the libraries that you're using, whether they support parallelization.
But yeah, so then if a single case just takes too long to run, like several days,
so if you're running on a cluster or on a supercomputer, you can usually reserve it
for a few days. But then if something breaks, you might lose everything. So it's important to
build in some checkpointing. So write everything to disk so that if you have to restart it,
it can continue from where it was. That's already very useful. It's not parallelization exactly,
but it just allows you to run for longer. Then if it still takes way too long,
then you just need to make it faster and you might need to parallelize in some way.
And then, if there's a way of splitting the data, like if you're running a simulation with a grid of points, you can split those points and run independently for each of those points.
That's a good case for MPI, possibly.
if you have big loops over a lot of small things inside those you might be able to parallelize with multi-threading options.
So basically though, well the multi-threading thing basically means use libraries that are multi-threaded,
multithreaded, which means NumPy, SciPy, Torch, TensorFlow, whatever. It depends on what you're
doing, but almost everything is multithreaded if it does a lot of calculations. So just
try to combine calls to NumPy, for example. If you have multiple calls to NumPy with the
same data, try to make it one call so that it doesn't get split.
One thing also, there's a few questions in the chat about the multiprocessing example,
like locking up. It might be due to the Jupyter locking the GL, the global interpreter lock,
what we were talking about. Because if you have a Jupyter, you have a JupyterLab running
Python interpreter, and then you try to run multiprocessing there, it might be that the
Jupyter and how it processes the sales and that sort of thing, it should work, but there
might be a situation where it somehow locks the global interpreter lock.
So that might happen, but it's hard to say.
We will check the examples and we will verify that.
There's at least two questions about this.
Yeah.
So we'll verify.
solution, like if you take the solution from the web page and it doesn't work, then it
might be, yeah, you might want to check compared to the solution.
Okay. We are out of time though. So let's take a break and then we'll move on to packaging.
Yeah. I'll quickly mention that there was also like a question about pooling, like
pool one getting bad results or like using pool was worse than not using pool. And this is
exactly what might happen in a case where you parallelize a thing that actually doesn't benefit
from parallelization. So the example of course is like a trivial example that we have. So it's a
very low, like the processor will just go through it in an instant anyways. Like it's going to be
like nanoseconds or microseconds or something to calculate it. So adding the constructions of,
okay, we'll construct a parallel pool and then we'll give everyone their own process to run,
it's a huge amount of overhead. But the thing happens is that when we are getting to the
runtimes of seconds or minutes, then suddenly the overhead isn't that big. But usually you need to
figure out what is the part in the code that requires me to parallelize it.
And usually, also, I'll mention that, for example, the map thing, writing it as a NumPy array and
just squaring the NumPy array would be much faster than any pooling because NumPy already
does the parallelization inside. So, not using Python objects, but using NumPy arrays would be
always faster than doing the pooling thing. So it's a trivial example, but it's just to
demonstrate how to use the tools. Okay. But yeah, so we are out of time. So
do take a break and walk around a bit. Let's come back in 10 minutes. All right. Bye.
Bye.