Thank you very much.
We are back.
So the last real lesson of the day is now web APIs.
So [name], how do we start?
Yes, so maybe it's good to start with understanding
what do we mean with web API.
And I don't know if everybody knows what API means,
but most likely everybody knows what UI means, user interface.
So for example, most, let's say they want to search something with the browser, with
the window, which is your user interface, you go to a website like google.com and that's
the interface that you work with.
You type something and you get an answer, the search results.
So API, the interface now is application program interface.
So it's like that the interface is not designed anymore for humans who can, you know, use the
mouse and type and do things like that.
that we can basically use machines.
So basically this kind of goes down
to the concept of server.
I don't think we need to go into the details
what is a server, but in general,
we are all using these servers,
meaning these softwares that when we ask for a page
or when we ask for some information,
whether it's with our smartphones or with our computers,
we get an answer, so we are served with an answer.
So what we are gonna cover here is that sometimes
in some cases, it's very useful to interact
with these sources of data that are not physically stored
on the same machine where you are.
Like the example that I gave that you might wanna query
something from Google, but instead of looking
at the answer yourself, you can have Python
look at the at the answer. And then of course there are other more advanced uses of the so-called
APIs, meaning that there are companies who might give you access to a specific API to do something.
I guess you all have heard about OpenAI and ChatGPT. That's another example that, you know,
it would have been possible to store this huge GPT model on your local machine so you can,
for example via Python, send the query or like the prompt that you would send to the remote
computer and then get an answer back. The most simple way of doing this programmatically with
Python is with this package called requests. So request is a Python library that makes
requests to web servers as I just gave you some example. You see here in the bottom there is this
Basically, the web page for this request is embedded there, and they label it as HTTP
for humans.
Maybe I could ask [name], what does HTTP mean, even though we type it almost every
day?
Yeah.
So, HTTP means Hypertext Transfer Protocol, and it's basically the way everything communicates
with the web server.
you send the request saying, I would like to see this web page,
and it sends back saying, OK, here's the data you requested.
And you can give other parameters,
like what languages my web browser is configured to show,
or things like that.
And for humans, means that request
is trying to make it a way that's well that's
easily easy to use by humans so they really
care about the user interface of this.
Exactly, which basically simplifies your work.
As usual, maybe one of the biggest lesson
here in this course is that often there's
no need to reinvent any wheels.
There are already very good packages
that can do the heavy lifting for you.
So here in this retrieve data from API,
the introduction text there is basically telling you
that there is a list of many
of these application program interfaces
that can be used without a key.
So this is something that if you will start working
with external API, sometimes you need to have a key.
For example, in the OpenAI chat GPT example
that I was giving you earlier,
if you want to query the remote model,
you need to basically show that it's you through a key,
through a token.
But in this case, we're gonna use an API called cat fact,
which is basically it's going to return
some random fact about cats.
And so maybe, you know, enough with the talking,
should we just get started with some Python?
Sure.
Okay, I'm arranging things.
Yep.
So I guess I will make a new notebook in my place
and rename it to, OK.
So how should I start?
Yeah, so if you scroll a bit down,
and you can also do the same for those who are watching,
there's a section a little bit more down in the materials
where we basically start with the import for this library.
And then the code will also have this URL.
So URL, it means Uniform Resource Locator.
It's basically, again, what we normally type daily.
It's the address of this,
in this case of this remote server API.
And then we can use this library,
this request library by getting this URL.
So what happens?
So now there should be something inside this response.
So it's a response object.
So with objects, you know that with "." and name of the name
of the field, you can actually get some content.
And here we see basically a string that starts with the B
and lots of stuff.
So, the string looks like JSON, but it has a B in front.
What does the B stand for, [name]?
That's a thing I like talking about.
So, it looks like a string, but the B in front means Python is interpreting this as binary data.
So basically, it's not assuming it has a text encoding.
In Python, all the things that look like strings are either unicode strings, meaning they should
contain text and can have any unicode character, like each index is a character, or B, which
means each position in the string is raw, like a raw byte from 0 to 255.
But I think we probably shouldn't go too much into that.
It's something you can get deep into later.
But then the rest of the whatever comes after the B
looks like JSON.
Did we introduce before what do we
mean with JSON, the JSON format?
I don't know.
Did we?
Maybe I should say again anyway.
Yeah.
So JSON is a way to turn objects into strings.
So this looks like it would be a Python dictionary,
but actually, it's all encoded in a string.
And basically, JSON is a way to do
that encoding in a way that's standardized and shareable
among different computers.
And many, many APIs that basically will return strings,
they will actually give you the answer in JSON.
And this is why this response library also has a dot JSON function.
So what if we tried the, um, exactly that part of the, so now basically is
this like, like, um, dictionary basically, let's see, yes, it is a dictionary.
So then we could know easily access, for example, using the keys, the
different elements yeah all right instead this this what you did earlier now it's listed
as bytes because it's it has to be the yeah
so now basically you are you're yeah you're putting the this dictionary into a variable
corresponds underscore json and then you're getting the key fact yeah all right so so far so good we
saw basically that we can basically get some data and get is one of these terms using this
http protocol but sometimes we also want to maybe send or at least tell the remote server that you
know maybe we don't want to just get the page like in this specific case but we want to filter
according to what the remote API is allowing us.
So often you might, again, have seen this
when you browse the internet,
you might see a URL and then a question mark
followed by various values or like key equal values.
So these are basically,
these are called parameters for the GET query.
And in this specific case, for example,
we use a remote API that is called
universities.hipolabs.com, which is basically
providing a list of all the universities in the planet.
But you see here that now this URL
has a parameter as a question mark, country equal Finland.
So if we run this code and we get the request from this URL,
Will it most likely give us basically a list
of the universities in Finland?
And as you can see already, indeed, it does.
In this case, why did you put like,
can we remind people what is this column 2?
And this says it's giving the first two elements
of the array.
So if I remove it, then it will be a log response.
Exactly. And we will see all the list. But then this is the thing. So now we were passing this
parameter through this question mark, followed by key, name of the parameter and the value.
But this library, the response library is actually,
with the response library is also possible to pass the parameters via the Python request.
So, should we try this bit of code, [name], where now, instead of, so the URL now is different,
it's just a general URL for the API.
But now we pass the parameter country equal to Finland, basically.
So I've just copied the whole thing.
Yeah.
I guess the key point here is this parameters equals parameters, which is a dictionary.
Exactly.
And now it will give the same results, but you can try, for example, with your own country,
you can put Sweden, you can put Norway, and then you can get programmatically, you can
get the list of all the universities that are at least listed in this remote API.
So this is basically the main idea behind this remote APIs.
rather than talking we could let people try exercise one it's an exercise where in this
case you don't have to how can I say think the solution the solution is actually following
after the exercise so it's an opportunity for you to test another API so even copy pasting
is fine and exploring the output and when it gives we could assign 10 minutes if these
are too short for exercise 1 you can also start with exercise 2 and then later we will
comment on what is going on with exercise 2. Does this sound like a good plan, [name]?
Yes, it is. Yes, very good.
So let's have until 12.23 start with exercise 1 and if you have time do exercise 2 and then
we will come back and do a recap and more stuff.
OK, sounds good.
See you later.
Bye.
There was a nice interesting question in our notes document, are there any best practices
or general guidelines, but when it comes to the coding, the examples that we gave you
with this request library, it's a good starting point for working with web APIs.
But then one should also consider maybe the ethical and sometimes even the legal aspect.
Ethical, it can be in the sense that, you know, are you allowed to use this data?
Is it ethical to scrape this data?
we do this for research purposes, so we can do these things, we don't break any law.
But then there's also the ethics of the fact that you are sending many queries to some
remote computer that maybe you don't want to overload the remote server, I don't know,
with 1,000 queries every second. So then often if you, let's say that you need to scrape
many many web pages and we will soon show briefly a little example on that maybe you
don't wanna you know maybe you wanna have a break between every every page so that your
Python code could scrape one page wait for a few minutes scrape another page and so on.
So there's no comments related to the exercises so most likely they were easy and understandable
Maybe regarding exercise two, [name], exercise two talks about something that we didn't really
cover before, the headers. In practice, if I understand it correctly, it's like what
we tell to the remote server, like I'm on this computer with this operating system and
this browser, but do we need to sometimes change these headers?
I've done it occasionally. So sometimes the headers can be used for, for example, passing
authentication information. So the API knows who you are and that you have permission to access it,
but oftentimes there's other things in requests that can handle this for you.
Sometimes the headers would say things like what format you want the data in, or things like that.
And I can't remember an exact time, but I've probably done it once or twice.
Exactly. In the learning materials, there is an example where there are some example
of these headers that according to what you need to pass to the server, you need to modify
eventually. But often, if your goal is, for example, to scrape materials from the internet,
it's okay to use the default headers of the request API, of the request library.
And when it comes to scraping exercise three, we don't have time to go through it. So please
go, please do it if you have time. So the code that we see here is basically an example
where we wanna download the full HTML of a remote server.
So now it does not an API in the sense
that there's some software that even the parameters
that we pass is going to return an answer
like we had earlier JSON.
But now what is returned is basically
the so-called HTML code, which is this structure
which is the language of the web pages that you see.
So, in practice, with the example that you see here,
you request the HTML of some page,
in this case, example.com,
and then there's another library that is used.
If you scroll a little bit more down after this HTML,
there is this beautiful soup,
which is one package that allows you
to basically parse the HTML so that, again,
you don't need to invent new wheels
to extract the information that you need here basically it creates a structure of all the
tags that are contained in this HTML file and for example one can look at the title
of the page or look for all the links the links are marked with this tag A and so this
is why there you see find all A there so that will search for all the links in this case
there was just one link in this web page but it's time to wrap up maybe there's also something
else interesting in this web page which is saving the data the example there it's a useful
example there's nothing too difficult there but it's a nice example of doing multiple
queries one after the other like I mentioned earlier and and you see at the very last line
there is this sleep.
If you scroll up a bit, yeah.
So this is exactly the thing.
So we put one second between the multiple queries.
In this case, there are three queries to this cat fact API.
And then what's happening,
this code that this JSON replies from the APIs,
they're stored, they're appended to the same text file.
And this is a useful way to deal with kind of
to basically building a data set.
So at the end, you will have a big JSON file
that everywhere, every line is a JSON string.
And then most likely from this type of data,
from this format, maybe you want to move it
into a pandas data frame to basically continue
your analysis.
I think we are done.
[name], do you have any comments on this data storage
from API?
Yes, I would say so how this data storage relates to what we talked about yesterday or two days ago.
So you might have different ways of storing data for different purposes.
So for example when it's downloading you want a file format where you can easily append
expedited to, and it won't get broken, like it can't really get corrupted. So for that,
downloading and storing in a giant text file with one line per thing, that's easy and relatively
foolproof. But when you're analyzing, then you might convert this to some other format,
which is more efficient for your other analysis. There's a comment there, like,
what a good way to be to store it in an SQL server of some sort. I mean, it could be done
if you have that set up. Many of our researchers have access to a big file system, but not an SQL
server. But another thing like saving it to disk first, just so you have it, because the file
system is more reliable than SQL server for, well, not getting corrupted.
Yeah.
I guess SQL would be a useful solution if these files, you know, if one is planning
to store 1 million JSON files, maybe that's not the best, but, you know.
Yeah.
I mean, it really depends on the site.
So even if you're scraping whole internet-level things,
you have to really think about this
and try to do it really well.
And that's not easy.