I can hear us on the stream, which I will now mute because the echo is, of course, annoying.
So we put two icebreakers in here.
What's the most surprising thing you've learned so far in this course and most surprising
thing you've learned so far in your career?
And if anyone has any other icebreaker ideas, please, well, you can also propose your own
questions there.
I'm trying to think of something specifically related to today's materials, which is a bit,
we have a wide range of topics.
Yeah, so what's our summary so far?
Where have we come from and where did we go?
We started with day 1, and it seemed like it was pretty normal Python stuff.
Like Jupyter, NumPy, Pandas, I mean, doing Python code.
Day 2 did we start getting exciting.
So day 2 started pretty normal with Pandas and Matplotlib.
again using normal Python code. Towards the end, we start seeing more interactions with the rest
of the world. So the data formats emphasizing how it's not just about the code, but how you
mess with this other, how you read and write data outside of Python can matter.
And then, of course, the things like the linters and so on, which is user interface.
But then yesterday, I mean, yesterday's the kind of stuff which is really important for
using Python, but you wouldn't see in a typical course.
So things like making the scripts, well, you might see that in a Python course, not a purely
theoretical programming course.
But yeah, the introduction to programming with Python
might not even use Jupyter.
It might use just scripts.
And the library ecosystem independency management,
well, that is, I mean, that's really
getting to the kind of stuff which we use
and we support people with on a daily basis.
So my estimate has been that about half of our
total support requests are helping to install software on the cluster,
a lot of which is in Python and could, in theory, be done independently.
But it's so confusing and hard.
Dependencies are a complicated topic and a big unsolved problem.
Um, it's also the reason, like all of these libraries, the fact that they
exist is the reason why Python is good.
I mean, the language itself is good, but the main reason people actually use it
is because there are already all of these libraries available.
Hello from my side as well.
Yeah.
Like I was just thinking myself at that, like, uh, quite often when, when using
Python, it's more about reading what some other person has done like a package and then reading
how they want you to use it and then just using it. And it's like, is this, can you call this
even like coding when you're like calling functions from other libraries and that sort of
stuff? But of course you are coding, but like, yeah. And, and, and, and using, using like, it
would be wasteful to not use the capabilities provided by the other people.
And it's usually the thing you find is not exactly the thing you want, but you can
coax your data to fit into that and kind of use it or modify it slightly to make it what you want.
Yeah. And it's like buying Lego blocks. You buy Lego blocks and then you have a world that you can
create with them and you can of course like just follow the instructions and do the set that you
have bought or whatever or you can go wild and do whatever you want with them like combine the blocks
in an unexpected way and create something new and that's what like usually happens but you don't
start molding the lego blocks yourself like that would be waste of time like getting like a 3d
printer to mold them. Of course, if you want to, you can go to Python libraries and start
writing C code and that sort of stuff, but then you're coding C code and you're not coding Python.
So I think we need to do a volume check.
So, well, let's start with an order, me, [name], [name].
1.
2.
3.
Three.
So, I think [name] is too loud.
I can also drop it here.
I'm actually not at 100%.
Is it better now?
You still seem pretty loud.
Better?
One.
Two.
Sorry.
Oh, yeah.
One, one, one.
Two.
Okay.
Is this better?
Might be just my enthusiasm rubbing off on you.
Yeah.
Might be just my enthusiasm rubbing off.
So I'm liking these icebreaker answers here.
I just thought of these last minute,
but it's good to see what's surprising in the course.
And also, I like these career lessons also.
So, last time there were some problems with a blurry screen, and one part might have been
Twitch, but also it might have been so people are sharing by Zoom, and then I render it
on the screen, and then capture it, and then it gets rebroadcasted.
So there might be a little bit of blur that comes here.
So if you see a problem, let me know, is it really bad or like a little bit of anti-aliasing
around the letters and let us know right away and we'll try to fix that.
Yeah.
On your side, I recommend in the Twitch, there's like this cog icon at the bottom right of
video where you can click the video quality and you can make it to appear as source quality,
because otherwise it's automatic and then it might degrade it based on the network performance that
you have. So you might like get suddenly a blurry flash because it's buffering or something like
that. So setting it to force it to be the highest quality might mitigate some of the problems.
Okay. Well, it's 10.01. Any comments from these surprising things or should we just
go on? Should us instructors say the most surprising stuff? Maybe we should just go
on. We can answer this in the panel discussion.
Okay.
In the wheel getting reinvented. But yeah, we'll talk about it. Well, at least we will
talk about how to package your own stuff so that other people
don't need to necessarily write it themselves later.
But first, we have some parallel processing.
OK, so I'll head out.
Can you share the screen?
Yeah, I can take the share if you capture it from my screen.
Okay.
I see it.
I will head off.
All right.
See you.