Hello. I hope everyone had a good break and is refreshed after 10 minutes. So, let's go
to packaging.
And yeah, we talked about all the different libraries
in the Python ecosystem.
Now we are going to add one, or at least add one
into the test thing, but show you
how to create your own package and how
to publish your own code, or at least make it easy for you
to use across all of your projects.
So should we do some talking first or just jump directly in?
I would jump in.
Or why are we doing it?
Yeah, I guess the main thing is to make it easy for you
to use your code.
If you have a piece of code that you
want to use in multiple projects,
make it easy for you to do that.
And just have it all in one place
where you can maintain that bit.
well, you can just maintain it in one place.
Or even to get it to the point
where other people can use your code
and only one person still has to maintain it,
which is, it saves time.
Other people might even be maintaining your code
at some point.
I'd actually say that is probably the most important point
for packaging in the end,
that you make it easy for other people to use it.
Yeah.
So that it is actually used.
Yes.
So, what do we need to make a Python package?
Well, we need some structure.
Well, yeah. There needs to be some structure that everybody knows is going to be there.
And that's basically kind of predefined.
There will be modules because a Python file is called a module so you will have code in
Python files and then we collect related modules into packages and in here we will
show how to collect them into a package. Then if you want other people to be able to use your code
you need a license. That's also if you want to accept contributions from anyone else you
need a license because they need to give you the access to use the code and that the license file
is usually in the root of the project the root folder of the project. You need a readme file
because you need to tell people what the code is and what it does. It's also good to have
other documentation but often in a small project or when you're starting readme is enough
documentation but it's also good to have other documentation and automated testing is great
because it allows you to check that everything works well at least like the things you are
testing work by just running one command. And it helps you a lot in staying backward
compatible so that what you're changing doesn't change for earlier results. Yeah,
Yeah, that's very important, very useful.
Okay, so those are the things we'll cover.
I'm actually not sure if we cover testing.
Well, let's see.
But first we'll start with creating a package.
So we'll assume that we have some useful functions
we have written that we want to use in other projects.
So the first of them is add.
Yeah, imagine that this is a useful function.
So this will add two numbers together.
Here we are.
OK, great.
Let's also write a subtract.py, or subtracting.py,
which will subtract two numbers from each other.
Okay, and finally, one thing that's slightly more complicated, which will do a numerical
integral.
You are cheating a bit, we don't really write the code, we just use a library.
Well, yes, but you should not write the code
for a numerical integral.
You should use SciPy.
So there's one question.
Can you do this packaging in JupyterLab?
So you can write the code in JupyterLab.
You can create the files in JupyterLab.
So almost everything we do, you can do in JupyterLab.
But it is, at least for me, we're
dealing with the file system more than with Python code.
So it's kind of more natural to do it here.
You can also, so, okay.
So the point is Jupyter is more made for, I guess, notebooks
and the packaging part,
like it's about creating Python files
and running commands in terminal.
So you can do it in Jupyter.
It's fine, but it's not using notebooks.
Sorry, [name].
[name], can you make your fonts bigger?
Is that big enough?
Well, probably good.
We can see what people say.
I think it's probably good.
I probably can't change them in the editor, at least not quickly.
Yeah, the editor will probably follow the terminal font.
Let's see.
Can you run ls just to see what's in the current directory now?
So yeah, we have some Python modules that are useful and we want to use in other places.
I think for now, if you scroll down in the notes a little bit, you'll see a general structure
for a package or what the folder could look like.
I think the first thing we want to do is to create a folder where we put all the modules.
So this will essentially be like, this is the Python stuff.
This is the thing that's called a package.
So this is where all the Python code goes.
And it's a folder.
It's just a normal folder, and we just move all of the .py files there.
So do you want us to start here with the project?
So is this what we're currently looking at, the project folder for our example?
example?
I mean, OK, so you created a folder that
will be the project rules.
OK.
OK, so let's just go there.
And then there we create another folder that's the package.
I'll just push all of this over so that we.
So this is a very common structure in queue.
We are back in here, but.
Yeah, so now let's create another folder.
So basically, the reason for this
is we want to have one thing we can import.
Like, when you import NumPy, you import all of NumPy.
We want to import calculator and be
able to import all of these functions at once.
But now, actually, we can't quite do that yet.
What we can do now is run from calculator import adding,
for example.
But we need to tell what Python needs to do when
we want to import calculator.
And we do that by adding this __init__.py.
That's something that it's kind of predefined in Python.
And it is what turns a folder into a Python package.
So here you can import things that you
want to be imported when you import this package.
And this is just normal Python code, really.
So actually, what happens is when you import calculator,
when you import this folder or this package,
it will run this code that Umesh is now typing.
And everything that's then defined in this Python code,
all of that will appear as calculator.something.
So there will be calculator.add, calculator.subtract,
and calculator.integral, and also calculator.version
with the underscores.
OK, so this looks good.
Should we now try importing it just to see?
Or, well, yeah, let's import it first,
and then we'll add a license and readme.
I hope I started the environment.
Let's see.
Well, right now, it's all in this folder, so you don't actually need to be in the environment.
SciPy isn't, potentially.
Oh, SciPy might not be there. That's true.
Well, if you try to `import calculator`, if there's no SciPy, can you run...
run so okay you just run from calculator can you run import calculator
no module name calculator is it yeah it has an init file oh uh wait
i'm not entirely sure but i think well okay let's see
Okay.
Nope.
Interesting.
Did you actually move to the folder?
Can you type ls?
Okay.
I'm in the wrong folder.
Yes.
You are in the wrong folder.
Okay.
So now you can import calculator and you have SciPy.
Yep.
So it didn't actually, it didn't fail.
All right.
So yeah, that's why we add this __init__.py and that's why we have all of these files in a
single folder.
You can, of course, you can have a more nested structure with multiple folders, but the __init__.py
makes this a package.
And then, well, you can also try, you can do from calculator import add.
This actually, actually this does require an input.py, yeah, okay.
Seems to work.
Yeah, seems to be doing things.
So let's exit this interpreter, or if you
want to try something else, fine.
Try an integral or something.
OK, yeah, let's exit the interpreter.
And now we don't have a license file or a readme file.
So we don't need to decide on a license for this test case,
but let's just create the file and a readme file as well.
Let's just create them for now.
Yeah.
They are empty.
Okay.
So, yeah.
Now we have two empty files.
If you don't, press again to show what we have.
Okay.
So, we have calculator, we have license, and readme.
Now, the next thing to make this a package, oh, what is the time?
22.
22 passed.
Okay.
So, yeah, so the next thing we need to add to make this package installable is this pyproject.toml.
And yeah, just create a file and we'll just copy the stuff from the example.
And this is what I do anyway.
Like when I start a project, I copy a pyproject.toml from somewhere and then I modify it according
to like my needs.
So you probably want to change my name because,
so the reason is we will actually be uploading this
to the Python package index,
which means you can install it with pip.
And that means, yeah, so you don't want,
you want a unique name.
If you have, if you try with a name that already exists
in PyPi, that's already a Python package,
then it will not work.
So let's just identify it as the package for Python SciComp 2023.
That's a good idea.
Okay, otherwise everything is okay.
It depends on SciPy.
There's a quick example, a quick description and readme file.
Yeah, so you can also add your name and email if you want to.
We could add additional ones.
Yeah, you can add multiple authors. You can add more dependencies. That's all. And, yeah,
there is something called a long description.
I'll leave that at example.org.
Okay. Yeah. So, this is it. And what this does, it makes your package installable with
pip. So, now we can run pip install. And, well, it's not yet on PyPI. It's not yet in
index, so we need to point it by pointing to this folder if we want to install. But let's just
demonstrate it quickly. So `pip install .`.   `.` is the current folder. Okay. You don't have pip.
Oh, okay. Okay, we will fix this. But that should have worked.
And if you are in the Anaconda environment, base environment, I think this should work.
I would just pip.
So the next thing we do is we go to the exercise which is essentially creating the package
we just created and testing that you can install it locally.
So we will give you, now we're running a bit late, we'll give you 15 minutes anyway because
This is the important part and that means we'll be back at 11.40.
All right, so, yeah, good luck and see you in 15 minutes. Bye.
Hello. So, yeah, let's go straight into PyPi. This will not take that long. So, we do this
as a demonstration, but you can also follow along and upload your package to test PyPi
preferably, because unless you have an actual package you're going to want to upload.
So yeah, we will be uploading to testPyPi. I guess I should explain what PyPi is, right?
So PyPi stands for Python Package Index.
And when you type pip install and just the package name instead of a folder, for example,
then it will look for that package in PyPi in the Python package index and yeah you can push
your packages there and then people can install them with just pip install the name. So it's a
very useful thing to have. So yeah we'll show you how to use it and you can follow along if you want
to and you can upload something to test PyPi with these instructions. And yeah test PyPi is
kind of what it says so it's for testing and your packages will get removed rather quickly.
I don't remember how quickly exactly but it's not meant for actual packages. I have the impression
it's not that quickly I just found that there's still one that I probably put on there a year ago.
Okay I'm kind of surprised but okay well fine. Anyway so it is meant for testing
So yeah, so let's just go through the steps on how to get this package into PyPi.
So yeah, first you run build.
This doesn't work.
Okay.
Build is a package and cannot be directly executed, but that's kind of the point, isn't it?
Should be.
Okay, so maybe we need to update the instructions a bit. Let's see.
What about twine.build, maybe?
OK, that could be.
Or, well, OK, let's install twine.
Yeah, OK, that's the next step.
So Python packaging guide tells you to, oh, come on.
And we are using setup tools.
Okay.
Well, it tells you to install build using Python, using pip.
Let's try that.
This is a relatively new site, right?
PyPi instructions.
Can you try running pip install, or did you try installing Twine and it didn't work?
I tried installing Twine and it didn't want to do, so I'm going back to the base environment
to see.
Oh, okay.
This, well, we'll try for another two minutes, say, but.
Actually, Twine might just be the uploader.
No, pip install Twine.
Okay.
Okay, and then pip install build.
Okay, now let's try Python 3 minus m build.
The tree is in the wrong place.
Yeah.
So there has been a relatively recent change in.
OK, that did something.
Good?
Yeah, that looks correct.
OK.
And then we'll try Twine upload.
So Twine is a Python package that
uploads things into the Python package index.
here we are specifying to put it into the test index. You do need a username and a password,
you need to create an account to upload anything and it will of course be associated with your
account. Okay there we are and now we can try installing it. So normally if you put
something into PyPi, it's just pip install package name, but in this case we need to
tell it to use the test PyPi instead. What was the name? It was underscore after four, I think.
I tried like this because it seems like it changed the underscores.
Oh, okay. All right, so yeah.
underscore is not allowed now it's installing our package yeah and now we should have it
so is it now called calculator for pysc 2023 or is it just called calculator we will see
oh well they are definitely not with minus signs it changes minus signs to underscores
Okay, well, we did run into a couple of problems here, but okay, fine.
So we need to update this example a little bit to use SciPy correctly and to, well, I
guess the instructions for uploading the PyPi were correct, but somehow it didn't work in
that one environment.
So something called build was already installed,
but it wasn't.
Oh, no, no, maybe it just wasn't installed
and it was just a folder.
In any case, it worked.
I have an impression that the SciPy version that
is being used here is not really what we want.
Could be.
Yeah, the SciPy 0.1.
0.1 is not what we want. Why would it – oh, because it's from test.py. It got SciPy from
test.py. So, it didn't get the latest version. It got whatever they used for testing a long time
ago when they tested uploading SciPy last time. All right. In any case, that is how you upload
packages to scipy and also to PyPi to the python package index and that makes installing them a lot
more straightforward for your friends and collaborators. All right so there's one thing
I quickly want to point out this question about what the license and readme files should say.
So in the exercise description we added a lot of details about well essentially we just added
links to Code Refinery materials which you can read up on your own time or come to the
Code Refinery course. We would love to have you there. There's something about documentation
in general, so that also tells you some ways of writing README files. In social coding,
is a part about software licensing the general instruction the most important thing is use an
existing license don't write your own because it's legal language and yeah it's better to leave
that for the lawyers and then there's a section on testing automated testing which we mentioned
it's nice thing to have in a package but we didn't actually show you how to do it so there
is a section on that. Otherwise we are right on time for a break. Anything else?
I think not really. All right, so let's take a 10-minute break and then come back for web APIs.
All right, bye.