OK, with that being said, I guess
next is our panel discussion.
I'll switch to the notes here.
Yes.
Unfortunately, not all instructors from the first two days were available, but at least
we have some Alto people here.
Yeah.
So it's basically like our team here is answering questions.
OK.
So yeah, this is something that we tried a year or two ago
and worked really well.
So basically, yeah, think of what you'd like to discuss
and send it.
Someone's typing at Jupyter.
Question.
Do you use Jupyter training?
AI?
Machine learning image analysis algorithm.
I mean, I would start with Jupyter for most, like, for training a relatively simple model,
I would start with Jupyter, but then at some point when I'm writing the model, I would
probably take the model definition part, for example, and move it into a Python file, a
module.
Yeah, what a problem can happen with Jupyter is that it's, by design, interactive.
And interactive is all fun and dandy if you're actually watching the screen and actually typing
commands. And that is, of course, when you're prototyping a model or something like that,
you're actually doing it. But when we're talking about longer AI training,
usually interactive doesn't cut it. Like if Facebook is writing a llama or something,
there's no one guy running Jupyter cells. They have a non-interactive script that they run on
a compute cluster. For example, for Lama, they were using two compute clusters with huge amounts
of GPU resources. If you're doing a big AI training, you usually don't run it in an interactive mode.
You run it non-interactively and then you store the model checkpoints and that sort of stuff.
and store results maybe in a TensorBoard or 1 DB or something like that to monitor the training progress.
But of course for prototyping and that sort of thing, running Jupyter is good.
But then you usually need to have access to a GPU card.
And especially in compute clusters, the GPUs are usually demanded by these longer term jobs.
term jobs, these jobs that run for days and interactive usage basically means
that it's idling, the GPU is idling most of the time.
So usually what we recommend is that people who are actively doing
modern development, they get a cheap gaming GPU to prototype on with
Jupyter or something like that.
And then they move on to compute cluster to run the actual
training that takes days or even longer.
There's one question about benefits or disadvantages of Python versus other scientific or other
programming languages.
The example given here is Matlab.
My personal take would be one big advantage of Python is that it's open source, mostly.
There might be some packages where it's a bit more difficult that rely on the proprietary
software. But overall, it being open source is a big benefit. I have the impression, at least,
that Python is better when it comes to backward compatibility than, for example, Matlab.
I think Matlab has a good track record on that. But I'd say that Matlab is basically like,
You get what you buy because it's a commercial product. There are many
answers and many programs that are designed for doing some coding or calculations or running
some simulations. For example, MATLAB is very popular with signal processing people,
electrical people and that sort of stuff because it has good support for that in the toolboxes.
but it's like if you want to do MATLAB or web scraping that's not like it doesn't have the
connections that Python have to other things but it's very good at those things that it's
been designed to do and what the developers provide but it's not like a generalist programming language
what Python is as well. Well nowadays MATLAB does have a lot of interfaces with other languages
So, in the end, it's a bit of a style question.
And one clear thing is that if you use MATLAB, whoever you think might want to use your code
also has to have MATLAB.
And that means they have to pay for it.
So, I would assume at least that Python code is more widely used just because there is no financial barrier to using it.
I remember once when I was starting in a previous research group, everyone that comes in says, okay, who has the bootleg MATLAB copy.
But, you know, I never did that because I use Python and it's free already.
So, you know, even though it is available, the fact that you have to deal with licenses
and all that makes it harder and your work less reusable.
the best way to export plots if you need them as vector graphics. I think Matplotlib does support
vector graphics, right? Yeah, like probably most of the plotting libraries you could find a way
to export to SVG or PDF or something. So basically, yeah.
Let's see. Now we're getting lots of questions here.
Are you planning to run a Python course on AI and ML? I had answered that up above a little bit,
and my general thought was there's so many courses about AI and machine learning out there that
that's not our main target. There's a similar question right below about parallel programming
which we I mean we covered a lot of things really quickly and didn't go very deep in a
lot of things. There are a lot of courses out there and materials out there and
And so, yeah, I'm not sure if we can actually get 500 people or even 100 people in a course
about MPI or parallel programming in general, but you can study it and then, like, talk
about it with your local IT people, hopefully it will help.
Yeah.
In both cases, like, I think there's this kind of, like, in the industry as a whole,
is kind of a situation where the examples and small courses on how to write an MPI Hello World
or how to write a Keras or PyTorch machine learning thing that analyzes the MNIST numbers
or something. There's lots of material on the first part of the thing. Then there's usually
how do you scale it up? How do you scale MPI up? Or how do you get a big machine learning pipeline
or deep learning pipeline, training pipeline working? Then it goes super technical, super
quickly. And then it gets into this kind of a valley where usually you cross that valley only
by having engineers or somebody, a support person, who actually constructs a huge scaffolding that
you can cross the valley. And of course, big companies like Google and Facebook and those
kinds of companies, they have engineers who do that kind of scaffolding. But teaching that
that scaffolding is very hard, usually.
The biggest issue is that teaching that in a general way
is often not possible.
Because what you need to do depends
on your particular field or particular problem.
So we can teach basics of MPI, how MPI works with our ranks,
what functions are available to you.
Then we can talk specifically about your problem, your research field or the program you're writing
and talk about how to apply that framework. We can teach how to do MNIST with PyTorch
or do image recognition with PyTorch but then you will have a specific case
and most of what we – those are – we can give you the basics, but then from there it's
too specific, so it really only applies to you and a small group of people.
And then we talk with three people in the room and that's fine, but it's not a course.
It's a garage session, which is a very useful thing to have.
Yeah, many of these things which we're talking about, or these other courses requested, they
already exist, or you can find a good tutorial online.
And we very carefully targeted this course to things that are important for a junior
scientist but are not really taught other places.
you might not know about because of course you have to go follow up for most of these things.
Can we talk about a little bit about what our daily jobs are?
So how do we relate to researchers?
Well, I think most of us mainly help researchers with a variety of questions when it comes to
programming, but we are mostly, I think we are not solving the scientific question, we are solving
the implementation of whatever they come up with, with their solution or enable them to
use that solution or make it available to others.
Exactly, so that to me at least is one of the issues with specific questions for specific
software where I would commonly say, ask an expert in your field, they have a much better
chance of having in-depth knowledge of, okay, these are the tools that are currently state
of the art when it comes to analyzing tools or analyzing data.
We can of course also search things, but we are not commonly using these tools ourselves
most of the time.
There might be projects where we get in connection and see things, and yeah, if we see that that
works well or is well documented or something we can sometimes make suggestions but in a general
principle they are specialized highly specialized software where we can help you get into it or
if you tell us that you need something or if people tell us that they need something to
to something done with a certain software or so,
we can probably set up a system that they can use,
a kind of building a small prototype
that they can then expand.
But as, yeah, on a more general level,
we are not the experts in the software, I would say.
Any other opinions?
Yeah, I'd say that throughout this course, you might get this impression that you start
with the coding, which is NumPy and Pandas and that, and it quite quickly goes into actually
what you're doing is doing library management and installing dependencies.
And that's, of course, where we usually help our users.
like, if you know about the scientific subject, you know, about the context of like context of
the functions you're calling, what, what does it mean to do a Markov chain or whatever?
Like, you know, a context of where, where do I use this? Like, I don't know, like,
genome splitting function or whatever, like, you, you know, the context of the function,
the mathematical context and the subject context. But we usually help with that annoying part,
which is like, okay, how can I get this working? And this is unfortunately a big part of the whole
field because there's so much available. And of course, everybody wants to utilize the tools
because if you've ever tried writing, for example, Fortran code, and then you get some solutions
out of it and you store it, then you have to think about, okay, how do I even visualize this?
How do I plot this? Because it's like a Fortran binary format or something. Nobody wants to do
that. Nobody wants to write their own data readers or CSV readers or that sort of stuff.
nobody wants to waste time on that. So you want to use already existing tools. But of course,
if you want to use the already existing tools, you encounter a lot of hiccups with those tools.
And that's where we usually jump in and help the users. We understand enough of the context
to understand what the tools, how are the tools are supposed to be used and that sort of stuff,
and what the user wants to do with the tools.
But usually, we don't know about the field that much.
We mainly know the general idea about it.
And then we can figure out how to apply those tools
to that specific case.
Yeah.
I like question 42.
Do you think Python will ever become outdated, replaced
by a different language, since some people seem to say that R
might not be used anymore in the near future.
I've put an answer in there.
I think it's possible, sure.
I don't think it's likely anywhere
in the foreseeable future, since the ecosystem has kind of
achieved a critical mass, provides
so much possibilities and has addressed the issues that the language has.
So all these bridging to other languages where you have a lot more efficient ways to do certain
and things, make the disadvantages somewhat less.
So like, let's say Python seems to have this really good balance
between power and user interface,
and also a way that it moves slow enough
they really think about how the language is developing.
It is being actively developed, so yeah, that obviously helps a lot.
So there is that one little design choice that it can't do multi-threading, but I mean
we make this ways to get around that and multi-threading happens in the libraries anyway, so it's not
really a big problem.
But yeah, the way I could see any language gets replaced is by the design issues becoming
problematic, or by a completely new paradigm becoming problematic.
Yeah.
Python has this kind of like a tendency of whatever, like people say, like if people
say that, okay, they don't like a feature in Python, like suddenly there's like a package
that somebody like implements that, like for example, like Python doesn't do static typing,
but nowadays people have written extensions that basically like for static typing wherever,
or they try to do type hints and they try to do typing as much as possible in Python.
Python is object-oriented and it's functional at the same time. There's people who like the
functional side and they write functional programming only and they try to implement
their stuff as functional programming and they find extensions that provide that. Then there's
people who like the object-oriented style and they write extensions that make that easier.
And then it's like, is it even the same language anymore? It's like a completely different dialect
of the same thing. And it's very hard to say like, yeah, what is the core language in Python
is so adaptable. And I think that's the main thing why it's so popular, that you can do all
kinds of stuff with them. There are libraries like, I mean, I guess TensorFlow is a great example.
It is essentially declarative. So Python is written to be, if you know, there are different
programming paradigms and Python is not written as a declarative language, but there are libraries
that actually make it declarative. So it can actually, depending on what library you use,
it can use a completely different programming paradigm. It's extensible enough.
And also the question about when people are asking there about R, I like R in many cases.
For statistics, I think R is a wonderful language. I wouldn't, again, do web scraping in R
necessarily or web servers or something like that. But again, it's not the forte of the language,
but it's very good at what it does. And I think the thing with the languages is same as
with natural languages? Are people actually using it in their everyday speech, basically?
Are people writing new stuff using that language? Are they creating new things or are they like
songs that some old person, like a hundred year old person remembers and that's the only
recollection that we have of a language and then we record it on a tape and then we remember that
we used to have this sort of a language, like languages are only alive when people use them.
Like in a normal, normal case, I think maybe some linguistics might be, might have a different
definition, but, but I think for programming language, the main thing is like who are,
who other people are using it? Not, not whether I'm using it correctly. If I have nobody to speak
with that language, it's not really helping me in any way. It's, it's about the whole like
community and ecosystem. And I think Python currently has a very healthy ecosystem. Of course,
there might be new things coming, but it's hard to tell. The timelines are so long.
Some questions about what to learn next. So there's not just the programming language,
but you might have seen a lot of what we're doing here is about how the programming language
interacts with the operating system, the data, things like that. And that's another good thing
to think about and follow up on, no matter what language you're using.
Question 45. If you want to learn Python or any other language, it's good to have a
problem and a deadline, and then you should try Advent of Code, just advertising Advent of Code.
But it's fun if you have time.