So, hi to everybody.
It's so nice to see so many people on the document and on stream.
We are so excited about this workshop.
My name is Saravan.
And together with Gego, we are today teaching Git from Tromso, northern Norway.
It's snowing here.
I work with the CodeRefinery project since its start.
So, this is now, I think, eight years that we do this.
In my work, I like teaching programming,
helping researchers and students with their coding.
So research software engineering
and also supporting people in computing.
Yes, and maybe a quick hello from my co-instructor Gregor.
Yeah, hello from my side.
My name is Gregor.
I'm working with the same group as another one
here at UIT in Tromsø, Norway.
So it's the high performance computing group,
but also the research stuff engineering group.
I started recently and before that I did a postdoc here
at the same university in plasma physics in my case.
So I've worked a few years as a researcher as well.
Yeah, looking forward to this course.
And since we both have been researchers,
we know how it feels.
We both haven't kind of officially learned coding
coding in our university curriculum, we did research and learned it a bit on the side.
We know the pain, we know what is needed. Before we go into Git, a little bit what to
expect and how to participate. So please expect, we will do an exercise soon, roughly
in 15-20 minutes. We will then also do a break in half an hour.
And the two things that I always have open in my browser, and you can have that maybe
open next to the stream on the other half of your screen, is I have the collaborative
notes. So we will be watching these as instructors, and please keep the questions coming. The
The more you ask, the more you comment, the better it will be.
We are following this and the best way to do it is to ask at the bottom because we already
have so many things open here on my side and on your side.
I will be watching what comes up at the bottom.
So add your questions, add your comments to the bottom of the page.
You will also find always here where are we at this moment.
The other place that I have as a starting point
is the workshop page.
So if you get lost and you want to find the material,
you can also find it here through the schedule.
And we have now finished the introduction section,
thanks to Samantha.
And now we will talk about Git and version control.
And I will now go into the first link,
which is also in the collaborative notes.
And I want to tell you a little bit what to expect today and tomorrow and on Thursday.
There is a side panel here with lots of episodes.
We will not do all of them.
There is a lot more than we chose to present.
But what we will present you is the most important parts.
The exciting thing is that we have a completely new Git lesson.
This is the first time we present it.
We have changed everything, but hopefully to the better, because our goal was to make
it possible for everybody to participate.
And you can actually choose your path, and I will tell you more about it in a moment.
I will now scroll down a little bit just to give you an overview and zoom in to make
it more readable.
so that you know what to expect today,
what to expect tomorrow.
We will now very briefly motivate why we do this.
And then the goal for today is these three episodes.
To browse an existing project,
to make changes to an existing project,
and to merge changes that have been done
on different branches.
So, today in day one, we learn how to,
how do we contribute to an existing project
that already exists?
And we imagine that today and tomorrow,
we want to learn Git for, even if you work on your own,
even if you don't collaborate with others,
what are the most important techniques?
Tomorrow, okay, and each of these three
will have one exercise.
So, please expect 20 minutes,
25 minute exercise blocks
in each of these three sessions today.
And then tomorrow we will move from,
we will move the existing project
and learn how do we work locally on our computer?
How do we inspect history
of a project locally on our computer?
And then super important,
since many of you already have a project,
you have a script, you have some code,
or you are about to start one,
how do you turn this project into a Git repository
and share it?
This is so important,
because we want to make it findable and reusable.
So that's the plan.
I will now go into motivation.
Why do we do this?
So our goal is nobody leaves the workshop
without starting some form of version control.
We want to really get you excited about this.
And this will be a really short overview.
And what is Git?
And I see on the document that many of you are new to Git.
You can think of it as a tool that keeps track of changes.
And we will learn how to keep track of changes on the web.
And here's a screenshot,
and you can even browse this example repository,
which I think is some of my projects.
So you can open it up in your browser and browse
and see what I was doing in 2017 and 2021.
We keep track of changes that we apply to the project.
And then whenever I want to go back
to a previous version, I can.
Some of you will also experiment with this
in your command line terminal.
Some of you will choose to do that in your editor.
So, one way to think about Git would be, it's like an undo button.
If you ever want to go back, something didn't work out, you want to try an earlier version,
you can do an undo.
But it can do a lot more than that.
And here are some questions that I have either heard or I have asked, and maybe you recognize
some of them.
for instance, oh, it broke.
Oof, hopefully I have a working version somewhere.
Or can you please send me the latest version?
Or where is the latest version?
Maybe you have asked, which version are you using?
Which version have the authors used
in the paper that I'm trying to reproduce?
Or you found a problem and you want to know
how long was it there?
And git and version control is the answer to these questions.
So it can do a lot more than just roll back,
roll back is like an undo.
One thing we will learn already today is how to branch
and merge and how to,
and then on Thursday, we will do collaboration.
But in order to do collaboration,
we have to understand branching.
It actually cannot go in Git, we have to.
And what is branching?
We try to visualize it with these cute gophers.
In Git, you can work on different features
inside the same project.
And for this, you can create
these different development branches.
So on this branch, you can implement a new feature
to give this gopher sunglasses.
And on a different branch, it could be the graduation hat.
And then you can so-called merge these changes
into the main branch, recombine them.
So we don't have to wait for each other.
Also, if you want to experiment with something,
you can create this branch, experiment,
and then you can merge it or not.
Different people can work on the same code,
same project without interfering.
And you can experiment with that idea and discard it
if it turns out it was a bad idea.
And Git is really good at that.
And finally, reproducibility.
This is really about making reproducible science,
reproducible computations and programs.
And if somebody asks you about your results
from some time ago, can you get the same results now?
And often you will want to reproduce somebody else's code
and then you are really happy if you can find
the precise version that the authors have used
in the paper you try to reproduce.
And there will be a day when you find a problem
and you will want to know
when precisely this bug got introduced.
Was it before I published a nature paper
or was it after?
I'm hoping it was after,
but at least I have a tool that tells me
when exactly it was introduced.
And we will, I will not go here into details
because we will actually practice this
in the first exercise.
You will be able to explore these tools.
You will see them in real life.
Just looking at the time,
I think we are still doing pretty okay.
Git also makes it easier for me to talk about code.
If I want to share with somebody a few lines of my project,
I can send them a link
and you can actually visit this permalink.
So if I want to tell you about this code that I wrote,
well, you can open it up in your browser
and you will see exactly what I'm talking about.
It's so much nicer than describing to you,
find a code, please go to the file, so-and-so,
search for the line that contains this text.
Oh, but please make sure that you use the version
from August, 2023.
And it's not just about software.
We can, with Git, we can version snapshots.
We can create these snapshots for software,
for scripts, documents, manuscripts, websites,
configuration files.
In the Code Refinery project,
we kind of use it for everything.
So the lesson that you see is on version control,
it's on Git.
The project website is on version control
and that will become all clear
as we show you the tools that we use
over the next two weeks.
Git is not the only tool,
but we show you a Git and GitHub
because they are the most popular versions of this.
I think I will not spend more time on the motivation.
I want to see whether there are any questions and there are not too many.
So please ask questions here, you will make really the.
We want to keep it really interactive to see.
We don't really see you in the stream.
We hope you're doing well.
There was already a question asking about why GitHub and not GitLab, for instance, so
maybe you could elaborate on that a bit.
Yes, that's a very good question.
Why do we do that?
And when you go back to the lesson overview, we have all this blue box that answers it
because it is a really good question.
And we show you GitHub, so we are not sponsored by GitHub.
We have no affiliation with GitHub.
we show you the service which is owned by Microsoft,
which is proprietary because it is the most popular
web hosting for Git.
And even if you choose other services,
like GitLab, like Bitbucket, and there are more,
and we will link to them,
it's, the probability is high that you
at least use somebody else's code that is on GitHub.
So we find it, it's probably useful for you
if you know how it works.
And all the things that we will learn with GitHub,
they also work with the other services.
And once you get the understanding of how it works,
it will be easy for you to move between those.
Good, thanks for keeping the questions coming.
Maybe just one quick comment about GitHub versus GitLab,
for instance.
My one motivation is also that most of the projects
that you will work with in the future
are most likely on GitHub
if they are publicly developed projects.
So therefore, I think it makes sense
to get you familiar with the tools that GitHub provides.
There are some very small differences in how the UI looks,
like the user interface looks on the websites,
but it's nothing that stops you from using it.
And I really appreciate the comments that come in.
We might return to those.
I will now navigate to we are almost at the first exercise.
And we will start with browsing.
So we will not make any changes yet.
But we will try to get an understanding of an existing project.
So I will go to this episode here.
Copy and browse an existing project.
please help me pasting the link to the notes.
And we will give you a, whoops.
We will give you a short intro of what this is,
and then we will send you into an exercise.
The exercise you will be able to do on your own
or with a group.
And then after the exercise, we will take a break.
And then we will discuss the findings.
Here we prepared an existing project for you and the project is, it's a recipe book.
So we will not only learn how Git works, we will also have a nice recipe book of cooking
recipes which you can then use at home in your kitchen.
Our goal is to really give you an understanding of what are the building blocks.
What is really nice about this version that we present now for the very first time is
that we give you different paths.
You can choose your own path.
You can spend everything we will do today.
You can do on GitHub alone if you want to.
So all you need is a GitHub account.
If you like, for those who don't want to do that on GitHub,
who would rather follow on Visual Studio Code,
you can then choose to follow that path.
We also offer all the steps to do also on the command line.
So really you can choose.
And in future, we plan to add more paths,
also for Jupyter, RStudio, Spyder, PyCharm.
Contributions welcome.
And we will start our very first step
and I will demonstrate it,
but you can then do it in the exercise
is I will create a so-called fork.
And fork is a new term.
And think of it as making a copy.
So I will create a copy of something called repository.
And if you want to know a little bit more
about what is really a repository,
you can even click on these
And it will take you to, we have a quick reference
and a glossary, so it will explain you
if some of the terms you never heard before,
what is a fork, what is a repository,
you can read these nice descriptions.
So I will show you that, but I want to tell you
that when you create this copy, you can then choose,
we created this recipe book, but we have two versions of it.
and you can choose which one you copy. There is this one, the recipe book,
and we have one which is called recipe book recorded.
Here on stream, I will only show the recorded one.
And this is just to make sure that those who don't want to,
if you don't want your GitHub account or anything you do,
ever to show up in any recording or stream, then choose this one.
one. But it will help us if few people work on this repository because then we have something
to show here on stream. Something that you will do then in the exercise is you can open
it up in a browser tab. And assuming that you have a GitHub account that you are logged
in and here we assume that you went through the install instructions. The first step you
will do is to forget to make a copy and I can see that three copies already exist and
I will create the fourth one. So what the first step will be to click on this fork boom
and then you can copy it into your own user account. And in this case, this is my user.
Yes, I want to keep the name. There is a description. Do I want to copy the main branch only?
Yeah, it doesn't matter. I think I want to copy everything. Why not? And we didn't even
tell you what is a branch, we will come back to that. So here doesn't matter so much, but
I will, I want to copy everything. And once I create the fork, I, it takes a few seconds.
I have my own copy of it. And you can see that this is your own copy. If on top left,
see your own username. And you can also see that this has been copied from forked from
this place. And the rest of the exercise will be, you will do it in this inside this fork.
So the exercise steps are here. And we know that you still need to learn how to do this.
So below the exercise, you can find solutions,
walkthroughs, screenshots, and you can choose your journey.
So choose your path, is it maybe GitHub?
So if you are unsure, just take the GitHub.
If you are sure you want something else,
then choose a different path.
And what we expect from you is to get an overview,
browse the commit history.
You will then see, visually see what are commits,
What are the changes?
You will see the network graph.
Maybe let me show you that so that you know what to look out for.
So something that you will see in this insights network.
You will see that there are these commits, changes, versions.
You will see that there are branches,
that there are different people.
And then we have a couple of questions for you.
Like when was a certain recipe
in this recipe book modified last?
How many changes?
Which recipes include a certain ingredient?
So you will learn how to search through our Git repository.
And you will also learn how to find out
when a certain line of code was modified last.
So somebody actually modified the guacamole recipe
and you will find out who added the cilantro to the recipe.
And then some more questions.
Can you use this recipe yourself?
Are you allowed to share modifications?
And also you will learn how to browse issues
and so-called pull requests.
And you should think about
like what this might be good for.
We have hints.
So in each of these steps, there is a hint
and then please go through.
So this is not a spoiler.
Go through the solution,
go through the walk through and try this out.
And I think we will give you 20 minutes.
And then when we get back, we will take a break.
We will take a 10 minute break after the exercise.
And then after the break,
Gregor and me will show you some of the aspects
that are the most interesting, maybe the most problematic,
and we will also react to the questions
that you have on the collaborative notes.
Here, on the bottom of the collaborative notes, where we are, what the expectation is.
So this is our first exercise.
It will be not until 55 past, but it will be up until six minutes past, and then break.
I will modify that.
Try it out, see you after the exercise,
but then we will go into break
and then we will discuss more after the break.
Let us also know how it's going
through the, during the exercise, have fun.
See you then, bye.
Welcome back from the exercise session.
Oh, I'm just waiting.
Yes, now I see that we have my screen share.
Just wanted to say that the thing I'm sharing here
on the bottom part, the exercise feedback
is really helpful for us.
It's really good for us to know whether it worked well
or whether it was confusing, whether you had problems.
This is really helpful because we don't see you.
That's the only way.
And now let's have a break.
Let's have a 10 minute break.
We'll be back 16 minutes past the hour.
And then we will discuss these things.
What did we see here in the exercise?
What did we learn?
We will talk about it and then move on to more.
See you in 10 minutes.
All right, and we are back from the break, hopefully.
I'll just try to control the streaming settings
and it's a new thing for me.
So hopefully you are back and everything is good.
I have the screen share.
Hope you had a good break.
Now I want to show you some of the steps from the previous exercise before we move on to
the next episode, because I know that there were many new things.
But it was a choice for us because we want to we wanted to really kind of throw you into
something existing.
And our hope is that when you see a commit, you will get an understanding of what it is
instead of us first describing it theoretically.
The other thing that we hope is that by providing these different paths, that it's a little
bit like if you've seen these books, which when you open it up on one side of the page
is one language, and on the other side is a different language.
and they can really help you learning a new language.
And here the hope is that if you have maybe already
been in GitHub, but you are curious about the command line,
you will recognize some of these things better
and vice versa.
But in a theory, let me show you some of the,
let's go through some of the steps now
before I hand over the mic to Gregor.
So what was the first thing I was supposed to do?
I was supposed to fork.
Here is my fork.
I was supposed to browse the commit history in my repository here are there are 25 commits,
25 changes.
And if I click this time timeline link, I can see these 25 changes.
They all have an author, they have a timestamp, they have a message.
So we have a one line summary.
So it's a little bit like a logbook.
a logbook of changes as we program our code. Also notice that each of these changes has
a unique identifier. And we will, we might, when we say commit hash, this is what we mean.
It's this is a short version of it. It's actually 40 characters. But each of these changes is
unique, we can uniquely label them. Okay, what was the next thing I was supposed to
to look at the network graph.
This is something I do very often insights at work.
And in the network,
we get this nice visual overview of these other commits.
And here the blue line and the green line,
these were different branches.
So there is a main branch,
there is a little sticky note main,
But there are other branches.
And in the next exercise already, we will learn how to create these branches.
We will also discuss what they are good for.
So here somebody created the branch, experimented with a vegetarian lasagna, and then found
that this was good and wanted to have that in the main, main branch.
So we see that developments got merged.
This is a merge point, this is a merge point,
and here's another one.
What else were we supposed to do?
If I go back, when was a file last modified?
You can actually see it here.
So this was last week.
You can see that we created this a week ago.
And if I want to know, how about the salads?
Yeah, so also here last week.
which recipe include the ingredient salt.
On GitHub, you can search for it up here,
but some of you have noticed
that it takes a little bit of time,
the very first time you search for anything,
because it needs to create this search index.
But now it will list me all the files that contain salt.
So this can be really useful
if you look through a code project
and you are not sure in which file was it,
was this error message that I'm looking for.
Okay, now let's go to the guacamole recipe.
Where was it?
It was under sides and guacamole.
And now there is this really useful feature
which has a really unfortunate name, or blame.
So that's historical reasons.
A better name would have been to annotate.
But it's so incredibly useful because it will split
my code into two halves.
On the right side, I see the recipe.
But on the left side, I see line by line
which commit modified a specific line, the last.
So now if I'm curious about who added this cilantro,
because personally, I don't like cilantro so much.
I would consider it a bug.
And much more important than who is when.
If I want to know when was this introduced,
I can click on the commit.
And this is the change that introduced it.
So this fantasy person last week introduced
In this commit, this change, this will be very useful for you in your like for reproducibility.
And I get the feedback that I was scrolling really fast and it's hard to follow where
the mouse pointer is.
So I will try to be more careful.
The good news is that everything I show now we have screenshots for this and you can find
it in the solution and in the walkthrough.
to the overview. Can I use these recipes myself? The thing that I would look for before using
anything is the license. Is there a license file? Yes, there is one. And GitHub even recognizes
it that it's a so-called CC zero license. We will learn more about licenses next week.
But if I click here on top right, I can even get some information of. No, I need to click
on the license file itself.
On top, it will give me a summary
of what are things I can do, cannot do,
any conditions, in this case, there are no conditions.
And then there are issues and pull requests,
but we will see more of issues and pull requests
on Thursday.
And some people asked,
So if I go back to my fork,
why don't I see any issues in my fork?
This is something that you can enable in settings,
but many projects decide to keep track of all the issues
and bug reports in a central place.
So I will be able to find them if I go back
to the place where I forked from.
I will go back to the so-called upstream repository.
And here I see that there is an issue tab,
there is a pull requests,
we will see what they are good for.
And issues is not only for problems,
it's also for sharing an idea.
So it can, you can even share an idea
for something before starting all the work.
Good.
I think I will,
Gregor, how about you take the screen from me and then we talk.
Now we will take it a step further and we will, instead of just browsing a repository
created by somebody else, we will learn how do we make changes to it on GitHub, but also
locally for those who want to.
Okay. Yeah, thank you. Another one. So we will now focus on the second lesson. For those
of you who want to follow the lesson yourself, you can find it here. It's on the top commit
changes. And in this part now, in the next hour, we will discuss in further detail, commits
branches, and also tags.
So you're already familiar with commits
since you've now inspected the history
of an existing repository,
but now we will discuss how to create commits.
So this is probably the Git feature
that you will use the most often,
since every time you change a file
or create a new file in your Git repository,
and you want to save it,
you want to have it available in the future as well
through the, when you go back in your history,
then you can create a git commit.
Now, usually we will start on the main branch.
So branches are different ways how to structure
or like how to have different versions of your repository.
So this is indicated here by this nice figure here
where we have this mascot of a popular programming language.
in this case, it's Go, which is lying on the main branch.
And branches can be thought of lines of development.
So nowadays, all new Git repositories,
if you create a new repository in GitHub or some GitLab,
it will be called the main branch,
but you could name it whatever you want.
In the past, it has been called master,
but because of historical reasons,
people have now decided that main should be the new default.
And in theory, you can still name it whatever you want,
but I think it's a good idea to follow
the convention of calling it the main branch
since that's what's mostly used.
Now, if we now want a whole team work on this code
or like in this painting, let's say,
it would be very difficult if it would be a real painting
to have multiple people working on different parts
of the painting at the same time.
However, with Git, since this is typically code-based
as we work with, we can create digital copies
of this branch.
In this case, we create two.
One, which is here, the sunglass branch,
and the other one, which is this graduation half branch.
And then one part of your team can then
focus on the implementation of the sunglasses.
The other one can focus on the implementation
of something different.
And then if you want later,
and you're happy with the results,
they can be merged back into the main branch.
So these branches here are sometimes also called
developer or the developing branches.
As long as they don't show any conflict,
which means that they work on the same feature
and then try to merge it into the main branch,
this will work just fine,
but we will discuss this in further detail later.
Now, the last thing which is mentioned here,
which you probably have not encountered yet
when you went through the history of the repository before
is called tags.
And these are selected commits
that you can mark as tags with a specific name,
which can be very useful if you want to have one commits
that you want to be easily accessible in the future.
So in the context of this recipe book, for instance,
could be when we decide to make a printed version of this book,
then of course, we cannot change the version, the printed version
anymore. So it would be good in the future to have committed we
can easily find which then is the same version as the one that
is printed, even though the project on GitHub might still
develop in other directions. Or to be maybe use an example,
which is more relevant for you as researchers, if you have a
manuscript or a publication that you submit to a journal, then it
could be a very good idea to create a tag for the version that
you submitted. And then once you receive the reviewer comments,
and then you change the repository which is connected to
your publication, then you can create a new tag for every new
version that you submit and then for the published one as
well. So this can be very useful for this as well. In my case,
when I wrote my PhD thesis three years ago, it was also very
useful to create tags whenever I wanted to have a version that I
I sent to my supervisor so he could read through it
and give comments on it.
So that way I could have,
I could work on my thesis,
which was written in LaTeX
and therefore easily storable on GitHub.
And then every time I have a version which,
or like a chapter which was done,
I could then create a tag on it
and then send it to someone else to read it.
So there was no problem
with having the latest version, for instance.
Maybe just one more sentence I should mention
for the branches.
I was mentioning before that this is very useful
if you have a whole team which is working on one code base,
but it can also be very useful if you work alone
since you want to experiment.
So you want to, you have an idea about a new feature
or like something which you could implement
in a better way, but you don't want to touch
the main branch since that's the one that other people
might take a look at, or also you just want to have
like a main batch which is kind of relatively clean
in its history.
So you can create a new branch,
try implementing some new code,
And if you're happy with it, you can merge it,
but if it turns out that it doesn't go the way you want,
you see that you haven't pulled through
all the steps necessary, then you can just delete it
without having to do any changes to the main branch.
Of course, in theory, you could have done this also
just to the main branch
and then kind of deleted the last couple of commits,
but I would say that this is not particularly clean.
Now, we have again an exercise set here
which takes approximately 20 minutes
where we'll now create commits
and on top of the branch, on top of the,
sorry, on top of the repository
that you've been working with in the past in a new branch.
And I will now show the first two, three steps live,
and then I will leave the remaining steps to you.
And then at the end, we can then,
after the exercises,
we can go through some of the questions.
I will do this now in GitHub,
but if there is time remaining,
I will do the same thing,
or at least show some of the parts also in VS Code.
Now, I go now to the recipe book recorded repository,
which is in the Code Refinery GitHub project.
And first of all, what I will do is to create a fork.
I've already done this.
So we just create a fork now.
I copy it to my own account.
Just a question, Gregor.
Should we, we should now watch or should we do something?
I will, everything I'm doing now is also shown
in the description.
It's just the first two steps, I thought,
so that we make sure that everyone uses
the right repository and first commit.
Yeah, and the fork people have already done
in the previous exercise, but here we show it.
It's good that we show it because just to make sure
that everybody's on the same page,
also if people join later.
Yeah, so this takes now just a few seconds.
And now we have a copy again of this repository.
And in this case, we are still on the main branch.
However, if I now want to introduce a new feature
or like a new recipe, I can now create a new branch name.
And then I click on create branch.
And this will now create, it'll copy over all the code
from the previous branch into this new one.
And the last thing I would just quickly show
is then how to create a new commit.
So in my case, I like pasta a lot,
So I want to add a recipe here so I can keep an add file.
I can copy now something into
a new file into like a new recipe.
I need to give it a name in this case
because it's a new file.
So in this case, it's a tomato basil.
recipe and I commit the changes.
And now this is the new part for you.
We can now create a commit message.
That's the one that the other one was showing just before.
So this would be this one line message.
And then we have also the option
to give a more extended description of this change.
Now, if you have a small project
and it might not be necessary
to have like a very detailed set of description here.
And in this case, I think it's not necessary
since it's kind of self-descriptive.
But in the future, if you would work with a larger project,
then they might actually have some expectations
or like some rules on how you have to create these commits.
So there might be some template
for what to add into the extension descriptions.
But in this case, we just keep it simple.
And we now see that we have, if you go now to the history,
we have now created a new commit
with the description that we chose before,
and also the new hash that was generated for us.
So this is the identifier of this commit.
Okay, I think this is enough for now.
I will now mute myself, and in 20 minutes,
we will get back and discuss some of the problems
that some people have seen,
and maybe discuss some interesting questions.
Yes, so we'll be back of 55 minutes past the hour.
And then we will do a quick summary before we take a longer break.
And your task is now to do the steps one to nine.
Again, let us know how it's going on the collaborative notes.
Ask us questions, and then we can return to the questions and discuss them here, here on
stream.
See you in 20 minutes.
Bye.
Okay, so we are back. We have five minutes before the break starts. So, there were two
questions which arose, which I would like to discuss now. And if we have some time,
I can also quickly show how to use VS Code for creating commits. The first thing was
about comparing. And one, in my view, simplest way to create two different branches or commits
is by copying the URL and just writing compare at the end.
And this will then open this interface
where we can then here choose which branches, repositories,
we want to compare.
So in this case, I will now just focus on mine.
And we can have here the main branch,
and we can compare it to the new recipe branch
that I created previously.
And this way, it will now show us
all the differences between the two branches.
So we see in this case, the only difference
is that we have the new file that I created previously,
the tomato basil spaghetti recipe in this case.
So you will see something similar
when you create pull requests,
but that's something we will discuss later in this course.
But in my view, that's the simplest way
of comparing it on GitHub itself.
So I hope this answers one of the questions.
Another question was there was some confusion
about the creating a tag.
And on GitHub, this can be some,
maybe a little bit confusing that it has a feature
which is called releases,
which is basically the same thing.
But the simplest way of creating one is just,
let's just quickly go back.
I click here on this button,
create a new release on the right.
And I can now choose a tag.
And now I need to actually write a new name into it
before I can create a new release or tag.
So I think this is the problem that arose there.
And I think it's kind of counterintuitive in GitHub.
So if I now write a new release, for instance,
then I can now give it a title again.
I can provide some more information, which I won't do now.
Then I can publish a release.
And Gregor, can I ask, can we take a step back?
So when do you use branches and when do you use tags?
And so how are they different and when would you use one or the other?
It's a very good question.
So branches I would use if I have a project where I still want to develop it or still
make changes to the project with the idea that I've eventually merged them.
I would use tags then when I'm not planning to make any changes to this version of the project,
but I want them to be easily accessible in the future. For instance, if I want to have like this,
the specific version of a manuscript that I submitted to a journal, then it makes sense
to have it as a tag in my view, because branches somehow imply that I would do some changes.
In fact, I have seen a few projects where they had like an own branch for the version that they
submitted to a journal or that was uploaded to archive for instance, which I think isn't ideal
because these branches in theory can still be changed. Now, of course, I can always go to the
history since I'm using Git, I can always check what was the date when I submitted it, which was
the latest branch back then, but I think a tag makes more sense. This would be my answer to this
question. Thanks.
Thanks.
Okay.
Shall I very briefly talk about VS Code
or shall we do that after the break?
What do you think about the one?
Just looking at the time,
I think we should do it after the break.
I'm just looking here to whether there's any questions
that we should pick up before we go into the break.
So let me thank everybody for the questions.
Let's have many more questions.
We want to be really overwhelmed by questions.
Let's take a, we will take a one-hour break.
This is lunchtime in some time zones.
We know that this is not ideal for everybody,
but in that hour, you can a little bit process
what we learned, and we will then do a recap.
And after the break, our plan is to learn
how to merge the changes that we did.
So we learn how to browse, how to create branch,
how to create commits,
but how do we get all of these developments
back into the main branch
that we will learn after the break.
We will be back in one hour.
Oh, Becky on stream.
See you then, have a good break.
And bye everybody.
From the break.
And I'm also watching the stream.
Let's see whether we appear there.
I can still see the lunch break notice on mine.
There we are.
And for those watching, we have a cat sighting.
Nice that it worked out
because cats was visiting during the lunch break
and we were hoping.
Excellent.
So we are back.
I hope you all had a good break.
Thanks for, we got more questions
on the collaborative document, thanks for those.
We thought that, so our plan is now
for the next one and a half hour for today.
We will in a moment look at how does it,
how can we create branches and commits
in Visual Studio Code.
After that we will practice
how do we combine these developments?
How do we merge the changes
and the branches that we created?
But before we go there, maybe let's take a step back
and do a quick recap.
Today we learned about Git,
about commits, branches, repositories.
Let's do a recap what these mean.
So what is a commit?
How should I think about a commit?
How can I imagine a commit?
Gregor.
I would say a commit is a new contribution
to the project, to the repository.
So it could be either a new file,
or it could be a change to an already existing file.
But I would think of it every time there's a change
or like a new contribution to the whole project,
I would think of that as a commit.
And then it can also be, maybe, sorry.
It can also be, of course,
multiple files that are changed at the same time.
So it's not one commit per file.
It could also be one new feature,
which spans over four or five files.
That's also a commit.
It's like one coherent change to the repository.
Is it easy for you to actually show a commit?
Can we click on some commit in your GitHub browser?
Sure, we can take a look at the repository
that we looked at earlier.
Yeah.
Shall I?
Let's click on one of those.
Because what I wanted to show is that
Here, everything that we see in green on the right side, these are, this is code recipes
that got added.
So I also think about commits, I think as a change, something gets added, something
gets removed.
Sometimes nothing, nothing gets removed and it can be one file or multiple files.
Then how do you, how do you think about branches?
What is a branch?
a branch is like one line of work was like one. It's one version of the
repository, typically belongs to like it also again, semantically should
reflect one new implementation. So it could be either the main branch or
master branch, which is like the kind of the default. But whenever we have any
changes then it's a new line of work and that then again belongs to like one
particular thing typically so you don't want to have a branch which has like 25
different things that have nothing to do with each other but you want to have
like one clear idea like I don't know one new feature and then finally what is
a repository what is a git repository what is inside so the repository is a
collection of files that are covered by one git project. So there's one dot git directory. We
haven't mentioned that yet, but that's like the implementation which covers the whole collection
of these files. So if I do some change at some of these files, it will be registered when I use git.
So it's basically a collection of files that, again, belong together.
Yeah, and we can think of a repository as it's like all the commits are in there, all
the branches are inside there, and also the tags, if we have any, so all the history of
the project.
And then one more question that just came in, which is something really good.
So when I want to use Git, do I then always have to connect my project to a repository
on GitHub?
And I can answer that is that no, you don't have to.
You can also use Git locally without connecting it to anything.
It can only live, if you want, the Git repository can stay on your laptop.
And it doesn't have to leave, it doesn't have to be connected to anything.
At some point, you might want to then copy it, make it available on GitHub, GitLab, and
similar services, because you want to have backup, and because at some point, maybe you
you want other people to use it or contribute to it.
And we will do a lot more of this tomorrow and on Thursday,
but you can really choose whether you want to work
on a service like GitHub
or whether you want to work locally.
And traditionally, we have given,
when we gave this lesson half a year ago and in the past,
we always started from zero, from nothing,
and we were trying to build it up in the terminal
and learn Git this way.
But this time we do it completely differently.
This time we start with something that already exists.
Maybe it's a little bit overwhelming.
There are lots of new terms,
but we start with an existing repository.
But our hope is that by browsing
and contributing to something existing,
you get an understanding of what it is.
And then the details of how do I do it in detail?
Like which commands to type?
These you don't have to remember.
You can look them up later.
Our goal is to communicate an understanding.
And now I suggest that we have a look at,
you wanted to show us how we can do that in VS Code.
And this is still the exercise from before the break.
So in there, we did, what did we do?
We created a new branch and we created a couple of commits.
Yeah, so I just very briefly wanted to show
how something like this is usually implemented
in a graphical editor.
In this case, I use VS Code as an example,
but we are not using this code
in order to endorse Microsoft products or so.
Probably if you use another type of editor,
it would look very, very similar.
And I will only show how to create a commit
and maybe some of the other features that VS Code provides
or like editors like this provide,
I will not go through all the steps.
But in this case, I'm using VS Code
with only a few extensions installed.
So it should, basically the feature that I'm showing now
is already implemented in VS Code.
It's not any additional thing that you have to install.
And typically you will see a sign like this,
which is called source control on the left side,
which covers Git.
So if you take a look at our project in this case,
it's again the same, it's the same repository
as we saw before.
And let's say we want to change the amount of cilantro here.
So we could, for instance,
now if we increase the amount of cilantro,
we've made a change to the existing repository.
And now we see that VS Code has registered
that there has been a change
and it shows it here in this source control tab.
So if you click on it, now it will list the files,
where a change has been registered.
In this case, it's the guacamole Macdon file.
And I can actually click on this file that has been created
and it will show me the differences to the previous commit.
So, or like the differences between the current state
of your repository and the last commit.
So in this case, it shows me that in this one line here,
I have changed one character.
I can also easily discard the changes
if I wanted to do it that way.
but I can also stage this file.
This is something we haven't discussed today,
but if I'm not misinformed,
this will be covered tomorrow
when we actually work with the command line,
where we stage a commit and afterwards stage a file,
and then we can commit it by writing our message.
So for instance, I can now write,
increase cilantro, you can see, of course,
then I can click on commit.
And now I've created a commit locally in VSCode.
So this can be very useful for those of you
who work with something like VSCode already,
because Git is something which is typically
already very well integrated with these tools.
At the moment, do you think this is enough,
or shall we spend some more time on VSCode?
Oh, that's good.
Yeah, we have screenshots.
Also, we understand that not some participants have different editors and our ambition is
that we then over time add instructions also for other very like popular editors and editing
environments.
But here the message is that we can do most of the most of the steps.
Okay, maybe keep it open because there is one more thing I want to say here is that
We can do most of the things in VS code that we would also do otherwise on the command
line or in GitHub.
But we hopefully have already a little bit of a visual understanding of what these mean.
So when we do a commit, it's the same thing we did before.
Sometimes you want to have a terminal.
So if there is anything that you know how to do
in the command line,
but you don't know how to do it in VS Code,
what you can do is you start a terminal inside VS Code.
And I think, so on the top bar, there is terminal.
And if you start that, it will open a command line.
And here you can then do git commands
if you are familiar to the command line
or if you want to follow the command line track.
So that's always an alternative if you feel limited
by what the source control that is offering you.
Good.
Should I take the screen from you?
Okay.
Oh, just a sec.
I need to keep it for the moment.
I need to navigate to the right thing.
Moment.
Yes, and here we are, and I have the screen share.
I'll just arrange my windows.
There was one more question that I wanted to clarify before moving on, which is
We have been using the word fork, and I think somewhere in the instructions, depending on
how you follow, we have also used the word cloning.
And I wanted to tell really tell you what the difference is.
And for the to clarify that I'm going to my I need to go to my work back to the fork.
So the difference between fork and clone is that both are copies. Both are full copies
with all the commits, all the branches, everything. But the fork stays on GitHub. It's here on
GitHub. It's not on my computer. But I copied it to my namespace. So instead of CodeRefinery,
it says my user account.
So that's a fork.
Cloning means making a copy from GitHub
or similar place onto my computer.
It's still a full copy.
The difference is that if,
when I make changes locally on my computer,
they don't automatically go here on GitHub.
I have to actively tell it to,
and we will show you how to do that.
We will practice that tomorrow.
So hopefully that clarified it a little bit.
But now let's learn something new
and we will do another exercise in 10, 15 minutes
but let me first explain what we want from you
and where we are.
So I will navigate out of here just to make sure
that we all know where we are.
Before the break, we have been committing changes,
creating commits, creating branches.
And now I will navigate to merging changes
and contributing to the project.
And you can find this also in the notes.
So this is where I am now.
And our goal for this episode,
which we will spend on for the remaining
training a little bit over one hour today, is how to merge changes from different branches.
We will see that on GitHub, it's done through something called a pull request. But the name
pull request is confusing for newcomers. And what I find really useful is whenever you
you hear pull request, think of a change proposal.
It's a proposal or a change of a branch.
We will create a pull request
and we will learn how to merge a pull request
within your own repository, within your own fork.
And then optionally, at the end,
we can try to send a pull request,
change proposal from one repository to the other.
And guess what I will try to do?
I will try to send a pull request from my own fork
towards the upstream, the central one,
the one that I forked from.
And we will already get a taste of how it is
to collaborate and contribute.
it will give us a really good basis
for tomorrow and for Thursday.
While doing it, we may, might encounter something
called a conflict.
A conflict in Git is when we modify the same part
of the code on two different branches in two different ways.
And we will, if we have time left at the end,
Gregor and me, we will produce a conflict
So it's just that you know how it looks
and we will also try to resolve it
so that you can see that it's possible
to resolve it relatively easily.
So that's our plan.
So as a reminder, in the last exercise,
we created two commits on a branch.
Let's verify that.
So I did that as well.
I was following along with the exercise
And let me show you what I did.
I'm navigating to, well, let me zoom in first,
to insights and network.
And I want to share with you what I did.
Okay, loading and syncing.
Oh, okay.
Okay, lots of people did something similar as me. What I did is I created a commit on
the main branch and I wanted to modify the pumpkin by recipe. But I also created a branch
called new recipe on which I created two commits. I had an idea for a pineapple salad and I
had a modification tonic water.
Not sure it's a good idea, but I just came up with that.
My goal now is to, I want to combine,
I want to merge this branch into this branch.
Notice how GitHub shows these branches as little labels.
Technically they work really like little sticky notes
which stick to a commit.
My goal is to combine these two, to merge these two.
I'm just reading up whether any, I forgot anything.
We will do it with a pull request.
Again, when I hear pull request, I think change proposal.
And again, we offer you three paths.
You can do that purely on GitHub.
You can also try to do that through VS code or command line.
And I just want to get you started here.
Before you sending you into the exercise,
I want to get you started.
on how to initiate this pull request.
This will actually allow me to also answer one question
that I wanted to answer.
So again, first thing you want to check,
are you on your fork?
Yes, I am.
Then, you want to navigate to the branch that you want to send the change proposal from.
So in my case, I click on the main, this will be part of the exercise, and you want to then
navigate to the branch that you want to incorporate into main, that you want to merge into main.
In my case, it's new recipe.
And then this thing changed here.
Now I know that I'm on the new recipe branch.
Somebody in the document also asked,
how do I find an overview of the branches?
I don't know where to,
I don't know how to rename a branch.
It's this thing here, this symbol.
And if I zoom out, it will change to,
it will tell me there are five branches.
And if I zoom in, it changes to a symbol.
And if you click on this one,
you can get an overview of all the available branches.
And here I could delete them or I could rename them.
So if I don't like the name, new recipe,
I could here rename the branch.
But I will not do that.
So back to my branch.
new recipe, and then to initiate this pull request process, you can click on contribute.
Contribute, open pull request, and this will be your first step in the exercise. So
back to the exercise, let me tell you what the goal is, and we will give you 20 minutes. Your
your goal is navigate to your branch, open a pull request.
Then in the pull request,
it will ask you to give it the title and a description.
Please also use the walkthrough and the solution below
because we added a checklist for you
of things that we check when we create a pull request.
And then after you have created,
Also, before you create it, browse your network.
What is the network?
It's this thing, Insights Network.
So when you open a pull request,
waiting, waiting, waiting.
So after you open it, have a look at your network,
you will see that the change is not merged yet.
Only after you merge the pull request,
have a look at the network again,
and then you will see that there is a new merge commit.
Then we have an extra step, which is
find out which branches are safe to delete,
and delete them.
And you will also see that deleting branches doesn't necessarily delete commits.
And then an optional step is, if you feel like it,
try to open a new pull request, but then this time towards the repository which you forked from.
And I will later demonstrate this. We will do that with Gecko. We will also try to actually
create, we will try to both change the same recipe in two different ways and we will see what happens
then. 20 minutes, we will be back. Is 20 minutes enough? 20 minutes will be enough. We'll be
back 45 minutes past the hour. And here, 45 minutes past the hour. Again, it will be really
helpful if you tell us how it is going. We get a status and an overview. Keep the questions
coming. Good luck with the exercise and we will then discuss afterwards. Good luck. See
you then. Bye.
Welcome back from exercise.
I actually cannot hear the jingle
if there was one on my side, but maybe there was one
and hopefully you all enjoy it.
Thanks to our colleague Matthias who created those.
My plan is now that I want to go through the exercise
but show you the key steps.
And I want to show you how we, how Gecko and we,
how we look at pull requests when we create them
and how we look at them when we merge them.
And I also want to go through this step
of deleting branches.
And then we will take a very short break.
So then only five minute break,
and then we will back for conflict resolution.
So let me go through the steps.
I'm now here, top left is my mouse.
I'm in my branch.
I will now initiate a pull request.
Let me get more space here.
And the first thing I always verify is from where to where.
So I want to go from this repository to this one.
No, I want to go to my own one.
So I will change this to my repository.
And then I verify from which branch to which branch from new recipe to main.
Yes, that's what I wanted.
I will change the title
because the new recipe is not very descriptive.
So we want to have a descriptive one-line title for this.
Also, if I remember correctly,
it was idea for a tasty pineapple salad.
Here, I can give more context, more context.
For instance, if, if we discussed this earlier in an issue, I can refer to it.
So more context, why I did this, what I did.
And then what I personally do before clicking create pull request, I normally scroll down
and I have a look, I had two commits.
Are these the one that I intended to send?
Yes.
see some commits that I don't recognize, then I stop.
I also scroll down to the bottom and I see
what is the actual change.
Is this the one that I wanted to send?
Yes, this is the one.
So this looks all pretty good.
Note that here, if I go on the little arrow,
I have a choice between create pull request
and create draft pull request.
This thing can be really useful,
but we will come back to that on Thursday.
I'm now ready to create a pull request.
Did I forget anything?
Hopefully not.
Let's create it.
When I create a pull request,
there is a new number here in the tab, pull requests.
Each pull request has a number,
so I can refer to them.
This is the pull request number one.
And before I review it and before I merge it,
I will try to reload my network graph
and it might take again a few seconds.
But what I wanted to show you is that
just by opening up a request, I didn't really,
oh, nothing merged yet.
The main branch didn't change yet.
This is still my branch.
the tasty pineapple recipe is still not on the main branch,
but now let's review it.
And when I merge a change proposal or request,
I look at the same things, the title, what is the context?
And notice that here we can even have a discussion,
you can comment on it, you can say this is a good idea,
is a bad idea or you can give ideas for changes.
More about that on Thursday.
I also look at what are the commits
and what has actually changed.
I often click here, files changed.
Yep, that looks pretty okay.
I want to have that in my main branch.
merge, merge, confirm
and now it's merged. So when I now look at the network and reload it
we will see a merge commit. We will see a new commit on main which combines these two
developments. And while this is loading and refreshing, I can already, if I now check
on my main branch, and I go to Sellads, here I can find it. Here's the one. Has this finished
in the meantime? It hasn't. Yes, here it is. Here's the merge commit. So now I have merged
these two changes.
And this is now a little bit hard to navigate
because we have now so many collaborators
that work on a very similar repository.
But this is really what I wanted to do.
So I'm happy with this.
But now I want to go one step further.
In the exercise we asked you to,
okay, scroll, scroll.
We asked you to delete a branch.
And what I will show you is that when I delete a branch,
I will only delete this sticky note.
I will not delete the commits.
The commits will still remain there
because the commits are now part of another branch.
So what we wanted you to see that deleting branches
doesn't necessarily delete commits.
And we also wanted to show you
how can you safely remove branches.
One way is I can click on the button and then it's gone because here Git knows that GitHub
knows that this has been merged.
It is safe to delete the branch.
It is safe to delete the sticky note.
But what if I forget?
I forgot.
I navigated back.
How can you find out which branches are safe to delete?
You can also leave them there.
I mean, they don't cost anything.
No problem to have them there.
But after a while, maybe you will have, I have now five branches.
After a while, you might have 50 branches and you want to do some cleanup.
So what I sometimes do is I navigate here to the branches, top left.
And this is a little bit tiny font, but this symbol here tells me that this branch has
been merged.
This one has been merged, the new recipe.
It is absolutely safe to delete it here, trashcan.
And now it's deleted.
And if I now reload this page, I would have to wait a few seconds. The commit will still
be here, but this sticky note would be gone. That's all we did with deleting branches.
And my suggestion is that we will take a five minute break and then Gregor and me will return
to step number seven and we will do a pull request, we will show you a pull request across
repositories and at the same time we will try to create a conflict, but it will be a
a conflict between two different code versions,
so it will be very friendly,
and the humans will help the programs
to resolve the conflict.
Sounds good.
Just catching up here with any questions.
Yeah, so let's take a break until the full hour,
so until, oh, I need to make that visible.
here, break until the full hour and then we show you some conflict resolution in Git directly
on GitHub. See you in five minutes. Bye.
And welcome back for the last half an hour of today.
Here we will continue on the idea of creating these change proposals pull requests on GitHub.
But now we want to take it a step further.
Because what I will try to do is I will try to create a pull request between my repository
and towards the one that I forked from.
At the same time, we will,
with Gaggle, we will try to change
the same recipe
in two different ways, and we will see what happens
and how do we deal with it,
because that can happen in real life,
that you work with somebody
and you modify a same portion of the file
in two different ways.
Let's see how Git deals with this.
Also note that when I'm now on my fork, it informs me that this branch, which is the
main branch, seems to be four commits ahead of the one that I forked from.
It's interesting because that also shows me that the fork and the so-called upstream,
they don't automatically synchronize somehow magically.
I have to, we can synchronize it, but we have to do it actively.
So until I do it, they are really separate repositories with their separate histories.
Why four commits? What are the four commits? I did two commits on the new recipe branch.
I did a different commit on the main branch, so three. Where is the fourth one? The fourth
one was the merge commit. It was the one where I combined new recipe with main. So my branch
is four commits ahead. But now I will try to create a new change. And let's see what
we do. We'll create a new branch and I will call it another recipe. It's not a great name.
It's also good if the branches are, if the branch name is descriptive. Let me take a
descriptive branch name. I personally like to call my branches with my name because then
and I can find them again.
And what are I doing on the branch?
So in this case, I will do,
I will make a change to modify guacamole.
So now everybody, please watch.
So now no more exercise.
You don't have to do the same thing.
Now, please watch and let's see if I make some mistakes.
If I make some mistakes, and please continue asking the questions, so I'm seeing the questions
coming in.
I create this branch.
What do I need to do now?
Oh yeah, here, create branch.
Yes.
And here it is.
So I'm on the new branch.
And guess what?
I will now modify the guacamole, which happens to be here, sides, guacamole.
And I can modify it directly here, the pen button on top right, edit.
What should we do with it?
So I personally am not a big fan of cilantro.
What I will do is I will reduce the cilantro amount to 0.5 tablespoons.
I like to do when I do this on GitHub is I switch on the preview so that I can see what
did I actually change showed it here I removed one I added 0.5 that looks good and now I
I want to commit the change on the branch.
This is not a good commit message
because it tells me what file I changed
but it doesn't really summarize what I did.
A much better commit message would be
reduce the cilantro amount.
And why did I change it?
Well, because I'm not a fan.
Does this look okay? Yes. Do the guacamole branch commit changes.
If I now go back to my repository on top, there is this yellow field that also some people
wondering about what is that. This is because GitHub now recognized that I have a new branch,
I modified it recently. I maybe want to create a pull request. Yes, thank you, I want to.
So this can be helpful sometimes. If you don't want to create a pull request, just ignore it.
But I really want to. And this time, I want to create the pull request not
not inside the same repository.
I really want to send it to Code Refinery recipe book.
So this looks good.
From my branch, from my repository,
towards the main branch, Code Refinery recipe book.
Let's summarize it in a title.
Reduce cilantro amount.
More description if needed.
Again, I scroll down.
What is the change?
Here is the change.
Now, how come I see all these other things?
Which I didn't modify now.
This is because my main branch was four commits ahead
and I created this new,
I created this, what was it called?
The other one modified guacamole from main
which was four commits ahead.
So what I see here is not only the cilantro change
but also all my other local changes.
This is fine, but maybe this is a bit misleading.
So it's not only the cilantro amount,
it's also plus new salad recipe.
So, here I bake together a couple of unrelated changes into the same pull request.
Not the best practice, but happens.
And now I will open the pull request.
Good.
Oh, there are already 18 pull requests, wonderful.
We will review them later.
We will maybe not have time now,
but thanks to everybody else who sent pull requests.
This is really cool
because we can now build together our recipe book.
But I suggest that now we switch the screen to Gregor
and Gregor makes a pull request,
which will also modify the guacamole recipe,
but in a different way.
And let's see what happens then.
And Gregor, you're muted.
Thanks for telling me.
So I'm now on my work of the recipe book recorded repository.
And I will now change the same recipe that Radovan has changed before.
In fact, in a previous in the previous exercise, I changed the amount already, but I will now
increase it to two tablespoons of cilantro.
Oh, go for three.
I'll go for three, okay.
So I will now make a commit.
So I will now say increase amount of cilantro.
Again, I could provide some more extended description.
It's, I don't know, I really like
So the intro, for instance, and like, of course, provide some more explanations, but for now,
that should be enough.
I will now commit the changes.
So I've created now a new commit.
So if I go back to my repository, I will see now again, if I click on commits, oh, sorry,
that's the wrong branch, my bad.
So I go now to the change cilantro branch.
And I take a look at the commits, it should appear now.
And it does.
So increase amount of cilantro, that's fine.
And now I compare pull requests.
Create a pull request.
So I go and choose the repository I want to
merge my changes to.
So this would then be co-definery recipe book recorded.
That's fine.
I enter the main branch and I do it from my local branch
here, which is in my namespace.
And I used to change cilantro branch.
So I can now say, again, I should also provide a title
which is more descriptive.
So increase cilantro in,
Oh, remind me of the way, it's okay.
Guacamole recipe.
Then I quickly check the changes.
In this case, I have two commits.
One in the first, which was in the previous exercise,
where I reduced it, now I increased it.
And here, down here again,
I see the changes actually in the files directly.
So this is what I want to merge.
And I can see here that I increased the amount of cilantro
by free. So I will now create the pull request and then I will give the screen
back to the other one.
All righty, I will take the screen and let's see how it looks on my side.
Just a sec.
Here I have it.
And I'm now looking at the, that's not my fork, that's the central repository.
And I clicked on the pull requests map, there are 21 open, 22 now.
Thanks to all of you, we will look through them and merge them.
Maybe some of you tried to merge these and now you realize that you cannot.
And this is a bit by design, but now because now only the code refinery team has the permissions
to merge and modify this repository, but don't worry, we will on Thursday, when we really
practice collaboration, we will create exercise repositories where you also have permissions
to review and merge and modify those.
So then he will also practice being the person
who is reviewing these changes.
So now I want to focus on two changes.
One is the one that I created
and the other one is the one that Gregor created.
And now I will do something which is not super nice.
I shouldn't really review my own changes,
but now for the sake of time,
I don't want to switch too much back and forth.
I will view my own change.
And of course it's excellent,
but I will still double check here.
Is this what I really wanted?
What's happening here?
Lots of changes, but looks pretty okay overall.
I will merge it into main branch.
And now it is, is it safe to delete?
Yes, it's safe to delete.
Now it is on the main branch in the central repository.
And that worked.
But let's see what happens
when I now try to merge Gregor's change.
This one, the pull request number 39.
Here we go.
Something is different here.
And it's this one.
It doesn't let me merge.
I can't really click here.
Because there are conflicts.
And why are the conflicts?
Because on two different branches, we have changed the same portion in two different
ways.
The git now doesn't know which one do we want to keep, like, do we want to keep the one
that is now on main?
Or do I want to keep the one that,
the change that comes in from this other branch?
And we have to help get deciding.
It's really good that it stops here
because it doesn't, it will not just accidentally
let Gago override my changes.
So it stops here, it needs some human advice.
So let's try that together.
And you can do it in many different ways,
but we will try it here directly on GitHub.
And Gregor will help me.
So I click first on resolve conflicts
just to see what is the conflict.
And it doesn't now show me all the...
If you remember, I have changed a couple of files.
I changed guacamole, but there was also some pineapple salad
and there was some other change.
But we only conflict in this one file
and we only conflict in this one portion.
These that I see here, these symbols
are so-called conflict markers.
They tell me where is the conflict.
And the conflict is between main
and between the main branch and the change cilantro branch.
On the main branch, I reduced it to 0.5.
On the change cilantro branch,
it was changed from one to three.
And we need to decide now.
And I will now not take my own version,
but I will take this version.
And the way to resolve a conflict is, and whether you are on GitHub or whether you are
in your editor, that's to decide which version and then don't forget to remove these markers
also.
They should not stay there.
So I will, I decide to keep three, remove these markers.
And once we are happy, mark it as resolved.
And now what we don't see because I'm zoomed in is that on the top right, there is a button
commit merge.
I also, this resolution needs to be committed to be a new commit that decides between the
two versions.
the merge.
So these were Gregor did in fact two commits.
One was this one.
One was this.
Where does this come from?
This was my resolution commit.
The conflict resolution created a new commit because it merges between Gregor's branch
and the main branch.
Now, before I merge it, I want to review
what did we get at the end.
Files changed.
At the end, it's changed from 0.5 to three.
Are we happy?
We are happy.
Let's merge.
This was a relatively easy conflict.
Sometimes, the conflict will require that you actually talk to the other person and
discuss with them on maybe you schedule a video call, but at least now you know technically
on how to tell Git which version you like better.
Back to the lesson, I will now scroll down to the summary.
What did we learn?
And what did we learn in this lesson?
What did we learn today?
We learned how to browse a project,
how to create commits and branches.
And in this episode, we learned how to merge them,
how to merge two branches together.
This is the basis of collaboration.
We will use this a lot on Thursday.
And it's really useful also for your own work.
If you want to put something unfinished
finished or something that you aren't sure about
on a side branch and not on main.
But when you are new to Git, it's also fine really
to start just with one branch, create commits.
Better to many commits than to few commits.
They don't have to be beautiful.
And same with pull requests.
If I may quickly mention this one question
which came up in the document, what to do?
Can I, if I have like a pull request
and I only want to merge half of it,
I think the best strategy is to create
many small pull requests if you are able to separate it
so that this situation doesn't arise.
So in the ideal case, you have one pull request
for one encapsulated feature or one change.
Yeah.
Instead of one huge one, yeah.
Exactly, so at the beginning, start using these features.
then later what is a good practice
is to not put unrelated things into a commit
because it is hard to separate unrelated things.
Also don't put too much into a pull request.
Not unrelated things into a pull request
is something I've done here.
So what if the guacamole recipe change was good
but my pineapple salad wasn't good?
So then suddenly it becomes a little bit difficult
to separate the one from the other.
So what would it be nicer is to create
two separate pull requests, which create nice little units.
A small pull request is easier to review
than a gigantic one.
Nobody wants to look through 20,000 lines of code,
but at the beginning, it's good to use them
and make it nicer later.
So don't let the beautiful commits
and the beautiful pull requests
be the enemy of just good enough.
Looking at other questions, we have nine minutes left.
We want to use it now.
We can do a little bit more discussion,
but one thing we should not forget is to,
we would like to hear feedback from you.
Maybe somebody can paste our feedback form
into these documents.
So what we would like to hear from you is
what went well today
and what should we improve today?
So what should we remove, change, do differently?
This is very important for us
because we look at the feedback, we use it.
If there is something we can improve already
until tomorrow, we will do.
And I hear that there is cut visible on the screen
on the stream and even audible, but I don't hear that.
So that's too bad for us instructors, Gregor,
but apparently there are some cut sidings on stream.
So please, now that I share it, please give us feedback.
Was it, how did it go?
Was it too fast, too slow?
Tell us one good thing about today.
This feedback is anonymous.
What was good about today?
Tell us one thing that we should improve for next time.
And next time is maybe already tomorrow.
Any other feedback welcome.
And while the feedback is coming in,
I want to look at, is there any other question?
Maybe the one about how exactly are conflicts happening?
For example, what if we change lines?
What if the change lines I moved
could be considered different lines
and therefore different entries,
even if they are changing the same thing?
That's an excellent question.
And Git is really smart about this.
it doesn't look at line numbers.
It uses some really smart algorithms to decide
which parts are the same thing,
even as the code evolves,
even across file renames.
So it is really smart.
It is often not a problem.
You will probably not see it
when working just on your own.
You might see it when collaborating.
When it happens, it's not a big deal.
You now know how to resolve it technically.
We will also on Thursday, when we do collaboration,
we will discuss on what are good strategies
so that we can avoid conflicts from even happening.
And in one sentence, the strategy would be
keep branches small, keep commits small,
don't do too many things at the same time,
then the likelihood that there will be conflicts is smaller.
We are doing amazing with time, five minutes left, yes.
Did you comment on how we do very similar things tomorrow,
but with VS code and command line and locally?
That's a great prompt here.
There was a question comment about that.
That's a great.
So let's, with everything we did today,
how will that connect to tomorrow?
Tomorrow we will learn how to clone a repository
and work locally.
Some of you have done it already.
Tomorrow we will take this recipe,
make a copy onto our computer
and learn committing, branching, merging locally.
locally, we will, this is possible either in VS code or command line.
But even if you don't, if the command line doesn't work for you, you don't want to install
VS code, please still come tomorrow.
Because the other episode tomorrow will not.
You can do them only on GitHub if you want to.
So the second episode will be we will do some of the repository browsing and history inspection,
but a little bit more in depth than today.
We will study a repository that we don't know.
It's written by somebody else, but we will try to figure a few things out about it.
This is a very typical situation.
And then tomorrow the finale will be to turn your own project and it doesn't have to be
a real project where you don't have to share your project
that you have on a computer,
but we will create your own example project,
but learn how to turn it, make it a Git repository
and how to share it on GitHub or GitLab.
And what would be the next steps
if you want to make your project citable.
So these are the goal for tomorrow.
We will then tomorrow also talk a bit more about the balance.
What is a good balance when you start using it of where to start, how to progress,
and what are typical things, typical problems that you want to avoid?
Of course, you're already welcome to browse these and then tomorrow come with lots of questions.
questions. So, if someone has tried the VS code track today. Are there is tomorrow something
different than today. Do you learn new things. Yes, there will be. So, if you have done this
already today then the first episode, there will be some repetition but I think it doesn't
harm, to get it a little bit more into our muscle memory, there will be something new
and that is, we will take a closer look at what is the difference between a local branch
and a remote branch. And we got a few questions about it today, we didn't really talk about
it by design, but tomorrow we will hopefully give an understanding that you see the difference
between what is a local branch and remote branch. This is something that confused me
a lot when I started using it. So that will be different already in episode one.
Yes. Okay. And if someone starts from tomorrow and hasn't been here today, I guess that works
fine. Also, that's fine. No problem. Invite your friends and so on.
Exactly. So even if, or even if you were here today and everything failed, and I don't know
you don't find the repositories again, please come tomorrow. You don't need to have the
things from today for the tomorrow's exercises. We invite your friends. It's really fine and
welcome to join just for a day or just for an episode. And thanks a lot for the feedback.
One thing that was really good and one thing to improve.
Yeah, and we should thank Radovan for this latest lesson redesigned.
And Richard.
Well, yeah, but I was gone on the weekend when Radovan was working on it.
But anyway, it was a great effort to rewrite it this new way that introduces it with GitHub as the main flow, main path, and the other things there.
there.
So we're really looking forward to see
how this goes for future days.
And you can all help us contributing.
We know that there are some rough edges.
If you go into the git history of the lesson,
you will see that there has been some weekend work
and late changes.
So this will evolve as we go.
But now, I mean, in this workshop,
we learn how to contribute to other people's projects
and your contributions and issues and ideas are really what makes this go.
Yeah. So, I guess there's no new questions. So, you can expect videos to be processed
by later this evening.
If you want to be more involved, consider
joining the Code Refinery chat and asking what you can do.
We've got different stuff that people can look at.
Anyway, yeah, anything else or?
Yeah, we need more cats tomorrow. So that's a clear takeaway here from the feedback.
But I think I'm happy. I don't know, Gregor, did we forget something?
All right. No, I think we went through most of the important things that we were planning to
go through anyway. And we can go through the documents today in the afternoon and see whether
we missed anything. And maybe if there is time, we can discuss it tomorrow.
Yeah. Thanks so much, Gregor. I'm looking forward to teach with you again then on
on Thursday, tomorrow, or we will be with Björn.
Really looking forward to.
Yeah, thanks everybody.
Also, thanks to all the people answering questions,
working in local rooms.
Thanks to Samantha for the intro.
There are lots of people who make this happen.
Have a nice afternoon.
See you all tomorrow.
Okay.
Thanks so much.
Bye.