Thanks everybody helping also in the document.
Maybe we should start with introducing the instructors.
So my name is [Name],
teaching here today from Tromsø, Northern Norway.
Really looking forward to talk more about Git.
Git is one of my really favorite tools.
I use it every day.
And this workshop is one of my favorite things in the year.
And with me is [Name] from [location].
Hello, my name is [Name].
I'm working at NTNU.
So I've been with the Code Refinery project
almost from the start.
So I'm looking forward to teach today.
And what I should do is I should take the screen share.
Give me a second.
And we will start with a little bit of recap
before we go into the first exercise.
We have today three exercises planned.
And I will just arrange my screens.
This page that I'm sharing is the introduction to Git
where we started yesterday.
If you joined today, no problem.
We will get you up to speed.
You can navigate the page either on the left side.
Now, just for the readability, I will zoom in
and I will tell you what did we do yesterday.
Yesterday, we started with motivation
And then we did three episodes, three exercises.
One was to copy and browse an existing project.
And if you don't have it, no problem,
you can copy it today.
We have then instructions on how you create this copy,
what you have to create the fork.
And then we practiced creating commits
and creating branches.
And finally, yesterday, we practiced how to combine these changes in through merging.
And many of you have even sent so called pull requests towards the upstream repository.
And this was a start to so you have seen how collaboration essentially works.
and we will return to collaborating tomorrow.
The plan for today is we have three sessions planned.
Again, three episodes, three exercises.
One will start in 15 minutes.
And here today, we will move from the web to our computer.
We will clone a repository to our computer and work locally.
And then you can choose your favorite track.
you can work with VS Code, RStudio, Command Line,
and hopefully in the future, we can offer even more tracks.
In order to work locally,
you will need to have an editor,
and we have recommended in doubt,
go for VS Code or the Command Line configured.
So this is something that you have hopefully done
before the workshop.
If not, not a big problem.
you can then during the exercise sessions,
look at the section,
how to configure Git for your command line
or for your editor.
If you use VS Code, there is very little to do.
Basically download, install, and you are ready to go.
So I will not go through this episode,
but you know that it is there if you need it.
And you might need it in the first exercise.
we will, so then we will clone, work locally.
Some of you, those of you who yesterday worked
in a command line or in an editor,
you have already worked locally.
So there will be a little bit of repetition,
but there will also be new things.
So then try to focus on the new things that come up.
Try to focus on seeing the difference
between what is a local branch,
what is a remote branch, how does it work?
And then we will do a little bit more archaeology.
We will give you a puzzle to do archaeology in somebody else's repository.
And there we will practice some of the history inspection commands that we have already seen
yesterday.
Then we will take a longer break.
And in the third session, we will take a different project.
It can be your own project,
or it can be your own new fantasy small project,
which is not on Git.
And we will practice how do we turn,
make it a Git repository,
and how do we share it on services like GitHub,
which is incredibly important that we all know how to do it
in order to make our code findable,
but also in order to have backup.
And as always, the instructors, we are watching these collaborative notes.
The more questions we get, the better it will be.
I have a different screen where I have it open at all times.
And the best way to interact then is to ask questions and comments at the bottom of the
document.
And [Name] and me will watch this and some of the questions we will then also discuss
see on stream. We really look forward to that. So please keep them coming.
And now I recommend that let's go into this part here, cloning our git repository and
working locally. And let's start with our let's get you started there. And also a little
with a little recap. So I will go in here and you find the link at the bottom of the
collaborative nodes. Our objectives are we are able to clone a repository from
the web and modify it locally. We can do the same things we did before, like
committing, branching, merging, but locally. But those of you who have done
that already, we will also get a feeling for what are remote branches and remote
repositories.
And little recap, what is a git repository?
What are we cloning?
A git repository contains all the files
and directories of a project.
It has a complete history of all the changes
to these files and directories.
And each commit is a snapshot of the entire project
at a certain point in time.
And it has this unique identifier and we call it the hash.
So if I go into, this is my practice repository
from yesterday, and if you don't have it yet,
no problem, you can then create it later.
And what I meant with hash are these, this thing here,
this is my latest commit, and it has the identifier
9C2A7E6, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
It's unique.
And now if I wanted to publish my work in an article,
I could say that I have used this repository
and I have used this particular version.
But you will probably tag it
and not use the hash, I guess.
Great point, because for humans,
for computers, this is nice,
but for humans, it's hard to remember these characters.
So, we often like to create so-called stack or a release.
So, what I would probably have done,
and let's just, let me just do it.
So, this is not something you need to do.
You can try it later on your own repository,
but what I will do here, I will create a so-called,
what GitHub calls release.
But from the Git perspective, it's really a tag.
And here, it's nothing else than creating
a little sticky note with something that humans understand,
which sticks to that commit.
Let me create it quick.
So create a new release.
I'm here with my mouse on the right side of the screen.
Create a new release.
Here I can decide from where.
If it's from main,
it means it will be from the latest commit
that is currently on main.
How should I call it?
I don't know, version 1.0.
First version of my project, first working version of my project with many nice recipes.
Okay.
I can give it a title if I want to.
Publish release.
But now this is what humans can remember more easily, and this is what I can put in my manuscript.
But it's really just a sticky note with a little bit of metadata that points to a particular
commit.
And the typical metadata would be release notes, a short summary of what has changed
in 1.0 compared to 0.9.
The source code is easily available now
since it's a zip door.
Yeah, that's nice.
So it creates this archive for me,
which people can download.
So they don't even have to know how to use Git.
They don't have to know how to clone.
We will learn that now,
but they can download this directly.
Now, whether this is enough to be findable
and reproducible for the next 10 years
is a different question.
So what we will do next week is we will show you
how you can go a step further,
because I could publish my work,
but I could still delete this repository
and then it will be hard to find.
A nice next step could be to make this citable,
create a digital object identifier and make it persistent
to make sure that this never disappears.
But we will learn that next week.
[Name], how do you use Git in your work?
I use it for almost everything. I try to be totally text based, just only use simple text
and simple text editors. And then it is very useful for taking versions of what they produce.
It goes for written text, configuration files, and code.
What do you find, or what did you find difficult
with Git when you started?
What was the most surprising, difficult thing?
The more, I think branching and merging,
getting a readable graph out of the branches
of the branches and then be at the right place to merge.
So I've done a little bit of backtracking
for getting graphs that are more readable.
What about you?
Yeah, thanks.
What I found difficult at the start
was it was never so clear to me.
Okay, I learned how to make omits
and I could create commits and branches,
but I didn't know whether they stay on my computer
or whether they travel somewhere else.
No, that was never very clear to me.
And I think we will clarify that today.
So we will create commits,
but we will see that everything we do locally
stays locally on the computer,
unless you tell it to go somewhere else.
So something we will see
is that we will have to actively push changes
if I want to publish them from my computers
to somewhere else.
And also if the GitHub repository gets new changes,
they don't automatically magically travel to my computer,
I have to actively pull them.
So we will learn about pulling changes, pushing changes.
And in a little bit, we will do a clone.
And maybe one thing we could try is that
And just to show you what, how this works, maybe one of us could do it in the terminal
and the other person could try it in VS code.
And where we clone our, or I can show both, it doesn't matter, where we clone the exercise
from yesterday so that you have a starting point on your computer.
And then the rest will be, there'll be an exercise with a couple of steps.
And like yesterday, there is no expectation that just by reading the exercise, you know,
the solution, the solution and the walkthrough is part of the exercise.
And then also in the solution and walkthrough, you then find also discussions and some thoughts.
I'm also looking here at the questions, anything we should lift to general discussion.
So there are some questions about releases,
but they are answered.
Should I show how to clone just to get us started?
How to do a clone in the terminal
and how to do it in VS Code?
Yeah, I think that's a good idea.
Then we'll get a good start.
Yeah, so that is, you don't have to do it now.
So for those listening now, it's part of the exercise,
but to show you what, what that means and what's going on.
And I will take
I will take the, my example from yesterday. If you don't have it, no problem. You can,
it is forked from another repository. And if you don't, you can fork it again. If you,
if you haven't done it yesterday, you can, there is a step that shows you how to do that.
and I want to now clone it to my computer.
Cloning means copying everything,
but this time not from one user space
into another user space,
but cloning means copying everything from now GitHub
down to my computer here.
I will show you first terminal in the command line,
terminal in the command line.
And then I will show you that in VS code.
And I will be a little bit clumsy in VS code.
It's not something I use every day.
I use the command line every day, but that is good.
It will slow me down a little bit.
I will show you how I clone.
And down here, hopefully you can see my command history.
The way I clone is that there is this green button here.
And here you can decide how you want to clone.
And if you are unsure,
that's, but then you can find the answer in this,
whoops, zooming out up here,
configuring git command line and editor.
So this is part of the configuration.
In my case, I have done that and I will choose SSH.
it's a way for me to authenticate that.
If you are in for this first exercise,
this one will work as well.
Sure, it doesn't matter which of the two.
What I do is I copy this address
and then on the command line,
and we have the instructions, it's git clone,
git clone the address.
And then where do you want to clone into?
For instance, recipe book, and this would create a new directory on my computer called
recipe book.
If I leave it out, then it will create a directory called the with the same name as the git repository.
I will show you that on the command line, you can practice later if you want to, but
you can choose your own journey.
Here, okay, I received lots of objects and deltas.
It's just, and now I have a new directory
on my computer called recipe book recorded.
And in that directory,
git log one line,
I have a, I have a git repository.
All the commits are there.
All the branches are there.
One interesting thing you can try later is that if I type git branch to see which branches
do I have on my computer, I only see main.
That might be surprising because on GitHub, zooming out, on the GitHub, I have four branches.
But part of the exercise is to find out what's going on there.
They are all four branches are actually on my computer, but I don't want to spoil it.
So in the exercise, you will see the difference between what is a local branch and what is
a remote branch.
And now let me try the same thing in VS code.
Should I try it or [Name], do you want to?
No, I'm more due to, I'm not that used to VS code.
Ah, yeah, me neither.
I was hoping you would take it, but let me try.
Okay, let me see.
So I will just navigate out of this.
And now I will have a sneaky peek at our instructions
on how to do that.
But let me first try, I will make this,
Let me, I will start VS Code.
I started by typing code
and where do I want to start it?
Code dot.
But you might start VS Code differently,
but that's how I started.
I just want to start it in exactly this place.
Ooh, it's very small.
Let me
zoom in.
Ooh, okay.
I see that there is this other repository,
but I don't want to be here.
I want to start something new.
I will start a new window and I will close this one.
No, I'll close everything.
Okay, let's try again.
And then we will choose exit.
Yes, I did the wrong thing.
No problem.
I wanted to do new window and in the other one,
I should do close window.
Here we go.
I have kind of an empty looking VS code.
And now what should we do?
We should, one way to clone it is to go under start.
Where is start?
There is no start.
I hope I see something here on the source code control.
Aha, source control clone repository.
No update right now.
I will go on clone repository
and now I can choose where do I want to clone from
And will it work if I do github.com,
past, cp, book.
You could just paste the URL, I guess, in there.
I could, I could.
So from here, from the green button now?
Yeah.
I will try what happens if I do,
if I just type it from the browser.
I'm curious whether it will work.
I think it might recipe book record that enter.
And now I think it asks me, where do I want to clone into?
So I know that this is outside of your screen.
Where do I want to go into course?
And I will give it a different name.
I know you cannot see this
because I don't want to reveal everything on my hard drive.
Oh, I will call it recipe book VS code.
create and select this repository. And now I got an error message.
So that doesn't work what I wanted to do. Okay.
Let's try again. Let's do it properly. So now clone repository. And now instead I should do
I should take it from here. HTTPS copy this clone repository here.
here. Yes. And now again on into the right place.
Why did you just exit the pass over SSH this time?
I wasn't sure whether it would work with SSH with the VS code. It might. I think it depends
how people set it up. Yeah. And now it will. Now it asked me, would you like to open the
the cloned repository, yes.
Open it.
And here it is on my VSCode.
And when I go on source control,
somewhere here I can see,
no, I need to click on a certain file.
I can see
somewhere the commits.
I should have practiced better how to do it on VSCode.
But you can do it in the exercise.
The essence is that now I have the repository
on my computer and you can choose
the VS code or command line or RStudio.
Here, one of the three.
And what are your goals?
Your goals are decide which repository you want to use.
want to clone your fork or the original repository,
actually both will work because in this case,
we are not pushing any changes.
We are only cloning.
We will learn how to create a new branch locally,
how to create a new commit, how to switch between branches,
how to merge them locally.
And for those of you who have done that already yesterday,
focus more on the question of where are the remote branches?
How does it work?
And down there, you'll find more notes on this.
Once you create these commits and branches locally, also compare the situation locally
and on GitHub.
And you will see there is a difference.
So all the changes that you create on your computer, you will see that they don't travel
to GitHub.
We will have to actively push them.
We will do that later today.
Okay, before we go into exercise, just having a quick look at the notes, whether anything
was confusing.
Yes, should be cloned to origin repository or the forked version if you have it clone
your own.
But both will work here because we are not all the changes that we do, we only do them
locally.
So it doesn't matter whether we are able or not
to apply the changes on GitHub.
All the rest of the exercises today will not depend on this.
It will only depend on the techniques.
So even if you mess it up completely,
it's not a problem for the remaining two exercises.
Good, we have allocated 25 minutes,
which would bring us to,
we will be back after the exercise at the full hour.
And after the exercise, we will play the jingle,
we will say hi, and we will remind you
that there is a break afterwards.
So after the exercise, we will take a 10 minute break.
So exercise until the full hour, 25 minutes.
Ask lots of questions.
We will try to answer as we go.
And in the meantime, I will practice with VS Code.
And we will then afterwards, after the break later,
show you maybe some of the tricky parts
and we can discuss them.
Okay, have fun with the exercise.
See you briefly at the full hour for the jingle
and the break start.
Bye.
And I think we are back.
I was just trying to remotely control [Name]'s studio, so hopefully that worked.
We are back on stream here, back from the break, and back from the exercise.
So hopefully that went well.
We will see if we can lift some of the many good questions
on the document here for discussion.
I wanted to talk about two things before moving on.
One is about branches.
Because now that we have cloned the repository
and I will try to show that here on VS Code,
I was curious about what branches do I see.
So on my lower left corner of VS Code,
if I click on the main branch,
during the exercise,
I create this one where I added French toast,
but then I see my local branches,
main, French toast, something else,
but then there are also these origin branches.
And these are branches that exist on GitHub.
These are so-called remote branches.
And here, VS Code tells me that remote branch
pointing to some commit,
remote branch pointing to a different commit,
another remote branch.
So actually, I can actually see them here.
And in VS Code, if I switch to a remote branch,
let me maybe switch to the origin [Name]/lasagna.
This is one that I created two days ago.
If I switch to it, so if I click on it here,
So let's see what happens.
It created a local branch for me.
[Name]/lasagna.
This is a local branch and I can make changes to it.
And if I make changes to it, you will then also see
that there will be a button that allows me
to publish these changes back to GitHub.
And in VS Code, this happens automatically for me.
If you tried it on the command line,
and let me test this now inside VS Code, new terminal.
In the command line, maybe you have tried to do git branch.
Git branch will tell you
what are all the branches that you have.
Well, actually, what are the local branches that you have.
And I have now four local branches.
But in order to see all the branches, you really have to do git branch dash dash all.
The remote branches, they are read-only.
I cannot really modify them, but the way to modify them was what I did in VS Code
by creating a local version of them,
which, where I can do my work,
and then later, if we want to,
we can push these changes back.
We will practice that later.
One thing that I was trying to find out during the exercise,
but I don't know the answer, is in VS Code,
how do I know, now that I have a clone of a repository,
how do I know where I cloned from?
And I admit that I don't know how to answer that.
I know how to do it in the command line.
So the way I would ask in,
and if you know, please give us comments.
On the command line, I would type git remote verbose.
So whenever I forget where did I actually clone from,
it will tell me that there is,
let's make it a little bit more readable,
it will tell me that there is a remote called origin,
which is, and this is the address where I cloned from.
And this is the shortcut for the address.
So whenever on the command line,
whenever you want to talk about the address,
I can use these interchangeably.
And there is a question on the document, what is origin hat and what is origin main?
And where did we see that?
Was this when I did this, maybe a hat is in Git, whenever you see head, it's, it's the
position where you are right now.
And this makes sense for those of us who remember still tape recorders, because they have those
tape and there is a recorder head.
And you can think of version control as recording changes.
And this is the position of the recording recorder head.
It's maybe less intuitive for those
who have never seen a cassette tape.
But what is this origin hat?
That refers to the default branch on GitHub.
So the default branch on GitHub,
I can see from this that it is main.
So this is not very technical, but I just wanted to answer the question.
What else should be clarified before moving on?
Oh, there was no jingle.
Oh no.
Okay.
I'm still practicing using these remote controls to the studio.
Thanks so much for these questions.
Maybe we are ready then to...
I will move this out of my way, the VS Code, but we'll return to it.
And I will now navigate to the next episode, which is inspecting history.
And we want, that's our goal now for the next 45 minutes.
Here we are still working locally.
Again you can choose VS Code, Command Line, RStudio.
You can also do it on GitHub.
So if you prefer not to work locally,
this is an exercise that you can do on GitHub.
We will work with a repository that we don't know yet.
It's written by somebody else.
And here are a couple of the toolbox
that we will practice here.
Some of it we have seen yesterday,
like how to navigate through our existing repository.
And just as a fun warmup,
We can try this git history browser.
This is just a fun tool to written where you can visualize the history of a project.
And the repository that we will practice with is on GitHub, it's a it's a Python project
doesn't matter.
It's called NetworkX.
I will open it up here.
And for the moment only watch you will, you will have the chance to practice in a little
bit.
So, this is a code that does some network analysis in Python.
The fact that it is in Python is not of importance for our exercise.
This is a repository with over 7,000 commits.
And one fun thing I will try here is to open this page.
And here with left and right keys, this is the readme file.
So if I navigate left and right,
I can navigate through the history of this README file
and we can see how lines were added and removed
and how things are changing.
I really like how this visually shows
the evolution of a file along a git history.
So that's just a warm up.
We will learn or
re-practice some really useful techniques.
One is to search
through our Git repository.
And maybe here I should take a step back and say that
this is a different repository.
So if you are on VS Code,
make sure to
open a new window with a different project.
And maybe there's a better way than what I did.
So we are not anymore in our recipe book.
We want to really study this NetworkX project.
And if you are in a command line, like I'm down here,
make sure that you are not inside an existing Git repository.
So if you are, then step outside,
we will create, we will make a new clone.
And I will now, I want to show you these,
some of these commands here in
I will show them in the command line, but you can then later try it out on the command line
or try it out on GitHub, VS Code, RStudio
and the first step will be to make a copy
except if you are on GitHub, you don't have to copy anything, you can really just
use their repository, so I will create a copy, the clone
and again we clone everything
I have to make sure that this is readable.
It takes a few seconds.
Because now suddenly it's a lot of objects, it's a lot of commits.
And here I'm in this repository.
The latest commit is 2e-ce-02.
Is that the case?
Yes, the latest is 2e-ce-02.
And some of the tools that you will practice that will be super useful is if you look for
a certain text in the project.
For instance, I want to find all the fixmes in this project, and you can even search case
insensitive git grep-i fixme.
It will list me all the files that contain the word fixme in this file and in this file
and in this file, etc.
This can be useful if you are looking for an error message and you don't know where
in the code, is it crashing?
Then you will learn how to look at the particular commits.
So if I want to have a look what happened
in a particular commit, for instance, this one,
I can look at it with git show.
If I know the identifier,
you don't even have to type the whole identifier,
Just the beginning of it is enough.
I will try that.
And it will show me when did it happen.
So this was a commit from 2020.
And what happened in this commit?
Good.
And the same, if you want to navigate to the same thing,
the same thing exists on GitHub.
So here's the same commit.
What was there before, what was there after?
Then yesterday we have seen this super, super useful way of annotating a file, which on
GitHub is called blame, unfortunate naming, but you can then try it in also in the command
line which will show you line by line when was each line of the code modified last.
And then something we have tried yesterday is to browse the history of a particular file
and see how does a particular file look, how did it look in the past.
And you will practice how to do that on GitHub or command line or any of the other tools.
But now let me let me explain you the exercise.
So in the exercise, your first step will be to make sure that you are not inside another
git repository.
And here is how you want to check.
And I think we didn't tell you how to go out of it.
But I see the question on the collaborative notes.
So thanks for asking that.
And then if you work locally, you will clone this example repository.
In this case, the HTTPS protocol will work.
If you're on GitHub, you don't have to clone anything.
And then we want to go one step further, and we want to make sure that we all work on a
well-defined particular version of this project, which happens to be, this is actually a tag,
it's a release.
So you will navigate your copy to that particular release.
And once you have done that, we have some puzzles for you here, and also a solution.
you will first need to, in this project that we don't know,
with 7,000 commits, you want to find where in the code
is a file that contains this text,
logic error in degree correlation.
And we can imagine that this, maybe we try to run it,
and maybe this is an error that we got.
And then we want to know where does it fail.
Then once you find it, try to find out
when was this line of codes last modified or edit
and find the actual commit that modified that line.
And you can do that with this annotation
with the blame function.
Here is not about who did it.
It's more about when did it happen?
What happened in that change?
And then have a look at this commit
with if you are on the command line, use git show.
If you are on GitHub, try to navigate to that commit
and see what happened in there.
And sometimes you want to then be able to,
if you find, okay, there was a change happened in the past,
I want to be able to get my project back to the state
of how was it back then when this commit was created.
So try to create a branch, not from main,
not from the latest commit, but a branch from the past,
from that commit in the past where this line was modified.
And then bonus question is,
well, how would you bring your code
to the version of the code
right before that line was modified?
We can imagine that maybe this was a mistake,
not in this case,
but if you know that a certain commit in the past
changed the behavior,
you want to be able to navigate your project back to
How was it just before?
And then you want to be able to navigate back to main.
So this is the goal of this exercise.
For those of you who have time left
and are on the command line
and want to try something more advanced,
you can even read up, read on this optional part
where about git bisect.
So the git bisect part is optional.
Our goal for the exercise is this green box, steps one to five.
And we have allocated 20 minutes.
Yeah, 20 minutes,
which means that we will be back 50 minutes past the hour.
I'm just now checking also with my co-instructor
if this was somehow clear
or if we should clarify any step
before sending people into the exercise.
So this is an exercise you can do in groups,
you can do on your own, you can do locally on your computer,
or you can do it, I think you can do all the steps
also purely on GitHub.
Please let us also know how it's going,
like whether this goes well or whether you have problems,
and let us know about the problems.
How is it going, all good from our side?
Yeah, I think we are covering it all.
Then let the exercise commence,
and we will be back 10 minutes before the hour.
And then together with [Name], we can summarize.
We can then look at some of the tricky points
before we take a longer break then.
Good, have fun at the exercise.
See you again in 20 minutes, 22 minutes.
Bye.
All right, we are back from the exercise.
Information to [Name].
I got an error message from my remote control panel.
So maybe people heard some jingle, maybe they didn't.
But I think we are streaming at least the right screen.
We have 10 minutes left.
We got heaps of questions
and many, many, many good questions.
Something that people observed is that actually
some of the steps are not so easy to do in VS code.
Some of the steps are not easy to do on GitHub,
especially for instance,
when we ask you to create a branch.
Well, that doesn't really work
on somebody else's repository.
So if you wanted to do it, you would have to fork first.
The solutions that we have here,
they are only for the command line.
So this is work in progress, we know.
Many changes that we did to the lesson
we did only last week.
So there is more work needed.
But what I will try to do here in the last 10 minutes
before the longer break,
to go through some of the steps here on VSCode.
And sometimes I will have to open up our terminal
inside the VSCode and use the command line instead.
There exist extensions probably for everything.
We didn't ask you to install any extensions
because we didn't want to make it more complicated.
We wanted to make it easy to join this workshop.
But one thing we might do is we collect
on the Code Refinery chat, we started collecting
what would be really useful extensions for VS Code
that we can recommend everybody.
And I admit that I have very little experience.
So I think I'm using it now for the third time in my life.
But let me try to go through some of the steps here.
And hopefully I will also have time to show some of,
to comment on some of the questions
on how to do certain things on GitHub.
And the first step was to make sure
we start from a well-defined version.
And this was because the code is evolving
and we want to make sure that this exercise still works.
So I will not work on main.
I will kind of downgrade my version
to this some past release of NetworkX.
And one way to do it, I can click here on main.
Is that visible?
I'm on the lower left here with my mouse point.
And, I can probably navigate to the specific release, what was it, 263, here we go.
So now it's changed a little bit because now we are, we have traveled into the past.
Now how to find the code, the line that contains this.
Ooh, I don't know, I will try the magnifying glass.
Logic error in degree.
It found something, good.
It's in network X algorithms threshold PY.
Good.
And I can even open it up, the file.
Let's do it, just that I don't forget the name.
Find out when this line was last modified.
Yeah, so that I don't know how to do in VS Code unless I ask the command line.
And I also admit I don't know what happens on all of your systems.
So if you click on new terminal, I don't really know precisely what will happen.
What I'm hoping is that it opens some form of a command line
that you can type and that looks similar to mine.
But now that I know the file name,
I can do git annotate,
and it was networkX algorithms threshold.py.
It might be too tiny on my screen,
but if I now hit enter,
it's on the very right side is the code
and the left side is the metadata.
When was it changed by whom?
Which date?
Which commit?
And I could know with my arrow down or up,
I could hope to find it.
One way to search through this is
if I know what I'm looking for,
it would be the forward slash.
So now I'm typing on my keyboard forward slash
and now I can search for logic error, enter.
And this is now a little bit hard to read
because I tried to zoom in and it's not big screen enough
but this is all one line.
This is the code and this is the metadata.
So the last, the line was last changed in this commit.
I will keep a note of that commit.
I will just write it down here on my paper.
It's 90544b4
How do I get out of this?
With Q.
If I type Q, I should, yep, I'm out.
And now we can inspect the commit with git show, git show.
90544b4, et cetera, et cetera.
And there I will see more details.
I don't want to open it up now
because I don't want to put other people's email addresses
onto the stream and recording.
We will edit this other person out.
But then I would see what happened in that commit.
And what, two more steps.
One was create a branch pointing to the past
when that commit was created.
Okay, let me close the terminal
because that I can do without terminal.
How do I go back here?
Let me close this.
If I know and remember the commit,
one way to navigate to it would be again,
click on the branch tag overview.
And a nice way to do this is to create a new branch.
Whenever I want to look around in the past
to some archeology, I personally like
to create a new branch.
It will create a new label, a sticky note,
but I want it to stick to this past commit way, way back.
Create a new branch from,
and now I can type the commit.
Wait a moment, is it asking me for the name?
I don't know.
Oh, I forgot.
Let's try again.
Create new branch from...
What happens if I type in the hash 90544B4?
And then I can give it a name, which is,
what should we call it?
Old code.
Enter.
And now I have a branch called old code.
I can navigate to it.
I can go back to main.
I can go back to old code.
And the code that I'm looking here right now
is the one as it was back then.
And now for the final question,
How do I bring it back to the commit just before 90544?
One way would be I could open the terminal
and type git log.
Git log.
Why do I see here, this hash and not the other one?
This is not what I wanted.
This doesn't point to the commit that I thought it would.
Okay, that's not what I wanted.
It's pointing to another commit.
It's pointing to 263.
So it created the branch on the commit that I was at,
not the one away in the past.
Not the one in the past, no.
Okay, so here I will try to do that in the command line.
And I see that we are basically out of time.
I will use one more minute.
and that is if I want to create a new branch
in the past git branch, I can call it really old code.
And now I can give the hash
from which I wanted to create it 0.544v4.
And how do I switch to it?
Git switch.
And it also, it switched also VSCode.
And now if I do git log, I see,
so I don't know why that failed.
This is what I wanted to see.
This is the commit right before.
That's one way of doing it.
The other way of doing it would be
if I wanted to branch just before,
I could say 9, 0, 5, 4, 4, B4, and then tilde 1.
It's the first parent of that commit.
It would be the commit just before.
That was a quick tour.
I think we're out of time.
I don't want to eat into the break.
We will be back in one hour.
And then before we move on to the next thing, which will be learning how to turn a project
into a Git repository and publish it, we will debrief some of the questions that I didn't
have time to comment on.
Good to see you everybody in one hour.
We'll be back here with [Name] and for a little bit more Git.
Looking forward.
Have a good break.
Bye.
you
Okay, it works. I'm just remote controlling here the studio from a different country.
Welcome back, everybody, after the break.
Thanks for the feedback.
Thanks for the questions.
I wanted, before moving on, I wanted to comment
that this was not an easy exercise, the last one.
It was possibly too short time.
It was also maybe cold water
because after yesterday, when we were on GitHub,
now suddenly we have to work locally.
Some commands only work in the command line.
It's a new environment.
So this was really advanced.
So I understand the frustration.
We need to improve the solution and the walkthrough to make it easier for everybody.
But also now we can relax because the next exercise that we will do in 10-15 minutes
will be a lot easier.
And everybody can do it and everybody will need this in their work.
So it will get better.
The other thing I wanted to say is that we don't expect that you remember all the commands
for all of these advanced techniques of how to navigate through a repository, but we
wanted you to know that you know that this is possible.
Now you know that these operations are possible.
Maybe you don't need them now, maybe you need them in three years, but since you start using
it will be possible later for you
to do these kind of operations.
It's not important to remember how to do it.
You can look it up later.
If you know where the episode is
and you can later look up how to do it in detail,
but we wanted you to know that these things are possible.
I wanted to show one more thing
before we move to the next episode.
This is just demonstration
because this was one question on GitHub.
You just need to know that, again, that this is possible,
that if I look at a repository here
and I see main and the latest commit from two days ago,
I can navigate to that commit.
And you can then navigate to browse files.
So top right, there is a button called browse files.
And something is different now in the address.
The address is now not anymore.
It will not show me the latest version,
but it will show me a specific version.
This is the specific commit identifier.
And if you want, now you can replace it.
So if I still remember the commit hash
from before the break, it was 90544B4.
90544B4, I don't even have to type the whole thing.
And now I can navigate through the project
as it was seven years ago.
So that can be also useful.
So many of the steps could have been done on GitHub.
It wasn't easy, we need to improve the walkthrough.
Yeah, and the I see that the URL here is hard to read it is very small, but the difference
is that if the first part is your project, then slash three slash commit hash, you can
and then navigate into the past.
It's like time traveling.
And somewhere in the,
well, let me paste it.
So I'll be pasted into the answers,
then you can try it as well.
Here we go.
Good.
We will now leave this NetworkX project.
If you didn't finish the exercise, you can try later.
you know where to find it.
It is not important for the rest of today
and it's not important for tomorrow.
So I will, I think I will close.
I will move this away.
Yeah, I will move it.
No, not this thing, this thing.
I will move the VS Code away.
I will bring it back in a moment.
One more thing that we probably mentioned,
but I just want to mention it again,
something that now that we are,
have a couple of different repositories,
something I did is on my hard drive,
I created a directory called course
and everything we create here, I will put in there.
And it's easier for me to find.
And also I don't clutter my hard drive
with different projects
because we will now go to a different project.
it will be, I call it my project.
It's my own project.
It's not on Git yet.
I will bring it to Git and I will bring it onto GitHub.
And if you want, it can be your real project,
but note that you will have the choice
of making the project public or private.
So we make it invisible for everybody else.
And if you don't want that,
you can practice with a small example toy project.
So this is what I will do.
Do you have a default license that you use when you publish a project?
Very good question. I have in my little toy project, I created two files. One is a Python
script, but then I start, I right away start with a license. So license is one of the first
things I will add to a project, license and readme. And often I go for open source licenses.
For coding projects, I often choose MIT license, if I just want to keep it as simple as possible.
And we will talk more about licenses next week. So sometimes I want to make sure that
not only my project is open source, but also all the derivative work is open source. And
then I choose a different license,
but more about that on Tuesday.
But let me navigate to the right place.
And the right place is on the bottom of the document,
how to turn your own project to a Git repo
and how to share it.
I will open it up in my browser tab.
And here, there is not very much to say.
We will give you enough time
to do this, but I want to really explain well
what the expectation is.
The expectation is that if you don't want to share
a real project of yours, it can be a small script.
You can create a new directory called my project
or whatever name you like, put a couple of files into it.
And this represents our own research project,
our own master thesis or PhD thesis.
and it is not yet a git repository.
And the two steps are now,
we need to make it a git repository.
And depending on which track you choose,
you will learn some new commands.
So for instance, on the command line,
you will see you have to do a little bit more work.
There are a little bit more steps to do.
If you go for VS Code, it's less to do
because it does lots of these Git commands for you.
Or you can do only using GitHub.
In some of these steps,
you will have to create a GitHub repository for the project.
Again, if you go for VS Code,
you don't even have to do that.
It will create a GitHub repository for you.
But at some point,
at some point it might ask you to authorize your VS Code
to be able to write to GitHub for you.
And I did that, you have to do it only the very first time
and I said yes to it.
So now my VS Code editor can create
and modify my own GitHub repositories
because that's what I wanted it to be able to do.
Scrolling back.
Your goal will be make it a git repo in one commit or a couple of commits as you like.
They will live locally on your computer, but then you also want to share this repository
to GitHub or GitLab.
Because the steps that we show, especially the command line, is very transferable between
all of these services.
And that's so important to do.
Because our ambition is that every coding project that we do will end up as a version
controlled project that is findable by other people.
And after you are done, if you need it for a certificate,
take a screenshot of it.
You don't have to keep it on GitHub.
You can, again, delete it.
So we don't force you to keep all of these projects there.
And we have allocated 25 minutes, which may be,
I think it's good to give people time
to experiment also a little bit.
and learn how to share the code.
And what we will do when we come back from the exercises
that we will discuss a lot.
We will really open it up for lots of questions.
We will try to have a discussion here with my colleagues
and we will talk about after all of these things we learned,
what is a good starting point?
How to progress?
What are the things to avoid?
What are typical traps when starting with Git or GitHub?
Yes, exercise until 35 minutes past. Try it out. Let us know how it went. Follow the solutions
if you need. And see you then again in 25 minutes. And then let's discuss a lot less
than spend the remaining time that we will have to clarify all of these questions that
are left. Good luck with the exercise. See you in 25 minutes. Bye.
Welcome back, everybody.
We, how did it go?
I will try it also on my side.
We got lots of questions.
That was great.
So my plan is I will,
I have this little toy project.
I want to, I will try it as well using VS code.
It will take only two, three minutes,
and then I can comment on some of the questions
that came up once I created.
So let me try that code here.
Code dot, it will start it at the place where I am.
I will make this more readable.
This is not on Git yet.
And all I have to do is source control.
I could initialize it.
I will not even do that.
So for those of you who did the command line,
you, at some point you had to type git init,
and this is what would happen if I click the button,
but I will not even do that.
I will go straight to publish to GitHub,
which will then initialize the repository for me.
It will create a commit for me
and push the changes to GitHub, publish to GitHub.
And I will first make it a public repository,
and then later I will change it to private,
because there was also a question,
where can we switch this to a public?
You can, I could change the name for my project
to something more descriptive, public,
all of the files, okay.
And here I'm following the screenshots
that we have in the solution.
Now, it created the repository for me on GitHub, it created a commit, it pushed a commit, and
I can open it up on GitHub.
Ta-da!
And here is my project.
This first commit is a commit that I didn't even actively do, VS Code did it for me.
Now, to the question about one question about public and private, this is a public project.
How can you switch?
How can you make it private?
And how can you delete projects?
This is something we have been asked.
So on settings, this is you can do it in settings.
In settings, you can rename it.
You can do lots of things, scrolling down, but I will go to the danger zone.
In the danger zone, I can change visibility, so from public to private.
And if I don't want the repository anymore, I can also delete it.
And it will still ask me, do you really want to delete it?
There is no way back.
Please type the name.
but then in a few steps, it can be, it will be gone.
Good.
Now, let me show you one more thing here.
And that is, how is this linked now
to the local repository with the remote repository?
And where is this information?
So I'll click on my Python script,
And then I want to see, is this the timeline?
No, this is the timeline.
Where's the timeline?
How do I, this one, how do I see the commits?
What I wanted to see is the commit messages
here on VS Code as well.
No, I don't. I looked for that several times. I haven't found somewhere we talk about timeline.
So where is this timeline thing that we talked about?
Is a certain file tracked in git open? Yes.
Should be would be. Oh, can you go to the file browser view? Not the git view?
Yeah, there, in their timeline at the bottom.
Ah, here we go, thanks.
Okay, first commit, good, brilliant.
And that was hard to find, for me, the first time.
So there's the timeline, there is the first commit, but now, where is this information
locally?
Where is this stuff?
And in the command line, you could do,
there is a hidden directory called .git.
And this is just a reminder that
when you create commands branches,
it all goes in there, all the metadata is in there.
This also stores the connection between this repository
and the remote repository.
If you want to
disconnect the two,
look for remotes, so you can remove remotes. It will disconnect the two.
And if I, if I on my computer would delete the .git,
then this commit is gone. The history is gone. The branches are gone.
I think just for demonstration, I will try it out. I don't know what will happen. Let me,
so please don't do it. This is not dangerous. I will do it only, only here on stream. I will remove
this. No, I will not remove this is dangerous, but I will do I will rename it. Get to renamed
folder. Because then I can rename it back.
And if you do a git status, I guess you get. But it's not a git folder anymore.
Yes, so if I now, like, remove it or move it away,
git status.
So this is not a git repository,
but I think VS Code didn't get the news yet.
I was wondering what happens here with the timeline
because there shouldn't be anything now anymore.
There should be, oh yeah.
So now VS Code also got the news.
It tells that, well, this is not a git repository.
You need to initialize it first.
And now there is no there is no timeline anymore.
So all the all the local git information was in the .git.
Let me try the reverse.
Rename folder.
I move it back to .git.
Now there is a timeline again.
So that was good.
What else is here?
Any trouble here?
Anything else we should talk about?
What did I mean by disconnect?
I meant disconnecting.
Okay, what do I mean by that?
The connection, there is a connection
between now the local repository and the remote repository
so that when I do local changes here on my computer,
I can push them to GitHub.
And if I or somebody else does changes on GitHub,
I can pull these changes to my local repository.
This is something we will do quite a bit tomorrow.
Pull changes, push changes.
And the connection between the two
was this thing that we called origin,
but I think we only mentioned it very briefly earlier.
It's a placeholder for,
we saw that earlier when we cloned our repository.
It remembered where we cloned it from.
A little bit technical.
I will now move away my VS codes
to get more screen space.
I will also move away my terminal,
more screen space,
and I will navigate what I want to do now.
I want to navigate to the last part and we will...
So let's discuss a little bit before break.
We will then take a short break.
We'll discuss a little bit more later.
I would like now to really talk about
all the questions that you might have.
So let's make this really a Q&A session,
ask everything about Git that you wanted to know,
anything about yesterday and today.
And to get these questions started, we have these two episodes,
but there won't be any exercises of where we want to now discuss here
some practical advice, how much it is necessary.
We showed you many things that are possible, but where should we start?
What should we do then? And what are typical traps?
So first, practical advice, and I will add the link also in the document
and so that you know where to find it.
We are now here.
So at the bottom of the document.
And there are a few topics
that people might be wondering about.
And one is,
Let's talk about commit messages.
So what makes commit messages useful?
And we try to summarize here that a useful commit message,
it's like an entry in a logbook.
It's if you can, in one line, summarize the change,
but also if you can provide context for it.
And sometimes it's hard to do it in one line.
I find it quite a challenge to write one-liners.
So if you need more than one line, it's still good to try.
Here's a good example.
If you write it in a command line,
try to summarize the commit message in the first line.
And why in the first line?
Because, okay, let me navigate to,
let me go back to the recipe book.
Recipe book recorded.
Because the first line is the one that I see here.
It's good if it's somehow descriptive
because then I don't have to click
and I don't have to look into it to find out more.
But if you need to give more context,
more explanation, why was this done?
What does it refer to?
It refers to a discussion that maybe started in an issue.
Then it's customary to do first line summary,
one empty line, and then more context if you need to.
And when we created commits on GitHub,
let me try that on GitHub.
Now I will modify something faster.
Let me modify this one.
So, when I do it on GitHub, I also have the option to give a short summary, your edit,
I will edit the file.
Well, we need more instructions, more instructions coming up.
Let's preview the change.
And when, when I commit, when I create the commit on GitHub, the top part is the first
line and this is the this this the empty line is the one between the two and here is the
more context and this is not a very useful commit message because it only tells me which
file has changed it would be much nicer to say what has changed what was the context
there. Why did I change it? Because providing context and hear more context.
Yeah. When do you have really short message commit messages? And when do you have longer
Most of the time, I have short messages. I have the longer one if it's, if it could be,
if it connects to something else, if it connects to a discussion that we had, if I need to
provide this context, or if it's a bigger change. And I want to summarize what I did
and why I did it so that people don't have to look through all of the change to understand
it. But most of the time it fits into one line. How about you? How do you do that?
I mean, like everything, it really depends on the project. So for, I mean, for small
projects that I'm just starting and are still chaotic. I mean, it's often really short.
Sometimes it's even things like fix bugs or so on if I'm busy and it's just all thrown
in things. Like, for example, this control panel for the stream I've been working on.
It's so young and things are changing so fast that if I take the time to make a good commit
message, it's not going to matter by tomorrow. So I just do whatever. But then there's other
projects that are actually like out there and mostly work. So every change has a particular
purpose. Like I'm adding a certain new feature to it. And then I'll go into more detail. Also,
it depends on who else would be reading it. Like if I'm contributing to someone else's project,
I'll use the commit message to explain why I'm doing it and what the reviewer might need to know.
and they know I may as well do it there rather than write it somewhere else,
especially because when you open a pull request, it will automatically use the messages from the
commit by default.
Right. If I have a pull request with only one commit,
it will suggest me that this is the pull request title,
and it will suggest that this is the pull request context.
And a good point about that, if you start,
if it's your own project, it doesn't have to be formal.
It shouldn't be formal.
Maybe still good to write the commit messages in English
because many projects start small
and then they become lots of people
and they live for a long time.
But as for bigger projects,
and some of them are listed here
and maybe these are projects that some of you use
like SciPy, NumPy, Pandas, Julia, GGplot.
It can be interesting to browse these projects
and have a look how do they do commit messages.
And you will see that they are a bit more formal
because they have to be.
These are projects with hundreds, thousands of people.
So then they agree on certain conventions
of how to document improvements,
improvements, how to document bugs, how to document,
how to write commit messages,
which automatically create release notes,
but we don't have to be that formal yet.
But it can be still fun because you can browse them
for some inspiration of how do these really well-established
open source projects communicate through commit messages.
Yeah.
If you take some project you're interested in
that's reasonably big and subscribe to its repository
on GitHub, you'll start getting a flood of these kind of pull
requests and messages and discussions that are coming in.
And this can be really educational to see
how people do things.
Like from subscribing to repositories
and seeing how they've worked, I've
learned many of the different techniques which I use now.
So I'd, yeah, so I'd, so for becoming better at things,
This is one of the things I'd recommend.
It's a great tip.
Like if you want to become a better writer, you should read books.
It's similar here.
I think from all of these, I want to point out one thing.
It can be more useful to say why something was changed.
It can be more useful than what has changed.
Because I can find out what changed.
I can go to the commit.
I can click on it and I will see it.
These lines got removed.
lines got added. But sometimes it can be hard for me to tell why was this done. So the why
can be more interesting. But that's the last thing before the break. Let's take a break
soon. Let the perfect not be the enemy of the good enough. At the beginning, let's make
it just good enough. More commits, they don't have to be pretty. It's better than trying
to do everything perfectly and then preventing you from creating commits and sharing your
work. And I suggest that we take a break, maybe 10 minute break, because then everybody
can think about what are the questions that you want to ask, and please ask them. And
then the remaining 20 minutes that we will have after the break, then we can talk about
complexity, how to where to start with branches, how to deal with branch complexity, repositories,
to start and how to progress.
Sounds like a plan.
Okay.
Sounds good.
So then let's be back five minutes after the hour, and hopefully with lots of questions
about Git.
And if you want us to show something, please suggest it and maybe we can show something
here.
Let's make this a bit of improv session.
See you all in 10 minutes.
Bye.
Okay.
Do you push the break button?
Oh yeah, let me find the break button.
Hello, everybody. Welcome back for the last 20 minutes, 25 minutes of today. It will be
a discussion session. It's a possibility to ask us lots of questions, which we can now
here discuss. Maybe we can also show one or two things. So thanks so much for keeping
this coming. I would maybe before moving on to branches, I would like to we can talk about
two things that came up. One was when do you clone and when do you fork? How do you decide?
I can comment, but maybe, yeah, beyond [Name].
And the cat is there, yeah.
The cat is there.
Yes.
I would fork a repository that seems like a bigger project.
Fork it first and then clone my version of it.
Yeah. Yeah.
So I can say that I fork when I somehow want to have it.
I want to make sure that I don't lose even the fork, the copy.
If I'm afraid that the central repository will, I don't know, disappear or something,
then I just make a copy of it.
Or if I plan to contribute to it and make changes and keep those changes somewhere
saved if it's just about i want to run it only today
oh then then i don't create a fork yeah i didn't think about this uh
keeping a copy in case the original changes but that's a good point
yeah it's a little bit like a bookmark yeah so if then the
central repository disappears it will not remove your fork
unless the central repository is private. If, at least it used to be like that, if the private
disappears, it also removes all the forks. I see. Okay.
But as a side note, how about gitignore? When is that useful? How do you use it?
What is it good for? It was asked somewhere.
did you talk about did you talk about git status before and
not so much because we didn't spend we didn't focus too much on the command line yeah
i can do a quick quick demo here of it in my in my project
gitstatus. Everything is, the working tree is clean. And what does that mean? Well, everything
has been committed. But what if I have now a file here? Give me an example for something
that should not be in a Git repository.
Test.py.
What about,
oh, sorry, I thought cats was.
PC.
Sorry, what was that?
.pc.
Yeah, but it's Python specific.
Let's say I have all,
okay, I will do something.
I have a file called passwords.txt.
Okay, yeah.
Git status.
And I don't want to put passwords into the git repository.
I don't want to put passwords
and sensitive information onto GitHub.
And now if I type git status, I see it here.
Git reminds me that there is this file.
It's untracked.
Do you want to edit?
No, I don't want to edit,
but I also, I don't want to be reminded.
And if I want to get to prevent me from adding it,
I would list this in a file called .gitignore.
Oh, and now I don't want to spend too much time here.
I can try to do it in VS code, code dot.
Oh.
So, yeah.
So the point of git status is it will tell you
what you're currently working on
what might need to be done. So for example it tells you these are all files that you've done
something on but they aren't committed yet which usually means you should commit them at some point.
I can even do a wildcard so anything that starts with passwords please
never put this into the git repository.
save now the thing is still there it's like to change color interesting
and if I go back to the terminal and I do git status
okay there is not a gitignore which I guess I should add to my git repository
how do I do that I do it by doing oh yeah oh I need to go into this thing
source control click add stage and commit in the commit message with a good
one will be ignore ignore files that start with password commit and back to
here get status now it looks clean the password TXT is still there it's not in
my git repository and I will not accidentally commit it it will not let
Let me I can even try or get add password. Let me try to do that. No, you cannot.
Yeah, so it even warrants you so you won't accidentally add it.
So that was getting our typical thing to ignore is sensitive stuff, password stuff. Yeah,
big generated files.
If, for example, files. Yeah, like if you're compiling code, you would ignore the results
the compiling stuff. If you're storing LaTeX papers, you'd ignore the generated PDFs and
other intermediate files, and so on. For our code refinery web pages, we ignore the generated
websites, and so on. If you have big data analysis kind of stuff, you might ignore all of the data
directories, because you store that some other way, for example.
A little fun fact, if you zoom out here on the lesson down here, you can actually view the
lesson in PDF format, in one big PDF page. And that's a generated file. We don't want to have
that in the Git repository. We generate this every time we make a change to the repository.
And this is not part of the Git repository. This could be something that is ignored.
Yes.
Back to the lesson, how about branching?
Do you create branches or do you work with one branch in your projects or beyond [Name]?
Well, I use a lot of branches, so.
How do you keep them organized?
Yeah, that's a good question.
I try to give good names and start with my username and then a feature name.
Do you usually work on big projects or small projects or?
I work on small projects, private projects.
So just make this more visible here.
For me, most of my projects are very small.
I mean, I guess for everyone, you have a few big projects and many small projects, which
you might not even consider a project because it's so small.
So for the small stuff, it's just working on one branch usually, unless there's a specific
case when I need to do something, like I'm actually testing something else.
For bigger projects, like small group things, well, if it's a small group but I'm the main
developer and there's no one else that has time to review things, well, again, it's mostly
with the main branch.
But there's often times I'm doing something and I'm like, okay, this is such a big change,
I know I definitely want someone to look at it.
And then I would do the pull request workflow, like make a branch and actually ask someone,
please take a look at this, I really need your help, and then review.
So start small, start simple, it's okay to have main branch, it's okay to put all the
commits in there.
And as soon as the project grows, so as soon as you have two people, more than two people,
a few people, one thing you could consider is, and we will see that tomorrow in exercise,
one thing you could do in your project, in your research group, you could even decide
that, well, we want to right protect the main branch.
you decide that the main branch is the one that works,
is tested, and you write protect it.
So nobody can accidentally modify it or push to it
or commit to it, but you can then,
and tomorrow we will show you how you can then configure it
so that all the changes have to be pull requests.
And then at least somebody else looks at it.
And it's not just to make sure that,
it's not about just quality control,
also about learning, then at least two people know about each change. And that's important
in research groups. You want to make sure that if one research group member student leaves,
that the knowledge is not lost, that at least somebody else understands what was going on there.
What happens if no one has time or really only one person is working on a project?
I guess then it's sort of too bad, like that's the problem itself.
So I think there are two questions in this one question. One is, what do you do if you
are alone and you have nobody else to look over the code? And maybe you can team up with
somebody does it can be somebody who works on something else, but at least can look at
the code part of it. Doesn't have even have to understand the science part of it. And maybe
Maybe you can help them reviewing their code, but it can be hard.
And then the other part of the question is, how about time?
Because code reviewing takes time.
And it can feel like, well, this is not, you know, work or this is not coding, but it makes
better code.
It makes better understanding within the group.
So we think it's time well spent, but we need to then also convince, well, we need to allocate
time for it.
So it takes time.
reviewing a paper. It takes time, but the system is there for a good reason.
Yeah. So when you were, like, doing research and stuff like that, did someone usually review
your work? Did you have enough people to do this?
No, we were we were not really back then.
We were not really using this code review.
Everybody was committing to the main or master branch.
We had tests.
So we would notice when things wouldn't go well, and we would run these tests before
committing.
And at some point, somebody would notice that something changed and you will fix it.
These days, also in the project that I used to work on during PhD, we use code review.
Somebody else looks over it.
We have automated testing.
We will show you that next week.
So even when you look at the pull request, we can see whether all the tests are passing
or they are not passing.
But this can be built up step by step.
It's good not to add all of this machinery
right from the start in small projects.
Okay, we have 10 minutes left.
I just want to see what else kind of topics we have here.
And looking at questions,
we could talk about staging and committing.
I'm just scrolling down here
and see what interesting topics.
How large should a commit be?
What, yeah, what is a good size for a commit?
Yeah.
Maybe let's start with this one.
My experience is that a commit shouldn't be large
than it's trouble, so that small commits are best.
Yeah, so it's probably better to do many small commits
than one commit every few weeks.
Because if you do many smaller commits,
You can always recombine them later.
It is easier to combine than to split.
If later you find out that some commit was a mistake
it can be easier to undo it when it was small
rather than when it was one commit that touched everything.
What I
try to do, but I'm not always successful
is that I try to not put unrelated changes to the same commit
and to the same pull request because that will
it will simplify the review for the other person. It will also simplify
the undoing if we later realize that was a bad idea
then I can undo the bad idea instead of
at the same time undoing the good idea that was packaged into the same commit.
Right, yeah.
Maybe in terms of time, often I try to make a commit at the end of the day, approximately.
One per day, a few per day, if all you do is coding.
So a unit that you would not like to lose.
Yeah.
But, I mean, does that imply you tend to do one thing per day?
Correct.
So then we need more commits, because often I actually jump from thing to thing.
I wish I would just work on one day and one thing the other day.
Yeah.
I mean, like I've said, I think it really
depends on the project size and what it is.
So we're teaching you some of the basics here.
But how to apply it to your own work,
well, that is something that you will figure out.
And I mean, it's OK to do it wrong also.
We talk so much about the right way to do things.
But doing anything and then seeing what works or doesn't work is even better.
I mean, that's how I've learned most of what I know by doing it wrong many times.
So, yeah, I fully agree.
I want to have a quick peek here at the what to avoid.
Maybe there's an interesting topic that we can talk about.
Yeah, that's good.
There is a lot of text, but
I think this is something that well many, many will identify with I, the code is never finished it's always unfinished.
It's, it's ugly. It's okay.
Just commit, share it, nobody will judge.
Don't postpone it just because it's unfinished.
I can give some metaphors. So when we've been hiring people, I've had to look at a lot of repositories, and I'd say, okay, so this is like practical advice. If you're thinking, oh, I don't want to share ugly looking stuff because people will judge me.
Well, when you're hiring people, you're doing judging.
And I would rather see a few, or maybe one really good project that shows this person
knows how to do things well, and then a lot of small, ugly projects, meaning, oh yeah,
like they're just, like they're not just doing, they're not too overly perfect, they're able
to actually track stuff and keep it, you know, that they understand that, wait, how would
I say this? So they're not just showing their perfect thing, but they believe in openness
for everything. And they know that it's better to share. And also, I mean, if you look at
history and it starts ugly and gets better, that's completely normal also.
And I would never judge anyone for that. I would actually, well, I would judge them positively
by thinking, okay, this person knows to start recording early, as opposed to something that
has one commit that's the final product, and then nothing else. I mean, I'm not relying
on that for anything.
That's a great point. I wouldn't mind at all ugly commits or ugly code. One thing I would
maybe look at is how do people communicate? So how do they review other people's code?
Is it done in a nice friendly way, in a constructive way?
So there is a lot of communication in issues and in pull requests and in pull request discussion.
And these days we often work collaboratively.
Yeah.
There's these last two good questions, or last two questions that are good.
Is there a way to do automatic git commit to avoid losing work?
So once I saw some sort of thing that it would hook into an editor and on every save it would
do another git commit on like a work in progress branch or something like that.
I haven't used that or seen it again, but if you want you can probably do similar things.
Maybe another way to do it is you can run git add more often.
So once you do get add, it stores a copy and it's hard to figure out where it's storing,
but it is actually stored somewhere.
And with enough work, you can probably find it again if you happen to completely mess things
up.
Indeed, that's, that's how I often work. I use the staging, I stage often. Anytime it's
an improvement, I stage it. But when I feel it is an improvement, but not yet a commit,
stage, stage, stage, and then a commit, I don't use anything automatic. Maybe now with
AI, it will soon do these things for us. We will just, well, we will not even write code.
it will write the code and do the commits,
but so I don't use any automatic committing.
How about the joining commits?
We have an episode on the more advanced topics,
which we will not go through,
but I want to show you what it is.
So here the optional episodes can,
if you're interested,
have a look at what is this thing staging area
and how can you undo recover from situations?
And then you will learn about git reset where you can do lots of these things like moving
commits around, reordering them, joining them, moving them to a different branch.
So all of this is possible.
We should also not forget to copy the feedback form into our notes.
Yes.
I'm just trying to find it.
We have it somewhere.
Okay, I almost have it.
I will copy it in, but let's continue the discussion.
We still have five minutes, but I want,
oh, somebody's on it, good.
Here it is.
So tell us what went well today, what didn't go well today,
what we need to improve for next time,
And whatever we can fix already for tomorrow, we will.
Did you all enjoy
this RStudio track? So we did it
relatively late at night, last night.
Based on feedback and seeing
how many people it would help.
So we can't make all of these different tracks perfect,
perfect, but is it worth it?
So I'm adding a new poll there, helpful.
And it is work in progress.
I mean, you notice that some things are not totally smooth yet because some of the changes
were last minute.
So if you look at tomorrow's exercises,
there is still work to be done.
So this afternoon we will add some screenshots
and solutions, but we have really interesting
and real life exercises for tomorrow
where we will collaborate.
Those of you who don't have an exercise team
or are not in a exercise room.
So those of you who participate here on your own,
you can still collaborate with us.
So hopefully you got an email from me.
If you signed up today, I will hopefully send it later.
And then there are instructions on how you can join, because we will need to add you
to an exercise repository so that we can all collaborate inside it.
Those of you who are part of a group and part of a team, I mean, lucky you, thanks also
to the team leaders and to those who help the local rooms and groups to help out, especially
because we try here really new material. This is also not so easy for all the team leaders
and helpers. It's really appreciated.
Should we write news for day two and what people need to do to prepare for day three
already before we go. So I listed, we did the things which are listed on the schedule.
We added links to the specific episodes we covered. Tomorrow we do a different lesson,
it's called Git Collaborative. It's basically the same kind of things, but it's really all
about working on these bigger projects together. So basically how to, a lot about pull requests
and central repositories and reviewing code and stuff like that. Is there any extra preparation
for that? Can it all be done through the GitHub web interface or the other methods?
Yeah, it will build on. Tomorrow we'll build on today and on yesterday. So for those who want to
to work on the command line,
we assume that you are able to, to clone,
and you are able to push.
And today we practice these two things.
So in other words, for those on the command line,
we hope that either the SSH protocol
or the Git credential manager is working.
It will be possible to do everything tomorrow only on GitHub.
it will be also possible and relatively easy
to follow on VS Code.
If you are already curious what the exercises are,
you can find them on top of this page.
We have a list of exercises you can browse,
but you will see that there is a lot of details missing,
but the big picture is there.
A list of exercises.
So tomorrow we will collaborate within the same repository,
but then we will also learn how to contribute changes
to repositories that belong to other people.
What, how to do it technically,
but also how to do it, like, what is the etiquette there?
And then we practice code review.
How do, how can you review somebody else's code?
How can you give suggestions to changes?
And how can we then implement these changes
without having to open a new pull request?
We will practice this inside the same pull request.
We will have a discussion
and we will have these suggestions and improvements.
And it's a really important technique,
whether you are on GitHub or on GitLab.
Yeah.
And we really have designed this where,
like our idea, like we need to teach the local things,
VS code, command line, and so on.
So our idea was we start with day one GitHub,
and then we start showing the local things other days.
And, even though we have these other paths there, unfortunately we can't support everything
as well.
But we hope that we give a base where you can go to other things and follow up yourself.
Yeah, I'm really looking forward to it.
So I think that's all from me.
How about a lot, a big thank you to [Name] and [Name] and everybody else helping.
Yes.
Any final words for me from you two?
Not really, I guess it's time we should get going, [Name].
Yeah.
Nothing more to add, really.
I think we're covered, that was all good.
Yeah.
Good.
Thanks, everybody.
Really looking forward to tomorrow.
It will be exciting.
And yeah, exciting lesson coming up.
Yes. Thanks so much.
Okay. Bye.
Bye.