Here we go, icebreakers. So, did everyone have a good night?
Or I guess the real question, did [Name] have a good night doing all the revisions
that we're going to benefit from today?
I feel good about it, yeah. So there were some late night changes, but
But when we really start, I will invite everybody
then to reload the browser tabs.
But I'm really happy about the changes.
I think we have a good plan for today.
We should do the audio check.
I forgot.
So remember how this goes.
So me, [name], [name], [name]
is the order on my screen.
One.
Two.
Three.
So...
Okay, I'm a bit lower than others.
I think that means...
I need to make others a bit lower.
Krager has sounded a bit grainy again to me.
Okay, I reduced the volume slightly, the input volume.
Now it sounds good to me.
Should we test again?
One.
Two.
Yeah, it sounds better.
Yeah, so it sounded a bit better.
I feel like for the future we need a different audio test.
They are so sharp, like one, two, we need words.
Maybe everyone needs to sing, like high and low, so that we get the full spectrum.
Yeah, like a canon would be really fun.
We sing to Jingle in the future.
Okay, so. Yeah, today we've got all kinds of cool stuff here. So, today's lessons have
been updated similar to days 1 and 2. It's still basically the same concept as before.
So we really practice contributing to other projects on a big scale.
So days one and two were all about sort of working on your own projects where you can
really push directly and sort of, um, like you push directly, you don't have to worry
about pull requests and things like that.
But today we go to the pull request and we'll actually work on some projects where everyone
in the course will contribute. And these will be really cool. But you will see how that
goes in a bit. So of these icebreaking questions, what did you have for breakfast? Or not that,
what's the biggest, most collaborative projects you've been on?
Yeah, that's the more interesting one.
For me, it's actually Code Refinery.
It is the contributing to materials and all the different repositories that we have to
work on different stuff.
Otherwise, I've only been working on my own mainly or with one more person.
How about you?
So I was also thinking Code Refinery for one of the biggest things.
Like I've done isolated pull requests to some bigger projects on GitHub, but it's more like
a drive-by contribution than long-term collaboration kind of stuff. So I think Code
Refinery still is it. [name], what about you? I'm not sure how many collaborators Code Refinery has,
but I would mention PlasmaPy, which I just checked has 125 collaborators.
I implemented some features for that library. So I would say that's the one.
Did this use the pull request kind of workflow or how did you contribute there?
Yes, it does. And it's actually very formalized. So I learned a lot there.
Okay. It's like they have all these rules and templates and this is how you should do it.
and what you need before you submit it and so on.
Yeah, these are very helpful.
Yeah.
And [Name], what's your biggest projects?
Maybe it's now Codefinery.
So I was collaborating to some projects
with over a longer time with maybe 20 active developers.
It wasn't very formalized.
So no issue templates or pull request templates,
but using issues and pull requests or merge requests.
So these projects are actually on GitLab,
but it's really the same workflow.
And then I like your term drive-by contribution.
So I have a couple of drive-bys
where I appeared, I did a little thing,
and then, but these are projects that I'm using
and where I sent in a small change.
And then lots of own projects, and some of them get the occasional drive-by pull request
from somebody else.
And will you talk later about how the pull request kind of workflow has made these large
projects possible?
Well I think we will get there.
We'll nicely build it up from a smaller group.
So today, we'll start with a setup
that can work well if you are two people or more.
And we will work towards a scenario
where you will be able to suggest changes
to basically any project.
We will not go into the very formal template
because that depends on the project and then
one or some really the big projects,
they have contribution guidelines that one should read.
So we will not go through into that,
but at least we will learn all the techniques.
We will also discuss them later today
on even how to approach a project of somebody else.
Like if you have an idea or you have a question
or you have a suggestion,
like how to do that in a good way.
Should we start, then?
So, do we go to who's screen?
My screen. Okay. Are you sharing now?
Yes, I'm sharing.