But, however, if you start from the workshop page, you can scroll to day number four.
And the first part, the first two hours is going to be [name] and I covering this topic
of reproducible research.
So if you click on the link, you end up on this page, I can briefly talk about the learning
outcomes for this page. So the idea and what we will cover on this first two hours kind
of builds up from where we started with the first week. Ideally by the end of this lesson
you should be able to follow good practices, good enough practices to keep your directories
and your projects well organized. It's important that you understand that code and software
in general, have basically dependencies
that can be related to the system, where you are,
or to other libraries and other piece of codes
that are written by others.
And so it's important to also document this.
Then, hopefully, you will be able to document
the computational steps and have an idea when this
can be helpful and useful.
And then we will briefly introduce you
to the world of containers.
we will just, you know, scratch the surface there.
We will not go deeper into that,
but it's an important topic to basically consider.
And [name], do you wanna say something else
here related to the learning outcomes or?
No, but maybe let's talk a little bit
about how it all connects in the next page.
So for those of you that have joined already last week,
you might be familiar with this wonderful little image here
by [name].
And this time it looks a little bit different
in a sense that we have added
all the Code Refinery lesson titles to this figure
because the Code Refinery workshop itself
could also be called like a workshop
on reproducible research.
Like everything that we do here
like leads to you being better prepared
for doing reproducible research with your code.
And we have these six helpful steps here.
And for example, the get your files and folders in order
is already, will be covered today
in the reproducible research session.
Then we have the good file names for,
on folder names, which is covered in tomorrow's lesson
about documentation, and then on day six,
modular code development.
We talk a little bit about like how already naming
can help you in starting your documentation, for example.
Then in general, documenting code,
writing read-me's, code comments,
and how that can help you help others
and you understand your code later better.
Then we had the version control,
basically whole last week, or not just basically,
the whole last week was all about version control,
introduction to version control,
and then also collaborative distributed version control.
If you have missed that,
you can always go back and watch the videos
to learn about that there.
And then this week, we talk basically on every day,
something about destabilizing your computing environment
and the software we will start today
with, for example, the containers idea, then Jupyter Notebooks tomorrow, automated testing
on day six, and also modular code development, we'll talk about how you can do this stabilization.
And then in the end, you will probably want to publish your research outputs, which means
your code, your data, your documents, and topics related to that will be discussed today
afternoon in the social coding and open software lesson. And that's basically how it all connects
and these two hours that we have now here on reproducible research are like a small glimpse
into the world of the tools and the concepts that can help you with making your research code more
reproducible. So do you want to continue [name] with the motivation for this lesson?
We can go to the motivation.
I like to what when you were explaining this to me,
when we were discussing, that one
can look at this in the sense of timescales
that the Git version control are basically
focusing on your day-to-day work or the weekly timescale.
But then sometimes you don't need to control
or you don't need to version control anymore.
The daily changes, you want to start
version in the whole project, which might last for months.
And so what we will cover here is
like moving away from the day-to-day timescale
to the controlling at the project level,
so at the month or year level.
Or it can even be bigger.
As you heard in week number one that we were time
traveling through Git, here we will do even more time
traveling, meaning going back to very old versions of operating
systems and and things like that so that you know the future the future selves and the future
other people who want to rework with what we did are able to to travel back in time
so it's good to start with some motivation let me briefly check if there's anything on the
HackMD that is worth mentioning all right there's nothing specific so
Basically, the motivation when it comes to this episode on reproducible research, one
could even argue that the whole Code Refinery workshop should be called reproducible computational
research workshop, because as you just heard from what [name] has described, everything
is kind of connected together with the goal of having a project in the specific case,
a research project that is able to be run many times over and over and with the goal
that you know that the same output is when you have the same input and the same code
you are able to reobtain the same output. So in this funny cartoon here this is funny
I don't know if it's that funny because it's actually a trouble not funny at all thing
for the doctoral researcher who is in this situation, and maybe many of you, if you've
been to this type of situation, please let us know in the collaborative notes. But here
you see the senior professor saying, don't worry, you know, you don't have to start your
code from scratch, because maybe some postdoc has written all the pipeline for the lab,
but the postdoc most likely has left to another lab. And the professor continues, you can
reuse the software that the previous person on the project wrote several years ago.
And then the doctor researches like, are there instructions for how to use it? I doubt it.
Is the code commented? Not likely. Where are the files? Who knows? But this is going to
be painful, isn't it? It's just a scratch. So I don't know about you, [name], but at
At least I have experienced this at the very beginning of when I started with the research
work.
And of course, here the context of course is academic research, scientific research,
but the same issue could also be applied in companies.
You wouldn't like to deliver a tool, a software tool, where one day you are able to make it
work and another day it's just giving completely different results.
So here are some more scary, funny, but not funny anecdotes in this box here.
So for example, a group of researchers obtain great results and submit their work to high
profile journals.
And then usually after six months, if not even more, depending on the field, the reviewers
finally tell you what's wrong and they ask for tiny changes to the figures or another
analysis.
And then when the people start working on the revisions, they sometimes realize they're
not even able to regenerate the same figures of the submitted version of the paper or then
maybe some data got lost, some code they used to work suddenly doesn't work anymore and
no one can figure out which part of the system stopped working. Why aren't we able to rerun,
know the same code that we did before submitting this paper and this of course lost everything
and in some cases even you know the manuscript actually stays there in the in the file drawer
as this ever happened to you [name] that in this kind of situation
oh yes especially when the when the reviewing process is very long and you basically already
forgot what you what you did like half a year a year ago and then you should fix just a tiny little
thing that the reviewer didn't like or that you maybe noticed even after submission and
can be very painful but it's a hard way of learning also. And you pointed out really well that
it's something that you did which is something that also came out in the first week that
the main collaborator that you have is yourself, and specifically yourself in the future.
So you know that if you document well the software pipeline, if you really write down today
how you created that figure in six months or in one year, your future self most likely will be very
happy that you wrote down these notes, that you made your research reproducible, because this is
is what we're talking about here. And so that, you know, you will not have to restart from
scratch like in this, like in this cartoon here. So most likely you heard about reproducible
research and again, I highly encourage to use our notes, shared notes document where
you can write your experiences on reproducibility in research. And even if you, there's many
nice talks and papers, so if you have a favourite talk or a favourite paper on the topic, please
link it in the collaborative notes.
But in general, kind of this so-called reproducibility crisis started maybe sometimes in 2010.
It kind of started with the field of experimental psychology, where they clearly noticed that
biases, which can be intentional biases or unconscious biases in the research process,
they were making the findings highly, how can I say, variable, basically irreproducible.
So then what you see here in this figure without going deeply into the details is from a survey
that the Nature Journal did in 2016. And so here they asked various scientists in various
fields, how they felt, you know, if they feel that they were struggling in reproducing an
experiment, could be their own experiment, could be some experiment that you read from
a study that you try to reproduce locally. And the sentiment in general across all fields
is that, you know, more than half of the respondents, they were saying that, yes, there is a crisis.
It's impossible to reproduce the top papers in my field. I'm struggling to reproduce
what I did six months ago and so on. So these levels of reproducibility this is something
that is important to understand because often in science what we see is just the tip of
this pyramid. What we see sometimes is just the article and within the article there might
be a description of methods and they might be mentioning although it's very rare if they
they use certain libraries or certain software tools.
But often the kind of this methodological details
down to the kind of to the code or to the computation
they're kind of left to the reader as an exercise.
And unfortunately, that's what makes it really difficult
that sometimes just by reading an article
it's just impossible to replicate what these people did.
So, hopefully an article comes with some documentation, meaning that, you know, the method section
in the article sometimes needs to be expanded so that it can start adding details on which
methods were used, what type of computational, I don't know, solutions were adopted, and
maybe a description, you know, if they are not able to share the data, they could at
least describe how they collected the data, how they measured the phenomena.
But you can already understand that sometimes without code and without data, it's still
impossible to reproduce the article that you're reading.
Some articles, it's a minority, but it's getting more and more popular.
They actually come with code and with the data.
In general, recently in the publication process, many journals are asking for this data availability
statement and code software availability statement exactly for this reason.
if there is a chance that the data can be reused and if it's possible to, you know,
look at the code that was used for the paper. This gives a great, you know, chances that
the whole, that the main results from the article actually reproducible because running
the same data with the same code should hopefully produce the same results. In practice, however,
It's not as simple as that because code on its own tends to depend on multiple libraries,
multiple versions of softwares that one might be using.
And then we have this layer of the environment.
So with the environment here, we don't mean our nature and nurture, but we mean kind of
the computational environment where the code is running, where the data are stored.
So that if one could truly reproduce the same computational environment, bring the same code
and the same data, most likely, if not very often, you are able to obtain the same results.
So this kind of gives the context of the reproducibility and why it's really important in research.
we have a little bit of a discussion item for our collaborative document and so
yeah it is already there and people are already answering so
you can show it a little bit yeah maybe i switch to
so
What are your experiences with re-running or adjusting a script or a figure you created
a few months ago? I really like the figure because I don't know about you [name] but
for me at the beginning at least like I was kind of I'm not saying that I was editing
my figures with Photoshop but for example the arrows they look so I didn't like the
arrows of whatever program I was using in those days and so I was always manually fixing
some arrows or the fonts in the arrows. Have you ever done that? Have you committed this?
This crime, yes. I've also done that. Because also when you're new to using
things like matplotlib in Python or something like this and you don't quite
easily know how to do it, but in some other software it is really just a few clicks to
add an arrow to highlight something, it's a natural step to go. But then it will come to
haunt you at some point, very unlikely. Yeah, I mean, there's not even anything
wrong per se. The issue is that often people don't write down that, after I generated the figure with
with Marble Plate, I open it with Inkscape and I change all the fonts to whatever fancy
font I wanted to use. If people would already document this, then there would already be
a one layer of reproducibility added in this process of the figure. But of course, in general,
I mean, it's clear that if one could create the figure all with the script, then you don't
need to write down whatever manual steps you need to do with Photoshop or Inkscape.
And it's super easy to forget those steps, these manual steps afterwards, because running
the script is easy, but then opening it again in another software is like one more thing
to think about always.
That's in general a big issue with this graphical user interface tools, that of course you can
document all the clicks and buttons that you need to do for re-obtaining the same output,
the same outcome.
sometimes it's difficult and then the interface changes and suddenly you can't, the buttons
are not there where they used to be and you can't do that anymore.
So here people are still writing. Have you continued working from a previous students?
I guess yeah this at least I found it quite common not just in my experience but with
the people that I help in my in my daily work.
It's nice that someone is talking about preregistrations and register report.
I'm one of the strong, strong supporter of this, of this way of doing science.
But maybe the clock is ticking and it's 1021 in Finland.
So if there's nothing else specifically to be mentioning here we could continue with
the next.
So organizing your projects.
Basically this is something that everyone came across that you start your it can be
your doctoral studies, master's thesis, or it can even be that you just joined a new
company and you're working on some software. It all starts with the project organization.
And so of course complex projects might have very complex structures and dependencies and
multiple locations with data and code. But most likely you are starting with your own
project where you are the project manager and the main responsible on the organization
of the project. There's of course hundreds of ways of storing data and organizing your
file system but here in this page we try to kind of give you the basics that are useful
for organizing your project so what you see here this is like a so-called tree view of
a file system where you would have a folder called project name and then inside that folder
there are some subfolders data process data manuscript result and this as SRC which is
like source, source for the code and doc for the documentation.
So of course this is not the only way to structure a project but you understand that let's say
that you win the lottery and you then decide to stop doing research work and you move to
a nice island in the Pacific Ocean and live there happily.
least the next person who will need to you know resume your project kind of gets a clear
idea if already sees the same structure that we see here it's a structure that is familiar
to the new person and then most likely you know there are some notes written on this
readme document that would explain what's in different folders and what is the status
of things and then it's easier for your collaborator basically to continue where the project was
left very different from the situation that we saw in that PhD comic where the poor doctoral
researcher had no idea about even where the files were stored.
So in general, this tracking that we've been covering in the first week, the tracking of
the changes of the code, it starts to now scale in this time scale that we said earlier
is now becoming also tracking of the data,
tracking of the results that, you know,
you might be producing.
And so, basically, I mean, this all fits into the kind of,
into what we were mentioning earlier
that it's not just about the tiny changes,
documenting the tiny changes with the Git version control,
tiny changes to the code,
but also depending on the project,
might also need to version control the data and there are tools for that or version control the
results because you would have more iterations of the same figure and then in the end you want to
keep whatever is the final version of the figure and so on. So when it comes to tools and templates
but maybe before talking about tools and templates we could also ask these couple of questions to
to the people who are watching us.
So how do you collaborate?
They're already being answered.
Okay, that's excellent.
You are so efficient this morning, everyone.
And so the first question that we wrote
in the collaborative notes is,
are you using virtual control for academic papers?
And this is of course very interesting
because now it's not about tracking the changes in the code.
One is actually about tracking, you know,
about changes in the manuscript.
And then the second question is how do you handle collaborative issues, for example conflicting changes.
Maybe before switching to the collaborative notes, I'm going to ask [name], are you using or have you been using some sort of version control for academic papers with your supervisor?
Yeah, like many others also already wrote here, we are currently using mainly Overleaf
for collaboration on academic papers. It's nice because it has the integration with Git
and you can look back in history and all these kind of things. And how we are fixing these
collaborative issues there, like conflicting changes is that, well, everyone sees at all
times like what the others are already working on so there is never that situation that some
change comes out of nowhere but then we also try to first comment like I would like to add this
here and then we all say okay and then we let that person work on on a section for example.
How about you? Yeah I mean I've been working with seniors in my in my in my previous research I
I was doing lots of basically neuroscience and some of the seniors I've been working with that
might not be at the level of technology that they could use, you know, get virtual control
or a system like Overleaf. However, even tools like Microsoft Word or Google Docs,
they also have embedded so-called version tracking or virtual control. So even with graphical tools
like Microsoft Word, you know, it's not the best tool for doing virtual control,
but it's still possible to travel back in time,
see what has changed in the document
and comment on each other
and then work with this type of conflicting changes.
But it's nice that people here are writing their experiences
and also maybe this is a trend that I've noticed
with the new generation of younger PIs and supervisors
that they're more moving towards this type of overleaf
or distributed documents,
distributed tools for for collaborative writing.
So we still a few minutes and there are some very nice links
here that [name] added to this page.
This is something nice that came out last week because last week
we talked about how you can have a repository that is a template
So, that by cloning or forking the template, you can basically work on the folder structure
or existing structure from the template.
And so, here there's a nice collection of templates that by basically by forking them
or by creating a new repository from the template, you are able to get a folder structure that
is similar to the one here.
So, this is good practice that if you're starting a new project, you can actually immediately
start it as a repository as a git repository and for example we can have briefly a look at the
touring way template where you see this type of similar structure there's more subfolders but
you know it doesn't really matter it we clearly see that it's a similar to the structure that
that we were proposing.
More recently, there's also this type
of reproducible publications.
And so Overleaf, the tool that [name] already mentioned,
is an important one, but it's not the only one.
And in general, this is also something
that journals are kind of catching up,
trying to also publish something
that is a little bit more dynamic,
in a sense that now there are publishing platforms
that allow basically to run the code
while you are reading the manuscript.
And so, for example, Jupyter is now
able to be in some publication platform.
They're using it.
I can mention a couple in the neuroscience,
at least in the notes document.
However, it's 10.29, which is exactly one minute
before our planned schedule.
So [name], what are we going to do next?
We actually had five minutes more for the collaborative document, but I think we looked
at it already and there's at least no new questions that need to be answered.
They have already some answer here.
So I think we can go on and then after the next section, we will have a little bit longer
break also to collect our thoughts.
So I will take the screen share from you, built-in display, just move the Zoom stuff
out of the way and show you the next section.
So please continue answering in our collaborative documents the question that we already have
there.
collection to look through also after the workshop of what kind of experiences have
different people made and how they solved it. Our next section will be about recording
computational steps. So we probably all have been in that situation that we have some steps that
we need to do in order to do our works. Like [name] mentioned before, the plotting can be
one of these steps. Before that we probably need to process our data in some way that already makes
two steps and there is probably many different ways of how we can record these kind of steps
that we need to run one after another and in which order and how they are connected.
And one way of doing this are workflow tools and that is what this next section will be about.
And that is one way of how these steps can be recorded also in a reproducible manner.
And for that section, just find my mouse, we will take a look at an example project
that we have in our code refinery space. It's called WordCount.
You can see here it has like a lightweight structure that [name] discussed before.
Here also we have some code data, some other folders and then some more files.
And we'll look into those a little bit more in a bit.
So first this repository provides us with some code that takes in some data.
And the data is also part of the repository, which are book texts.
And then it provides us with some code.
Maybe we can take a brief look here.
So in the data section, we have four texts that contain the text of a book.
And then when we go into the code section, we have two scripts.
Those are small Python scripts.
And no worries if you don't use Python in your work.
You don't have to understand what's happening here.
Basically, the name already tells a little bit
about this story.
So we have a count script, which counts
the number of times each word appears in a file.
And in this case, we want to know
how many times each word appears in each of these books.
And that gives us then the word and the count.
And then the second step in this workflow
that we'll be working with today is
plotting this frequency of the 10 most used words
in these books.
So a pretty simple workflow.
First, we analyze the data, then we plot the data.
And there can be many more, of course,
but this now just simplified to look at it.
There is also mentioned in this readme here
that there is dependencies,
and this is something that we will look at
a little bit later in this lesson.
So for now, we can maybe ignore it
because I will demo this now here.
If you want to run this on your own computer later,
then you can have a look at this environment file
and see what to do with it.
And you will learn that in the later lesson.
And so in our case, we have kind of a given structure
of how we run these things,
because we first have to count the words
and store that somehow.
And then we need to use that data to plot
the frequency of each words.
And one way of how we can do that,
and which is maybe the first thing that comes to our mind
is to just run one Python code after another
with the inputs and the outputs.
So let's do that.
I will move this aside.
The link to this repository is in the collaborative document
so you can follow there.
I hope you now see my, yes, you see my command line.
So I have my terminal here.
I've cleaned it up a little bit and then I also have down here,
for example, what if I type something here,
you can see the command I typed in the bottom
just so that you can follow along a little bit better.
Let's now first do what we learned last week.
First, we get the code to our computer by using git clone.
I'll get the link from outside of your screen, I'm sorry.
Hit clone, paste the link, okay, and then we go into the word count directory.
Okay, so now we can take a look that all this information is really here.
We have the code, the data directories, we have some other files.
Everything is here.
If we now want to run,
for example, our Python code on one book,
we can copy the line for
the Python code from the readme file,
which was something like this here.
We call Python, we call the script that we have.
We want to run it on the book called IELTS.txt,
And we want to store that those results in the statistics
out of the data.
OK, that didn't take long.
And now we can, for example, look with any kind of tool
what we have in statistics out of the data.
So there we now see the is 3,822 times in that book.
then the next one is off, and so on.
This will probably look quite similar for the different books,
but we still want to get these names.
What we can do now is we can also plot the whole thing in similar way.
Luckily, the readme already provided us with these code lines,
so we can copy them from there.
Here, it looks a little bit different,
So we call Python on the plot.py script.
We have an input data file,
which is our statistics.data,
and then a plot file where we want to store the plot.
So we can run that as well.
Yep.
And then we can take a look with this program,
for example, to show the plot.
And let me just check that you can see this.
Yes.
So this is one of the plots, what we want to have.
In our case, we now have four books.
So it seems easy enough that we just run
these Python scripts one after another for these different books.
Then we could make ourselves a note,
we ran Python script 1, 2,
3, or we can even write them down.
We could even collect them in a bash script or some other kind of script.
It could be a Python script or something else where we just
record running one script after another.
We also have that actually in this repository.
It's called runall.sh.
So there you can see now we have multiple rows of the same stuff.
So we have Python, code count i,
and then one book after another, we run through.
Then the same for the plot lines,
we plot one after another.
So that would be one way of recording these computational steps.
One shorter way, because you maybe are looking at this and you're saying,
okay, we could also do this a little bit shorter.
Yes, we can. We can, for example,
loop through the different files that we have in our data directory,
and then apply each script on each book file automatically.
That would then look something like this, a little bit shorter.
Don't worry about the bash.
we just have here a for loop and we loop through all these four books and then we apply these
count.py and then plot.py on our files. So [name] what do you say this is now more reproducible?
Are we there? Can we stop here? I mean already this is quite an advanced project in a sense that
that I can see from what you've been describing that we're trying to remove the human from
running the script, from the interaction with the data, because often when I inherit some
code from some project, and even me, myself, I'm responsible of that, instead of having
a generic plot.py, I have been having plot underscore book1.py, and there inside I would
have hardcoded the name of book1, and then it would be silly that I need to create many
plot underscore book two plot underscore book three so this project is already excellent that
this plot and count they're like functions modular that then depending on the input they can be they
can be rerun but they should that maybe i would criticize on the reproducibility what if the books
would be 1000 that you know sometimes these four loops with this bash terminal scripting you know
maybe something dies with one of these 1000 books, is there a better way for, you know,
scaling kind of in a more reproducible way? Yeah, good that you're asking. Of course,
we also have a better way or a way that helps with some of the issues that you have mentioned here.
and so now we are going from basically saying do this and then that so in this
case we said first count the words how often they occur in the
text and then plot it. We describe the dependencies between those plots because
Here we can see that the second one requires the first one to be run because we need the
output of the first script to be produced before we can even run the plot.py file.
Workflow tools are one set of tools that can help with that so that you don't have to worry
to make clear, run this and that, but you state, okay, this plot requires count to be run,
so the workflow tool figures out how it can do that and how it can connect these different steps
that you have in your workflow. And one example workflow tool that we will be looking at
that today is SnakeMake.
It's one of many tools to create
this reproducible and scalable data analysis workflows.
In the case of SnakeMake,
we can already take a peek here in the repository.
We scroll up.
There's something called a snake file ready for us.
It describes the workflow in a human readable way,
but that also the machine can deal with.
This is a Python-based language,
but you can run all kinds of script with it.
In our example, we run a Python script,
but you can run also R scripts or
any other language that you might be working with.
One nice thing about this SnakeMake workflows is that they can
scale rather seamlessly from your own laptop to
high-performance computing cluster or the Cloud without the need
to modify this SnakeMake file.
While when you are running some other kind of script,
you might have to modify things there to be able to run it like in a different environment.
There was one question in the collaborative document,
what's a script?
The answer is pretty good.
So we collect all the commands that we want to run
into one file and have a series of instructions there,
similar to like a cooking recipe, for example, where it's described like what you need to do
and step by step. Okay, then the snake make file. So, you can see it here. Maybe I
make it a little bit bigger still. So, we can find already some things that we have seen before.
For example, we have our Python script mentioned here,
the countered pi, the plot.pi,
we have our data files mentioned here.
The way this is set up,
so this is already set up for us for
the workflow that we just showed.
The first thing here is that we define variable data with
snakeMakeSpecific function that finds us all the book titles
in our data directory that end with the extension text.
Then we only want the title of that book in this data variable.
Then we have a so-called rule-based system here.
So in general, every rule within SnakeMake has an input,
which is according to what we also were calling it.
There's some questions about what is SnakeMake,
like didn't understand that, and reasons
for computational steps.
So could you?
Sorry.
Oh, wait.
It's like the last two questions.
our SnakeMaker is used for.
It's for recording the computational steps in a different manner.
Maybe this becomes clear now when we go through it a little bit better.
What is the main reason for recording computational steps?
That we can reproduce our computational workflow also later.
So if we would now just run.
Let me just show this again if we or if we
would just run our one Python script after another.
Then we would.
Maybe forget like what did we actually run and in
what order did we run those?
So we try to write it down somewhere and one
way is to put those calls into a script that
we then store.
For example, alongside our data.
or in our repository.
I hope that answers.
But at least the snake make what it's used for.
I hope that will become clear during this section.
If not, please move the question to the bottom again,
and we'll try to explain it in more detail.
So the snake file contains of rules.
And every rule, as a minimum, needs an input.
Or every rule has an input, an output, and a shell command,
every normal rule.
So we define what kind of things does this rule need to run.
And in this case, we need this Python script.
And then we need the book file defined.
So now there's some questions like snake make
versus a script that runs stuff in a loop.
We will also get back to that a little bit after this demo.
OK, yeah, so we'll see.
Good.
What are the differences?
and it might also be like this is one example of a workflow tool and it might help you in some ways
but it's not the solution to everything like if you only have a few steps in your workflow and
little input files and are very sure that you will never have to like run it on many many more files
for example then probably SnakeMake or any other workflow tool is overkill and like you can just
run it by using a script instead of like kind of adding this another layer of complexity
that you do with the workflow tool. Okay I'll get back to the other questions
afterwards but yeah please keep them coming. So we have our rule that we call count words
where we have our Python script for counting our input file.
We define what is the output file.
In this case, it's collected in this statistics folder
with the same name as the input file and the data extension.
And then here we define this very same call
that we also had in our script before.
And we use these wildcards for that.
So we don't need to write out this here,
but it will be filled in
when SnakeMake is running automatically.
And then we have a second rule here for making a plot,
which takes in also the script again, a book.
This time it is the output of the previous script here.
This is the important part for Snake Make to figure out how to
run these scripts and how to deal with the data that you give it.
Then we have output file,
which is the plot, and again,
the Python call in this case.
Here you can see that it's not like Python specific,
but you could have any other shell commands here.
Then we have this overarching rule here called all,
which is basically that collects
everything that is to be done in this workflow.
It waits for inputs to be there that are the statistics,
the data file, this book.data file,
and the plot figure.
Let's get back to that in a moment.
Let's first maybe run this once.
SnakeMake can be run with the command SnakeMake,
and then we have to give it how many cores to use for this run.
Then right now, because I have already processed one of the files manually,
we first delete all output.
I have forgotten that I need to go into my Konda environment,
and [name] will tell you what that is after the break.
I have to first Konda activate
Code Refinery environment to make my SnakeMake available.
Now I can run the delete all outputs command.
It tells me something about building DAG of jobs.
We'll get to that in a moment.
Then it deletes all the outputs of
previous runs that are also part of the repository.
So we want to now see what SnakeMake does when we run it.
So we have this snake file in the base repository.
So we can run SnakeMake like this.
And then it tells us a lot of things.
And for some reason, this is not updating.
I'm sorry for that.
I hope it's slow enough to follow along
if you want to do that later.
So I'm scrolling up to what SnakeMake actually told me.
So here, it's, again, building this DAG of jobs.
And that is how SnakeMake figures things out how to run.
So it will first go and look at the all rule.
what are the expected inputs for this very last rule.
And then it will go further up or look at the other rules.
Where do these files actually come from?
Where is this plot produced?
And then it will run, try to run that rule.
And then it will notice that, okay, for creating the plot,
we actually need the data first.
So we need to have counted the frequencies of the word first.
So then it will find the rule
where that is the output and run that.
And it summarizes this all here.
So we have the name of the rules,
all it found out that it needs to run it once
to collect all the outputs.
Then we have the count word rule,
that it figured out because there is four books.
It needs to run it four times
and the same for the make plot.
And then it tells us why it ran each step that it ran.
So it figured out statistics IELTS.data
is not existing at the moment.
So it finds out what it needs to run
to bring it into existence.
And that is then step one out of nine, and then it checks further what to execute and goes on and on.
And one thing to note here is that there is different job IDs that are not necessarily in order,
So it will figure out that for each book it first needs to run the statistics file and then the plot file.
But it does not necessarily run first the statistics file and then the plot file for each book.
But it may mix it up a little bit so that it runs first two books, the statistics file and then one of these plots and then another of the statistics and another one of these plots.
and that it all gets to know through this snake file.
Now I see that I'm already very short on time,
basically already over,
so I will check what I wanted to show here still.
We could now go and check that all the files are there.
Maybe for right now you can trust me that it
created all the plots and all the statistics files.
And now the power of SnakeMake comes really from this
that if we now had a script that would run all these steps,
and we now added a new file, for example.
Let's do this briefly.
There's a question, the last one.
Yeah.
Maybe useful to go now I don't understand this code how come it runs for multiple books the files only run once
Oh
Um, which code is maybe like in the snake file
I assume maybe it was talking about the snake file or something. Like how does the snake file run for all the separate codes?
Okay, this is figured out in the snake file by using these wildcards.
So in this step here, it figures out what all text files are available in this data
directory.
So it knows that there is four right now.
And in the command line, it showed us, like, for each of the books that it ran it, like,
for Sierra was one book, last something was some book.
So we can see that it actually ran it for all the files.
So if we now, this same thing we can do with a script.
But if we now have a new data file, for example,
this, don't worry about the editor.
It is now just an editor.
And there is some text in here, is some text in here,
which I would like my script to count and plot.
And I save that.
In the script case, I now would need to run my script again,
or I would need to run the steps separately again.
In the SnakeMake case, if I now run SnakeMake again,
you could maybe see it was very fast,
that it now was a little bit faster.
And we can see in the job statistics
here that it figured out that it only
need to run one file and that is,
you can find it here probably,
the new.txt, so it found there's
one new file that it has not processed all the way,
so it processed only the new file.
The same thing happens also if there would now be,
for example, a change in one of the scripts.
Let's say in the plot script,
We don't want to plot the script,
the bars in blue,
but want to put them in red, for example.
We would go into the script and change it.
If we then tell SnakeMake to run again,
it will figure out which files are affected by this change.
It will figure out that it will not have to run
all the statistics again, but only the plotting.
And that is, unfortunately, the time over for this topic.
If you're interested in this, I would highly recommend to go on the lesson page.
is also the example and some discussions around it and all the steps that I had planned to do now
and that I didn't get through are mentioned also here and also some more explanations of each
of the rules and then also take a look at the solution how to do it. You can also visualize
this workflow, this DAG directed acyclic graph, what SnakeMake is using in the background.
And we are using SnakeMake here because compared to many other workflow tools, it has a rather
gentle learning curve. I understand that this was probably a little bit confusing. Sorry
for that. But if you take a look and try to apply it yourself, I think you will better
understand how things are connected and why this could be a benefit for also your workflow.
You can use it on many different platforms. SnakeMake is also very smart in a way that
it can figure out if there is independent steps that it can run those in parallel.
You can also run it with the next two topics of this lesson, the isolated environments and
also containers. It's very much used in bioinformatics, but as you can see, we can
use it for counting words as well, so it's not specific to bioinformatics, so you can run all
kinds of workflows with it and they have a super extensive documentation with lots of videos and
lots of tutorials going on and there is lots of similar tools that you can also find here
that you can use for that. So we can collect these computational steps in many many ways
and workflow tools may be able to help with doing this and I will still go
through the questions and look at it but I think now we should take a break, right?
Yes, thanks [name]. I think now we can have a break, 10 minutes break, so we can be back
on the stream at 11. What is that? Finnish time 11.14. And I can write this in the notes.
Thank you.
Hello, and welcome back.
So hopefully you're all still well motivated
to make your work more reproducible.
So it's really nice that there's many questions on this topic
that we've been covering so far.
And compared to previous rounds of the Code Refinery Workshop,
I think this is great that we decided
to focus more on giving you demos and showing you the tools,
because then the questions are actually more you know at the general level that rather than trying
to you know rerun the same scripts that [name] was running for example and focusing on specific
errors that are not related to this topic and in general we will have time to answer all these
questions with more details during the longer break and all the answers of course will be
archive so hopefully this is a great resource for your for your future learning goals.
All right so we kind of if we go back to this time scales of tracking changes and making things that
you can rerun what you did six months ago or a year ago after tracking the tiny changes
with the version control from week one then we look at kind of recording the steps because
Because in some cases, maybe, you know, there's just a single script that you need to run.
There's just a single data file that you need to load.
And maybe that is the single step of your research.
But in many cases, one needs to, like we saw with the books, run through 1,000 books or
1,000 parameters, hyperparameters, 1,000 whatever training input files in machine learning.
So then the computational steps and all the steps
that one needs to record, they start to scale up,
that it starts to become impossible to manually remember
that you still need to run whatever permutation, 1,555.
But then in general, if we keep on increasing the time scale,
so what we're trying to document and what
are trying to record, then we go at the time scale of the system of the project. So in
this funny XKCD figure here, this is not just about actually scientific research. This is
in practice when it comes about any modern digital infrastructure can be popular social
media that you use or, I don't know, your email service provider. So people, companies
and scientists and researchers they build on top of other people's work and sometimes
you know there might be a tiny little element that is literally keeping all the infrastructure
together and when it comes to scientific research and scientific code of course you want to
document if you truly depend on that little you know project that some random person in
Nebraska has been maintaining since 2003. In the Internet, actually, there's one tool
very useful in the Internet, which is called Curl. And for many years, the Curl command
has been basically maintained by a single person for free, even though it's one of
those core elements that is inside any software that uses the Internet, basically.
So continue with kind of the kitchen analogy because we always like to talk about cooking.
So this also came up in the collaborative notes that if the software, if the code is
like the recipe, so they're like the steps that you need to run to cook whatever you're
planning to cook and if the data are like the ingredients that you need to mix together
to obtain what you want to cook then we have the so-called libraries or modules or whatever
you want to call them that they're like the cooking books because most likely you don't
want to write your own cooking book you don't want to write your recipe you want to reuse
an existing recipe and libraries maybe many of you are familiar with the Python programming
language most likely you're using libraries like NumPy or pandas or matplotlib so that you don't
need to write in pure python you know how to take care of big matrices or how to work with
tabular data but you can easily reuse existing libraries so that you can focus on the actual
you know enjoyment of the final cook cooked product rather than you know focusing or rewriting
something that already exists so with this specific page here with this
specific lesson we're trying to understand that there needs to be a way
when we want to document all our process all our steps there also needs to be a
way to document how we depend on other libraries because maybe today there's a
certain version of NumPy and it might be that in one year or in five years from
now that version will have drastic changes to the current version that is right now and then
your code will not be able to run anymore because it was depending on these external libraries.
So to understand this in a more practical way and here I'm asking the help of [name]
to do this exercise together. So let's consider this so-called WebRotier time capsule of
of dependencies. So that could be that. All right. You inherit some code from the previous
postdoc of the research lab that you're joining and all you see in the code that there's a
couple of imports of some libraries. So that's it. You don't really know which libraries
the codes need but you just see maybe like in the Python case would be you see some import
NumPy. Then you have another a little better case maybe or is it better where with the
code there's also a readme file which basically writes down you know you really need NumPy
for this for this project. But it doesn't mention which NumPy do I need the NumPy from
2011. Did it even exist or you know a NumPy from 2024. Then you might find you might be
more lucky and with the project that you inherit you might find that there's also some sort
of a structure file this specific file format is this is just a text file but it's called
YML yet another markup language and the YAML file is just a way to basically write in a
in a way that is machine readable something that also a human can understand and this specific
case we don't need I'm not going to tell you right now what this means but at least you see that
here we explicitly say that we have our code depends on having NumPy and
and SciPy and SumPy and other Python projects and here interesting actually they even have
references to some git projects. So in this case, [name], would this mean that
this dependency file is also referring to a specific branch in a specific project, isn't it?
Yeah, to the master branch in the GitHub repository of some user called some project.
Okay, so then if I inherit this file with all the other files of the project, then I would know that
i also need to figure out how to basically git clone this branch from this project and
make sure that it's visible with the rest of the libraries but we have more cases in this
challenge in this case this is a similar file than the one before but i see some differences
there's more added numbers so [name] do you think or at least i guess that these are the
numbers is more like trying to fix the version what I was saying earlier that maybe one really
needs to have version 1.16 but what about this this thing that you see at the end of the git url
yeah because if you don't have the versions then you usually get like the latest possible the
latest that is available and that of course might change between years or even already weeks and
And then for Git, now we are not referring to a branch anymore,
but we are referring to a specific commit.
And we have learned about commits and also tags
last week.
So it's way more specific than referring to, especially
the master branch, which also is something
like the tool might have developed over time.
So the master branch might not be the same
as it was a week ago, a month ago, a year ago.
But the commit stays or the tag stays.
So that basically we are literally
traveling to the exact time point
where the project, some project, had a specific tag
or specific time point.
And then the last case, if you see what I see,
that now this some project and this another project,
now they have their own version.
So most likely here, the person who
were working with this project, they also made a release
and they gave it a tag name that is, in this case,
the number of the release.
So that it can be made more clear in this dependency.
So now we have these five scenarios.
And in your opinion, [name], which version
do you expect would be the easiest to rerun and why?
I would choose version E, because there you have actually all packages, so also the things
that were in version D and the previous one were on GitHub only and linked to there, and
linking to some cryptic commit hash or something now have versions, so they have been packaged,
it's like a much nicer way of referring to them. But already D is very good, I think, in terms of
reproducibility because you have the version. So even if you run this one year from now,
that old version will hopefully still be available somewhere so you can still use it.
Whereas when you don't specify the version and rely on the latest and greatest, then that might
be have more features or have like good stuff coming with it as well but it might also have
deprecated so some functionality just doesn't exist anymore or has been replaced with a different
function call or something like this so there can be issues coming from that as well. How about you?
Yeah I mean I kind of naively thought that the C would be the way to go because I get the latest
of whatever the latest NumPy, the latest Python and the latest, you know, but if I, and I've
been working with this type of, you know, get the latest of everything, but then suddenly
things don't work when you get the latest of everything, then you need to go and track
in this some project that actually they clearly specify it stopped working after NumPy went
to whatever version.
So long story short what we're trying to motivate you here and I can tell you this is so important
if that's one of the things you need to remember from today and if you want to learn one thing
from today learn this. This is absolutely one of the most asked questions that we get
in our support work at Aalto and in anywhere and it's the versioning of the dependencies.
So there's one tool there's various tools for doing that and some tools are specific
of some programming language here for the purpose of focusing on a single one we will
talk about Conda.
And so Conda is this type of tool that can be used with Python but not only with Python
Conda can also be used with R for example it's one tool that is able to track this type
of dependencies.
So what you saw here in this YAML file,
these are actually machine-readable files
so that the Conda program is able to read these
and, for example, create a so-called Conda environment
with the specific version.
Now, what maybe some people struggle
at the beginning to understand what
are Conda environments or Python virtual environments,
I usually give this example that in one operating system,
you might have one installation of Python.
and that has a specific Python version
and it has some library with it.
By adding more environments,
it's like that you're reinstalling Python.
You are installing a new version of Python
without a set of libraries.
And with this type of virtual environments,
you can have multiple versions of Python,
for example, installed in your computer.
And it's actually a great thing.
One could argue that, is it that I'm wasting disk space?
Sure, maybe, you know, you are wasting some disk space,
but we're still talking about small files, small library.
The price of wasting some disk space
and having multiple versions of Python
storing your system is that actually you can have
for different project their own specific
Conda environment, their own specific Python installation.
And so you're sure that, you know, for that project
you can work with a specific Python version.
Here we see 3.10 and some specific, you know,
NumPy, or whatever libraries you need to use.
And the second advantage of using virtual environment
is also, of course, the portability,
because I might now start a new project today
with this type of dependency.
I don't really need to fix NumPy and Pandas,
because I'm happy with whatever I'm starting today,
the new project, so just give me the latest.
But then I might want to move this project to another system,
or I might want to share this project with a colleague.
And so it's possible to so-called
freeze the environment, meaning that with some commands
after activating the environment or after going
inside this other installation of Python,
then I can also tell, ask the program,
give me all the libraries that have been installed so far.
So how are we doing with the timings?
I guess, do we have time that I will give a quick demo of this?
Or?
Go ahead, a quick one.
OK.
So let me get the right windows.
So in this white window, you see where I'm going to type.
And in the bottom window, you see the comments
that I've been typing.
So here I have this file that you saw there, myenv.yaml, and now what I'm able to do is that
with the command that you see here I'm able to actually create this environment. Specifically
now instead of typing the same command that you see there, conda env create, so start a new
environment, I will actually use a program called Mamba and we listed it there. It's basically like
conda but it's again one of those tools that you should learn about it's a it's a conda that is
being rewritten in c so that it's much faster than the conda otherwise i timed it yesterday it
would take 20 minutes for conda to to resolve this environment with mamba it takes maybe less than a
a minute. So mambaenv create and then I specify this file. So now what happens is that it's
basically first seeing what type of request, what type of libraries I'm requesting. But of course
you understand that even though I'm requesting only Python and NumPy, Pandas and Seaborn, so very
basic stuff. These tools themselves, they might depend on other, many other libraries because,
I don't know, Seaborn needs to depend on Matplotlib plus some other opening some specific
file formats, figure formats or writing in different figure formats. So in the end, actually,
this Mamba is now installing 72 packages. So there's actually 72 libraries that are needed
for this specific environment for this specific project and now it's downloading and extracting
all the packages and now the environment is ready so right now i'm not in that specific
environment so as you see here at the end i need to activate the the environment so i activate it
And in the name of the environment, it's called myenv.
So now the prompt has changed.
If you have worked with Python and specifically from the terminal, you might be familiar with
this, but if you have not, this is something that is worth investing some time and learning
about the Conda environments.
And now it's like I connected to a new system with a new Python installation, and specifically
the new Python installation that I asked with all the dependencies and now here I'm able let's say
that I have to pass this environment to [name] so I'm able to type this command conda m export
and this will show all the files all these 72 packages that were installed and you see that
there's quite many of them and now it even has so-called resolved down to the tiny version
out even to, you know, to some specific hash of which version of CBOR am I going here. So with
the syntax that you see here in the learning materials conda m export and this greater than
it means dump the content that you see here on a file environment.yml. There's an easter egg here
that one can also one can also export from history and this is again important to look
at this so let me try running also this command
and now the difference from this command is that actually this kind of is able to give
me back the original environment that I used. So with conda-envexport I got a fine-grained
detailed version down to the tiny hashtag hashes of all the 72 packages. With conda-envexport
from history maybe this is useful for the next project that I can start. I hope this
This was, you know, motivational enough for people to get started using Conda, but this
is, again, I repeat, the most frequently asked question every day.
We even have a joke in our support room that how many days have been going on without Conda
being mentioned, and usually it's zero.
But if we scale down even more, so now we're trying to look at the dependencies of the code,
dependency of all the libraries. What if we scale even bigger, [name]?
I can keep the screen share if you just tell me when to scroll or do you want to take over?
No, you can keep it. You can scroll down a little bit. So yeah, so now we have been talking about
how to record the computational steps, how to record our dependencies of the tools that we are
already using in our workflow,
but what if it's still not enough?
What if we want everything in one file?
What if we want an entire operating system
together with the dependencies,
with the code, maybe even with the data?
That's where containers come in.
Now, we also get back to the icebreaker
before, like this topic of it works on my machine.
And these containers are like one of the answers to that.
And there's many different like tools
for building using containers.
One of them is Docker.
That's where this meme here comes from.
And if you scroll a little bit down,
we can again think back to our kitchen analogy
that we have our codes and scripts,
which are basically our cooking recipes.
They tell us what goes into our dish and how to prepare it.
Then we talk in the world of containers,
we talk about container definition files,
or in the Docker case,
it would be called a Docker file.
They are like a blueprint,
how to build a kitchen with everything in it,
that you have everything ready to prepare the dish that
is described that you have in your cooking recipe.
So the container definition file is the blueprint.
It shows us how to create this kitchen.
Then container images are
then example kitchens that are built from this blueprint.
Now you scrolled away from there, sorry.
Then we have the containers themselves,
which are built from the images,
from the example kitchens,
that are really the kitchens
where you can prepare these cooking recipes.
And you can go through here, these images
and have a guess which of the images
represents which operating system.
Containers can come to you in many different forms
and in many different occasions,
you may have come across them.
And that's why we also ask this question
in the very bottom of the collaborative document.
if you ever have been in contact with containers and how you came across them,
because that can be very different for people.
Please go and answer that question if you have come across containers,
because that might also help others to see where are
the use cases for this kind of systems.
The benefit is that you have really everything in one file,
not just the dependencies, but really,
like you can have a whole different operating system.
Like if your laptop is running on Windows, for example,
and you find a tool on the internet
where you only can find installation instructions
or prepared software for Linux system, for example,
that might be one case where then a container
can be very helpful to like have this operating system
that you need to then install your software
inside of there and run it via that.
These definition files that already mentioned what
we related to the blueprints,
they are usually text files,
and a little bit further down,
we have an example of that,
and [name] will show it also in a little bit.
They instruct you how to build this environment.
What do you need?
What kind of operating system do you use?
What kind of software do you want to have installed in that environment?
And then when you build an image from that definition file,
from this container recipe, that is then basically like a piece of paper
where you have the operating system and these base tools installed on it.
And then whatever you do then on your command line or on your computer
within that container,
then you're adding a layer of transparency.
Maybe you have seen it when you want to
update your house or something like this.
You have the blueprint of the house in the bottom,
and then you add a transparent layer where you draw
all your ideas that you want to add to your house,
that you want to add a staircase in the middle of
your living room just to try how it looks.
Then at some point, you're like,
oh no, that's not the idea.
I throw that away.
That is also then why the image,
the container image, it always stays the same.
These transparency layers, they are then thrown away after you
close the connection to that container that you're running.
Other use cases for containers are exactly this.
If you have your code and that runs in a certain environment
and you want to make sure that everyone is using the same environment,
you can provide them with an image of this container
or you can provide them with this definition file,
like the instructions on how to build that image
and how to run that in a container.
Here is now the example of a definition file.
This is now from Singularity.
I mentioned already Docker and then there's
also Obtainer and Portman and probably even more than that.
But these are, I think, the most famous ones maybe.
This you may come across also when you're
working on clusters, for example.
It's very much used there.
And here you can see that this definition file is a text file
similar to what we have seen with Conda.
We are defining like the operating system first.
Here we are using a Docker image
that is somewhere on the Docker hub.
I think it's called of Ubuntu,
which is a Linux operating system.
So if [name] would, for example, have a Windows laptop
and would want to run an Ubuntu on that laptop,
you could use this file to build a container to run Ubuntu in.
Then you can provide a few more things that you want to add there,
so you can define environment variables,
you can install stuff which is done here in this post section,
And then you can also add scripts that should be run when the container is executed.
And is that now maybe where we go into the demo?
Maybe we can come back to the pros and cons of containers when we start wrapping things up.
So I think that this demo is a funny one.
So, in this specific container recipe that you see here, basically the user wants to
run the command, the Linux command cow say, which is a funny command that it displays
some ASCII, ASCII art, ASCII cow that can say whatever you tell the cow to say.
However, if I would be working on my own computer, I would have all the rights to install this
specific Kause command and I wouldn't need to, you know, start containers, install containers,
create the containers. But often when I need to scale because my laptop is old and it doesn't
have enough RAM or enough CPUs, I'm most likely going to work on some remote machine.
It can be one HPC cluster, it can be the Lumi supercomputer, it can be various things.
So let's now go to this remote machine where I am right now. I could even call that deactivate.
OK. Let's see where I am. I have a subfolder called the pen sorry environments because now this is the stage where we're really recording the whole environment operating system.
So if I try to run the command, which is called Kausei,
hello world.
All right, the command is not installed in this remote
machine.
I could now open a ticket with the administrator
of this remote cluster and ask them,
can you please install Kausei?
Of course, maybe I feel a bit silly
because it's a silly command.
Maybe I don't want to ask the administrators to install
this type of thing.
But it could also well be that the administrator actually
not supporting installations because they get too many requests and what the administrator
could tell you, you know, create yourself a container so that you can run this command.
So given this recipe that I've written here in this kaose.dev, so this is the same recipe
that you see there and it's again another one of those machine readable format,
machine readable and also human readable that the human understand that we want to use Ubuntu
get and it's like really that I'm installing a new Linux machine and make sure that I run
this type of installation script. So let's build it. So the software that I'm going to
use now all the steps that I'm talking about the year they're listed in this exercise
two in the in the page. So the tool I'm going to use is called Obtainer. Let's see that I have it.
Yes, I have Obtainer 1.2. And so Obtainer is one of those tools that kind of emerged from
the Singularity project. Obtainer became more like the branch dedicated to scientific computing
while Singularity CE is more supporting enterprises.
I left this here because these are something
that often is problematic because Obtainer
to create the images and it's to download,
you really need to imagine that you are downloading
a full operating system.
So it can require lots of disk space,
but I already set this step here.
So I can look at the environment variables
in my in my and I already have set this temporary folder and and a cache folder and now I can
finally build. So now it's like I'm installing this new computer. So obtainer build the name
of the image that I'm going to create is this CIF and then the definition file is cow say
all right so now what is happening it's really like that i'm connecting to a
new laptop and i'm installing the operating system
so first it needs to download the image of the operating system
it's now installing everything that is needed for ubuntu
in this operating system it's installed it's really so fast
it's installing all the kaos and everything else
it's making sure that you know the file system of this computer of this virtual
virtual computer is you know has everything that is needed installing some other dependencies and
hopefully in the very next few seconds it will say that this is done and I can now basically
like connect to this computer it's funny that I'm still in the same computer so now it's actually
creating this this file so now this CIF file becomes like a new computer that I can log in
into. And when I'm inside this new computer, even though it's a virtual computer, it's not a physical
computer, I'm able to finally run the cowsay command. So I remind you that we are where I am
when I type cowsay, command not found, but now I can actually enter this computer, this virtual
machine, this container, obtainer shell, and the name of the image that I created.
it. And now I'm inside. You see the prompt change. It says obtainer. Now I'm in a new
computer and now I can test the command. Let's see if it works. Yes. And we got our cow that
can say whatever we want to say. So suddenly without any administrator rights without any
special permissions I was able to install a new program and run it. You can understand
and how powerful this is if you depend on specific,
especially in machine learning,
people need to work with some specific version
of libraries PyTorch,
which might depend on specific version
of so-called CUDA GPU card drivers.
And with this system,
you can specifically go down to the drivers,
down to the libraries for your research work.
So it's 11.49.
We still have good 10 minutes for wrapping up.
So [name], what about the pros and the cons of containers?
Yeah, one nice thing here is now also
that even if something goes wrong, because it still might,
there is so many levels where these things can go wrong.
Because everything is now in one file,
it is very easy to remove, rather than if you think about
if you install something on your computer,
you might have to go into different places
to find all the files that were actually
involved in the installations you're working on at the moment.
Then also, many of us are nowadays working with huge datasets,
and sometimes these datasets are getting too large to transfer.
So containers are also one way
of sending the computer to the data, so to say.
So we don't have to download the data,
but there's probably some Cloud service that is set up,
where you can then like run your container very close to the data and don't have to worry about
this transfer. And then if it's like if you have a lot of dependencies in your in your work
you can take away some of these challenges to deal with these dependencies because they might
be on different levels. It might not just be like within Python that you can solve with Conda but
already like on operating system level there might be some libraries that you need that you need to
install in some certain way to make it work. So this is also one way of like recording on how
this can be done and also then with the image you can actually provide a working machine so to say.
So it also can solve this works on my machine situation. And then [name] could now send this
this C file that he just created to me and I could probably run it here on my computer
and also like happily look at the cow saying different things even though I don't have
it installed on my computer. But then of course with this same thing you can also like solve
your installation problems by hiding them behind this kind of container solution,
which may discourage good software development practices.
Of course, we hope it doesn't,
but it may result in that.
It can, of course, then also change that.
Now, we don't have this works on my machine problem anymore,
but we have this,
okay, it works only in this container.
and then if you have a colleague who for some reason
cannot install this container software
on their laptop or something,
how do they then deal with this?
But it still helps with this works on my machine problem.
They can sometimes be difficult to modify.
So if you, for example, go on Docker Hub
and find some image that does almost what you wanna do,
do but not quite there's something missing it can be sometimes difficult to modify those
and there's many different ways on how you can go about this by for example just adding another
layer on top of that image that already exists if that works for your use case and then
In the similar as with Conda environments, also container images can become very large.
They may take up a lot of space on your laptop.
So it's always good with all these tools to, as one of the first things that you find out,
find out how to clean up unused images, unused containers, not running containers, things
that you don't need anymore, how to clean the cache so that you don't run out of disk
space because you need to try 10 different operating systems with your software.
And then good little red box, do you have anything to say about the danger, [name]?
Well, I mean, that in general, it's like when you install software, you might only want
to make sure that you're using official and trusted images,
that you never know what you might be installing
if you use an untrusted source for, let's say,
Ubuntu operating system.
So this is, as usual, it's good to trust those trusted images.
And if you are not sure, talk with your local helper
or colleague.
In the same page, there are also some other demos
that you can try yourself.
For example, if you install Docker on your machine,
here, there's a nice demo where you
can travel back in time to a specific version of RStudio.
And here, we've done a conda, with conda,
basically, that you can install a specific version.
But maybe it's time to wrap up.
So where do we go from here?
I checked the notes document.
I don't see there are many nice questions, interesting
questions, but we will answer them there.
I think it's now too important, though,
to understand that now we discover
and we uncovered all these timescales
of the documentation of the project
from the tiny changes of the Git
down to the large changes of operating system
and libraries that are in a specific version
of our OpenStreetMap system.
So in general, the take-home message for you
is that this is important for every project,
but the second important take-home message here
is that you don't need to feel anxious or stressful
or stressed about all this, you know,
knowledge and all these tools.
It might well be that some of the tools
that we show here today,
you don't see an immediate use right now.
It's more than it becomes you,
like it starts to become a personal choice
that maybe you understand that workflow tools are important
and you understand that there will be some learning curve,
some time that you need to spend to get it running,
but then this will make maybe benefit you in the future
if you know that you will be running,
you know, many workflows, many pipelines,
or you will be building pipelines in your future career.
But for sure, it's important to worry about dependencies.
Again, maybe you're just, you know, playing with code
and you're just happy with one local Python installation
and after a few months by installing random packages,
you see that it's all a mess
and then you will just reinstall everything
and start from scratch.
But sometimes when it's not about working alone anymore,
when you need especially to show to other people
your work that you've been doing, the dependencies,
so the conda environments,
and even writing down the steps,
it becomes kind of part of your work.
So at the end of the day, it's not just sharing your code
to show what you did in your research,
but also sharing kind of how for other people,
how other scientists can rerun your code.
And then last comment, when it comes to the containers,
again, you got a nice overview on the pros and cons.
You might wonder, do I have a use for them?
It might well be that right now you don't need
to learn Singularity, Obtainer, Docker, and so on.
But then you start facing the issue
that you need to use a remote supercomputer
and suddenly you can't install the tools that you need.
Or more in general, you did such, such an important work
that you really need to document it,
that this work, this result should really need
to be reproduced in 10 years from the future.
So again, with the higher requirements of your project,
you might start thinking, you know, maybe I really need to use containers for this case.
Hopefully the overview that we gave is kind of useful for everyone from the most
beginner to the most advanced users. Is there anything else to cover, [name]? Anything to
mention from the collaborative notes? No, there's very many questions and it's
Really really great thank you and we will still go through these and answer a bit more and also
please ask follow-up questions if the explanation you got there is not sufficient or doesn't solve
your question. Yeah I mean thank you for listening everyone as usual we wrote in the
collaborative notes this feedback part because we are continuously improving our
our lessons, workshop after workshop. And so if there's something that could have more
clarity or that would require more justifications, just write it there. All comments, all feedback
are welcome. So [name], will you now go and start using Singularity after this?
I did start actually using after a CodeRefiner workshop
many years ago.
And I hope, well, yeah, that everyone got an impression
what these tools can be useful for.
And as mentioned before, like the easiest way to get into it
to start using them and then ask from your local IT support
if you run into issues with them.
And I think now we have a one hour break before we go into the next lesson, which if I remember
correctly is social coding for the afternoon. Is that correct?
Yeah. Excellent. Thank you, [name], for being here with me again. It was nice to teach
together. It's 12 o'clock in Finland, 11 o'clock in Central Europe. So it's time for a lunch
or branch, depending on the taste. See you in one hour and thank you. Bye.