I'm less loud than the other two, but it's always, I don't remember who said that people
always start with, so, so, let's get this started.
Exactly.
I'm sharing this collaborative notes document
that most likely you are familiar with.
And there you will find a couple of icebreakers.
Should I start asking [name] about the first icebreaker?
Works on my computer.
Like, I guess you heard this sentence.
You know, what does it mean in practice that you
trying to, I guess the context here is that you're not able to get something work on your computer
and you ask me and I'd say, well, it works on my computer. Has this happened to you or?
Oh yes, it has happened. And we have solved it in many different ways. Sometimes we just say,
okay, I don't need to run it. You can run it. It works on your computer. Please do the work now.
In other cases, restarting, like it says here also, has also helped to solve the magic of
these computer problems and more recently, like in, let's say, in recent years after
visiting the CodeRefinery workshop many years ago, also stuff like containers have helped
and I guess we're going to discuss that today.
How about you?
Yeah, no, I was just thinking that in general, this is such a common problem that, you know,
you might be trying to help your grandparents with their phone and you look at their phone
and it behaves in a different way than, you know, even though you have the same model
and same everything, it's, it's, it's quite amazing that, you know, that technology in
general tends to not be that, how can I say, reproducible or, you know, stable, robust.
But usually, yeah, restarting it or when it comes to software, reinstalling it sometimes
fixes magically.
I mean, isn't it actually pretty amazing when something does work across other computers?
I mean, like, just imagine if I write something and it works on three different operating
systems of computers and three different operating systems of phones, or two phones, and who
knows however many other things.
Yeah.
That's a big deal.
It's certainly still a feeling of magic when that actually works, like, first try.
And you send some code or try to run it on a different computer, and it just works.
And you're like, wow, I tried it.
So what are the reasons why something usually doesn't work then?
Good question.
Exactly, there's so many reasons.
Like even this part, this thing of the restarting, you know, I was trying to explain to my child
that your phone went to a state that it's not the usual anymore, so you need to restart
it too.
Yeah.
So wait, what's a good metaphor, a non-technological metaphor, where you have to restart it?
Yeah, that's a very difficult one.
I'm thinking of cooking, because cooking is our usual one.
I guess that you know that if you messed it up, yeah, you have to restart in a sense that
you have to throw away everything and re-remake your, I don't know, or...
What about one of these forever stews where there's a pod and you keep adding stuff to
it and taking it away, and it keeps going for, well, days or weeks, but sometime it
gets messed up and it's too spicy or too whatever.
or poisoned or something, and you have to throw it all out and start from the beginning.
Because many other things, I mean, when you're cooking, normal cooking, you restart on every
new recipe.
Of course you can get the master chef who is able to fix if it's too spicy or too bland.
But we still have a couple of minutes and the second icebreaker is about what do you
know now about programming and scripting and software, which you wish somebody told you
when you started?
This is the kind of question that we have always been asking each other and always been
asking to whoever comes across that.
It's not truly or strictly related to this day, but in general, you know, some kind of
advice for your younger self or future self?
For me, what it says there, how to organize folders and code is definitely one big one,
and how much it matters. Because maybe you have heard about that before and you're like,
ah, yeah, but I'm just trying something out now. I don't have to worry about this. And then
it grows and grows and it's more messy and messy and at some point someone asks you hey can you
share this and then you have to like either put some order in your mess or write like
super long documentation where to find the different files and where to find the different
data so how much also this organization actually matters for your future self and how much time it
it can save you would also be my answer here about you.
Yeah, I mean, I feel in a way related to this kind of about the physical
geography of the systems we use, because I feel that sometimes,
especially the the new generation might be growing with iPads or other devices.
They don't know the kind of, you know, geography of the file system,
that there are folders, that there are processes.
And so, and then when people start working with, you know, super computers or HPC clusters,
then suddenly, is it now on my computer, am I, you know, where am I in the network of
computers?
So, this actually helped me a lot, understanding where am I, what is connected to the place
where I am now, to kind of, you know, then understand, okay, I can't do this, what I
would normally do in my laptop, because I'm not on my laptop
anymore.
I'm somewhere else on the internet.