Hello, and welcome back.
You hopefully can hear us now.
Let's see, I'm adjusting something here.
So, yeah, hopefully you had a good lunch break.
So what do we have now?
Well, first off, we should tell you if the things from the previous lesson were a bit
difficult.
We have these things called bring your own code sessions, where you can basically bring
your work and we can look at it and provide a little bit more
hands-on support in using these tools for your own work.
So there's not much we can do.
We can't help everyone, but we can at least get you started.
If you do have more questions and you have collaborators
or support people locally, try talking to them.
And you can show them the Code Refinery lesson saying,
Oh, I saw this, I would like to use it, can you help me?
And they can probably help quite a bit.
So what we have next, the lesson, is called Social Coding and Software Licensing.
This used to be called Software Licensing and was about, well, the permissions of reusing
software.
But it's been changed so it's much more broad now.
So in the previous lesson, we talked about ways to make it where your code could be used
by other people.
But do they have permission?
And do they have permission to contribute back to your code and make this whole cycle
of all the different things going together?
Yeah, so, is there any other introduction or should I send it straight to you all?
You can send it to us, we should maybe say briefly who we are and give it over to you.
So yeah, who are our instructors for this lesson?
We have [name], who I think is new here.
Yeah.
Hello, I'm [name], I work at Aalto University as a research software engineer and well,
I suppose that's enough.
Yeah.
And [name], I think you know from last week.
Yes, University of Tromso, Norway, research software engineering and support for computing
software development, high performance computing.
And I'm really looking forward to this lesson.
It's a really important topic.
It's something that we all need to think about.
And I like how it nicely connects to the earlier session from today.
is about, it's again about reuse,
but less on the technical level, more on the social level.
And what I will try to do is I will be here,
be [name]'s sidekick.
I will be watching the notes
and hopefully we get lots of questions.
I will try to keep a really lively discussion.
So for everybody, the best way to participate
is that you watch and listen what we do.
there will there will not be any exercises here we will have some we will try to involve you through
the document we will ask you some questions through the document we hope to get many answers
and i will try to lift some questions also here into the discussion
so this is more of a discussion session than a um well than an exercise or a demonstration
but we'll still try to spend a good amount of time in actual discussion.
Should we get to it?
I will also have questions for [name], because he's actually the expert here.
But I'll also try to keep this on track.
Yeah, I'm not sure about the expert part, but I'm also sure that I will have questions to you too.
So let's keep it really...
We'll see.
Let's see.
Yeah. So yeah, social coding and open software. So
yeah, this is a relatively broad section. It's about how you
some things you need to think about when publishing your software and how to get credit
and allow people to reuse it and in general how to interact with people around your published code.
So let's get down to it.
This is the plan for the course, for this section.
So we'll first talk about social coding, general topic.
Some about licensing and then how to get people to or how to enable people to cite your software.
And what to consider when sharing data.
data. So it's more about laying out things that you need to, or
that are good to think about when you are publishing your
work. And kind of prodding a bit at your brains and getting
getting some ideas out so that they come to mind when you are
actually working on this. So let's get directly to the
or actually i can click through here social coding section and here we have our first
exercise discussion topic so maybe i should copy this to the notes
yeah i'm working on it so i can i'm testing okay thanks it's it's in there now okay so yeah so
So there's a few things about,
initial thoughts about social coding.
So why would you want to share your code?
Of course, talked about this already.
Hopefully there's some ideas out there.
So can you click to the collaborative notes?
Yes.
So here, what we would like is,
we would like you all to add your votes.
you can vote by adding these little O's
and you can choose many in question one.
Yeah, so we'll get a little paragraph
and feel free to add something
if you see something missing.
Yeah, and here we want to hear from you.
Yeah, what are your motivations to share code?
What are your concerns?
So have a look at also the other questions,
question one, two, three, four,
And then together now with [name], as we discuss,
we will then return to your answers.
And we are really curious to see
which ones are the most motivating, most concerning.
So why would you not share your software, basically?
Well, why share your software?
Why would you not?
Yeah, how is software different from papers?
There's a lot to talk about there, we'll come back to.
So how about, how is it for you, [name], when, when question one, what are for you?
Why share them?
Out of these, which ones are the most, which one?
Yeah, I guess.
I mean, as a research software engineer, we mainly work for, with open software.
So it also comes from there, but just thinking of my own projects, which are not all research
projects.
One big thing is to just have it out there so that I don't lose it.
That's a really actually important motivation for sharing.
So you never lose access to it yourself.
That's a good one.
Also for me.
Jay, answer is important to me.
How about the good for your CV, is that important for you?
I mean, to an extent, I'm not looking for a job, or I'm not expecting to be looking
for a job very soon, but yeah, it is an important point, especially after working as a software
engineer for a while, if you don't have any code out there that people can see, that would
be a bit concerning, but as a researcher, yeah, as well.
And yeah, I mean, it is good to keep accumulating your portfolio as you go.
But yeah, I mean, actually one of the main reasons though is that I want feedback on
what I'm doing.
I want to see if people are actually interested, and if they're not, then I will work on something
else.
So yeah, that is the main thing.
I want people to actually see it, read it and I want to know if it's if other people
think it's interesting because if I'm doing some research that nobody cares about then
I should work on something else.
What's the most concerning thing for you when sharing or and maybe what what used to be
and what is it now? Yeah, like 10 years ago when starting my career, I was afraid that the code
looked bad and people would just think it looks bad basically. I don't know what the downside of
that actually would be, what would be the problem with people thinking my code looks ugly, but
But that was a real concern.
And right now, I think the main thing is,
there's a definite thing on my mind.
It's mainly that if something better already
if I haven't actually noticed it and I'm somehow taking some eyes off the better version of it.
How about you? What is your main reason for sharing and also for not?
It's the, so that ideally I can reuse it in future. So I share it with everybody else
but I also don't share it with my future self.
So the answer, J.
And the CV part is important,
and the job search doesn't have to be this year, next year,
but how about in five years, what, in 10 years?
I would like to be able to show what I worked on,
which means that if I have the choice
between working on a project that is open
and where my contribution will be visible
and one which is completely closed
and I cannot show it to anybody,
I will probably choose the more open one.
So it works also, it can also work the other way
in attracting collaborators.
So a project that is open will,
is more likely to attract me to work on it
because then I can show my work inside there.
And how about the worries?
Also, I used to think a lot about
that somebody will like go in and, I don't know,
steal the idea.
I'm not worried about it because,
I mean, I have a hard time understanding my own code.
I don't think anybody else will figure it out before I do.
And an ugly code.
And I think if we look at the answers,
so the answer B, it will expose my in quotes ugly code.
It's the answer that wins today.
And it's the answer that wins every single time.
And hopefully it is nice for all of us to see
that we all think that way.
And it actually doesn't matter and nobody will judge
and the code is never finished and it's okay.
And when you go and find somebody else's code and it's useful and it does what you want it to do, you are happy about it.
I mean, you don't think, well, this is ugly.
So I find it really comforting to see.
On the positive side, there is the more general, I mean, not just the CV, but the reputation you get.
it's a social reward you get for publishing something that is maybe more important than
the professional side of it. It is natural to think that if your code looks ugly then
maybe that would kind of go in the wrong direction, maybe people don't like it,
but in practice it's more important that there's something out there that kind of works and people
will always be happy to find anything and I mean of course if it if it's nice and if it's ready
and if it's usable that's good but it's still better to find something than nothing
okay should we look at the other questions
so
So software is different from papers, which is true.
So yeah, in my mind, the analogy is between software and papers.
Papers are often usually mainly about the results, about the scientific results.
A software publication is kind of like a publication that describes your methodology,
your experimental setup. So if you're running an experiment or especially if you're building
a device to run the experiment then it's also important to describe the entire process in
detail so that people can repeat your and reproduce your study. So yeah, publishing the
software is kind of analogous to publishing the blueprints for your experimental device or
publishing the entire methodology of your study. And here I can say that there are
journals that specialize on where you can publish, you can describe the software part.
But it's not so much about publishing the research results used with the software, but
where you can focus on the software part.
And hopefully, towards the end of this session, we will have time to mention those and discuss
those.
Yeah.
Question four is essentially, well, it's a large part of what we'll come back to.
I don't know actually if there's a huge difference in software for question 3.
There's about publishing rights, so I'm assuming who can publish what and what is considered plagiarism.
I don't know that there is a huge difference there.
Software licensing works differently because software is something you can run, you can use to do something.
a paper is mainly the it is the text that you just read
um so software can be used in different ways
in more different ways than papers but in general i i think the publication
rights work almost completely the same way
good point and i think we will return to that to that aspect also question four
here we wanted to hear from you but we will discuss that also in a little
moment, I believe, or should we go there now in question for,
um, well, I mean, we can do that.
I don't mind.
Um, so what do you look at?
Um, should we answer this ourselves first?
What's the first thing you look at when you find a, um, software written by
someone else that you could use in your project?
So this is about, you want to do something,
you search for it, has anybody done it?
And now you see that, aha, there is a repository on GitHub.
And it's very similar to what I wanted.
Can I just reuse it and change it?
And the things that I would look at is license.
Yeah.
So can I even change it?
and am I allowed to change it?
And especially, as we will see in a moment,
I can do almost anything
if I just keep it on my own computer.
But the important question is, am I allowed to change it
and then publish the result?
Because that's what I really want to do.
So can I change it and share it?
Because publishing and sharing is often related.
So that's one thing I would look at,
but there are many other good answers there.
Yes. So how is the project still alive? How recent are the most recent commits? Are there
open issues or pull requests? So yeah, is it being developed? And if it's old enough,
it might not run or you might need to do a lot of work to get it to work.
Yeah.
It's of course also nice if it stays up to date and people can use it later.
yeah and i do look at that when was the last change um will it be hard to install yeah but
then if you see a project that hasn't been touched in three years i think it's it's nice if we are
also uh it's i mean i also understand the other side i mean i have many projects that i started
i worked on them and then i stopped working on them because if i if i would support every
every single project that I ever started,
at some point, I would not be able to start anything new.
So it's a normal process that many projects,
most projects at some point stop.
And it's nice if we are constructive about it
and nice about it.
So you could also be the person
who then finds a project that has stopped
and takes it up and revives it.
So sometimes I feel bad when I get,
I see comments on my own projects,
this is this this is a dead project nobody has the issues are not followed up the pull requests
are not merged yeah well uh yeah maybe somebody else can do that this is open source and at some
point i need to move on to other projects yeah it's always better to have it out there than
not so even if you cannot actually continually develop it you just need it for your current
thing and then it's done it's still better to have it out there
of course it is also good to communicate clearly that you are no longer developing it so that
other people feel free to pick it up and yeah continue working on great question on
line 247 so what exactly is software if i write a python code
a script that does an analysis to get the result of a paper.
So is that part of software?
Is this what we're talking about here?
Should we then, do we need to think about licenses?
And it's a rhetorical question.
So yes, yes, it is software.
It can even be, it can be a short script.
And then we don't have to do much.
We can add a license file or on top of the script,
we can write that this script is shared under the,
MIT license or GPL, and we will see what they mean
in a moment, so it can be, that can be enough.
But basically anything to reproduce the results,
data, software, we need to think about license.
Because I made a little script that
maybe it takes me 20 minutes to write.
Maybe it will save somebody else days.
somebody else will be really grateful if they don't have to write it and can reuse it.
Yeah, or even if it takes 20 minutes that's still time saved.
So especially it is important if this is actually something you've used to
produce a figure or a result in your paper to actually publish it in such a way that it can
actually someone else can use it to reproduce the results in your paper and then go from there to
add on to it. Yeah, it is important to publish that. And it is software, so it needs a software
license and all of that.
So I'm watching as questions will go on, and I might trace them, but maybe, yeah, maybe
you can move on and follow up.
Yes, let's go on to. Yeah, so, well, comparing, sharing papers and sharing code is exactly
what we were just talking about.
Something we didn't really go into is academic credit, which all researchers roughly know
how it works.
You use an idea from another paper, you're not directly using any text from the paper,
you just read the paper and then you are continuing to work.
you cite the paper in your own publications. And that is kind of the currency of academia in a way
that shows that people are actually interested in your work and
you are building or you are adding something important to a field of science.
So yeah, the thing you want to do as a scientist is put papers out there, have people cite them
and you never want to put any restrictions on them or anything like that
yeah good point and often there are restrictions but they come from maybe from the journalists but
not from the researchers you want maximum visibility for your papers
yeah of course I mean yeah if you publish in a journal then it might not be openly available
hopefully there is an openly available version somewhere
Okay, so software or code can or works a bit differently, so you can kind of mix and match
and well, I mean, you can mix and match research trials in a way you create some understanding
of a topic and then you cite them.
But here you can actually take blocks off or copies of lines of code from something
or you can use a library that someone else has written. So you can mix and match in a more
complicated way and build on top of other people's work. So one quick question is,
should you cite software that you use? When should you cite it? Should you cite
the Linux operating system? How far do you go? I guess we will come back to that.
that question at some point. But yeah, with software the situation gets more complicated.
So there's the dependencies on which you build your software and then there is
the algorithms, the scientific methodology that is kind of implied by the software.
So there's a lot more considerations there.
Okay, so I mean a lot of journals require you to share that share your code much should
we go in there we spend a good amount of time looking at the questions but this didn't actually
come up
We can just summarize that yeah today we and in future we might not have the choice whether
we like want to share it or don't want to share it and it's a good thing I think there
is a yeah so it seems that in future we will be required to personally I find it a good
development but it also means for us now that we we have to start thinking about it so whatever
I use now I have to be ready so that if I then share it in five years when the project
is done and we are publishing then I need to be able to share it yeah yeah so when from
From the start, you need to think about this licensing and these sorts of things so that
you can actually share the code when the time comes.
Yeah.
Okay.
We got a couple of great questions, so maybe we have time, I just want to raise them.
So what was the biggest thing that raised your awareness of this, like the biggest event
and led you to adopt better practices?
Was it seeing other people using these practices?
Is it that conferences I think in my original field where I was most of my work most of
my time as a researcher where I was developing the code there wasn't really a tradition of
sharing or publishing openly, anything. It took quite a while. I think I was actually
a research software engineer by the time I properly started sharing my own research codes.
I think the main thing was actually seeing it done in other fields, but also I was often
frustrated when two groups came up with different results for what is essentially the same question
and there was no clear way of checking, even checking that their code produces that result
because you didn't have access to their code.
So yeah, that was quite frustrating and of course then you see people just publishing
their code that is the obvious solution to the problem of course it's still good to have both
codes that produce those different results so that you can actually figure out what's going on but
yeah not publishing it is the original problem there is one more question that but it's more
general i wonder do we have time now for one more question or should i postpone it it's not
it can also wait well i think we should have time the questions that are now on the screen
are actually something we already talked about.
Yeah, one thing that I wanted to discuss a little bit
is this, whether we can give examples
of repositories we've worked on.
And I'm paraphrasing here.
So the person says that,
I'm working on one project over many years.
And is the project too big
or am I just really inefficient?
And I just wanted to say, no, I mean, probably not.
It's normal.
I would say that's the normal thing
that I think many researchers will work years,
maybe even decades on one coding project.
And there's nothing wrong with it.
Because then you really know it well.
You know all the ins and outs, you know what it can do.
You can implement new ideas in it quickly
because you know it so well.
We as research software engineers
would typically help researchers.
So we often jump from project to project
because at least in my case,
I'm now often, I'm not driving the project.
is somebody else and I help out. So then I do more jumping from project to project. But
I just wanted to say that there's nothing wrong with it. I think that's the normal
situation. I think it's a good sign if you end up spending a lot of time on a single
coding project. I have some that were kind of one and done, wrote down an algorithm and
and publish the paper on it.
And then I have a few where the project evolved
for years and years and years
and someone else is now working on it.
And those second ones are of course the ones
where other people are actually interested in the results.
The first ones are the ones
where the paper didn't really get cited
and I moved on to something else.
That is why I didn't continue developing them.
Yeah, great.
Okay, let's move on to licenses.
Should we talk about licenses the next episode?
Yes, we did we talk about reusability yet?
Well, that is actually something we will talk about
in the next section as well.
What from here do we need to bring up before we go on?
The thing that I would bring up here
is also contribution guide.
It can be nice to see in a project how to contribute.
Yeah.
How to get started?
What is the decision process?
Especially in a bigger project,
it can be a bit daunting to just see a huge bunch of files
where you have no idea how everything interacts
with everything else.
It is important to have a good style guide
and contribution guide so that you know how to get started.
And yeah, mostly everything else we have already talked about.
So let's move on
and talk about licenses. Okay so this is obviously a very important topic when it comes to publishing
your code without a license no one can really do much with your code you're just kind of putting it
out there for people to read but with the license you state what people can actually do
with with the code that you publish so we'll need to talk about derivative work
what actually is derivative work so when you take someone else's project or actually well
I'll just finish the sentence so when you take somebody else's project and make some changes to
it when does it count as derivative work and when not when can you just share it and when do you need
to follow the license and I guess the answer to that the way I just said it is kind of obvious
because if you're actually working on someone else's code that is the route to work but it
can be even more than that. And then we'll talk about available licenses and what do they mean
and give some practical advice. So what you should take away from here is basically
when do you need to think about licenses and where to go and check what my license means what.
And we will try to keep it really practical so we will not go through all the different licenses and
discuss the pros and cons but we want to give you practical advice of where to start,
where to look for, how to compare and what to do in your repository to be ready for this.
So there's a few things around this general concept of copyright.
We'll mainly talk about copyright specifically, but there's trademarks.
So the trademark is a name for something.
It could be, of course, the name of your software,
but in general, it's just a name that is public,
the sort of public face of a product or a thing.
A patent is a technical invention, that's novel and non-obvious, but the basic idea
is that it is a technical invention rather than a product or a thing you can just kind
of look at or it's not an object, it's not a file.
And then copyright applies to almost everything else.
So it applies to creative expressions, something you spend time on creating.
So it could be software, writing, graphics, photos, books, movies, and yeah, copyright.
you have right to the things that you create for basically forever from your point of view.
So lifetime of the author plus 70 years. I don't know what jurisdiction that is but it's
roughly correct in almost any jurisdiction. Yeah, of course, try to reproduce it and 70
years later. So let's see what is the running but the yeah. So the important takeaway is
we we create creative work so we are creative people when we write code and scripts it falls
under copyright and then [name] you mentioned that you have copyright so the question is who is you
it could be the person it could be your employer so that sometimes it depends
it depends on the country depends on the employer yeah depends on your contract
so this is also something to think about and practically speaking that can be complicated
even if like people try to make it sometimes as clear as possible so maybe it's that the
company always owns everything or maybe it's the idea is that you or the person who writes it the
employer owns like if you're working in a university you might own the copyright to
everything but it can still get complicated so it is just easier to make sure you handle the
copyright situation immediately so that it doesn't get into so that you don't get into
a complicated situation which means deciding on a license and publishing under a license
and a great question on on the notes is that now that we have generative AI and we have AI
artificial intelligence assisted coding. Yeah. It opens a whole new set of questions
about licenses, about copyright, about ethics of it.
And we, I guess we may have a section on it, but most of these services, all of these services
as far as I know right now, they do give the user the copyright, they give it away or you
buy it from them. But even if they do that, you only have copyright if it's not derivative
work or if it's not a direct copy of something that already exists, which is something you
just have to check yourself. You cannot trust that the system will take care of that for
you.
Yeah, but it's also hard to check. It's hard to know where this code comes from. And a
completely different question,
which is really hard to answer is,
the original creators, do they get credit?
Are they credited?
Are they, did they agree to it?
And was their license respected?
So that's a completely different set of questions.
Yeah.
Yeah, there, if you are thinking
that there might be an original author,
then the simplest case would be that,
oh, the best way out of it would be
to just assume that they have copyright and respect it
because then you will not get in trouble.
Yeah.
So [name], what is derivative work
and why is it so important for us
when we write and change software?
Yeah.
So derivative works, the name says,
basically means you have taken something
and made changes to it.
It may be even completely re-implemented it,
but it is somehow derived from someone else's
copyrighted work.
So it's derived from something
where someone else has copyright.
And it could be sampling.
We have some nice images of historical images
of actual resampling going on.
Yes.
It works on many levels there.
I think we have a clip for people.
I will copy it to the notes.
You can, you can,
Yeah.
You can vote on it.
So there's some examples
and the question is if they are derivative work or not.
So I don't know if I should,
well, I'll give the quick guide to how to answer it.
But when you are,
yeah, like I said, when you're taking something
and changing it, that's kind of clearly derivative work,
but often it's also derivative work
if you are taking an idea from something,
but not like you're using someone else's code,
for example, to write it in a different language
just rewrite it, that might still be derivative work. As long as it's derived from a copyrighted
work, it is derivative work. It depends on the field. If you are taking ideas from a painting
and creating your own painting, usually we don't consider that derivative work.
If you are translating a Python library into R, even if you are completely rewriting it,
it's still considered derivative working well usually so I hope I didn't give out the answer
to a direct question maybe I did but that's kind of the general guideline so it can be quite expensive
and so we have to we have to think about it both when we if I find some code on the internet
then I change it I have to think about derivative work let's go and we have to think the other way
to think about derivative work is do you want to make it easy or difficult for other people to
change things and that you can also then steer a little bit with the choice of license
yeah so yeah the license can give you can give it people the right to create derivative work
as much as they want or it can restrict it a lot okay um should we start going through this
i guess so yeah so a couple of them are maybe not so surprising the thing that was surprising
to me many years ago is that when even changing the whole language nothing is left from the old
code not not a single character everything has completely changed i i was surprised that
that is that is derivative work yeah so nobody has voted for linking to libraries
But, in fact, if a library is published under the traditional, standard GNU public license,
for example, and you statically link to it, that can still be considered, that is still
considered derivative work.
So for some licenses, it depends how we link to it.
I think maybe that's a little bit technical, we will not go into too much details.
So for plugins and libraries, typically it's not derivative work, but it can be depending
how it is included, linked into your project.
And maybe it's a bit arcane because this is mainly talking about compiled languages and
like old engine stuff like C and C++, but I mean, people are actually still of course
using them.
And the reason I bring it up is because I was using this when I found out about this
and I was kind of surprised and had to change some things.
But answers, so questions H and I, they, so when we, when you, so H means clean room design,
it means that you don't see, you never see the code, but somebody explains you what the
code does, how it works, you can think of explains you the algorithm, and then you write
the code.
So that is typically not derivative work.
Also, if you read the paper, read the algorithm and write the code based on the algorithm,
typically not derivative work so an algorithm is typically not something that can be copyrighted
yeah yeah so if you're implementing an algorithm that's not derivative work
if somebody describes you what the code does um on a more detailed level and you just write down
what they're telling you telling to go to do then that actually probably is derivative work
so yeah i mean clean room design means you know the algorithm but you don't know the actual code
Okay. So containers. Okay. So yeah, recipes are like source code. Containers are like
a program. But we didn't actually talk about specifically the licenses yet. Okay. Let's
go there. Because this is an important topic. It's about choosing which license to use
use and also what it means when a code has been published under a specific license.
So there's, well, there's proprietary licenses, which generally mean you have sold a piece
of software and you have rather restrictive, you sell a rather restrictive license that
they can, only this person can use it for this purpose.
Yeah, that's because you're actually selling it and getting money from it.
But mainly talk about open source licenses.
So they range from strong copyleft, which means derivative work has to be published
also under a strong copyleft license.
You can think of it as the license kind of infects everything it touches.
So everything that uses a strongly copyleft piece of code also will be strongly copyleft
or at least copyleft.
So I guess that the main difference here
between strong copyleft and copyleft is that
copyleft is the less strong version is usually designed
so that you can actually link against it or use it,
use the products, use the library
without having to publish your code as copyleft.
Whereas strong copyleft is kind of,
it just tries to make everything copyleft
as much as possible.
And I think it's useful to not think in too much in terms of using because the using could
be linking plugin.
Maybe let's think in terms of remixing.
You take a couple of codes from different places and you remix them with your own work
and this is your code.
So remixing and then what is interesting are the little arrows.
So in the in the image that Tiano is sharing there are these fields and the arrows between
they actually show the compatibility.
What license can you combine with another license?
The one on top, so the so-called strong copy left,
the arrow goes only one way.
Then if we go a little bit lower towards the dark green,
we have the permissive licenses,
and they are called permissive
because they can be combined with almost anything,
even with proprietary licenses.
but you can see that the arrow there goes only one way.
So you can take a code that has been licensed MIT
and if you want, you can make it proprietary.
You can sell it, you can close it.
So all of this is possible.
Right.
Yeah, and yeah.
So a copy left software cannot be used in a,
software cannot be used in in a well yeah there's there's often a separate proprietary
license for a copyleft library but that license cannot be directly used in a proprietary thing
oh it cannot be it cannot be distributed together with a proprietary thing and um
which means that now now let's think in two different perspectives one is that
that I just want to use the code. That's one perspective. But the other perspective is
we develop the code. And now you can decide what do you want with your code to happen?
Do you want it to be used in as many places as possible, proprietary, not proprietary,
then you would prefer probably a permissive license. If you want to make it as easy as
possible for everybody else. On the other hand, if you want to make sure that your code
is not distributed with another proprietary code,
then you probably want to move up on that green pyramid
and choose a more so-called copyleft license.
Right, yes, this is mainly about distributing, not running.
If you're just running on your own machine
or even making changes on your own machine,
that's usually not something we think about.
So the license doesn't really restrict you from just running or even changing it on
like locally and never showing it to anyone. Although it's kind of hard to
never show something to anyone, but in principle that's allowed.
So it is mainly about distributing. Somebody's asking, what is the
difference between MIT and Creative Commons? Because here they are on the same image.
Yes. MIT and BSD are traditionally software licenses and Apache. The differences between
them are small. Creative Commons is traditionally more for data and for both artistic things
like books, like lecture materials, and not so much for software that's intended to run
and produce a result, for example. So there are differences in the way it's written. And
I would basically just use software licenses for software and creative commons for other
things. What if you have both earlier in the session,
we had on we had a repository example repository, there was data and there were scripts and
read me's and maybe a manuscript. So what can you do if you have data and code in the
same place. And I can answer it myself. You can, you can put, you can then put both licenses.
You can say that, well, all the data, all the slides are licensed creative commons attribution
and all the code is licensed MIT. And that's what we do in, in our code refinery lessons.
So that's how we license our material. Yeah. So yeah, nothing forces you to just use one
license for an entire repository, you can have different licenses per folder or per file.
The only thing to take into account there is that you have to then, well you have to look at those
arrows there, you are distributing them at the same time if they are in the same repository.
So there might be some compatibility issues. Also even there you can have the data be
creative commons and have a gpl strong copy left license for the software that will not be a
problem the software is not so directly linked with the data that that would be a problem
but still you you in that case you do need to take those arrows into account
okay um well well something we didn't really mention is this lowest level here which is
It's so permissive that there's not really even a license there.
It's just published as public domain and anyone can do anything they want with it.
Often these lower levels here might require at least attribution.
You need to tell where you got the code or the data.
So yeah, there's a great resource here for this join up licensing assistant is very useful
when you're trying to actually figure out what license to use.
Should we, it's 10 to two, I should say.
I think what I would like to do before, we will take a break soon.
I would say maybe in five minutes, what we could try to do in before the break into five
minutes is that we, there were some good questions that I want to bring up later when we discuss
But one question that we could talk about now is what should we do practically?
So we have this overview, let's say we choose a specific license, but what should I do then
practically with my repository?
And so one thing that we advise you to do, and I think this is so in the material people
you can find it a little bit below that scheme,
is add a license file to your,
it can be either a file called license,
or it can be, if you need multiple licenses,
you can create a directory called licenses,
and add the license text into the repository.
The other practical advice is to do it
early in the project.
because when there is nothing there, when the project is small, it's only one person,
it's easy to change it. When the project already exists for 15 years and there are 20 people there
from five different institutions, then it's more difficult to change the license.
Unfortunately, a common problematic situation which we did run into with those
long existing codes in the field of science where stuff wasn't really published when I was there.
Several of those software were published later and somebody did actually figure out where I was working at
and write an email to my work address and ask if they can publish the changes I made to the code under a specific license.
So, you have to do that with every author that has made changes to your projects.
And when it's just you or just your team, it's really easy.
So yeah, do it then.
And when somebody has left and gone through five different postdoc positions and is now
working as a research software engineer in, well, you have no idea where, it's really
hard.
Yeah.
Because then you need to possibly reach out to all of them and get their agreement.
So, do it early.
For most projects, a license file is enough.
On top of your code, you can add that this code is licensed under this and that.
It's not strictly necessary.
So you don't have to add the copyright header for it to have the copyright.
And then another thing that we recommend is to have this discussion with your group.
So if maybe have a discussion with your supervisor, or if you are the supervisor, have a discussion
with your students at the beginning of a project.
Discuss, it's a little bit like a data,
what is it called?
Data management plan.
Like, what is your plan?
What is our plan to do now,
three years later when the code is done?
How do we want to share it?
What is the license strategy?
This is, discuss it with your colleagues,
with your project.
Discuss the ownership.
Yes.
And the copyright matters, ownership matters, because only those who have the copyright
can change the license, and it may be your employer.
Yeah, and it is also, so a lot of these bigger projects, for example, will have this contribution
guide or contribution agreement that essentially states that you are giving away copyright
or you're publishing it under this license.
So if it's an MIT license, for example,
then it's enough that you publish under that license.
But they might actually ask you to give away your copyright
to that change that you're making to a big project
because then they don't have to chase you up
if they want to change the license.
So that's also something good to talk about
already in the beginning with your team.
If somebody leaves the team,
then do they give away the copyright?
do you does your team have permission to do whatever with the code which I mean usually
it should it is good to have so how about we take a 10 minute break then we can think about
more questions hopefully we will see more questions and then in the last half an hour
we will talk about software citations data and hopefully we get lots of questions that
that we can hear discuss.
Does this sound like a good idea?
If yes, then let's be back five minutes after the hour.
So a 10 minute break.
Okay.
Yes, let's take a break, walk around.
See you.
Bye.
Hello. We are back. Hopefully you can hear us. And I hope you had a good break. Stretch
your legs a little bit will be another talky section but we'll have some well we'll have
a lot of interaction with the notes like in the previous section hopefully.
So you wanted to bring up a question which I'm conveniently already have visible here.
Yes.
Yeah.
So I wanted to say thanks to all the really good questions.
Please keep them coming also for the remaining 20 minutes.
This is the best way of creating the session.
And one thing that we thought would be good to discuss
is the question that,
so the one,
so what happens if somebody actually uses a code
without permission?
Is that the one?
Yes.
Yeah.
How can you show that they used it?
And what can you do?
I mean, there's the legal side of this, and then there's how things work in academia.
Because universities or researchers don't want to be fighting each other in court, especially
when they are in different countries and different jurisdictions anyway.
But I mean, legally speaking, it is actually breaking the law.
doing something illegal and there are systems to handle this. It might be too minor to really
get a lot of attention and like I said, you probably don't want to go to court with it.
But that is at least for big companies or universities that might be something
that they think about. And more practically speaking though, if somebody publishes a
paper using your code and doesn't credit you or does it breaks the license when they do it,
does it against the license text, that is academic misconduct. That's like if they publish the paper
then the journal would probably take it into account and maybe retract the paper.
It's also true that academia works a lot through reputation.
So, um, basically just talking about it is, um, is part of the solution to the problem.
Yeah.
And it can be another motivation also to, to open up our own code and put it on Git,
because at least if somebody steals my code, at least I can show it because I can show
the git history and i can show that well that's weird the code that they published looks exactly
like the one that i put on github 2014 how come so at least you have a you have a basis
for an argument so this can maybe help us to motivate to share our own codes
Another thing we didn't mention about licenses at the end of the previous section.
So at the end of the licenses section there is a part about choosing a license in case what you're publishing is not derivative work, you're starting from scratch and you actually have to choose a license.
There's a lot of practical tips here, it's a useful read when you're actually choosing
a license, it's good to come back to this.
But one important thing is it's just practically not a good idea to invent your own license.
So these standards exist for a reason, they've been written by lawyers and you don't really
want to try to do the work of the lawyers.
plenty of standard license texts available and importantly this this is
tools around that people use that recognize standard licenses so if your
license is not standard people will not know what to do with it the lawyers will
probably say just don't use it I don't know what to do and if you if you can
Let's scroll up a little bit to that image again.
It's, what's the scenario here?
It's really about the compatibility.
So these are the arrows between licenses.
And if you invent your own,
it will not be clear what it is compatible with.
So that's really the problem.
So don't invent your own license
or take one of the standard ones.
And [name], which, what is your most favorite license?
Which one do you typically take for your projects when you have to choose?
When I'm starting and there's no reason to choose any specific license, then I would
probably go with MIT.
And why?
Just by default.
It's the most permissive license that allows people to do anything they want with it, but
still requires that they acknowledge you. I don't want it to be completely in public domain because
I still want people to acknowledge that I've done some of the work, maybe slightly selfishly, but
it's not very selfish though to put it under MIT. I want it to be as widely used as possible,
but i also want to be recognized um yeah what's your favorite
it's either so mit for the things that i just want to share and i don't really mind so much
what happens to that code yeah sometimes i i want to make sure that when people make changes
changes to the code that they are obliged to share the changes.
And then I go for the share alike, the reciprocal.
So here it's on this image is called reciprocal licenses.
For instance, the MPL, the Mozilla public license or the EUPL, the European public license.
So often I go for those if I want to make sure that whatever people come up with all
improvements i can remix them into my own projects also so it goes both ways so when i want to insist
on the both ways i go for the reciprocal licenses but they are a little bit more restrictive
if i don't care yeah or if it's such a like a little project and
probably nobody will do anything with it anyway than mit
Yeah. At some point, I think I've maybe done it once. I could move from MIT to a reciprocal
license, but I would generally start with MIT just by default. When there's no other
file in the project, except the license file, then it's MIT.
That's how early I think it's good to start thinking about licenses.
Shall we talk more about the credit part and the technology of it?
So how to cite, how does it work, software citation and software publication?
And this is also about academic citation.
So the MIT license requires acknowledgment,
but that's not quite the same thing as a citation
as researchers think about it.
So this enables also citing software
as an academic publication.
Well, that's one thing we'll talk about.
So a couple of questions there that we'll try to answer.
If you put your code on GitHub, GitLab and so on,
is that publishing?
We already talked about licenses.
So assume you also put a license there.
Is that publishing?
Where do you publish software?
How can it be cited?
How do you make it cited?
How do you make the software citable?
Yeah, so let's get into it.
So just putting your software on GitHub and GitLab,
that is a good part of publishing.
We've mentioned these FAIR principles, I think last week at least.
It's a collection of four words to think about when it comes to publishing and doing
reproducible science in general, so not just software.
It comes from findable, accessible, reusable and interoperable.
So, if you put something on GitHub or GitLab, it's accessible.
If people can find it, it's accessible.
It's also pretty findable.
GitHub is good at indexing things and GitLab, if GitLab here means the official GitLab.org
interface, then it's pretty good at indexing things so that search engines can find it.
doesn't make it reusable necessarily depends on the license and how on the
coding practices and it does not make it interoperable interoperable would mean
that it runs on different system and it plugs into or it can be used in in
different different kinds of situations with different types of data and so on
and there can be also problem with which of the findable there is a very simple
simple trick on how I can make my code not findable anymore. And that is by what if I
delete the repository? What if I delete my account? So it's a good first step, but it's
it's not enough to make it really findable for the next, I don't know, five years, 10
years. Yeah. I don't know what the horizon is that we want to make things findable. So
we want to go a step further. And one way is to really make it citable and persistent.
Yeah. Okay, so we'll talk about making it, well, first citable and then persistent.
Okay, Katz is here. Hello. So, of course, we also already talked about reproducible and
how to make it work after five years. That is also a big deal. But yeah, so let's talk about
that a little bit. So what do you actually need to cite something? And I guess one
pretty important, very important question is what software do you actually cite? So
if you use, I mentioned the Linux operating system, I guess that's an obvious thing.
If you use the Linux operating system, you probably don't cite it. But if you use a
a specifically scientific software library that someone else published with their paper,
then you probably do need to cite it. But there is some balance there. Different fields have
different conventions about what you cite, even when it comes to papers. We never cite
Einstein, for example, in physics these days. No, I mean,
that was about those I said in the wrong way around, I was
about to say we don't cite Newton and not even Einstein,
but I kind of said it the wrong way around. But anyway, so if
something is really fundamental enough, and it has its, it has
intrinsic value already, then it's known enough, you don't
need to cite it. But that, yeah, that depends a lot on the
field and the same applies to software but earlier today we talked about dependencies
so in the other session and so are dependencies fundamental like if i if i want to cite a code
but the code is using five other dependencies and each of them uses five other dependencies
do i need to cite all of those yeah that is a good question and i think my answer would be that
But we don't have to.
So you don't have to cite all the different dependencies.
You cite the libraries that you use, that your code is using.
And then you are hoping that the libraries in turn, when they publish their papers, they
are citing all the other libraries they are using.
So for a lot of things, just having it as a dependency might be enough.
Like if it's a really commonly used library, you might not cite it in a paper.
I would actually, I would maybe follow a citation trail kind of.
So if you are citing a piece of software and that piece of software is citing another piece
of software, then you should consider whether to cite it or not.
But if that other piece of software just has it as a dependency, it's not citing it, then
it's also probably the case that you don't cite it, although it depends on the situation,
depends on how much.
So citations are about the giving credit for the science.
So it and dependency is about being able to run the software.
So you use them for those, for different things.
And one thing that will help so much when citing is in your code, write down how you
want to be cited.
Already this relatively simple thing.
If I can find it easily, how do I will cite you?
I will cite you that way make it easy for me to find out how you want to be cited.
So for that I mean there are things you need to know how to for citing a piece of software
or a piece of paper or a paper or anything and I mean here's a complete list or maybe
an almost complete list but you can make life easier for other people by creating these
citation.cff file and it is a structured way of writing it down in a machine readable way
and it contains all of the information that's needed to cite your software.
So this is a message that's displayed or it says essentially just this is how you cite my software
but yeah this title, version, maybe a digital object identifier or it is actually very good
to have one, we'll come back to that, and then the names of the authors and maybe identifiers for
them. So that's the same information you would look for in a paper to cite it and you just
provide it here in a format that makes it easy to find. Now github for example will read this file
and process it to different standard citation formats so that you can put them into whatever
software you use to write your paper and cite other software. Okay so that's a good thing to
add it's a really these days it became a standard and many services understand this file so if this
file is in your repository, then many services will use it. So have such a file, get a digital
object identifier on services like Zenodo, where you can make your code really persistent. So then
even if I delete my GitHub repository, people can still find the code thanks to the DOI.
Zenodo is nice in that it integrates with GitHub so that whenever you create a new release
on GitHub, if you have enabled Zenodo, then it will create a new release also on Zenodo,
make a new copy so that you don't really have to do much to keep it up to date.
Here's some examples of how to cite software following standard formats.
There's also some journals that allow you to publish software papers. That's another way
of making your software citable. There's a good list of those here.
I think that's all you need to know how to make it citable.
Is this another section?
Yes.
No.
So the last section is about sharing data.
Yes.
So we have a few minutes, so you should probably go there.
But yeah, for getting the DOI, that is a separate section.
Okay, is there anything in the notes about citations?
Yeah, there is this question about citations in the CFF file.
And I think it's a good question because it's very general.
It's about which particular version should people cite when they use the code.
Because one thing you can do on services like Zenodo is that for each version of your code
you can get a different DOI.
Yeah.
And then you can, you can recommend people to, to cite.
So I would probably, my recommendation would be
that people should cite the version
that they've actually used.
But then you are maybe interested in knowing
what is the combined number of citations
that my software has.
Yeah.
And that you can also get this information.
So you would be more interested
in the sum of all of the versions.
but it might be also interesting
to see the evolution of versions.
So Zenodo actually creates this sort of sub-DOIs.
So a DOI that essentially ends with the version number
or a numeric identifier for the version.
And that allows you to,
so you can cite the specific version using that identifier
and it will still count the citation,
all the citations to your software together
when you want to.
So, yeah, I mean, digital object identifiers
actually support versioning directly.
So that's something you can do.
The service will also create one
which will always resolve to the latest version
if you find it practical.
So maybe that's the one that you can have in your readme.
Yeah.
Okay, so.
About sharing data is at the bottom, by the way, if anyone needs to really.
Yeah.
Oh, yeah.
Please do fill in the feedback.
We have five minutes so we can quickly look at sharing data, which is not that different.
But there's a few more considerations you need to take into account.
But also data.
You don't need a software license for data, essentially.
essentially. So it's also a bit simpler in some ways. I think the main thing though with data is
that it tends to be bigger than software. It tends to take more space. So there's some registries
that specialize in publishing data and they can go up to, I mean they have a limit of how much
data you can actually publish there but Zenodo goes up to 50 gigabytes per researcher and
there's a bunch of other options that may have more or may have less. Zenodo is run by CERN
so it's something you can kind of expect to stick around for a really long time
but all of these are good options.
Then there's local options in almost every country
that you can usually use to publish larger datasets.
So giving everyone internationally access to save a lot of huge datasets is hard,
but you can usually have a local service that allows,
allows, for example, all the Finnish researchers can publish
in these places and can publish a much bigger data set
than is possible on Zenodo.
But this is something essentially
that when you get to that problem,
you need to read up on a bit.
So, one practical thing can be that what you really want to do, at some point you want
to have a paper that is citable, that is a DOI, at some point you want to have a software
that has a DOI, and maybe you have also data.
And sometimes they go to three different places, so the paper goes to the journal, the software
goes to, I don't know, Zenodo, and the data goes to one of these services.
And it can be really useful if each of these three sides the other two, so that you Yeah,
somebody who finds the data can find a paper and can find a software and vice versa.
Data is a little bit different than software in terms of sort of licenses are similar but
different in data, we are less concerned about changing, we are more concerned about reusing
in the software, we are very concerned about changing because we want to change software,
we want to create derivative work.
Data, it's more about how is it used?
How is it combined?
With data, it's much more depends on your community.
So different academic communities
have different preferred platforms.
It depends on the country.
But the principles are the same.
You want it to be findable
and you want to connect the software, the data,
and the paper because they belong together.
they all tell a story.
Yeah, so probably the biggest difference
is that data tends to be,
it data doesn't tend to change.
Once you publish a data set, it usually stays the same
or you get a few updates, but not very often.
And software changes a lot.
Okay, just one more quick thing about AI.
There's, you, well, you can take the existence of AI
into account in different ways with data and with software.
But yeah, so essentially, most licenses allow, for example,
well, they allow data mining.
And so they kind of also allow your data
your software to be used for training AIs. But this is an evolving field. The laws are
not setting stone in any way when it comes to training AIs. So the current state of affairs
is we have a bunch of links here but if something is public it's likely okay to train AI on it.
But yeah, I mean, it's not necessarily very useful to go into much detail because the
situation is changing so quickly.
And can we maybe show now that we are out of time on a collaborative document, just
a feedback form.
It would be really nice to hear one thing that was good that we should keep and one
thing that we should change, improve for next time.
Of course, any other feedback welcome.
So this is what we would like to hear.
Also can we prepare news for the day?
So we are essentially done with the material, we would appreciate feedback, but if you need
to leave now is the time when we've covered everything.
So let's see.
we covered the things mentioned in the schedule. It was more, how do we say,
more discussion, demonstration. It's a different style. You see from the
feedback that we see that some things are too advanced. We still believe
that it will be really useful. Tomorrow we will look more on documentation. How
How can we document code differently approaches?
Yeah.
If anyone is watching just a conclusion
or reading this later,
there's many good questions during the day,
which are in the notes document,
which will be archived on the website.
So tomorrow will be,
well, tomorrow and Thursday for that matter
will be like today.
So it will be lots of demos and discussions and time for questions and answers.
So you don't need to prepare, but if you want to, you can try to follow along.
There will be things that you can possibly do, but we'll be running it as demo.
What did he think of this format? So, less exercises and more showing things. I think
it worked really well because instead of lots of questions about small technical problems
and things breaking, we had a lot more high-level questions about why things are used. And thus,
That allows us to focus on, well, the interesting part.
And then you can review the other things later.
But it can also feel, I can imagine that for some it can feel many things went too fast.
But then let's remember that we don't need to remember how we did it.
We can look it up.
And the how is not even the main point.
more the why and what is possible again what is possible why do we do things we know that
it exists we try to now show many different aspects and focus more on the why so like the
main takeaway probably yeah the main takeaway from the social coding section would for example
be that you recognize when you need a license for your software and you remember that the
material has a lot about it that you can check out when you actually are deciding what license to put
to use. So it's not something you do as an exercise right now because it's actually pretty trivial to
just click add license file and choose which license to add. It is much more important to know
what the differences are and remember that that information is on the course website that you can
check and the same kind of also goes for the for the first section so it's more important to know
that the tools are there and to recognize when you need them than it is to actually have used them
in an example yeah and i mean yeah yeah like it's there's lots of things saying today was too
advanced. I mean, yes, we know what we're doing is sort of advanced stuff using SnakeMake,
Conda Environments, or Containers. Any one of these things could become its own whole workshop.
So, don't feel that you're left behind or left out. Feel that you know what you...
feel that feel inspired to learn something in the future so it is so it
is true that doing an exercise forces you to be more concentrated and allows
you to learn something more deeply so if there's a topic that you think you need
to learn better, you can always repeat the demonstrations
or do some of the exercises in the notes.
And well, at least I don't think
it's any problem to ask questions
about those in the notes.
We might not be as actively there outside the workshop
time, but it could still work.
So tomorrow we cover, is it Jupyter and documentation?
or documentation in Jupyter.
Yes.
So documentation is about how we can use Git repositories to make
basically websites which are useful for documentation.
Basically, it shows how we make these lessons themselves.
We use these same practices.
Jupyter shows many Jupyter tips and
tricks for reproducibility that you might not know.
Then day three is really cool.
really wraps everything up. There's automated testing, which sort of puts everything together.
And then modular code development, which is an exciting demo of starting with some small code
and making it better and better incrementally, hearing the analysis of all of these steps.
So, anything else? Any other comments to address here?
Just a big thanks to everybody involved, and we'll be looking forward to tomorrow.
More time for discussion in a collaborative document. That would be... I guess we can
try to do that.
Yeah, OK.
Well, thanks a lot.
See you next time, I guess.
See you then.
OK, bye.
Bye.