Thanks. I will take over the screen share.
Oops, where did the window go?
We have already put into a question or three questions about motivation and what our kind of wish list or what we think or what you essentially you think about documentation, what should be in there?
So, I think it's kind of expected that the best documented projects people have seen
are really big projects.
So they are things where you don't want to go through the source code and try to understand
what it's doing because it's so big.
Also, they are aimed at an audience who doesn't necessarily need to know all the details of the
thing that the package is doing. You just need one small piece. In Scikit-learn, you usually
don't use everything that Scikit-learn has because it has a lot of things.
things. So PyTorch is really big. Scikit-learn is really big. There's NumPy, SciPy. Pandas,
okay, yeah, Pandas is a bit – I often have to go and actually find stuff in the documentation
to use Pandas, and it often helps. But that's true. I think Pandas can be a bit complicated.
I'm not actually sure about FlutterDust.
Do you know that?
No.
And then, yeah, Tidyverse is really good.
Yeah, sorry?
Tidyverse is good at enforcing good documentation.
In my experience, it's not necessarily
that big project means good documentation, actually.
It's more active use by a lot of people,
which are activated by a lot of interested people who then also re-contribute a bit,
doesn't necessarily make all big projects having a good documentation.
Yeah, that's a good point.
Especially for details.
So, if you've ever actually, so that there is a built-in documentation thing for the new
operating system. All of these things you can run in Linux, for example, the commands like ls and
cd and so on. It's kind of a running joke that those are almost unreadable,
but they do have all the details. Being a really big project doesn't guarantee that
the documentation is especially good. Although it kind of does guarantee that there's a lot of it
available. So someone might write a tutorial who's not even involved in writing the code.
I guess my point is small things used by a small number of people don't necessarily need
so much documentation and you kind of have to decide what level of documentation is appropriate.
It depends on who's going to use it and it depends on how much time you have
and a lot of other factors. Well at the same time a small project that has
little documentation can still be well documented. Yeah I mean it's a small project it doesn't need
it doesn't have as much the document because it's also not that complex it's easier to just grasp
what it's actually doing okay but yeah i don't know what flutter does but if you wrote down
something that you think has really good documentation then there's the question
what actually makes the documentation useful what makes it good so that's the second question here
of course, what makes it important? Well, actually not a huge number of answers. Can
we think of some more? Well, okay. It's important for at least anything that's more complex
than a few simple functions to be actually useful to someone else. If you don't have
any documentation and everyone needs to read through your code to understand what it actually
does, then it's very likely that people just won't use it. They will have a look at, okay,
there's some code, I don't care. I have no idea what it does. I don't have the time to go through
the whole source code. And this applies to you yourself in the future. So yeah, if the future
is important, yes, that's a good answer. So if you go back to your code, even if it's a really
short simple code that has only three functions or three main functions. When you
come back to it in three years you're not going to remember what those function names are and
it's much nicer if they're mentioned in the documentation somewhere you can quickly see
so rather than you have to go digging through the code to figure out what you need to do or
how do you need to call the functions so it is also useful for yourself
okay so what is good documentation how would you describe useful documentation
um it helps you understand the code it gives you examples on how the code is being used
so that and yeah yeah okay so a really good point so it helps someone else use the code in without
them having to ask the creator. So if it's code that you wrote, then people don't have to always
come and ask you. You can offload some of that work to the documentation. Of course, you can
never write perfect documentation, so there will always be some questions and some things will
just not be correct. But it's much better than having to always show people exactly how to use
it for everything. That second point to me is, well, clear engaging not too long. Not too long
is a very relative thing, but I think that mostly applies to the initial readme, which is only
some part of the documentation. Yes, you shouldn't put useless information or repetitive
information into your documentation, but I'm not sure if I would agree with the not too long
in general. Well, too long is always... You can always make something too long.
Yeah, that's a good question. Can you add information that's actually relevant
and make it too long? I think it's possible. At some point, it's easier to just read the code.
So, at some point, it's no longer useful.
But also, it is important to structure it so that there is this, like, the first page
you see something relatively short that tells you what the software does.
Something like a README.
And then there are tutorials that tell you how to do the things that the software is
designed to do.
And then for each user-facing function, each function that a user could need, there's some
description of how to use it and what it does.
I would rephrase that, for every function that you intend to use it to use.
Right, yes.
It's also good if you want to, if you have the time, it's very good to have documentation
for all the functions that you never expect any user to use because of course someone will be
developing the code. Might be you in three years or might be someone else.
So it is good to document everything at least a little bit.
I think the third point is also quite good with having examples that actually help you to get
started. So, yeah, which is the tutorials that you mentioned is and the points here generally are
good. Yeah, I think. And yeah, the last edit point is actually something
easy to navigate. Yes, easy way to find what you're actually looking for, which is really
difficult. That's probably one of the most difficult bits in my opinion because a good
structure is not easily found. And if your code is growing then it's very likely to get messy
structure-wise at some point. So how do you motivate your colleagues to contribute to the
documentation. I mean, the first point is they explicitly say it's meant as a joke,
but I'm going to take it seriously because the best way to motivate someone, especially like
if you're developing something as a job, if it's part of your job to develop software for research,
actually paying people for spending time on it would be a good idea. It's not
something we always do very well, but it is actually a very good way of motivating people.
actually pay them for their time. But yeah, there are other ways as well.
So, yeah, explaining why it is important, explaining why it helps them in the future
and helps get their work cited, so it helps other people use the code. And for researchers,
citations are the kind of important so if other people can use your code then they can also
contribute to your field and help you in your career as well. And what I think is important
both in an academic or non-academic setting if you have undocumented code it takes a lot more
more time for someone else to get into that code.
Yeah.
And might even be impossible.
So just documenting saves money, if you want it like that.
Or in the academic instance, heaps knowledge.
It saves you time, and it saves your research group
time in the future.
There are so many non-doc, there's
so much non-documented code around
that is essentially, okay, well, this was done by a PhD master student, whatever, last year,
and he's gone. If you're lucky, he answers to emails. If you're unlucky, he doesn't,
at which point it's, I have no idea how this works, and I can't understand the code, so this
is dead upon the person leaving the group and might even have been dead before.
That last point being added is true, very important.
So we have talked about how to cite software and how to make sure that the correct people
get credit for software.
Documentation is part of the software.
It is an important part of the job of actually doing the research and getting to a result
and publishing the software and publishing the paper and all of that.
So the person, someone contributing to the documentation really should be looked
at, someone who's actually spending time contributing to the research project.
At least if we are at the point where we can actually talk about citing software,
then definitely someone who writes
documentation should be included in the authors for that software.
Okay, I think that is quite a good piece of information and let's head to what should
documentation actually contain.
So we basically covered everything in the first section, but I just want to quickly
show what we're going to do in this lesson.
So in the first half, essentially,
will be discussions about documentation
and then how to write good README files.
And then in the second half, we'll
go through a demonstration with a slightly more
complicated documentation than README files
and how to get that viewable online,
how to deploy it on a website.
So let's go to the motivation section and feel free to answer of course in the notes
even though I'm not sharing them right now. So why documenting code is essentially done.
Yeah so let's talk about that. So yeah what should a good documentation contain?
Should we, let's wait for a moment before we start throwing around ideas, give people
some time to talk.
We can already collect what we had further up, which is how would you describe a useful
documentation?
Sure.
Yeah, so there are some points that go to that section, so okay, so the arrangement
should be boring.
So yeah, it should contain the things
that you expect it to contain,
which is installation instructions,
some quick start, and how to,
so these are tutorials on how to do a specific thing
the code is intended to do,
and a reference, which means,
I guess we'll get back to it,
but some documentation for almost everything in the code,
but in a structured way,
so that you can find what you're looking for.
.
where to report bugs, where to report issues or where to report or where to discuss about
features that you would like to add or would like someone to add to the software
and then in general how contributions work.
okay so here's our checklist it's mostly the same things so you would want to have in the
documentation you would want to mention the authors of the software the license purpose
is something already mentioned how it should be cited it's useful to have that's also in
the citations file of course and then some examples where you can or tutorials how to get started
dependencies um installation instructions is important
the reference documentation is already mentioned um yeah and how do you want people to contact you
and some frequently asked questions section this is roughly almost everything was was there in the
answers so that's a good thinking we've roughly have the same ideas okay um we do have um in the
next step kind of a list of popular tools and solutions let's go there um we will go over
some of them in more detail and I think the only things we really want to mention here for these
tools and solutions are the formats that we commonly use to create documentation or
which is mainly markdown and restructured text. Okay right so yeah okay we have a whole section
on in-code documentation, which basically means the documentation that is embedded in the code
itself. And then I think in the next section we'll have readme files, so we'll talk more about that.
So yeah, Markdown you already know because the collaborative document is in Markdown. I was
I was going to just open it and show, but it's, you can,
if you're looking at it, you can see it.
So this is Markdown.
Yeah, and the restructured text is another option.
So can you, do you want to say more about
why use either one of them?
Well, the one biggest reason is that
it's a relatively simple format.
It's all text-based.
So you, well, yeah, it's all text-based.
So you can easily put it into version control
and see differences.
So it's not a binary format
where you get a big binary dump of the data,
but you can actually follow what changes were made.
It has most features that you need
for having a nice looking, at least online document.
So I guess, I mean, they look a bit different, but they have roughly the same features, and
I guess restructured text, because it is what Sphinx uses, and Sphinx is very commonly
used to build documentation, it might have some features more, some features are there
more by default, whereas in Markdown, you might need some expansion plugin, something like that.
One thing is that Markdown is maybe a bit simpler. It's maybe a bit faster to learn,
but it's not a big difference. It's a very small difference. There's many flavors of Markdown,
unfortunately so some syntax that you use on say github readme files might not work in a different
place so yeah there's um and there's multiple flavors that implement for example equations
So they might do it slightly differently, unfortunately.
But the standard, the text formatting things generally work the same way.
Yeah.
yeah so we'll in our example in the next second well not the next section but the
the next hour we'll use a mist flavored markdown in Sphinx but yeah you can you can use
essentially whatever you want in Sphinx and of course Sphinx is not the only thing out there.
And there is a list of other static html site generators on this page as well so
feel free to have a look at that. But really the main thing the main reason to use markdown or
restructured text is that it is text so you can version control it and you can use it with your
source code very easily. So yeah we will use Sphinx and one reason is that it is actually
what we use to build this course website. It's very commonly used in Python projects but not
limited, of course, to Python. It is itself, it runs in Python. There's plenty of other options
and a lot of these use Markdown. I guess that's probably enough, probably all we want to say
about this. Sphinx is a built-in thing for API documentation as well.
Okay, let's head on to Encode documentation.
Well, I mean, wikis are another popular option, but they don't exist as text in your repository.
The advantage is that it's pretty easy to start editing it.
You don't even really need to learn any new language, even though Markdown is an easy
language to learn.
But yeah, it is not connected to your repository, which is the main big downside.
Leite is very common and that produces PDFs. The advantage is that it's very popular and
people in certain fields know how to use it. The disadvantage is the PDF format.
It has some restrictions on how you can use it. It is not easy to turn Leite into a website,
although it is possible and it's not easy to automate building it although it is possible
so it gets a bit more complex.
Doxygen is well you can use it for it's very popular for C++ you can use it again for API
documentation so it's kind of like Sphinx it's just another option and here's some other tools
and they kind of seem to go with certain languages but in principle you don't need
to pick a specific one based on what language you use. It just depends on the community.
Okay, so in code documentation. So anything that's inside a source code file is in code
documentation and it's probably the first thing you do maybe after the readme file.
So when you start writing code it's good to already start including some documentation
in the code itself.
So let's take a look at these two comments, I wonder how much should we go back to the
notes even, well let's say, let's paste something into the notes and, okay, let's
Okay, it's already there, so yeah, which one is better, what is useful about either option?
Let's just do a vote, you can write down some comments below, but yeah, vote for option
A or B. So what makes comment B so obviously better? Maybe this was too obvious a question.
This is a pretty obvious question. Well, comment A only says what's plainly written there already.
no additional additional information obtainable from comment a is comment b wrong on purpose
you record temperatures below minus 50 as measurement errors and this checks
if it's larger yes if it's larger than it i don't actually know if it's i don't think it was on
purpose but um yeah you're right now we check if so this one actually doesn't if you just have this
And then this line of code, it doesn't actually
tell you that it's wrong.
But here, you say why you want to check
if it's bigger than minus 50.
And that's a measurement error.
So yeah, now you know that the code is actually
wrong when you just know what it's doing.
It could well be on purpose, actually.
So the comment definitely is useful,
because you just spotted the bug.
Yeah, is there anything here that we didn't mention? Not really? No. Yeah.
Okay, yeah, and there's some situations where people often use
comments where having version control is actually a better option. So sometimes you see people
comment out a piece of code and, you know, for testing that's fine. You comment it out, you run
it once and you see if what you're doing is working. But it's then not a good idea to just
keep it lying around in the code because when you remove a piece of code and you commit it to version
control, commit it to Git, the code exists. Before removing it, if you have committed it to Git,
the code exists in Git and you can get it back. So there's no reason to keep it also commented
out in the code. It just makes the code harder to read.
And this is not even the worst thing. So if it's at least commented out,
it's not looking as if it were a normal code, but I've also seen things like if zero.
Okay. Yeah.
Or if to comment stuff out.
Yeah. I'm guilty of that, but it's usually to force. So for example, if it checks for a file
and then creates one if it doesn't exist. I might force it to delete the existing file and overwrite
it by doing that when developing. But yeah, just keeping that around in the code is not a good
idea. It makes it harder to read. Another one is emulating version control.
So a comment that tells people why you changed a piece of code is not really that useful or that's
what version controllers is meant to do. That's why you write a comment for each comment that
you make in Git. You tell people why you're making the change. So it's not necessary to
make those in the code as well or in comments. I think what's important with these kind of
of in-code comments is that they explain things.
They don't state what's happening,
but they explain why things are happening.
Why are you doing these kind of things, and so on.
And that's where these kind of inline comments become useful.
Yeah.
And then there's a second type of ENCODE documentation.
Yes, so this is more about the API documentation.
There was already a question a little bit further on and
further up in the collaborative document about it.
Ah, right.
And this is, I think, the answer to that question.
What should be in a doc string?
In general, yeah, what's going into the function, what's coming out of the function, what does
the function do so that whatever kind of API documentation generator you would be using
can pass this and create a nice looking documentation out of it.
the better structured for whatever parser you use it is the more the better it
the better it is for the for usability in the end.
Yeah so it is actually very common to see the comments take more space than the actual code
Even though this is a relatively constructed example, it's also relatively realistic.
So it is useful to tell how you're converting between Fahrenheit and Celsius in this function.
And what is the expected input and output.
And it is actually just having this line of code inside your code is less descriptive
than calling this function.
So yeah, this is a good example.
This is how you do it in R, just occasionally change from Python for variety.
Okay, so, yeah, so docstrings can,
they do more than just comments
because you can pass them out into this documentation.
And so you can automatically generate
this API documentation part of your documentation,
which is very useful.
And what that really means is
that your API documentation lives with the code.
It exists in the same place as the code.
and you, well, that makes it more likely
that you will remember to change it
when you change the function.
So there is no separate file
where you have all of your API documentation.
It is in the same file as the code, which is very useful.
Okay, so a good docstring will describe
what the function does.
What are the input variables and what are the outputs?
Format as they are the input variables, so what types?
So essentially, how to use the function and what is it doing.
Oh, and one very good point is that the name of the function
is also important for documentation.
So here, the function name tells you exactly what it's doing.
And that is important.
So then finally to README files, let's go over this section and then have a break.
So README files are kind of the first, well I said that you might want to first start when you're
starting to write the code, you might want to start with in code documentation of some kind,
but then README files are the first thing that a user would see and that anyone you share the
code with. When they get your code the first thing they look at is a readme file and if it's
on GitHub, GitLab, something like that, then it's a nicely formatted section on the front
page of your code. So it is the first thing people see and I think it is very important
to have. So you should always have some kind of a readme file. It might also be enough
in a small enough project to put everything in the readme file.
I would agree.
In general, I think the readme is kind of your way to advertise your code.
Yeah.
So we have a few fun exercises for readme files and I think we should take a little
bit of time to so we have already talked a lot about what is required but we should spend a
little bit of time playing around with it so let's do the exercise one as a demonstration
but for that we need a readme on github so in the next section we'll use this
this documentation example, but I will also use it in this readme example.
And if we open the readme file here, we'll see that it's written in Markdown.
GitHub nicely renders Markdown automatically.
So what are these things?
some more information about what kinds of formatting you can use here. But let's try
make a note. So if I copy the whole thing, maybe it doesn't copy these ticks. Let's see.
So what is each of these things? No, it does copy the ticks. Oh, because the ticks are
part of the Markdown language. Right. Okay. So the first thing is a note.
It will do some fancy formatting. The second is important. And one thing you can do if you're
editing it on GitHub is you can preview. So let's see what it looks like. Okay. So there is a blue
information thing. There is a slightly more red and well I guess yellowish but
more visible version of it. Okay so that's a fun thing you can do. What is this
details and summary? I guess this is some kind of card section. So let's try this.
so if you add this details tag and it has a summary on top, short summary.
Oh okay so details is something that's hidden by default but it has a title
and then when you click on it it expands. So this is useful for making the readme more
readable but still you can include some additional information that people might need.
Okay and then there's some batches. So a lot of projects have these automatically updating
batches that fetch some information like is the documentation up to date and building correctly
or do the tests currently pass in this branch and so on. So this format creates some sort of a batch
This is from image.shields.io, so it builds you this image with the text that you put in.
Which is essentially the address that you use converted into text.
Yeah, so this is also a link that goes to example.org in this case.
this case. But there would be a lot more realistic cases for using this. So you can use a batch,
for example, to show, well, like I said, that the documentation is correctly compiling.
Which would probably come from a different source because that commonly comes from some kind of
of continuous integration or a system that tells you okay it actually builds properly and so on.
Okay so we should go on a break soon. Let's take an example readme quickly
so we can find something on github. Do you have an example in mind that has some batches and
what other useful features we would want to see.
Let's look at
NumPy
is the one that always comes to my mind when I think of a Python project.
Go for NumPy, I think that's fine.
Okay, so NumPy is a huge
project. You have to scroll down a bit to get to the
to the readme file. So the batches are on top. There's a DOI that links to the digital object
identifier of the software. There's a stack overflow page for NumPy where you can ask questions
and it shows how many downloads per month they've had.
And an open SSF. I'm not actually sure what this is, some sort of score. So you might have
something like the coverage of tests and or whether the tests are passing is one I mentioned
all sorts of useful Ataclans information in there and then they have everything
you need to know about NumPy right on top
code of conduct and how to contribute or call for contributions in this case
and yeah, so these are the most important things. In the documentation itself, actually this one,
this readme already tells you how to install it. Does it tell you how to install it? Well,
it has a pypy tag, but it doesn't really tell you how to install it. Okay, fine,
it tells you how to test something, test that it runs correctly.
So here's the documentation page though and let's go to the web version.
So there's a getting started section, there's a user guide, there's the API reference
and how to contribute. So the most important parts are quickly there,
there's installation instructions and links to important things like issue tracker is where you
report bugs for example and support QnA.
Okay so maybe I should still quickly show what an API reference looks like
like so this is I want to function well let's just do infinity so somewhere in the code
they define this numpy.infinity which represents an infinite number and there they have a doc
string that's essentially converted into this section of the documentation okay so I think
that's enough of that example and let's take a break before we go to the next section so
I would say at least until five past then we'll we should have plenty of time all right
so see you at five past bye
Hello, we are back, um, hope you had a good break.
There was a question about the repository that I showed. I didn't actually save the
changes but that's actually the template, that's the repository that we're going to
use in this next demonstration anyway. So I will show it in a moment. Sorry, we don't
use it in this one. We use it in the next one. So let me just quickly hop over to that
just to answer the question that I started to answer.
So there is this documentation example repository
that allows you to generate an example that we
will be using today.
And what I showed was actually generated
from this documentation example.
So it's something that I will delete in
after this course is over.
but you can also generate an example from here.
It will be more important later what the contents are,
but of course, for the thing that I showed,
it was mainly that it has a README file.
Okay, so Sphinx and Markdown.
So yeah, we mentioned that Sphinx is the thing
we use to generate these course materials,
and they are large part written in Markdown.
And you can also use RichText in
RichText with Sphinx, that is probably the default
but it's also easy to use Markdown
and since you're all used to Markdown by now
because all the nodes are in Markdown, we will use that.
Okay, so this is mainly a demonstration
so I will soon move into the
Visual Studio window
But you can also try to do this probably better to just follow along for now but you can also
try to do this in a project of your own or just following these steps.
So I will just expand this window a bit.
Okay, so the instructions start with some checks that everything is working as expected.
So Sphinx runs in Python, so we need to have Python.
We do have Python.
I will just quickly run through this, just that we don't run into problems while doing
the demonstration.
So we need Sphinx build. Whoops, I clicked on Sphinx build, and now I'm no longer copied.
I have no longer copied what I was expecting. So, okay, Sphinx quick start is a descriptive
tool we'll use. It has the correct version. Everything's fine. And one important thing
that you need to install separately is this mist parser. So for this to work, you need
both Python, Sphinx, and Mist parser.
So Mist is the kind of markdown we will be using.
Okay, so let's get started.
So right now we are in an empty folder.
So there's nothing in here.
I will make a new directory.
I'll actually use the file view for that.
new folder
doc example
and then in there we okay we need to go in that folder and then run
Sphinx quick start in that folder so let's go there to documentation example
and then run Sphinx quick start right here
Okay, maybe I need a bit more space for this. Okay, so it asks you a few questions.
Let's say I don't want to separate the directories now. It's usually best to just
stick with the standard, with the defaults. Project name is something we of course need.
need. This is only a test project. Let's call it that. Or should we have a funny name for
it? I'm not great with funny names. I will not start because then I will not be able
to continue. Okay. Author's names, that's my name. Project release, so that's the version
number, let's say. So it's 0.0.1. And language, let's do English. So it will support English.
English and no other languages by default.
Okay. So now we have a bunch of new files here.
So quickstart created
all the files that Sphinx needs to run in this folder.
There's this conf.py,
which has all the configuration for this project.
there's all the project name, copyright statement, all those name,
version number and then we have some extensions that you can add
and we will in fact add one since we are here why not do it now. So we want to add this
mist parser extension here. Okay and that's probably the only thing we want to change in this
in this file. Let's look at the other files. So okay, conf.py has the configuration options
for Sphinx. Then we have an index.rst, which is the main file for this documentation. It's a
rich text file. Oh, sorry, [name], did you say something?
No, I wouldn't call it the main, it's the root file.
Okay, yeah, the root file. So, in this case, it has a title and then it has a talk tree,
so a table of contents, yes. And then you can define some indices in here that it will
use to generate the documentation pages.
Okay, the makefile and make.bat are something you use to actually build the documentation,
so they're workflow files.
We don't need to go into the details of what's in there because it will look pretty complicated.
And it's essentially like you never modify.
Yeah.
Okay.
So there's an empty build directory, an empty static directory, an empty templates directory.
So the build directory, it's where Sphinx puts things that it creates.
So you generally don't put anything in there.
is for your own HTML templates, you will not be creating any of those in this example.
And static is for static files for the HTML site like images or CSS for styles and so on.
So mainly images are the ones you will run into first, those will go into the static folder.
Okay, so let's look at the index.
So we will not use this indices and tables section, so we can remove it.
And then, okay, so this section here is a comment in rich text, so this will not be
displayed on the website. Let me show the whole thing. It states that it's the master file created
by Sphinx Quickstart. Then we have this table of contents, max depth of the table. If a file
contains sections, like how deep do you want to go in those sections? And then in here,
we can add our own pages. Sorry, let me
disable that because it is definitely going to make things
weird for what we want to do here. Okay, so I should actually probably have logged out of
everything. Okay, so here we go. We can add a page into a documentation, so somefeature.markdown.
This is a file name and that file doesn't exist yet, so we need to add it, but
once we add it, it will be in the table of contents. Okay, so let's add that file.
Let's call it somefeature.md and then we can start adding things here.
So this is now marked down so it should look relatively familiar by this point.
It has a title, it has a subsection title, some normal text and a list and some nested
items in that list.
And I need to also save this one.
And now going back to the terminal, I could probably run something in VS Code as well
to run this. But, well, let's just run it in the terminal, follow the instructions to
the letter. So, what we run is Sphinx build. Then we give it the directory that we want
to where the input files are in,
which is this current directory, so dot,
and then where do we want to put all the build files?
And that's the underscore build directory.
Okay, there's a warning, non-existent.
It didn't find some feature.
Okay, so did I do something wrong?
Yes, some-
There's a typo.
Oh no, wait.
somefeature.md. Yes this is somefeature.md. So then the right folder. Okay it should be.
No. No it's not. True. This isn't right. So I originally opened
the folder one above this one and then created this folder. Okay so it was in the wrong folder.
It's a slightly unintended. Okay, let's try again. So I'll go to the terminal and run the
same command again by pressing up arrow. There we go. And there it was.
Am I sharing the entire terminal window now? I think there are many.
Might be cutting off a little bit of the bottom.
Yeah, it's actually complete.
OK.
It just looks odd because it's line breaking.
No, I mean, I think the last thing I'm seeing in the stream
is this line here.
Yeah, sorry.
OK, I've updated it.
Yeah.
So the command I just ran is this things build dot
and then underscore build.
OK, so mostly it was visible just
when it reads the end of the last line, then you maybe didn't see it. Okay, but here we are.
It's a little bit wider as well.
Okay, so now we should have the files. It didn't complain about anything.
And now in this build directory, this is what we had previously. And now we have
Well, we have some HTML files, importantly, an index.html.
So we can open that in a web browser and see what's inside.
So there's different ways of doing that from the terminal.
I think in this case, we can try to do this in VS Code.
We can go live, on the live server.
The problem is that it will open the folder that's in the bottom of the, but while it
will open the folder that's currently open in VS Code.
So this font is really small, okay, now it's really big.
So yeah, that's the build directory and finally, okay, so now it opened the actual documentation
page.
So this is what the default looks like, it's a table of contents, there's some feature
and a subsection and then there's this navigation area.
Okay, so let's go to some feature and this is now the page we wrote in Markdown for this
some feature section.
Okay, so how are we doing?
are actually we haven't spent all that much time here yet so let's do a bit more
so we can go and edit the somefeature.markdown and try some
try some more fancy features of the mist markdown.
Okay, so maybe not as that fancy,
but there's different levels of titles,
which we are already seeing.
So just level one,
level two.
so this will look slightly different once we run oops that's still level two with three of these
hashes it will be level three and with four hashes it will be level
four okay so this will look slightly different actually why not
why not just keep recompiling and show as we go
Okay so this is what the different levels of titles look like.
There's a useful feature here so there is a permalink
to each of these heading each of these sections so when you say
hash then the section title it will take you directly to that section in the documentation.
Okay, so what else can you do? You can do numbered lists, so let's do three items,
but now we don't actually have to keep numbering the items correctly. You can make edits and
sometimes the numbers come out or sometimes you forget to change the numbers, but
but the Markdown Renderer takes care of that for you, so the numbers will come up correctly
in this case, yeah, that's expected. Okay, then some other things you can do and you can
also test this in the notes. Maybe don't add too large tables into the notes, but okay,
This is what a table looks like.
So you need to have a header and a line below the header and then the renderer will realize
that this is supposed to be a table.
Okay so this is a table of whether each number is prime.
I'm always a bit confused about why one is not a prime,
but fine.
Two is a prime.
Maybe one is a prime.
What do you think?
Let's also add a bit of spacing there just to,
so one useful thing, of course, in Markdown is that
the texts written into,
The text document itself usually looks good enough on its own, so you don't even need
to render it to be able to read it properly.
But this creates a table, so 4 is not a prime, which is good to know.
And then, well, you can have, importantly in software documentation, you can have code.
So this is Python code.
So we'll start with three ticks and then the language name.
So Python.
So let's just do a quick function.
hello world or just hello and this function prints
hello world okay so that's an example of how to include code in
in markdown and i will language yeah in a certain language so i will quick
also just copy paste in an example from that's written in C so that you see there's multiple
languages I just didn't write to write all of this C code into the markdown file okay
because there's a lot of a lot more you need to do in C to get the same result okay
OK, you can also include a file directly.
So this is literal include directive.
So it's the same three ticks, and then literal include,
and the name of the file.
That was the question, if you can give a bit more
explanation of what you can configure and what you can do.
and I think going through the conf.py a bit would be useful. Okay yeah.
Let's see so there's one more thing so we don't have an example.py so this will not actually
work so let's get rid of this section but one more thing before that so you can
also write math equations which is important in many fields
So this is a math section and this is something that the specifically missed flavored markdown does for you.
I think that's also for the literal include, that's also missed.
Oh yeah, okay, that is true.
We do need to do something in the conf.py to get this to work, so we'll be there in a second.
So we'll just write this very interesting equation with a green theorem.
Okay, and you can also do an inline equation.
So again, math is, it's not square brackets, what are these called?
Curly brackets.
Curly brackets, okay.
Okay. So that's an inline equation. Okay. And so, okay, this will actually not work.
No, let's see. I'm quite surprised.
Well, it mentions that in some older versions of Sphinx, you needed to include it.
Okay, yes, so this Sphinx is, so now this is included in Sphinx or with the Mist
parser extension directly. We don't need to change the config file for this to work.
Let's change the config file anyway.
So here's the config file. So there's not that much here actually.
That's where to look for HTML templates and what files to not include.
And we could change the HTML theme.
Yeah, we can do that. I don't know what the defaults are.
Well, you could use the Sphinx RTD. I think that should be part of the Codefinery environment.
Okay, let's do that. So is it Sphinx RTD?
I think read the docs RTD. Yes. Let's see if this works. No. Okay. So we don't have
that one. So that failed. It's things RTD underscore RTD underscore theme. Sphinx read
Orthodox theme with underscores.
Okay.
Okay, that works.
So yeah, this looks a lot nicer, doesn't it?
This looks pretty much like our course documentation,
which is built on this as well.
Okay.
It's half past, so yeah, okay, we are doing good time.
time. So I mean in principle there's a lot you can change but a lot of it is not in the default
configuration options here. So you have HTML templates so you can write any HTML file you
want and include the contents in that Sphinx creates into that. There's also a number of
these themes that you can use and you can install third-party themes as Python packages.
So there is a lot you can do.
But yeah, so I don't know if there's anything we can easily demonstrate here in the time we have.
I think the theming is probably the easiest that we have done that.
Yeah.
Okay.
We could build this example.py file to show how it actually works and just add a example.py.
this literal include section it also specifies the language and we are putting emphasis on
lines two and three here so we don't know what those lines are yet because we didn't
create the file yet lines two and three that means if I'm importing
something, it will probably be those lines.
So those are the lines we're emphasizing and then we do something.
I think that's already sufficient.
Yeah.
Okay.
So that's some Python code.
And let's demo.
And your example of Py is again in the wrong folder.
True.
Let's move it to the right folder.
Okay.
Good.
Thanks for noticing that.
Okay.
So now it's including the example code directly,
and it's added some emphasis on these two lines.
And that's pretty convenient, especially in our case,
where we sometimes have examples that build on one another,
and we just want to highlight what changed
in between the previous and this piece of code.
So that's something that's quite useful there.
yeah and of course this is a way of including the same example in multiple different places
for example okay so we did the math we did the so we we did not add one thing we didn't add
is api documentation and we have talked a good bit about that so maybe we should do that one
as well before moving on to the next part. One thing I want to mention is that this is
also a nice way to, in general, present examples and keep the examples as actual runnable files.
So I think you can do literal includes that only include certain lines and don't
not just highlight but just include the specific lines that you want to show.
but you essentially have the example files as whole scripts or whatever,
which makes it more usable in the end.
Yeah, that's a good point.
Because often you write a tutorial with some code examples,
but it's hard to write that in such a way
that the code examples actually work and actually run.
run. It is hard to test those code examples but if you instead include certain lines from a script
you can always run the script and see that it actually works. Okay so I've deleted the
script-like part that I added but instead now I'm adding this multiply function and importantly this
function has in code documentation, it has an API reference. So this is now our code for this
project and we want to have an API reference added to our documentation. We don't currently have one.
So how do we do that? First we need to go back to this index.rst file
and we will be documenting the example module example.py here. So let's just call it the
subsection example. Let's actually add a whole main section API reference.
I assume the example will work but this looks a lot like
Markdown and RST are getting mixed together so we'll see. It looks suspicious.
Okay, so this is another of these tree tick sections, we'll call this eval RST.
I am very much starting to think that I'm doing something wrong here.
No, I think that's perfectly fine.
This is already RST, so why don't I just have an RST section directly, like this.
Ah, yeah, but then you can't use the hashtags for the titles, the API reference.
Yes.
Well, this title is already in RST.
This title is already in rich text, so why not do it this way?
Okay.
So let's have an example of how to do titles in rich text instead.
So this is a big title and this is a small one, I think level one and level two.
So this will be auto module example.
So module in this case is a Python module, it's this example module here.
And then some magic words members so we include all of the members everything that's in example.py.
Okay and now we do need to go and change the configuration file conf.py.
We need to add an extension autodoc extension we need to make some other changes as well.
So, there is an auto-doc extension that generates this API documentation.
The rest of this stuff, I think, maybe goes on top, but below this first comment, maybe.
Yeah, on top.
So we need to import some things.
What we essentially need to do is we need to inform Sphinx on where this can be found.
And that's what we're doing here.
From OS, we are getting the path we are currently on.
And this allows us to set the path Python
is looking for code in.
So if you are not familiar with Python,
you can think of this as a magic expression.
But then you put whatever your source path is in here.
So our source path is the current directory,
so we just use dot.
OK.
Should it run now?
I think it should run.
I think it should.
In a normal Python project, you would probably
have something like source in here and not dot.
Yeah, or the Python package name.
You know what I did incorrectly here?
I've just added this section directly to the index.rst,
and not as a separate file.
That's why I got confused.
It doesn't hurt too much.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay, so it should build.
Build the example, build import module, example.
No module named my project.
Okay, so what is happening?
Right. I still have these lines that don't work in my code.
Yeah.
I should be importing something else. Okay. So yeah, now it should work as long as I have
NumPy available.
Which I think you have.
And let's do some proper formatting there. Okay. Now it works. Okay. So now let's go
back to the main page and here we have the API documentation directly in the main page which is
not the best thing. Not optimal.
Okay. Normally you would do this. Yeah normally it would be a separate section here
in a separate file. Okay but it's, we have a limited amount of time it would not be that
complicated to fix this, but it works already, so let's keep it as it is.
Okay, so that was the Sphinx and Markdown example. There's a lot of stuff there you can play around
with. You can try doing this yourself either with the example or with your own project.
Are people confused about Mist and Markdown and restructured text?
Not a huge number of questions in the notes, so I guess we're fine.
Well, there's a bit more information here.
Write them in the document. We can come to them later or they can be answered in the document as well.
One useful thing to mention that often saves me and often I forget to do and therefore get into trouble is there is a way of checking links in this generated documentation.
So, at least if the links just don't work at all, this will help you.
If they lead you to the wrong place, it might not save you, but it's a very common issue
to add wrong or incorrect links, so this is useful.
Okay, let's then head on to the next section.
GitHub pages and how to deploy Sphinx documentation to GitHub pages. This is again using GitHub
and GitHub is not the only option, but it is a common and easy option. Since basically
everything we have is on GitHub, we will demonstrate using GitHub.
GitHub. So we will be using two things, GitHub pages, which is a way of including websites
essentially in your repository and showing them as HTML as websites instead of the source
code. And GitHub actions, which are things that run automatically when you push something
to your repository so this is a really useful thing in general we'll see an example of.
Okay so yeah this is pulling a lot of stuff from the past two weeks and putting it all together
so we'll just go into it and see how it goes. Okay so there is this documentation example
repository and I already made my own version of this documentation example, so it's generated
from this template as it says here and at this point I should have the instructions
available for me. Okay, just a small moment. Here we are.
So this is a repository that contains,
it's already on GitHub,
but it contains essentially what we just did.
So there's a documentation folder in this repository.
It has a conf.py for Sphinx
and all of this other status,
some feature.markdown that we just created.
It is very familiar looking.
and then there's a source folder for our actual software. It's actually an empty folder
just as a readme file that says this is where your code would go. So yeah, this is an example.
Okay, so
we could clone this locally and do what we just did to build the documentation,
but instead we're going to do it with a workflow file so we will add a new file
is the um is the text too small
that may be slightly better okay so let's create a new file
and this needs to go into dot github slash workflows
And now we can choose whatever name we want for the workflow, so let's call it documentation
and it's a YML file, a YAML file.
So this is something I would rarely type out, basically never, I just always get an example
from somewhere and change the parts that need changing.
But the syntax is not that complicated.
So a workflow has a name, documentation.
When do we want to run it?
So we run on a push, a pull request.
So if somebody makes a pull request,
we want to run this documentation builder.
And then workflow dispatch.
This means that we can manually ask this workflow to run.
which is useful for an example. Okay permissions so it needs so the idea is that it work this
workflow will build our documentation and then put it in our repository in a branch
and then that branch is our website so it needs the permission to write into our repository.
Let's give it write permissions to the contents of the repository.
Okay and then we'll define a job for this workflow to run.
So there's a job step called docs.
This will run on so you need to tell it what operating system you want your job to run on.
Ubuntu. That's the simplest option for me. And then we define some steps to run.
Okay. So at this point, maybe I will quickly tell you what each step does,
but I will not write out the details. So first we need to check out or clone our repository.
and then we need to install Python because Sphinx runs in Python. Then we need to install
some dependencies and that is a piece of code we write ourselves. So this step install
dependencies runs a piece of code which is pip install and the dependencies we need.
Okay. Am I now on the same level as the name? Yes. Okay. Then we want to build the documentation.
So it also runs a command. It runs the Sphinx build command. The source for the documentation
is the doc folder and the build folder is where the documentation goes.
Now, importantly, the build folder will not appear in our repository. It's not modifying
our repository at this point. It's just running on some random machine in the cloud and creating
a build folder. So, we need to copy it somewhere where other people can see it. So, deploy
to GitHub pages. Now, what does this do? This runs a workflow
someone else wrote for us that actually does the deployment but we need to give it some parameters
and well okay before we give it the parameters we only want it to run if the push is to the main
if something gets pushed to the main branch so this looks a bit complicated it is a bit
complicated but what it does it it prevents this from publishing documentation that's
in the wrong branch. That's in a pull request, for example. So, only documentation in the main
branch gets updated to the actual documentation. Okay. And then some parameters. Publish it to
a branch called GitHub Pages. It needs a secret token to actually modify the repository.
and well that's where it should find the build documentation.
Okay, so a good number of steps here but each of them in principle is hopefully something that's
familiar to you by now. So we are cloning a repository, installing Python, installing
dependencies, building the documentation,
and the last thing is new.
We are pushing it to a new branch
in our existing repository.
OK.
Now I have a new file.
I want to commit this to GitHub.
Actually, this is a pretty good commit message.
to build and publish documentation. Okay. And I'll just push directly to the main branch
in this case. I'm the only one working on this project. Okay.
Here we go. Now we have a new workflow file. Okay. Well, did anything happen? Not really.
Yes, there did.
it is something did happen. It is already running. So the workflows are already set to run
in this repository. They are automatically set to run. As soon as you have any workflows being
set up, they will run. Okay, that's nice. There's a workflow that hasn't completed yet,
but we can look at the details from here. So this is all the steps we just defined.
And now it is done.
Now it is done.
Okay.
So it prints some output at each step.
It's installed Python, Sphinx build and so on.
Okay.
So what did it do?
It created a new branch.
Oh, that's still yellow.
Maybe I need to just refresh the page.
Now it's, yeah, it's a nice green tick.
So everything's working.
created a new branch called GitHub pages which is here and now this has this index.html and
everything that's needed for the website. That's essentially a copy of the build directory
as we specified in our. Okay I would assume that it's not working as a page yet though
I need to go to settings. Yeah at least it's not deployed as a page yet. So if I go to settings
there's a pages section here and here I can select deploy from a branch
and the branch I want to deploy from is github pages
gh pages okay and the root of that branch save the settings
Okay, and now if I go to, so the URL is slightly different from this repository URL, but it's
related.
So I need to go to myusername.github.io and then the name of the repository.
Okay and here we are. So now my documentation is online. Anyone can go to this address and
see it. Actually one very useful thing to do after this would be to take this URL and
edit the readme file and add some sort of link to it in here. I will do the simplest
possible job of adding the link here but you might want to format it slightly better.
Add a link to documentation in readme.
Okay, so now we have, I guess, I made a mistake in Markdown syntax here.
Okay, so now we have a link to the documentation in our README and it will get updated automatically.
So now I did a new push, it's rebuilding the documentation, although even though there
wasn't any change to the documentation.
It's always when I change anything in this repository,
it will rebuild and publish again.
You can also, which people very often do,
put it into the About.
Yes, so the About section is not visible now
if I make it a bit smaller.
So here is an About section.
So if you click on that cogwheel in the top right corner,
there's the website URL.
OK.
Or use your GitHub pages website,
which will point to the correct one,
even if you change the name of the repository.
You can also add a description here.
Example of building documentation.
OK, now that's updated.
So now there's a link to the documentation
right here in the sidebar for anyone who's
looking at the Adjurable story.
After this is the lunch break, right?
So we have five more minutes.
We definitely don't want to start on the next section, which is
how to publish your own website in GitHub Pages.
It is quite similar
to this one, and you can check it out on your own.
I guess the biggest difference is that we're not automatically building
the documentation. We're not automatically building
the website. We are only publishing it on GitHub Pages.
Yeah. Well, I did mention there are alternatives. There's GitLab. CI GitLab is a common alternative
to GitHub. And GitLab Pages, Read2Docs is commonly used. And well, those are the alternatives
we mentioned here, I guess. There's essentially all the places where you can host your report
stories. Almost all of them also have a way of hosting a static website because it is
actually just HTML code.
Which you could also on whatever other server, web server you have that you in some way control
and just point it to, okay, this is the static website.
Yeah.
True.
GitHub Pages or GitLab Pages is just a very simple way to have a web host for you, that
you don't have to explicitly pay.
So we will skip over the hosting websites and homepages on GitHub and go to the summary.
And probably the best way of doing this would be to ask everyone, if you have any questions
questions, please ask them in the notes and see if there's anything interesting there
or anything very important to bring up.
I think the first point in the summary is actually quite important. There is not the
one right way to do things in documentation. And I would add to that, it's in general more
important to have some documentation than to have a perfect documentation yeah yeah this is a typical
case of better have something incomplete than not having anything at all well now if you feel
this went too fast or you just want to learn this better to actually use this on your own
repository. The instructions are on the course website or on the website for this section.
So I essentially followed this deploying Sphinx documentation to GitHub almost exactly. So
just take a look there and the Sphinx and Markdown section where you can set up your
documentation first.
But yeah, so there's always a balance you need to find with how much time you spend
writing documentation versus how much time you spend coding and how much time you spend
doing research and other things in your life.
So for smaller projects, a README file can easily contain everything you need, especially
you have in code documentation as well. Something that takes that in code documentation and turns it
into an API reference is nice and you can do that very quickly with Sphinx even if you don't write
any other documentation in there. But that's a small step further and then in a bigger project
you will have a full-fledged website with lots of examples and so on. So it depends on
practically speaking how much time you have to spend on this and you want of course to spend
time actually writing your code as well and not just documentation so there is a balance there.
In most projects, just a README is enough, because most projects are small.
And you can essentially put all the examples also just in the README if it's a really small project.
Even kind of API definitions you can put in the README
in a small project and you don't need to set up a whole Sphinx environment for it.
Okay but it is time to go for lunch break. After the lunch break we will have a section
on Jupyter notebooks. Anyone who is around do you want to do a quick outro or a quick teaser
of what's after the lunch break? Jupyter notebooks are a really useful tool for research so
Yeah, I mean, I guess many people know Jupyter in general.
Here we go over just a little bit of the basics in case anyone doesn't know.
But more important than that, we talk about how to make them a little bit more reproducible,
like some ways of sharing them, which perhaps you didn't know about.
of diffing and merging them using them with version control and so on. So
basically it will help you go from using them and a big mess to using them and a
little bit more organized and closer to regular code. So with that should we go
to lunch yep so okay we will see you later then enjoy your lunch okay thanks
bye bye