♪
file, where the code is really nice. Yeah, that's really reproducibility right here.
It's this can be a nice, really nice way of sharing supporting information that should
go along with the manuscript. So the manuscript has the has the summary. But then if I want
to verify it or to understand it, or I want to reuse it, I have all the steps here available.
a wonderful solution to share. So instead of just putting graphics, I mean images and
tables into the manuscript, it can be a nice way to put images and tables into the manuscript,
but then put all the steps into a notebook. And here we show you Jupyter notebook but maybe
if you are developing R, maybe you're using R Markdown. And that's a similar idea. So
So here's more about the idea than again, than really, it's more about the why than
the how.
Yeah.
So basically, in our studio, can you do the similar thing in our markdown?
I have never used it, but I think it's possible.
Yes.
Sorry.
I was just, I will answer one question in the, in the notes, but it's the same idea
that you can interleave code and markdown text in the same document.
And please, all the comments and questions, as usual, in the collaborative document, especially
[name] is now checking out them and can raise something out loud if we find something that
we particularly want to share in the stream also.
Scrolling onwards to the lesson material,
there's use cases and pitfalls.
So as with any tool, Jupyter is good for something,
but then not so good for some occasions.
And here we try to have some overall view
of the good stuff and then the not so good stuff.
stuff. So, the basic use case is this kind of linear workflow. And how I understand the
linear workflow is that it starts from a point and goes forward from there, not doing any
branches and so on. So, do you agree, [name]?
Exactly. It's really an excellent fit for when you have this step-by-step workflow and
at the end comes a figure, an image.
Yeah, you mentioned data analysis. So you start from reading a data in and then some
data manipulations cleaning up and then doing the plots and there you go. So that kind of
I think Jupyter is really good.
And as mentioned also, if you want to experiment and test,
it's really easy to experiment
because you can have the different versions there
next to each other and run them as you like.
And there's many, yeah.
So the service that [name] shown,
and we will later demonstrate,
it allows people to run the codes
without like installing anything, they can run it in the browser. So we will come back
to that. Yeah. And maybe if we have time, if you if it's easy for you to open up the
notes, we are getting a couple of really good questions. Yeah. And I want to encourage more.
So at the bottom, there are two that we can briefly discuss now one is how does it work
with privacy and sensitive data. And what we what we will later show is that it can
be a good idea to put your notebook onto GitHub and make it runnable for everybody and make
that part of your paper. But now how about privacy and sensitive data? So what can you
do there? I mean, you don't want to put the actual sensitive data then on GitHub and make
it publicly visible.
Yeah, never a good idea to put sensitive data in GitHub. But like, I would like to start
from the fact that Jupyter runs, if you want to do locally, you can run Jupyter locally
on your computer, so you don't have to share anything anywhere if you don't want to.
And then considering GitHub and sharing and reusability, you can share your code, but
But not the data.
And I think that's the case, regardless of the tool that you are using to write the code.
But it's still nice to share some data so that people can actually run it.
But then you don't have to share the actual sensitive data.
You can show you can share an example data set with John Doe, Jane Doe, example person.
And so that people can still verify this is working, they can still replace it by the
actual data.
But then the sensitive data can be then protected on a dedicated server.
So that can be a good solution.
Similar solution is if your data is big, gigantic, but if you have terabytes of data and it's
difficult for you to share it, it can still be nice to share a small example data set
so then people can still run your notebook, but then replace it by the real gigantic data.
How about kit and notebooks?
I just want to say that we will come back to that.
Yeah.
In before, in the next half an hour, we will show you what are some of the challenges when
working with Git.
Because we still want to work with Git, we still didn't forget what we thought last week.
We want to use Git.
But there are some challenges, but we will show you that there are really nice solutions
to to use all the tools from last week to in combination with notebooks.
So we will get there.
And keep the questions coming.
This is wonderful.
Yeah.
And there's an upcoming question about the privacy in Google Colab.
So I think in there, it's the question of Google's privacy and should refer to the privacy
statement of the Google Colab service.
Yes.
And if I would run them the notebook with sensitive data, I would run it on the infrastructure
made for it.
And maybe that's my own computer.
Yeah.
You can run also JupyterLab in many HPC clusters, so then the data can be in your cluster, but
you can still use Jupyter if that's what you like for your workflow.
Some of the pitfalls in Jupyter, especially when there's this non-linear code flow.
Would you like to elaborate on that a little bit right away.
So if it starts to, if you have, if you write a program that has lots of modules, and it's
not first we do this, then we do this, then we do that, then we do the other thing.
But sometimes you have a code that maybe we go in here into this module, or maybe not
maybe into the other module, then it, it doesn't really fit into a notebook.
Your notebook is really like a recipe of do these series of steps.
If it doesn't fit into a series of steps, then maybe notebook is not the right thing.
But you can use modules also in Jupyter.
You can so the and we will get back to that tomorrow, we will actually show how to do it.
So you can if you have reusable code blocks, and you realize that while I'm using the same
code block in all of my notebooks, and I'm tired of copy pasting it.
You can put these into module and you can include modules in a notebook, but it should
be this series of steps.
If it's a series of steps, then yes, yeah.
And mention some good practices, Jupyter, the basic Jupyter usually renames that you
use is the default naming of untitled.
So when you start a new notebook, it's a good idea to always have your own name so that
you later know what the notebook is about.
And also run all cells before saving.
I think that's something that we can show in the example later.
Yeah, let's demonstrate the good practices.
Yes.
So the notebook interface and how to actually start the whole JupyterLab.
So I will go into a terminal here and get it started.
Let's see where I am.
And typically, so we everybody else than Matias, we should watch and ask, but I just wanted
to comment here that typically we want to start the notebook, you are often inside some
environment.
So now we are in inside a software environment.
And often you have a specific environment for each of your projects.
This is something that we have recommended yesterday.
And in there, we will now start up a notebook and the notebook will then open up.
we start it, but then we, we interact with it through the browser.
Yes. So as mentioned in the material, I create a new folder and I go there and then it says
I have to launch the JupyterLab. But first I need the Codefinery Conda environment, right?
Yes, so here you activate your programming environment that we have set up with all the
dependencies that we need.
For this example, if people later want to try it on their own, like you can, you can
create an environment that is looks exactly like ours.
And in this you can run this around the JupyterLab.
Is it the JupyterLab with minus in or is it JupyterSpaceLab?
work actually, with or without the minus.
And I wanted to mention that you actually can, if you don't want to mess up with Code
Refinery and Conda environment stuff, you might be unsure how the Conda works or something.
We encourage you to try and ask for help if needed, but if you don't want to, there is
also a version of JupyterLab as a desktop app. I'm not sure which platforms
it supports but that exists at least. So here now I'm launching the JupyterLab
in the terminal. I'm using this no browser option because I want to
decide where in which browser I open it. There's a lot of text coming up but we
We don't want, we don't need to care about that.
Only thing we do is we copy paste this URL in the end.
So if you would, if you would have left out this no browser, it would open up your default
browser somewhere.
But if you want to have more control of which browser it is, I also do the same thing as
you.
I take it into my browser, then I decide where this is opened.
So I copy-paste this to a browser into URL field and it opens.
So now the...
Actually let's go to see how this Jupyter is structured.
So in the core there's this kernel and notebook server and they are now running in the terminal
here.
And then the browser is what shows you the user interface, and then you can happily use
it.
So now we have the user interface in the browser, and now we should go to see what's around
the Jupyter interface, right?
So in the material there's this screenshot that you can refer to whenever you want to
if you forget something.
Is it easy for you to zoom in a little bit?
Yes, I think so.
Yeah, great, thanks.
So we have this toolbar containing some tabs.
Then there's some buttons, some menus and the file view in the right side.
So the toolbar contains the file explorer and open kernels and the git integration and
this works if you have used the CodeRefinery Conda environment because this is an extension
and it's there installed.
why we recommend trying the CodeRefinery Conda environment and other extensions in here.
But we focus on the file browser and later on in the Git extension.
So now what we do, we create a new Jupyter Notebook and the launcher in here is the place
to go.
The first option is Notebook.
There are other options.
You can open a terminal or text file or markdown file here if you want to.
But as we are in Jupyter, let's go with the Notebook option.
I'm going to zoom out just a little bit.
And as I mentioned, it creates a new file and it's untitled.
So what I do first is rename the file, right?
Is there questions or something?
Should I just go on?
All is good.
Yep, great.
So now in the Jupyter notebook file, there are different types of cells.
I can create more cells and I can delete cells.
I can reorganize cells and this is obviously some keyboards or how it looks very fast.
Yes.
And I can say that the way I do it often is that I click on these symbols.
Also, if you move the mouse over the cell,
there is a symbol like I want one more cell above or below.
Yes.
Just quickly mentioned that I'm gonna explain
from the material, I'm gonna explain these cells,
but afterwards there is the list of keyboard shortcuts.
And as with any tool,
if you want to use a tool quickly and effectively,
I really recommend to learn the shortcuts it applies to any any tool basically
Everything is of course like credible mentioned it's it's all here you can
Yeah I meant the symbols in the cell like if you yeah this you know the third cell from
the top and then the symbols to the right there I use those
Yeah, so you can reorder.
You can add cells below, above and delete cells.
Yeah, I use the keyboard shortcuts.
There's a A for,
actually it shows the keyboard shortcuts in here.
So you can hover your mouse and start to learn.
Nice, I didn't know, okay.
That's right, that's a handy one.
So they are different.
Now, these are all code cells.
I'm gonna remove all but two.
And what would be the first cell
if you start a new notebook?
Would you start with the code cell?
In reality, yes, but later,
I would like to have a title there,
but maybe I will come up with the title later,
but let's start with the title.
Yeah.
So here's a small menu that you can open and see all the different types of cells that
you can have.
Usually I use Markdown and of course Code4Code, but then there are certain cases you might
want to use raw, that means it shows you the raw text, nothing fancy there.
But we want the fancy thing, so let's go with Markdown.
And the point there is that it renders nicely, so it looks fancier than just the plain text.
How did I get it to render?
I use this run command, and it tells you that shift enter is the shortcut there.
This is now the start of my cool coding project, and then I can start the coding stuff.
What should I import there?
Sounds good. Yeah. Right. So there are markdown cells and there's code cells. What else you
can put in the markdown cells than just text?
I'm wondering whether we should follow the example that we have there, just that people
can recreate it step by step or? I just found and copied the Markdown cell from
that lesson material and now if I run this one we can see different options so
there's headings, there's links, there's different formatting for the text and
even equations and images. So this is really nice and the equations work as
everything that's in between these dollar signs is an equation and the
syntax is the LaTeX syntax.
Okay, so some of the shortcuts and navigation.
If you double click the cell you go to the edit mode
or you can go with Enter and Esc keys to the edit mode and back.
you can with arrow keys like from here from the edit mode I run or click ESC
and then I can with arrow keys navigate the cells back and forth.
And let's not forget to save.
Okay. I think we go forward. Is there any questions?
All is good. So just to summarize, we, you, you have often two, two ways to create cells.
It can be a code for it, for example, Python, and it can be a markdown cell and markdown.
we have discussed earlier today markdown is what we see in the in the notes document and
then you can do more you can do equations and images and then we will build up notebooks
by putting code and documentation and try to tell a story so what's the example that
we will show next. Yes. Go next. And there's the first computational notebook example.
And you mentioned the magic word story. So one of the benefits is there that you can
have this narrative around the code. And that makes it easier to understand for people that
are new to your code.
So in this example, we are creating this code that calculates pi, the value of pi with this
statistical method.
And scrolling onward, we first launch the JupyterLab.
That's what we have here already.
I'm going to hide those first cells that I can get a clean slate.
We can also start a new notebook even inside, isn't it?
Yeah, that's even better.
So here's this plus button and we get the launcher back and new notebook.
And again, it's untitled.
rename it. And here again we are, this is demo only, [name] will type and we will
check that there are no typos. Yes. And everybody please ask questions. So if you
don't remember anymore how I did open the Jupyter in a browser that I wanted
it. Here's the command in this demo.
And I think now your goal will be to scroll down to the first point and we will build
up an example notebook by following these points 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8. And if people
later want to try it out on their own, you can, you find everything here.
So first I copy-paste, it says that add it to a markdown cell, so I copy this line here,
go to my JupyterLab and I'm using the shortcut M to create this, to change this cell to be
a markdown cell.
Of course I can use the option menu here as well.
I click into the cell and Command V, I'm using Mac, so Command V or Control V to paste.
Then we go to see what else is there.
So all the cells that are needed to create this demo, they are included in here.
So what you basically can do is to copy paste the cells.
be careful that you use the appropriate cell types. So what happens if I use a code cell for this?
At first it looks not so great. And if I try to run it, it does not run because that's not
a code syntax. So that's why... Yeah, it's not Python. It will try to interpret
that's this with Python and Python is then confused.
Yes, and then it's again Markdown cell.
Oh, there's a cool picture.
So this is now a conceptual explanation
on the method that we're gonna use on this Pi calculation.
Again, now this, I took this one, so fourth one.
Now this is the first code cell, which is there.
So it imports the modules that we need.
That's why we don't see an output for this code cell
because there's no output.
It just imports the libraries that we want to.
I will continue copy pasting the cells.
The point here is not to understand this code or the Python syntax,
but to figure out why this Jupyter Notebook is
then a nice way of structuring the code or
a nice tool to use for this kind of code exercise.
So now these are the all the cells if I didn't miss any in between and we got
these plots and they are visualized in here like right after the code cell and
then there's also the final result here outputted so oh well it's quite close to
the actual pi value.
Yeah, and the big picture here,
like don't worry if all the steps are not clear.
This is, it's a certain approximate way
to compute the number pi.
Here, the big picture, what is really important
for all of us is that we have documentation and code
and images in a notebook and the computation,
it's a series of computations.
So something that we will try later is,
what if we run them in the wrong order?
And what does it mean for us?
What does it mean for our like good practices
of how we should use notebooks?
Yes, and an example of this documentation in between,
I could add here, for example,
a subtitle that start plotting,
I'll start and more explanations, of course, if I have any.
So going onward from the lesson material, it mentions that there's possibility to use
other languages.
So there's R Markdown for R and Pluto for Julia.
So the workflow there is similar to the JupyterLab.
So we hope that even if you want to use R,
you still get the idea of this workflow from this lesson.
Did we show how to run things in the wrong order?
I was just a little bit distracted
here answering questions.
Right.
So what I... I can do it now. So what I do is, let's say I want to start over the whole
calculation. Now the values of all the variables and everything, the code has run,
the variables are there. So what I do first, I want to demonstrate what if I want to start over.
I go here and restart the kernel and it says that all variables will be lost
which is okay because I want to start over and now I will go and run the
cells one by one with this shift enter but let's say let's say I forget this
one I grab a cup of coffee and I forget this cell and I continue running from
here now I get some error message and what should I get from this error
message yeah now the notebook doesn't know the variable points has never been
defined it doesn't know what the value is because we never ran the cell so two
two cells up, three cells up.
We sort of sell them before.
All right.
What's next?
Actually now, just a new question.
Is there a search function in here?
What if I don't find this name points in anywhere?
Can I do some searching?
I normally, so maybe there's a clever way.
What I do is I use the browser search.
Yeah, okay.
for these kinds of situations.
Actually, now that I press command F,
it actually opens the search inside here.
So maybe there is, let's see, points.
Okay.
Now I can see that this matches to the one in error message.
So I run this one.
Now I run the erroneous cell again.
Now it works.
So if I run the cells,
So often when we develop it try things out and then improve and you develop you
often you when developing you don't run everything every single time you run the
cell until it works and you go somewhere else you try something else but
what can then happen is that we can get into a situation where you think
everything is working but then you give it to the next person or you come to it
in a week and suddenly it doesn't work anymore because what what the next
person will do the first thing that the next person will do is they will run
everything from top to bottom. And so the good practice and the good recommendation is to run
everything from top to bottom before you save it and before you share it with other people
to make sure that this is working because this is the first thing they will do.
Yeah. And in addition, I would also restart kernel and run all cells because then you might
have saved some variable value somewhere in different sections and it remembers the last
saved value. So if you restart, you kind of make sure that your code works from top to the bottom.
Yeah. Should we talk about Git or version control and notebooks?
Definitely. Before we go into the break. Yeah. Going to the next part in the lesson. Notebooks
and version control. And this is still a demo demonstration. And let me know if there's any
questions in or such questions that you should address here.
So there are tools to do version control on this Jupyter files.
Underlying format there with the Jupyter files is this JSON.
So if you only use the basic git diff tool, it may look much more complex than your original
code and then your face goes like.
So there are tools to make that easier and which one of these we have in this conda environment
here?
JupyterLab, Git and mbdime.
Checking.
Yeah.
So the mbdime we definitely have.
We have, I think you have some of the Git extensions.
I'm just verifying here.
Yeah.
We have, we have JupyterLab Git.
We have mbdime in there.
I think the GitHub web interface nowadays
can also render the Jupyter.
Yeah, and maybe this is something we can show,
but this is something you need to enable.
So there are these three steps there.
Okay, so let's first go in JupyterLab interface.
So yeah, this is what it would look like
without those tools.
This is a difference of an image that has been edited.
It's pretty horrible,
unless you like the underlying format of a PNG picture.
But going forward and using these RichDiff tools,
we can actually see how the picture was previously
and how it's in the new edited version.
So let's see if we can do it in here.
What I need to do first is to initialize the repository.
So we are in the folder that I have this Jupyter Notebook
files.
And I can create a Git repository out of that folder
without leaving this Jupyter Notebook, which is kind of cool.
So I click Initialize Repository.
So now this folder is a git repository.
It shows that there's untracked files.
So why there's four files untracked,
although I have only two files in here?
And what should I do with this?
Let's see.
And these look like the original two notebooks that I created.
And these are some checkpoint files.
So what should I do with the checkpoint files?
So the checkpoints, I think they are directories, maybe checkpoint files, but these are often
things that I ignore.
I get ignore.
I add them to my git ignore, because they are, I see them as temporary local files that
I don't want to have in my git repository.
Okay.
So I right click and ignore that file.
And it tells me that git ignore does not exist,
but actually it just creates one.
And then I can track all the files
and make my first commit.
And now this is only going to the local folder.
So, I run the JupyterLab in a local folder, I created the git repository that's again
in a local folder.
Later on, I can upload the folder in GitHub if I want to.
Now there's the first initial commit done, so there's the snapshot of these notebooks
as they are now.
Now let's change something.
Okay, let's then verify what we will see.
For instance, you can change the size of the figure.
So somewhere there is this figure set size inches,
because maybe make it larger, smaller.
I'm scrolling to the lowest cell with the, yeah.
Or change the colors or something like that.
Yeah, I would love to change the colors,
but I don't remember how it's done.
Let's start with the size.
Yeah, let's go with the size.
Now it's smaller, this one.
So basically, it still renders the output
as a regular size, but I think this went bigger
so it's actually, the actual image is smaller.
So now if I would print out or save it to a file it would be smaller in size.
Now I save and let's see.
Now the Git extension shows, yeah there's some changes.
So before I commit the changes I want to show what has been edited.
So I click this small icon that says Diff and now this is how this Git, Jupyter Git tool
shows the difference.
So here's the code that I changed, the lines and the output.
So this is the old one and here's the new one.
everything with red is the old one everything is with green is the new one and that's that's good
and this works because we use this nbdime extension which is notebook diff and merge
and which helps us to really easily see what was before what was after if we used if you
try this with a notebook or with a jupyter lab without this extension we might see a difference
in the underlying source code.
Can we, so long story short, we recommend to use this extension.
And also on GitHub, we recommend to enable that extension so that you can see nice differences.
What is your question?
Yes.
I mean, I just click the show source button and this is the horror lying in inside.
Yeah, I really prefer the nice render here.
Yeah.
Great.
And if you want to try it out on GitHub, we have done on our lesson, we have, we have some
steps on what you need to do.
So it's a, you need to go on preview features, enable this rich Jupiter preview, I forgot
the name.
So I now wait, but I'm on GitHub, and then some settings.
So on yours, yes, on your picture there, and then you go on feature preview.
Nice.
Yes. And then on the left side, there is rich Jupyter Notebook diffs. I think you have it
enabled.
Yes, I have it enabled. So this is basically the same similar looking feature exists in
GitHub, which is really nice.
And then if you go back to the lesson, we have an example. So if you click on scroll a little
bit up, up, yes, there is this sentence that will be down. So on the bottom of your screen,
You can click on that link.
It's actually a diff.
It's a comparison between two versions.
And you can all try to open it up.
If you don't have that enable extension enabled, it will look not very understandable.
But with that extension enabled, we can see what was before what came after.
Okay, great.
I guess now we are up to a break, right?
Yes, we got a couple of interesting questions, but I, I will take the questions.
Let's take them after the break.
So after the break, what we should discuss, like, what are the advantages of notebook
versus script, or script versus VS code VS code versus notebook.
So that's for after the break.
I will add here.
So info box.
So when should we be back?
Is it sharp?
Let's be precise here.
Zero one.
Okay, great.
Thank you.
And then we'll do more Jupyter.
See you soon.
See you.
Welcome
Welcome back from the break. We continue with the Jupyter notebooks and a big topic for
the last half hour or so is the sharing notebooks. But how about if you share the notebook to
someone who does not use JupyterLab but instead wants to use Visual Studio Code. And for that
I wanted to show you how it looks like.
This is the same folder that we used in the previous examples,
and there we created the Jupyter Notebooks in the JupyterLab.
Now, the same folder opened in Visual Studio Code.
I can see that here's actually
the same notebook that I created as an example there's the same plots and
everything showing up oh this is smaller because we created it smaller so they
open up just nicely did you have to install anything other than VS code I'm
gonna check my extensions. So yes, there is a Jupyter extension installed in, but it's,
you can find it in the Visual Studio code and extensions and search for Jupyter. Yeah.
And you personally, if you like write a notebook, do you write it in VS code or do you write
it in a browser? I really like the JupyterLab interface and the looks. I don't know why,
but I prefer this one. How about you? Yeah, me too. I use the browser for notebooks. Yeah.
I use Visual Studio Code for a bunch of other stuff, but yeah, both work, which is nice.
So then to the sharing of the notebooks, there's many different ways to share and actually
too many.
Which one of these you have actually used?
I mean, they obviously both are all useful, but which one you have used?
So one, one thing that I'm even sure we listed this one step is to put it on places like
GitHub.
Yeah, so there's one way one way to share it and somebody else can view it there.
It's static because it will it actually you can only see the image of it, you cannot go
in and change it.
But we will also show you a way where you can share it in a way that people can really
run it and change it.
So which one I've used GitHub, I have used binder. I have also experimented a little
bit with Jupyter light. I have not tried the other ones. Yeah, I think further further
down we have also some alternatives that are there are some companies behind it. So I have
Yes, I've tried to co-calc. Sorry, no, the, is that the one? No, I'm, what I meant is
the Google collab. Yeah. I have tried. Yeah, some of those. Yeah. And well, if static is
enough for you, then in JupyterLab, there's this file menu and there's this export options,
options but some of these might need some extra installation so just so that you know but this
is of course the probably the easiest way to just share the file but let's go with the
use case where the people that you want to share the file with want to also
So experiment on your notebook.
So this is a demo about that.
And the use cases you want, you want people to be able to run it without even installing
any software environment or Jupyter or JupyterLab or anything.
All they will need is a browser.
Okay.
So it says that I should create a new GitHub repository.
So let's do that.
I'm going to GitHub and this is a Jupyter Binder demo, and I will, what I will do is
I will then, once you create it, I will share the link with everybody else so that people
you can see what we did there.
So do you want to link to this repository?
Yes, but I will add it to the document.
So it's public, just a second, I need to find it.
It is this one.
So the next step for me is to add a new file.
It took me some time to find this button because now it's zoomed in so much that it's in here
but it's next to this code button, create new file.
I want to upload a new file right yep because I yes I have the notebook that I
just created in the previous example and commit message yes we always have to
write something here it's a difficult to come up with useful ones though don't
worry we are totally not judging the commit message. Yeah and committing
directly to the main branch because I know that there's can't be no one else
doing any editing yet because this is so new thing so new repository I mean. Okay
now it's there with the readme nice what would be the next step?
Next step, I need to also navigate to the right place.
There's this requirements.txt, right?
Yeah, that's a nice connection to yesterday.
This is a file.
So we need to describe the software environment that we need.
It can be either a requirements.txt file.
It can also be an environment.yaml file.
Both were mentioned yesterday in the reproducibility lesson.
And here we can list what are the libraries that we need.
And in this case, we will need the matplotlib,
which is a Python library used for plotting.
And we-
So if, how do I know that which libraries,
which things I need to list in the requirements txt?
Well, that's a good question.
If sometimes it's a bit trial and error.
So it depends a bit how you installed the dependencies
that you use in the notebook.
I like to, personally, when I install dependencies, I put them into a file like requirements.txt.
And then I install from the file, because then I don't have to remember it, I can look
into the file.
But if you don't have the file, and maybe you installed this half a year ago, and you
don't remember anymore, then I go into my notebook, and I see, I look at all the imports.
And now, yeah, this is at least a starting point here.
Yeah.
And with with some Python knowledge, you would know that random is actually not.
It's a standard library, it's part of Python.
And but botlib is an external library.
But this is now about this Python knowledge.
Right, so we don't need to take this random now, but we have to take sorry, I'm navigating
back to the GitHub, we have to mention matplotlib and the version.
If we don't, if we leave out the version, we will get the latest one, okay, which will
still work today.
But the question is, will the notebook then still run in five years.
So depending on what your use case is, you might want to put the version there or not.
If we forget to put something into the requirements of text, we will notice it.
Because this is now this will run as an isolated thing.
And if there are dependencies missing, we will notice.
So sometimes I do like I add something, I run it, something missing, okay, I add something
more until it works.
Yeah.
So the next step shown in the lesson material is to go to my binder.org.
And this is just a web page, right?
How does this help our cause?
Here it will help that once we have the repository, there is this GitHub field where you can put
a GitHub repository address.
And if people want to try it out later, you can notice that it doesn't have to be GitHub.
The notebook can be on other places.
Let's see.
GitLab or it can be on Zenodo or some other places where you can deposit a notebook and
even get a digital object identifier for a notebook.
So that would be even better than putting it only on GitHub.
But here we want to show how to do it when your notebook is on GitHub.
So you take the address.
So can I just use the URL the URL from the URL field
without the tree without the main yeah like this so that will hopefully work
notice that on the left side it says head it will take the
it will actually take the main sorry the main branch the default branch you could point
it to another branch or attack if you have that.
Yeah. Do I need this path to notebook file? And it says optional. So I guess no.
And you don't even have to launch it. You can. What we can do is there is this one.
What you can do is just below the line below there is the launch partner batch and right
of it is the little arrow, click on that little arrow. And now there is a markdown version
and RSD version. What you can do is you can copy that markdown badge. Yeah, because that
will form a nice link to documentation lesson and let's put it into our readme. Okay, so
I copy this one and go to my repository and to the readme file. And I want to edit it
it now. And maybe you can zoom in a little bit. Let me see. Yeah. So I copy pasted this
markdown tag in here. So it's an address to a web server and this web server, which is
which will be running on my binder.org.
It will be generated on the fly.
On the fly, it will create, hopefully, let's see.
It will create a container for us.
It will install the dependencies into it,
the dependencies which we have described
in requirements.txt.
And in this container, it will run the notebook, hopefully.
Yeah, so now I have this party started.
And now it's a cool looking tag in my readme and it didn't cost anything.
So I click the tag and now it took me here.
So it's loading up and while it's loading up it's showing me this static version of
files. Can I actually click here? Okay, click on it, but it only gives you a static preview
because now, yeah, now it's installing the dependencies and why it's installing. If we
are impatient, it will, it at least wants to give us like the preview of how it will
look. Yeah, it's nice to see at least like, is this what I'm looking for? I mean, if I
realize here that no this is not that this is not the droids we are looking for no the
tributor lab that we are looking for then maybe I go away but now I see that this is
exactly what I want to see so I shall be waiting for the actual binder container to start yeah
and it's the first time we do that it can take seconds minutes once it is has been set
up it's faster to to run and this is normally not not a problem because this is really for
now we imagine that we are the person reading the publication and now we want to reproduce
the steps and I don't mind waiting waiting three minutes for this thing to start for
me yeah in the meantime what we can do while this is spinning up we can have a look at
the questions and discuss some of them.
Yes.
Let's open up the notes.
There are some more detailed question,
like one more bigger picture question was,
of what is the advantage of like,
when should I use a notebook?
When should I use VS code?
When should I use Python scripts?
And it one answer that we gave is that it's also a bit personal preference.
It's we show you different tools and you can choose the one that feels more comfortable
for you and for the use case.
There's a question.
Oh, yeah.
Okay.
Here's answers as well.
some funny rendering here, just comparing JupyterLab and VS Code. I think VS Code can
do about the same things. There's also the Git integration right in there, so I guess
that's all in all easier to start in VS Code. The Git is there already, I think, and you
you can add the Jupyter extension.
So maybe there's less overall installation thing,
maybe less hustling in the terminal
if you want to avoid that for some reason, like me.
So it's a question of what people prefer.
It's also a question of who do you collaborate with?
Yeah.
Is there something else?
So there are interesting questions at the bottom but I need to look it up.
So one question is that it is definitely possible that you have different environments in different
directories.
So you could imagine that if you just move out of a project and move into a different
project that it automatically switches environment.
I need to look up the details.
I know it's possible.
something called .env, .env,
but there's just one solution to this,
which will change your environment
if you go into a directory
and it will change it to something else
if you move out of it, but I need to look it up.
Yeah.
Then there is another question
which connects more to what was discussed yesterday,
like what is the best tool for managing dependencies?
I think that's hard to answer
because there are so many tools.
Maybe the two most popular ones are Conda or virtual environment, but there are really
many and, and again, it depends a bit on what you prefer, what your, what your collaborators
prefer.
Often these tools can, but the idea of isolating environments to have isolated environments
per project that's a good idea and any of these tools allow it and often you
can convert one to the other yeah like for me for example I think I've used
conda and virtual and but more more in the way that if I have instructions I
I know how to launch the virtual environment
and then I can navigate myself around the code
or run the code.
So to all those people who might be wondering
that, oh, this is all too much,
start, if you have the collaboration case,
so there's someone who created the environment,
start from trying to run the code
and launch the virtual environment and run the code,
that's already enables you to start the collaboration there.
So don't worry, although it might feel overwhelming
discussing all those different virtual environments
and tools for that.
Okay.
So in the context of Binder, it's often a requirements.txt or environment.yaml.
How are we doing there?
Is it still in the process of?
So if you, if you go to that link again from your readme, does it resolve?
I think I've lost my...
Did we not commit it?
Because I can also, you have committed it, what people can do, I can also start it on
my side.
No, I mean, I just lost my tabs.
Yeah.
But lucky you put this in in there.
Oh, yeah.
So you can start it from there.
And I started it on my side, people can try to but let's not, let's see whether it's overwhelms
binder.
So on my on my computer, it started up.
So it will also soon do it on yours here is now we see the planets orbiting.
So the moons are orbiting Jupiter and there it is.
So this is now not running on Matias computer.
It's on somewhere in the cloud accessible through the browser, you can try to visit
it too.
And you can try to run the notebook that we just created.
And you can even go in and change it.
So what if I change it? Does it save and where?
No it's so if you change it and then leave it at some point this this container will vaporize.
So I can basically I can mess up everything here in this environment if I want to and
so you can original is there. Yeah.
If you wanted to change it and keep the changes you would have to save them so you can you
you can take the notebook and save it onto your computer. So that will be the way to
preserve them. But here we can all experiment. I mean, go in and try to modify some numbers,
try to run it. And we have a we have a dynamic notebook. And if we know we could go one step
further and get a do I for it, and which we will not do but but then we are sure that
this thing will be available the next 10 years.
And if we are careful about dependencies
and about documenting dependencies with versions,
we can be reasonably sure
that this thing will still run in 10 years.
Pretty cool.
Right, so I made some edits. I wanted to see how close this statistic result was, so I
compared that result to the actual Pi provided by NumPy library and well it's in two decimals.
Quite okay.
Yeah, this is very cool. Binder is a wonderful service. It is non-profit. There are different
services that do similar things some of them are non-profit some of them are
for-profit here we wanted to show you a really nice service that is there's a
lot of good for community and is a non-profit one yeah there are some
optional exercises about tracking the dependencies which we also discussed a
a little bit what to put in the requirements and TXT
and how to find them.
And then there's an optional exercise
about sharing an interactive notebook.
So what does the interactive mean in this case?
This means, and it will connect to somebody ask a question
of how can you have interactive images?
I mean, interactive graphics in a notebook.
And this is one way of doing that or doing it.
So you can have a slider for instance,
that you can slide from left to right
and then you can make it change values
and then you can define it
so that images automatically adapt to it.
There are many ways to implement this,
but here we show you one.
Yeah, so I really encourage you to go to see the,
like optional exercises that there's a quite a lot of nice material also some
new things for me also I guess one that I actually would like to advertise here
now is this shell commands magic and widgets so there are some extra features
in Jupyter, you can ask it for help about some object, so if you don't know what this
np.sum() does, you can add a question mark there and apparently it will tell you.
Scrolling a little bit down, you can run shell or terminal commands in Jupyter by adding
this exclamation mark. That can be really nice for example in a case that you want to
know in which folder you are in. Now this is probably going to look curious because
it's in the binder container, but anyhow.
And then, oh, there's some magic.
I think I have never tried this.
And then the widgets that we mentioned that you can add more interactive elements in the
JupyterLab. Yeah, do we go to the summary?
Let's do that. And also, a reminder to everybody else, on the bottom of the notes, I have pasted
requests for feedback. Please let us know how today went. There are also some questions
that we can discuss in voice, but I don't know if you wanted to share some summary slide
or say a few words, [name].
Yeah, in the lesson material,
there's this nice summary, more links
and blog posts and articles.
And then also, again, mentioned these other tools
for other languages than Python.
And like a reminder on the thing
that we already also mentioned
that when you start with the JupyterLab or Jupyter notebook,
you start experimenting and develop more and more.
At some point you have a really long notebook,
but then it starts to grow.
So the one good practice was to,
every time before you save and share,
restart kernel, run all cells
to see that your notebook actually runs in order and there's no errors and then
also try to organize it and use the subtitles or headlines headings to keep
the notebook in order so that it's easy also for you after one year to
get back to it.
Yeah.
You mentioned some questions.
Is there still something that you would like to raise?
So we can, that was commented.
Tomorrow we will connect to this.
We will, when we discuss modular code development,
we will actually tomorrow start in a notebook
and we will then experience a moment
when maybe it feels like, you know, uncomfortable
and it feels like we want to move out of notebook.
So we will see that, we will see a situation
and the situation will be once we start adding tests,
that, so we will start in notebook
and maybe move out into scripts.
We will also tomorrow talk about automated testing.
So two really exciting lessons coming up.
We hope to see you all tomorrow again.
And thanks a lot for giving feedback below.
Tell us one thing that you liked about today.
Tell us also one thing that we should change or remove.
Yeah, I think we've been changing at least something in in every time we have this workshop,
right?
Yes, because this the topics they are evolving, so we need to evolve with them.
And this is this goes more about the content but it also goes it's also about the forum
and how we present it.
Yeah.
So thank you for this lesson.
Thank you for following and thank you for the feedback.
Keep it coming.
And thank you for having me here.
Yeah.
Thanks, [name].
Always pleasure.
of music. Sure.