So, as usual, we have some icebreakers here, some interesting questions to think about.
And today we've got, how would you explain your current job to someone from the year
1700, which is something I saw on some sort of social media in the last few days.
So I guess if many of us do computer things, this will be hard, but let's see how well
we can abstract ourselves back down.
is what's the best documented project you've seen? And do you prefer reading short social
media posts or long blog posts? So, of the people here, how would you explain what you
do to someone from...
I mean, I like the first one, actually.
Yeah. I mean, that's what I wrote, so...
Oh, okay.
Yeah.
Some would guess that that was one of us in some way.
I mean, it's at least clear it's a research software engineer or, yeah, a support person.
I mean, I guess that is sort of general.
Like, there's complicated machines or other tools.
People need to use them, but aren't the specialist in there.
And people exist to help with that.
I think one of the problems that I see was explaining it to someone from the 1700s.
I see my work at least very much as helping people to allow them to keep their specialization
and not, well, having to worry about anything else or having to worry about nitty-gritty
things.
While in the 1700s I think there was not that much really specialization in science at least.
I mean not necessarily in science, but in 1700s we are already in the industrial revolution, right?
Yeah, I mean very, very, very beginning.
Yeah, I mean the first industrial revolution is sort of going on or done, the second hasn't started.
So you have people whose job it is to operate a big machine like a windmill or a certain part of a boat, I think.
Yeah.
At least mills.
It's like applied research and science and so on.
Or, you know, something like that.
What do you think the, well, the second job, reading letters and writing letters,
is that a scientist making journal articles? Maybe? Maybe.
That's what a scholar does. Yeah. Organizing assemblies of
people to discuss that conference organizer or something.
email and chat. So, okay, so it could be any job, but you're so busy writing emails that
you can't do your main job, which is a lot of manager, I guess. I guess that's also partly
me. Mathematically rephrasing what people have already invented in 1700. What is that
job. Could it be some sort of programmer or other researcher that's using math that's
already been known then but doing it faster in computers now?
A lot of math, actual math research is rephrasing, I can't speak right now, rephrasing stuff
that people have already invented, but making it easier to use and clearer.
And, well, even making it usable, because there was just not the computational power
before now. There's quite a lot of stuff that, well, in theory would work, it just
took too long, and now computers are fast enough to, yep, now you can actually do this.
So if you're just joining now, we have an interesting icebreaker there.
If you registered, you should have the notes link, and well, you can read the questions
as well as I can read them, so let's play this game.
But so today, well, [name] will have some interlater.
How do you think the workshop's going overall, everyone here?
Have you all been happy?
I think it has been going well, like the week one redesign was very successful, like looking
at the questions that we got, more into towards how researchers actually encounter version
control and GitHub on their journey.
And week two, I'm still a bit unsure about the no exercise sessions
because they have always been very nice.
And I've gotten people into looking at these things themselves
and trying to figure them out versus us showing it on stream.
It probably depends a lot on how people learn best.
Yeah.
What is more beneficial?
Very true.
What do you think?
This is definitely helping us cover more ground and not feel as busy and not feel like we're
always running out of time.
I do hope that this also moves more to the direction where we can then support people
after the workshop and make this more of a mentor thing.
I suppose that means people joining our Zulip chat and asking questions there when they have questions.
Because, of course, during the workshop, we have the collaborative document, the notes, which we will not be actively checking after the workshop.
Yeah.
I mean, yeah, my ideal would be for the second week, imagine if we could do the workshop like
we've been doing now, but then in the afternoons we could arrange some sort of like, well, like
the bring your own code sessions, which we actually have for Code Refinery, but we should be doing as
part of our own individual or institutions also. We could tell people, okay, next week come to
our garage with any of the questions from Code Refinery about how to do it and we'll help you
set it up and or you know help you do the exercises test it out whatever it may be
and that would be good but it's almost time to get going um if you're joining now please write your
job. So you can see the icebreakers here. How would you explain your job to someone from year 1700?
And if you can't figure it out, write down what you do and we'll work together.
So I propose some sort of workshop for other teachers or people that run workshops
that will discuss how we do this very kind of streaming workshop. So basically, I would help
train people, train other people to do it. If this is interesting to you, look at the most recent
Code Refinery blog post and see what it says. We can announce that at the end. I guess it is time.
So, [name], I think you have an intro for us. Yes. Do you want to play the jingle, the short
one. So, welcome! [name], I believe you have our first intro. Yes, are you sharing
my screen to the stream? There you go. Okay, very welcome to day five of this Code Refinery
workshop. We're almost at the end already. Very sad about that. Soon it's over. But we still have
two days ahead of us. So week one of this workshop was all about version control from really the
basics of Git to collaborative use using GitHub. And then yesterday we started week two with an
overview around the reproducible research. We discussed how to record computational steps with
SnakeMake as an example tool, dependencies with Konda as an example tool and environments
with containers. And in the afternoon we then took a peek into the FAIR research software
development practices, licenses and what you need to know about these kind of things.
related to your research code. So today we're going to look into different ways of documenting
your research software, meaning from comments to readme files that we now have been looking
a little bit at already, and then to actually doing really nicely rendered web pages similar to
the Code Refinery materials pages and how you can do that like with a few small commands yourself.
And then in the afternoon we will take a look into the world of Jupyter notebooks and that you maybe
have already come in contact with during computing classes or while like working by yourself.
And here we're going to focus on things that can make your research also more reproducible
using Jupyter, for example.
So even if you know it already, I think there will still be something new in that lesson
as well.
And then for newcomers today, this workshop is fully live streamed.
So you will all watch the sessions via Twitch.
And if you know the workshop from before this year,
we don't have any dedicated team exercises in this second week.
But we have a lot of time for interaction
with our collaborative document, which
I will be showing in a moment.
And then we plan to have a minimum of 10 minute
breaks every hour plus a one-hour break over, well, in Finland,
midday lunchtime.
So our collaborative document, you should have,
or you have gotten the link after you
registered to this workshop.
It looks something like this.
And depending on how wide and how zoomed in you have this,
you will find a little pen symbol up top.
me it's now up here to the right for you it might be somewhere here up to the left where you can
switch to the edit mode if you want to add something here. Here we have all the links
also to this welcome session and then to the materials and the archive of previous questions
and let's switch to edit mode for a moment then we can scroll down we have our icebreaker question
here. Today we have three questions that you can answer. How would you explain your current job to
someone in the year 1700? Quite tricky one. For me I think the first one fits best. We have really
big complicated machines and I help people use them. So I try to help people use supercomputers
and maybe I can add a plus one here or a little dot. What's the best documented
project you have seen? Since we're going to talk about documentation we can pick
up on that later. For me I think it's also the scikit-learn documentation that
is really really great if you haven't seen it. Take a look and do you prefer
reading short social media posts or long blogs. And this is now a voting system, so like I added
my little O here, I basically added that me too. And here I also prefer
maybe often more longer blogs and also in the code, well more often the longer source code to
have everything at once. And then if you go down here, then here you can actually edit your
questions that you have about the upcoming session. So you can see some people already wrote some
here, so you can always ask that during the workshop and instructors will pick it up.
workshop. All the materials are linked from the workshop page and you can like come back
to it and look at them and you can also reuse them if you want to for your own workshops.
And we also record this whole workshop. So for some days the recordings will still be
available on Twitch and then after that you can find them on YouTube. There's usually
playlist and then you can look through the lessons and to jump to the lessons that you're interested
in. If you need a certificate for this course for university you can find instructions for that on
our web page and as mentioned before this session already we have this bring your own code session
so if there was a tool during this workshop that you would like to start using in your own work
You can come to these sessions and can take a look at these things with our experts or if you have a question related to tools like SnickMake or whatever.
They will happen next weekend, the week after Tuesday.
And now I will give over to [name] and [name] for the documentation lesson.
The floor is yours.
Thanks. I will take over the screen share.