We'd like to get feedback for today.
So we do have a little bit more, so don't leave yet.
We have an outro session.
And also, we plan on talking.
There are some requests to talk a little bit about AI code
generation and things like that.
that. Should we talk about the AI code stuff first? So what are the specific
questions? Maybe we can add a section? Yeah.
Let's see, what do people think here?
What should we talk about, if anything?
So who uses AI to make code?
I must say that I do not right now.
I have now started using it all the time, since my employer is providing the license,
and then why not?
So yeah, GitHub Copilot.
So how does it work?
It essentially makes suggestions based on the code you have right now.
There is a chat interface as well, so you can ask it to write some code that does X.
But the interface that works better actually is usually the code completions.
It's mainly like there's always been this code completion systems that try to guess
the kind of code you would want to add and allow you to, for example, write in languages
that have more boilerplate code, create a class, like write all the boilerplate code
for a class with a couple of, typing a couple of keystrokes, and Copilot is doing a lot
of that for me. I see. It's like all the standard ARC parse stuff that I'd always be making. Yeah.
Yeah. Okay. But it goes a little bit beyond, but it cannot do anything
really new or really complicated. So it's just this basic, relatively basic things.
It will usually have a suggestion for even more complicated things, but it's more often than not
not that you just have to go and change a lot of things. It's only the basic structure
that's correct. But it's still doing a lot of work, though. I don't know, how would
I evaluate? How much time is it saving? 50% or a bit more of actual coding time?
Yeah. What's the license of the generated code?
For Copilot it's essentially they just give you the copyright as long as you know
as the usual warning is it might in some I think relatively rare cases output code that is an exact
copy of something that already is out there. In fact, it will do that very often if you
take something really simple, but that's just like you would type it out by hand in exactly
the same way anyway. So that code is very structured. So there's a lot of exact copies
out there. But yeah, I mean, at some point when it gets complicated enough, you have to
You have to know yourself that it's not a copy of something.
And that's a big caveat.
But yeah, otherwise, usually they just give you the copyright,
because otherwise the service model wouldn't really make a lot of sense.
So, I heard that we should do the outro before this discussion, too, before people leave.
So, okay, mix that up.
So, [name], would you like to grab the screen and summarize everything for us and tell us what we should do next?
Yes, hello.
Okay.
Hello, hello. Can you hear me all right?
Yes.
and can you see my screen? Yes I can see it's now also on the stream. Okay thank
you very much [name] and [name] for this very interesting session. So this was now
the very last session of our workshop but it's not the very last thing
that you can join for this course. So stay with me for a moment to tell you
more about that. So this was the Code Refinery workshop for this spring. We would like to
thank you, the participants, very much for participating, putting so many questions and
so good feedback after each day in our collaborative document and discussing the questions and like
being very active there. We'd also like to thank our team leaders and hosts that have
made this possible to spread to even more people and provide more personal support to some of our
participants here. Then also a very big thank you to all of our instructors of this workshop. It was
a quite big group this time. I think it went all in all very well. Then we also had some
Some people working in the background that have so far never appeared on stream that
were answering the questions in the collaborative document in addition to the instructors.
And then we also had some local partners that hosted the rooms there and answered questions.
So you all make these workshops possible and so enjoyable.
Thank you very much.
[name] and [name] have already told you about the feedback section, so if you go to the
collaborative document and in the very bottom we have our feedback, a little bit about today
and then you can also let us know what you thought overall about this workshop, no matter
if you joined all the days or just a few of them, like let us know how you like this workshop,
you like this format, things that we can do better, things that you really much like
that we should not get rid of, and all these kind of things.
And if you come up with something later, you can also send us an email to support.coderefinery.org.
Or you can also, and you are all very welcome to, also without feedback, join our chat.
It's on Zulip.
So you can find this behind the link.
Actually, is this document linked from the collaborative document?
If not, I would like to ask one of my colleagues here to link that so that you can click those
links also.
Then if you have struggled with some of the exercise instructions or found some broken
links or have some update suggestions for our lesson material, now during the first
week of this course, you have learned how to do issues, pull requests, so you can practice
that on our lesson material and we are very happy to get also like feedback that way and we are
always at least trying to develop this workshop materials further latest before the next workshop
so we are really relying on your feedback here and also we will take a look at the
questions that you ask and see if we can improve the material to make these things more clear.
At some point in the future you will likely receive a post-workshop survey that is then about how your work in the long run has been affected by visiting this workshop.
So we know that there is like a lot of topics here and it's a lot of things to take in at such a short time.
But maybe after like a few weeks, you may get back to some of the topics and you may get an understanding to where these topics can help you in your work.
So that's why it will take some time before you will get this workshop, but it will come.
And if you get it, then please answer it. That helps us a lot to continue the work that we are doing.
Yeah, because it has been a lot of material, a lot of possibly new concepts for you.
This is just a starting point and there is so much more to learn and dig into.
You may have noticed in this week too that we tried to show some of the exercises on
stream, but there were also in many lessons, many more exercises that we did not go through.
So you can go back to the material, look through them, try to do them yourself.
And if you do that within the next two weeks and you have some trouble with this, you can
also come to our bring your own code sessions.
And this is also if you have some more questions like we had this morning, for example, for
the automated testing, many people were asking something about like how to do this, how to
apply this to your own code.
If you have questions like this, then this bring your own code sessions are a very good
place to come.
Many of our instructors will be there, and we will try to help you further with the topics
discussed in this workshop.
So it's the next Tuesdays, 1, 2, 3, and the link will be sent to all registered participants.
As mentioned many times already, our materials are publicly available.
are all open source and will continue to be updated. You can also reuse them for your
own workshops and this link leads you to the main overview of all the lessons. So there's not just
the lessons that we went through here in this workshop, but there's also a few more there.
So you can go and take a look. The videos will stay on YouTube, you can always like re-watch
them. They also have these little nice section tags that you can jump around to the topics that
are of interest to you. And then we have a lot of local partners that provide support
with the topics around this workshop. And you can find the list of the partners here
for Finland, Sweden, Norway and Denmark. Many also with their link to the training calendar
where there is like further training going more into high performance computing or
I don't know what we other have, scientific computing with Python and these kind of things.
So you can check them out and some of them are also not necessarily only for the group for example
at Aalto University in Finland, but some of these trainings are also open for all.
So even if you are not in these areas, I would recommend to check out the training calendars of
these institutions. And then again, a reminder about the certificates. If you want one,
check out the course web page, you can do that briefly. Up top you can find this tab to
certificates, if you click that there's instructions on what you can do to get a certificate for this
course. And then how you can support us, so we are a project and it always helps to like tell
everyone about us, tell your friends if you like this course, tell them about our materials,
our webpage, use our social media handles. We have been trying to post a little bit about this
workshop too, so use those to re-share your experience about it. We are also eagerly reading
these posts, so please make use of that. And we will probably have more workshops of this type
further developed in some way, so you can always come back as a team leader, for example,
so you can bring your colleagues, sit together in a room and watch the stream together and then do
the exercises together, for example, like some of you have already done. And then you can also
become part of the Code Refinery team. In general, the project lives currently still from
in-kind contributions by the organizations, meaning that our organizations sponsor our time
for the project. So if that is something that sounds interesting to you and especially your
organization, please get in touch. As mentioned, we live in the chat, so that's where really
everything goes, where we also have a nice help channel where you can add your questions that you
have for example surrounding this workshop or also later when you implement these things you can
go and ask for help there's a lot of so-called research software engineers especially around that
really enjoy helping people with their computational research challenges and then we also have a
newsletter about once or twice a year where we update about upcoming workshops or this we recently
switched our newsletter provider, so let's hope this goes well. You can find the link
on our webpage behind the newsletter. And then I mentioned already this research software
engineers, so many of our instructors are actually research software engineers and we
also have an association, the Nordic Research Software Engineers, where you can find the
link behind this one here. I think it's just nordic-rse.org. Let's see. And so the research
software engineers, they are like these people that are between the researchers and the software
developers that combine this experience of both of these worlds. And basically, the code refinery
workshop could be also called like a introduction to research software engineering. So if you liked
what you learned here and would like to go further in that, then the Nordic RSE community is a very
nice place to be in. Basically we live also in the same chat as Code Refinery
in the Nordic RSE channel. We sometimes have some like seminar series and upcoming now also
So a conference in Espoo in Finland in the end of May that you can still submit contributions
to that you can still come and join us for.
And we are also on Twitter X, sorry.
And that was it with the wrap up.
Do my fellow colleagues here on call still have to add something to this?
other upcoming courses do we have? Someone commented on that in the feedback.
Yes, I guess the next one that is by some of the code refinery community is the
tools and techniques, Tuesday's tools and techniques for HPC, but we don't have a
event page for that yet. It will come up in April and you can probably find these
information soon on the Aalto training page, I would guess.
So, the other courses of the similar form, in the beginning of June, we have a live stream
kickstart course, mainly hosted by Aalto University, but each year some others join.
And it's about scaling your work from your local things to a computer cluster.
And, ah, okay, I'm under attack.
So okay, well at least you get some entertainment
Yeah, and then in the autumn, we have a yearly Python for Scientific Computing course,
which is quite similar to what we're doing here. And who knows, maybe more in the future.
Through Code Refinery, sometimes we advertise other courses by partners,
which should be of similar quality.
Should we go back to the notes? Yes. What other? So one of the biggest changes we've had is we
made the second week more demo-based rather than exercise-based, and we'd like your comments on
that. So part of the reason was that we didn't have as many exercises the second week anyway,
So when people came prepared for exercises, then there were not enough
and helpers, the people who were prepared to help with the exercises, didn't have
enough to do. So, yeah.
Yeah.
Any other comments?
Do any other instructors want to join here and give general questions and answers?
Yeah. Should we? Oh, [name] is here. Do you have any thoughts on AI coding?
Yeah, first of all, thanks for today. I was watching it and I was typing. Really enjoyed
the many questions. I had to really type a lot. It was really cool today. Yeah, I mean,
AI coding exists, it's an important tool.
Do you use AI coding much?
Yes, I do.
Okay.
I do, so AI-assisted coding.
Sometimes I write comments and then it tries to code,
or I write a code and it tries the comments for me,
or I ask it to write a test,
or I write the test first and ask it to write the code
that matches the test.
It saves a lot of time.
There were a few questions and points about translating.
And that's kind of one way of thinking about what these AI models are really good at.
It's essentially, well, I guess there's two big things.
And one is translating from one format to another.
So that would include also taking a code
and writing tests for it,
or taking a test and writing code that fulfills that test.
And like sort of trying to go from one type
of information to another,
or just going from one language to another.
Yeah, and that works really well.
So I, for instance, I'm now learning R.
So I'm a beginner in R.
So what I've tried a few times
is that I have a Python code and I ask it to translate it
to R and then I have a really good starting point.
So it can help me actually learn the language.
I can see like, okay, this is something that works
and I can study it and I can improve it
and maybe it's not perfect,
but I believe that it can also help beginners
to get started and learn coding.
So the other big thing that it's really good at
is just remembering stuff.
So it's like, in principle, Google also is useful
for finding any, or any web search is good
for finding all of the same information
but this is more integrated to the actual coding workflow.
So it can not just find the documentation for some library
but actually suggest how to use it in your code.
Although the information does tend to be old pretty quickly.
So you have to take that into account.
Yeah.
So from the whole workshop, what are your main takeaway messages that you'd like people
to carry with them.
Anyone? Version control is super useful. It makes everything possible. Yeah.
Everything runs on top of version control and publishing your code as early as possible
is relatively, it's easy and it enables a lot of useful things.
What do you mean by publishing as soon as possible?
You mean putting on, like making it available by GitHub or similar?
Yeah, or at least putting it online somewhere, and preferably with a license.
Yeah, because GitHub and many of these platforms, they provide free stuff to public projects, usually.
So the sooner you go public, the sooner you can start using these.
Okay, does anyone else have any other comments in the notes?
Or should we wrap it up?
I see a question from earlier, where to find more resources and examples on modular development
in testing for research?
What would you say there?
It's a great question.
I'm not sure there is this like one resource for it.
Yeah.
I would study.
Have a look at the code that you are using.
And how do they do testing?
How do they structure their code?
But it can be a little bit too big.
So maybe look at the smaller projects.
Have a look at other projects, how they do it.
I'm not aware of one book that will discuss this in one place.
Are you aware of any other things that cover these topics specifically for research in
this much or more detail?
Did most researchers sort of figure this out themselves, or how does it go?
I mean, I really don't know.
I learned this sort of by following other projects and having to figure it out myself.
So that's why I like this course so much, because it can save other people that effort.
I have a feeling that still a lot of it is figuring it out yourself, but at least you
see the vision and, well, if our audience is researchers, then you're good at figuring
out new things.
So as long as you know what to look for, you can find and adapt.
There are a couple of papers that are nice, which is this Ten Simple Rules to etc. etc.
Ten Simple Rules to Make Your Code More.
Oh, they are nice.
They are good summaries.
Yeah.
And I guess it would be nice if we made a collection and listed all of them.
There's a link to a book called The Turing Way, which I know about.
it cover the details of coding? I see chapters on code testing, code review, and so on. So
I guess that would be a good thing to look at that goes into some good depth.
Yeah, okay, should we call it good then?
We're almost at the hour now.
So thanks to everyone who attended.
Yeah, I can just say we will send an email to everybody with some summary. We don't forget
that in a week. So next Tuesday, the Tuesday after, you can show up at the sessions, bring
your code, bring your questions, it will be on zoom, it will not be recorded, not streamed.
We will email you the connection details. And I hope people show up and that we can
and show up with questions.
Yes.
Okay.
Well.
Should I hang it up then?
Thanks a lot and good luck in your future research.
Thanks everybody.
See you soon.
Thank you.
Bye.