Okay, I will take over the screen share.
I'm also showing the same document. Okay.
Okay, here we go.
Okay, good. And does that look correct? It does.
Yes. Good. Okay, so let's get back. So we already
talked a bit with the icebreakers and people can read those but yeah so where do we start so we
are first lesson is automated testing yeah so um yeah let's get down to it so um or first uh
before you learned automated testing. Can we share the lesson? Yes, we can. So,
the link is in the notes and also in the schedule, and here we go.
Yeah, and I guess this title show is exactly what our icebreakers were asking,
preventing yourself and others from breaking functional code.
So, yeah, so what's the way you do this, like, without automated testing?
What were you doing before you learned and what are people probably doing before learning
about this?
Yeah.
Can we go to motivation, maybe?
I guess.
The first motivation lesson has some...
So yeah, and this first point, if you've ever been an experimental scientist, you probably
know that calibrating your instruments is an important thing you do.
So you have to get there, and anytime you have some microscope or measurement thing,
You run it with a known sample to see if it gives the value you expect.
And we see a quote here that says the same thing should apply to software.
If you haven't done some sort of test to see if it works, then are you really doing science
Or are you just making some hopes or whatever?
So this would be something like checking
that you can reproduce known results.
And essentially, every time you change something,
move the thing around, or just come
into the lab in the morning doing some basic checks
that everything is OK.
So let's give an example, if we scroll down.
So when you're programming, you might have some function.
So here, can the font be made a little bit larger?
Yes.
Okay, that's hopefully good, yeah.
So what do we see here?
Yeah.
So this is Python, there's other examples here, but yeah.
that converts from fahrenheit to celsius which is pretty easy yeah and we can look at it and we
think it works but how would you actually test it in real life like if you're making this function
and you didn't know automatic testing yeah would you so i guess i would run it with some number i
know the result for. I would run it with temperature in Fahrenheit being zero, because I know it
should return 32. Not exactly, because that's the wrong way around. I would give it 32 and
then expect zero, I guess.
Yeah. So you give it the known obvious values.
Yeah.
And since you can probably know your function is linear, if you can test two values, then
it's probably good.
this case that would be enough. But are you sure? I mean I guess it's worth
testing a few more if it's easy and also some special cases like negative
Kelvin does that give you something or null values and so on. Yeah. Integer and
floating-point inputs. But anyway so this is what we're going to see during this
lesson. And this is at the smallest most micro scale testing a single function
but you can also test much more than this. So for example down below we see a
test of a whole program. Not like that far down but just a little. Oh you mean
I mean, we don't see what it actually is, but it shows it looks like it runs with some
sample data and says this is what the output should be.
So it is telling us that it's correct, which is good.
So what else can the test help us do?
I mean, I guess in addition to telling whether it's wrong or right, it would be useful to
know where the problem is or how the test figured out that there's a problem.
Like, this just tells you that it's correct, which I guess is fine as long as it's correct.
But it would be nice to know what it checked, more nice to be reminded what was the check,
what passed.
And if it fails, where did it fail and how?
Can we scroll down a bit to see what else is in, what else it says?
So preserve functionality.
Okay, so that means if it works, it keeps working.
Help users.
So basically, actually this happens often on our computer cluster.
We install some software for a user and we wonder, did the installation work correctly?
If we, the admins, can run a test suite and it says it works, then we have some reasonable
confidence that we didn't completely break the installation.
Help other developers modify it.
What does that mean?
Well, if you're changing something, you can be confident that you didn't break anything.
It also kind of helps with documentation.
It tells you what should work and how it should behave.
Yeah, like for example, if I'm modifying someone else's code and there's tests, then I can run
those tests, and if they pass, then, like, if it's someone else's code, I usually don't
know how the whole thing works. But I might know enough to change just a little bit of
it. But I don't know how my section relates to all the other sections of the code.
So having these tests is really useful, because I can be reasonably sure that I haven't broken
something unexpected. And same for the other developer. If I say, oh, would you like this
change, then they can see if the test still works and not have to read my changes so much.
They can just look locally.
And this complexity is also a good one.
I've written some things before that are really hard to test, and eventually they become hard
to modify and maintain.
And that's just not great.
There's a good question.
Is this about testing code?
What about other things, Python?
This is a really good point.
And for example, the thing that we'll show later on,
GitHub Actions, has exact ways to do this.
You can basically install, like test installing and running
your code your package on different operating systems on different versions of the operating
system and so on yeah yeah that that's really helpful um yeah and if you want to test that
it's installed correctly in your system then hopefully you can also run the tests included
in the package. Yeah. So when's it okay to not add tests? The next section here.
Oh, we should be... I will also add this as a question to the notes. So you can ask is everything
that we do test it? And the answer is probably no. And to me it depends on how important
it is. If it's a small script that I will also always be, there will always be a human
in the loop watching it and verifying it worked, then whatever. But as soon as it gets big
enough, I'll try to have some at least sample data to show.
So often the time when it's really time to start adding tests is when you're going from
a single script or a Jupyter notebook to having some functions and having multiple files and
so on, at least for me. But of course if you have a big untested block of code in a notebook
or a script, then that's maybe not as trustworthy as it could be. And maybe that's fine.
So, what are some examples of things that are easy and hard to test in your own opinion?
Okay, let's move that also to the notes and see what people come up with.
What's hard to test is interactive things.
Something that requires a human in the loop to properly work.
Like, you can simulate a human by some predefined answers, but it's not quite the same thing.
There are also things like testing frameworks, which basically, like for web browsers and so on,
that can go and virtually click on things on a website and see if it works. But
since our audience is probably scientists and researchers, that might be getting a bit deep,
but you can bet for sure that big companies making websites and so on have these kinds of things because
Well, it's better to do it once then need a human to do it all the time
Okay, should we go
On um
There's some other advice here, but I think you'll probably see the types of tests well
You can read that yourself later, we don't really need to go.
I guess the main point there is you can test at different levels.
Like above we saw a test of a single function.
But maybe for your case it's better to get some sample data and test the whole thing.
Like an end-to-end test.
Or whatever.
Often times it's some combination.
I would try some end-to-end test, and then
test of individual functions where it's easy and the risk of breakage is high.
So, where do we start?
Yes, so let's go to the next section, but at this point I think I will move on to my empty
example folder and we can start because the next section is a demonstration.
Yes, so we are at the section testing locally.
Maybe, well, is there anything we need to show from the web browser window?
Maybe I'll show on my screen quickly.
locally. So here we are on testing locally. The link is in the notes. And we will be using
PyTest. So we'll start with some simple code, which Wiz provided to us. And we will slowly
add it to files and make some tests. And this is a really reasonable thing to do. So pytest is what,
at least my default package for testing Python code. It's really common, it's relatively easy to
use. So, yeah, it's a good start.
I actually, I cannot say that I've seen any other framework being used to test Python.
There are other frameworks and people use them, but in Python, it's essentially the only one.
I'll create a new Python file, example.py, and put some code there.
So we start with example.py.
Did you make a new directory to store this stuff?
Yes.
This should be an empty directory, but I did try running pytest to check that it exists.
So there is a pytest cache.
So we're adding example.py.
And it has, and so this is supposed to be a demo.
So you can try to follow along, but we're not giving you time and we're not going slow
enough that we think it's easy to follow.
Okay, so I have this extremely complicated mathematical function and I want to test it.
So what should I do?
So the way PyTest works is it automatically looks for functions that start with test underscore.
It also looks for modules that start with test underscore, but we don't do that yet.
So let's define a function called test add, test underscore add.
So the important thing is that it starts with test underscore, and then I guess I will write
in the function name what I'm testing, so I'm testing the add function.
Let's close the side panel.
Okay, so what does assert mean? I went a bit ahead of my house, sorry.
Assert, what does that do?
Is it self-descriptive? It might be if you speak enough English.
So assert is a Python statement which runs whatever is after it. And if it doesn't evaluate
to true, it prints an error. So PyTest uses this. It uses standard Python statements.
But if there was an assertion error, it would capture that error and then print some extra
debugging information beyond what Python would do.
So what if there's a different kind of an error?
What do you mean by different kind?
Well, I don't know. I gave some parameters that you cannot add together.
Well, I think Python would probably, or PyTest would also capture that and print it well.
Okay, so any error will, PyTest will capture any error essentially,
but assert is a nice way of producing errors when things don't work.
Okay, well let's, should we add something that evaluates to true? So if we add two and three,
that should be equal to five. No, five. Okay, what else? What else would work?
So, what else in Python should be added?
Well, there's this, we see it adds two strings together.
So, yeah, let's try that.
So, the way strings work is if you try to add with the plus operator, two words, space
and ship, and that should return space ship, so it just puts the strings together, concatenates
the strings.
Okay.
So now we have our test function, and notice the test function takes no arguments, so PyTest automatically finds it and runs it.
It has all the test data directly embedded in here, as you can see, and will print any errors it finds.
Open a terminal window.
I will need to activate the code refinery environment.
Can we split the window so we can see?
Yes.
So whoops, looking at the tests and the...
There's not a huge amount of space.
Can you split the window so it's on the bottom?
Right, that's a good idea. It should be possible. Okay.
Okay, yeah, so there's a question in the chat. What are we trying to do here?
So we have some pretend code, which is add A and B. We pretend this is our highly advanced
scientific code, and we want to demonstrate a test for it. So we run this thing called
test add. So we've made a function test add and PyTest will automatically run this for us
with some nice extra stuff. So the simplest way to run this function would be to run
PyTest and that's it. Yeah so we do PyTest. I think we need to tell it example.py.
That's true, because example.py doesn't start with test underscore.
We need to give it the file name.
But let's also add a verbose flag so that it will tell us what it's doing, give some
more information.
Okay.
So we see test session starts, whatever.
So it ran test add and said that it passed.
Yes.
It did tell us that it, yeah, it ran the test add function.
Yeah.
Okay.
So yeah, all it did is run this function and it didn't encounter any errors.
So it passed.
So if we had a hundred times more code here and 20 different test functions, we could run
them all automatically, all at once.
And yes, and in this case the testing function is doing nothing more than running the function
with some real life values.
Of course you can get more advanced, but that's essentially what testing is.
Running stuff with sample values and seeing if it comes out right.
So what happens if something's broken?
Should we do a test and see?
Okay.
Let's make a break the function.
So now it's clearly not adding.
So I will not run it from here.
I will run it from here in the terminal.
So pytest.
Okay.
Okay, so now it gives a lot more information.
Yeah, and we see a really nice error message.
It says, failures test add, def test add,
assert add two, three equals five.
It says that assert minus one equals five
or minus one equals add two comma three.
So if we had a hundred different test functions here,
we could go and know exactly which function failed
and with which arguments.
OK, so that's the basic idea.
And there was some comment in the notes
about how someone was using unit test.
And it seemed really hard and in a lot of boilerplate.
And you notice here, this is really easy.
Yeah, there's not that much boilerplate in here.
Just fixing the code to make the test pass again.
Okay.
Yeah.
These are all one-line tests.
Of course, the function is very simple, so writing one-line tests is easy, but still.
So the next part here is a test in the episode is a test that considers numerical tolerance.
So can we add as a test add 0.1 and 0.2.
So we assert something.
We want 0.1 and 0.2 equal to 0.3.
I'm actually curious if this will work or not.
No, it did not work.
So it does this work?
Yeah.
Adding 0.1 and 0.2 produces 0.300000000000004 because it's a floating point number.
So it goes in powers of 2.
Floating point numbers are never quite exact.
Yeah. So what's the solution here?
What do we do?
Yeah, good question.
I guess we could check that the difference between the result
and 0.3 is small enough.
So basically we would test with numerical tolerance somehow.
Yes.
So should we try that?
Yeah.
Like, is the difference small enough?
So we take the difference.
but now we want the absolute value of the difference because also if it's
negative that is not good but this is some number and it should be smaller
than some arbitrary number let's say
in the notes it's the power of seven is this seven so basically yeah okay does
it pass now? Now it passes. Okay, great. Let's go to the notes. We have some really good
questions there. I'll switch here locally. So towards the bottom. So yeah, so there's
lots of questions about how this works with more advanced code.
So this is simple.
So whenever I'm doing things, okay, there's the classic case.
You have some simple functions, but you're writing code not because you know the answer,
but because you don't know the answer.
So what do you do?
So several things I would do. I'd break down the big complicated code I don't know the
answer to into small pieces and make sure each individual piece is tested and correct.
So that way, known things are simple, but the complicated thing, hopefully it's correct
with the known parts.
Can you get any really simple sample data? So, for example, you make a test function
that processes millions of records from somewhere,
you give it a list of two records
and see, can it average this correctly?
So basically, in your mind,
there's all different ways you can think
and try to simplify things down to a smaller example.
And actually, after the break,
we go to a test design episode
where we'll talk about this a lot more.
So maybe save some of these questions, and let's discuss more there. There'll be lots of time.
Yeah, this is...
Yeah, so many of these test design functions, let's get to in the test design episode and not
now. Do you see a question, can you test a particular test function without running
through all the functions in the file so you can tell pytest run only this particular test
function and so on do you remember the syntax for that or is it something we should just
i think it's dash k someone should check you can look it up as easy as we can look it up yeah um
And we always have a test in the file that we're wishing to test.
Not necessarily.
You can split them into a separate file, and that's something people do often, or even
a separate folder.
Yeah, I guess for big enough projects I usually see the test in separate, yeah, separate files.
Okay, there's a mention of this benefit, this approach versus plain code that can be automated.
I'm not quite sure what that means, but I'll answer what I think it means.
So what do I think it means?
So you could have a separate script, basically a separate Python program that imports this
module and then runs some stuff and says, is it correct or not?
But that's not that different from what we have here.
And PyTest provides some extra, like all these extra debugging error messages that deselect
certain things if you want to test only that.
It will print output if you want to or don't want to.
But that being said, quite often I do basically have a test function that, you know, is just
a plain Python code.
It loads stuff, does an analysis, and prints, is it correct.
So there's times they start that way or have that in addition.
The point isn't to use OmniPyTest.
The point is to see that you actually can make these tests.
And maybe next let's go to automated test and leave more of these questions for the break
and final discussion, because I think a lot might become clear later.
So with that being said, let's see, first I'll come to my screen.
So automated testing.
So we did this ourselves.
So what if you forget to run PyTest?
So the part we did ourselves, well, we did write the tests, but we run PyTest manually,
I guess is what you mean.
If I forget to run it, the tests don't run, and then I can easily make changes that break
something.
Yeah.
The tests don't really do much if they don't run, I guess.
So it is nice to set it up so that they run automatically.
Yeah.
And that's what we're going to see.
So we're going to see how GitHub, on every push and pull request, is able to run all
of the tests that we have defined.
So let's go back to [name]'s screen, if you're ready.
Yes.
Okay.
So what should we do next?
I guess we want to publish this.
So we will take the same exercise repository, or is it the same one?
Well, no, it says make a new one.
Okay, fine.
I guess we can use the same directory though,
because it's pretty simple.
So we do need to make a new repository
because this is not the repository.
This is not using Git.
Okay, yeah.
So I need to go and initialize.
I could directly publish to GitHub as we go.
Yeah.
So let's try that,
because we are going to need to do this at some point.
Yeah.
Right?
Yes.
see us use everything we've learned during the past two weeks. So we will see
using Git from day one. You will see making GitHub repositories from
days two and three. You will see us setting up a GitHub actions like in day
5. And how this can be made social in day 4. So this might be fast, but we'll tell you
and we'll slow down in the important parts.
Okay so and yeah my the user interface here vs code does a good number of steps in one go
when I click here. Okay so yeah what do I want to include not the pytest cache not pycache just
example.py. Okay and there we go.
Open GitHub.
Where should I go next?
Should I keep showing the code or should I go to the new GitHub page?
Maybe let's show what we would really do in real life.
So would you be using VS Code for?
Well, okay, what do I want to do next? What's the next step?
So, what I want to achieve is I want these tests to run automatically
whenever I make a change, or at least often enough that I don't forget.
So, how would you do that?
So, wait, let's back up here.
we're doing the example under automated testing and it gives us some sample code to add to a
repository, a functions.py file. Okay, let's do that. I guess [name] will go and copy
the functions. Yes, so we'll create a functions.py file
This is quite similar, actually, to the example.py in that it has this add function.
But now we also have a subtract function.
It has this comment because I copied it directly from the notes.
But you can also see that comment, so fine.
It has a multiply function.
And we will also have this one I missed, Fahrenheit to Celsius, or convert Fahrenheit to Celsius,
which uses these other functions.
Okay.
So, this code is provided in the exercise, and we will commit it and push it to GitHub
now.
Okay.
So, add it.
And [name] is quickly here doing all the git committing stuff.
We're not explaining it again.
Yes.
Commit message and then push the changes to GitHub.
Okay, there we are.
But now we don't have any tests for this functions module.
But we add that later.
Okay.
Or do we add it later?
Yes, we do add it now.
Yeah, that is, I guess, the next step.
Yes.
Or at least it's a necessary step on the way.
So, what am I doing here?
I should explain as I go.
We add a file test underscore functions.py.
So, as you said, PyTest will also check for files or modules with the name test underscore something.
and now we actually don't directly have access to these functions so we we need to import them
so let's say from functions import add should you copy and paste from the
This is Python and it's also hopefully clear enough.
So I will rename the convert Fahrenheit to Celsius function as I import it into F2C,
but otherwise I'm directly importing the ones we have.
And this first test is what we already saw.
two and three equals five and add space and ship equals spaceship should i include the other test
as well yes copy everything we will uncomment it later okay so we'll keep them commented for now
and i suppose um i feel like i'm done with something so i will add and commit
So, and now [name] is doing the committing, which we pushed for.
Okay, so step two in our exercise, or demo, is to run the test locally.
Okay. So, we did that already. Let's try it. So, now we can just run PyTest and it will
find the test underscore file. This test underscore functions. And it will find one
test and it passed.
Yes.
So, collected one item means there was one test.
Okay.
Okay. So, seems good.
So, next up in our demo is to enable automated testing.
So, now we switch to the GitHub view.
Okay. So, let's go there.
And this is the GitHub repository.
It opened in my browser window when I clicked open.
And it is this PyTest example.
So, it has an example.py.
Um, I need to refresh and it should have more files.
Yes.
Okay.
Functions and test functions.
Good.
Yes.
So we can, now we do, this is the main part, the main point of what we're doing
here, so we will tell GitHub that every time there's a push run pytest on test
functions.py and we do that via GitHub actions, which if you look at the top of
the tab bar. There's actions. So click there. OK. And I don't have any actions yet, so it's
suggesting a number of things I can run. Yes. And one of them is Python application. Yes.
OK. So go there. And it even nicely says create and test a Python application. Yeah. And it
It gives us a bunch of boilerplate.
So this basically is what you need here.
But I think there's some edits that we'll do.
Okay.
What do we need to change?
So it says to modify the highlighted lines.
So we need to say jobs pull requests have write access.
I'd probably copy from the notes.
So it needs write access to pull requests.
Oh, right, to post comments to the pull requests.
And we'll see what these things do later.
is basically lots of different configuration. Yeah okay so let's add um under install dependencies
we need to tell it to install flake 8 pytest and pytest-cov. So this is something called
test coverage which we will talk about later. And then down here below instead of just running
to test, which would work and run the tests, we will also use this coverage report then. Yes,
and let's see, does this match? So, before we leave this window, let's slow down and take a
look at what it does. This is called YAML, and it's a configuration, well, it's a simple markup
language. It defines data. So we see on line 15 there's jobs. There's a job with the name build.
It gives some permissions and steps. And this uses, it says first checkout. It sets up Python.
It installs some things. And if you look at lines 31 to 33, this doesn't look, this is basically
the same kind of stuff you can run in a terminal. So this is basically creating a virtual machine
of some sort and letting you run Python stuff inside. There's lint with flake 8.
Line 42. We see it runs pytest with this extra option coverage report. So
So these options are new to us, but PyTest is not new.
So it's running the same thing we've run before, but automatically.
And if PyTest detects any errors, it will exit with a failure, and then GitHub Actions
will detect PyTest failed, and then give us a warning.
And that's the main point here.
Yeah, so when will it run? It will run whenever we push to the main branch or whenever there's
a pull request to the main branch, which is often enough for me.
Yeah, okay.
Okay.
So, yes, so it says commit changes.
Okay, let's do that.
And testing workflow. And commit. Okay. Did something happen?
Yeah. Can we go back to the code view? Yeah. There's this yellow thing that we saw previously.
So what have we done now?
So we have made some code locally.
We set up PyTest.
And now we've told GitHub to run the test we've made on every push and pull.
And yes, there's been a lot of different code and stuff we've pasted here and there.
you can you don't like we have gone fast you haven't had time to read everything
we've been pasted the point is that now
github is running it as we see from this yellow dot can you click on the yellow
dot yeah so it is actually done okay we can still go take a look what it's done
And here is the section where it runs test.
So it has completed the test.
Yes.
So.
Okay.
Sorry.
I out of habit moved back, but is there something else you want to point out there?
Yeah.
Can we go back?
Let's give people time to take a look and see.
So now here, GitHub has run all of the different rules we've defined.
It checked out the repository, set up Python, run PyTest, and PyTest worked.
So it will run it on every commit.
So let's continue.
So we've done this verification that it's run.
So let's add a test that reveals a problem.
So I guess [name] can go back to VS Code.
Yes.
Just move the window here.
So I believe that is this next step.
Test subtract.
Yes.
So first, can you do git pull to get all the updates?
that happens by clicking here and now we can see that we have added this workflow here so now
github has the file we added on github is now present in our local repository
so since we're up to date we can do some new things okay
Okay, so let's uncomment this function and save.
And now, given that you said we were uncovering a problem,
I assume this test will fail if we run it.
So should we try it locally or just push
and see what happens?
Commit and push.
Okay.
test subtract so we added a new test for the subtract function and push it to github and
i will show the github view again go to the main view and now it's again running the tests
Okay let's go to the action view instead so it shows the previous one that worked and now there's
a new push that's well the tests for that new push are running let's see it usually doesn't
take very long but we'll see oh you can actually see how far it's progressed
So by clicking on it, it's done.
We see it fixed.
Yes.
OK.
Now I think it's the time I take over the screen share
as your partner and make the fix.
So I will click here.
So can someone, or actually, I can
paste this repository in the notes.
So here I am, I'm logged in.
Why don't I see the dot that shows the failure?
If I click on Action,
I see a test failure.
So what do I do?
So first I'll make an issue about it. So I click on the issues tab, click on new
issue. I'll be quick about it.
So, this issue says there's a bug in test subscrap outwork on it, so basically someone
knows that it's there and it's being fixed.
Of course, if someone was working on your own project, you would just fix it.
But here we're showing if something was bigger, took more time, and we wanted to synchronize
better.
So how do I fix it now?
Well, we go back to day three, and I would make a pull request.
And I guess I will do that through the GitHub web interface.
So I click on code, and we know from, ah, now there's the red X.
So we know from GitHub that I can edit directly here.
So I click on Functions.
And I've identified the problem.
I know that I can click on Edit in GitHub and make the change.
So if this was a big enough project,
I'd be fixing it on my own computer.
But for a demo, this is good.
I need to fork the repository, and notice that [name] hasn't given me any permissions
here.
So for any other code online, I could be doing the same things.
So I fixed the subtract function with one line.
I will commit changes.
So this is all happening quickly, but it's day three kinds of things.
commit message will be, and then the extended descriptions.
So, I'm giving some notes about what it was, and I will propose changes.
So, here we go.
So, again, this is day 3 kind of stuff.
So there's my head repository of RkDarst, and I'm sending it to the other repository.
There I see the changes, I will create pull request, and it's the same things here.
I should include in the description fixes number one, so the issue number, so the issue
will be automatically linked and closed and created.
And now, here's the cool part.
So it says that I cannot update it.
And also, I have a feeling that it's not running the tests because now GitHub doesn't run tests
from new contributors.
So let's switch back to [name]'s screen, if you're ready.
Yes.
I'm ready.
Okay.
So if you go to the pull request view.
Yeah.
I noticed I have a new issue and a new pull request.
So if I go to the new pull request, fix the subtract function. Nice.
Yeah, the test hasn't started running because I haven't approved that [name] can run tests
in my repository or can run workflows. So I will approve it.
Okay.
And now they're running.
It's running.
And we just wait a second for it to turn green.
And we will see, does it work?
Okay.
that's happening. It says it fixes, changed plus to one, plus to minus.
Oh, it failed. I wonder why. I was going to go here to see,
so the plus has been changed to minus. That seems fine. Okay, let's take a look at the,
I guess the fastest way is to go through the pull request. Yeah, let's click on details.
What happened?
Ah, the coverage report path failed. So the tests passed, but
something failed here. Resource not accessible by integration.
Well, okay. This is something, well,
no, this is something we added. Yeah. I guess we'll leave it be.
I guess this is what we call the demo effect, so
something in github has changed but okay well the test did pass so i'm fine with merging the pull
request yeah confirm merge here we go and the pull request is automatically closed and the issue is
also automatically closed yes okay now since the main branch has been updated it's actually
again running the test here i'm kind of interested in it whether it will actually work here or not
but we'll see i guess this is because it couldn't write to the pull request or something
or save the data yes now it did work okay um
so actually creating the coverage thing doesn't work from a pull request now yeah
yeah well um we can fix that later but um and we also noticed the issue is closed
Yes. So I guess I will switch back to my screen and let's wrap up and go to the
break. Yeah. Okay. So this was relatively fast work here. We used PyTest. We made
same example. We committed to GitHub. We added a test in GitHub which can run PyTest on every
single commit, whether [name] makes it or whether someone makes the commit in a pull request.
test. And this can really remove the friction in contributing to projects. So I make a project,
I add some tests. Once people start contributing, I'll make sure that the GitHub tests are set
up. So that way, when someone said something, I can see really quickly, has it worked? And
the person submitting can see before and see, okay, like, have I done everything I need before the
original author should take their time to look at it? And this helps a lot.
It works for both the centralized and forking workflows for one repository or multiple
repositories. And GitHub Actions can run on Windows, Mac, Linux operating systems. It has
this marketplace to run different kinds of things easily. Basically it's this thing that automatically
adds things to you. It's completely free for public projects in line with GitHub's normal
philosophy. But this is not only a GitHub thing. So GitLab has a CI kind of thing. There's other
services, some of which provide free time and builds for open source projects. So I propose
now that we go to our break, and we can keep taking questions then. And the next episode,
we will go into test design. And there, a lot of the question people have been asking,
like, how does this apply to a big, complicated project that's not these really simple functions?
we will start discussing them then. So start adding your questions. Anything else for now?
No, I think that's fine. Okay, get to the hard questions in the next section.
So let's go to the break and see you in 10 minutes at 13 past hour. Bye.
Bye.
you
We are back, I hope.
And I see some messages from the streaming software, I hope that's not bad.
So
Well, is everything okay with people in the stream?
Yeah.
And now we go to test design.
And people have been asking previously, how does this work whenever I have some really
complicated code?
I can't make a two-line function that tests it.
Should I really have a lot of small test functions for everything?
And now is the time to ask those questions.
We probably can't answer everything, but write it in the notes.
And this is really the core here.
It's really easy to give these demos and show usePyTest on a one-line function.
Whenever you're testing a software that uses random numbers and has thousands of lines
and has no one fixed result, how do you even test it?
How do you make sure it's correct?
I mean, you have to have something, right?
Because if you don't even know what the right answer would be, how do you know that it's
it's giving what it should.
So yeah, and for a lot of it, there's a first question that's been asked, do you have a
practical way to test load-level functions that interact with external hardware?
So once I was reading something, and it was like, here's a way you could run the Linux
kernel on custom hardware and it has some network interface which is used for running tests so
when you have questions like this if you say to me okay this is hard to test
do some web searches and i bet someone has figured out how to do it before
just because well yeah yeah i assume this is a common problem i've dealt with it a couple of
times. I guess in practice it ended up being quite similar. It's not exact, so you need
some tolerance. You check that an absolute value is smaller than a number. And of course
the tests run slower because a physical thing needs to move from place to place while it's
running.
And maybe we don't see it here, but a lot of test design is structuring the code so
that it can be tested.
So if you have one 1000 line function, that's really hard to test.
But can you break it down into 800 line functions, which are complicated but can be tested, but
the unknown part is just contained in a very few parts, so what you can't test you can audit
separately. So anyway, this episode we're about to cover is normally an
exercise and we would give you a lot of time to basically...
Well, I'll scroll down quickly here.
You would see there's a lot of different sample functions, and we would challenge you to test
them.
But we're going to do that ourselves.
Do we have time to do all of them, or should we focus on a few?
Or should we just discuss some of them?
do you think? Well I think probably not all of them. We probably don't have time to do
all of them. I guess so if when things come up in the notes it's probably worth discussing
and otherwise we could pick some of these and actually write the tests. So maybe let's
start at the beginning and but depending on what people request we'll jump to
those so I will switch to [name]'s screen. Okay and I'll be doing actual coding
yes so I'll show the VS Code window. So do you make a new file to put these in?
or that would make sense how would we so let's do this what's the first example
the first factorial example the first example is this factorial function so
this factorial dot pi since the solution is basically the same as what we've done
already should we actually do it or should we discuss I'd say let's discuss
yeah maybe it's enough to discuss. So maybe I'll switch back to my screen then.
Okay. So we see here the proposed solution is basically what we've already
already done. It adds, it tests some values. How do we test really big values? Can it even
be tested in this case?
There is a limit to how large a normal integer can be. Is there in modern Python, so there
There is a way you can handle really big integers, but is that built-in in modern Python?
I'm not actually sure.
I think so.
I think Python by default will go to big int.
So I guess in theory this works for anything big.
Are you happy with these tests here?
Do you think this is enough?
What else would you test?
I would like to see some, to test some larger numbers,
because these could easily be hard-coded into the function.
So a larger integer.
So I guess at least one example case
that would go to the big integer realm.
Yeah, that would be nice.
Okay.
And to check that that's correct,
I think you would first compute it somehow by hand
or in a different way.
Another thing is what if you give it an incorrect thing, like something that's not a number or something that's a negative number or a non-integer number.
So, in PyTest, we can actually test if it will raise an exception when you tell it to
do a negative number.
Should we do an example of that, or should we move on to more interesting things?
I think time's ticking, maybe we should go on.
But anyway, the point is, if you search PyTest test raises exception, you'll find an example
and it will tell you how you can check does it actually give value error here.
Okay.
What's the next one?
a function which receives two strings and returns a number.
Okay. Is there any challenge here beyond what we've already done?
I mean, yeah, it is. I could easily come up with a few examples and
and compare them to the correct result that it does not seem like there's a lot of complication
here.
Yeah.
This again, like maybe it's not a string, maybe, maybe it's something different.
But then I think it would raise an error.
Okay, so let's look at the solution quickly and I guess this last one here,
word occurrence. So it tests, does it detect substrings? Which is actually a
very interesting point. So triple a is contained within five a's?
That's true.
So I'm not sure if that test actually...
That is not the result I would expect from a function called word occurrence.
Yeah. So is the test wrong or is the function wrong?
I mean maybe this is the intended result, but then it needs to be documented. I'm a bit surprised.
So the point here is that by making the test, we considered the corner case and realized maybe we need to update our function also.
Which is good.
good. Okay. A function which reads a file and returns a number. Is this worth doing
for real? Or?
There's a lot of places in code where you need to read a file and do something, or where
have a function that reads a file and does something with the contents. You could always
split that into one function that reads the file, another one that only does the work on the contents
and then test the second one separately. But still, yeah, I think occasionally testing,
reading a file is worth the trouble. It's maybe not complicated enough that we want to go through
it in detail. Yeah. The solution, I guess, should I just give the solution? Yeah, I guess.
What I would do is make an example file and the test would be reading that example file
or a number of example files. Yeah, so if you ask me, this is where my opinion would be
this function is doing too many things. The function is both reading the file
and doing some analysis. So doing the analysis is worth testing. Reading the
file is difficult to test. So why doesn't this file... why aren't there two functions?
One which reads the file and returns maybe the file object or the raw data,
and another function which does the counting. And then the one that does the
counting is easy to test because I give it some arguments and it gives the
results out. And the one that reads the file maybe I wouldn't test yet because
it's so simple and not worth my time to do this boilerplate code where I make a
contemporary file, I open the file, I save the data, and then I run it on the file.
Yeah, the file opening function is a built-in Python thing, so it doesn't need to be tested
necessarily.
Yeah.
I mean, if this was a really big program that had thousands of users, then yeah, maybe testing
opening the files would be worth it, but for most of what I do, I don't care that much.
And this is a case where making it easier to test improves the function itself. So,
for example, whenever I was working with someone once, they had a lot of really great
analysis functions and a lot of really great analysis functions but the
functions read a file and then did the analysis instead of doing so instead of
having it separate so that whenever they wanted to apply this to a new case like a
new kind of project, they had to arrange all of their data into exact same format, which didn't
make sense anymore. So making it easier to test makes it more modular, which incidentally we'll
talk about later, and would make the code better overall. Okay. What's next? Something with an
external dependency. Is this worth testing?
I mean a lot of functions will have external dependencies.
It is worth testing unless you are just testing the dependency.
But I mean hopefully the dependency will have its own tests.
I'm not sure about this one though. So what's the point here? There's
It's from reactor import max temperature.
So this seems like it's really testing whether the reactor itself is working correctly.
Although you could also think of it as testing whether you understand the reactor interface
correctly or whether it's working the way you are assuming it should be working for
your code.
So it might be worth testing, but it's an edge case, I probably wouldn't.
So yeah, this is what you said, is it testing if maxTemperature is set correctly, or if
changing maxTemperature changes the function as you expect?
But let's look at the solution and see.
So here, this monkey patch is something from PyTest.
And you might look at this and say, where is the value of monkey patch coming from?
How does PyTest find this?
So the answer is this is PyTest magic.
So if you give it the name of some standard argument, it will pass in something to the
functions and let you do things like this.
So this means monkeypatchoh, do you know the definition of monkeypatch?
How would you describe it?
I think monkey patch is a coding term, one module like this test function is changing
the value of something on another module reactor when it's really not designed to be changed
this way.
So in plain language, this code means when this runs on reactor, it will set max temperature
to 100, so it's a known value. Then the test can run. And then when the function is over,
it will restore it to the previous value. So this allows us to make sure that maxTemperature
is something known, so we're testing only this function and not the external dependency
of what is max temperature.
Have you ever done things like this?
I can't think of an example, but I, well, yes, in some case, not often.
So essentially replacing something in a library because, for example, I don't have access
to certain hardware that's required to run the library, you just replace a function in
that library with a function of your own and run that instead.
So yeah, it is a useful thing to do.
In most of my cases, the maxTemperature would be a constant, so I would just test the function.
And if the function fails, I have to see, did the maxTemperature change or did the function
break?
And that's a bit unfortunate, but there.
But in a case where maxTemperature is really defined somewhere else in dynamic, you have
to do something like this.
Or maybe the original function could be defined to take two arguments.
It's up to you.
Okay, should we continue?
Yeah.
Should we do this as the talk about this and then test-driven development, then do that
as a demo.
Sorry, so first talk about this and then do test room development as a demo.
Yeah.
Yeah, that makes sense.
So we have a class here, a Python class.
If you haven't seen this before, then don't worry, but we won't explain it now.
We see it sets, it models a pet.
The pet can be initialized with a name and hunger level.
And when we call this go for a walk function, then hunger gets incremented.
So how would we test this function?
What do we have?
What's the steps you would have to do?
Yeah, you would definitely have to create the object.
We have to create the object.
And then if this is something you wrote yourself, you know that it starts with hunger equals
zero.
Mm-hmm.
So I know one thing you can test is whether the  you can test the init function immediately.
Okay.
Yeah.
And then I suppose you would run go for a walk a few times with different starting values
and check that it increments by one.
So by starting value, do you mean we would set hunger to a certain value, then run go
for a walk, and then check the final hunger value?
Yes.
Okay, yeah.
At least that's one thing.
Makes sense.
Yeah.
Should we check the solution?
Yeah, let's see.
So, pet Fido.
Yes, so we check that it's initialized to the value we expect, zero.
We walk, and then we test isHunger greater now.
Okay, that should always work.
And then we set hunger to minus one, if that makes any sense.
We run go for a walk, and then we check isHunger zero.
And I guess what's the lesson here, that whenever we have something that changes state, we have
to set the state, check or run it, and then check the state after.
And this is pretty normal to do.
There was also a couple of questions about, for example, a stochastic thing or a thing
where you cannot necessarily predict the result, and we did talk about that a bit, but
I'm just saying it would be good to get there, have time for that as well.
Should we go straight to testing randomness next?
Yeah.
Let's do that. Okay, should we go back to your screen?
Okay.
Are you ready?
So I will get a...
Actually, first let's look over the thing here.
So, we want to test randomness. We can try fixed random seeds, so this is where basically
you pre-know what the value is, or we know what the random number generator would make.
We can see, does it follow the expected distribution, or we can look at it by eye and think, what's
the i thing we're looking at, yeah.
And there are often some hard parameters
you can test even in a completely random case
without setting the seed.
You can test that the value is not outside some boundary.
Yeah.
That it makes sense for what it is.
Yeah, like if I was testing randomness,
first I would test, well, I can make a test
and not even look at the value.
does the function run without errors?
Yeah.
Is the answer of a dice rule, if I run it 100 times,
is it always between 1 and 6 inclusive?
And if I trust my random number generator,
then that's better than nothing.
And we get better from there.
So if we're testing Yahtzee, do you know how Yahtzee even works?
Roughly, I mean, you throw dice and then you check if the dice match certain predefined
sets.
Yeah.
I guess we can look at the code in more detail.
Should I just copy paste the entire code to my file?
So in yatsi.py, okay, so what do we have here?
Can you explain?
We have a rollDice function, which it seems, oh, it rolls number of dice.
So it returns a list of a random choice between one and six inclusive integers and yeah, in
the parameters, you can set the number of dice you want to roll.
Okay.
Yeah.
And then Yahtzee.
And then Yahtzee itself, play with five six-sided dice and three draws.
Okay.
So first, you roll some dice and you check.
I'm not exactly sure how this will end up playing Yahtzee, but let's see.
What's the most common number visible in the dice, I suppose.
That's the most common side.
And then how many of those do you have?
So if you have like three fours, this would be four and this would be three.
Yeah, I would expect the most common side is called the target side.
Number of same sides is how often.
So how many of those you have.
If it's equal to five, you return five.
Okay.
I guess you get five points from that.
If you get five of the same, then that matches something.
you can try again. Okay. Throw a second and a third time and do the same thing again.
Okay. And then it returns the number of same. So this is counting how in tree throws how
many of the same number you can get. And if you're rolling five dice, right? Yes. Okay.
So if you get five of the same, then you don't need to roll again. That's the best result
you can have. So then you just immediately return that.
Can we try running and see what it says?
Okay.
But to be honest, looking at all this stuff, it doesn't quite make sense, but we can use
it as a code.
It's not a standard Yahtzee game.
It's a much simpler version of Yahtzee.
This is running a number of games and then printing how many times you got five.
Okay, so back to the terminal.
So let's run the code.
It did not do anything.
If name equals main, why doesn't it print something?
Did you save the file?
Good question.
Okay.
I did not.
That makes more sense.
Okay.
So six guys.
So it ran 100 games, and on six of those games, we got five dice showing the same number.
which is called a Yahtzee, I guess.
So, what are the different levels we could test it at?
Should we test just the dice roll first?
Yes, that makes sense. It's not a completely trivial function, so it makes sense to test it.
In practice, we always throw five dice,
but I guess since it's general enough,
you can test it in different ways.
Should I just write test directly into this?
Yeah, I'd say just throw it right in there.
Maybe just directly after the function I'm testing.
Yeah, let's do that.
So in the solution,
says test roll dice with no arguments and the solution suggests we set the
random number generator seed to zero and then we test the actual value. So this
function random dot seed it's so in random number generators there's
something called a seed and if you start with the same seed the generator will
always give the same values out. So that by giving the seed, we should be able to predict
what comes out. So we can assert RollDice5 equals the list, and from the solution the
values are 44135. So what's the problem here? Or what could be a problem here?
What if Python's random number generator has changed since we last did this workshop?
Yeah, well, then the numbers would be different. And I guess this test doesn't really tell you
whether the rollDice function has broken or whether the random has just changed in some way.
Yeah, should we try running it and let's see if this works?
Yeah.
So pytest.yatsi.py.
It didn't find a test because I didn't save it.
Okay.
Okay, trying again and it passed.
Okay, so it didn't change.
So this actually works pretty well for testing this function, I guess, so what's the disadvantage though?
If the function changes, these outputs would change, so it will verify it's always giving the same output,
but it doesn't give you any flexibility for changing how the dice are rolled, because then it would give something different.
Should we go to next? So there's test Yahtzee. So maybe this one you should copy from the
notes okay so basically in this test it will play Yahtzee 1 million times and
we'll check did we win approximately 4.6 percent of these million games okay this
also sets a random seed. Yeah, so this time we don't have the problem that if random changes
then the result will change because actually with any seed it should be roughly the same,
approximately the same result. If you're running it enough times it should work. Yeah, okay.
Okay.
The downside is that it takes a while.
Yeah.
Okay.
It's done.
And now it says two tests passed.
Good.
So it was the correct number of wins.
Yes.
So I guess this is in the category of testing distributions.
We check that the, we set up a specific version of whatever random process is running and
And it needs to, given some correct number, plus, minus, whatever random error.
Yeah.
Okay, let's go back to my screen and see what is next.
So we did this testing randomness with Yahtzee.
Designing an end-to-end test. Maybe we should go to discussion now and let's see what people
say. So please start asking your hard testing questions.
So we'll get something. Designing an end-to-end test.
So this is basically... This is a bit hard to read quickly.
So it's basically some shell function, the unique command, and how would you test that?
And basically you give it some input data, and you check is the output what you expect.
And this is also a pretty reasonable way to test some things.
So, instead of each individual function, just run the whole thing on some known data.
Do you have any comments here?
Well, I mean, this is something that's very common with my projects.
So, they include some test data and you run some full process of, you take some actual
processing steps and it should always produce the same expected result.
As long as there's no randomness involved, this is a very useful test, very useful type
of test.
The downside is that it doesn't give you a lot of detail.
If it fails, you only know that your process fails.
So hopefully you also have a unit test failing at that point.
But if not, you kind of need to go digging and figure out what's going on.
Yeah.
I mean, my philosophy would be if the end-to-end test failed, at least I know and I'm in the
same place I would be otherwise, which is go down and debug it.
And maybe I would use the opportunity to guess where it is and make some unit tests now that
I know how it can't fail, or what's likely.
Let's go on.
More end-to-end testing, create an actual end-to-end test.
I think we don't have time for this.
Let's go to the notes and see what good questions people have.
So down to test design, there was this good question, do you have a practical way to test
low-level functions that interact with external hardware?
I think that's probably answered there well enough.
think we talked about something like that. Yeah, yeah. How to design a test without running a
whole solver whenever it's very complex like this? Hmm. I guess, yeah, can you break it down to
several small subroutines. Can you give it a, what's the simplest problem that has a known
non-trivial value? So this is not exactly answering this question, but some of the tests
that I was most proud of, it was during my postdoc, I was had to generate random graphs
according to some particular algorithm. And the algorithm was in fact the thing that
the research was about. So I had nothing to compare to. So how would I test this kind of thing?
Well of course I ran it and looked at it by eye, but is there some glaring bug here?
So here's what I did. My algorithm took some parameters. Basically the problem,
their probability of making links in certain forms. So I set this probability to zero,
and then I should get an empty graph out of it. And then I did it again, and I set the probability
to one, and I should get a complete graph. And since there were two or three different
parameters going in, I could do different combinations of these parameters,
0, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 0, with different probabilities that are 1 and 0, and C is the
graph that comes out what I expect, which is usually either a complete graph or an incomplete
graph or some known number of edges in there. And this actually let me define some bugs
in my code that I couldn't see by eye. And I was really happy with figuring this out.
think that's a good example of end-to-end. Is it end-to-end or is it integration? I'm not sure
what kind of test it is, but in the end the name doesn't matter. The point is it worked.
I guess that's an end-to-end test. It's not checking whether multiple libraries work together.
Okay, a good workflow in Python. What's this question? If I do a test, it will apply to
a version of the code. I need to add a test to a new function. Do I new test? This is
a really good point. So, test-driven design. This is something we skipped in the previous
lesson. You can, in fact, write a test before you write the function itself. So, this is,
is it extreme programming or something like that, test-driven development? Anyway, once I saw it
written this way, you want to add some new functionality. You make the test for it, and
then you run the test code and you see it fails because the function isn't defined. Good. Now,
you write code until that test passes. So this ensures that everything you do has a test
and you think about how you want to use the function before you write it.
So this is basically defining what the functionality should be
before you start writing it and first writing down what the function should do.
and only then writing the function, which makes sense.
But it really depends on how you want to do things.
So I've used all kinds of strategies, and I don't think I've ever done anything that's pure test-driven development.
I guess test-driven development does  it requires that you can define what the end
result is, that you know what the end result is before you start working on it.
And that works in small steps, but it usually almost never works for an entire new feature
or a new code base, especially in a new research software.
are unlikely to stay, the requirements are unlikely to stay the same.
This next question, some kind of research test which determines how successful the proposed
approach is. If you can define an overall success as a test then I would definitely do that
and probably start with that. It's relatively easy and probably high
impact because you can quickly run it to see where your errors are.
Yeah.
Yeah, again it relies on you knowing what the result should be. So you can probably
know some features of it like a range or errors or how fast it should be, but often not exactly
what the number is at the end because if you knew that then probably you wouldn't write the code.
This next question.
I have no tests working with images.
This idea of getting some test images with easy cases manually annotating and comparing,
I mean, yeah, that sounds exactly like what I would do.
Of course it can be difficult to make the initial images, but if you don't have some
test data for something like this, you're going to be looking at some images to see
if it's correct anyway.
So why not make an image that doesn't have any confidential data and is small, add it
to your repository and then it saves you a lot of looking separately every time
you make a change. Do you consider...should we look at this screenshot here?
Example of how a research test is formulated, can we comment? Um, question
Ideally, parameters shouldn't be hard-coded but uploaded over a file.
I mean, if it's easy to hard-code, then why not start with that?
So, is it a test?
If it's a test, then hard-coding parameters often make sense.
You will change them much less often than in when you're running an actual code.
So hard coding is much less of a problem.
Yeah.
So it looks like so, yeah, so there's different use cases depending on the parameter.
it will either run the first use case or the second use case.
And then it will see, does it give the right output?
This is better than the check.
Where's the check?
Or is it checking if it runs?
Is this a check here?
Oh, it's an equal sign.
Would that be a comparison?
Or maybe the test is below, lower, and we don't see it.
Yeah.
But I mean, as a starting point, I would start here.
And if there get to be so many test cases,
I can't keep track of them, then I'd probably
start splitting them out.
So one small thing here is that which test cases run
is hardcoded here.
So I guess what I would do is turn this into a function
and then run it with two different input parameters, either use case equals one or
first use case equals zero and then use case equals one. Of course, then you could instead of
use case as only single parameter, you could include all of those numbers,
all of those parameters into the function parameters.
It makes sense.
Then you could easily run both cases, post-test cases, in a single script.
Yeah.
Okay.
If a test fails, how does it fail?
Will it be printed, or what?
So it depends on the frame...
Wait.
Ah, this is commenting on that.
I think there's a lot there.
So let's go to the last question before lunch break.
Does a big project include test codes in source code
or C only final?
So for every good open source project I know of,
the test code is included in with the actual code itself.
There's little reason not to.
And it really improves confidence of things
if you want people to be modifying it and improving it and if not well
i mean yeah i guess someone could release the code without the test code but then don't expect
other people to be able to contribute to it that well
um yeah if um if the tests are not included then you cannot check that you installed it correctly
or at least it's not easy to check that you installed it correctly so
So also for that reason, it's good to include the tests.
So did we miss anything?
I'm not seeing many chat messages or other questions,
hopefully.
So should we?
Well, what's the overall summary here?
So, we've seen different ways to write code which ensures other code works.
And by making it automatic, you can run it much more often than you could otherwise.
And it will hopefully make your code more correct.
But more importantly, it makes your development easier.
Like, the few times that I've started with tests really early for some research code
where I didn't even know what the answer should be, I've been really happy because I run this,
I can see all my really simple syntax errors and debugging syntax errors and so on much
faster than I could otherwise.
then I could use my brain, do manual effort for tests
and checks, which are not easy to automate
and actually are difficult. So with that said,
do you have any other final wrap ups?
Well, having to test run automatically
is super helpful because you will forget to run them
otherwise. So we've seen how to do it. But yeah, it's just automating it, making it as easy as
possible is an important thing. And it's also useful for others because, of course, it's much
easier to get everyone else to run the tests when they don't actually even need to run them.
They will just run automatically.
I guess we should go now. At least I need to get or go out quickly.
So thank you and see you in about an hour.
Have a good lunch break.
Okay, thank you.
Bye.