Hello, hello, can you hear us?
So should I go to [name]'s screen, I guess?
Yes, let's do that.
OK, so this next section is a type-along or something,
not a type-along, but a demo, but something
between us doing things in the stream and an exercise.
So it works best when there's a lot of active participation
the notes document. So this is about modular code development and just to get
started in the document we have a few questions so please go and take a look
at those and answer those.
Yes, we see them here.
Yeah, so there's also some answers given away in this image that is linked from the materials.
So we'll quickly show that, but we're also already getting some answers, which is good.
So to you, what does modular code development mean?
What does modular even mean?
Yeah, what is modular?
The first thing that comes to my mind when I think of what is modular is the International
space station, because I think I learned the word from there, but it consists of this kind
of a central structure, but that's also kind of a module of its own.
The main thing is different groups have made these sections to the station and you can
plug them together.
They're like Legos.
You can take one piece and plug it into another piece, and the idea is that all the wiring
should work and that there's some sort of interface between the two that helps all the
parts work in all of these sections.
So basically you can ship up one new module and connect it and that works.
Like you can add and remove things, you can understand each part separately.
Yeah and someone can design one part of a bigger whole and then as long as the interface makes
sense you can plug it into a bigger thing and out of those smaller modules then make something even
something bigger and more complicated and it's still kind of it remains understandable and
manageable. Yeah so why do we have a lesson on modular code development? Like what's the
big point here. Well yeah, so a software project can get really big and it can get and in fact it
does get so big that or software gets so big that it's hard to understand. Like if you have
the whole thing written down in one section it is very hard to continue developing it.
it. Plus, when you make something modular, it's not just easier to understand the modules
and then understand the whole that the modules make up, it's also easier to split up the
work. So you can split the different sections, the different modules between different developers,
different people in your team, and someone from the outside can come and write a module
for the thing you designed.
So it makes development easier, it makes testing easier,
and it makes it easier to share your work.
It kind of pulls together a lot of what we've done
in the past two weeks.
So at least in Python,
the things you import are called modules.
Does modular code development have to be about these modules
or is that what this is about?
It's not exactly.
Modular code development is also about functions.
Small functions that do individual things that you can pluck out of a code,
then move into another code and will still work.
So making your, first of all, writing functions,
but then also writing functions that are in themselves modular,
They are independent of the whole project in some way.
But it is also organizing those then into modules, so organizing them into separate
files that could be depending on the language, could be Python modules, could be libraries,
could be shared objects and so on, depending on packages.
different languages or different programming languages have different words for these but
the structure is roughly the same.
What about this last question? Would you prefer your code to be two times slower if it was easier
to read and understand? That depends a lot on the situation. Yeah, if it's a high performance
computing thing, then the main code of course should be as fast as you can make it.
But in most cases, the code should be first understandable and then maybe also efficient
if that's necessary.
But first you should have a code that works and then you can try to make it faster.
But that's actually something I didn't mention in testing, but one very useful idea is to
write two implementations of something.
So you have a slower algorithm, and then you also write a faster algorithm.
And if those produce the same results, then probably both of them work.
The more different they are, the better.
Yeah.
I did that once to, like, verify something.
I've done a lot of high performance computing work
and that's a very useful approach.
Because things you write for the main thing need to be really fast.
But then they are not readable. So you also
write a slower version.
So does modularity always make it slower?
or no I don't actually it's an interesting question because I can't actually think why
it would make anything slower okay that's good principle I mean code that's easier to
understand is unlikely to be really fast just because it's a different you're optimizing
for a different thing. So they don't have a lot of overlap. And I guess making something
more modular might also make it slower just because you are optimizing for a different
thing when you're writing it.
So I guess this question F, would you prefer your code to be twice, two times slower if
it's easier to read and understand? That's not exactly the trade-off we're making here
then.
Yeah, not exactly, but I mean that it's still a good question to think about and it is kind
of related to this lesson because modular code development is ultimately about making
it understandable and manageable.
Taking a really big complex system and making it manageable is, I guess, mainly what we're
talking about.
Well, understandability and being able to reuse it is definitely things I want.
So what do we do next?
I'll pop back to your screen.
Yes.
So yeah, here is one answer or some answers that you could have copied from if you were
looking at the notes.
But this is a link from the notes.
Okay.
So yeah, there's a lot of things that do go wrong with research software development, like
long functions and overcomplicated design that's kind of a maze of problems in the code that you
have to get through. So is this sort of like if you have bad code design non-modular code
maybe it works in the short term but in the long term you're going to have a major problem?
Yeah, that's the idea. So it becomes complex and something that is complex is hard to maintain
and hard to take care of in the long run. Gets to the point where you don't understand
the code you wrote a week ago very easily.
That's good.
Okay, so here are the questions we already talked about. Just skipping through that section.
I will not go through the learning examples in a lot of detail either because we partly
already talked about that, but this is taking a lot from the past two weeks, maybe slightly
different point of view than in the testing lesson where we took a lot of this social coding and
sharing things aspect of it, but now we're mostly working locally by trying to make
a local code better. So let's just get to the task itself.
Okay, so what do we do? So here's an example task and now this is much closer to real scientific code
than the add function in the testing lesson. So it's hopefully somewhat readable if you go
go through it, you can see what's happening. But it could be made a lot more modular, a
lot better. So let's just start by copying this into a Jupyter notebook. And can you
switch to your screen if you have the notebook ready?
There is my screen. Let's adjust the size of stuff. I've made a new directory for this
I will start a Python 3 kernel.
Should I just copy and paste from?
Yeah, let's just start by copying and pasting here so that
we can all see the code in the same way.
Okay.
Then we'll see what it does.
Should I run it?
Yeah, why not? Can you make
this screen either wider or show the entire lines?
Or what do you call it? Wrap the lines?
Okay, so now it's visible.
Okay.
We need the temperatures file.
So you need to download some files.
So should we actually just go through, like, how did we know that?
Yeah.
What is happening here?
What do we see?
So it says read CSV temperatures dot CSV.
if I scroll down, no such file or directory.
And it gives the file name, hopefully.
So we are missing a file.
And if we start looking at the code,
if we had started looking at the code before running it,
we would have realized that it's reading a file.
So why don't we just download the file?
Do you have the link?
Should I do it from Jupyter?
Yeah, why not?
Let's see if it works.
I know on my computer I have a program called wgit installed that will download a file and
save it in the current directory.
So I will run this.
And it says temperatures.csv saved.
Okay, so now we should have the file.
And I will delete this row.
Yeah.
Okay.
So now we should have the file.
Yeah.
Okay.
Let's do what we were thinking of doing.
what it does first. It's taking a while to run. Well, at the meantime, we can look at the line.
It is importing pandas and matplotlib. Matplotlib is a plotting library and pandas is for data
processing. Then we define the number of measurements is 25, whatever that means,
and we read in some data from a CSV file.
We do have this in the notes.
It's data provided by the Finnish Meteorological Institute
about observations of air temperature at the Helsinki-Vantaa airport in 2022.
Okay, so there's another error somewhere.
Well, let's see.
Key error, air temperature.
Well, let's walk through the code and hopefully it will be-
Yeah. Should we look at the file,
like open it and see?
Okay. So what we're doing here is we're reading this data from
the CSV file and taking this number of measurements,
number of rows, so we're taking
25 measurements from this data file, and then the temperatures should be a column from this
CSV file with this name. So, yeah, I guess it doesn't have a column with that name. It's
probably the structure of the data has changed between the Code Refinery workshop, so maybe
we should take a look at what the CSV file contains.
Should I open it through the file browser?
Yeah, I mean, oh, you mean the one in Jupyter, that makes sense.
So it seems a bit broken.
It did not download.
It links, it doesn't link to the raw data.
So this is, okay, it should be raw data from GitHub, there's a mistake in the link.
Okay.
So I can send you the correct link.
I have the correct link here.
OK.
So now I'm again using Jupyter to remove the temperatures.csv
file.
And now I will paste raw data, raw.githubusercontent.
So this should be raw.
Yeah.
And now it says it's saved.
Should we try again?
Yeah. Let's see what happens.
Okay. That looks better.
Okay.
Okay. So we're reading 25 rows of the data and plotting something, but it's calculating some statistics here.
So it's calculating the mean of the temperature measurements.
and then it's plotting the temperatures oh and it's adding this dashed line for the mean
of those temperatures okay and i guess this is the first 25 days of the year so we're talking
january so the temperatures range from minus 2 to minus 12 or so yeah so it makes sense it
actually looks okay. Okay, so what could we do to make this better or specifically more modular?
How is it not modular now? I mean, I can see some immediate problems.
This notebook has to have a file with one certain name, one certain output, and runs everything at
once. So please go to the notes and add any suggestions on what should we do, what we can
do to make this code more modular specifically or just better in some way. And yeah, we can
spot a few problems here immediately. Yeah. We do have a couple of goals in mind though
So, as we start working on this, we want to be able to create a plot, create several different
plots.
We want a plot with 25 measurements, but we also want a plot with 100 measurements and
with 500 measurements.
And I guess, so then just, well, let's start with that.
We have some suggestions here. Don't load the data when creating the plot,
load it separately. Separate the plotting and loading to data. That's a good idea.
Separate to read data from file and compute statistics and plot results into different
functions. Yes, that is a very good idea. Three different functions.
okay so three functions yeah let's let's do that and should they be in three
separate cells in Jupiter I mean yeah that that works I don't have a
preference on whether to split functions into cells or not so what
should I do can you okay well the situation now is related into three
different cells. So let's make a cell for a read data from file function. Okay. And
copy split the cell there. Yeah. Should I split the measurement cell? Yeah. So the number
of measurements needs to be set here, so yeah, split it out.
Okay.
But now I make these functions, so can you give me some advice?
Yeah.
Well, okay, so to make the, so how to split it into functions, yes.
Okay, so the suggestion was to make a read data from file, so I guess that would be running
this pandas.readcsv, but we probably also want to keep the temperatures equals something
because we don't want to write a function that is just the pandas read from csv function.
We wanted to do a little bit more. So, let's do read these two lines, readcsv and then
temperatures equals column. Okay. So, yeah, define a function and it could be just read
temperatures or get temperatures is fine yeah okay and then we need to call that in the original
cell right right good idea return temperatures that's right i almost forgot that yeah and then
we need to call that in the original cell to get the temperatures uh variable set so temperatures
equals. Now, actually, the read data from file comment has become unnecessary.
Yeah. Or has it?
Does get temperatures tell you that it's from file?
You can make it a doc string.
It could also be the function name directly could be something like read temperatures from file or
what would be read data.
Sorry can you say that again? Something like read data or read data
from or read temperatures from file. If that's the function name then it's
clear what it's doing. Yeah.
Get temperatures
like this. Yeah that that works. Okay yeah. Then we want two other functions
So, should we give this function arguments?
Well, do we do that later? Yeah, so that has not been suggested yet, although I'm not sure if they
thought about it. Okay. They didn't write it down in the suggestion. That's another thing that's
important, of course, in modularity, modular code development. But let's do it as it,
let's stick to this now. So then the other one would be for compute statistics.
Okay, so maybe I'll split here.
Wait. Okay.
Okay, so this returns the mean. Well, it should return the mean. It currently doesn't.
It's missing the return. Okay, so it returns the mean temperature value.
you. Should we get temperatures inside that function? I guess it's fine. I also don't
want to make too many suggestions that are not yet in the discussion. Okay. So let's
keep it as it is. But we need to no, we actually we do need to keep the temperatures. We need
temperatures to be defined in the main part of the code.
Okay. Yeah.
we we need to do mean temperatures equals get temperatures in the main code so i copied this
to here but then we do need we need to pass the temperatures variable to compute statistics
okay so mean so i guess we need to do mean equals compute statistics and then yeah pass the
temperatures there okay okay um there was one more suggested function was plot results
would that would be i guess um everything below this mean equals would go into computer plot
results. Yeah, and I guess I should make the cell above this. Yeah, so I will copy and paste it here.
Okay. Okay, that doesn't need to return anything, but we do need to call it.
and we need to pass temperatures to it it's a not defined inside the function
otherwise so the temperatures and the mean also I guess yes true it need
unless we call well like let's not call compute statistics inside plot and the
plot results. It's probably this way and then we need to give it this argument.
Okay. Okay. Now what else? So I mentioned that in the long run we want to create three different
plots with three different numbers of measurements.
So, what could we do about that? Right now, we are actually, so we have hard-coded a good number
of parameters directly into these functions. And I think the, well, the number of measurements
actually is kind of semi-hard-coded into all of them.
Right. That's just-
So we define the number of measurements there.
So we should make it a parameter in
some one way or another of all of these functions.
Okay.
So yeah, let's start with getTemperature from file.
That should get just
numMeasurements directly as a parameter.
And I can delete the cell then?
Yeah.
Because it's not hard-coded anymore.
Then we can just call it with 25.
Compute statistics.
Should compute statistics get num measurements?
It can.
The other option is to use the length of the temperatures column.
So doing len temperatures works directly.
And because it's actually a pandas data frame,
it doesn't even take any time to calculate.
It's already calculated, so we can just use it directly.
Yeah.
I guess, since this is pandas in a more real project, we would just use the mean, but this
is pretending that some big pandas could do a mean for us.
But anyway, okay.
Yeah, that's true.
Good.
And actually, I mean, that is a good suggestion.
Using pandas functions directly is better than writing your own.
But yeah, let's stick to this for now.
And then in the plot results, we have a few options.
I don't know, there's nothing in the notes right now about this, but how should we do
this?
Well, actually, there is.
Pass the file name as input is a suggestion.
So should it be the first or last argument?
I would make it the last one, because it could, in principle, be optional.
Should we make it possible to do it without a filename?
So you wouldn't save the figure then, I guess.
That would make sense.
So basically, we can plot it only in Jupyter, or we can plot it and save it?
On that note, later we'll want to move this into a script and there we will not have,
we will not be able to show it in Jupyter.
So that could also be an option maybe.
So but I'm not exactly sure what would be the best way of doing that.
I don't know if people have suggestions.
So let's just leave that for now.
We do need to fix all of these function calls now.
Yeah, so getTemperatures needs a number of measurements.
So that was 25.
Compute statistics actually doesn't.
It doesn't?
Okay, yeah.
And then plotResults needs a file name, which previously was 25.png.
Okay.
Okay, so let's see that it runs.
getTemperatures.
Ah, so yeah, I have to run everything in the notebook.
Yeah.
I will do restart and run all.
I wish it would just automatically rerun everything with the click run.
Get temperatures.
Did I misspell it?
No, we renamed it.
Oh, right.
Get temperatures.
File.
There we go.
So one suggestion is we could add some styling arguments to plot results.
That's true.
Okay.
I think it's a bit out of the scope here.
So, do you mean we would add them here?
Okay, let's do a couple of things.
Okay.
So, first of all, there's this hard-coded arguments.
There's this R minus and color equals B, blue.
So, there's red.
What this R minus means is red and connected line.
And the B is for blue, color is blue.
And then the line style with two dashes is, well, a dashed line.
So those could all be optional arguments for this function.
Yeah. So should we do that?
Let's do that.
One thing to think about here though is how much reuse does this function have?
And if this is for just producing plots for your paper, how much options do you want to add?
But optional parameters are generally always fine.
You don't need to give those parameters.
So we can say, yeah, OK, good, temp color is R.
And I guess mean color, maybe.
OK, so what's the benefit of doing it this way?
Well, it makes it easier to go and change the colors in your,
when we have a script that plots all of these,
that creates all of these plots for our paper,
it's easier to go and change a,
the color of say all of the temperature plots.
And I guess if we wanted to plot some with different colors, depending on,
like what it was.
So the one thing I mentioned that we want to do in the long run is to plot at
these three different ways.
Let's do that.
The easiest way to do it here is with a for loop.
So let's start with that.
Should I do it here?
Yeah, let's do it here. So let's do a for loop
of four n measurements in,
and we want the 25, 50, and 100.
Okay and we need to indent these things so what else needs to be changed this
should be end measurements. Yeah and then we probably also want to change the
file name. Should this be, we used a Python F string thing. Yeah F string for a format
of formatted strings. All right useful way of doing that. All right okay nice
looking way. So one suggestion is, should the color and font markers be global variables?
What do you think? I mean, that would make it less modular in the sense that the function
would depend on things that are defined outside it. So it would make it harder to take out
of this specific notebook and use somewhere else.
But the upside also is if you want to enforce a uniform style across your paper with of
course users, some function calls could also use this current optional parameters to change
them.
could do that with global parameters. Although even then I would suggest making it a Python module
and then using this space, the global space in quotation marks inside that Python module.
So yeah, it depends on the situation. There's upsides and downsides. But we want to make
things as modular as possible here because, well, this is the modular code development lesson.
So let's try to reduce global variables as much as possible.
Do we actually have any global variables left? I guess not.
No. Okay.
That's fine.
So everything's controllable here.
And now I think we also, so one thing we haven't, we've been talking about,
we haven't mentioned the word or the expression is side effects so previously these functions
did have some side effects and that means they changed things in a global scope
so some global variables depended on whether these functions were run or not and now
Now we pretty much don't have side effects anymore.
The plotting thing might be changing default axis, but otherwise, yeah.
Should we run it?
Yeah, let's run the whole thing.
I'm curious to see.
And now let's see what people say.
Is there something we can do to improve these plots?
it look different? I guess, yes. So, it's... Yeah, it has a bit more data. But why does
the first one have... Oh, sorry. There is a 25 there as well. Okay. Yeah. So, it's very
hard from... So, okay. We don't have access labels. So, it's a bit hard to tell these
plots apart from each other if you just see one of them. And if we put them in a paper,
should have access labels yeah so where should we do that
in the plot function or in here
is the cell function only going to be used for temperatures and means in the
future or multiple things i would think so
it takes a temperatures and means mean argument
in making it too general might not be a good idea because then
we kind of end up just coding in the parameters instead of coding in the code.
But also we want to make it somewhat general.
So of course, in order to avoid side effects, the label should be set in the plot function
but also we can we can make the labels in the parameters oh one good suggestion
is to set the a global y-axis I'll set the same y-axis to each of these plots
so that we can directly compare them okay
So now we are how do I the X label needs a closing quotation mark okay how do you
actually so it's Y limit right is it PLD dot Y limit or do you need to get the
axis from the plot. ylim or set ylim let's see do we have a okay yes someone
says this so do I call it with zero and the upper limit yeah and first a lower
limit and the upper limit should I have a hard-coded upper limit or as an
argument it I think it should be an argument because it would depend on the
data but then we probably so we need to pass it as an argument okay we can do
that
should there be a default value yeah we're not something like 20 degrees or
oh wait this is yes okay mm-hmm but that means the lower value should be lower
yeah okay the lower value definitely shouldn't be zero because we're actually
always below zero yeah so what would you reckon well it should probably be
variable. I guess this also should be a variable. Minus 15 probably is a good default value here.
Okay, this is not maximation. This is max temperature.
Okay, so we have 20 minutes, so I think it would be good to move to the part where we
make this a script. Let's just try running it first, though.
Okay.
Yeah, okay, well.
Well, okay, now I'm a bit unsatisfied by the fact that the lower limit is not a parameter,
but the higher limit is.
Yeah.
They should both be parameters.
Should I reparse, pass them together as a...
Yeah, okay, like temperature range or Wylim I guess is good enough.
What was the lower one? Minus 20, minus 15.
It was minus 15, but minus... I mean, given what we know about the range actually, you can just pass the, yeah, you can just pass the tuple directly.
like you're just wilding oh well that also works uh like this it works yeah yeah okay i'll try it
yes okay okay and um for measurements from january i guess we probably don't need to go as far as plus
15 but um yeah i find it interesting that i know that this is a higher average temperature
Okay, but yeah, so we got it
Yeah, so okay. It works now. It does what we want. Um
Why would we want to move it to a script?
Well, I mean, I guess we'll have different input files
And yeah in jupyter I have to go actually edit it every time I change the value
Yeah, and
With the script, I can somehow, like, basically, we can make another script that will run this
with different parameters automatically.
Yeah.
And you can, so we can add parameters to the script that you can then from the command
line, you can pass parameters to the script and different temperature, different Y ranges
or different numbers of measurements and so on.
Okay, so to do that, do you want to move the command line or, well, yeah, should I, whatever
text editor you want to open, that's a.
Should I create a new Python file from Jupyter so I can make a text file and we can call
this.
I should give these names.
Temp analysis.py Descriptive name is good.
So one thing that happened when we were moving things in the functions is that we essentially
removed the comments and the function names became the comments and the same goes for
file names.
So a good file name is in itself a comment.
Makes sense.
So the first thing to do to make it a script is to copy everything that runs all the Python
code into the script and in the correct order.
Actually should I export it as something?
Yeah.
Okay, let's try that.
Is there an...
Save and export notebook as executable script.
Okay.
Okay, well, it downloaded it.
I'll go to the command line now, if that's okay.
Yeah.
New Terminal.
Let's see, can I move this down? Yes.
I saw it was called untitled one. So I'm using Linux command line commands here
to copy a file from the default download location to the current place and
and replacing the temp analysis script. I guess I should open it again.
Yes, I guess it didn't.
Yeah. Okay, here we go. Okay, so now there's some extra comments. The good thing is that there's a
comment in the beginning that actually is a useful thing to have. So that tells most
operating systems that this is a Python script so you could run it directly
without calling Python script name but yeah it's not 100% necessary but I mean
it's a nice thing to have, nice thing to know. Should I show that? Yeah, why not.
So we need to make it an executable so we need to change the permissions.
So this is a Linux command.
It says make this like chmod, change mode, and now I can run like this.
It doesn't work.
Does the graphical plotting even work?
I actually don't know.
It probably is actually stuck in the show statement.
So let's go to the plotting.
OK, it did open.
It popped it up.
OK.
And if I close it, it does another one.
And then another one.
So yeah, for the script, we probably
want to remove the plot.show line.
OK.
Or at least make it optional.
Let's make it a parameter so we can
add a parameter that says show plot or something like that.
and then if show plot, plot.show.
Maybe default it to false.
Yeah, yeah, default to false.
Okay.
One very good question.
How about version control?
We are pretty far with our code
and we haven't started using version control.
Should I start with that?
Yeah, let's start version control.
So git init and then I guess we'll commit the script
the script and why not the why not the notebook as well should I give the
notebook a better name first yeah really what should it be called why not temp
analysis temp analysis.ipy and b okay yeah
okay so there is a very good suggestion to include tests but since the previous lesson was tests
i think we will prioritize adding a command line interface
Another suggestion is to add a command line interface using "argparse".
Do you remember off the top of your head how to do that?
Because if not, I suggest we use "click" instead of "argparse".
So, I can do it with argparse.
I think I could do that off the top of my head.
but I'm new to Click, so maybe we should do that
and you can teach me something.
Okay, let's use Click.
So Click is built into Python 3,
at least most latest versions.
So you probably don't need to install anything.
You can just import Click at the top of the script.
We probably should remove the cell name comments as well.
That's not useful information.
So, yeah, click as it sounds.
And then at the bottom where we have this main section, we make that into a function.
Okay.
Should I call it main?
Yeah.
That makes sense.
usually the thing you run as a script in a Python script is often called main.
Now, to keep this as a script, though, we should add the standard Python boilerplate of
if __name__. That's without the...
On the left side, it's without quotation marks on the right side with. Okay. Then run main.
Okay, what does this do?
Okay, so if you are running this as a script, then the name will be main, otherwise it will
be the file name.
So if you're running this as a script, it will run the main function.
If you are just importing it, it will not run the main function, it will just define
all the functions that are in this file.
So this is useful if you think you might ever want to import the functions we have defined
here.
It's something you usually just do when you write a Python script, at least at some point.
So now we need to change the main function a little bit.
So what parameters should we add?
Let's do at least the number of measurements.
So the first thing we add though is we add a decorator above main that's at click.command
and parenthesis open and close.
And then below that at click.option.
And in the parenthesis, we need to first add the name of the option, the command and argument.
So it would be minus minus measurements or dash dash measurements or num measurements
maybe.
And then let's make it a required parameter.
So comma space required equals true.
Let's say type.
So another argument type equals int and at a help text.
So another parameter help equals
number of measurements to plot.
This though, this is not a list.
Now we're just plotting one number of measurements.
So remove the for loop.
Yeah, remove the for loop.
And now we need to add an argument to the main function
called num underscore measurements.
So the dash becomes an underscore.
Okay, that looks good.
So now it gets num measurements as a,
this function gets num measurements as an argument.
Oh, yeah, good catch.
Yeah. We can also add an input file. Oh, this is something we didn't do yet. So let's add
an input file parameter.
Okay. Could it be before or after numMeasurements?
Well, it should be after, but the order only needs to be the same as the order of arguments
in the function.
So let's call this in file of minus minus in file.
And then the required is true.
And the help text is something like file name or file
name for reading data.
OK, that makes sense.
OK, and we're going to remind people it's CSV.
But now, and now we need to add it as an argument.
So may needs to take in the file argument.
Before or after?
It should be after the number of measurements.
OK.
But now, we are not actually using this in getTemperature.
So let's pass it to getTemperatures.
Maybe the file name should be before,
or well, I guess it doesn't matter that much, but.
To my brain, before makes the most sense,
like most important.
Yeah, it's the, yeah, the most important
for first modifiers later.
Okay.
Okay, so then we go up,
look up to the get temperatures function
and add file name parameter.
And this has a different file name
or different name of the argument,
but I guess that doesn't matter.
Yeah, that doesn't matter.
Okay.
Should we add an output file argument as well?
And then try running it.
Okay, so I will save.
And actually we haven't run it yet.
Python.
Okay, now we have two required arguments.
So let's just see what happens
when we run without the required arguments.
So it tells you that number of measurements is missing,
and it also tells you that you can get
more information by writing dash-dash help.
Should I do dash-dash help?
Yeah. Let's do dash-dash help.
So that will print each possible argument
and the help text we have added to these arguments.
So we need to add a number of measurements,
which is an integer,
and we need to add an input file.
So how many measurements should we do?
Not 25. 25 is standard when we started.
And in file is...
What was the file name?
temperatures.csv
temperatures.csv, okay.
And it saves it to the standard 25.png still, right?
yes yes so we didn't add an output file argument so the output file is numberofmeasurements.png
which works for now but we could also make it an optional argument okay yeah so let's run this
and it should have created the plot file we have created them a number of times so well
six seconds ago. Okay, the other ones are older. So, yeah, it clearly worked. Yeah. Okay,
let's do an optional argument and give it a default value. So, it's almost the same
as the infile. Sorry. Does infile need the two dashes here? Can we make it a positional argument?
If it's always there.
I am not actually sure how you can or whether you can do that with click.
But I mean, there is usually a way of making using.
Yeah.
Creating positional arguments.
Let's try it and see.
So what's the other option?
We need to add a file.
Maybe this could be optional, equals, it's optional, right?
Yeah.
Required is false by default, you don't have to give it the required, but you can give
it the default value.
So it's not required, you probably should give it the default value.
But in this case, I guess the default should be none.
And then we can construct the filename from the number of measurements.
Okay.
Yeah.
Non-output filename default, or no, default, how do you do?
So then we need to check if outfile needs to be a parameter of the main function.
It should be the last parameter of the main function.
Do I need to set a default to none?
I don't think so.
I don't think it makes a difference.
Yeah.
OK.
So
should I try something here?
If.
If outfile is none, outfile
equals.
This thing based on the number of measurements.
Yeah.
and then we can use that out file and I guess I could do more complicated things
here like also include the input file name as one of the options and so on
yeah but well I mean I guess this is good enough yeah okay
save it and give it a try yeah let's do that okay so I come back to my
terminal. And now, if this works as I hope, since there's not the dashes here,
so there's two kinds of arguments. There's optional arguments that have dashes,
and traditionally they can be in any order. And there's positional arguments like this,
which have to be in a certain order, but you don't need to give the name of them.
So, oftentimes, the important arguments that are always required become positional, and
you give them by order, and optional ones, well, they're like that.
Should I try running?
Yeah, let's see.
Let's see if it works.
Default none.
Ah.
Okay.
Default equals none.
Syntax error.
There's a comma missing.
Yes.
No options name.
Okay, so I guess it has to be.
Dash dash file.
So it should be possible to have an option or maybe it's an argument then.
Could it be argument?
Well, let's see. Yes, it needs to be an argument.
So, it's a click.argument and then just a name for the argument, and it can be required.
Oh.
making an argument instead of option has probably failed somehow.
It might be that it needs to be before the options. I'm not sure.
Okay. Well, let's go back to option.
Yeah.
So we have to give it the infile. Let's see. What else?
So yeah, someone asks if the click.option lines need to match the order
in the function arguments. And yeah, that is how click works.
So it doesn't go by name.
They always need to be the same order. No, yeah, it doesn't go by name.
Okay.
Yeah, there we go. So it worked. I guess we don't need to look at the plot again.
But can we try saving to a different file name?
Yeah, let's try that.
And then I think it's time for a break.
Yes.
Because we have a couple of good questions and a few other things to do after the break.
How many can we plot?
Can we plot 500?
I don't know how many measurements there are in the file.
There are not 500 days in a year.
might fail well let's do 200 okay I'm gonna do it now I push enter and it
worked okay so there should be a new file with a name called 200 plot 200 and
yep it worked yeah it's probably not one measurement per day because otherwise
stay number 175 you wouldn't expect to go below minus 15.
Right, yeah, yeah.
So it would make sense to add more arguments and make the script more general, like adding
the option of giving three different numbers of measurements if we actually want these three
different plots in our paper, or just write another script that does that instead.
Yeah.
Okay.
But otherwise...
Yeah.
Let's go to the break end, I guess.
So there's a correction that says click is not in the Python default library.
I'm actually not 100% sure about this.
Maybe it's not.
I have the impression that it is in some of the latest versions of Python.
At least I generally don't install it, but maybe I just have it somewhere.
But it is good to include it as a dependency anyway.
So yeah.
Okay.
It's not a part of the standard library.
So yeah, it needs to be a dependency, which we'll do after the break.
Yes.
So see you at 12 past.
Sounds good. Bye.
Hello, we're back.
Hello.
Or so we hope.
So where were we now? We had just done this command line.
So, [name], for this command line thing, how is it better than making a notebook I can rerun?
Yeah, so one thing is that it could be a utility that you share to many people,
that people just install and can run without knowing any Python. But really for a lot of
people also a notebook is something that's easier to run than a command from the command line.
So that's actually a bit hard to say which one is better. So I added a question in the notes
actually. So please vote and give your opinions on what's actually better. Which one would you
rather get if someone's sharing a project with you. But the big upside in a command line interface
is that you can then use it to script an entire workflow from downloading the files
to producing the plots and maybe producing tables for your paper, plots for your paper.
Like you can go from raw data to a finished paper in a single command once you write the script.
Yeah. And I guess for the computing clusters and so on, that's very relevant, isn't it?
Yeah. Yeah, it is. Usually you don't get an interactive environment for command,
so you don't get a Jupyter notebook or a computing cluster.
This actually happens pretty often when people come to us. They have a Jupyter notebook and says,
says, I need to run this on the cluster for 10,000 different values.
And well, if it's a loop in a Jupyter notebook, you can only run it on one processor.
But once it is as a command line, it's really easy to write another interface, like whether
it's using state make or your own script or whatever that will go and run it 10,000 separate
times on 10,000 different computer processors and then combine them later.
Okay, so we have some time rather limited I think.
One thing we probably should do is move a bit closer to a package and also this is something
that also helps answer this question. So what I'm thinking of is taking the functions from
this file that could be used in a different project and turning them into a module that
you could share with other people. So one question is, do you think the plotting function
is too specific, or should we just include all of these three functions?
Should we pretend the plotting function is too specific and the other ones are the general
code?
So let's say the plotting function is something we wrote to have a uniform plotting thing
for a single project or for a paper, and the other two are something that could easily
be used in other projects as well. So let's take the first two functions and create a
new file or a new Python module.
Okay. So to the browser, new, new text file.
So this could be something like temperature utilities, that's pi.
And then we need to paste these functions here.
So these two get moved.
Yeah.
Does this need any other dependencies?
it does depend on no it's not doing any plotting does it it depends on only on
pandas I guess okay so that we need to import pandas is panda still needed here
I don't think so.
I will move it.
Okay.
And now what do I have to do?
Okay, so now we need to import the functions
from this temputils.
One way to do it without having to change any of the code below is to import
from TempUtils, but then this maybe depends a bit more on,
oh, sorry, this makes it a bit less readable
because now if you import specific functions
and then you're looking at the code below,
nothing about that function name
tells you that it came from TempUtils
and not from Pandas, for example, or Matplotlib.
So yeah.
So maybe import temputils.
And you can give it a shorter name if you want to.
But it's fine as it is.
And then when we call the functions,
it needs to be temputils dot something.
And compute statistics also.
OK.
Now it should work again.
And then for distributing this code,
one very important thing that we haven't done yet
is keeping track of dependencies.
So in our original notebook, we didn't really
have any way of doing that.
I mean, you can always create a requirements.txt file
and have a list.
So, okay, so how would you, let's think if this is a bigger project, let's imagine that
you have more than two files in the project that import things.
How would you figure out what the dependencies are?
Well, what I usually do.
What I usually do.
Yeah, what would you do?
You don't actually have to do it to show it, but what would you do?
So I'd make a new virtual environment with nothing installed in it.
I would try running my things.
I would see what fails with import errors.
I would add that to requirements.txt in the virtual environment and then repeat until
it's done.
That would be basically exactly my answer as well.
We would create an empty environment and then install packages until it works and put all
of those package names into requirements.txt.
But now we do know what we want, so we can just write a requirements.txt file for this
project.
Another way of doing it, of course, is you start a requirements.txt when you still can
track all the dependencies in your head when they are just in a couple of files and then
you write them down and when the project grows you keep adding stuff to the requirements.
Because it just pandas and click that's required. And matplotlib.plotlib.
How do you make sure that we got this correct and that it hasn't become
doesn't go off after a time.
Well, I mean, basically the same trick.
You create an empty environment, you install the stuff in requirements.txt, and then you
see if it runs.
But actually, since we just set up tests in the previous session, what our test workflow
on GitHub did is install all the requirements and then run the tests.
So if the tests succeed, clearly the requirements were sufficient.
So that means not only when we have the test, it's validating our code, it validates all
the requirements.
So if someone else wants to use the code, we can be reasonably sure that it has all
they need and there's not something obvious being left out of it.
Yeah, exactly.
So that's a great thing about these test workflows, because they don't run on your machine.
If the test succeeds, then it runs on at least two different machines.
It runs on your machine, but it also runs on this cloud system that's just installed
from scratch with only the dependencies you specified.
So that's a lot better than just running on one machine.
Yeah.
Okay.
So requirements.
I guess we already have the Conda environment, so there's  well, and we shouldn't be
too specific about how things are done in Python. We have another course for that, actually.
Yeah, so that's fine. So yeah, now we have specified the requirements and should be
installable by anyone. I mean, we don't really have a lot of time. We could just move to wrap up.
One option would be to add tests to
to all the functions we defined, but how complicated would that get? Yeah, compute statistics is
easier to test, we can just test that one.
One more thing that we touched on, but we didn't, I guess, quite finish. What do you
think about the function name compute statistics that's a bit general for what
it does yeah but it computes one specific statistic it it just computes
the mean yeah so maybe we should change it to compute mean yeah should I do it
or yeah yeah let's do that but that's that's these I was about to say last
step, that's the second to last step, then we commit the changes to git and give it a
nice name, or give it a nice commit message.
compute statistics, compute mean.
Now we probably did too many changes between commits, so we're going to have a big commit
that changes a lot of things.
Yeah.
Should I try running it to verify it works?
Yeah, yeah, let's do.
Okay. And you could also run PyTest on test and you need the name of the file.
So it's temputils.
Name error compute.
Ah, of course.
Yes.
So I forgot to rename it.
Compute.
I typed the name wrong.
Assert to, I did the test wrong.
Hey, it worked finally.
Great.
Okay.
Now, there were a bunch of things wrong with the test.
Now that it works,
are we sure that it's correct?
You shouldn't stop thinking if the test is right,
just because you get the correct result.
Yeah.
But yeah, I think the mean of 1, 2, and 3 is, in fact, 2.
That's correct.
So from the command line, I will git add temp analysis,
temp utils, requirements.
From before, we have learned git status to see what's missing.
We have the plots that are generated.
Should we make a gitignore file?
Maybe we can...
That kind of, well, that would eat up the time
of the, well, the wrap up and discussion.
But it's a useful thing to remind people of though.
Yeah.
Should we go to notes then?
Okay, yeah, let's go to notes.
And yeah, just please continue to have a conversation about it.
How could we still make this better?
What else would you do to in this project?
Did you think it was useful?
I thought of another benefit of the command line.
So let's say we send this analysis,
and it's some reasonably complicated thing, to someone,
and they want to run it on their own data.
It's easier for them to have this defined interface
that says, here's how you give the input file
and how you configure it,
than to have to go figure out your code,
modify it, and whatever.
If we run several different analysis, so let's say we have a different input file that we are testing,
then we don't have to modify our main code for every individual task,
and have to remember how to go back to the tasks we had before.
How similar is this to what you would do in your own work?
It depends a bit. Often I don't start from Jupyter.
I often start from scripts, but if there's a lot of plotting involved then I would start from Jupyter.
And then it would pretty much follow this workflow.
Yeah.
I think at some point, certain parts get complicated enough that they make more sense as a separate
utility module.
And then that might become a package of its own.
That's just the dependency of the script.
And yeah, if the end result is something other than displaying plots in Jupyter, then it
would become a script at some point or a command line interface.
But Jupyter is pretty good at displaying plots and running a relatively simple Python script.
So one option here would have been kind of to go back to Jupyter.
If you want to give this analysis to someone who finds Jupyter more comfortable than the
command line, then you could import this utility functions into Jupyter, import all the functions
needed into Jupyter, then just call them in the Jupyter notebook in a single cell, basically.
So we might have the Jupyter notebook that's used for development and testing and exploring
new data, in addition to the command line which runs known analysis on existing data.
Yeah.
Okay.
Um.
Hmm.
Okay.
Well, this is our time limit.