So any ideas?
And someone has reminded me, today is not completely the last day of Code Refinery.
It's the last day of streaming, but the teaching continues with the Bring Your Own Code sessions,
where you can, well, bring your stuff and you ask us questions and we look live at things
and give advice.
So from these icebreakers, what's the worst bug you've seen or experienced?
So anyone want to go first?
The ones that are resolved by restarting your computer.
The ones that you cannot pinpoint why they happen.
They just happen and then they are not there anymore.
And then you're like, okay, is this fine?
So I wrote down my answer, but it was a memory issue in the C code, which is always.
very hard to figure out.
But also at that time, I was not using either version control or tests, so just I was working
on something for a day and something else broke and I have no idea what's going on.
At least with C, I think that's a relatively common experience.
I had something similar once, and the only way I fixed it was by running the code in
a loop a thousand times, which would some sort of reliably cause an error message when
quitting, and then commenting out half my code until I could narrow it down to one
line.
I'm sure there's better ways, but that was what I knew how to do at the time.
Yeah, unfortunately, this was a problem where the code runs from the beginning to the end
and produces incorrect results, but also in a statistical way.
So you have to run it a bunch of times before you can notice that it's slightly off.
It really was the worst kind of problem.
Yeah.
So my worst bugs, or you could say maybe what's been worst to solve, has been things like
I'm editing some code, but that code isn't even running because the bug is somewhere
else.
Like once I made a, was it debugging or testing tutorial or something, and I had the same
code in my same code was in the file twice the same function was defined twice and people were
editing the first one and towards the second definition took precedence and it wasn't even
running and yeah there's another one um that i think is kind of a good lead-in
for today's topics. So this was that I wrote a measurement for a high-performance computing
program that we were spending millions of hours to run, like hundreds of thousands of euros worth
of computing time. And I wrote a measurement that calculates A, B, and C, and then it should
add A, B, and C together and print the result. I added B and C together and printed the result
instead and never printed A anywhere in the program. That wasted some time.
It's also one of those things that no matter how well you test A, it's not going to help.
Properly testing the program before starting to run it would have been
and very helpful.
Yeah.
So, how do you make sure your code continues to work
when collaborating with others?
Like, if it works one day, how does it work tomorrow?
Have you ever had these kind of bugs where something worked, it was nicely tested, but then it got changed and broke, and then everything...
I guess that memory issue in C is one of these things, you can easily break something in
a completely different place of the code.
also just manually running it and printing some variables values brings me quite far.
And I guess that's quite often the starting point of testing,
manually looking at prints. I guess as a spoiler alert, we're going to talk about exactly this
kind of stuff today, and you'll see what we tend to do these days because it's best practice.
So I didn't see a good suggestion for what to say. Someone suggested
Sally Scripps' sleek software solution swiftly, but we need something quick and easy to say,
not that we're gonna trip us up. What if we say fair software? So me, [name], [name],
I'll repeat fair software. Fair software. Fair software. Fair software. Fair software. Fair
software. Fair software. Okay, is it balanced? To me, [name] might have been a little bit louder
than [name].
But I'm only here for a very short time, so it's better that you are balanced.
But it's 10.
Should we start with Jingle?
Yeah.
Okay.
Let's go.
Hello.
Welcome.
Hello. Welcome. And we have [name] for the introduction.
Already here. Okay. Yeah. Hello. And very welcome to this last day of streaming of the Code Refinery workshop.
So we are in the last day of the teaching sessions of this workshop,
and yesterday we looked at documentation and Jupyter and saw some demos.
Today, this goes on and it basically wraps everything up.
So everything comes together again in today's sessions.
Now in the morning, we have a session about automated testing.
So really putting all the Git and GitHub things together,
and implement tests that can check
your code when you are collaborating with others or working by yourself.
Then in the afternoon,
we will have a session on modular code development,
which is a live coding session where we take a code that is right now
in Jupyter and plot something,
and then show live how to make this more modular
so that it can be more easily reused
by you and others in the future.
And this is highly interactive,
so we are kind of dependent a little bit on you there
to give us hints in what to do with the codes
in the collaborative document,
and I'll show in a moment how to do that.
But also, please stay until the end because we will tell you a little bit about what can
come after this Code Refinery workshop and also talk a little bit more about our Bring
Your Own Code sessions, which you might have seen in the schedule already for next week
and the week after, Tuesday afternoon.
So if you're new here, if you're joining us today for the first time, this is a live-streamed
workshop so everyone will watch the live stream here on Twitch and then you can interact with
the instructors and with some people behind the scenes also via our collaborative document.
For that you need to register to this workshop via the Code Refinery web page and then you will
get the link to this document which looks something like this. So here we have some
information for you where you can find all the questions and answers, the workshop web page,
the schedule and the link to the lesson materials and then we also have some icebreaker question
for this morning and the way you can add your answers there is to find this little pen symbol
which might be here or somewhere to the right depending on how you're looking at this page.
So you click the pen symbol,
you switch into edit mode,
and then you can scroll down here to the questions,
what's the worst bug you have seen or experienced,
and then find these little three dot lines
here and add your own answer to the question,
and the same for the next ones that we have here.
And then we will have titles here about each section and underneath here you can ask your question.
Is this the place to ask questions? And then hopefully someone will answer. Yes, there's someone answering.
And we will provide these documents after the course. You can find them on the course web page.
course webpage so you can go back and see what have others asked, what may help
your understanding. We'll also have breaks about 10 minutes every hour and
all the lesson materials that you might see during this day are available and
linked from the workshop page and they will also be available afterwards and
And you can also reuse them to do your own workshops, for example.
The recordings will stay online on Twitch for some days, and then they will also be
available approximately tomorrow or today on the YouTube channel.
If you're interested in certificates, you can find instructions on that also on the
workshop page.
Maybe I can show that briefly.
there's up here this certificates tab where you can find this and all the materials are linked here
behind the schedule. And then yeah the bring your own code sessions we'll talk about
a little bit about this more in the end of today. And now over to our instructors for today
[name] and [name]. Great, thanks [name].
Okay, I will take over the screen share.