the intro. So, welcome to Introduction to Scientific Computing and HPC. Very briefly,
what is this course about? Well, it's structured over three days and we kind of gradually build
on the skills, on the basic skills that are needed for basically scaling up your computations. So,
in Finland, and also for those of you who are not in Finland, most likely you
have access to an high-performance computing cluster, which basically means lots and lots
of servers connected by a very fast network so that they can run lots of computations.
And it might well be that you don't need thousands of servers connected in parallel,
but what is useful is that you can just request one for yourself, do your work in a secure way,
and then happily, you know, continue with publishing paper and things like that.
So who is attending this workshop, this course? Well, there's multiple people
from multiple universities. We are very happy that today with us, beyond Aalto
University, there's also Helsinki University and Oulu University, but in general we
span across borders. We have people from all over the Nordics, Europe and even
beyond so the practicalities this is not your typical kind of zoom workshop or
zoom course where we are all in the in the same zoom here we use this type of
live stream strategy which you can understand that it's very useful because
this is like a TV studio and we're like all watching the TV together and by
doing this we can make sure that we can provide immediately high quality
recordings of all the training that we have today and more broadly you will later see
that everything is to be stored in our YouTube channel so that you can re-watch something
that we're going to mention in these days but also sometimes we don't cover things that
we have already covered well in the past and so there's more videos that we will refer
to.
The communication with the instructors happens through this type of asynchronous chat and
you can understand already that this is much better than something like the Zoom chat which
makes it impossible to communicate with this type of shared document that we are all editing.
Right now there's 105 people editing it in parallel.
You can basically ask questions and then maybe some of you could answer or one of the helpers
can answer and so on. At the end this document basically forms a nice diary of the whole
day which will then archive and you can later go back to it and check it. As you might have
already tested this once you open the link that you have received in your registration
email there's a pencil at the top, the screenshot there is showing that. By clicking on the
pencil basically you enter the edit mode and then you're able to add the text
where you need to add it. The share document is powerful but of course if
there's hundreds of people editing in parallel it can be you know challenging
even to just type so if you're if you know that you don't need to write
anything you can switch back to the view mode by clicking that eye icon so that
you know the load of the service is is smaller and other people can write freely
Right. So where do we focus or where to focus because you can understand that there's different windows and
In general focus on the on the streaming on the twitch TV window
We provide this type of vertical
layout so that, as you can see in the picture there,
you can kind of keep the Twitch window
on one side of your laptop screen, for example,
and then you can keep, let's say,
this notes document in another browser window
or your terminal.
We would use a lot the terminal
to connect to the remote cluster.
Of course, if you have multiple screens,
then you don't have these issues,
but we are thinking for those of you
who are working with a laptop
so that they have enough desktop space to arrange all the windows together.
Maybe one thing that I did not mention when it comes to Twitch.tv streaming,
it is important that you set the bandwidth to basically source,
which means the same bandwidth of the original broadcasting stream.
Otherwise, Twitch will do some sort of compression,
and so things will start to get blurry.
but if you make it so that the bandwidth
is basically the maximum available,
you will see the stream.
All right, anything else that we are missing?
Yeah, maybe on the learning styles
that there's many learning styles.
I think in general, we've been running this
kind of new way of online teaching for a few years.
We really like the fact that it can happen
at everybody's, at anyone's pace.
Those who want to learn live with us,
they can watch right now.
Some others might learn later.
And when we chat with our previous course participants,
some people find this also useful months after,
so they can go back to the stream,
watching the videos, checking the notes document.
In general, to conclude,
when it comes to the community and to good rules,
let's just try to be respectful.
At Aalto, we have our code of conduct
any universities we have a good code of conduct. If you see some inappropriate
behavior just let us know and we can do the best to kind of you know compensate
for that or make sure that it doesn't happen. There's few things that could go
wrong but usually they don't get wrong. In general if you feel that there's too
much information coming in too short time it's totally normal especially if
it's the first time that you work with this type of HPC systems but this is why
it's it's it's great to have everything recorded and you can later you know
rewatch at your own pace if the notes are too fast to follow don't worry you
don't need to follow the notes you don't need to you know we basically will
highlight some important notes on the on the stream and then again later you can
always go back to the notes and have a look.
I already mentioned this that sometimes if there's too many people editing at the same
time the notes document might feel slow so please switch to the view mode and we won't
have time to cover everything so some of the materials that are linked in our main page
course page are actually videos from previous rounds of this course or there's other videos
for example this kitchen metaphor to HPC, in general we encourage you to, you know,
explore all the materials we have and what we will show here in these 10 hours together is kind of,
you know, a small or a large subset of all the materials. What else? Well, we try not to deviate
from the schedule but you know things happen and when it comes to possible technical issues
it has happened only once that the whole internet collapsed during the streaming hopefully
the internet will be up again but eventually if something goes wrong just wait a little bit and
the stream might come back or then you will receive another email from me saying that
I don't know, we could have a plan B. All right, well I guess maybe the most
important thing is to mention that the cat, [name]'s cat, will visit the stream.
I think it's too early now. Is the cat still sleeping, [name]?
Yeah, it's in the room but sleeping. It's usually later in the afternoon,
so motivation to stay to the end.
Exactly. All right, well, final notes. Everything is recorded. Credits I think
already wrote in the notes that for this course specifically we don't give credits
and at the very bottom there's a link to our mailing list and for those of you who have ticked
in the registration that you would like to hear about future courses you will be added to this
mailing list and now it's exactly 10 past 10 so I'm happy to pass the ball back to [name]