Hello. Hello. Hello. We're back. Yeah. So yeah. Yeah, that's like the recovered. Yeah,
that's the like the like the shortest Linux terminal crash course ever. So it's like,
Yeah, it can be a bit like, okay, what is happening here, like kind of a situation.
But it gets better once you get accustomed to it.
But if you still have problems with it, don't hesitate to put the stuff into the notes,
because we'll be using that example as a stepping stone for the next things.
So do check that if you can run the code that we put there.
There's an example solution now.
Sorry about not having an example solution ready.
We are moving some of the materials around.
But now there's an example solution there in the notes.
So you can try it out if you had problems.
Yeah, over here.
Okay. Here, I guess.
Yes, you can try that one out if you still haven't managed to.
Yeah.
But don't worry about this too much. Don't worry about if this seems quite complicated.
The idea is that you will get more accustomed to the terminal once we start writing the
scripts and everything like that and we start using the terminal more and more. But now,
should we move towards like, we've been talking about the terminal, how to use the terminal
and where's the HPC, where is the computing stuff? But this is needed for us to be able to
actually do the HPC stuff. So, [name], maybe we should talk about the next step,
which is the queuing system. So, let's view again our cluster here. So, what is the queue?
Yeah. Actually, you know, I could grab my demo materials from one of the HPC kitchen
videos and go and give a live demo here, but I'm not prepared for that.
that. So let's see. In short, when you have hundreds of computers and thousands or hundreds
of thousands or millions of processors available, how do you know what each person can use and
for how long? So Slurm is the thing that takes all the requests. So you might say, I have
this job where I want 10 processors and 200 gigabytes
of memory, and it will find the resources
and tell you where you can run it.
Or someone might come and say, I need between 1,000
and 1 million processors with 4 gigabytes of memory
per processor, and it will find what's available,
wait for them to be there, and then give them to you
and let your thing run.
All in the background without you having to be there
and wait for it to happen.
Yeah, and the queue manager is called Slurm.
So whenever we are talking about Slurm,
the name sounds strange and it is, but that's what it is.
But whenever we're talking about Slurm,
we mean the queue manager.
And many clusters or some clusters
use different queue managers,
but at least here in Finland,
I think everybody's using Slurm.
CSC is using Slurm, we're using Slurm.
It just rolls out of your tongue once you get used to the word, but once you know how
to reserve resources with Slurm, you can use it in various other clusters as well.
So once you know the parameters that the Slurm takes, you can get resources.
So if we look at the picture, we can see that most of the time we are spending our time
in the login node, or maybe you have reserved like an interactive session with the on-demand,
but anyways, you're in some interactive session and you want to run the stuff in the actual
like CPU nodes in the other computers.
So should we now check how can you reserve those resources?
Yeah.
Oh, actually, can you scroll down?
I think there's a nice picture here that shows
the box that's scheduled.
There, yeah.
So whenever you are scheduling a job,
it's basically a rectangle that the number of CPUs,
the amount of memory, and the time.
And then optionally, you can throw
in some number of GPUs there.
So that's the kind of thing.
So we need to define what these boxes are.
And usually, the good way of starting to approximate the boxes is compare them to your own computer.
So if your computer has four CPUs, you might want to request four CPUs.
If your computer has 16 gigabytes of memory or 8 gigabytes of memory, you might take the
same one.
And if you have, if you put outcome rounds on your laptop for an hour, you might want
to request something like two hours.
So you have this kind of like size of what is your job?
What does it need for it to run?
And then you can estimate the first guess, what is the size of the job?
then you can refine the guess later on.
Yeah.
So, [name], what happens when you tell Slurm these requests?
What does it do?
So you tell it a request and it first, you tell it what the
requests are and then the batch scripts.
So basically what will be run and then it adds it to a database
of everything that's requested.
and then it stores it,
it sorts it by priority.
Most clusters, actually,
isn't most clusters in Finland and the world now,
use something called fairshare.
So basically, it's not
a strict queue where the first person to submit something goes first.
Instead, it takes all the requests,
and the more you run,
the lower your priority goes.
so that it sort of tries to balance it out
so everyone gets about the same amount of stuff.
So it's something like CSC, where
there's a limited number of billing units
that might take that into account.
But at least in our university, it's
designed to be relatively equal.
And if we check the resources, so we already
mentioned that there's the time memory, CPUs and GPUs.
And for each of these, there's usually
some arguments or parameters that are listed over here.
We'll go through them when we are actually
going to be submitting the jobs.
But you can always come back and reference, let's say,
this page or the relevant tutorial pages
to figure out what were the magic flags that Slurm needed
to know about these resources.
Yeah, there's also on some other clusters, there's other parameters you might need to tell,
like for example in CSC you need to tell which account you're using, like which is the
one who will be built, and in some cases you need to also give partitions. So often
the cluster, if you look at the cluster here, the cluster is split into different partitions based
on what sort of job they need to be running or what sort of architecture they have.
For example, the GPU nodes are often separated into their own partitions.
So sometimes you need to give this information as well when you're submitting a job.
So in these cases, please refer to your own clusters, documentation, what magic flags you
you need to add in order to get the job running on the compute
nodes.
Usually it's like partition and then the name of a partition.
Yeah.
Is there anything else here, or should we
go on to the examples?
I think probably, yeah, I would say,
do we have anything in the chat?
Any good questions?
No, nothing we need to.
There is one question, how to decide how many resources
to allocate for the job.
And actually, yeah, maybe we can briefly mention that.
Yeah.
So you made a page on this once.
Yes, yes.
There's like a, you can check, there's
this quick guide on the job size, like what is the program size.
Yeah, and you can check that and basically, it's like I said, you can often compare it
to your own computer, like what are the resources over there.
And often you can use the, let's say, if you don't know if your program uses multiple processors,
you can run it on your own computer and check the process manager in your machine.
There's hints in the guide, like you can check how many processes are being used by the program
and then determine from that how big is the program.
But what you usually give these resources, you don't want to give exactly the limit what the program uses.
want to give it a bit leeway so that it doesn't get throttled or anything like that. So basically,
if your program uses one CPU, then you usually want to have it one CPU. If it uses like eight
gigabytes of memory, you might want to give it like 10, just to have a bit of option of going
a bit over. And if it takes like an hour, you usually give it like hour and a half. So you
you give it a bit leeway that if it runs slower this day,
then it will still finish.
And usually it goes like you first guess some number,
if it crashes, like if it is too small,
then you just increase the number.
If it's too big,
we will talk about job monitoring tomorrow.
So we will talk about how you can get the numbers out
after the job has run,
like how much it actually used,
and then you can like limit it.
And you usually want the submission
to be quite close to the size of the box
because then the queue knows that, OK, this
is the amount of things needed by the job.
So you can fit it best into the queue.
So then you won't get a bad priority
because the job you're requesting
more than you actually use.
But should we start running?
Let's go on.
OK.