Bye.
OK, so now about connecting to a cluster.
Essentially, there are many, many different ways
how you connect, how you can connect.
and it also depends a bit on what cluster you're trying to connect to, what things are being
offered. We are mainly focusing here on the options that we give at Aalto, so with Triton,
but most of them are also applicable for other HPC systems. The traditional way to connect
to a cluster is essentially SSH. You have a command line tool, be that Windows command
line, Windows PowerShell, the WSL, Windows Subsystem for Linux on a Windows machine or
on any terminal on a Linux or Mac machine, and using the SSH command, which is just secure
a shell which lets you connect to a cluster.
Maybe we can just show that quickly.
Yep.
I've opened a Windows command prompt.
Let me see, you should be able to see it.
So it's SSH and there will be.
Your username?
triton.aalto.fi, in the case of Triton.
In the case of Triton or in the case of Aalto, you need to be connected to the virtual private
network or have SSH keys set up, but for this demo, [name], it's connected to the VPN?
Yep.
And then, where am I here now?
It says Login4.
Where is this on the cluster?
So essentially, what you get to when you connect to a cluster is not one of the compute machines.
It's normally a login node, which is kind of a control node where you submit jobs, where
you send jobs to the cluster, which will be discussed about later.
important thing to know about this is that this logger node is not a place
where you should actually run computations because on most systems
your resources that you can use on the logger node are restricted and if they
are in use you might really get problems actually connecting again to the cluster
because if the let's say 10 gigabytes of memory or so that you are allocated and
the two CPUs are in full use by some Python computation process even your
terminals might start to become really sluggish or not react at all
because you don't have more resources on this machine because it's a shared
resource and everyone should be should be able to work on there without the risk of someone saying
okay I'm just running a computation here and slowing it down for everyone. So this is just
the place where you connect to and where you start then distributing the work and we can also
maybe quickly show this via OnDemand. OnDemand is a service that also
many HPC systems nowadays provide and it's essentially a web interface to the cluster.
On Triton, it's ondemand.triton.aalto.fi.
So then, when I open this.
And commonly, you can get a shell access there, you can get a desktop access.
And there's one big difference here.
If you want the shell, if you get shell access on Triton, this is, again, just a shell, so
a command line for the login node.
Essentially, exactly the same as what we
had with the terminal connection earlier.
But if you would request a desktop session,
that's commonly a job that is actually
running on one of the compute nodes.
So that's, if you request a desktop or interactive graphical session, that is normally
some type of job on the node where you can also then run computations and similar things in a
user interface way. Which is why you need to define the resources that you want there.
And then you maybe need to wait a little while. Yeah. Another important note here is that
very often these interactive resources are rather limited.
And the reason for that is that
interactive resources on tendency are kind of inefficient
in the sense that
you are very often sitting in front of this and thinking.
And that means the whole time you're thinking about something,
the computational power of whatever you requested
is idling on tendency.
If it's currently running something, then that's fine, but very often
it's just idling. For heavy
computation jobs, you normally need to go through
the queue system and submit jobs that are explicitly
just running one thing. It's also this UI and the
whole user interface thing, of course, takes resources.
So you are essentially spending some resources
just to have this UI.
And if you want to have an as efficient job as possible,
getting rid of that overhead is definitely beneficial.
So it's actually not good for what the cluster's made for,
namely running big computations.
But if you have results on the cluster
that you want to just quickly check,
you use it as one way to have a graphical user interface
to look at the figures or something that would be produced.
And that's well connected to the cluster
in contrast to trying to mount this remotely
where network connections might be slower and so on.
Yes, and it's available also from outside.
So you don't have to be on the VPN or close by.
Yeah, there's one last way
that we want to quickly show
because it has become quite popular recently
and that's VSCode.
VSCode has a couple of features,
mainly one extension that's called the Remote SSH plugin.
So I look for remote SSH like this.
SSH like this, there it is, and I can install it.
With that plugin, you can essentially do an SSH connection almost the same way as you
would do it with the shell.
When you have installed this, you will see this remote explorer icon.
You can then either add or [name] already has it added.
So you can add it by clicking the plus on this H to tell new remote or if you already
have one, you can go on that and essentially indicate location.
If you wanted to add, you would add this, like the same command at Triton.
And why we want to show the VS Code in particular is there are a few issues with VS Code.
It can be a great tool, but if you connect to a cluster with VS Code, on general principle,
never open a folder or never connect opening a folder that has lots and lots of files in
there.
Open things that actually have code and not data.
And also don't open, for example, your home folder.
And the reason for this is that if you would do that, VS Code tries to index files that
are in the folder, and it does this for all files in the folder, which means that it will
constantly ask, has this file changed, has this file changed?
And if you do this for a folder that has a lot of files in there, you are essentially
starting to run a small denial-of-service attack on the file system servers that are
around on the cluster.
Please don't do that.
So that's why we want to mention here that, yeah, use the subfolder that actually has your
code to connect to it and use it like that.
One more thing with VS Code,
in general, try not to run VS Code Jupyter Notebooks.
Because VS Code, essentially,
when you use this remote SSH plugin,
it starts a VS Code server on the other side.
If you have Jupyter Notebooks open on the other side,
that is not being closed, that is not being shut down when you disconnect.
The server will keep running.
And that means if you have computations done in that Jupyter Notebook,
you still have this running and you're running this on the logger node.
So, when you use VS Code, try not to use Jupyter Notebooks interactively.
So, is it that I shouldn't even open this ipynb file?
That I think depends a little bit on the plugins that you actually have installed.
But I personally wouldn't edit Jupyter Notebooks on VS Code with the remote SSH plugin.
You can potentially run VS Code on a cluster node and do things like that, but I wouldn't
do it on the remote SSH.
But with that, I think we will stop here to leave enough time for questions, for individual
questions if things don't work during connection, so that we can get as many of you as possible
it on the cluster and connect it to the cluster. People from Aalto or Helsinki should all have
a link to Zoom where we can help with connecting to their respective clusters. I think we will
to pause the stream here now till 11 finish time.
Or is it no?
Wait.
Yeah, essentially till 11 Finnish time
and allow people to try to get connected to the cluster.
OK, so yeah, we're going to the break time.
So yeah, so this is the first exercise time.
So we will mute the stream.
We will go to the notes here.
You see there's lots of questions
that have been asked about this.
We'll put in the bottom a little thing that says what
you should be doing right now.
So yes, there are lots of things that can go wrong here. Don't worry. Don't be afraid.
You can keep asking questions here. If you're in Finland, we have a Zoom that you can join,
and we have breakout rooms for some universities there, and you can ask for live help. And
remember, if you don't have time before the next presentation starts, there's still two hours until
we actually start doing stuff on the cluster. So you can keep asking questions in the notes
during the time. We'll try to figure out what can happen. If you're at Aalto you can send us
emails to the addresses and we can look because you shouldn't be adding your usernames to this
document. Yeah, and good luck! Now you have time to read stuff. Okay, talk to you later then. Bye!
Let's see, hello, hopefully you can hear me out there.
So now we're going to a break pretty quickly.
So if you look at the notes here,
you see there's many questions happening.
So that just goes to show how hard it
can be to even get connected to the cluster.
So I wouldn't say it's necessarily hard,
just there's so many different things for everyone. Where you are, what university you are,
how you're trying to connect, how your computer is set up, is your account new or old, and so on.
So, like we said before, if you can't do it now, it's okay. You're welcome to keep watching the
course. Next, we have a demo of the cluster after a short break. A demo of a cluster from CSC,
see. So you still have more time to work on this. What else? Yeah. And you notice here
in the notes, there's this little poll here. So you can add an O to done if you finished.
If you couldn't get connected, then you could put an O under trying connected and an O under
not trying if you weren't even trying, and that way we can sort of see what the status is.
Yeah, overall, basically, don't worry. If this seems hard, it's one of the hardest parts,
unfortunately, and just keep coming back. Don't worry. And with that, see you in 10 minutes
for the next session, bye.