Yeah, first focus on this one.
Yeah.
So should we advance and do the batch job now?
I think that's what was next in the notes.
Yes, if you didn't.
Yeah.
So let's do a batch job for this one.
Yes.
So now in the batch job, we introduce you
to what's called a slurm script or shell script.
So this is the first time we're going
make a new file on the cluster and in this file we will put the instructions to slurm to say what
resources are needed and the instructions to our code to tell it what to run and it will all look
quite familiar with what we've done so far. So to edit a file on the cluster we'll use the
editor named nano so it's a really basic editor it's not fancy at all but it's simple to use it
It tells you how to quit it from within the editor.
And from what we can tell, it's on every cluster.
So it's a good starting point.
So we're calling the new shell scripts count1grams.sh,
where the .sh means it's a shell script.
So [name] pushes Enter, and Nano opens.
So the shell scripts always start
with what we call a shabanglang for like hash bang
with bang being exclamation mark.
And it tells it this will be a bash script.
So bin bash, bash is the shell that we're using.
So it's the-
And this is basically like the kind of magic
that is like, like you will always just write this.
Like how often, like when you start writing these scripts
you often get into the automation
that you will always write the shabang this.
You can use different ones
But usually, it's easier to just.
It's like some magic words.
You open the, you're making a magic spell.
You give the standard magic words at the beginning.
And it's something that you copy from the cheat sheet
every time you do it.
So now we see the comment symbol and sbatch here.
So this sbatch is an instruction for Slurm
to read and do something here.
And now we add the same options we did from the command line.
So for example, we'll tell it that it needs memory one
gigabyte and sbatch time equals 10 minutes.
And we could add whatever else here.
OK.
And should we add then the thing that we want to run?
Yeah, so now we get to the actual shell.
And we'll enter basically the same thing
we typed ourselves there.
So ngrams count.py, words, and then Gutenberg fiction.
Actually, do you know the file name of the thing?
Yeah, it's below there, down there.
Yeah, you can copy from the note down below.
Should we try to do two grams, actually, like now that I think of it, should we do two grams?
Yeah.
So, if we add here, what's it does in, we can get two grams, I think.
Yes, dash lowercase n.
So, now we count word pairs, right?
Like how many word pairs we can get.
So let's save this file.
And actually.
And saving with Control-X and then pushing Y.
Yeah.
And actually, I'll rename it to 2grams.sh.
That's so now it's save under a different name.
Yes.
It's a better name for the file.
So.
OK.
And now we actually do the running.
So this is it.
We run the command sbatch, and we give it the script file.
And with luck, there won't be any errors,
and it will start running.
Yeah.
I'll try to be fast here.
So [name] will push, enter, and immediately run slurm history.
No, it already finished.
Actually, maybe slurm queue.
Yeah.
So now this is sort of a wide thing here.
And maybe I'll push it.
Yeah.
So there's several key Slurm commands
that you will need to know.
One, well, actually, so this Slurm
is only available on our cluster.
So on other clusters.
I think it's also on some other clusters.
But it's not part of the Slurm installation,
but it's present in many clusters.
Yeah.
I'm writing some stuff in the notes here.
So sbatch.
But you can, there's other commands like squeue.
Yeah.
You can use as well.
But OK, so what's the general thing?
We basically, we made our food order
and we handed it off to the manager, so the Slurm.
And now Slurm has a queue of everything there.
And when you type Slurm queue, that tells you what's queued.
And we see the second command.
Now it's done running.
So we can type the command Slurm history
and see the status of how it ran.
So Slurm history needs to be 8 by 12.
It's OK if it scrolls off the screen some.
Yeah, that's good.
So we see here in the history, there's
three jobs with IDs that end in 10, 43, and 30.
So it tells us the job name.
And we see for the last one, it's count2grams.sh.
So that's the file name we submitted.
When it started running, it said it
requested one gigabyte of memory.
And it used 602 megabytes of memory.
So 2 grams took a lot more memory
to compute than 1 grams.
That's good to know.
It says it took 22 seconds of CPU time.
And towards the end, we see the state
is COMP, which means completed.
Yeah.
And at the end we can also see what was the name of the computer, like the nodes where it ran.
So you can see that some of these other programs run on this pe78 and this run on pe8. This is not
usually important unless you run into problems or something and then if the computer breaks or
something and you need to contact us that hey my code didn't work but usually like
the queue manager can decide which computer can fill your things fill your requests and it will
decide the best computer to run it on yeah um yeah and that's basically it so with this
as you learn more and more shell scripting, or not, if you don't need much more, you can start
making these programs that will do more and more for what you do. Yes, and also an important thing
with the script, when we now run the stuff, we run it non-interactively. So when we submitted
the job, but we immediately didn't see any output or anything. What good is that if I don't see
anything? The reason is that Slurm will divert the output to files. If we look at the count
n-grams again, over here we have the output of the Python code itself, or the count.py.
We use this to divert the output of the counting program to this file, but Slurm will also
record everything that the program prints out, and that will be saved into an output
file.
You can change the name of this output file as well, but the default is that its name
is slurm, then dash, and then the job ID.
So the job that we run, the job ID discount n-grams, we get an output file out of here.
So we can later use pager less to view what was the output over here.
So we can see that this is what the code program printed.
So it's the same as we would have run it interactively.
We get the output over there.
So often in your program, you might have program write some output into the disk, but you also
want to print out, okay, what it is doing and if it's encountering problems and whatever.
And you can later see them in these output files.
Yeah.
Okay.
Should we give people time to work themselves now?
Yes.
Let's see.
I will info add.
When should we come back?
we come back five minutes before the end time,
and we can briefly wrap up.
Yes. I will add, yeah.
It may be a little bit short on time to do this,
but if so, it's okay.
The course will be over and then you'll have
time to work on it yourself before tomorrow.
We'll keep answering questions afterwards.
And did we mention how in the Slurm history command,
it showed what Slurm tracked as the resource usage, which is?
We can talk about it tomorrow in the monitoring.
Right, yeah.
While we're talking about the other monitoring as well.
Yeah.
And I guess we will, in the notes,
will add the commands that we ran,
so that way you can copy from there.
Yeah.
OK.
Well, good luck.
See you in about 20 minutes.
And yeah, have fun, and be happy with your first Slurm jobs.
This is an important day for you.
Maybe I shouldn't be so philosophical.
Okay, see you later then.
Okay, bye.
Hello and welcome back.
So sure, a lot has happened here in these notes.
In the bottom, there's a place you can respond if you finished the things. That would be good
to figure out. Also, we've started adding some feedback at the bottom. So, just like before,
this is a poll. You can add the O's in order to say if it's too fast, slow, basic, advanced,
whatever, and any other feedback for us. So I had several things from the questions I'd like to
bring up, but it might take a bit too long to go and actually find them through the material,
so I'll just say it. First, one important thing to note, once you have the batch script file to
run things, now your work is reproducible. So if you save the batch scripts that you run
and you come back in a month or six months or a year and need to run the same things again,
you can basically figure out what arguments you gave and how things should work. And that's really
important and shouldn't be underestimated. When you're doing this scientific work,
you have to remember things for a long period of time. And if, for example, a year from now,
you have to try to do something again for paper revisions or to verify the work,
having these batch grips will help you quite a lot.
Next up, many of the clusters are different. So we saw something down here, for example,
on the CSC computers, you need to specify the account and partition for every job you run.
So on some clusters, it sort of automatically does it because the time isn't tracked by project.
So this is another case where you need to find the reference for the cluster you're using and then
well, you know, copy that and translate it to what your work is doing now.
Next up, there was some point a question about the output files.
else. Where does it save the output? Okay. Maybe like this here. So there's different
types of output that a script can have. One is the output files that the code itself makes.
And the second is what the code is printing to the screen, which is what in the Unix world
is called standard output or standard error.
And this standard output and standard error
gets captured by Slurm and then saved
to a file for your reference.
So basically, there's two kinds of things that happen.
So your program runs, it saves the main results,
and then the information about how the program itself ran.
And usually, it's the second one that you
would look at to figure out what happened
if it didn't work correctly.
So, yeah, these dot out files like this are very,
okay, I can't select,
very important to look at when things go wrong.
And even when things go right,
just to make sure that it's going right the way you expect.
Yeah, and maybe we didn't emphasize enough
in the, when we wanted to get to the exercise
as quickly as possible,
why are we even doing this script?
So the important part is that you want to program to the computer what you want it to do.
You want to tell it what to do. And in the case of Slurm, you want to tell the Slurm that, hey,
I want you to do this thing for me, and I want you to give me the resources and do it somewhere
when I'm not watching. Basically, in the kitchen metaphor, you're just asking
basically you're ordering food from a restaurant, like you want somebody else to prepare it
to you at a later date and you will get it done later. So you want to be able to tell
the instructions to the computer in a way that it understands what commands it should run
when it goes to the compute node. And the output is basically the way that you can then monitor
what it actually did. So in your code, you can have print statements and stuff like that,
that will tell, okay, I am now doing this, I'm doing that. And especially if you're running a
job in the queue, you might want to monitor what it is doing. But if you submit it to the queue,
you don't have an interactive session there, which is a benefit because you can then close
a laptop and closer connection, nothing will break. It will run remotely there, but you want
to monitor the output and that's why you have the output files. Yeah, okay. And the last one I wanted
to note, which can I find it from here, is the difference between sbatch and srun and bash directly.
So sbatch will take a script file and hand it off to slurm to run it sometime later non-interactively.
srun when used directly from the command line will try to run something through slurm but right now
attached to your terminal and it doesn't read the different sbatch comments that are inside of a
shell script. And finally if you run something with bash only it doesn't know anything about
slurm and will just run it where you are directly. So this is something that
well you don't have time to go much more into depth than this now but if you read a little
bit more, you'll see us discuss this a bit more in the notes. Also, I mean, we're out of time now,
and there is, like, this was very fast. Like we said at the beginning, it's impossible to give
a course that will teach you everything about the cluster, about Linux, about the shell,
about version control, about the data storage within 10 hours.
So we aren't even trying to do that.
Instead, we're trying to give the broad overview
and show some demos and have good materials for you
to follow up on just the parts you need later.
Because also, everyone needs different parts
for their own work in the future.
So not everyone can sit through weeks of courses
to learn all the details.
So don't feel overwhelmed if it's overwhelming. I mean, yes, it is overwhelming. We know that,
but that doesn't mean that you personally need to feel overwhelmed. It just means that you are
learning things. With that being said, is there anything else we should talk about,
[name], before I go to the final notes of the day?
Yeah, I'll add that there was a good question of, like, is it not possible to write the
commands directly on the command line instead of writing them as scripts?
And yeah, like that's of course an option, but that requires then you to have the terminal
open and writing them and remembering to write them in the correct order.
And that's like extra effort that I don't personally want to do.
So that's why usually you write the scripts because they tell exactly what to do.
They tell the computer exactly what you want the computer to do.
And then you can tell the computer that, hey, do this for me.
And it will run those for you, run the commands that you specify for you.
And you can later see that, okay, these were the commands I used to run my code.
was the actual, like, what was needed to run my code. And you don't have to be there typing
the commands, because the computer basically, the queue basically types those commands for you.
Like, when it gets the job reservation, it will type those commands in the Slurm script into
the terminal, and it will run those. Yeah, like, for example, there have been
times I needed to use the cluster. I had one thing I needed to run that uses 200 megabyte,
or 200 gigabytes of memory.
So there, I'll go and I'll run it direct from the terminal.
I'll load the data, do a quick calculation,
and be done with it, because it's only a single thing.
But when I need to do something 100 times,
because I have 100 different data files,
then I want to make scripts for it.
So yeah, it's what's it called?
Spectrum of ways you use things.
Yeah, so for tomorrow we covered what was on the schedule and if you look on the schedule
there's the same stuff, links to it, in tutorial format that has more information.
Yeah, so you can read that and catch up, learn more, whatever.
we know you might need more time for the exercises,
so keep working on it later
or for the rest of the day today, tomorrow, whatever.
Maybe we can even make a Zoom session in the morning
to review things for those in Finland.
Or ask your colleagues, your friends, whoever for help.
I mean, a lot of the things here,
it's hard to do by yourself,
but if you have another pair of eyes
who knows things looking at it with you,
they can help you quite a bit.
So find that person who will help you.
And what we did today is needed
in order to continue tomorrow.
But also that means what we do tomorrow
will help to review what we did today.
So if it doesn't completely make sense now, it's okay.
Take it for the day, digest it a bit, think about it.
When you come back tomorrow,
we'll start again from the beginning.
Well, beginning like, you know, what's it called?
You'll see new examples starting from the beginning.
and that may help to put things into perspective
and understand the power of what we do here.
For example, we'll take the Gutenberg books
and run it for every book in parallel,
and it will be really easy and very fast.
And please do fill out the feedback poll here.
There is, if you don't tell us what went wrong,
it's hard to improve it for later.
I'm glad that things are mostly looking okay here.
And yeah, we realized that we need better instructions
for what we do before the lecture.
So we've recently created a new example.
Before our example was calculating pi, now it's Gutenberg,
and all the written material isn't updated for it.
So that makes it just a little bit, well.
Yeah, we didn't have a good thing to point you to.
conundrum with this course is that if the example is way too of a toy example, it doesn't reflect
the real situation. And if it's closer to the real situation, it can become more complicated.
And we try to adapt everything all the time. But yeah, sometimes, especially when we are doing
doing a switch from one example to another,
the material doesn't necessarily follow immediately.
So yeah, that's unfortunate.
We'll definitely improve that in the next iteration.
Yeah.
Should we just end now?
We will keep, there's a question somewhere up above.
Do we have homework for tomorrow?
the homework is just to try what we did, read stuff. I mean, basically the homework is to
keep reading and trying stuff until you feel comfortable with it. There's no strict homework
like, you know, you're not going to be graded or whatever. You're only here for your own benefit.
And don't forget, if you're not coming back a future day,
Once you're done with this course, come to our garage if you're at Alto and ask for help.
We're here to help you to see you through all of these steps.
You're not alone.
Yeah, okay.
Should we go then?
Yeah.
Okay.
See you tomorrow.
Same time.
I just saw in chat that yes, we can have a Zoom session before the day starts
tomorrow.
So if you're one of the Finland people that has access to the Zoom, stay tuned for an
email to come and get help then.
Okay, now let's go for real.
Okay, bye.
Bye.