All making tons of heat.
OK, here we are.
So we're talking about parallel computing in the kitchen.
So this is sort of a metaphor we've
been developing to make, oh, you need to see me.
Yeah, this is a metaphor we've been developing, because oftentimes people will come to our
courses and expect to start using the cluster and think, ah, well, this is a supercomputer,
so everything must be super fast. Well, actually, it doesn't quite work that way. It's a bit
more subtle than that. So after many years of working here, we've sort of found a way to explain
it using a kitchen. And if you look at the video playlist that's here, you see one of us basically
going to the kitchen and pointing to different things and explaining how this is a computer.
But we don't have time to watch all that. Hopefully you could watch before or will
a watch later, but let's just summarize it a little bit.
So first off, what is a computer?
What do all the parts do?
This is why we're here right now,
to explain what these are.
So on the left side is a blade server from a server computer.
This is probably part of the old Triton.
And on the left side is a desktop computer
that has what looks like four GPUs in there.
So how do these compare?
They're actually more similar than you think.
So in this metaphor, what are the different parts
of a computer?
So first off, there's the, well, in the metaphor,
I take the stoves to be the different computer cores.
So the stove is where you actually do the computing
and you cook stuff.
The processor has multiple cores inside of it.
So these days, four is a pretty typical number
for processors for cores in a processor
of a general purpose computer.
The people doing the cooking are the processes.
So basically, you need some code that's
running to actually use the processors and do things.
The memory is the counter space, so basically where
you can leave all the stuff lying around
and things that happen.
The food you're cooking is the data.
And you have to do things like move the data
from the refrigerator first to the counter,
and then prepare it, and then copy it into the pot
on the stove to do the actual cooking.
recipes, or programs, and so on.
So this is the main point here.
So is a cluster faster than your own computer?
So here I have, on the left side,
a about 1.8 kilowatt induction countertop cooker.
And on the right side, my stove.
So does the stove let you cook something like pasta
faster than this induction cooker?
And the answer is probably not.
Their power output is really quite comparable.
So it might be a little bit faster, but really not much.
So why do people use the stove?
Can even be slower, I would say.
Yeah.
So why do people use the stove?
So actually, recently, a few months ago,
I had a friend that their stove broke.
So they borrowed this induction cooker and were they happy?
So they were not happy
because they could only cook one thing at once.
And that's the main thing here.
The supercomputer lets you do a relatively normal thing
but many things at the same time.
So imagine a factory kitchen that has
you know, hundreds or like 10,000 different stove
or burners in it,
then you can start cooking a lot of stuff.
So what else?
So it's really important when you're doing your cooking
to understand the memory hierarchy.
So if the data are ingredients,
there's different tiers of storage places you can put that.
For example, stuff can start in the fridge.
And if when you're cooking,
have to go to the fridge to take every single thing you work on, that's pretty slow. But if
you take it out of the fridge and put it on your counter close to the stove, then you can do your
preparations and stuff a lot faster. And managing this sort of data flow is one of the big things
on the cluster. Also on your own computer, but it's sort of too small to really notice.
It's also very often that on your own computer you do have a comparatively fast hard disk which a lot of the compute nodes in a cluster just don't have.
So there is no local disk that it can quickly access and that essentially means that you need to go to something slower on Tendency or keep it in memory.
there are some machines that have local disks but even there you if you want to use it you need to
first move this move your data over from the fridge to the local disk kind of yeah
let's see is there anything else to talk about maybe i won't go over this um you can read it
yourself. But the main point is that it's not that much slower to take something from your fridge
as it is from the countertop. But on a computer, the processor cache and main memory is many orders
of magnitude slower. The difference there is orders of magnitude. So you really have to start
worrying about this. Imagine if every time you needed to get something out of the fridge, it took
took you several hours to go grab it.
That would really change the way you do the cooking,
and you need to do much more planning there.
This is one of my favorite pictures.
So what happens when you don't have enough CPU or memory?
If you don't have enough processor,
then stuff is just slower.
You cook it a little bit slower.
But once you don't have enough memory, you can't do anything,
and stuff becomes really slow.
And that's why when you get a better kitchen,
it's not really more burners you get.
It's more counter space.
And this is something I wish more people would realize,
not mentioning anyone or anything.
But yes, so I think let's stop here.
Maybe we discuss a little bit before we go to the next part.
There. So any questions or comments?
Nothing in the slides yet.
Or yeah, in the documents yet.
One comment that I give is that
you might really experience
the situation that something runs in a certain time on your local
local machine, and it's actually running slower on the cluster, on a single CPU, if it's single
CPU. So, most desktop machines are actually pretty fast nowadays, if they are not purely
office machines. That's a good point, yes. It's just something I want to mention, to lower
expectations as to what the cluster can do again. You can do more things at the same time,
you can run the same computation a lot of times at the same time compared to your own desktop.
But the computation itself will not be faster. Yeah and that's something I think if you go
deeper into the slides you eventually get this and at least I cover it in the videos.
So when you start to use a cluster you're not a cook anymore. You're not someone that's making
one dish in one kitchen. Instead, you're becoming the manager of all the chefs.
You have to take your problem, divide it into something that 10 or 100 or 1,000 people can do
at the same time. You make the script to divide up all the data or all the problems so that all
these different cooks are working separately and then recombine things together. And that's why
why the cluster seems so difficult and interesting.
And if you don't need to divide stuff up
among lots of people to do it more quickly,
then a lot of what we're talking about
isn't that important overall.
It just sort of, you know, it's OK.
But when you do, the cluster saves a lot of time.
And one more comment I want to give,
because that's also mentioned now in the notes here.
But it commonly takes quite a bit of effort to go or to make
your code actually use multiple CPUs if the libraries you're
using do not, under the hood, already do that.
So it's also often a question of,
is it really worth it spending the time to make something
work in parallel when you could potentially just run it
multiple times for smaller problems.
So how you divide things can be important as
to getting quick and useful results
and how much time to invest into certain parts of the code.
And on a general principle, if you
can divide your problem into smaller parts it's way preferable to trying to actually parallelize
in code. So rather run the same thing or the almost same thing 50 times than try to implement
that this is now using 50 CPUs. Yeah there's a question about what's a GPU and I just really
like this picture I got, not because I eat chickens.
But so the CPU, the processor, can do basically,
and you can cook anything on the stove.
But a GPU is a very specialized cooking appliance.
So with this appliance, you can cook one thing.
You can do some things in parallel, in high parallel.
And very fast.
So this, I think, you could cook maybe 20 chickens at the same time on here.
But how much pasta can you make with this chicken cooking device?
And the answer is basically nothing. It's not designed for it.
So if your problem, like the GPU lets you do something in parallel a lot and very fast,
but only certain types of problems can be adapted to the thing that the GPU is made for.
And if you haven't adapted the code
and put it in the right modes and all that kind of stuff,
the GPU will just be wasted.
OK, well, I think we should go on.
Yeah, it's time to go.
And go towards connecting to a cluster.