Hello, we're back.
I hope you had a good lunch.
So, [name], what's coming up now?
Yeah, so, now we already got from the great CSC talk that we had before the launch,
we had a quick glimpse of what it actually looks like to run stuff on the HPC clusters.
We saw some magical terminal stuff happening there and that sort of stuff.
And here now we are going to be actually like, now hopefully you had a good lunch and you're
full of energy to type a lot of commands. So now we're actually going to go through various things
on how to run stuff in the cluster. And we will start working on the clusters itself.
So we had a glimpse of what it is to work in a cluster. Now we're going to be working
on a cluster and these are easily transferable, this information to the other sites. So there
might be some differences between sites, but in the notes, if you ask questions, if you
encounter any problems, just ask there. And all of these lessons that we are coming up to,
we will talk a bit about what's what, like theory, but we'll mainly focus on demos
demos that we have prepared. And then we'll have plenty of time for exercises where you
can do the same demos as well and do the same things that we do, plus some extra exercises
if you feel like it. And yeah, first, we'll look at the clusters. What are they? So was
that a good intro, [name]?
That's good.
Yeah.
So, we've already gone over clusters a bit, but remind us, so what's the important part
and what's going to make these exercises difficult?
Well, hopefully not difficult, but it might be a bit different than what you have been
used to.
So in the previous talk, we already had a bit of a mention regarding what is a cluster
And what is a cluster? Well, it's a collection of computers, basically,
like computers that have special jobs, and you can use them through this queue system.
And how it's organized, typically, a cluster is that it has some login node, a place where you
can log into the computer and then it has some data storage in case of Triton we have two file
systems we have this home for like small scripts and maybe your logging information and then we
have this scratch storage which is the main work storage and here is where you usually spend most
of your like you put all of your code here you put your data here and here's what stores your
results and stores your code. But when you want to run stuff, you actually run the code through
the queue system in these computers called nodes often. A node just means a computer.
So we have CPU nodes that have only CPUs and memory, of course. And then we have GPU nodes
that have CPUs and memory, but they also have GPU cards that you can reserve to run your code if it
can run on GPUs.
Yes.
Okay.
That's a good introduction.
So, once we're
actually, or was there something else?
Once we're actually using it,
what do we do?
I mean, I start with my own computer
and I guess I've developed
something there.
Yeah, how it usually
goes, like when you start working
in a cluster, it has a
workflow something akin to this setup here. So often you just like when you start a new project
you have this initial setup phase where you usually like have to set up everything to work
and then you run stuff in the cluster. So the initial setup is basically you go to the cluster
usually you immediately go to your work directory because that's the main place where you want to
store your stuff and when I say you go to the like we are going to be using terminals to to like
change directories you change the directory to your work directory and then usually you get your
code into the cluster you get the data that your code uses into the cluster somewhere in the work
directory and then you install the software needed by your code and this is like the initial setup
that you usually do. How long does this initial setup usually take?
Well, it depends on a project. If it's a code that you have already created and you have,
let's say, a version control, your code in version control, you can easily transfer the code over
there. And if you have your data already in order, you can usually quite easily transfer it there.
So that shouldn't take long. Sometimes the software installation, if the cluster has
all the software you need, no problem, then you just use that. Otherwise, you might need to do
some installations or ask help doing the installations for the code. And that might take
some time. But usually this is like, when we talk about a project, it's like a few days,
is maybe like a week if it doesn't go smoothly
kind of a thing.
But usually, you start it up from minutes to a few days,
maybe.
But the actual meet, yeah.
So basically, be prepared.
It's not instant to just get running, but reserve some time
and yeah like yeah it's like like if you if if you think about your computer is your home your
laptop is your home and you go abroad on a hotel you stay in a hotel you want to like first put
your stuff into the right place so maybe you go to like a cottage you have rented a cottage you
want to put your stuff in the right places and then you can start actually like seeing what are
the sites in your city or start hiking now that you have your base set up.
Yeah, okay. So in this little loop where you run something, you see if it works,
you edit code and you run again, how does that work? What are these options for?
So most of the time, usually when you do stuff in the cluster, you are in this sort of a loop where
you run something in the queue system, you usually submit it through the queue system,
and then you check the results, okay, whether good, and then you just keep going until you
reach, get the results that you want. And here, the edit your code basically carries a lot of
weight. So, because this is, and checking the results, it's like very, like self-evident,
but how do you actually do it? There's multiple ways you can do it. It involves what editor,
what way do you want to use the cluster? Here's some examples. I hope the text is not too small,
but examples that you could use. In this course, we will be mainly editing the code in a terminal
because that's available for everybody. What you can do is in a command line terminal,
you can open the files and you can edit the code directly. And then you can do modifications to the
files and then you can submit them to the queue. Some people want to edit the codes in their own
computers and then use something like Git to, like a version control system to push the stuff
into like let's say github or version alter file is kind of version control systems and then get it
into the cluster and use that to transfer like changes to your code some people like easier
option is usually to to get the file system available in your laptop so you can you can
basically mount so mounting means that you you basically make it available in your computer
the Triton file system or the cluster file system.
So you can do the edits with the editor,
whatever edit you want in your laptop,
and it will transfer all of the changes into the cluster.
Or you can use an editor
that remotely connects to the cluster.
So this might be like VS Code remote shell,
or it might be like you use the Jupyter
in the on-demand or something like that.
or you might use the virtual desktop through the on-demand.
But there's multiple ways you can do it.
And it's really important to pick one that suits your work style
because in the grand scheme of things of the workflow,
you are going to be spending most of your time over here in the loop.
So try to pick a style that makes it easiest to do the edits in the cluster itself
so that you don't have to constantly transfer stuff back and forth. It's easier to do the
things in the cluster itself. But okay, enough about the workflows. We should move forward
and look at an actual example. Yeah, so what's our example? What are we going to demonstrate?
Yeah. Go a bit back. So, let's, we need to get our code to the cluster.
Well, first, can you talk a little bit about what the example will be and what our overall plan for the day?
Yeah. So, the, yeah, I think the example is an example about the calculating these n-grams.
And it's stored in this examples repository that we have.
And maybe, [name], you can explain what are ngrams and what does the code do?
Yeah. So, what this example is... Okay, there's a cat that's trying to sit on keyboards and
stuff like that, so I can't type that well. Okay. So, in this example, we have books from
Project Gutenberg, which are open source book or no, it's public. It's digital copies of public
domain books from long ago. And with the books, we'll do some text analysis. So, the sample code
we have divides the books into words and then computes all the sequences of words. So, for
For example, there might be the house.
So how many occurrences do you have of the house,
or every pair of two words, or three words, or one words,
or whatever?
And this gives us sort of an interesting insight
to what the books are.
And well, people like doing text processing these days
because it's close to what language models are doing.
We're not anywhere near close to that,
but you can see the starting point there.
We have this code, it's called the n-grams example,
and we'll keep doing it through the whole rest of the day,
and keep developing it slowly over time.
Maybe we should start demoing,
how can you get the code in the cluster?
First things first, I have
Logged into the cluster over here.
Oh, and I guess we should say first,
are we going to do some demos and then we'll give
time for people to do the exercises? Is that?
Yeah. So you can focus on what we'll be typing here,
and then you can do it in peace afterwards.
Yeah. So I'd recommend focus on watching what we're doing,
And then later, focus on typing and doing it yourself.
Because trying to follow and type along at the same time
will be hard.
Also, for what we're doing, we'll
demonstrate something that works on the Triton cluster.
But you'll have to adapt it for other clusters.
Because every cluster is different.
It may have different storage locations,
different options you need.
So ask in the notes in whatever.
And if you can't do it on whatever cluster you're on,
that's OK.
Just if it goes completely off the rails,
then just stop, switch to watching mode, and just watch.
And then take the time later to figure out what went wrong.
Remember, all the materials in the videos
will be available for later.
OK, so copying the code.
Yeah, so the code is currently in a version control repository in, I guess it's in GitHub.
So that, which means anyone can clone it with the git command.
And hopefully every cluster has git installed by default without any extra stuff.
Yeah.
And now we are, I have a terminal open here.
I have taken an SSH connection to Triton beforehand,
so I won't be showing that.
All of the commands I'm going to be typing
are going to be shown here at the bottom,
so you can see the history of the commands.
And that's, I've set it up,
so I don't want to break it
by doing another connection to Triton.
But first things first,
what we usually want to do in a cluster
is go to the working directory.
So and this is the first place that clusters may be different.
So on Triton, we have this variable
called work directory, which will
lead to our Scratch directory, which we'll actually
talk about shortly.
And other clusters, every cluster probably
has a variable called home, which is a home directory, which
works there.
Actually, should we just use home
because that works for everyone?
like if you don't have a working directory or if you don't know what the cluster working directory
is you can use the home directory but I would recommend using the work directory because it's
like it's good to get the muscle memory in there to go to your cluster's work directory always
because usually you want to do everything there anyway so it's good to do that but if you don't
know what the work directory is, you can use the home directory, of course.
And you can use the command pwd to print working directory. So, which directory you are currently
in or which directory the terminal is in. So, in the terminal, you are basically always in some
directory and all the commands that you're going to be running are running relative to that
directory so if like when i did the pwd it shows now that i'm here and the cd is changed directory
so you can change directory to a new directory yes okay so we've changed there and next up is a
command a git clone command which should work for everyone.
` git clone https://github.com/AaltoSciComp/hpc-examples.git` yes and if we do this now if [name] runs the `ls` command
um we see there's a bunch of directories here which are from previous work but now we see
hpc-examples. And we can change to that directory with the command `cd`. So right now we're not
going through the details of what all these shell commands means. The first time we use it we'll try
to say what it is but this is not a shell course. We've listed some shell courses and materials
as part of the preparation for the course and you can go read there or later. Yeah ls is a list
So list files in the directory.
So you can use that to check what files are available.
Okay.
And now we've got the code here.
So now we need to get the data.
Yeah.
So how do we do that?
So for that, let's try for this case,
we'll try using on demand to do that.
Okay.
So we're going to, yeah.
we're going to demonstrate a somewhat realistic way of doing things so that we're pretending the
data is not available online. So first you download the data to your computer and then
we'll upload it via the on-demand service to the cluster. So basically using a web interface.
There's many different ways to copy data. We're trying to give a couple options that will work
for most people without problems.
So I will copy it by, I'll first download it into my own computer by going to the link.
We'll post a link to the notes for the data and I'll store it into my computer's temp
folder for now.
And now it has been downloaded there.
It's quite a small file, so it's already downloaded.
So next step is to log into the on-demand server that we are using.
You can also use these to get the terminal if you don't, like with the Triton shell access,
if you don't want to take an SSH connection
or if you have problems with the SSH connection.
But let me make this a bit.
So yeah, so on the top bar, there's files over here.
And over here, I can go to work directory.
OK, got it, yeah.
And now what we see here corresponds
to what we saw in the terminal.
Yes.
So two views of the same thing.
Let's create a new directory for that so that we don't
immediately lose track of where the files will be stored.
So let's create a new directory.
So `gutenberg-fiction` is what the examples say.
Okay.
Yeah. So now I get a new folder over here,
And if I go over here, I can now see
that there's nothing over here in the file system.
I can upload a file.
Yes.
Browse files.
Here's the Gutenberg.
Gutenberg Fiction.
And let's upload it.
Upload, OK.
Takes a little bit longer.
And now should we go back to the terminal
and see if we can see the new data visible there.
So I'm currently in the SBC examples folder.
So if I want to go one folder back,
I can type `cd ..`
So I will be then in the work directory,
and if we go to the gutenberg-fiction folder,
I can see that now the file is there.
I'll navigate back into the HPC examples, because that's where we want to be.
You can usually use a tab to autocomplete, like the tab character, you can use that to
autocomplete, like if you have started writing something, if you see that I'm typing something
and something appears, it's just that I'm so used to pressing the autocomplete, I forget
that I use it.
So don't worry about it.
So there, we've transferred the data.
Should we do an initial test to see if the code runs?
Yes.
Yeah.
OK.
So which folder is it?
We can stay in this folder.
So if you do Python, and then space, then ngrams.
Yes, Python 3 ngrams.
It is count.py.
Actually, you can first run it with the dash dash help option.
This is something that each program has to do itself.
But when a program has a dash dash help option,
it usually tells you a bit about how you use the program.
It can really be helpful when
figuring out some new command line stuff.
Most commands like if you run,
let's say `cd --help`,
it has a help manual that shows what it does. Most of the commands in Linux,
at least system commands, they have this `--help` included. So let's check the ngrams.
So I happen to know that we need the one input argument, which is the input text file,
But it can also be an input zip file.
So we will do Python 3 and grams count.py.
And now we're going to refer to the data that's
in a different directory.
So we start with that dot dot, which means
go up to the parent directory.
And then gutenberg-fiction as the directory.
And then the zip file name.
Yeah. Yes. So now should I run it? Yeah, let's push enter and see what happens.
So this should analyze 100 books in there and print out all the word frequencies.
Sorry, cats is getting hungry and starting to look for cables to eat.
It's a good time to have the exercise in a second so that you can feed the cat.
Yeah.
OK, well, it finished.
So what do we see?
So by default, it prints out just word frequencies,
so word one grams.
And then it also prints out just letters.
So let's modify how it runs.
Can we run it again, but with a dash dash words option?
Yeah.
I press the up arrow on my keyboard
to get the previous command.
is very useful for if you want to do modifications or something.
You can press up arrow to get the previous command.
And you're going to use the left and right arrows
to go scroll in the command itself.
So we can write something in the middle of the place.
In the middle.
Yeah.
We're modifying.
Yes.
OK.
Yeah, so I hope it's `--words`.
That doesn't, well.
Yeah, okay.
At least seemed to work.
Yeah, and I guess while we're waiting now,
so what will come next?
This will be an example for you.
So it looked pretty simple when we did it,
of course, lots of things can go wrong for you. For example, how you copy data to your cluster.
If you don't have on-demand, you need to copy it either by the command line or you can use this
wget command in order to download file from the internet by the command line.
So it's like web get, get something from the internet, download some file.
You need to figure out where to store the data, whether it's in your home directory
or some other scratch or work directory that's available on your cluster.
You need to be connected.
So different things can go wrong here.
But let's not focus on what can go wrong.
Let's focus on what you're able to do.
So what if you, like throughout this exercise, we have basically completed the initial setup
because this code doesn't require any installation or specific installation.
We have basically completed the initial setup of our program and now we can start working
in the cluster.
So in the exercise, like basically we now, this is the thing you usually need to do when
you do any initial setup.
You get usually a code repository into the cluster and then you move your data into the
cluster.
you get that done, the vast majority of stuff ends there,
and then you can start running.
Yeah.
And this is definitely an artificial example
compared to usual work, because it's
designed to have no dependencies and work only by Python.
And the data file is nice and small.
But anyway, we're about to go now.
I've put the exercise here in the notes so you can see try to repeat what we just did
that kind of stuff. If you have problems, ask questions down here and don't worry,
we expect there to be plenty of problems. We will give some time. You can also report
Oh, why is this not updating?
Oh, I'm writing in the wrong place. Many windows open.
Done.
And then comment on the problems you have down below, and we'll try to help you.
If you're in Finland, you can join the Zoom we have and get interactive help.
Is now when we wish people good luck?
Yeah.
Is now when we apologize for needing luck to get it to work?
I think this is the kind of problem that it's annoying first, and it's annoying because of
historical reasons and lots of stuff. But once you get it sorted, then it quickly becomes a
row thing that you do often. Yeah. Yeah. And there's already one person saying it's too easy.
In that case, if you look at the different links from the schedule, there's a lot of more advanced
stuff to try that lets you really see a little bit deeper into things here. So I'd say do that,
scroll down to the exercises and try that.
And in the boat, just add an O character there,
because then there's less risk of people
adding counting at the same time and doing this kind of like,
if you ever played the game where
you need to count up to a certain number,
you know how hard it is.
So it's easier to just add an O there.
So yes.
So let's set up the projects.
And are there any problems that you have into the chat?
We'll try to answer them.
So yeah.
How long should we give?
I'd say 15 minutes.
Let's say 15.
OK.
Yeah.
Great.
Good luck.
And see you soon.
Bye.
Okay, hello, welcome back.
And from looking at the notes here,
it seems things went pretty well.
Y'all actually did really well.
You make me proud.
So yeah, really what we do now is probably
one of the hardest things we've done,
or we'll do the whole course.
This idea of having all these abstract folders
on some other remote system,
needing to keep track of what is where
and where all the data goes,
is quite a hard thing.
Yeah, usually like if it's like the cluster is beat up,
like it's like your computer,
but it's like, again, it's like different.
And so stuff is in different places
especially if you're used to using graphical interfaces and stuff, the terminal can become
a seem daunting to do. But basically, it's the same kind of thing that you would do in your
normal operating system, like opening a file browser or something and going to a folder and
opening a file. But all of that is done via the command line, because then you can program
basically, and you can tell the computer exactly what you want to do. And that's why the command
line is so popular in the HPC clusters, because you need to be able to tell the computer what sort
of operations, like file system operations, you need to do, like go to this folder, move this file
around, and that sort of stuff. And this is often the most annoying part when it comes to using the
the clusters, like the transferring files and managing this kind of like, especially if you have
like copy of your code in your computer and then you want it to be in sync with the code in the
cluster. So yeah, like the getting accustomed to the like, okay, there's another place that has
this only, I cannot see, but I can only ask it like it's like, you can only use the terminal
interface. Often you only use the terminal interface to interact with it. It can be a
bit abstract, but once you get a hold of it, it becomes easier. [name], if you want to share
my screen for a second, I might show a refresher of a few of the commands that we did.
So, when it comes to these kind of terminal files, it looks like we just have a blank
screen over here, but it's always in a folder.
We are always in some folder, and the folders are organized in Linux.
They are organized with these slashes, and everything starts at a root.
And then usually you have, let's say, in our case, we have the work directory is like slash
scratch work and whatever.
And this is the so-called absolute path to the folder.
So if we have the HPC examples over here, we can see here's the folder.
And if I run pwd, I can see that this is my current directory, and I'm currently here.
And of course, you can also have relative parts.
So you can have parts relative to this folder.
So you can, let's say, have the dash dot dot meaning folder above me, one folder above,
and then gutenberg-fiction.
So it's basically like you have this, like every folder is separated by these forward
slashes and then like you have this hierarchy of folders inside of it.
So getting accustomed to navigating this kind of like maze of folders can be a bit haunting
at first, but it's always good to remember that PWD shows what folder you are in.
You can use ls to list whatever files you have in that current directory.
if you want, you can always use CD to go back into your home directory. So you know where you
start. If you run just CD without any commands, and you can give it the whole path if you want
to go back into some directory, you can get CD apart and then you can go back into directory.
And this is what it's first daunting, but once you get accustomed and you know that now your
files are in this kind of folder structure,
it becomes easier all the time.
Yeah.
Did you talk about what the `..` means, to go up one directory?
Yes, and you can chain it as well [../../.. etc].
You can have dot dot go one level up,
and then you have go two levels up, and so forth.
And you're going to go up and up and up until you reach the end.
But yeah.
So one other thing I saw in the notes several times
was about the zip files.
So this is sort of interesting.
So we've written the program where
it can analyze books directly from the zip file
without you needing to uncompress it yourself.
So this was an interesting choice of ours.
it meant that it didn't take up as many files, like it's more efficient in some ways.
Yeah, but it's just an interesting design choice. Also, there was a good question about where the
data was saved. And for that, well, I don't know, I can't find it in here.
Yeah, here it is. Where is it saved?
In this case, right now,
the program is just printing it out
from the terminal and not saving it anywhere.
There's an option to save the output somewhere,
which actually we will start using later on.
Were there any other very important things we should talk about?
I will quickly mention that all of the commands in Linux, they have this syntax, this form
that you can follow.
That first command is the actual name of the command that will be executed.
So let's say the Python 3 will be the command that we executed.
And whatever you give after that are so-called arguments.
You can give arguments to the command.
Let's say if I have the count at pi, I can give it as an argument.
I will run the command Python 3, and this is called an argument.
It's usually called a positional argument if it doesn't have anything to highlight it.
It's the next one in the line.
And then you can give more arguments.
For example, we gave the name of the input file, the zip file, that we want to process.
That's another argument.
And you can also have these dash-dash arguments or sometimes with single-dash arguments that are like special toggles or options that toggle different features of the program.
So, for example, the words was this kind of thing.
And all of the commands usually are written in such syntax.
Of course, there's always exceptions to the rule, but all of the operating system commands,
they follow this syntax.
It's like back from the Unix days.
It's very old syntax.
Once you figure this out, you know that and use the `--help`, for example, it will
make everything easier in the terminal.
There's several questions of similar things up above.
So when you're running it from the command line,
or really anytime you run things,
but things are really
picky about how you give the paths and what you use.
So for example, if someone gives the path to a directory,
then it expects a file that doesn't work.
In this case, I think the problem is this person.
You need to give a .zip as part of the filename on here.
So in Unix, well, yeah, really anywhere.
But Unix, what you give is what it uses.
So it doesn't automatically add or remove
filenames from anywhere.
I propose we go to a break now.
We can keep answering some questions
and we'll come back and move on.
And if things are still not working quite right,
please let us know you had problems down here
and we will be aware of that for next time.
But during the break, even if this hasn't worked yet,
consider how cool it is what we just did.
So since we're typing things on a terminal,
it has several effects.
One, you can copy what you typed
and put it in another notepad and remember what you did.
And that's much easier than remembering
where you did a bunch of clicking.
Second, since we're typing it here,
we can make another program called the shell script
that will run these programs automatically for us.
So instead of having to sit there
and click buttons to run something 100 times or 1,000
times, we can run 100 things at once
with just a little bit of work.
And this is our first step in that direction.
And that is, without a doubt, cool
and what makes clusters useful.
So with that said, I guess we have a 10-minute break.
And we'll come back at 8 minutes past the hour.
Sounds good.
OK.
See you then.
Bye.