OK.
So the way we usually present this
is first we run things interactively.
So that means, unlike what we've been saying,
we don't make a batch script and set it to run in the background.
But we're going to see the results right here
in front of us.
So we do that by running the same command as before.
So [name] can push the up arrow key.
And then if we go to the beginning of the line,
now we add a wrapper here that tells it to run through Slurm,
and that is srun.
So srun means like Slurm run, whatever.
Different clusters may have different practices
you should use, but this is the generic Slurm one.
And you can give, first we tell it what resources it needs,
how much memory is needed.
How much should we get?
The input data file is 18 megabytes, at least
the 100-book one.
Yeah.
And it has to make a copy of most of the books, so I mean.
Be safe and put 1 gigabyte.
Yeah, that's not enough, probably.
And for reference, on the cluster, 1 gigabyte is tiny.
So there's no need to even think about going
less than a gigabyte.
So it's not even worth trying to see how small it should be.
And then we should give it, what, the time.
So how long did it take to run?
Like 10 seconds, something?
10 seconds, yeah.
So we can put like 10 minutes, maybe.
10 minutes, yeah.
Usually, you don't want to have very small jobs.
But in this case, because we're just testing out,
it doesn't matter.
And the time syntax is like hours, minutes, seconds.
There's also days.
if you run really long jobs but that's not necessary for here yeah and we didn't tell
the number of processors to use so it probably defaulted to one and here immediately we see
something interesting so we see it says s run job some job id has been submitted in waiting
allocation then it said job has run yeah it's so maybe we should uh add the output there so that
so that we can see the output.
So we can push the up arrow key.
And then at the end, do dash o or double dash output,
whichever one.
And then give it some file name.
And it will now save the output to that file, which is words 1.
Yeah, let's say like that.
Oh, OK, now we can see a bit more clearly.
So job srun queued, waiting for resources.
srun job has been allocated resources.
It found the files.
It's waiting.
And it says it found about 111,000 unique words in there
for however it defines words.
Do you want to look at the output of the file?
Yes. We can use a pager. Maybe you can explain what is a pager, like a list to view it.
So by paging, it means pagination. So since the file's too long to just print to the screen,
it will show us one screen at a time. And less is the most common pager these days.
So once it opens, now [name] can push page up and page down to scroll through. So if we
go to the top, what are the most common words in the books? Yeah, not surprisingly in the English
language book, like many of the pronouns. Yeah, so that looks about like what we'd expect.
Yeah, and to quit the pager, you can press the Q button. Yeah, so there's a good
question in the notes. The SRUN outputs wall time, user time, system time. So actually,
that wall time, user time, system time is coming from the program itself. So we programmed it to
say what the output is. But Slurm also tracks these. So wall time is like the physical time
that passed. So like the real time. User time is how many core seconds was used. So if it ran for
10 seconds, but use two processors, user time would be 20 seconds. System time is the amount
of time spent with the operating system doing stuff, which would usually be things like reading
data or managing memory, something like that. Usually you want it to be low in your programs,
And Max RSS tells it how much memory was used.
So now in order to, well, let's check
Slurm to see how much resources it used.
Or should we do that later?
We can do that, I think, later in the monitoring.
Like maybe we should first check.
Yeah, first focus on this one.