So yes.
Well, I guess the purpose here isn't
to talk about specific applications.
But if you're using a cluster, you want to run something.
And it's either an application someone else has installed,
or it's something that you need to install yourself.
Or for example, you need to install Python or something
and then run your own code.
And this is just a very broad overview of what's available.
Since everyone needs different stuff, we're not going to take the time to go into any detail
here because most people would be bored and you will need to find it again when you need it anyway.
But this is the general idea. So some people come to the cluster and say, why can't I do
sudo apt-get install something, which is the command you would use on a Linux computer to
install something. And there's several reasons, but the most important of the reasons is that
this is a shared cluster. And if you can install something or change the version of something,
then it will break it for everyone else. And even if us as admins do stuff,
any little change we do has the possibility of breaking someone else's code.
So it's very conservative what's installed as part of the operating system.
So if we go down, that's us.
So yeah, there's a few things we install that way.
But for the most part,
anything you need is not just available by default.
Yeah. Maybe demo in the terminal a few of these applications.
So many, at least here in Aalto,
The computing cluster, all of the computers are very minimal installations, so they don't
have a lot of software installed, because they're not installed into any disk or anything
when the computer is booted up.
Everything is in memory, and this is quite common in many clusters, so the whole operating
system is in memory, and the more you have in the memory, the less.
The more stuff you have in the operating system, the less you have memory available for the
users.
So that's why usually the image is very small.
But there's some programs there.
So if we, for example, look which Python 3, so which is this tool that checks, like if
I would run Python 3, what is the actual application that will run?
So we noticed that this is, it comes from user bin.
So this is like, Linux has this file systems through the operating system.
Yeah.
Linux has this file system hierarchy where like user is the applications, the operating
system applications there and bin is usually like the executable binaries.
So it's part of the operating system, but we want to still run multiple things in the cluster.
So often, we admins install stuff into the cluster
and make it available for many of the users.
Yes.
And we do that with, well, the most common one
is called the module system.
And this is a way you can run a command,
and it makes other software available by manipulating
the paths it looks at for software.
And we don't need to go into depth about exactly where this
comes from and how it works.
But can you give one example, then?
Yeah, let's check if we have MATLAB available.
So if we run this module spider MATLAB,
yeah, we can first check if we have it.
And it says there's no MATLAB anywhere.
OK, yeah.
So if we now run module spider matlab,
so this module spider is a tool that it checks like,
is there, like, can you find matlab in the modules?
You can just run module spider to run you
all of the available modules.
But you notice that now we see that there's multiple
versions of matlab available over here.
Yes.
You see that there's matlab
and then there's like multiple versions.
So let's pick one of those versions.
So let's pick the latest one.
Maybe that one.
Maybe the latest one.
And we can press Q to quit, and then module load,
and then give that name.
So I paste it once.
And what happens?
Looks like nothing.
Well, yeah.
But we still, if you are on module list,
yeah, module list shows what modules are loaded.
So we can see that there's now the MATLAB module is loaded.
There's also this kind of like environment module.
So many of, many clusters have this kind of like
overall yearly installations or something
and we have them now too.
So it makes a lot of software available for you.
And it makes it possible to install a lot of other software.
But let's now check which MATLAB, did we actually get MATLAB, so okay, now we see.
Manual installation software MATLAB, yeah, okay.
So there's now like a system installed MATLAB.
So this is the most common way that we provide software or the system providers provide software
for you.
Maybe we can start the MATLAB and test it.
let's try that. Let's see, I hope it doesn't do something weird.
Yeah, we started with the no JDM so that we don't want the graphical interface. But yeah,
you can see that this is the muscle. It returns. Yeah, okay, so that worked.
Okay, and what's available in the module system? What kind of stuff do we have there?
Well, a huge bunch of software. There's many libraries, many finished software installations
and all sorts of stuff. So you can find it in the applications page and running module
spider will give you more information on that. But we also have some very specific software.
So this might be, again, like some of this
is also only auto-specific.
You want to check your cluster's stuff, how they are doing.
But one for whatever, is it safe to say
what every cluster you have, the first thing to do
is read the documentation for what you need
and see if it's already installed
or there's special instructions, because it
will be different for everyone.
Yeah, especially for the very complex programs,
there might be a specific reason why
installed the way they are. And the admins have used a lot of effort trying to get the most
like performant version and most stable version installed to the system. And doing it manually
by yourself can be quite tricky sometimes. Yeah. Okay.
Should we demo? We could demo a few more software. So we have in our
So in our cluster, we also have these containers available.
So there was, yesterday at least,
there was a question about like what,
can you run Docker containers in the cluster?
So containers, for those who don't know,
is this basically like an operating system
paired with the software, like everything is there.
Like everything is contained in the same package.
And we use these apptainer containers,
or they used to be called singularity containers.
They are called, in some sites, singularity containers
to have these kind of very complex software
that wouldn't install into the operating system
that we're using.
So, but these can be run in the cluster,
and we have a few of these available.
They need usually a bit more manual work to get working,
But in the notes, we'll link a course page with Code Refinery that we did on creating
these containers. So if you are interested in this, please check that material.
And on Triton, at least we do have some software already installed in containers.
So it's not just, despite what it says here, it's not just under install it yourself.
So yeah.
But should we give a demo of running stuff,
something with a container?
Yeah.
Yeah, let's look at it.
So one example is this FreeSurfer,
which is this Neo4j imaging suite, which
is they provide existing containers.
So it's easiest to install using that.
So for that, we have this module,
apptainer-freesurfer.
So if you load that, it will tell you
how to get more information on how to run it.
But we have read it, so [name] can maybe execute the command.
And is this a typo here?
Should that be a curly bracket?
Oh, that's true.
Yes, good point.
We need to fix that.
So now we run it with aptainer execute,
and I guess the path to it?
Yeah, the mesh path.
And then we execute some program inside of it.
So this is running.
So if I can unpack this command, apptainer's the container
program.
Exec means we want to run some command in a container.
Image path has been defined by the module that tells me
this is where the container is.
And if you make a container yourself,
you would just give it the path there directly.
Yeah.
And FreeSurfer is now a thing that will run inside of there.
So it's like it's starting up this other, almost
like an operating system that's self-contained with all
the stuff, and then says, hey, you, this box I just made,
run FreeSurfer.
And it connects it to what's outside.
Yes.
Yes, very well.
And I guess we can run it with the Help option
to verify that it does something in there.
And it sure looked like it gives us help from it.
And I guess if we do FreeSurfer outside the container,
there's nothing.
So yeah, OK.
Are there any other big, major ways of software?
I guess there's Conda that we already
went over in the morning.
So actually, what is the most common way of doing things?
Yeah, well, that's, at least in the Python world,
it's quite common.
But for many people who don't necessarily
like who want to use Python, but they don't necessarily
want to do stuff themselves or install their own environment,
we provide existing environments that
are like handcrafted to have a huge bunch of packages
available, at least here in Alta.
So we have this SciComp Python environment
that has a lot of packages already installed.
But of course, you can create your own environments.
So maybe we should demo that quickly, loading that.
Demo, ah, so the pre-made content things, yes, OK.
Yes.
And I have a visitor here.
So let's see how much I could type.
So module load.
And I know from my experience that it is called `scicomp-python-env`.
And what's in this environment?
A huge bunch of Python packages he installed already.
So now we can see that the Python has changed.
Like, what is the Python version that we're using?
It comes from our installation.
But like, yeah, these are something that we provide,
but there's a lot of stuff you can, of course, install yourself.
And if you encounter any problems, it's always a good idea to ask help
from the admins, or if you know a software
that other people might be interested in using,
it might be good to let us know, then we can install it for everybody.
in the cluster because that's that makes it life easier for everybody.
Yeah, and even if you aren't sure about it, you can ask. So there'll be sometimes we'll say,
okay, yeah, I mean, we haven't had many requests from this. It seems easier to install yourself
and we'll help you install it yourself. But as we see the patterns, we might add it to one of the
existing environments, especially if it's a Python or R thing, install it within one of these. If it's
it's LLM-related, install it to our standard LLM environment.
Yeah.
So, and depending on your, yeah,
but usually like as a good rule of thumb,
go check out module spider in the cluster
that you're running in and check what's there
and it's your program that you're planning on running there.
That's a good starting point usually.
and check the application page for the program.
But I think now is a good time to switch gears,
to talk about, like we have a talk by [name and [name].
And I think the cat is getting pretty hungry,
so it's a great time to switch.
Yeah.
There is this interesting question about using Python 2 on Triton.
So that's one of the cases where we'd say it's not installed in any default environment,
but you can install it yourself with Conda.
And then we point you that way and give you any help you might need.
And that's that basically.
Yeah. But also, I would say that if you have to run some Python 2 code, that's the least
of your worries. It's been deprecated for so long that transitioning to Python 3 in
that code might be... Asking people supporting you, can they help with the transition process
from Python 2 to Python 3 might be a good worthwhile investment.
Yeah, but I mean, if it's some code that they haven't made
and someone else is like, yeah, you just
aren't going to update that.
But yeah, OK, so with that said, let's close this out.
There's a lot more to read about applications.
We've just prepared you to do your own reading.
So by all means, go do that.
And if you have questions about the application of your choice,
put them into the notes, and we can try to answer, like,
well, how it should go about installing.
Keep writing there.
And now we're switching gears for the second to last session
of the day, which is a more philosophical discussion,
I guess.
So it's more about how you use stuff.
Or no, not how you use stuff, about how
you do the science itself.
And this is with [name], who's one of our, well,
I want to say one of the reproducibility people.
But really, we all care about reproducibility in science.
So anyway.
Yes.
Yeah, have a good one.
Thanks.
Can you switch to my share?
Screen share, please.
There you go.