later or find us, talk to us later. Next up is a session that's about Conda. I guess the
instructors seem like they're here in the room, so you can start appearing. So this session,
So, you may know of Conda as a way to install Python packages.
But it's a lot more than that.
It's also a way to install R packages and other compiled code kind of stuff.
And we have a running joke in our Garage session.
It's day's-
Okay, now you're just doing my intro.
Okay.
Go ahead.
I'll let you do your intro to that.
I mean, yeah, we have the running joke. Days since there was a Conda question in the garage.
Okay, how was I going to go? Yeah, it is always zero.
But that means two things. One, Conda's pretty important for installing software because it's
the best way to manage Python and compile the scientific software on a cluster.
And two, it's harder than it should be.
Or maybe it's as hard as it needs to be.
It's just that it's actually a hard problem.
So us as cluster admins before the RSE things started,
the software installation probably
took up most of our time.
Took up most of our time.
And yeah, so where was this going?
Yeah, software installation is quite a difficult thing.
And now, lucky you, you get to learn one way of handling it.
So maybe I'll just go and let [name] and you
do their introduction.
So see you later.
All right.
Bye.
Yeah.
So I mean, my starting intro was going
to be that joke specifically.
So yeah, day since we've had a question about Conda
is always zero because Conda is very useful
and you also run into complicated problems.
But if you then include the kinds of questions
where it's about installing some software
or problems installing some software
and the solution is Conda,
well, you get even more of those questions.
It's basically like a half of the questions
or something like that.
So yeah, what is Conda?
I can be honest.
The name of this page that I'm sharing
is Python environments with Conda.
And that's also linked to in the notes page.
But Conda is not just about Python installations.
It's a very general dependency manager.
So to install a specific piece of software,
you have a bunch of dependencies
that need to be installed as well.
So this could be a system,
or what would normally on your own desktop laptop
be system libraries
and specific versions of those system libraries.
You can install those with Conda
and then get the software to work.
And it's also useful for separating between projects
because different projects
might need a different version of some library. Often they're not designed to exist at the same
time, but Conda takes care of that as well. So it is very useful. It also does have some problems,
especially when used with Python on some HPC systems. So we'll come to that later.
But yeah, I guess one important point about HPC specifically is that it's always a shared system.
So installing all the software that everybody using it needs on the system level would get very complicated very quickly.
And that's where conda helps. It allows you to install software that you need that maybe not everybody else needs.
Okay. I mean, I did not introduce myself or you. Do you want to introduce yourself?
Yeah, my name is [name]. I'm also one of the RSEs. I'm very happy to be here today.
And I'm [name]. I'm also an RSE here in Aalto.
Okay. So, let's get started. So, yeah, I mean, Conda is actually language agnostic. There's
nothing specific to Python. We use it often to handle Python environments. An environment
is, so an environment is when you have this certain set of dependencies for a specific
project and you can have a different environment for a different project.
So you can have a completely different set of libraries for a different project.
So it's a very general solution for handling software environments.
And actually yeah we use Mamba most of the time. Mamba is a replacement for Conda that's just
faster. It uses a different algorithm on the background. But it's essentially the same thing,
a very small difference. So let's actually go to the terminal and get started. And there's some,
well, we load a module called Mamba. Module is its own kind of, it's a system level way of handling
the fact that people need different software. There will be a separate section on the module
system later in this course, so I will not explain that much of it, except that I will show you.
If I try to run Mamba, it does not exist. I am on Triton, we do have Mamba,
but I do need to run module load Mamba in order to get access to it.
And now I have Mamba. Oh, it printed a long, long list of commands you can run.
but it did work, so the command is found.
And then we have this initial setup.
This is very much Aalto-specific.
It's something you probably should not run on other systems,
but it's here in the documentation.
And if you are on Triton, you should run it.
So if you're not on Triton, ask,
and probably don't just take our Aldo instruction
or Triton instructions directly.
Okay, and that's the first time set up.
Oh, there was one thing I was going to talk about
before going to an example here.
So about conda channels.
Channels are where conda pulls the software.
So they store a bunch of these libraries, binary packages,
and allow you to install them into your environment.
So there are many options.
conda-forge is probably the biggest one
and you almost always want to include it.
It has a lot of packages and it's,
well, the licensing is good for research.
It's mostly open source
and the channel itself is open source.
So it's very useful.
There's also the default channel, which is maintained by Anaconda Inc., who also maintains the conda command itself.
There's licensing issues though, so you mostly want to exclude it.
And if you do want to include it, it's a specific case and you know what you're doing.
Okay, there's also Bioconda, for example, okay, Bioconda has specifically bioinformatics
packages.
It's a separate place for those and if you are in bioinformatics, then you will often
end up using it.
PyTorch, the channel doesn't exist anymore and I should have deleted that line, but I
didn't notice that it was there.
So we will demonstrate installing PyTorch for machine learning later from CondaForge.
Okay.
So I will do a quick example of creating an environment with R. This page is about Python,
but you can also install R and R packages there.
Or any questions?
Anything before we delve in?
I have a question, actually.
Yeah.
How to exclude the defaults from the channel,
from the conda config or from the YAML file?
I always use the YAML files,
And I guess, well, let's make a YAML file.
I mean, so yeah, I always use the YAML files instead
of the config, because the file, essentially,
you can have it with the code and with the whatever version
that you've been running that has produced a specific result,
specific.
You can include it with your paper, basically.
So everybody can reproduce the same thing.
So if you push it to a GitHub repo, it will be there?
Yeah.
Then everyone can reproduce?
That's good.
Yeah.
Was there anything else about environments and managing software in general?
I guess we can come back to any questions if there's there.
there. Left side of my terminal is slightly off screen. So now it should be on the screen,
I think. Okay. Okay. So in order to create an environment, my workflow and workflow I
generally recommend is to create a YAML file. So let's make, I use a Vim to edit the file.
can use nano or whichever you want. I'm creating a file called tidyverse.yml or yaml and this will
describe the entire software environment for my project. So first name for the environment
and I will call it tidyverse. Tidyverse is an R package or an R, well it is a single package
but it contains a lot of useful things.
Then I will describe the channels. So this is a list of channels that
Mamba or Conda is allowed to use to construct this environment.
I will say Conda Forge. That's the only one I need for this one.
Okay and then dependencies. So this is the list of software we actually need
and I will only specify one, r-tidyverse. So because this r-tidyverse depends on r,
we will also get r, the entire programming language ecosystem, into this environment
and it will automatically have a version that supports whatever version of r-tidyverse it
pulls up. You could specify a specific version. I don't actually know what versions
exist though so let me not just do that.
Okay and then I'm saving the file so have it on the screen. Let's cat it.
So this is what the file looks like although very quickly
it will actually disappear off the screen when I run
the next command. So we can do mamba. I actually did not write down the
command. So let's see if I get it right. Mamba env for environment, create,
`-f`, f stands for file, and tidyverse. Okay, so now it's looking for first tidyverse
in ContaForge and then it looks for possible dependencies. It's
It's taking a while before printing again.
OK, here we go.
So it found a bunch of stuff.
If I had one more character width on the display,
it wouldn't break the lines, but that's fine.
So yeah, it takes a while to download all of this.
Tidyverse is relatively small, so it doesn't take that long.
That's why I chose it.
But it takes a while to get all of the system libraries,
like X-Org, the window manager, graphics manager,
display manager for Linux, and a lot of other stuff.
FontConfig and GNU, C libraries, all sorts of stuff.
OK.
So it is essentially constructing an entire software
environment.
me oh okay it's done then i will not yet take a look at the um the chat uh the notes
okay yeah there's a question uh asking us to clean the terminal so that they can see the
commands on top so maybe move the terminal a bit upper or clean the terminal so um i guess
does it mean that they cannot see the lowest line? Yes, I think that's the problem. Okay,
you can move it up a little bit. Maybe that's it. Maybe run clear.
So, I want to comment on the text that is showing here. So, because in a lot of systems,
you actually do not want to run this command. On Triton, you do not want to run this command.
So, instead, we use source activate tidyverse.
But okay, let me clear the terminal first.
The reason that we don't want to run this command is that it requires you to modify
the shell environment in some way.
You need to run this mamba init command.
will tell you to run it if you run this mamba activate. So we want to avoid that to avoid
complicating things even more. So instead we run not mamba activate but source activate tidyverse.
Okay, so now it's showing that this particular environment is active and since I have it
active now, I have for example the R script command.
So let's make a HelloTidy.r, an R script.
If I was using a graphical system,
I could also run RStudio, for example.
OK, I'm not going to explain that much about what
is happening in this script.
But maybe I should say it will check
if I actually have Tidyverse.
and then it will tell me and it will say tidyverse could not be loaded or dplyr could not be loaded.
So I can use our script to run hello tidy
and it should report that the tidyverse library is available.
Okay, and there were some conflicts that became errors.
It loaded successfully, though.
I do not know enough about R to actually know if this is a problem or not.
Probably not a huge problem.
Okay.
So, yeah, that's the point of this demonstration, though, is to show you how to
to record the dependencies in a YAML file,
and also to show you that this is not just for Python,
that you can install a lot of other things as well.
The next thing, though, will be Python,
because it will be how to set up an environment
for a large language model.
How are we doing on time?
Not bad.
Okay, so
next
I have a section
about why you should track
dependencies, which we actually
did touch on a little bit.
So maybe
at this point, do we have any questions
in the notes?
Or do you have
have other questions just in general? There's a question about how do I exit the environment
tab? I think that's asking about the deactivation. Yes, so now I still have the tidyverse environment
active and that means I do have for example rscript. Version of rscript is yes. So to exit I
could run source deactivate.
Okay. It will complain about the source activate, source deactivate
thing but I do not want to like change the environment to run mamba
activate and mamba deactivate so this is fine.
Now if I try to run our script
version. It will not find R script. So now I'm outside the environment. I don't have
R anymore and I don't have the libraries. Okay.
Okay, there's another question about, it's kind of like a Python 3.0, I suppose it's
asking the Python's own virtualenv and how it's different from Conda.
Yeah, so, oh, so I guess like venv or venv comes with Python 3.
Yeah.
So, yeah, there's plenty of different environment managers.
The Python 3 venv thing is designed for Python specifically.
It can install Python packages.
So it cannot install system level packages.
it cannot install R for you.
So Conda is more general.
It's not just for Python, and it can install
some system-level things.
So for example, we'll soon install an environment
that has CUDA in it without you needing
to set it up for your system in the same way.
Yeah, I think maybe it's the time to go to the next question.
But there is also a question about the CSC thing.
The background of this is that Conda creates a lot of files in the environment, especially
if you install Python packages, it can be millions of files.
And this is often bad on an HPC system.
So if you want to use Conda to manage environments,
there is this solution from CSC called
Tykky, the container wrapper.
So it can create something very much like a Conda environment
for you.
It is actually a Conda environment,
but wrapped into a single file that is a container.
So you can read up about it in here.
And yes, there is a link to it already in the notes.
So most of the things I say apply,
but the commands are different.
And this is probably true on a lot of systems.
So yeah, if you're using a different system,
you do need to figure out how to do this in your system.
Maybe there is even a different manager.
OK.
But yeah, so let's move on.
Okay, so we already mentioned,
talked about how using a Conda environment,
so using a file like this inside your code
makes your code and your research more reproducible.
reproducible. So you can track the entire environment, your entire coding environment,
in a single file. And then you can include it either with your code or with your data,
for example. So if you publish a bunch of data, you can include some software to
to analyze the data and you can include a file that describes the entire environment
that you use to analyze the data so that it is way more reproducible.
People can install your environment and run your code and get the results from your data.
It also helps with debugging, so you will get a lot less of the it works on my machine
problem when other people can reproduce the same environment that you have and it allows version
controlling so if you are doing some heavy software development you are probably hopefully
using version control with your software and you can also conversion your environments so you can
create different versions for different versions of the software so it is it's very useful in for
yourself it also it is very useful for helping your teammates your people in your research group
set up the same environment and run the same code so you can give them the file and give them these
two three commands and they will be able to they will have the same software environment as you do
it also works across different operating systems
with some caveats.
So Windows might require different versions
of system libraries,
but if you don't specify exact versions,
they will mostly figure out to you
how to use the correct ones.
Yes.
So it also helps with a lot of this Python dependency
problems and especially problems
where you need multiple different versions
of the same package for different versions
of your software, different projects.
So those are the main points
for why to use conda in general,
or why to use software environments in general.
It becomes very,
it becomes an especially useful thing
if you have multiple projects running
at the same time with different code.
Okay.
So there's one more thing that I want to mention about practically how to use this.
So we have it somewhere. There are some
a list of useful commands that I could also demonstrate while we go.
So I still have mamba and now that I have an environment I can run.
one more. I was not in an environment. I exited the main. So, okay. If you're in an environment,
you can list. So, let's activate the environment. High diverse. Source activate high diverse.
And let's try. So, you can list all of the packages that are in the environment for additional
reproducibility to make it extra clear what's in,
and then to check to do some debugging
on what is installed in your system, in your environment.
Okay, you can also remove an environment,
but really with this,
which is necessary and useful occasionally,
cleaning the cache is necessary
if you run out of disk space.
But the main thing that I want to highlight
is how to update an environment.
So you can install a package directly into the environment that already exists,
but what I would do essentially always is I have this idverse.yaml file
is to edit the file. So what should I add?
I have R already but I can add it explicitly as a dependency and I could specify a version
for example. So let's see. So now I can run mamba-env-update and then use
`-f` or `--file` and the environment file.
So let's see if it works when I specify the R. I did not specify a R version, I just specified
that I want R. It did install some new packages, which is interesting. Maybe I didn't have the
R command specifically before I just had R script.
Okay, so you can update the environment,
you can add new packages to the environment
and keep track of them in the file as you go, which makes it
makes the file more useful in the long run.
Okay, so here's about setting default channels and like I said I
always use the yaml file to track the channels but you can set default channels in your
conda rc file or in your conda configuration and that can also be useful
okay and that's the motivation for using conda section which essentially we already talked about
So yes. And a section about how to set up environment with CUDA, which we'll be talking
about next. But essentially, I will do this by not that much looking at the documentation,
which you can read yourself, but rather by just creating a new environment. So let's see how it
goes. So, let's create a new environment file. And this time, I want to develop some
language models, large language models with Python and PyTorch.
So, to do that, I will create a new environment. Let's call it PyTorch.yml.
And, again, the environment needs a name.
So I'll call it PyTorch and we'll need to list some channels.
So now we want NVIDIA as one of the channels because this environment will depend on CUDA
and that comes from the NVIDIA channel or some CUDA-related packages come from there.
We'll also want to use conda-forge. That is almost always there.
And then list the dependencies. Dependencies. It is correct, I think. Yes. Okay.
We will definitely need Python, and I want to specify the version of Python,
because if you – it's actually missing a dash here, a minus sign there.
So if you don't specify, it will probably – well, it will first of all try to check all different
Python versions or possible PyTorch packages. And that will take a long time. Not as long as
installing PyTorch, but still. So that's one reason. But also, it will probably actually try
Python 3.13 and then just fail because I think some of the packages don't exist for Python 3.13.
I'm not sure why it doesn't figure it out before it tries to install, but there's something there,
some configuration issue somewhere there in the packages.
Might actually be useful to just demonstrate what a failure looks like, right?
Okay, well, actually, that will come, so let's see.
So we want PyTorch GPU, and I'll just specify larger than 2.6, less than 2.7, mostly just
to show the syntax, but also because I don't remember the exact version.
I didn't write it down in the notes on purpose.
So TorchVision, this is often useful if you are dealing with image models.
Let's do TorchAudio as well.
Just commonly installed in the PyTorch environment, although if I'm using large language models,
maybe I don't need them.
But I do need definitely these transformers.
Okay.
So there's some useful packages for machine learning stuff.
And let's save this file and show what's in there.
Okay.
And then let's see how long it takes to construct the environment.
So mambaenv create and use the PyTorch file.
The first thing it does is it recognizes that I'm on a Linux system. It can also use no-arch
version, so no architecture or system-independent packages, and then it's looking for specifically
system packages and dependencies that work on Linux to get all of these dependencies.
Okay, so we have a critical issue.
I almost transitioned to the nodes, but not quite.
So the problem here is that it doesn't find CUDA.
And it doesn't find CUDA because we don't actually have any GPUs
on the login node.
So there are nodes on Triton that have GPUs,
but on almost any HPC system,
you're not gonna have GPUs on the login node.
So that is confusing, Mamba, yeah.
And it's thinking that you're trying to install
some GPU dependent stuff on a system that doesn't have them.
I mean, technically it is correct about that,
But I still do want to install this environment that
depends on GPUs existing in the system.
So we can override the CUDA version
and just tell it that we have CUDA 12.6.
So that is also mentioned here in the notes here.
So we export that, and then we try again.
So mamba and create pytorch.yaml.
Okay, so this version of the command worked yesterday,
so we'll see.
It's always possible that some library got updated
and broken somehow.
But while we wait, let's see if there's any
other interesting questions in the notes
or important questions.
What are the channels?
So yeah, I guess we went over this maybe a bit too quickly.
But yeah, channels are repositories of packages.
So they are servers somewhere that store all the packages
that you might need.
Well, all the packages that somebody has added to them.
So conda-forge is one of them.
And it says, it contains a lot of different packages
that most things depend on.
So conda-forge includes torch-vision here.
I think `transformers` also comes from conda-forge.
Does anything actually, there's also
the NVIDIA channel that we included.
Does anything actually come from there?
Yes. Some libraries that have to do with CUDA and
with NVIDIA GPU specifically are coming from the NVIDIA channel.
So conda-forge is the big channel that has a lot of open source packages and most stuff comes from
there. But Nvidia has things that Nvidia maintains. So this is a channel where Nvidia provides a
bunch of packages and it's necessary for this environment. Okay, so let's run this to install
the environment and this will take a while. It should succeed but the main point though is how
to create the environment and how to use it and not actually finishing this download process
where it gets all of the PyTorch and all of the system stuff. But yeah so it is actually now
downloading this from the
channel is where it's actually pulling all of these dependencies.
If you have something cached, will it be faster?
Yes, definitely. If you have a similar environment
installed before, then it will be faster, right?
And I think it will even slightly prefer cached versions if they exist, but also
quite often when you create one environment and then you create another one with almost the same
requirement, it will still end up using slightly different versions and redownload stuff.
But yeah, in principle it does cache the packages.
I think it also done some fancy system or fancy linking where it actually uses the same
files in different environments if it just has the same exact same version of the package.
Okay. I think it's almost done. And so is also our time. So, unless there's anything
else, I guess we could move on to a break. I mean, showing that it works is kind of fun,
but not necessarily worth the wait. So, what is next on the schedule?
I think it's a break, or?
Yes.
Yeah, we have a short break.
And then we get back to hands-on with, I think,
it's Array Jobs, which is the start of Parallelism
and the Power of the Cluster.
OK, so I'll stick around and answer questions, of course.
There's a number of questions coming up, so just keep them coming.
So I guess, I guess we have a break until two minutes past the hour.
So yes, there it is.
See you later.
Bye.
See you.