Hello.
Welcome back.
I hope you can hear us out there.
Hello, hello.
So, where are we now?
What's going on?
So, [name], can you let us know what's upcoming?
Yeah, so we had great talks in the morning with [name] and [name] and [name], and now we
are jumping back to where we left off yesterday.
So yesterday we were writing stuff, we were running stuff in the queue, like we were testing
stuff in the queue and we were testing out the submission scripts. So, we were trying out
how we can write scripts that can be run in the queue. So, they can be run like we can submit
them to the queue and the queue will run them later on. So, that was the thing that we were
doing yesterday. And now we are going to get further in our users of the cluster because
we don't only want to do one thing usually, we want to do a lot of things. So that's why we want
to make it so that we can run a lot of stuff. So that involves parallelism. And the parallel
is like the whole thing about this day.
So we'll first talk a bit about different ways
of doing stuff in parallel in cluster,
because we have a lot of computers in the cluster
and we want to use as much as we can
to get all of our stuff done.
And we'll talk about the different ways you can do it.
And then we'll tackle three of those four ways today.
So we'll talk about array jobs,
then we'll talk about a shared memory parallelism and then
MPI jobs.
And that's about it.
And we'll do some exercises on those.
OK, great.
So I guess I'll switch to my screen.
And so what now?
Where do we start?
So let's first look at, if you want
Let's just show the serial jobs, what we were doing previously.
Let's look at a diagram that might refresh us.
So previously, we were writing these scripts, and we were doing also interactive runs, where
we were running something in the compute nodes.
And we were currently using only one computer, only one processor.
And these are called serial jobs, because they do the commands in order.
They run like a series of commands.
Like we write one script and then we execute that in the cluster and it executes everything
in order, like it does everything.
And it uses one CPU currently.
So we're taking only a small slice of the whole cluster.
Like we are taking one CPU in one node and the whole cluster is a big thing.
So we want to use more.
And the first and the easiest way of doing this is usually to split up your job, what
you're basically doing, split up what you're doing and do an array job.
So maybe we could talk about the different parallelism modes and let's, we could maybe
show a picture of an array job.
Yeah.
So I'm opening this, the parallel one from the schedule.
I guess we're looking at these things.
So let's go down.
This is an Array Job.
So what's the characteristic here?
So the idea behind Array Job is basically like, let's say you have a script that describes
what you want to do, but you want to do it with multiple data sets, or you want to do
it with multiple different random numbers, or you want to do it with different options,
different startup options.
You want to have different parameters for your model or something.
But they're basically the same thing, but there's something that changes.
And you want to do the same thing.
So we take the big problem, you make it a bunch of small problems, and each small problem
is only slightly different.
And you can basically load up every small available place on the cluster.
You get independent jobs, and it's often called embarrassingly parallel, not because it's
not embarrassing to use it, but it's because it's so easy to parallelize.
Previously, we had the HPC kitchen metaphor, and we talked about CPUs being like stove top
burners. So if you put two kettles in two different burners, they're independent of each
other. They're not interacting, but you can cook two pasta varieties in different pots,
And they work independently of each other in independent learners. So this is basically
the idea. So the array jobs are spread out throughout the cluster. And there's this nice
syntax that you can use to easily create even a large array job of, let's say, 100 jobs running
at the same time. And each of them works independently. Okay. So we're not doing it now,
but should we preview the things we'll do? Is it the end of the day?
Yes. So the other methods that we're going to be talking about are a bit more involved. And the
first one of these is shared memory parallelism. And this is basically what your laptop is doing
right now, or your computer. You have multiple processors in your computer, but it's all inside
this one computer, right? Like you don't have other computer there like connected to that.
You only have one computer, but it has multiple processors. So you can, if you have a problem
that way, it suits the problem. You can use multiple processors in the same machine
to calculate something faster. So this is like, this just usually makes calculations faster if
if your program supports it.
Yeah, and I guess this is relatively easy to do.
Yeah, so your job ends up in one of the computers
and then you can have multiple processors
working together to solve a bigger problem.
And this is like, it's of course limited
by the size of the computer
that you're going to be using or getting,
but this is something that we'll be talking
in more detail later on.
Yeah.
Okay.
And finally we have the shared or
We have MPI jobs.
Message passing.
Yeah. So message passing jobs.
So, so this is like the traditional
high performance computing, like supercomputing.
If you think about like big weather models or whatever
they often use, or most often use
this message passing interface,
which is like this standard that has been created
since the 90s or something like that,
that makes it possible for a lot of different processors
in different computers to know about each other
and talk with each other to solve a really big problem.
So it can, you can utilize multiple computers
at the same time, and you need to, you can, you can,
like each of these can communicate with each other,
but this is a bit more involved
and it's specific for programs that use this.
So we'll talk about this later,
but nowadays I think vast majority of problems
are Array Jobs or like vast majority of parallelism
is nowadays Array Jobs or shared memory,
but in the big clusters, the MPI is still a very big thing.
Right, yeah.
Okay, so should we get started with Array Jobs then?
Yeah.
I'll close this window and let's go pin array jobs.
Yes. We're going to be demoing few of the array jobs,
and we're going to contrast them
with the serial job that we did yesterday.
If you didn't manage to do it yesterday or if you weren't here,
There's instructions in the notes on how you can bring yourself up to speed.
So basically how you can download the example data set and the examples repository.
And there's an example like solution script for the CDL job script, so that we can like
then compare the results.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, since I didn't do the typing yesterday, I've set up where I've walked into the cluster
and I've copied the data to my personal work directory
in a Gutenberg Fiction folder, just like before.
So hopefully, it will be pretty similar to what
we did yesterday.
We're in a fairly similar place.
Yeah, so I guess the first thing I'll do when I've logged in,
I want to see where we are.
So I type `pwd`, and I'm in my home directory.
And I know I need to go to the same place I was yesterday,
which is the HPC examples directory. So I'll change there.
Yeah. It's always a good idea to go to the work directory whenever you go to the cluster.
Yeah. And verify where you are before you start running commands.
Yeah. It's a small but important thing.
OK, so here we are.
So do we have the do you have the previous script there?
The previous?
No.
Maybe let's go over.
Well, let's.
Well, then.
Yeah, let's.
We can.
I can copy it from the notes here.
If you'd like.
Yeah, let's.
Yeah, let's do that.
So nano.
What was it called?
count-ngrams-2.sh
Yes.
Yes. And I'll just put it in this directory, I guess.
So, do you want to remind us what these things are as I type them?
Yes. So, there's the first line is the is the shebang or that tells which like it's the magic
that runs everything with the terminal. I think our pictures are a bit cutting off the terminals.
Yes, and then we need to tell the queue system what were the requirements that we want, what
memory we want, what time we want, and then we need to tell what we want to actually run.
In this case, it was the n-grams.
We took the two grams, so every two-word pair, and we wanted to get those calculated.
And we gave it the folder of where we had the dataset downloaded and part of the dataset
that we wanted to analyze.
And you can use, [name] is using this backslash syntax.
So if you put, as the last character, you put this backslash, you can continue from
the next line.
So basically, it means that just continue, combine these together so that you can fit
more stuff into the, without wrapping.
And make sure it's the very last line.
Should I run this just to make sure that it actually works?
Yeah, let's do that.
So I do Control-X to exit.
Y, yes.
Yeah.
So now [name] is checking that it's in the queue.
So it is running.
It's the last one over there.
Yeah.
So it is running, and then it probably finishes quite quickly.
Yeah, it takes a minute to run.
But now the question is that, okay, like this is quite a simple program, but let's imagine
that our data would be a lot bigger.
So let's imagine that we would have a lot bigger of a data set.
So in that case, we might want to do these calculations of these n-grams in, or like
we would want to do it in pieces, right?
Like, we don't necessarily want to have one job that does everything.
We could do it so that, like, every job, like, we could split it up, the program, so that
every, we could split it up to, let's say, ten programs, that each program would do
one-tenth of the analysis.
So are you roughly saying we have 100 books in this sample data?
So we'll have one program do 10 books, the next do 10 more books, and so on.
We can run 10 things at the same time, and then I guess that means we get 10 different
output files?
Yes.
That have to be combined?
But it can in theory run 10 times as fast.
Yes.
And that's very, very well put.
And for this, we can use like the program, the ngrams program, it supports these start
and step functions.
So you can decide, you can tell it that, hey, I want you to take every 10th book.
I want you to start from a certain number.
So we can modify the count ngrams to code.
So if we make a copy of it into, let's call it an array, count n-grams, and not the output,
but the count n-grams.
Oh, yeah, not the output.
SH.
So this is not good.
Oh, yeah.
Wait.
Yeah, yeah.
Yes.
So let's modify the code a bit, and let's try to like split it up, split it up the work
to multiple workers.
So if you look at now the array script.
Yeah, OK.
So we can do small additions here.
Yeah, so we can do small additions here
that make it so that we can split it up.
So the first important thing about the array thing
is that when you want to submit an array job,
you add this `sbatch` and then `--array`, and then let's say it's from zero to nine [`--array=0-9`].
And what this syntax, this looks a bit interesting, but what this syntax tells
the queue system, like the queue system will read this comment and it will recognize that,
Hey, the user wants me to create 10 copies basically from zero to nine.
Right.
And it wants me to create 10 copies of the same job.
All of those jobs are independent and all of those get the same requirements.
So it's not like additive, you don't get like 10 gigabytes, so you don't need
to modify the requirements in a way.
Of course, like in this case, like, like some of, like if we split up a big
program. Each of those might have less requirements to do, but that's not necessarily
something we need to think about. We're not thinking about that now.
Basically, we're running 10 identical copies here, but if we don't do any modifications to the
running part of the code, like the Python call, we are going to be running the same thing 10 times,
and that's no fun. That's a waste of resources. Hopefully it's exactly the same ten times. Yes.
But instead what we can do is we can like this program supports a different starting point.
So we can use a different starting point for like which book we want to analyze.
So, if we add here, that's the start, and then we put there a magical environment variable.
So, in Terminal, you can have these environment variables that are like something that will
be filled later.
It's just a variable that will be filled later.
And for the array, it's called `$SLURM_ARRAY_TASK_ID` with underscores and all capital letters.
So it's very important that it's written correctly.
Exactly like this, I guess.
Yeah, exactly like that.
But once you have written it out loud a few times,
you will remember it and it will become more natural.
And what this...
Like for me, even every time I do that,
I almost always look at a reference
just to make sure I'm spelling it right.
So don't be afraid there.
Okay, so this means it starts and `$SLURM_ARRAY_TASK_ID` becomes the numbers 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9,
I guess. Yes. So, when we submit the array job, we will get a number for each of these
these array tasks. So, we get a number. So, the number, well, that's a task ID running
based on what are the numbers we are giving in the array, like lying over there, the Sbatch
array. And each of them gets a different one. So, what we do with those numbers is
up to us. And that's the beauty and the complexity of the array jobs, that we can map this number
to any sort of like parameter values, we can map it into datasets. You can do whatever you want
with this number, as long as you map it to something different for each job. There's many
examples in the ArrayJobs tutorial page of different kinds of structures you can use
to map this into different things. Yeah, and I guess if the program didn't support the start
option, it wouldn't be easy to do this with arrays. You'd have to somehow add it yourself.
Yes, quite often you want to implement this sort of functionality in your code. Like,
if you know that you are planning on using the code for, let's say, running a hundred different
things, you might want to implement in your code functionality where it can take a number and,
based on that number do something different. Yeah, but so is there anything else we need to do
for this then? So we need to like currently we are setting up a starting point but we are not
setting up a stepping like stride. So if we would only have the starting point we would
like everyone would start at a different number that but then they would analyze all of the rest
as normal. So, we need to set this step over here to be 10. So, everyone takes, or in every 10th
book. So, zero, yeah, like Riks is writing, we get numbers like that. And then 1, 11.
1, 11, 21, and so forth, 91, I guess.
Yes.
And this, so when we made this program,
this is basically like the Python array slicing.
So you give a start and a step.
And I think you could also give a stop there.
So it's, well, if you know the Python syntax,
it looks familiar.
If not, well, that doesn't really matter.
And yeah, but we could try out submitting this
and see what happens.
Should we adjust the output?
Because it looks like it will be writing.
Yes, great point.
I almost forgot.
So if we wouldn't change the output,
everyone would be writing into the same file. So, instead, let's call it `ngrams2` and then
then `-array` and then `_$SLURM_ARRAY_TASK_ID` [so `ngrams2-array_$SLURM_ARRAY_TASK_ID`].
So now, because all of these programs will run independently, all of them need to have
an independent output as well.
So yes, we want them to write to different files.
And again, the SlurmArrayTaskID will be filled when the code is actually running.
So it's based on the array number that it gets.
Now I think we are ready.
Okay.
Yeah.
So I exit and save.
Do we trust it works?
I think it's going to be fine.
It looks good to me.
So let's hope.
Yeah, `sbatch count-ngams-2-array.sh. And if you now look at the queue, what does this queue say?
So, we see, yeah, we see that we have now this weird job ID for the job. So, what that means
is that, maybe you can try running it again and trying it again with the scheme.
But this structure means that we get the same job, but with basically 10 copies of it.
And we have only one ID for the whole average.
And this makes it easier for the queue system to also understand, okay, now we have the
same thing, but 10 times.
And now we see like how it looks actually in the queue.
So once the resources are, yeah, once the resources are reserved, we get these array
jobs running and each one gets a different ID.
And you notice that some of them are running in completely different machines, or most
of them are running in completely different machines because they are independent, right?
all of these are independent and they would be running independently of each other. So let's
look at the output. Did it crash or did we get anything in the output files? Oh, there's a lot
of output. I see this output is doubled here. Should we look at what should we look at? Let's
look at the ngrams output first. Let's verify that it worked correctly. So we get a lot of
output over here. Yeah, and it looks 7000. So, that's about one tenth of what was there before,
I think. If we look at number one. Sure. Yeah, okay. Yeah. So, what we get is we get independent
outputs from all of these, but we also get this slurm outputs as well. And by default, when you have
this array structure, you have the slurm, it's called slurm, and then you have the job ID and
the array task ID after that. And again, it captures all of the output from each array job.
So let's say you need to do some analysis a hundred times, and each one takes an hour or
something, and one of them crashes. You can look at the outputs and see that, okay, that one crashed,
what was the problem with that one, and then you can figure out that, okay, maybe there's
like a corrupted data or something. But each one is independent, and each one gets an independent
output. Yeah. Maybe we should almost go to an exercise. Yes. Let's look at one of the outputs,
and let's then check the combined data, like what did we actually get what we wanted. So,
So if we look at one of the SLAM outputs.
The output of 0.
It says it found 100 files.
It didn't say which files it's processing.
Yeah.
Yes.
But it looks like it ran in about three seconds.
So each of these was very fast because now we're
splitting it into 10 parts.
But let's try combining the data together.
How do we do that?
So we do it by running combine counts.
Yes.
I'll run help first, and let's see what it says.
So it needs the output count files,
and then it has an output file.
Yeah.
So we combine counts.
And don't worry, we'll post all of the commands that we're going to be running into the notes
in a second, so that you can try them out in the exercise.
So I guess this is how I'll run it, Python 3, the program name, and I can use an asterisk
to glob and capture everything that starts with this, which I know will be the 10 files
that are needed.
Yes.
And then you specify the output.
I saved it somewhere.
Yeah, you have the out and the ngrams.
Yeah, to array out.
That looks good.
Dot out.
Yeah, OK.
Takes a while to combine them.
Yeah.
So this is kind of like, yeah, this
is the kind of map-reduce kind of situation
where we map a lot of map the same functionality
onto different data, and then we reduce the results
into together.
So if you look at the output.
I can look.
Should we see if it looks the same as the non-array one?
So like 62,000.
Top number is 62,3.
And if we do array ngrams2.out, exactly the same,
at least the first number.
So this is a bit of, again, like a toy example.
But if we would have, let's say, the data would be a lot bigger,
then this would really speed up the execution.
And to use an imaging example, if we
have 100 brain images to process and they each take a few hours to do, we can do them in
parallel, even 100 times in parallel. Okay. And now let's go to exercises. So the exercises,
we'll post the commands that we just ran into the notes and you can create your own
ArrayScript, or you can already start writing it if you feel like doing that. And after that,
in the array examples, there are many examples. They use this py example, but there's many
examples of different ways you can choose the different array IDs in different ways.
And if you have more time, check out a few of those
and run a few of those examples and see what they do.
But yeah, let's go to the exercises.
And should we have about 20 minutes?
I guess that will start getting into the lunchtime a little
bit.
OK.
I guess we can go some people.
Or should we just combine the exercises with lunchtime
And then people can beat the cues of the places or whatever.
Maybe we'll have 50 minutes of exercise,
and then we'll talk about a few of the questions,
and then we'll return to it after lunch.
OK.
So 40, no, 50.
Well, yeah.
Let's go 55.
55, yeah.
And you can try some Ask Questions,
And there's more time during the lunch break.
So yeah.
OK.
And the task of people will be to do basically
what we've done here.
Yeah.
Is that the case?
OK.
And I think [name] will be pasting in commands and more detailed
instructions to the notes.
OK, great.
So see you in about 11 or 12 minutes.
OK, bye.
Yep. Bye.
Hello, we are back.
So, our plan now, I believe, is to go over some of the questions and stuff and then we
go to the lunch break and we can do one more array example after lunch.
So, which questions were most relevant here? There's some on best practices, like, oh,
Oh, yes, please, even for a reference or a future,
please let us know if you did the exercise,
weren't trying, or had some problems,
because this will help us plan for future years.
So yeah, so this is a good question here.
So if someone goes and makes an array job,
Like you run 1 million array jobs that each take 10 seconds.
That's not a very good thing, because it's
a lot of scheduling overhead to constantly be
finding these spaces, planning it, running it, stopping it,
and restarting it.
So that's sort of an extreme example.
But what's our rule of thumb?
Try to make the jobs at least 15 minutes, but if it can be longer.
Yeah, like usually we talk about half an hour or an hour
is better.
But yeah, it depends how in a hurry are you.
If you want to get most done, you usually want it to be, let's say, an hour.
If you want the results now, less than 15 minutes is fine.
But if you do, let's say, 100 jobs in less than 15 minutes, that's going to...
At some point, somebody will send you a mail of like, why like this?
Because it's not good for the queue.
The queue system doesn't like if there's a huge number of jobs happening that are very
small.
It doesn't usually like that.
And there was also a question in the chat, why not just use a bash script that submits
jobs or something like that.
And the reason behind that is the array structure is much better handled by the queue.
been designed for this sort of workflow. If you have a bash script that just submits stuff,
then each of these are independent and the queue cannot reuse the same information it gets from
all of the array types. So, it's not as good. So, please use the array structure instead.
And a good benefit with the array structure is that it's reproducible because you then know what
is the mapping between the array indices and the different things. And it's very easy to then look
at it later on and see that, okay, I run it with these array indices, so I get these results.
And there was also a question...
One of them fails, they don't all fail or something.
Yeah, yeah. There's also questions of more complex parameters. So after the lunch,
we'll talk about an example of how you can map out different combinations of
parameters. If you have multiple parameters you want to do, you can use array to map to those.
You can map one number to multiple things. That's possible. And if you have a situation
where you have very small things that you need to do a lot, what you can do is you can have an
array job where inside each job you have a for loop that does 10 things or 20 things. If you
If you have something that only takes 10 seconds, but you need to do it like 100,000 times,
you can split it up so that you have, let's say, 10,000 or 1,000 10-second things running
in each average job.
And then you can set up what is the run time, basically how many iterations you want inside
one job.
But usually it's this kind of like, okay, you can think of it a bit like you can have
either like a really thin rectangle with the same surface area as like a very wide one.
And as long as you keep the number of things that aren't needed to be done the same, you
can rearrange it in a way that you can do it in like, you can do a small number of jobs
that do a lot of things, or you can have a large number of jobs that do a few things.
Yeah. So I guess most of the people asking these questions, like, can I do x with array jobs,
the answer is always yes, if you write the code, whether it's in Python or Shell or whatever else,
to do the splitting up, and if it doesn't make it too short. And this is why we have other courses
on shell scripting and stuff like that. Knowing a little bit of bash can save you a lot of time
doing other stuff. Yeah, and if you have problems figuring out, okay, that's my program. Can I
split it up? How do I split it up? What would be the best way? Again, asking for help is a
good thing because for different projects, you might have a different thing you want to split
it up by, and all tasks are individual. So it depends on the task at hand. How do you want to
split it up? But yeah, maybe we should go. Anyway, I guess it's lunchtime. So should we
head there? See you in an hour.
Yeah, and when we come back, we'll
talk a bit more about arrays, about more complex array
things, and then we'll jump into applications and other things
in the cluster, monitoring jobs and that sort of stuff.
So a little example and some more philosophical stuff
before parallel.
OK.
Yeah.
Great.
As always, you can keep asking questions.
So talk to you later then.
Bye
Hello, are we back?
I think so.
I hope you had a good lunch break.
I think we did here.
So what comes next?
So my understanding, we have another quick demo
of Array Jobs, and we talk about monitoring and applications.
Any other notes and stuff to review from, or questions from the notes to review?
I think, yeah, there's plenty of good discussion there. And I recommend reading up on it later on
if you feel like it. But I think we can move forward. And let's do, like, many of the topics
in there touched the subject of, okay, what is, like, what can you do with the array jobs? And
Let's look at one of the more complex examples. Let's run one of these from the
examples in the course material. [name], if you want to run the case example.
Yes. So, what do I type? So, this is a new thing. This is with calculating pi.
So, in the parallel part, when we are going to switch into another example, which is much more
like computational example, and it was already mentioned in the beginning of the day, and it's
a bit of a toy example, where it calculates or estimates the number of Pi using a stochastic
test. Basically, it's like throwing a dart at a dartboard and whether it hits the dartboard,
it will calculate how many hits do you get and estimate Pi by that. It's very like a toy model,
but it's very easy to pack analyze for multiple CPUs and stuff like that, or relatively easy to
optimize for that. And here I see we have five array tasks, 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
Yes. And for that, we want to test out a different kind of way of
of choosing the parameters.
In this case, we might want to choose a seed number
for the random process that we're going to be doing,
so we can decide which number we want to use.
And in Bash, it's a whole programming language,
the terminal, so you can do, for example,
this case statement that [name] has written.
So, basically, based on the number of the Slurm array – it's mistyped, actually.
So, based on the number in the Slurm array task ID,
a different value will be set to this variable seed. So, let's say you want to test different
If a parameter is out, it's very easy to test it with this kind of like a syntax.
Then there's more complex syntax that you can use in the other examples.
You can take the parameters from a file or you can do all sorts of things.
But this is like very easy way of testing out.
So over here, we try...
So I guess, yeah, there's the seed.
Yes.
we try out what we get from the slurm/pi.py.
And you notice also in the #SBATCH statement,
we have changed the output file name
of where the output of the,
up in the top, like in the #SBATCH statements,
we have changed the output file name.
And you can use these test wildcards.
are documented in the documentation sections. You can use this %a to denote the Slurm Array Task ID.
So, if you want to create your own output file for the Slurm output, then you can use this
sort of a syntax for that. But let's... I guess everything's configurable.
Yeah. Okay. So, what this will do is that it will do two and a half million iterations
slurms with different seed values, and it will print out the outputs into pi underscore
and the seed number, and then it will print out the slurm outputs into the pi array hardcoded
with the array index. So, let's try it out.
Exit, save, yes.
And there's, like I said, there's multiple of these different things that, different
ways that you can do this array kind of like expansion.
So first, I make sure I'm where I expect to be after the break.
pi-array.sh.
If we do `slurm queue`, it's already running.
So four things.
And it's done.
If you want to look at one of the outputs and.
Okay, now this is a lot of files here.
Yeah.
So, what are the new ones?
The pyarray hardcode.
These are the output files.
Yeah.
Should we look at the first one?
So, this is the output that the code, yeah, what the code runs.
But the actual output of the code is going into the py underscore and then.
1, 2, 3.
OK, yeah, and it's a JSON structure that says stuff.
So I guess this is a way where if you
have different file names that aren't predictably named,
you can sort of hard code what the inputs are
or what the hyperparameters are or whatever like that.
Yeah, and there's a lot of flexibility
in the array chops for this.
But OK, I think you probably get the idea that you can
Yeah.
You can check this out later.
We'll check out the different examples.
So maybe we should jump into the next section,
which is about monitoring.