all that. Yeah. What's the point? Yeah. But anyway, now it's time to begin.
Right. Let's see, what do I do? I scroll down. So
we already have some questions here that people are answering. So welcome to day two of the
course. We start with something we've done for a few years, which is a quick, I guess
I guess you could call it an interview, but it's not really.
I guess it is, technically.
So we talk to different people that
work on our team or similar teams
and hear about their careers, how they got where they are,
and you can ask questions and see some examples.
So today, right now, we have [name] here,
who actually, I think, is the newest member of our team, technically?
Yeah. It's been nearly a year now, but technically, I'm the newest member.
Yeah. So anyway, what's your background? How did you end up here? What did you study?
Yeah, I think it's maybe a bit of a sort of winding garden path. So I started as, well,
I started studying, originally I started studying Japanese and computer science as a side, then
switched that to studying bioinformatics, which is computer science with a focus on
some biological science. And I picked neuroimaging for that. So then I, I studied
further to do neuroimaging. And that's what I did there was mostly analyzing lots of neuroimaging
data. And yeah, I continued doing that for a little while, did my PhD, did a postdoc.
And yeah, I came to Aalto as a postdoc. And then at Aalto, I met, it must have been around
the Corona time, I met people from SciComp. So did you come here in 2019? Yes, I came to Finland in
2019, November 2019. And then, I don't know, I was in Finland like four or five months when the
the Corona lockdown started,
and everyone went basically working from home.
And my research group sort of didn't really have
a good on staying online presence.
So the psychon chat and partly the code refinery chat
sort of became my coworkers, my office.
Yeah.
And yeah, then I kept working as a postdoc for quite some time still.
Right.
For, I guess, five-ish years.
Yeah.
Ish.
Okay.
And then in the meantime, my husband had gotten to work as an RSE, and then at some point
I applied and got a position here. Okay, nice. Yeah. So was there, well, the next question I
have written, what led for the transition from science, like the direct academic science to
research support? And I guess the obvious answer is it was a job, but is there anything?
No, actually, it's not so much it was a job. Because for me, I've been always more interested
in doing the computation and not so much in getting the results and not so much in interpreting
them and writing them up. So to be honest, if I were on an academic career path still,
I would probably be failing right now because I'm rubbish at writing papers. So that's
one reason. And then there was also, so when I was still a postdoc, I started actually
trying to chat with a colleague who's also sort of into computing a lot, talking about
about that in NeuroImaging, there's a lot of code being written, but many people don't
know how to structure code, what to look for to make code reusable and readable in 10 years
time or even in two years time.
So we then decided we're going to do a little workshop, just for newer ending.
And that was something that I really, really liked, teaching people about how to do programming
really.
And yeah, that was one more reason why I wanted to do more of the teaching to code and less
of the actual science interpretation.
Yeah, yeah. Okay, well, then that's perfect, then. Yeah.
That's where I really wanted, I really, really wanted to go get that kind of position.
And would you say that's what you're doing now?
Yeah, I guess. I mean, there's the kickstart. And there's also a lot of other sort of
of small things. When people come to the garage and they've got a problem with their code,
we had a few people coming just lately that said, oh, it's running so slowly, we need
some help here. And then that sort of turned into a slightly bigger, let's help you restructure
the project and get it into a bit better shape so we can actually get started with improving
the how fast it runs. And that kind of thing. And then there's lots of other projects that
aren't really teaching that are more like trying to get the code done, but that's fine as well.
I do like coding. So I'm quite happy, actually.
Okay. So before, let's say when you were offered the job, were you worried about making the
transition anyhow, and how did it turn out?
Well, I wasn't so worried because I knew the team quite well. I've been in contact with
it through, well, since 2020, I guess, with the one or the other person. So I kind of
knew what I was getting into, and I'm still sort of on a retainer for my old postdoc project.
So I do still work a little bit on the science side.
Yeah. Okay. Right. Yeah. Yeah. So it's like a slow transition.
It is really.
I also had the same, like, I kept working into other things for a while.
What do you know now that you wish someone else had taught you when you first started as a researcher or like your first
I wish I had known when I started my PhD that use version control and use it regularly.
Like, it doesn't really matter whether it's Git, which is the thing that people use most at the
moment now, or I had come into contact with Subversion before that, which is a bit
bit more complicated and less featured, I would say, than Git, but it works. Anything
is better than having files by date with the code or having final, final.1, final.2, and
kind of thing is because it's a mess. Any sort of version control is better
than what you can come up on your own. And you will need it.
How often have you had something where you've edited some code and it's somehow broken and
you've spent days trying to undo the breakage because you can't figure out what it was?
Because that's happened to me many times.
Yeah, well, I don't know how many times, I remember a few, I mean, it's always something
breaks and then there's the, especially in science, if you've already sort of written
up a paper or presented a poster, and then you notice there's a mistake in the code,
you don't know, has it, does it affect my results? That's, I think, the worst kind of thing
that you can ever, that happens and it happens. Yeah, yeah. I know the feeling.
Okay, so next up, what would you say to someone who might be interested in careers outside of
tenure track. Well, already it's great that you're thinking out of the box, basically,
and interested in this. For me, it was mostly sort of talking to people to get to know what
is out there and it doesn't even have to be someone outside academia. A lot of the stuff
how I got into the RSE bit was talking to my colleagues who had heard about this and who
had heard about that. And then there was the CodeRefinery Coffee Hour. Actually, that's
quite a friendly place to go to, or it was when I was going there. And you can just chat to people.
No one bites. Even if it looks a bit intimidating, no one's going to bite you.
And I guess you could say like all the people at Aalto that are helping you,
if you ever want to chat about other stuff. Yeah, I mean, we're here for that. You can
chat in the process of other stuff or whatever. Actually, I think a few times I just went to
Garage because I didn't really have a problem, but I wanted some company of people who
know how to code, I guess, and have a similar mindset.
Your department here was Neuroscience and Biomedical Engineering, so were you sort of
the coder, computer person of the research group?
Well, strictly speaking, that would have been [name], because I wasn't the only one. I was
more or less the junior one. But yes, I was one of the people who knew how to code in
a field where not everyone knows how to code.
Yeah, yeah. And I guess that sort of leads to the next question. So what would you recommend
or what do you think someone could do to prepare for, you know, some more diversity of careers
after they're done with their degrees or postdocs or whatever?
Well, I think just realize that it's not as clean cut as it sometimes sounds.
And to not stress about, if something doesn't go, you do your bachelor, you do your master,
you do your PhD, and then you get a postdoc, and then after two years you get a professorship
or whatever.
That's not how it goes.
When I was still a student, I met a postdoc at the Max Planck Institute, which is a very
high-profile research organization in Germany, if people don't know.
And he, I think he started out as a gardener, and he said, yeah, don't bother.
Don't bother with the pre-set path.
Don't worry about it.
Everyone finds their niche.
If you just want to find something, you will.
It might take a while.
It might be frustrating, and yeah, it's going to be frustrating, but don't stop believing,
basically.
Yeah, okay.
And that sort of, yeah, that gave me some, I guess it gave me some peace of mind, because
my path isn't the straightest of them all.
Yeah.
And it hadn't been back then already, because I had changed degrees and changed universities
a few times.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, last question, and we can...
Yeah.
Go ahead.
Last question.
We can look at some of the notes.
you want to continue learning and what comes next?
I continue learning all the time about things that I didn't know about. So I can't say
what I'm going to be learning next time. I don't know who's going to come into Garage
tomorrow and say, hey, I've got a problem with this and then I'm going to learn about
it. Because that's something that happens quite often that I don't really know in-depth,
but I know where to look.
Yeah. Okay. So there's some interesting questions in the notes. Do you use ChatGPT or similar?
Well, me personally, I do not, at least not really regularly. I've used it a few times
to just get like a bit of a code snippet or just an answer that I didn't want to Google
about, or just to try it out. I could have just as well Googled it and found it out myself.
And I'm a bit, well, I'm a bit worried about everyone using ChatGPT because people then
tend to forget that it has a lot of downfalls and it starts hallucinating things.
You can't actually really trust it.
So you need to check it anyway and then some other source.
Yeah.
Okay.
But I know that a few people use it for things that are easy to check and you can see the
answers there.
Yeah, we can see what people have written there.
What's the most exciting thing you've worked on?
Well, the most exciting for me is the teaching.
I guess you're relatively don't have that many projects yet, but yeah.
I don't have that many projects, but yeah, I think for me, the teaching is the most exciting
thing.
Yeah.
The thing that I'm nervous about before and then sort of elected after.
Yeah, next one, what's the most important skill you look for when hiring RSEs like people
for our team?
Yeah, I guess that would be your question to answer.
That's more, yeah. But my answer is there, like, it's easy to find people that have good
technical skills, but harder to find the people that want to use those skills to help other
people instead of just only developing the skills for themselves. And that's sort of
main thing there, if you ask me. There's a question recommendation for someone in neuroscience,
but maybe you can answer that by writing afterwards. Here's an interesting one.
Most common easy-to-learn fixed mistake people work with high-performance computing make?
what's the most challenging part. This is a good one. We should actually discuss this all
as instructors at the end of the day or end of the course. Do you have any thoughts now?
Or should I try to answer? I think you've got much more experience than I do.
So once someone was talking about how hard it is to learn, how to teach people how to use a cluster,
And my comment was, if you know sort of the Linux operating system, like command line,
how files are stored, the Linux fire hierarchy, and stuff like that, then it's relatively easy
to add in the extra bit to the cluster. But when you're learning to cluster, most people tend to
be learning how to submit jobs. At the same time, they're learning how to write shell scripts,
how to ssh there, how to use the command line. All these things at the same time,
everything depends on everything else. So it's quite overwhelming, even though if you
knew everything except one thing, that one thing would be relatively easy and make sense.
So that's my take on it.
I think the first bit of the first comment is quite something important there.
How to look for parallelism, because if you really want to use the power of the cluster,
you want to run things in parallel.
And getting into that sort of mindset of identifying what can I run while I'm doing something else
and not doing it step by step by step.
Like usually when we're teaching, a lot of the time it's like you do this first and then you do this
and then you do this and then you do this.
this, and then taking this, what you've learned about the flow, and then trying to think what
can I actually do out of order? That's something that's somewhat hard to grasp, I guess.
So unfortunately, it's time to go on. I guess we can keep answering questions about this
later or find us, talk to us later. Next up is a session that's about Conda. I guess the