Oh, hello.
We are back.
Hello, hello.
So I see a shadow moving under the table.
I wonder if my feet are about to be attacked.
OK.
Yes, so we're back for the last session of the day.
Go ahead, [name].
Yeah, I was going to say the exact same thing.
Yeah, you go right ahead.
OK, last session of the day.
And this is something which you need a little bit
of an introduction to.
But like many things, you'll probably
come back to it in more depth whenever you actually need it.
We're not telling you how to write code in parallel,
but how if you have a code which should run in parallel,
how you can actually use it and run it on the cluster.
Yeah.
Maybe.
So let's look at, maybe we should
start with the picture of the Shared Memory Parallelism.
OK.
So I'm opening this page.
Yes.
I need to go to the right screen.
There we go.
Yes.
So yeah, we talked previously about the Embarrassingly Parallel and the
like array jobs and how to run it. Lots of individual jobs basically in the cluster and
that's already like very good, like you can get a lot of stuff. But there's of course a lot more
available left on the table when it comes to the parallelism in the cluster because the
the computing nodes, like these computers,
they are basically, the CPUs are pretty similar
to what you would have in your laptop or in your computer,
but there's just usually more of them.
They're like server CPUs,
and they usually have much more resources.
They have more memory, more CPUs.
So if it's possible for your code
to utilize all of those resources,
you can, in theory, get a lot of speed up to your code.
And you can get your code done faster.
And that's basically this part of the parallel.
So the array jobs are more like maximum throughput
kind of parallel.
You get maximum amount of jobs through the system
and maximum amount of stuff done.
And they're very good if you have this kind of problem
that you can split into chunks.
But if you have like, let's say a big simulation
something and it just takes a long time. It takes a long time and it would benefit from
having multiple CPUs to run on. Then, yeah, let's look how you can do that in the cluster.
Okay. Should I go to the terminal for a demo? Yeah. So, there's two things you need to
think about. So, the first thing, of course, is that does your program work in parallel? Can it
do stuff in Parallel? That's a big question. Many programs can nowadays because many normal
computers have multiple CPUs. They are nowadays written to be able to utilize those CPUs. For
example, if you use Python, libraries like NumPy, Scikit-learn or whatever, they allow you to use
parallel CPUs natively, or MATLAB does. Or if you use R, you can use parallel in R to do it.
And there's various ways you can run without many code changes utilized. But of course,
like the efficiency, whether you get best efficiency, that is up to the air. But at
at least in principle, they could utilize multiple CPUs.
And to test it out in the cluster right now,
maybe [name], if you were on module purge
to verify that there's no like previous modules loaded.
Yes.
So we can start by testing out an example code that we have,
by testing out an example code that we have,
which is the Pi code that we mentioned previously
in the example.
So we have this in the Slurm folder,
that is Pi code.
And if you give it like a thousand or whatever,
like a number of thousands,
and if you run it like here in the login node,
okay, you see that.
That's very fast.
Yes, it's very fast,
but of course it's only like a thousand tries.
And this is like a very simple code,
but because it only does calculations,
it's quite easy to parallelize.
And that's why we can use it as an example
of how do you reserve resources with multiple CPUs.
So let's try running this in the queue
with a bit more requirements.
So if you add the normal stuff at the front there,
like srun meme.
what does this `--pty` mean yes so we didn't think i'm copying yeah yeah we didn't
mention it before but you can add this that's a pty and it means like zelda terminal so
uh what it means that it will uh without spaces origin yeah i'm just verifying i'm doing it right
Yeah, like the PTY, it will allocate like the input and output for the terminal. So, basically,
if your code would have like interactive stuff and that sort of things, like it would ask for
input or something, it will work. It prints, yeah, okay.
Yeah, it will print everything automatically. It looks just like the normal shell. Okay, yeah.
Yeah, if you're running with this interactive SRUN, you might sometimes want to add the PTY there.
Yeah. But yeah, so let's add a bit more numbers here. So we have now, what's, is it 50 million?
It's 50 million. Yeah. Yes. So let's run it. It takes a bit longer. So this is about,
I think, maybe 40 seconds or something, if I remember correctly.
vc srun says it's queued. And now this is doing what we learned in the interactive job part
yesterday. And this is the kind of a program that, okay, like this could use multiple CPUs and it
could run faster with multiple CPUs. So let's get first a benchmark. What often you want to do is
that you want to, if you have this sort of like a program, you first want to try running it out
without any bells and whistles like with single CPU and then see how long does it take. If you're
running it already on your own computer you can look at the process manager usually and see how
many processors it's using and then try using the same sort of requirements in Triton for that.
So it shouldn't take that much more longer.
Yeah, let's see.
But we can see that, like, yeah, it takes, okay, now we can, yeah.
So it took some time.
Maybe if you run quickly the seff to check what is the, how long did it take?
On the job ID, and it says 95% efficiency for 40 seconds
and 42 real-time seconds.
So if we now want to allocate more CPUs for this job,
what we need to do is tell Slurm that we want more CPUs.
That's done with this CPUs per task flag. We just say CPUs per task, and let's put four
equals four. This would allocate four CPUs for that. We'll talk about tasks later. You don't have
I can't worry about that too much right now, but that is just a Slurm internal thing.
But basically, you just specify how many CPUs you want to get.
And we need, of course, the code to understand this as well.
The code needs to be able to utilize those, because otherwise, it might run with a single
CPU.
So in this case, we use this nprocs, `--nprocs`, and we give the same number.
And it's important that the numbers match, because otherwise you might run into a situation
where you reserve more CPUs than you use, or you use more CPUs than you reserve.
And in both cases, like in the case where you reserve too many, you underutilize the
CPUs.
So you basically underutilize the resources.
And if you use too many CPUs, they can get crowded.
So they compete on who gets to use the CPUs, and then the code runs slower.
So sometimes if you run some code in the cluster, you might encounter a situation where it runs
slower.
And the reason might be that it tries to use, let's say, all of the CPUs, but it's only
getting one, and suddenly it's slow.
you need to tell the code to actually use the CPUs you want it to use. So let's try this out.
And I guess this is a hard problem. I've often seen codes that say it can use multiple
processors, but it doesn't tell you how it actually works. So you don't know if it's doing
the right thing. The most annoying one is when you run something and it says,
Oh, I'm running on a computer node that has 40 processors.
So I'll try to use 40.
But it's actually only been allocated four.
And it's just a huge slow down then.
OK, it's done.
Should be seff.
Yeah.
Yes, if we check the efficiency of that.
So compared to my other nodes, this
says 83% efficiency, compared to 95.
And we ran the same 40 seconds of CPU utilization,
because that's how long it takes to run.
But now it took a shorter amount of time in real time.
Only 12 real time.
OK.
And so basically, it's nothing magical
about the reserving of CPUs in the submission scripts
Or in the command line, you can just
specify the CPUs per task to SLURM,
and that will give you more resources.
And there's a nice question in the notes.
Are you going to answer the same thing?
Yeah, go ahead.
I guess we're thinking the same thing.
You can say it.
Yeah.
So what I've just highlighted here,
This is the argument to srun and to slurm. So, the CPUs per task equals 4 is a slurm option
that says please give whatever I'm running for CPUs. And then that wraps this other command.
And the --nprocs=4 is a command that was programmed into the pi.py file, which tells it I have four
processors available, I can try to use them. And you can tell if these don't match up,
then stuff can go wrong. Should we demonstrate what happens if you don't get it right?
Or is that just maybe people can do that themselves? Yeah, I would say probably.
But yeah, so maybe we should just jump into exercises. If the exercise is basically
do the same thing. Okay. Yeah, I see it's already appearing in the notes there.
Oops, I copied the wrong one. Sorry. Check the right one.
But yeah, the question is, how do you tell the program what you want it to get?
Yeah. How do you tell the program what resources it should use? In many cases, this is something
like nprocs. Many programs use this OMP_NUM_THREADS environment variable, and they use that. For
example, NumPy uses that to determine how many processes it should use. They are all
listed in the documentation. So, there's many environment variables that sometimes set these
numbers. And if you look at the documentation of a library that you're using, it might say
that, hey, give it the number of processes with n processes or nprocs or nthreads or whatever.
like there might be various flags for there's no like consistent language across the board
so you need to look at your your application and if it provides a possibility of using
multiple processors and if it does you need to give the information to it
yeah and there's a good question what's the limit of the number of CPUs a program can use
Yes, that's an excellent question. And the answer is that it depends on the hardware.
Like in many clusters, you have compute nodes that might have a number of CPUs that might
run from, let's say, 28 to 256 or something like that. It might be small or it might be
very large. But because you're all limited into this one computer, so it depends on the
hardware available in your cluster.
And of course, you might reach the parallelism maximum.
At some point, it doesn't run any faster
after you reach a certain number of processors.
Usually, quite often, magical numbers
might be something like 8 or 16 or something.
But there might be something that
works with 64 or 128 as well.
Yeah. I guess it really depends on what it is you're doing.
Yeah. But usually it's on that ballpark. So we're talking about tens to hundred
processors usually. Yeah. So how long should people have to try this themselves? And is there
anything else to try other than what we just did? Let's just do this. I think that's enough.
and you can run stuff in the examples and run more exercises as a bonus exercise after the courses.
I will also note that in the exercise, there's a submission script that you can test out,
and in that we're using an environment variable called slurm CPUs per task,
which is very useful if you want the job to find out the number of CPUs
automatically. So Slurm will set this number if you ask for more than one CPU. So you can
use that in your code to determine numbers. But try it out.
Okay. How much time do you have, people?
Like 35, maybe?
Still 35. So that's seven minutes or six. Well, seven minutes. Okay. Yeah. Okay.
Then see you in a little bit. Yeah. Bye. Bye.
We're back.
Hello.
So what now?
I think we'll go straight to the next parallel part
and take all the questions later.
Yeah, if you want to fill out, I'm
adding the poll to the exercise block.
Forgot to add it previously.
So if you want to feel there, if you
managed to do the exercises, sorry about there
being quite not that much time for these.
But hopefully, you got it done.
But yeah, asking to see this, it's basically one flag.
So hopefully, you got it done.
But yeah, now we are switching gears to,
so this is quite a quick explanation
of the overview of the MPI, like parallelism, what it is.
So there was already a question in the notes about,
OK, how can I parallelize across multiple CPUs?
So how can I analyze across multiple computers, basically?
And this is why MPI originally was created, like the MPI thing.
So MPI stands for Message Passing Interface.
And it's basically like this kind of library that allows you to do
message passing between computers and different processes running on different CPUs
through various network messes.
When writing for these supercomputers, there's a high-speed interconnect usually connecting
these CPU nodes.
If you want to have a really large program, so if you think about a weather model, if
you want to predict the weather, you need to have a very big simulation of the weather
happening at different places, at different times, and you integrate the physics equations
to get the next time step of, okay, what is the weather going to be tomorrow?
And for that, you need a big computer to calculate together.
You need the whole simulation to be able to be calculated together.
And for that, MPI has been constructed, basically.
it's still a standard in many of the supercomputers when it comes to this kind of big-scale programs.
It's important to remember about MPI is that either your code uses MPI or it doesn't.
If your code hasn't been constructed around MPI, if it hasn't been constructed in a way
that it will use message-passing interface, it won't use it. So it's very important to remember
that if it uses MPI, if you see in the documentation that there's an MPI build of this,
or you can add MPI support or whatever, then it uses MPI. Or if you build a program from the
ground up to use MPI, then it uses MPI. But if it doesn't, then it doesn't.
Making a new MPI program is a very big process.
Yeah, depending on the program, but yes, usually you need to figure out whether your program can use MPI.
But there's already lots of programs, especially physics programs and that sort of stuff, that use MPI on the background.
And for those users of those programs,
this is a very good way.
Like, you just install your program
with the MPI capabilities available,
and then you can utilize multiple computers
at the same time.
Yeah.
So should we do the example?
Yes.
Let's look at the example.
So we have the Pi version written with MPI support.
And because you need to bake it into the program,
so the Python version doesn't cut it.
There is this MPI for Python that you can use
to use Python and MPI together,
which is a nice library if you want to start,
if you just want to use Python,
but that requires additional libraries.
So for this example, we are going to use C,
like C compiled, like C version of a program
does the exact same calculation that the Python one did, but it does it in C and it uses MPI.
Okay, and so how do I start? So in order to, usually when you have an MPI program,
the first thing you need to do is you need to load up the MPI installed by the cluster
administrators, because the MPI is tied directly to the queue system and it's tied to the network
infrastructure. So it's very laborious usually to install the MPI. So that's why the system
administrators usually provide it and you install your code using that MPI.
This will be different for every cluster.
Yes, yes. So if you run module spider MPI, open MPI is one flavor of MPI. That might be
be something you want to use.
So then we can compile our program using MPI CC.
So if you type `mpicc -o pi-mpi slurm/pi-mpi.c`.
Yeah.
So what this does is, yeah.
What it does is it compiles this `pi.mpi` executable that is now MPI-capable.
You can check what the source code is if you want to.
But now, okay, we have this.
Maybe you should try running it with srun, with the normal stuff, and see how it goes.
Like, if we just put like 10 minutes and 500 megabytes of memory and just run it.
So without anything, it should run similarly.
How many steps should I do?
Let's put the same 50 million.
It shouldn't take that long because it's C code,
so it's faster than the Python code.
Let's see.
I bet it will be very fast.
Yeah.
So it's quite a bit faster.
Should we SF it?
Yeah, sure.
Yeah.
So it said it used one second of CPU and took one second.
So it's quite a bit faster than the Python version.
So that's how it usually goes if you use the lower level stuff instead of like higher level
languages.
Of course, Python can be fast if you use the correct libraries, but in this case.
Yeah.
I mean, that's why you write a C library and run it from Python.
Or you use NumPy and that's fast itself.
But in this case, let's try now adding some more MPI tasks.
You notice that in the output,
it said that what was the computer's name,
where it was running,
and then it says something about rank.
MPI has these MPI ranks,
so basically, every CPU in the MPI tasks,
it's this rank number.
It's similar to the array ID,
but in this case,
they are like a collective.
So in the MPI, everybody works as a collective,
and they get this number.
So we can ask for more of these tasks.
So previously, when we saw the CPUs per task kind
of a situation, so these are now the tasks
that we are requesting.
So if you give the SRUN n tasks, yeah, nodes 1 and n tasks.
Let's go with 4, yeah.
Yeah, okay.
And let's add at least one zero at the end, so we get some like reasonable, like 10 times,
make it 10 times harder.
So maybe it runs for a few seconds.
Okay.
So, in this case, what we are asking the queue system, we are asking, okay, give me one computer
and give me four, on one computer, give me four of these MPI tasks.
So we didn't mention the CPUs per task here.
We are asking these MPI tasks.
And what it does basically is that when the program starts, it starts the individual programs
and then each of these connects into a collective that then solves the problem together.
But if you use the end tasks without an MPI program, you run into all sorts of problems
and the same program might run multiple times and overlap.
don't use the end tasks if you don't have an MPI program. Okay. Yeah. And I guess the pi-mpi,
we didn't tell it how many tasks there were, so it sort of automatically knows what's available.
Yes. It creates this communication world where everybody knows about each other and then they
can do the work together. And you might see here that the output is a bit scrambled because
everybody works independently and they might print out stuff in different orders. Some might
print out stuff before the other tasks. It's like one starting zero, it's done,
and then two and three report they're starting. But that's pretty typical when
you're trying to do this stuff. Anyway, should we SF it? Yes, let's do that.
It used nine seconds of CPU and the efficiency wasn't three seconds.
Yeah, because the efficiency wasn't that good because it's still so short.
So if we would have increased the.
Yeah, like these numbers are so short, it's not good statistics.
So, yeah.
It's clearly taking those times four and dividing nine by that.
Yeah.
Okay.
And in the notes, we have a good question of like, does it mean that the end tasks for
that we run for independent tasks and they are not independent.
They are a collective, like in MPI, everything is a collective.
So there's like four tasks running in the same collective, which is the whole program.
So let's say you would run with 30 computers, if you run in Mahti or if you run in Lumi
or somewhere like a really big machine, you might run with, let's say, a thousand processors.
And in those cases, you need to run with, let's say, 20 computers.
So you might ask for a thousand tasks and then get that from the queue system.
technically, it's not threads here, but it's independent processes that communicate between
each other. But if that doesn't make any sense to you, it really doesn't matter.
Yeah. But yes, so this MPI is still, for many bigger things, it's still very
like very heavily utilized.
But it's like many of the smaller programs,
it's usually better to use the array structure in addition
with the shared memory parallelism to run your stuff.
Because this requires your program
to support this from the ground up, basically.
OK, so what now?
We've got 12 minutes left.
Should we give people time to try it themselves and then come for a wrap-up?
Yes.
Okay.
Yeah, I will copy the commands we run.
In here also there's the SBatch script that you can use to run this in the queue.
And do note that if you're running this in the queue with the script, you will want to
add the srun before you run the program.
And the reason, well, it depends on the cluster, but in most clusters, you want to do this.
And the reason for that is that the srun basically ties the program to the queue system that
then tells each program that they're part of the collective.
If you don't run it with the `srun`,
they don't necessarily understand
that they're supposed to know about the other ones.
Because basically, Slurm starts multiple processes
at the same time.
And all of those call home and ask, who am I?
And then they start working as a collective.
So if you don't add the `srun`, then the program
doesn't necessarily work as intended.
Yeah.
OK, there's the exercise stuff.
So should we return at what time?
Maybe, again, five minutes and then have a wrap up.
Yeah, OK.
We'll take a short bit of time, see what you can do.
See you in five minutes.
and bye for now.
Hello, we're back, all four of us.
So yeah, what's the wrap up here?
From the notes, there's some good questions.
a question like, what does nodes and what does tasks mean?
The different MPI implementations.
This can get really deep really fast.
And I guess we're not even trying to go into it that deep.
Yeah.
So I highly suggest looking at our documentation
and other sites documentation if you plan
on using any of these frameworks.
Like the problem with, I would say,
like there was a great feedback that there
be more exercises, and I completely agree. But especially for these topics, it's very hard to
have exercises because they depend so heavily on the application. But the main thing to remember,
I would say, is to remember that these are the paradigms that are usable in the systems.
If you have a program that mentions something about threads or workers or whatever,
it usually means that you can use multiple CPUs.
And if you have something that mentions MPI,
then it usually can use MPI.
And remembering these words and these connections
allows you to then ask the queue
to provide you those resources.
But those exact flags you want to use
and exact implementations you want to use
differ based on the cluster.
And then it's good to look at the documentation.
But basically, in order to make the connection
okay, now we are talking about this sort of approach is very good, because then you can
make certain that your code uses all the resources it can use.
Yeah. And I see in the notes here, there's two questions about weird internal MPI errors,
which are caused by who knows what. And yeah, this is what I think of when I think of MPI. So,
So having to figure out the cluster thing,
get your code working, get all the problems solved,
it can make stuff run faster, but it takes some time
to figure it out.
And at least if you're at Aalto, come ask us
rather than digging into it, unless you just
want to dig into it, in which case, by all means, go ahead.
And I don't think we can really answer these here.
Who knows what it is?
I guess you've probably seen there's feedback of the day here.
You can start filling that in.
Is there anything about parallel or any other general questions we should answer before
we leave for the day?
I guess if so, write them down.
Any other general questions we may have missed from before or you'd like us to talk more.
So what's the expectations for day three now?
We covered what was in the schedule.
Are there many exercises and hands-on things tomorrow?
Does anyone know?
Well, at least in the GPU part, we
will be doing some small examples.
But again, it depends on the application you're using.
So it's quite a hard thing to say.
And in the LLM session, in the example,
we will definitely show you how you can do stuff, at least
here in Aalto.
And we show code that you can use to run local LLMs.
But yeah, we will have hands-on exercises, but of course, yeah.
Depends on how involved you want to be.
And we also have two philosophical sessions, one about how to ask for help with supercomputers,
which is a talk written by one of our collaborators in Norway, but I'll be
presenting. It sort of gives you some insight for, you know, when and how and what it's like
to ask for support. And then there's a wrap-up session at the end of the day which has 20
minutes budgeted. And what's usually happened other years, sort of all the instructors come
here and you can ask us all the questions about anything at all. So all the big broad things,
putting stuff together and we can see what happens there. So, yeah.
Yeah, so do stay for that. And I guess there's nothing special to prepare. If you have access
to the cluster, you can probably run the stuff we do tomorrow. The GPU stuff may be different
on different clusters. So it would be good to review the GPU info for whatever cluster you have
and then come prepared with that tomorrow to see if you can get it working.
Or even see if you can get it working over the night. If you are hungry for more exercises,
like all of the tutorial pages linked in the material, they have at the end multiple exercises.
Because if you want to do them, and even better, if you want to give feedback on if you had
done them, like how could they be improved, or which one would you want to see in the
course, let us know, that would be great.
But no worries, there's no homework, we don't force you to do something if you don't want
to do it.
But if you feel like you still have the hunger to write some Slurm scripts, do go and check
the tutorial, basically.
Yeah, OK.
Great.
Should we wrap up for now?
And I guess see you tomorrow at the same time.
Yeah.
Come prepared for all your stuff.
Yeah, OK, great.
Have a good, or wait, was there any other feedback questions?
No, no questions.
Lots of love for the cat.
Yeah, thanks for all the stuff.
Hopefully cats will come back tomorrow.
It's only morning, so it might be sleeping.
OK, great, see you later.
See you.
Bye.