you will hear later about this.
So to have a little break and consider if what you're doing is worth doing and I don't
want to, you know, depress anyone here, it's good to also consider and be aware of the
responsible conduct of research and specifically in the case of computation one could talk
about responsible computational research and you can write if you want in the notes document
what type of ethical or moral or legal issues that you might not even know that you have
or maybe you think that you have but they're not issues at all but in general what is making
you doubtful about your research. I wrote there, for example, that reproducibility,
which we have mentioned many times, is something that kind of I feel that often in my past
as a researcher that I had issues of reproducibility. What about you, [name]? What is your kind
of...
I completely agree. Either other people's stuff that I wanted to replicate or my own
stuff. In both cases, I had issues with getting things to run again.
Yeah. And you actually mentioned really well my own stuff, because one could think that
reproducibility is something, you know, I'm trying to figure out the universal law of
whatever. And, you know, it's good that other people repeat my experiment. But sometimes
the issue is really that I was doing six months ago something, and I was able to obtain some
results and I'm not able to rerun the same code anymore. Was it that the library has changed?
The operating system has changed? So this is very common. I've seen it many times with my work,
with other people's work. So a few of the topics that I will mention now, they cover or they show
you ways on how to deal with reproducibility issues. And you kind of already got a glimpse
of this when earlier we talked about Conda and the Conda environments and now someone was just
asking about Python 2 which is like traveling back in time and trying to reproduce or replicate
something from the past. So it's impossible to cover everything exhaustively when it comes to
research ethics and responsible conduct of research so I will try to give you a very
short five minutes intro but this page has lots of links that ideally every researcher should check
and read and be aware. The kind of conceptual framework that you can think of is the so-called
normative cascade which is how basically society works. You can understand that or you maybe feel
that there are these general ethics principles that can drive basically the creation of laws.
In the ideal case, ethics, all the good ethical principles would overlap completely with the laws
but in practice it is not like that, so there is never a full overlap between ethics and law.
And then of course laws will cause the creation or will influence so-called research policies,
so how the legislations stemming from the ethical principle will actually be applied in the work you
need to do with research. And then at the end of course it's the actual researchers that are
affected by the cascade. On the other hand, if the researchers notice that there are new
issues that the core ethical principle needs to be revised, they can together influence
the cascade and go back at the beginning and change the ethical principles.
So if we talk about the ethical principle, I'm not going to talk about as many ethical
principles. The Universal Declaration of Human Rights is one example. But in the context
of Research, I hope that everyone here, if you are in Europe, you should all read this
very short book which is the ALLEA European Code of Conduct for Research Integrity. Basically
there's everything there. If you know that book by heart, you just need to apply that
book whether you do computational science, I don't know, artistic research or whatever
type of research activities that you are doing. The four principles of the ALLEA Code of Conduct
are reliability, ensuring basically the quality of your of your research. Honesty, that what you
develop and what you do can be basically audited by others. So again, we're kind of covering this
type of reproducibility and transparency. And of course, respect is very important,
respect towards your colleagues, respect towards the administrator of your cluster, respect towards
the people that you will encounter on your career, others, authors in other universities
and more in general respects towards society and the ecosystem and so on.
And finally, accountability, given that, you know, from the accountability for the research
from the idea stage, the publication stage, and all its type of management and organisation,
which also requires you know this type of relationship between supervisor and mentors
and let's say junior researchers who are supervised and so on.
So that is kind of the general level and then from this core ethical principle there are
many legislations that apply to research where I will not go into the detail of any of these
But the typical case, maybe I can ask this actually to [name],
have you ever experienced in your work
that some researcher thinks
that they're not working with personal data,
but actually they were processing personal data?
Almost the other way around,
is there anything that's not personal data?
Exactly.
Yeah, I think the biggest issue with respect to personal data
is that it's really, really difficult to define what exactly personal data is, or rather what
does not constitute personal data anymore.
Yeah, I totally agree.
It's very difficult to anonymize data and we see this, you know, very often with people
who come and ask for help that they think that they're not presenting personal data
because whatever direct identifiers are missing.
But if it's a data about an individual, then let's just agree that it's personal data rather
than trying to mathematically demonstrate that the probability of re-identifying this
person is whatever is your favorite threshold.
But in general, again, here we don't have time and maybe we don't even have the energy
to go through legislations, but at least this list that is mentioned here is something that
you should be aware if your research kind of you know applies in this with this type of data.
And then of course from the core ethical principle to the legislation and regulations we have the
kind of national policies or even university level policies. So in the page you find some
links related to Aalto University but if you're from other university most likely you have the
similar policy whether it's about the ethical review if that's what you need in your research
or open science policies, open data policies, code of conduct and things like that.
So then at the end it's you the researchers who will depending on the case need to consider
these policies and this legislation and maybe these core ethical principles and trying to do
the best you can. I want to stress here that sometimes the best practices are some,
how can I say, state that it will never be reached and I really like that in this paper
by Wilson 2017 that is linked here, they mention good enough computational practices in this case
because sometimes it's trying to avoid that type of sloppy practices so that by adopting good
enough practices you can, you know, do the best you can and maybe slowly adopt more good enough
practices until you reach the best practices. I would like to add that one problem with
best practices is that very often to actually achieve best practices you need multiple people
working on the same thing and one person doesn't have all the knowledge and very often also not the
capabilities to do all things that would be best practice because it's just getting too much.
So this concept of good enough practices is something that is quite important in my opinion.
I totally agree. In this figure here, I tried to represent this is not exhaustive. I'm sure
there's more best practices in computational science and there's more, how should we call
them, worst practices. But in this continuum, so basically in the green side, we would have,
you know, that all the data is archived with the DOI, there is data versioning, we have protocols,
register protocols for data collection, version control for the code, so full reproducibility,
unit tests, you can add you know all the things that also we have mentioned today earlier,
and on the other end you really have this case that there are no backups, there's no documentation,
no readme file, no idea how to rerun things, no dependencies listed, no history log on which
script was from before the other. So I'm not asking you now, [name], to disclose something
sensitive, but if you put yourself in this type of continuum, or maybe let's rephrase this. Have
you had experience of some worst practices, actually? Okay, I have myself been in the
situation that I had code that was not documented well enough and that where I then two years later
was trying to think okay how did I do this, where did I put the configuration files, where did I do
this and that and needed to go back and not completely reinvent but it took me quite some
some time to set this up again. I have seen enough kind of bad things online from others
where it's like, you're providing the data, but informants that are completely unusable
and that essentially it would feel kind of more honest
to just not provide the data.
And I hope that I'm nowadays somewhere
on the yellow to greenish border there,
because yeah, I also won't be always able
to go through all the different things
that should be on the list.
Because it's also quite a bit of things
come with a lot of administrative work,
which essentially means
while you're doing the administrative work
on a couple of things,
you're not actually doing anything
to progress the project that you have.
And that's getting frustrating very quickly.
I agree. And the administrative work is sometimes not even valued, meaning that, for example,
I wrote this here, this single folder for all projects where all the researchers from
the same group have read and write. And, you know, basically I've seen myself, I was part
of this type of, you know, gigantic research folders where things, I don't know, more
or less self-organized, but never really, you know, nobody had the time to do this type
of administrative work, even though the policies, whether they come from EU horizon or whether
they come from Academy of Finland, they kind of stress the importance of managing the data
and managing the software. But, you know, maybe you get a very good point earlier that
when it's not anymore this type of single person job that needs to do everything from
inventing the idea, collecting the data, writing the code, if it becomes a teamwork that then
you have the data steward, the research software engineer, and then it's the researchers,
the expert can focus on their expertise. And then in the end, best practices and even
administrative tasks can be taken care of. Just along those lines, I often see the problem that
that I would like to follow best practices,
but the best practices are written down so vaguely that,
yeah, like I just said,
they stress that you should care about data management,
but how?
What should you actually do?
These kind of really concrete guidelines,
they are, at least to me, very often lacking.
Just to mention it again,
with the administrative stuff that is undervalued,
especially as a researcher
that does something with personal data,
you fill in the same data into 20 different forms
to submit to 20 different places for approval.
And it gets really frustrating.
Why can't you just do this once?
and everyone who wants to know something can extract from what you just submitted.
So these are the kind of things that then lead to people not following protocol, not, yeah.
Yeah.
But I would say in general, I feel that things are much better.
I don't know if it's because I've been involved in dealing with these issues,
but maybe there is more awareness in general among researchers.
It is getting better. Also because higher levels are enforcing it more.
That's too good. All right, but basically to conclude, this page also has this little mention
of cyber security and again the point here, you know, it's not to give a course on cyber
security and most likely your organization has a mandatory course on cyber security.
What is very important that I often try to remind to our researchers is that they need to understand
the classification of information, meaning that they need to understand whether it's a script,
whether it's a piece of data, whether it's your internal note or the picture for the summer trip
of the department. You need to understand is it public data, is it internal data,
is it confidential or is it secret. In general you could assume that most of the work we do
goes between the confidential or internal if you are for example drafting a paper or
still working on something that you're not ready to fully make public.
But then of course there's also lots of public work that we do whether it's our open source
code projects web pages and things like that.
Maybe I would say that a minority of us need to work with secret data but of course there
There are legislations, for example,
when you need to reuse health data,
so data that was collected for medical purposes.
There are legislation that forces to be secret.
Then in this last three minutes, we
were discussing a few days ago that it's
important to maybe mention what could be the issues,
whether they are ethical or legal.
It's a blurt of using generative AI in your daily work.
Now here, I try to think of many types of issues,
but to keep it short without,
you can read the whole thing yourself.
In general, I see when it comes to computational science
as to write code, that there could be
this type of unwanted plagiarism issues
that I might be, that the generative AI
might synthesize some code that is verbatim,
some excerpt from a library,
but then I might not realize this,
most likely I would not start searching
if that code is verbatim from a library.
And then the issues becomes that maybe that library
had a specific type of software license
that wouldn't allow me to reuse it
unless I also adopt the same license.
There's no point here to go down to these details,
but you can understand that there are multiple risks
of using this type of generative AI
without carefully considering basically the output.
So again, if you are so-called vibe coding afternoon project
because you just want to make some funny cat pictures
through some code, maybe it's OK.
But if you're writing the core functions for your research
analysis, and you are not sure if the output
from this generative AI system is the actual output
that you would need, you need to reconsider or maybe
ask for help from other experts for doing code review
things like that. Maybe one that I like to mention is recently they noticed that
when you work for example with Python you might need to import some NumPy or Pandas or whatever
and if you don't have them in your system you need to pip install NumPy, Pandas and so on.
And recently there are some consistent hallucinations of packages and then in the Python
ecosystem but also in many other languages there is this type of typosquatting so that
malicious people actually have created packages with a similar name and then you do a typo when
you or the generative AI does a typo and then suddenly you have basically you know some
malware installed in your system. I would like to add something that also recently came up
when it comes to tools allowing the LLM to collect and process additional data or additional
public data, and particularly if that same thing also allows the model to access some
private information, because there have been recent attacks where essentially the public
data that was consumed by the LLM contained instructions to the LLM, at which point it
generated content that, when you looked at it, had image links or things in there that
essentially were leaking private information.
So essentially my recommendation is assume that the LLM is just another human, just another
random human and think about whether you want to give it access to whatever you are currently
giving it access to and that includes the whole conversation that you're currently having with it.
I had to quote this, it's not [name]'s quote but [name] often says this that there is no cloud
computing it's just someone else's computer and in my opinion it's the whole point because unless
you run these LLMs locally and truly locally in your machine you're just sending data to
somebody else's computer and even if they promise don't worry we will never give this data to anyone
you know it's exactly yeah all right but hopefully this was motivational enough to think if what
you're doing is good, is right, is moral, is ethical, is legal and so on. Feel free to
write something in the chat of this type of philosophical thoughts but I guess it's time
for a break and then later we can go back to code and computing. Thank you [name] for
the nice conversation and I guess see you in 10 minutes
I don't see any clock now so 12 p.m. bye