Okay, yeah, some fun with the streaming stuff there. Okay, so welcome.
The first talk is this,
How to ask for help with supercomputers.
This is actually not my talk,
not my slides, though I've contributed a bit to it.
It's by one of our colleagues,
[name], who worked in Norway,
basically doing a lot of the same stuff that we do.
What's the point of this talk?
To give you a perspective of whenever you come to us,
when should you come to us and how to come with us,
and ask us things.
So yeah, what kind of help is available? When to ask? Especially this like how to write a message
that looks good and we can answer quickly because we probably both want to be able to
for you to be able to answer stuff or to have good messages so we can answer quickly
and a little bit more advice on getting started. So yeah, here's the credits.
There's some people you know there. Okay, so when you need help with something,
what are the different places or ways you can ask for the help? So there's
different things available. So often a good place to start is asking your
colleague. So it's really simple to ask someone who sits at a desk next to you, hey, have you had
this problem? If they say yes, then that helps you. If they say no, then you can keep working
on it yourself before asking again. There's these official, like, live help sessions,
garage office hours, stuff like that, search engines, chat, the real information.
One interesting place is that you can search, if you're at Aalto, the issue tracker we have.
So we ask people to make their issues there in public, so that way you can help all the
next generation of things. That also encourages us to give better answers, because we know that
it won't be helping just you, but all the people in the future. Anyway, people sometimes wonder
when do you ask for help? So should you work on it forever? Are you going to get bitten if you go
ask for help? Is that seen as a bad thing? So my philosophy is that computers are way too complex
these days and no one can possibly tend to know everything they need to know about it. It's just
too much. Even within our team here, we have a policy that if you don't know something, ask
someone with a really low threshold because it's just not worth spending time trying to
solve a problem that's already been solved. Unless, of course, you want to
do an exercise to solve it. But, you know, your exercises are probably the actual research or
other work you're doing and not some solved computer problem. But do at least try a little
bit yourself, do your googling, start at the lower levels, and then work up as you see it's needed.
You know, basically do enough that you learn something so next time maybe you can
solve it yourself or know where to look for the future.
So this is an advice I got when I asked someone what do you wish you knew now that
what do you know now that you wish someone had told you? They had this philosophy. So,
for every problem they had, they set an internal limit in their mind. So, they might say, okay,
I'm trying to get Python to run on the cluster. I think it's reasonable that it should take me
an hour to do that. So, I'll work on it for an hour, and then I'll go to the
Science IT Garage and ask for help because that's the reasonable thing. If it's
not done within an hour, then there's clearly something wrong here that is taking much longer
than it should. When you ask for help, if you come especially to our live thing, you can ask,
can you do this for me? Can we do it together? Or you could ask, should this be a hard problem?
am I looking the right direction and should I keep going with where I am?
And at least if you come to us and you say, is this the right direction? Like, can you help
point me in the right documentation? Am I looking at the right page? We're happy to say, yeah, it
looks like the right page. And then you can keep working and come back the next day if you need to.
So, I guess if you're seeing this talk, you've already seen a lot of the people that are on
the other side here. But the people answering are also humans and we're also not great at
everything. We're not superheroes or something. We just try to be as good as we can.
So this says something for the other side. So we do a lot of work in our team to try to
teach, like remind people that we need to be nice when people are coming to us. So we have
people at all sorts of different levels of education, or not education, but different
points in their careers, knowing more or less who are studying computers or are not studying
computers and it's just some sort of tool, and we need to be respectful and understanding of
all these different types of things. And on the other hand, realize that, yeah, like it says,
Because we don't know everything either.
We're also really busy with possibly too many problems.
So this is an example from the author of these slides.
So someone wrote a super long message saying something, and it was actually hard for the
person who was reading it to figure out what you even needed.
So they responded with this one-line email saying,
oh, I guess you want to get the code.
Sure, here it is.
So it could have been a much quicker request there.
It's good to have a good email subject and things like that.
So of course, you don't know what the actual problem is,
but try to give a little bit of clarity of what it is.
Because when someone goes to the issue tracker,
they see a bunch of titles.
and they'll start at looking at the stuff that they think there's the highest chance of them
knowing and answering first. So that is something like my job is crashing today but not tomorrow
or yesterday. Then we know, okay, so this might be something that has changed in the last day.
we can look in there more quickly.
It's good to have all this different context.
So the more we know about what happened better.
Sometimes someone will send a request saying,
hey, my job isn't working.
But they don't say what cluster they're on.
So if you send it to the Alto people, that's obvious.
But if you send it to, for example, CSE people,
that's not obvious at all.
And that just makes more time that has
to be spent to figure that out.
Or we have to send something back saying,
can you please tell us what you actually did?
And that's not fun.
And we don't want to just say, reply always with,
well, we don't really like your request, so just tell us more
so we don't have to do anything.
The more initial stuff, the better.
So anything special that might be here?
Is there anything special about the environment?
Are we allowed to look at your files directly?
And so on.
OK, and this is something that I had thought up.
So there, as soon as you see these lists of how to ask
questions, and it's a long multi pages of do this, and this,
and this, and this.
And that's basically saying, we don't
want you to ask questions because we
I want you to have done all this other stuff first.
So I tried to narrow it down to like a really simple thing.
What are the most important things for us to know to answer
without making it seem too overwhelming?
And this is what it is.
So has it ever worked?
So if you're trying to run your first job on the cluster,
that's a lot different than the jobs works yesterday,
but not today.
If it's never worked at all,
that means we need to start with a much broader perspective.
If something worked yesterday, but not today,
and you know it's the same, we know to immediately ask the person that's been working on the cluster
recently and, hey, have you changed anything? Did we just break something there?
And what are you trying to accomplish? So not just like I'm trying to run this job on the cluster,
but I'm trying to run, what's the program? I'm trying to run PyTorch on the cluster to do
inference or whatever. So we'll see a little bit more about this later, but having the big picture
of what you're trying to do is important, because if we don't have the big picture,
we might give a too specific or too general answer somehow. Actually, no, I'll come back to this
later. So what did you do? So what have you actually typed and done there? If you say,
my job doesn't work, but you don't give the job script, well, we'll be like,
please tell us the job script or whatever.
The more you can copy and paste, the better.
I recommend don't use screenshots because we
can't copy and paste text from screenshots.
Also, it doesn't appear in
the e-mail messages we get and so on.
But go to the terminal,
copy, paste it into the message.
It doesn't matter if it looks bad,
we can dig through it.
And this is like the exact commands you ran, the files,
stuff like that.
It's usually better to give more stuff rather than too few
stuff, because we're quick at scanning through all this text
and seeing what we need.
And it doesn't take you very long
to copy and paste relative to trying to describe it.
And finally, what do you need?
So are you looking for a complete solution to someone
to solve the problem for you and give it back to you?
Or are you looking for, hey, is this expected?
Should I keep working on it?
If you say, I just need help with this one little bit,
that's OK.
If you say, hey, I'm completely overwhelmed with what this is,
can we look in more depth and do it from the beginning?
Then we can start reserving time and doing it that way.
Especially if you need something small,
say that you need something small.
That helps a lot.
Yeah, this is the tell us what you tried.
So have you tried narrowing it down?
Is it failing in only one way or multiple ways?
There's different ways to tell us
how you've done the narrowing.
And this is something that has been called the XY problem.
There's some website around it.
I don't know where it came from.
But the problem is that someone has a problem.
They try to do some solution to the problem.
The solution doesn't work, so they ask
about what the solution is.
Like, I can't run this or that script.
We go, we help them with that solution,
and then it turns out that they were
trying to do the original problem that wasn't actually
a good solution to the problem.
So we could have said, hey, you're
trying to get a content environment solved,
do you know we already have an environment
that's designed for LM usage
and it probably has what you need,
so why don't you use that instead?
So basically this big picture is quite important
so we can see, do we need to take a step back
and go down a different way?
Also, if you don't do this,
there's a problem that the staff will answer
the one exact question you answer
then say okay it's done and close the issue because they get measured by how quickly they
close issues and how few issues there are so yeah
I guess this is more advice for us that are here but if you're ever helping people
think of these kind of things so it's important that we the staff answering make the person
realize or think that they're valued and we want to actually help them. The worst thing to do is
send back different links saying have you read these pages first what you need is in here and
then like a two sentence answer or something like that. So we try to consider this and do well
but if we're ever not perfect we're sorry and it's okay to let us know.
So when you send requests, I guess
this is perhaps more from other people.
I guess it basically applied to us.
So when you send a request in written format,
it goes to a issue tracker.
And then there's a bunch of issues there.
And the people coming have to find what's available.
So at least within Aalto, we sort of all
try to look at it and ask the right person
to answer it no matter what time it is. But at some point, in some organizations, there's like
one person that's answering for one week and then they have multiple weeks when they're off
and doing other work. So there can be very different types of people answering these questions.
And if something takes too long and you don't get an answer, then consider asking a different way.
if you're at Alto, then come to our daily garage
and ask questions.
Because if we get a written message
and it's not clear what the question really is,
people are always going to first work
on the ones that are more clear.
And if you come talk to us live,
then it is much easier to do this quick back and forth
and narrow things down and that works better.
OK, we're a bit running out of time,
so let's not go into this too much.
But example request, I'm this username.
I'm trying to do something.
I can log into the other clusters.
I can't log into this cluster and the exact message
that's there.
This is a pretty good request.
So it gives the context.
It gives what does work.
And then it gives exactly what doesn't work.
And from us, at least me as a cluster admin, if I see this,
I immediately know what to look at.
And I will check something.
Here's another request.
So it says, I'm not sure this is the right support.
I'd like to do this and that.
They're asking for a web server and a database.
But then they say, this is the kind of thing,
like this is what the big problem is.
So we look at this and can say, hey, for 2,000 records,
that's really not much.
Maybe you don't need a full database.
And here's a much easier way to do things.
And we save you and us time.
So it was very important that they
gave this extra piece of information
about sort of the size of the problem and the usage.
Okay, maybe I'll just stop here.
You can read here a little bit later
or maybe I'll summarize.
Yeah, so the summary here is that
when you go to a new computer for the first time,
don't immediately start with the biggest thing possible.
Start with the smallest job.
Like we started with an interactive job on one core
and then a serial job, a batch job on one core.
and then a few multi-processing. So start small and slowly work up so you can tell at exactly what
point it stops working and it stops being efficient. And then that helps you to figure
out only one thing at a time and it helps us to know where the problem is. Okay, and with that
being said, I will shrink the screen. When you are with us,
we have this thing called the Scientific Computing Garage. This is an Aalto University thing.
I think some other people might be trying it some. But the basic idea is that
that every workday at 1 o'clock, we, as in a lot of us,
instructors and more, are in Zoom.
And you can drop by and ask us any questions.
This is a time you can join and share screen and sort of show
us what's going on.
You can ask, oh, is this a real problem?
Should I do this?
Should I file a issue request about this?
And so on.
And well, that's basically it. So it tells a lot about stuff here.
Join us and ask for help with a low threshold. We have multiple people coming per day.
And yeah. Oh, and finally, I'm running out of time here, but if you're new and you're at
Alta University, we have people that have time in the next few weeks specifically to help with
new problems and new questions. So, by all means, if you're new, okay, basically everyone that's
starting new projects as a summer intern, we're trying to have time for you to come and spend
an hour, half an hour, whatever, talking with someone live about how you're doing the problem.
And we can't do everything in one garage next week, but we'd like for all of you to try to find the time to come by and have a quick chat with us.
And we think we can probably do it in the next month.
So, who knows how this will work, maybe we'll send an email with more instructions for reserving time or something like that.
But, um, yes, please do.
So OK, with that being said, I'm done.
Hopefully this was a sort of useful starting point.
And next we have GPUs, I believe.