we'll jump from how to ask questions into a topic that raises a lot of questions.
So GPUs are the kind of stuff that often, like nowadays they are very popular,
so they introduce a lot of questions to our users. So let's maybe start by talking about
what is a GPU? Maybe we could look at quickly into this sort of a diagram and maybe use that
as a starting point for the GPU. It's a bit small. [name], how would you describe a GPU?
I think GPU is also a component of a computer that does the calculation
but in a faster way. It's very good for parallelism. If you have small calculations,
it's very good for it. But otherwise, the CPU is the way to go.
Yeah. So, GPUs are, like [name] said, they're like a specific kind of an extra hardware component
in the computer. And usually GPUs, they are like special cards or pieces in the computer
that have this graphical processing unit that has multiple computing cores inside of it.
So basically, I hope the font isn't too small here, but basically there's usually like,
like you transfer your program and your data into the GPU,
it has its own memory
and it has a lot of these parallel computing cores
and you can run various kinds of calculations on the GPU
in parallel using all of these cores.
But because it's a separate thing to the CPU,
the central processing unit,
it means that the code needs to specifically be written to utilize these cards because
otherwise it won't use it. You cannot run normal code on a GPU, it needs to be a GPU code or needs
to be using libraries that use GPUs in order to be able to access all of the power inside the GPU.
Yeah.
So how do you, like, nowadays there's lots of different GPUs available.
So [name], how would you choose between, like, how would you know what is inside your
GPU or what kind of GPUs are available nowadays?
So I can talk about Triton, but in general, when you're talking about the GPU, you can
see the model of the GPU but the beside the model and like that the specifics
about the watt and energy usage and everything, the most important thing
that you have to consider is the memory available for the GPU because as [name]
mentioned the GPU memory is different than the normal RAM memory of the
computer and the reason is they have a specific memory inside the GPU component
and it's like very faster to write and read from. So if you go to the bottom of
this page, [name], we have a list here that shows the different GPU types that we have,
and also it shows the memory as well.
It's a bit narrow, but if you can scroll...
Yeah, I'll try to change the size a bit.
Yes.
Okay.
If you go to the left a bit, yes.
So now, for example, you can see that different GPUs have different number of, amount of memory
that they have.
For example, one have 616, one have 81, the advanced ones that we have, and at the moment
the state of the art of the industry is 141 gigabytes.
So it depends what you are choosing.
You also have another thing that's called the architecture of a GPU, which I would say
you are not an advanced user and you haven't heard of architecture of the GPU, you don't have to be
worried about that. But just to have an idea, if you are compiling your program for a specific
architecture, it doesn't run on another architecture. You can think of it as like
ARM, like in a CPU world, ARM versus Intel, or like in the old days like 32 bits versus 64 bits.
So if your program is compiled for another architecture, it doesn't run another architecture.
Nowadays in the AI world, some of the advanced techniques like flash attention and these kind of
things that we were going to talk about in the LLM part are actually
compiled for a specific architecture, so you cannot use it in the old ones.
But if you haven't heard of it, you don't have to worry about it and you can just
go ahead and learn your program. Yeah, like in most cases, when you are going to be using the
GPUs, you're going to use them through some, like in vast majority of cases, you're going to be
using them through some libraries that are compiled with various backends of this architecture,
so they can run on different versions of the GPUs. So the question usually arises that when we
talked about, let's say the memory and the architecture and stuff like that, is that
the GPU you choose, especially in case of Triton, where we have so many different
packagings of these GPUs, is that it depends quite a bit on the problem that you have.
If you have a very small problem, like you try to do some, let's say the first MNIST
data set, PyTorch model or whatever, you try to do a quick AI test thing, it won't require
any much resources. So it will run basically in the same time with any of these GPUs because
the model is so small, it cannot use all of the compute capability in the card and it doesn't use
all of the memory in the card. So it doesn't matter which thing you use. But if you're going to be
doing the LLMs that we'll be talking about later. You might have heard a lot of talk about the
parameters, like how many parameters these models have and stuff like that. The number of parameters
means also the amount of memory consumed by storing those parameters in memory increases.
If you have these big LLM models or stuff like that, they require a lot of memory. In those
cases you're usually forced to use the GPUs in the higher end that have more memory available.
But you notice that the total amount of GPUs, we have a lot of these V100 cards, so we have
plenty of these smaller cards that you can use for smaller projects. And it's not bad to use
GPUs, like different kinds of GPUs. But maybe we should quickly show how you can see, how
you can differentiate or choose between these. And how do you do it in many clusters in Aalto
as well is by setting up in your code which partition you want to use. So you can, there's
other ways as well, but the easiest way is to set up the different partitions. So, when you submit
a Slurm job, you want to give it that, hey, I want the card from this partition. Or you can
put multiple partitions over there, and you can use slurm-e in your terminal to view all of the
available partitions. It will print a lot of information over here, but what you see is that
you can get the partition names and you can of course look at the reference as well. But if you
want to use a certain kind of a GPU, you usually need to provide the partition that I want to use
this sort of GPU. That is true. I guess in our cluster you can also make the constraint for the
architecture as well, but the GPU partition is the easier way to go. And if you don't specify
a partition, but you request for a GPU, the Slurm would automatically assign to all of the
partitions available, except for the one that you have to specifically ask for, the advanced ones
that we have, which you specifically have to ask for it to be assigned to that specific partition.
Yes, and usually when you're working with these cards, quite often, like I mentioned
previously, you are going to be using them through some libraries. You're not actually
going to be using them directly because all of these cars, they utilize something called CUDA.
You might have heard about it. CUDA is this computing stack that NVIDIA provides. AMD has
its own called ROCm, but basically they are the same kind of idea. And in there, there's usually
you have the GPU, which is the hardware part, and then you have this driver library that is
installed on the GPU nodes, and then you have some CUDA library that your code uses to actually do
the calculations. So in the case of most cases that you see, you need to have some CUDA library
installed into your environment or you need to use a module with a CUDA in order to actually
use the GPUs. And in most cases, you probably will use something like you install PyTorch with
GPU capability and it will bring you the corresponding CUDA toolkit that you need.
So that's about installation or setup that we forgot to mention.
Usually you want to have the specific CUDA toolkit for your program that will then use the GPUs.
But, okay, maybe we should mention also other ways you can use these, maybe interactive
usage.
Yeah, that's actually a good part because GPUs and GPU computing can be a bit tricky
and when you have a large program, as [name] mentioned, and if you have a large pipeline
of training or doing simulations. It's very hard to and if it doesn't work it's very hard to
understand why it's not working. So it's very good to start small at the beginning and when you are
when you you know that your code works then you can jump to the higher end of GPUs if you need them.
So in the SLURM that the partitions that [name] is showing we have a partition called the
gpu debug partition if you jump back to the yeah it's i don't think we have it here but
yeah it's probably yeah i think it's mentioned somewhere there but uh yeah i think it's mentioned
here yes yes uh so we have a partition called gpu debug and the limitation is you have only 30
minutes of the time uh so it's like very good for testing your program or start uh running your
program at the beginning for one run or one epoch if you're training a neural network and then see
if it works then you can request for a large node. The reason is sometimes if your code doesn't work
it's not your fault but like there are a lot of things that you have to be considerate about
and it's good to start small because if you request for a large one, one it's harder to debug
Second, you have to wait probably longer time in the queue,
so then your program would run and then it would fail.
Yeah, if it fails, you can run
the partition with the debug and see what is going on.
It's hard to work with the terminal.
There are some ways you can
connect with the VS Code and everything,
but come and ask us in the garage.
It's a bit complicated to talk about it here.
But since the beginning of this year,
we also have the GPU debug available with some conditions on the Jupyter on demand.
Should we show that, [name]?
Maybe we could show the interactive uses from the terminal.
If we want to reserve a GPU, like if we go to the, like how do we get a GPU?
Let's first take one from a GPU debug partition.
So what we do is we would run the exact same things that we would do normally.
Like we run the srun, we would add all of the things we want to have here.
So let's say like 10-minute job.
And I'm going to run a program called NVIDIA SMI.
This was mentioned in the monitoring part that this NVIDIA SMI is a program that shows what
the GPU is doing. Basically, it shows what the GPU is doing. But currently, I haven't requested
any GPUs here. I haven't actually added any GPU requests here. I can add that by first adding the
partition I wanted to use. So I want from the GPU debug and then I can say GPUs one.
So that's the only thing you need and GPUs equal one. And now if I submit this to the queue,
it's allocated resources and let me make this a bit
And you can see over here, it prints out the output of the nvidia-smi, so now it only runs this
one command in the node and then it returns back.
And you can see that I have a GPU called Tesla V100, 16 gigabytes.
So I got the 16 gigabyte V100 card.
So, yeah, as you can see, like the GPU debug is almost instantly allocate the resources
because it has the limitation of 30 minutes.
So usually there are like free GPUs for you to get allocated.
And then you don't have to wait a long time for that for the slurm queue to get your resources.
But at the same time, the topic that I want to mention is that when we are talking about
GPUs because they are more expensive at the moment as well because of the demand and everything.
If you look at the stock of the NVIDIA, you would notice this.
But be more careful and be more responsible about the GPU usage because we don't have a lot,
we have much, but we don't have enough, I would say.
So when you are requesting, try to not be, like, make it idle or, like, don't actually utilize it.
So if you notice that you are not utilizing the GPU, the utilization is not high or you are not,
I don't know, like, your program is not as fast as possible, please come to us and we will try to
help you with optimizing your code. So your simulation or your training will run faster and
also, we would make the computation that is available as much as we can.
Yeah, especially the interactive usage, it can get quite quickly. You could use the GPU,
but whenever you're not actually running GPU code, the GPU isn't doing anything.
So, it's just waiting there. So, it can quite quickly just underutilize all of the GPUs and
because the demand is heavy, it's a good idea to utilize them as much as possible.
What we usually recommend is that if you, let's say, want to do a training or something,
like a deep learning training, if you can do it one batch, basically, if you can train it for one
batch or one epoch, you can train it for a thousand epochs, basically, because you can do it, just
continue doing what you're doing previously. So just run it longer, basically. So it's quite
easy to run them usually in the debug partition. You can just run the GPUs in the debug partition
like a small job. And once you have run the code, you notice that, okay, now it has run.
And now, basically, I can start coding again without preserving the GPU for the whole of my
coding session. But let's quickly look at what the GPUs can actually do. So, this is again,
like, unfortunately, a bit of a toy model. So, what we're going to be doing is from the
the documentation we're, whoops, clicked the wrong link.
We are going to be running this Pi example again,
our friend Pi, and what we're going to be doing
is that we are going to be building our own GPU code.
So let's first check which folder am I in.
I can get, sorry, terminal, I'm hiding, yes.
I'm currently at the wrong folder, so let me go to the work directory and then I'm going
to go to the hpc-examples.
What we are going to be doing is now building a GPU program, basically.
For that, we need a compiler and a CUDA toolkit.
This is basically, if you don't use a program that is pre-built, and most of them nowadays
are, but some aren't.
And if you don't use that sort of program, you need to give this massive, usually these
flags when you're compiling in order to make it so that it works with different architectures,
the code works with different GPUs.
And now we have a program called pi-gpu.c.
So you can try this in your own cluster in a minute.
You can try it out.
And let's run this pi-gpu in the queue.
So let's add the GPU.
So this is the exact same kind of a Py calculating code, but this time it's written so that it
gives us the GPUs.
So I will add all of the Slurm flags.
So we want the interactive terminal,
and then 10 minutes, 500 megabytes of memory, one GPU,
and we run in the debug partition.
And then the pi-gpu.
And let's give it some nice numbers.
So let's say, because this is so much faster than the CPU one,
So let's say like, is it a hundred million?
Yes.
So previously we run, yeah, yeah.
It's, it's way too low.
Uh, so this is like billion.
So previously we run with the CPU.
It took 40 seconds to run 50 million and it's basically instantaneous
to run a billion with the GPU.
So it's, they, they are for this sort of calculations.
GPUs are much, much faster, so in order to actually utilize the GPU, we need to, well,
even add more zeros there. They are way too fast for this sort of a program.
So, you can see already the power compared to the CPU. And this is, of course, just a toy example.
But now we can of course write a script that would do the same exact thing.
So here's an example script that would run the same thing in the queue.
But maybe it would be a good time to have some exercises.
So you can try out the demo that I just posted here.
Yeah, of course, the major caveat is that in your cluster,
the modules might be different.
So in order to get the CUDA module,
you probably need to maybe load a different compiler
or different module.
So they might be different
and the partitions might be different.
So now it's a good time to also look at the documentation
and check in your cluster, what are the GPU partitions,
what GPUs are available
and what CUDA modules, for example, are available.
I just want to add one more thing that although GPUs are very powerful to use, but it doesn't
mean that it's for every code.
So every code is different and if your code knows how to do depolarization and you have
a small task to do, I would say, they are very good, but it's not for everyone.
It's not for every computation.
For this Pi example, it's a very, very good match and it can be run a lot faster than the CPU
because you can do all of the calculations in parallel.
Let's have the exercises. We'll probably answer a few of the questions in the notes.
like we'll answer them through the exercises and we'll probably answer a few of those and
then we'll have a break. So try out the demo that I posted here. I'll post this into the
notes as well.
Yeah.
And hello, we are back.
So I hope you had a possibility to attend the exercise, it was quite a short amount
of time, sorry about that.
There was a lot of good questions or good discussion in the notes.
So there was a question about the GPU RAM, and what is the rule of thumb for requesting
RAM and GPU?
So the RAM in the computer and the VRAM, like the RAM in the GPU, they are different.
they often are different when you're doing all sorts of calculations. So as an example,
like if you're doing machine learning or kind of a thing, you usually need to reserve the VRAM for
the model that you're going to be training and the data that the model is going to be taking in and
the data that the model is going to be putting out. But you often don't need to reserve data
for the whole data set, unless you load the whole data set into the GPU memory.
But quite often, the data set doesn't even fit into the GPU memory.
So you have a situation where you might request more RAM, like the normal RAM,
and then you have a GPU with a different amount of VRAM.
But sometimes, of course, like so often the situation is something like you might request
the same amount of RAM as the GPU RAM or a bit more, but it depends on how your data is going
to be loaded into the GPU. But they're different, and you cannot request a different amount of
VRAM unless you choose a different GPU. You cannot partition or split up that VRAM in any way.
you will either get the card or you won't get the card.
It is also true about the computation as well, right? When you are requesting the GPU,
the whole GPU is for you, the whole RAM of the GPU and also the whole compute nodes.
Yes. And there was also a question about what is the difference between the GPUs, so
the different numbers here. So they are like the technical numbers, what is the brand of the GPU,
basically. And the newer the brand, they are usually faster, they have more memory,
they are faster, they have also some more advanced specialized computing units for
certain kinds of calculations that we don't have time to go through here. But basically,
that's sort of a situation happening there. But usually it's like the newer is more powerful
and bigger. That's the situation.
Yeah, and there's lots of great questions here that we'll answer, but we need to go to break,
I think, at this point. We'll return to the questions here, and we'll talk a lot.
we'll answer all of them here and we can after the LLM session we have the panel discussion where we
can probably raise some of these questions there as well but in the LLM section you will hear more
about like what is the actual use like how do you actually use the GPUs like how do how does it
actually look like when you use the GPUs but yeah in order to get to there we first need to take a
bit of a break. So, we'll be back at 11.10. Is that good?
That's good, yeah.
Yeah, we'll be back at 11.10. Bye.
See you.