So we have the wrap-up and summary.
So maybe [name], again.
Now you can hear me.
Yeah, I'll switch to the notes.
And so as usual, at the very bottom,
there's the feedback of the day.
And not just the day, I guess, this
should be for the whole course.
Do we have two feedbacks, one for the day
and one for the course?
If someone wants to duplicate it twice, you can.
But usually it's just one.
No, let's go with one.
At least for this part.
But then now for general Q&A. So now's
the time when we can all be here,
and we'll just reflect on the course itself.
Yeah, so who remembers at the beginning
when we said that it was impossible to teach everything
that was needed in a, what's it called, in a 10-hour course?
HPC system?
Yeah, so I still think that's true. I mean, here in this course, we've only had time to give you
a summary, do some examples, and so on. But by no means do we think that this course is the end of
what you need. It's just a starting point. It basically, hopefully, lets you realize what's
possible and have had the initial experience with stuff. And now, you will know when and
how to go read for what comes next. What do the other instructors think? Was it?
Yeah, I think, I don't remember, when was the first time I was doing this course back
in 2016 or something, and the ecosystem has changed dramatically from those times.
Don't be afraid of thinking that, okay, this is a lot of stuff happening, because it's
There's a lot of stuff happening for everybody.
Back then, it was basically like we wouldn't have even, let's say, the GPU day at all basically
because the GPUs weren't being utilized, but not in this sort of a level.
Many of the concepts like AI and whatever, they weren't things that are happening constantly.
a lot of stuff currently happening in the space, like the computational space is getting
very complex. But at the same time, I would say that it's good to differentiate.
If you have certain things that you need and you want, it's good to know that, okay,
I don't need to necessarily know everything about everything. You can focus on learning
those things that you need for your work and then learning the rest later.
Yeah, so some of these questions. The first question is about
COMSOL and how to get started. What would you all think?
Depends on your time limitations. I would suggest coming in on one of the COMSOL focus
days that we have in Garage, because then there are plenty of experts here that have a lot of
knowledge of Comsol and also a lot of detailed knowledge on how Comsol exactly works.
While if you come in on another day, we do have a few people that do know about CompSort,
but you might be unlucky and, well, not get the right person on that day.
But it doesn't hurt to show up any other day, and you're welcome to, but it's just possible that
we might not be able to help you on the spot. And I would say that Comsol is one of
these kinds of programs that once you get it sorted out and it works, it works.
It's the kind of a program that, because it has this, you can submit it straight from
the graphical user interface and then it just runs stuff on the background and you don't need
to think about it. But to get it working, that's the problem. And that's usually like,
yeah, it's a good idea to ask for help because it's not fun doing it by yourself based on
just looking at the manuals. Yeah. And it's the kind of thing that you'll always find people
that know about the cluster itself but might not know all the buttons Comsol. So if you can get
it most of the way there and show us an error message that comes from the cluster,
you can probably get help almost any day. But if it's not that, then no.
Next question is also pretty good. So a custom library which is not written for Triton,
and not available, and the default instructions
don't work on Triton.
So yeah, what would people do there?
I guess, what's the name of the library?
Like, is there a public link or something?
Is it a common library?
So if it's.
So I would say, in general, I would say, yeah,
come to Garage and let us have a look at it together.
I would say it really depends on what kind of library it is.
If this is something that is, for example,
or is a Python library, then you can normally
just do it yourself if you know enough about Python
so that you can just run the code
from a customally installed library.
If you don't, also, come to Garage.
We can try to help you there.
And if there are no really strange things happening,
normally we get the things running.
But yeah.
Yeah, quite often, especially for scientific coding
and scientific programs, for the whole ecosystem,
like the Linux ecosystem and stuff like that,
like the GNU ecosystem and everything related to that,
There's standards that are very engineer focused, but they follow them very well.
So they have, usually if you have a code, you have certain configurations or configure
flags or whatever, and you can spot the pattern and use that.
But the unfortunate thing is that because it's so engineering focused is that I remember
one CMake manual, a tutorial from those people was like 500 pages. So it was insanely long,
like all of the tutorials, but it's very strict and very regimented and everything is where it's
supposed to be. But when it comes to scientific programs, nobody has time to read those 500 pages.
So you might end up that the scientific program, it doesn't follow those standards completely.
So it becomes kind of like a translation problem where you have like, okay, this is what the
creators of the program intended to be done, but they use different names for the flags or
whatever. And now suddenly you need to do this kind of translation. Okay, what did they, like
this XY problem kind of situation, what did they want to do and what things that the installation
thing need and it becomes this kind of guessing game. You need to go through the source usually
and check what it actually tries to do. And sometimes getting outside feedback on this,
it can be really helpful. Like somebody else who has done enough of the pattern recognition
to see that, okay, like, hey, they're probably trying to do this kind of thing and they mean
these and these things. And sometimes that can happen with many libraries.
Or even just knowing where in the error message you actually have to look for what the actual
error message is, because you get like three pages of outputs. And if you don't, or if
haven't done this before. Okay, this is so much stuff. I don't even know where to look
for things. And there's a thousand different warnings, errors and stuff. And yeah, we kind
of have seen these things and we know which things are important and need to be considered
and which ones are, yeah, this is just standard output that it always prints.
But I would also say that I wouldn't discourage you to try checking out the pattern recognition
yourself.
But the problem, the important thing to realize is that the problem often necessarily isn't
in you.
It might be that somebody misheard something five years ago and now it's in the code.
Now it's like this game of telephone that happens with programs and sometimes somebody
doesn't follow a standard or something, and then it gets baked into the code and everybody
uses the code already, and now it's like a standard in the code, but you need to know
about it.
And it's like hidden in a readme five pages deep, and it's not necessarily your fault
that you didn't recognize the pattern, or you didn't know about this, or you didn't
know about the thing.
But what you can try, like at least I do, is that if I see something, I'll usually go
back to the source and check, like, okay, how is this supposed to be written?
Like, let's say, like, how are they expected these flags to be given?
And why aren't they given like they are and what flags they want to give them and that
sort of stuff.
But it becomes this kind of like, it's very hard to say, how do you recognize these things?
Like what [name] said about the error messages, it's very hard to say how you spot the right
line in the error message.
It only comes through time, but it's not the problem that you're wrong because you didn't
understand it.
The message always can be bad, like the error message can always be bad, but you just plow
through it.
At a certain point, you just know to look for a certain place after you encountered
it more and more times.
It's like, unfortunately, it's sometimes like that.
But so I would encourage everybody
to just also try it out.
Like, just try reading it and try googling as well.
Because after a certain time, you
get accustomed to seeing those patterns.
And just where you mentioned this
has become standard in the code, or there is
something that is happening.
It might also be good if this is a project that
is hosted on GitHub to just look for something
similar or something where you think this could
be related in the issues.
Because often enough, there is an issue from five years back
that, why the heck is this the default?
This is completely unintuitive and not documented anywhere.
And could this place be changed?
And yeah, it just never was.
Yeah, and I have a personal example for that
just from a Microsoft library.
Yeah.
And my comment on this question,
when I see there's an install.py file,
that's not the standard name of a package project thing.
So if it was setup.py or pyproject.toml,
I'd think, OK, most likely, I can
make a virtual environment or content environment
and run a command.
And it will install it and mostly do all the stuff
automatically.
I might need to tune some, but not.
But install.py makes me think someone
has written a custom script that tries to install it.
Who knows where it installs?
And if I need to do it myself, it's
probably going to be a lot of manual work
in figuring out how they did it.
Of course, if you're using this, there's nothing you can do now, but this is a lesson for the
future. When you're releasing something, it's worth taking a little bit of time to understand
how the project, how Python stuff is supposed to be packaged, and so on, and then do that if you
want people to use it. We actually have other courses in the Python for Scientific Computing
course that's usually in the autumns. There's a session where we very briefly talk about the
packaging standards and it's not that hard. And I want to add on that, also to consider
what should be happening in an installation script in Python and what should not. Like
things where Python assumes that underlying system libraries are installed. So your installation
script should not try to install system libraries, because that is always operating system dependent
and Python says, no, I don't want to do this. This is something that the user has to take care of
in a different way. Conda, for example, does a lot of wrapping around that and adds
some things that are system libraries in the environments, but don't try to do this in a
the custom installation script, you will just most likely make it extremely complicated
for someone else to actually install it.
Yeah.
But like, like, again, like, yeah, I will quickly mention that the, like, again, like,
but it's often, like, also high burden, like, to, like, think that, okay, this needs to
be perfect and whatever first time. If you want to do something and you want to publish it,
don't worry if it's bad the first time. It's the continuous process of improvement that matters
more. I have published code that is really bad, and I have made repos that I still look back and
think that these are bad, but they were bad because I didn't know better at that time.
You will go through the process and that will happen for everybody. Everybody will publish
code that is not using the standards. It's missing something that you realize later that,
hey, I should have used this and that. Don't put too high of a burden on yourself.
But in the next iteration, know that, OK, maybe I
shouldn't use the previous one.
Maybe I should try improving it in the next iteration.
Yeah.
Yeah, I sort of say something similar.
So you don't have to be perfect, because perfect is always
too far away.
Just try to do a little bit better
each time you do something.
And then once you, like, if you do something often,
you'll get better at it and reach the level you need.
So what, I mean, OK, so for the feedback parts here,
it looks pretty similar to other days.
Yeah, so what should we recommend people do next?
So what we covered was in the schedule.
There's a lot more written material to review.
Yeah, like at least I would recommend just trying out whatever you are planning on working
on.
Like it's like if you have a bunch of cookbooks in your bookshelf, but you never go to the
kitchen, you will never learn how to do like cook food.
Like you really need to go to the place and start cooking and tasting the food for yourself.
And then of course, use the cookbooks as this kind of like reference point that, okay, it
should look like this, but why does it, why my food doesn't look like this?
And then you're like, you can do the improvement procedure, but like, I would highly recommend
that you pick a program or a thing that you want to do in the cluster.
And first, let's say you have a program that you run currently on your laptop, and let's
say it heats up your laptop and you can't have it in your lab anymore, it's too hot
because it's constantly running some program.
Can you move that to the cluster and what does it require from you to do that?
And try out, would it be possible that it heats up the computer in a machine room somewhere
so that your computer isn't overheating?
So try some program, move it into the cluster,
and get accustomed to the workflow
that you basically put something running somewhere else,
and you don't have to worry about it anymore.
Yeah, that's a good way to do it.
What courses would you recommend people to follow up next with?
Well, on the autumn, we have the Python for Scientific Computing coming up again, like
that's our course.
And there's also the Code Refinery course coming at some point.
They are good ones, of course.
I think Code Refinery is mid-September now.
So I guess you'll get links to this in your email
if you've registered.
And Code Refinery and Python for SciComp
are a lot of these same kind of instructors
and the same teaching style, where
it's live stream with the notes to ask stuff
and lots of exercises and so on.
Yeah, the focus is more on the workflows and how to use Git and that sort of stuff.
Improving your productivity, basically.
Yeah.
Should we discuss any feedback?
I think the feedback is good and honest.
And it's always complicated with this course, and especially with the time frame, how to
get everything into that.
Yeah. And there's this thing we struggle with for every course. So if you make it
advanced enough to be useful, then it excludes most of the people that could benefit from it,
and is basically saying, do all these other more basic courses before you can get to what you need.
But with today's academics and so on, like the academic system and the time pressures people
have, people just don't have time to do a ton of prerequisite courses before they start getting
stuff done. And that's why we emphasize the big courses that sort of set the basic level,
ways for people to study what they need themselves, and then also our help so we can
help you with the specific parts that you need help for. And, you know, sort of like one-on-one
working together. So time's up. Are there any final things to say? So I propose