CodeRefinery.org
you
You
♪
Is it better now?
Yeah, now I can hear myself.
OK, so we were muted.
Let's start again.
Basically, hello, everybody, and welcome to the day four.
Today is an exciting day for me, because for the first time,
I will be the movie director controlling the streaming.
And as you might have just noticed,
I forgot to unmute ourselves, but I guess now you can hear us.
And we were just chitchatting about reproducibility before we actually get started.
The faces that you see here today are those who will talk about reproducibility and so-called
social coding and licenses later in the day.
So that's me, [name], and [name], and [name], and [name].
We're all from Aalto University, and we're basically working together here at Aalto.
Hello.
Hey.
So we still have a few minutes before...
Should we make an audio level check?
Yeah.
If my audio is still up there.
To me, you sound a bit loud, but I'm going to say 1, [name] says 2, [name] says 3 and
Osain says 4.
So 1, 2, 3, 4, 1, 2, 3, 4.
So let's hear, let's see if anyone can give us feedback.
So yeah, I would also say Tim was a little bit louder
than [name] and [name].
But yeah, we tried it earlier, and there
wasn't any real change in the audio volumes from then.
But that's interesting, because I basically
halved my input gain.
So I don't know if Zoom is kind of like compensating the maybe.
Did you change it in Zoom, or did you change it on your system?
Hardware.
Because Zoom sometimes has its own gain changes.
Well, but it's actually the Zoom doesn't let me.
Yeah, and it's compensating.
Yeah, basically, someone is writing in the notes that [name] is a little bit quiet.
Should I try to...
Oh, hey, there is an...
Is this any better?
Yeah.
Okay, now I can, because there was...
Now [name] is getting quieter.
Now you're quiet.
Yeah, because the zoom was compensating.
Yeah.
Now you're, I think, a little bit too quiet, actually.
Maybe now.
Keep talking.
I can.
Yeah.
I can keep talking and I will.
[name], could you say something?
Check.
Hello.
Yeah.
I think it's quite balanced now.
And of course we can improve on the way.
So before we actually start, we still have three minutes.
So actually, actually in the, in the end or in the beginning, my settings were perfect.
consume compensating. Of course, we always blame the technology.
So there are three icebreakers in this notes document. So if you open the notes document that
you at least receive in your emails when you register, which is the same notes document that
we were using also last week during the Git part. So there are three questions related to the topic
of the day, kind of reproducibility at large. And maybe specifically the way we talk today is
the so-called computational reproducibility. So can you recreate, are you able to rerun the same
software and hopefully re-obtain the same results? I don't know. How is your experience
with reproducibility? Have you ever faced challenges, [name], for example?
Yes, which started from not having any code for something and trying to do it from the paper and then noticing that there is a mixed up lower equal, which should be a larger equal sign, or having a data model that's provided as a PDF.
Which is kind of, okay, this is almost completely useless, because you can't really parse that easily.
Yeah, plenty of that.
And then a code base without documentation.
So it's really hard to do anything with just a code base.
Yeah.
Yeah, I share your pain in a sense that this has happened so many times that you read the
And then the professor PI asks you, can you just do how they did, and there's just way too many options to just read the words and try to convert them into a code or procedures, protocols.
All right, well, we start in one minute, so people can still keep on writing on this notes
document your experiences.
A quick reminder on how to do that.
At the top of the document, there is an eye symbol, this kind of two table or two column
symbol and a pen.
pen and if you click on the pen you're in edit mode and you can simply write in there
and give your comments, you ask your questions and so on.
All right, so now it's 10 a.m. in Finland, let's start.
I will first introduce you and then I will let you do the show.
So let me switch to [name]' screen.
All right.
Welcome, everyone, to the fourth episode
of this Code Refinery workshop, September 2024.
I'm [name], and I will be the host for you,
with you today.
And today the topic is reproducibility,
specifically more kind of the computational reproducibility.
So trying to replicate the results of other people
or even try to replicate what you did
a few months or a few years ago.
The first part of today,
which will last for a couple of hours,
will be presented by [name].
[name], do you wanna say something about yourself?
a research software engineer at Aalto, which is the scientific computing group, same as [name]
essentially. And then [name] will be joined by [name]. [name], do you want to say something about
yourself? Hello, I'm [name]. I'm also a research software engineer at Aalto. So we are basically
all colleagues here now. Thanks. And then later after the lunch break, which will go from 12 to
one finish time. There will be [name] and I talking about social coding and licensing.
[name], do you want to introduce yourself?
Yeah, sure. I'm [name]. I'm also one of the RSCs at Alto. Happy to be here.
So it's a full Alto team this time, all based in Finland. So apologies if I will use the finish
time zone as a reference, but I guess you can convert it to your central European or wherever
you live. Just a reminder that the materials for today are linked in the main page of the workshop
and if you keep the notes document open we will also post the links to the materials that
the instructors are showing. This week compared to the first week is a week where we will not do
actual exercises. But of course there will be lots of questions for you and discussions. So in
practice the notes document is our main tool for interacting. We decided to do it like this for now
a couple of times. The reason being that sometimes all the material that are presented in the second
part of the week, in the second part of the workshop, it can be overwhelming to try to do
the exercises and also understand what's going on. So there are exercises written in the materials,
and of course you're welcome to try them later if you have time. But in general, try to follow
our demos and our discussion and try to contribute with lots of questions,
because that's the best that we can get out of this experience.
So I think, yeah. I'd like to add one thing here. One of the reasons that we don't do the exercises
also because some of the tools that we are showing this week are very specialized tools and not
actually useful for everything and going through the exercises if you think yeah think it's useful
for you yeah it's definitely a good idea but some of the tools can just be skipped
yes all right i think this is all for the introduction so i'm gonna leave the scene
and the screen to [name] and [name] and I'll be back later for the break.
Okay so yeah this week and particularly today is about reproducible research
and it essentially starts with getting files in order. You have already last week seen a lot about
version control. No, sorry. It's about how to code, what to use as names for your functions
and so on and this will be done. We'll mainly focus on tomorrow and on Thursday.
As mentioned earlier, documentation is a very important part of reproducible research because
without documentation it's very difficult to redo what others have done
and that will be covered extensively tomorrow. The last week you've already
had a version control of code of text and how to do that, how to do
collaborative and distributed version control and what are the challenges
there. You further have things like stabilizing your computing environment
so that others can more easily reproduce what you have done
because they know what your environment actually looked
like, and part of this is covered today.
And other ways to do this are shown in more detail
tomorrow and on Thursday.
And it's, of course, also about how you publish your research
outputs, how you publish your code, your data,
your documents that you need.
And social coding and open software
will also be discussed later today.
So, but let's jump into reproducible research
and why we want to do that.
And there's a nice PhD comic about this
where Professor Smith has his PhD student in front of him
and asks, well, that's it.
Well, don't, don't worry.
You don't have to start your code from scratch.
You can reuse the software that the previous person
project wrote several years ago. And are there instructions for how to use it?
I doubt it. Is the code commented?
Not likely. And where are the files?
Who knows? This is going to be painful, isn't it?
Just a scratch. And I think this is, at least to some extent, very much what a lot of people
in academia have experienced. I myself had a similar thing where I was told here is code that
we want to have in our library, please connect it to the library that we have. And there wasn't a
lot of documentation and that was essentially my bachelor thesis in the end. So this happens
all the time, unfortunately. And while that's bad, there's also the problem
that's here in this anecdote where a group of researchers have obtained great results and
submitted their work to a high-profile journal. The reviewers ask for a few more figures and some
additional analysis, which is actually quite common. The researchers start working on those
revisions, generate modified figures, but find inconsistencies with their old figures.
And then the problems start because the researchers can't find some of the data they used to generate
the original results and they can't figure out which parameters they used when running their
original analysis. And well, that manuscript is likely to just end up in a drawer and never
really be published because they don't know what they actually did.
Yeah, this is actually the anecdote highlights the most, to me, the most important aspect of the
reproducibility and things we want to do for reproducibility, which is that you should make
your own life easier, that you can reproduce your own results.
And this graph also highlights that problem.
Yeah, it's, at least to me, it's somewhat understandable
if there are some issues with reproducibility
in experimental fields, where there are so many confounding factors,
where there have been examples where a changed water pipe changed the results, because there
was something coming from the water pipe that wasn't expected, that they didn't test for,
and that changed the results. But in a computational setting, this should not happen,
on, because we can a lot better control what we are doing.
And this should be a lot more reproducible.
And anything in a computational field that's not reproducible
comes essentially down to badly documented steps
for the experiment.
And there are different levels of reproducibility.
By the way, can we highlight in the graph the question
that I have failed to reproduce an experiment and my own, and it's like...
There isn't a big difference between your own and someone else's.
Yeah, there isn't a big difference, and there is a huge amount of percentage in both cases.
So yeah, and this was 2016, but basically in eight years, I don't think anything has
fundamentally changed.
One would hope that this has gone down a little bit, but yeah, I would also expect that it
hasn't gone down substantially.
And essentially, as I mentioned earlier, so you have different levels of reproducibility
and you have a kind of pyramid on what can be reproduced and of course the environment in
especially experimental settings can be something that is potentially very difficult to control
but we can control it reasonably well in a computational setting and in a computational
setting it's also we have code and data and that should be controllable because the data has been
it's there it has been generated so and it shouldn't change and the code also has been there
and shouldn't change then it comes to how has the code been used that's documentation what
parameters have been used that's documentation and only in the end once we have all this we create
we build an article and if something below here fails then this article fails because
it can't be reproduced because if we don't know what parameters we had well nice to have the code
but how did the results actually get obtained we don't know so the whole basis of this article
crumbles essentially and we have asked you in the collaborative document to post a few of your
experiences with reproducibility of the things and I actually want to highlight this first
one that was in here because this is something that happens both to the person writing it
and to others coming there, but you have stuff and you try to read it and think well yeah
has been done, but I don't get anything here because it's not well documented or it's not
well written and you essentially have to redo things and that's something that's very, very common.
Here, this is also the typical, yeah, a new version of the package has been
been published and the old version doesn't work on the current system anymore, or you
have to go to great length to go through this, which is a really huge issue.
I can relate to all of these answers, and one thing I actually want to point out is
that in the question it says that a script or a figure you created a few months ago.
For me, I don't have to wait a few months, because like a day or two is completely enough.
Because like I, if I don't document stuff for myself in two days, it's basically I may
have to start over.
So I completely know what people are coming from with these comments.
Yeah.
So I think all of these are really good examples of why we need reproducible research.
And I hope we can show you a couple of things that help you in making your reproducibility
or making your work more reproducible, either by others or yourself?
Okay. So just an overview of the next two hours. So we have four subtopics here.
So first is organizing your projects, so files and folders, structure basically. The next is
recording computational steps. So what was run and when and how. Then recording dependencies,
which is that what is the software or what libraries and which versions of software and
libraries your code is using to get the results. And then recording environments, which is
is what operating system, what system libraries.
So essentially going one step further down
the environment chain.
Yeah.
One step further down the rabbit hole of reproducibility.
OK, yeah.
Sorry, go ahead.
So let's get into organizing your projects.
So yeah, it's really one of the first steps
to make your work reproducible is to organize your projects well so to know to have a structure that
you understand that you where you can actually find things again because even the
finding the right function finding the right piece of data can become difficult if your
data and your project is not properly organized so first of all of course have
you have everything that belongs to a project in a single folder because then you have something
where you can have it or where you know okay this is what it is and if that's not possible because
you have for example some big data that needs to be stored elsewhere have links or indicators where
that data can be found early on that can be in a readme or in some other or in some other way
how this can be stored. Use different projects in different folders. Don't mix. It will only
lead to a mess and you can't get out of that mess again because untangling mixed up projects
will always be a problem. If you have things like code that you use in both projects,
Set up a git repository for the code and clone it into both projects.
And potentially have a branch for each project if they really do have different
code in the end, but try to get the code in a way that both can use it.
Use a consistent and informative directory structure.
This, for example, this is an example of what you can do.
Have data, process data.
So data is the raw information.
This is what you got from your experiments
or what you got from an external partner,
this is the raw data.
Process data is anything that you have
pre-processed or modified.
The manuscript is everything that's connected
with writing the article in the end or the articles
if you have multiple for the same project.
Results is essentially finished data,
some tables, figures, and everything that you want to put
into the manuscript potentially.
Source is your code with a license,
with requirements and information about it.
And doc is the additional documentation.
Your README can already contain some of the docs
or contain information on, OK, this
is where you find the documentation for this.
Also, I'd like to point out that in many, many, many cases,
README is enough.
So you shouldn't be kind of, um,
A well-written README is enough.
Yeah, well-written README is, extensive README is enough.
But the point is that we shouldn't
be kind of intimidated by the thought
that the documentation needs to be a whole HTML documentation
web page.
But I think the simplest check is,
once you've done your stuff and you have your README,
ask a colleague that's not in the project,
could you take this and reproduce the figures
and not help them by doing it?
Yeah.
One small thing, try to avoid spaces
in directories and filenames.
Yes, it's uglier to read, but a lot of times
there are programs that don't handle spaces well.
So not having spaces in there can make things a lot easier
computational-wise. It's not absolutely necessary but
it's, I would say, good practice. If you need separate public and private
parts, you can create a public and a private git repository.
Make sure that they are not in the same
git network. I would really create separate repositories
for it and not fork from the one to the other
and then make it private.
If you need to separate public and secret data in the same repository,
you can use gitignore, as was, I think, discussed last week.
And having and setting up a gitignore early on always makes sense.
And yes, and the rest, I think, we already mentioned.
Yeah. So about the project structure, does your project always look like this structure?
Does it often look like this? Does it never look like this, this example?
It looks similar.
I don't really have these parts at the moment anymore,
but I do have their source code data, potential documentation.
But as you mentioned, I'm actually mainly readmes
that sometimes point to a second MD markdown
file for a specific setup of development systems
or something like that.
But yeah, conceptually similar.
It looks very standard and it's always nice to use standard practices.
Yeah, so, sorry, yeah, the tracking your data and your project is also important.
Well, all code should be version controlled and should be in the source code folder.
So I have a license in there.
You can also version control data files
if they are not too large.
If they are very large, you can still version control them
with systems like Git Annex or Git LFS.
Large file.
Large file system, where you can essentially,
where the file is essentially placed somewhere else
And it's just the version that's being tracked.
And Git Annex essentially builds an additional network
of repositories where it knows where the data is residing.
And you can get the data, but if you don't explicitly want it,
you don't have to download it.
You can also, if they are sensitive or too large
for being tracked, put them into gitignore
and provide them on a different system,
which is perfectly fine,
especially if it's research data
that doesn't really change.
So if you have all your experimental data done
and you're not going to get more experimental data,
you can essentially put this into a folder,
into a folder, put it onto some data server and then just point to it in the README or somewhere else.
Intermediate files don't really need to be tracked. Commonly there might be
situations where the pre-processing takes a long time and you actually want to keep that data
stored and potentially tracked as well, but in general I would say process data can be reproduced
from the original data or should be reproducible from the original data and therefore doesn't need
to be tracked. Using git tags to mark specific versions of results is always also a good idea
because you then know okay this is the version that was submitted for the thesis or for the paper
and people can and you can essentially in the paper point to this version because that's the
data that was being used for the paper while your code could have developed on.
Yeah, so we have two more questions here that we can also put into the... that are already
in the...
Yeah, they are in the notes and everybody is welcome to...
It's mainly questions about how...
The first is mainly, if you use version control for academic papers, and the second is, if
you do, how you handle collaborative issues.
Personally, I never used version control for manuscript writing, or rather, I never used
it for manuscript writing.
The main reason for that is that writing collaboratively
on Git is painful.
There are tools like Overleaf or Google Docs where you can,
or HackMD, what we are just using,
where everyone can write in the same document.
And these things can be used to easily create
academic paper, and I personally prefer those tools because they are especially suited for
concurrent editing. While Git can solve concurrent editing issues, but depending on how many
changes there are and how much stuff two people did on an article, you can easily end up with
smudging conflicts, and it can become very painful.
So personally, I have used Overleaf, I have used Google Docs, and HackMD is also for first
draft, and then you need to put it into a form for the journal in the end anyways.
Would you say that the Git is a very powerful version control tool, but in this case, it's
a bit maybe too generic because there are tools that are specifically designed for co-authoring
papers or text? Yes, what I would say is that GIT is very good suited for code editing where
if you work on two different things but you have some modifications you then need to merge and then
need to find out okay what happened and what changes can be let go in and how do we need to
merge that where you anyways need to think about this but if you for example have two people who
edited a relatively final version of an article and made spelling or changed spelling mistakes
and stuff. You will get so many lines, because GitHub essentially goes line by line, where
you have changes on both sides that it gets really messy. And you need to manually then
select the right and you essentially do double the work if not more when editing a document and
that's something that is unnecessary in my opinion because there are tools like Overleaf
or HackMD that or Google Docs which do exactly that and are exactly for this purpose
where you can work together on a document and don't get into these kind of issues.
So I would use those instead. We have from the notes, we have interesting distribution between
are you using version control for academic papers? It's about 50-50, like yes and no.
It is interesting.
I have used, well, I have used version control for academic papers, no question whatsoever,
but I haven't used it for writing the manuscript.
And I think that's also...
Okay.
It's a distinction there, okay.
It depends on how people see this, whether, yeah, there is a comment on the how to handle
collaborative issues, one author being responsible for merging everything.
Yeah, that author will, if they are lucky, everything goes fine.
If they are unlucky and you have concurrent edits or a lot
of concurrent edits, they will spend a lot of time
in merging them.
And it's just, yeah, as I said, to me,
writing the manuscript there is a waste of time.
Having the code under version control
and merging there, yeah, absolutely makes sense.
Okay. Yeah. Should we move on?
Yes. So there are other tools that help in making academic or scholarly output more reproducible.
Jupyter Notebooks can be a good way to present the flow of your code more easily. Binder
gives Jupyter notebooks and makes them available in an executable environment so that people
don't even need to install the Jupyter stuff initially. And for R, there's also R tools
or Research Compendia, which are nice tools to use to show your results and show how your
code is being used. Okay, so a key point here an organized project directory structure
helps with reproducibility and makes it a lot more easy to later on redo what you have done.
So the next is essentially then the question. Okay, so you have your structure, your folder
organized. How do we actually go about running our scripts? So you have some steps that need to be
run to do your work and how do you actually run them? Does that rely on you remembering how you
run them? Or is it reproducible for anyone else? How do you communicate these steps to
others or in particular future you. And here we will also go into how we can
create a reproducible workflow and what scientific workflow management
systems are and when to use them. So as an example here we have a example
project from the HPC Carpentry lessons, which is essentially
a small project that counts the frequencies of words
in some books, and then plots them.
So the example use of this is, let me just check something.
So the example use is where you simply have Python code, code.py, and then plot the output
file into an image.
And [name], do you want to explain what the problems with this kind of approach are?
So it's a very manual approach.
And so if we want to, I would say that if we want to have multiple books.
So let's say we have 100 or 1000 books, then we would have to...
We do all of those manually, and then there is no record of what books were processed.
I think that's at least the first thing that comes to mind.
Yeah.
And we also, it's not really extendable.
So if we have this, what do we do if we
want to run this for 500 books?
We could even have a small GUI or something,
but then we would need to click like 500 times.
And of course, you can essentially
write a script that does run or essentially run everything,
which would be something like this.
This is now on binder on the JupyterHub.
In the JupyterHub on binder.
And you could essentially run all of these.
And then you have your results.
But that doesn't really help you when you have to extend that
to 500 books.
So this is more of an imperative style.
We tell it to do every single step in order.
And we can potentially also use something
like a loop for this, where we just indicate the name.
And then we can still run it for all of them.
This is a bit better, because we only have to put in the name.
But we are still explicitly telling it what to do.
Yeah, and also the loop looks much better.
But there is one problem, is that if we
want to rerun something, or we want to add some books
and rerun the experiment, then all the books will be processed again.
Yeah, and that's really not what we want to do, especially if the stuff that we are running
takes a little bit longer. So if we are running something that takes half an hour for everything
and we suddenly have to rerun 500 iterations of this.
Yeah, we really don't want to do that.
So this scripted solution is reproducible.
Yeah, definitely. But if we start to add more things it
starts to get problematic, as Timo mentioned.
And that's actually the point where workflow tools come in.
Workflow tools in more complex scenarios,
so where it goes away from the simple,
I have three things that I need to run,
and I don't have more than these three things.
But I always get additional things after some time,
and I'm still producing my data, for example.
And I need to do something for every data point.
that's where workflow tools come in very handy. And we will give an example here with SnakeMake,
which is inspired by GNU Make and is a very popular tool in bioinformatics,
but also in other computational fields. We also chose SnakeMake because it's very close to Python.
So, in the SnakeMake files, or Snake files, you can write code in Python essentially.
And we have a demo here in Binder that I will show you in a moment, but I would first like
to go through the way that SnakeMake actually writes your or that SnakeMake files are actually
created and how SnakeMake works on a logical basis. So SnakeMake works with rules and rules
have to be fulfilled for SnakeMake. So for a rule to be fulfilled it needs to have all
its inputs and then generates all its outputs by the command that's being called in shell.
And that's a bit unintuitive because commonly what happens is you define in your rule all
the inputs, which are the endpoints of what you want to create.
And in here we have in rule, in our all rule, we have, we want to create all the files in
statistics book data, where the name of the book comes from this data, from the data field,
which is essentially all file names in the data folder.
And we also want to create all the plots.
And this defines our final results.
And then SnakeMix starts to look, okay, how do I get these?
Is there any other rule that creates these?
And it looks on, so there is a rule count words, which has as inputs a script called
counted by and a book data file txt and these files come and these file this is just a placeholder
again which comes which in the end comes from data because it knows that okay this entry
comes from here then.
And then you have a Python script that says,
OK, well, from the inputs, I take the script,
and I take the book, and I create the output.
And if we look back up, this is exactly what we had here.
So this is the first step.
So that's what the rule, the count rule essentially is doing, or the count words.
And in the make plot, this is essentially the same structure and again as above.
And I will show you this on Binder.
So how the SnakeMech works, the rule works, is that each rule will take an input file
and then it looks that if that input file doesn't exist on the disk, it will find a
rule that has that input file as the output file.
And that's why we start from the end.
is, yeah.
And one thing I need to mention here, in our current,
in this binder, the results are already there.
So we already have these final results,
and we also already have the statistics being processed.
So the first thing I actually need to do
is remove them, because otherwise it
doesn't do anything, because it has everything already.
So I delete all these files.
And if I then start to, as you can see on the left, statistics stuff is now gone.
And if I then run this, what SnakeMIC does is it essentially checks, okay, what do I
have to do?
I have to create, or I have to fulfill the all once.
To do that, I have to count words four times
and I have to make plots four times.
So in total, I have nine things that I have to do.
The all is just a final check.
So that's pretty simple,
but the other code is something that needs to be changed.
And there I have my data again.
Now, the beauty of this is if I, for example,
remove this last data and run it again,
it will notice that, okay,
I'm missing one count words.
Since I'm missing that,
I also have to redo the plot because yeah,
I don't know if the data that is being created
will lead to the same picture or the same output here.
So I'm rerunning this and I have to execute the all again because I'm missing something from there.
And one more thing that I think is very important and why we have these code pieces in our
rule as inputs. If I change the count.py here
and run this again
10. It doesn't know what was changed, but it knows, okay, the count has changed. Oops,
this was too far up. The count has changed. So I need to rerun everything that depended
on this input count.py. That creates me the data or statistics data information, which
my make plot depends on. So I have to rerun the make plot because I don't know if that
has changed and it will essentially rerun everything that's necessary to keep in sync
with all the inputs.
And that's the real beauty of these things.
So you can go through it and you can make sure that only the stuff is rerun that is
necessary but everything that is necessary is rerun.
And that's really something that allows you to keep all your results in sync and allows
you to run additional code or additional inputs without rerunning everything.
It also has the possibility to use containers or environments.
And you can visualize the graph that is being created here as well.
Yeah. Okay. Or not. At least not in this environment.
It was a good example of, like, un-reproducible.
Yeah. So we would need to install the, well, we can probably just install it here as well.
But I'm...
That could take a bit of time.
that can take. So essentially what's happening is for all I need to create the count words
with the input of the file sierra. This is also the input for the make plot and all needs to have
make plot and that's the same for all the other inputs. So the all depends on all of these
individual things and only then all is fulfilled.
The reason why using snake make and or why we're representing snake make and not
other tools, I would say some people claim it has a
relatively gentle learning curve. I think it
depends a lot on your example or on your use case whether it's
gentle or not and how many features you actually need.
if you don't need too many features from it then yeah it has a relatively gentle learning curve
if you need a lot of features then well like with any system if you want to use all the features
that it offers it has quite a bit of stuff that you need to learn i think for me mainly it's
it's free it's open source and it installs pretty easily via conda or via pip and you can use it on
both Windows or all Windows, Mac OS or Linux. And that's also, it is highly compatible with
high-performance computing. You can essentially tell SnakeMake that run these things on a cluster,
run these things with the HPC scheduler. So don't run them on the local machine,
but run them elsewhere and run them as individual jobs, which lets you parallelize all of these
parallelizable steps very easily.
Yeah, it's, as I mentioned earlier, it's possible to define software, isolate software environments
in Perlul, so essentially defining that we will now use a certain conda environment or even to
use a certain container to run these things in. We'll come to containers later and what they are,
how they work, and as we mentioned it's heavily used in bioinformatics and it's a nice functionality
to archive your workflow and to properly archive it. You could, for example, put in the parameters
that you were using in a snakemeg file and then have everything that you were using in
that snakemeg file. And if you want to use a new parameter set, you could create a new
snake make file and keep the old one or if the snake make file is under version control you can
simply go back to that version. So that helps a lot in also remembering what was being used in the
past. There are additional similar tools like make which is very heavily used in C compiling.
There's Nextflow, Task, and other tools that help in doing this.
And about 200 others.
Yes.
There are a lot of workflow managers.
Yeah.
And of course, computational steps can be recorded in many ways.
A script can be perfectly sufficient.
But make sure that when recording your computational steps, you also record input parameters.
You also record what was, what input parameters, what stuff was used to run the analysis.
And in snake make, I would put it in the snake file, in a batch script or any other script,
I would try to put it into the file there as well,
because otherwise, you will forget it.
I know that I would.
Yeah.
In the notes, there is a question about parallelization.
So how does Snake make the parallelization happen?
Does it require the user to set some parameters?
The minus J, I think, is the number of jobs
that you can run in parallel.
Yes.
So if you would run minus J20, it would try to run 20 things in parallel.
So what SnakeMaker does, it detects from your rules that, okay, these rules can be run in
parallel.
they don't depend on each other.
And then it checks from the minus J parameter
or the option, the number of workers,
that how many CPUs do you have available?
And if you have more than one CPU available,
then it can start running the rules.
rules in parallel. I think that's the short of it.
Yeah, and on clusters, there is integration with SnakeMake and Slurm, but we won't go
into this in detail at the moment. If you think that you would benefit from using SnakeMake,
I would highly recommend going through the documentation, because what we have given
here is a very small example and a very simple example and like always with simple examples
they look easy to do on the surface and once you actually want to do that want to use them for you
you have to go back to the documentation. This is mainly to show you this is something that's
is possible, and that's available, and how to find it.
We are at the stage when we could have the break.
Yep.
And I would say we have a 10-minute break
till 2 past the hour.
Yes.
OK.
Keep posting your questions on the collaboration document.
We can keep answering them or take your break
and have a small walk around so that you
can come back refreshed.
OK, then.
Bye and see you in 10 minutes.
you
Okay, and welcome back.
So, we've talked about organizing your folders, organizing your code and recording the steps.
And the next thing that we want to talk about is recording dependencies and how to communicate
different versions of software dependencies.
And well, our code often depends on other codes or other libraries and that in turn
depends on other codes and so on.
So for reproducibility reasons,
we can version control our code with Git,
but how can we version control dependencies?
How can we capture and communicate them?
And connected to that is that we can easily end up
in a somewhat of a dependency hell
where different codes that need to be run
for the same analysis actually have conflicting dependencies
the one depends on a different version of a library than the other and that
starts to get really problematic. And there is this nice XKCD comic that
shows very well how our modern computational infrastructure works and
that it's a very complex pattern of libraries and libraries and libraries
depending on other libraries and this on top here that might be your code and it depends on a lot of
different things down below down to operating systems kernels and then it probably depends
on some project some random person in Nebraska has been thanklessly maintaining since 2003
and if that piece of code breaks the whole thing tumbles down and there is actually a very
recent example that happened way after this comic was created, where there wasn't a breakdown
as such, but there almost happened to be a very, very, very severe security issue because
someone socially engineered themselves into a maintainer position of one of these tiny
bits of codes that everything relies on. And had managed to get some backdoors into the code
and that was almost shipped to the stable versions of some operating systems. That was the xz library
which is essentially a compression library that is used in a lot of systems as an underlying library.
So, this picture is very accurate, and yet, unfortunately, it's very accurate.
So to make this whole thing a bit more understandable, a bit more tangible, we can also think of
a kitchen analogy to your code and what you're doing.
And essentially, your software that you have, that's the recipe.
That's the recipe on how to process the data, which are the ingredients, to get your results,
so your dish.
And to do that, you normally take some libraries, which are pots or tools.
And now it's very simple to imagine that, okay, you have a recipe for a huge amount
of pasta, because that recipe is supposed to feed 40 people.
And your recipe says to take a 10 or 15 liter pot of water, well that wouldn't work, that
whole recipe wouldn't work if the only pot that you have is a 1 liter pot.
So if you only have the 1 liter version of that library, so only the 1 liter pot, you
can't your recipe just doesn't work because you can't fill 10 kilos of spaghetti into a one liter
pot. So that's how you can think about how software data and libraries work together.
and there are plenty of tools that try to help you specify what tools you actually need
and try to help you in specifying the specific library versions that are needed and handle
all the dependencies that are underlying these libraries because you might be working with,
for example pandas but pandas needs other libraries to work and this kind of dependency
tree is something that you don't want to care about yourself and so defining if having a tool
that helps you there is very beneficial and common tools that have there are conda pip virtual
environments, poetry for package building, the requirement.txt which lists the
individual requirements, the environment.yaml which is the equivalent to conda and so on.
And they try to help you in defining the specific set of dependencies,
possibly with well-defined versions. They help you in installing those dependencies
because they get the underlying dependencies. They help you with
recording the versions for all these dependencies. And Virtualenv and
Anaconda for example also help you in isolating environments so
that you can have multiple different sets of environments on one computer so
that if you have two pieces of code that have conflicting dependencies you can
still run both of them, you just need to change the environment for that. They even help you
with changing the versions of R or Python per project or even within the same project
if you have code that needs, if you have very old code that still needs Python 2, you can
do that. If you have code that needs an R version below 4, yeah, you can do that.
So some of these tools or approaches are Python specific and some are more general.
So Konda, Anaconda, they are quite general.
Yeah, while virtualenv is more a Python or pyenv, while renv is more R and so on.
And one really beautiful thing with, for example, conda, yeah, mainly conda, mainly with actual
or also pyenv, virtualenv, so with these whole things is that if something goes wrong, or
want to try something out and it didn't work, you can delete the environment and recreate
it from the environment file. So you can test, okay, I have found a library that seems to
be solving a problem that I have, let's add it to the environment, test it, didn't work,
okay. Before I try to remove that library again, because there might have been other
things that came along with it that I didn't properly record yet, I just throw away the
environment, recreate it, because it will be the same as I had before. And we have here
five examples of students that wrote code, which depends on a couple of libraries. And
the code was uploaded to GitHub. And let's assume we travel three years into the future
and find the github repositories and try to rerun the code before adapting it. There are
a couple of questions in the collaborative document now which we would like to have
your opinions and I would give that like three minutes or so or five minutes to read through it
and answer that and just say okay well what do you think is this reproducible or isn't that
reproducible. Okay, so see you in five minutes.
You can also, if you have comments about it,
write the comments there and what the issues are.
I think we will start discussing once we have a few comments for one of them and
you can go through it and just listen to what we say about it in general.
Looks like A is starting to get some...
Yeah, I think A, we already have a clear tendency.
Yeah, consensus.
That this is not reproducible and yeah, absolutely.
if you just have imports you might not even know which libraries are actually being used
because sometimes there are two libraries that provide the same imports and that essentially
means that you can either load library A or library B and or you can have a dependency
on library A or library B but in the code they have the same import statement because you have
conflicting import. That's absolutely possible. So yeah, this is anything but reproducible.
And also not very nice if you think about the workload you are putting on the
next person trying to figure out. Or on yourself rerunning it.
Yeah. B, we also already have a
quite clear thing that, yeah, if you have a list of libraries that are used, that's at least helping,
but if you don't have any versions you sometimes have breaking changes in between versions and
you don't necessarily know which version was being used. You can try to guess what version
was being used but if this was being created somewhere in the transition between let's say
major version 2 and major version 3 of the same library it's a whole lot of guesswork which
version was actually used, because very often published code is already older. So it was
essentially developed a year ago or so, and the version that was used back then was being used.
And yeah, we just don't know. Yeah, for example, so this function uses or this
This class uses a function that was introduced in version two, but was deprecated in version
four, or say, deprecated in version six.
So it must be somewhere between two, three, four, five, and then the subversions.
And it's, again, it's not very nice thing to do to yourself or to the next person trying
to figure out your code.
see, again, yeah, as people mentioned here, it's nice that you have an environment file
that already helps quite a bit, but there is, of course, still missing version numbers,
so you don't know which versions were actually being used. Is this now Python 3 or Python 2?
So, and what this file is supposed to tell you. Okay, that's actually a good question here.
So the environment.yaml file is a file for Conda.
Conda is a dependency management system
that reads through this and says,
okay, well, I'll create an environment
with the following name.
And then I'm using these channels,
I'm using these sources.
And in this case, it's Conda Forge.
conda-forge is a pretty popular repository for packages.
And the dependencies are then listed as scipy.
So the scipy package, numpy, sympy, click, python, pip.
And conda also allows you to do installs with pip
because not every package is actually in conda.
And it allows you to create an environment
that has pip installations.
And here, this indicates that, okay, this is Git.
This is a PIP installation from this Git repository
at the master branch.
And actually that's a problem in itself
because master can have changed.
There is no idea, there is no information
on what master is nowadays.
This can be completely different, so.
And very likely is because the latest master.
Well, yeah, most likely, assuming that this is
from other users that actually still develop their code.
4D, we have heard of the commit.
And the versions are, okay, so how you fix that
could be like in the nodes.
In version D, where you essentially have
a specific git commit or a specific tag
that this project is being used at.
There is the comment that there might be different builds.
That's true.
There's one problem with builds.
Builds can be operating system specific.
So for absolute reproducibility, yes, you need the build.
But commonly, the version is sufficient.
The version is sufficient to hopefully get the same results.
If you really need to go down to the build number,
it's very likely that something fishy is happening,
and I wouldn't rely on my results too much actually.
But yes, for complete reproducibility,
the build should be in there, for usability I wouldn't put it in, a place like that.
And I'll come to that a bit later actually, in the next demo where we show the differences here.
Um, yeah, uh, anything else?
Um, yeah, this has the advantage, the E has the advantage over D that, um,
these projects that were referenced here have now been put onto Conda.
But actually, if that is, you can be happy. If that isn't, well, that's also something that's
very common, that you need some pip packages or that you need something from a different
git repository. And of course, there is the problem that these git repositories could
have been deleted. But if you want to make sure that you keep those git repositories
and you need a specific version from a specific git repository, fork it and use your own fork.
Because you are in control of your own fork and as long as you don't delete that fork, that stays.
So this way is perfectly fine if you make sure that the repositories don't disappear.
Okay, and that's essentially also what's listed in the solution.
So, what about PIP packages and conda packages? Do they not disappear ever?
They can. Hopefully not, but even conda packages can disappear, especially in very fast moving
fields, or if you use, let's say, more unstable channels, more developmental channels.
I have seen some PyTorch versions no longer being supplied by some of the providers because
they are too old and considered as not useful anymore, but that's, of course, a real problem
for reproducibility.
Yeah.
So in general, if you use well-known and widely used channels and packages from conda or pip,
it is very unlikely that they will disappear. But yeah, they can. And how to solve that problem,
we can come to, well, how to switch that problem to a different level,
we will come to in a bit.
So now, we will demo creating our own small time capsule for an environment and for the
future world and yeah, this is essentially, I have created this environment.yaml and as
As explained above, I can quickly show that this is essentially what's written in here.
So conceptually, again, it wants to create an environment called myenv with the channels
on the forge, and in this case, defaults, which is the Anaconda environment.
One mention here, this can become a bit problematic, because Anaconda recently changed
their change their policies for even that even academic institutions now have to pay if they
have over a certain amount of users and it might be good not to use defaults here.
CondaForge normally has all the packages that you need and even has more packages than default
than the Anaconda environment,
but the Anaconda environment is a bit better curated.
Okay, and then it is the dependency.
So this would be something that depends on Python 3.10,
also wants to have mountain NumPy, pandas and seaborn.
And yes, it doesn't give any,
it doesn't give any version numbers here at the moment.
moment. So I will be using Mamba instead of Conda and the reason is that otherwise Conda
can take quite a bit of time to actually create environments and I want to spare us all the
time. Mamba is a drop-in replacement that's just faster because it uses C while Conda
is programmed entirely in Python.
Okay, so this will essentially create this environment,
check the sources that I indicated,
and start to then download the files.
Or it should.
So it checks for these and I should have them already downloaded.
So there's, oh, it actually found something that probably has a newer version and it wants
to take the newer version.
So that's something which is actually quite nice to see.
So if I had created that a little bit earlier, it would be slightly different now because
this is a different version.
So, and if I then, let's say,
conda activate myenv,
I have my environment where in Python,
I can import Seaborn and have my Seaborn library and so on.
So, I can now also export this environment.
And that's essentially what was mentioned earlier in the notes, that this lists everything
including the build number, the build ID.
And if you look into this a bit, you will notice things like this one, where libplus
is Linux 64.
So yeah, I'm on a Linux system and this is a build that's specific for Linux.
So if I would provide this dependency file, anyone who is on a Windows system will have
problems installing this environment because this is not available for Windows.
That's why this kind of system, where you have all the individual build numbers, might
not be the best thing.
It's good to have, and I would put it in as for reproducibility, so that people can actually
see what exact builds were being used.
But for usability of your code, so if someone wants to use that library in a different project,
This is questionable.
There is the other option, which is very convenient.
You can say from history, and if I check into that, this is exactly what I installed.
This lists exactly, even if I later on would install something with mamba install whatever,
would list exactly the right packages here. There is a third option, which is called nobuilds.
And that is the same as the environments file, but without the builds.
That can also be useful if you want to make a clear specification which underlying packages
were being used without providing builds.
But it still has the problem that there are things like the LD implementation in Linux.
So yeah, that might still not work on a Windows system.
So what is the recommendation here?
Can you repeat that?
What I personally would recommend for a project
to provide is the export from history, so this.
And for reproducibility reasons, I
would put in the complete export.
Because that shows, then if someone
has the same operating system and so on,
this should be really exactly the same environment
that they get when creating that.
While the FromHistory will create an environment
that is as close to what I would recreate
if I would start this now, and is
the one that solves on all operating systems,
so is more general.
But at the same time, we have to admit that this is not a good initial environment file.
Your initial environment file should have the NumPy version, should have the Pandas version,
should have the Seaborn version that you want to use.
Okay.
So, yeah.
So, to summarize, because this is...
So, in your initial environment file do have the version numbers.
But then for completeness, it is OK to also include in your repo the complete export with the builds.
I would even recommend it as an additional piece of information.
Yeah, because it doesn't hurt.
Yeah.
OK, good.
OK.
We unfortunately don't have really time
to go into details with R. But essentially, you
can use Conda with R as well.
Conda does have R, does support R.
And I have created several environments with Conda
OS for R with using Conda.
So, but since we saw that an underlying library, a system library can cause problems.
And up until now, we mainly considered non-system libraries, even though Conda already does
some system library stuff.
Let's go to recording the environments.
And I think everyone has heard the, well, it works on my machine, comment from someone
at some point.
And this meme sums up the idea behind Docker or other containerization systems quite well.
That it works on my machine, well, then we'll ship your machine.
And yeah, that is how Docker was born, essentially.
So we want to ship something or give something that provides as much as possible of the operating
system to the user in the end.
And to go back to our kitchen analogy, so as we said, our code scripts are the cooking
recipes and then with containers you have container definition files and they are like
blueprint to build a kitchen with all the utensils and stuff that the recipe needs to be prepared.
The next thing is we have the container images and those are kind of showroom kitchens based on
these container, based on the blueprints that we have created before and a showroom kitchen is not
connected. So there they are, electricity is not plugged in, water is not plugged in,
and you can't really use it.
And a container is then essentially
this showroom kitchen connected to everything.
And in addition, there's a protective layer
being put on everything so that you can work with it.
And in the end, you remove this protective layer
so that you still have the original container
kind of. As we said, containers can be built to bundle all the necessary ingredients, data,
code, environment, operating system, even though including data might be problematic,
depending on your system. A container image is somewhat like, yeah, also like a piece
of paper with all the operating system on it and when you run it, you put a transparent
sheet on it to form essentially the container.
Then that container runs and you write on that transparent sheet and do all the changes
on this transparent sheet.
And when you're done, you pair off that transparent sheet and you still have your original container
and everything that was done on this transparent sheet is gone.
And the definition files are essentially text files that
contain a series of instructions on how to build these container images.
So to recap here, we have three concepts.
And first, kind of like a starting point would be the definition file,
let's say a docker file or a similarity definition file. And we use that definition file
to create an image, a container image, or image for short. And that image and that definition file,
of course, they are persistent. But then when we create a container out of that image,
image, then that container is not persistent. So the container is what is actually being
run. And when that container is stopped, it stops running, then it vanishes. But the image
is still there on the disk.
Then everything that was changed in the container vanishes. Yes. Okay. Yeah. And why would you
want to use these? There are two main reasons. One is installing a certain software is tricky
or not supported on the system that you're using. That's very common on HPC systems. HPC systems
in general have a very very minimalistic operating system with as little
with as little software installed as possible as to leave as much computational and memory
available for a user to exploit and use. But that means that a lot of small libraries that
code depends on are not there. So what you can do with a container, you can essentially
put all the stuff in that container
and run your code via that container.
The other option is that you want to make sure
that whoever is using the code
use it in the same kind of environment
or same environment as you.
And then you can provide them an image of your container
because then you essentially
have provided the whole environment.
There might be a problem if people are using different architectures than you.
And there might be a problem if people are using different operating system menus.
You can run Linux containers on Windows.
That works reasonably well because Windows has a Windows subsystem for Linux, but you
can't really run Windows containers on Linux, unfortunately.
So one way it works, the other, unfortunately, doesn't.
Yeah.
So the shipping the machine is a bit of an exaggeration.
So let's have a look at one of these container recipes.
This is a Singularity definition file,
and there's a link to the reference
if you want to look into it in more detail.
And Singularity commonly starts with an information
on where this is coming from, and Singularity
can use Docker images to base your new images on.
And if it says a bootstrap essentially indicates,
okay, this is where it's coming from.
So this comes from the Docker repository.
And from is the statement on what is the original image
that we are using as a base for what we are doing here.
And that's commonly some operating system
or some programming language that you're using
where essentially all the packages that you need
for that base operating system or base programming language are already installed and then you can
start to do more things with it. And POST is then essentially what happens after that
basic installation. So what changes do we need to do to our system to make it do what we want
the container to do. And at least on any Linux or on any Ubuntu, this commonly starts with
apt-get y-update, so just get the latest updates, which can in itself be a bit of a problem if you
want to redo that. And then install the packages that we need. You can set some environment
variables. You can potentially also copy over files and so on. And then you have a run script,
which is the final command that is being run when this container is being run.
So this container would run date pipe to kawase pipe to locket. That's what this
container would be doing. It's not very useful, but it's just an example.
Yeah, and so does every image that we build, do they all like run a script or?
No, you don't necessarily need to run a script.
You can also have a container that essentially doesn't do anything and just provides an environment.
the way you need to tell it, okay, what do you want to execute in the container?
Okay. So then it's kind of like a generic platform to run whatever script you want
in that specific environment. Okay. And there are a couple of different
container platforms. There's Docker and Podman, which is more of a, which are, I would say,
more of a single user. In particular, Docker is more of a single or a container for a single
user system because Docker has the disadvantage that it essentially needs to have administered
for pseudo rights and it will run essentially as a super user, so it can do everything on
your system. Singularity and Obtainer are pretty popular on high-performance computing systems
because they essentially get rid of this requirement of running it as a super user.
And you can run and you can still run these containers.
Potman is very close to Docker and yes, what's the default container engine on Red Hat systems,
for example.
Okay.
So, if you have a single machine or like a single user or multi-user.
If you have a single machine, yeah.
If you have a single machine, you can, no super user rights, you can use singularity
obtainer Potman.
If you have super user rights, you can use Docker.
If you don't have super user rights, you can't use Docker.
It's pretty simple.
Someone can add you to the Docker users,
but that would essentially give you super user rights.
So they can as well just give you
administrative rights then.
So pros and cons of containers.
Well, they allow you to move workflows
across different platforms with the constraints
that we mentioned earlier.
They can definitely solve the works on my machine situation
because you essentially ship the operating system
or the underlying libraries.
For software with many dependencies,
they can offer the only way to preserve
the computational environment future of usability.
What we had previously where this conda environment had things, now we can create this image and
we can actually ship this image because that image, regardless on whether the repositories
are no longer in the, or the repositories no longer have these versions, they are in
the image.
If the image is created, they are in the image.
So for reproducibility, you need the image.
You don't necessarily need the definition file, but that is very, very useful to reproduce
the image, but if you want to have it reproducible, you need to provide that image.
It's also a mechanism to send the computer to the data when your dataset is either too
large to transfer or when your dataset is in a secure environment and you just can't,
you don't have an internet access,
so you can't just install conda packages or whatever,
but you can give the image file to the system administrator
and they will put that image file onto that computer
and then you can run the tools that your image provides.
It's a further set of separation
where you can install software into a file,
so that image file instead of onto your computer,
separating again or essentially meaning that you don't have to change your computer setup
to install something. There are of course also some drawbacks because containers can be used
to hide away software installation problems and which should normally have been solved by
better development practices. So yeah it's too difficult to install, yeah we don't make the
installation easier, which would be the right thing to do, we'll just provide a Docker image
so that people can use it. Yeah. You can run into the, instead of works on my machine,
works only in this container, which again leads to the same question, why does it only work in
this container? What's in this container that makes it possible? And if that is, yeah,
a specific version of a normally available software then yeah there might be problems
with what you have actually. They can and are difficult and are somewhat difficult to modify
and depending on what you package in there they can become very large. So every bit of data that
you would put into a container that's why I said shipping the data in there or putting data into
a container is a questionable thing that will make that container larger. For example, if you have
large language models, you don't really want to put those large language models into a container
because you will just increase the container size a lot and if you use that model in multiple
different containers, imagine a 40 gigabyte model and now all your containers are 40 gigabyte in size
Instead, what you can do is you can have that image elsewhere or have the model elsewhere
and load it into the container when it's run.
That makes it a bit less reproducible because you're not shipping the data, but overall,
it's I would say the better choice.
Yeah, so then we are assuming that hopefully the language model will be distributed in
some other centralized place, for example, Hackingface or something.
Yes.
So, there are different places where containers can be found.
Docker Hub is very popular, KUAI is also quite popular, GitHub and GitLab container registries
can also be used, or even Zenodo.
So there was this warning about only use official and trusted images.
So what is your definition for an official and trusted image?
To me, it's the same as any other software that I use from the internet.
If I want to use a container, it should be coming from the essentially creators of the
the software that I want to use, not from some third party,
whatever, that provides me WinZip or whatever.
Yeah, if I want to have PuTTY, I'm
going to the PuTTY web page and download it
from the PuTTY web page, and not from some third party where
I don't know if this is actually PuTTY or just a Trojan that's
trying to, that I've been installing on my system.
Yeah, so if I want to use an image of Ubuntu, then I will use an image provided by the Linux
Foundation or whoever is responsible for Ubuntu development.
And similar to what we had earlier with the environments or the dependencies, we also here
now have a dockerfile and I want to quickly go through the dockerfile to see what is actually
how the dockerfile can be reproduced or if there are problems with this dockerfile
or reproducibility. One mention right at the beginning, if you really want it to be
reproducible provide the image not just the dockerfile because only the image is what you
actually used. And the Dockerfile is only the way how this image should be generated, but
we'll mention why this is a bit problematic. So we have the, or the singularity file here.
So again, we have a singularity that depends on Docker and it starts from Ubuntu latest.
Is that a good idea, Timo? Yeah, that's immediately a problem that the Ubuntu latest
just is dependent on when you are building the image.
Yeah, three years ago, this was Ubuntu 21 or something.
Nowadays, it's 24 or something.
So yeah, it's building on a completely, not completely,
but a different operating system.
So this would definitely not be the same
if I run this now than three years ago.
Then we start with our post, so with our installations.
we export an environment for the or environment variable for the installation and time
we upgrade update as we mentioned before we upgrade install with a couple of libraries
and this already this is where this problem also comes back in these libraries can have changed
changed.
Even if we have a fixed version, these can change depending on whether the default libraries
have changed over time.
Then this is some cleanup, which is fine.
We create a virtual environment, we upgrade pip, and, well, install some requirements.txt.
That of course depends now a lot on the requirements.txt, how well defined the versions are in there,
there, but if they are not well-defined, we again can run into easy problems.
This singularity file also has an additional section with files, which indicates what files
are copied over into the image.
So it copies over the requirements.txt, and I would assume that this requirements.txt
is in the same repository as this file, the same with the app.py.
So those files we probably have.
And then it copies something from Home, Myself, Data into AppData.
Yeah, Home, Myself is not something that we have.
So this is stuff that is probably not even in the repository.
So we don't know what that is.
In that case, it's probably the data that is to be used by the app.
And we said that we want to reuse it with our data, so we can probably replace it with
our data here.
But yeah, that's not very helpful.
And this is then a real problem, because this has some fancy lip where we have no idea what
that is.
And yeah, puts it into the libraries of this container.
So this makes the whole image not reproducible, or even not reusable, not only not reproducible.
So to recap the file section here, so I think I read the instructions again, and yeah, it
doesn't say that this singularity file is,
definition file is in a repo,
but yeah, we are assuming that it's in a git repo,
and there is in the git repo with this definition file,
there is the application code,
which is the app slash, no, app.py,
and that we have a requirements text file there in that Git repo. But like we talked earlier,
then data is not usually in the Git repo, especially if it's big data. And
so the first requirements line and the app line are fine.
line, the copy data line is quite iffy, and the last line highlighted now with the fancy
lip is like a definite no-no.
Yeah.
But so these are the problems that you have with Docker definition files, which means
that essentially, if you want to have your Docker file reproduced or your code reproducible
by providing a Docker, provide the image.
Yes, it will be potentially big, but it's the only way how you can actually have the
environment that you used saved.
And not to confuse people any more than necessary, this is a singularity definition, right?
Yes, sorry.
Not Docker definition.
So key points here is containers can be helpful if complex setups are needed to running a
specific software and they can also be helpful for prototyping without messing up your own
computing environment or to run software that requires a different operating system than
your own.
It depends a bit.
Okay so we are coming towards the end and the question is where to go from here and
what to take away from this.
So I think for me, we have shown you workflow tools and how and where to use it.
And we have hopefully given you an idea where they will make sense in the future.
In many cases, these workflow tools are probably not needed and a proper script with all the
information is sufficient.
But you probably want to consider using them when you are processing many files with many
steps.
your steps or files may change, if you're still collecting your input data or if your main script
connecting your steps starts to get very long because then it starts to get unreadable essentially
and you start to want to make different parts of it. Containers seem amazing but do I have
actually use for them? Well, maybe not, but knowing that you can use them is already pretty useful,
that you can run Linux tools on your Windows computer, you can run different versions of the
same software on your computer, that you can follow the easy installation instructions for
an operating system that is not your own, that you get a fully configured environment instead
of installing just a tool, and that you can share your setup and configurations with others.
So, yeah, they can be very beneficial, but as with workflow tools as well, you will need
some additional read up on how to use them.
This was mainly to present that they are an option.
And what we think is important for every project that you create, have a clear structure for
your project, have a clear file structure, clear directory, so that you find things again.
your workflow and write it down in a script file,
or if it's complex enough with a workflow manager.
Create a dependency list and keep it updated,
optimally in an environment file,
because that makes reinstallations a lot easier
and makes it a lot easier for others
to follow what you have done.
So software packages and their versions.
Yes.
and consider the possibility that someone, maybe you, may want to reproduce your work.
Can you do something small to make it easier? Write down some more instructions or similar things.
If you have ideas what you can do in the future but no time, you can add an issue to the repository
that you're creating your code on and maybe someone else can help or you in a few years
time noticed, oh well, I had this idea back then. Maybe now I have a bit of time I can actually
implement that. Yeah, so as I've mentioned a few times, not everything in this lesson
might be useful right now, but it's good to know that these things exist. If you ever get into the
situation where you would require such a solution, then you can come either back to these documentation
and documents or you can go to the of course to the respective documentation of the individual
software to see okay how do I actually use them and caring about reproducibility makes work easier
for the next person that's working on the project and as likely as not that will be you.
So that's I think it for us. Timo do you want to add anything?
Okay. No, good recap there. Okay, then. I would say thank you, and...
Excellent.
I think we almost ran out of time.
Exactly. Thank you, [name], and thank you, [name]. I don't think there's anything to lift.
still have four minutes. Should we consider some of the questions in the notes, but otherwise...
I'm looking at the notes and there is a comment about the future viewpoint is really important,
and I agree that I don't think it can be emphasized too much, that it is most probably
the person looking at your code later is you, yourself, or your experiment setup. And all these
things that we have discussed, they may seem at first that, okay, this is, again, new learning
curves. They will take time to get into, but they will save you time and energy in the end.
and also they help the scientific community at large
because you are making things more reproducible.
Yes, so we still have a couple of minutes,
but of course we can also end it here
if there's nothing to add.
I just remind you that now we will have
one hour lunch break.
And after that, we will talk about social coding.
will be me and [name] talking about basically the social aspects of coding with other people,
sharing repositories and that comes of course with some kind of legal requirements and so
we will talk about licenses for code and software. All this in about one hour. So I thank you
[name] and [name] for the great discussions and I thank everyone for the comments on the
notes. You can keep on writing comments and answers. And so we see each other in one hour.
Thank you. Bye. Bye. Bye.
you
You
a
little
more
ah
so
easy
huh
so
easy
i
love
it
so
easy
huh
so
easy
i
love
it
so
easy
i
love
it
this
is
the
country
also a good thing. Another thing that at least I use is because the code is more clean, it's
easily more reproducible for me at least. So I think these three are the main aspects
that I use in social coding. What about you? Do you have any preference?
Yeah, I agree with you, especially like that you mentioned this kind of CV idea.
And this also goes with, in my opinion, what I like about the Code Refinery workshop, that
the type of skills that you learn here are skills that are reusable in other fields outside
academia.
So if the majority of the people following this workshop right now are doctoral researchers
or postdocs or whatever, but already learning it and starting with whatever, little by little
sharing, it will also open doors for maybe other jobs in the future that might not be
related to academia.
Yeah.
Me, of the options here, I really like the kind of reproducibility part.
I'm biased, I'm a reproducibility fanatic, so that other people can truly rerun my code.
But sometimes I publish code that was really ugly, but I still thought I'm going to put
it out there because no one had that type of function in whatever language I was publishing
it.
And then I saw that my ugly code was actually reused by so many publications completely in
different fields.
Sorry to interrupt, there was a comment that they cannot hear us but apparently it was from the computer.
Sorry, go ahead.
Yeah, that's good. Yeah, if I was muted it wouldn't be nice.
But basically let's have a look at what our people online are answering.
answering looks like that to my eyes at least A and B seems to be very popular. So the reproducibility
and also the trustworthiness. Exactly. It's interesting that the H doesn't get any votes,
not for this year, also for previous years it didn't get any votes either. But yeah, it's
interesting. It's nice also this that maybe the kind of social thinking of the people here is not
that we are in a competition even though the grant system makes us believe that we are all
competing with each other. Another thing that I wanted to add is maybe another aspect that I think
about is being part of the community. So there are like a lot of codes that you can use and are
open source so you can try them and if you try to also publish your code you become part of this
community, which is very, very interesting to be part of. You can collaborate with others and
after some time you will be known for some of your work, although they might not be exactly
your expertise. For example, I have this. It's not exactly a source code on GitHub, but it's about
like a, like how to do something like more of administrative work. And at the moment I'm known
for that work among like non-expert people for like research software, which is, which is an
interesting thing. Yeah. Yeah. That's, that's great. And in my opinion, it's also, I mean,
it's, it's, it's exactly this that it's, even though we will talk about this later, that
sometimes maybe code you might feel that you're not recognized in citation or whatever impact
is the measure in academia. But at the end of the day, people will notice it and people will see
it. Maybe you start getting new collaborators or reaching people that you would have not just
reach with your papers.
Yeah.
Maybe we can go to the next question.
So it also had some downfalls a bit, right?
So when you publish your code, do you have any concerns or?
Well, I would say initially I felt this kind of B, that my code is ugly.
I was never really afraid of the A, because actually by publishing it with the timestamp
I could eventually prove that, you know, you scooped my code, I have a timestamp that shows.
But then at the end of the day, would I really see you, someone else like me, or for what?
Just at the end of the day, I'm happy if people scooped whatever I did, it means that it was
something good.
But what about you, out of these answers, which one?
I think for me, B, like having an ugly code, was the most concern.
I never thought about like A or F, about like a lower quality copy or even F, like the code
could be stolen because you can add licenses and it's also true about your original paper,
right?
publishing your idea, it can be also stolen, but it's completely okay.
Like you have like patents and everything to have this protection.
And here I think it's the equivalent is licenses, which we will talk about.
Yeah.
It looks like B is also the most popular.
Exactly.
Another thing that I have some concerns about, which is not here, is like, because no software
is complete, right?
as a perfectionist, I'm always thinking about is it complete? Is it good enough to be published?
Not from like being ugly or like not following the clean code structures, but just as a whole,
like with all of the functions and like, is it complete to be published or not?
Yeah, I personally like the release early, release often. And so I rather just publish
something that is even half broken, but already there's an idea out there and then I will improve
and then maybe someone will try to reuse it and I realize that I completely missed,
I don't know, one exception in the conditions and so on.
So like based on age I can see like other people have this perfectionist idea as well
and it's good that I had some votes about the licensing which we are going to
to talk about in this course, in this section.
Then we have question three and question four,
which are kind of free form.
So please expand on that.
And now we will have a look,
why software often treated differently than from papers,
because some people, for example,
also have a ugly English, ugly way of writing.
Why wouldn't you be ashamed of your ugly paper
rather than your ugly software?
And then the fourth question is,
you find a repository with a code or with a library that you would like to reuse,
what are the things that you look at to decide whether you will use it?
So let's have a look at question three.
Yeah, I like the first answer because it's this overly fixation with citations and metrics.
It's also true about like one of the comments is it's usually seen just as a tool not a
scientific product and it's kind of true right because in my opinion like papers are more
about the results and the methodology that you used and the code is just a tool that
you did it.
Although like there are some aspects about like optimization of the code and how fast
it is, how much memory does it use, but in the end, it's just a tool to achieve your goal, right?
Yeah, it's true.
It's nice though that now this, or at least I think that it's nice. I'm sorry for some people,
maybe this would be more work and maybe they don't have the resources to ask for help,
But this making, or I wouldn't say forcing, but at least trying to have the code attached
with the paper, with this software availability statement, is a little bit step towards this
reproducibility and transparency so that it's clear that maybe the method section is more
meaningful if I can just read the code rather than try to infer from a very short paragraph
the method section, which filter was actually applied or which machine learning algorithm was
used. In question three, do you agree with the last comment, not peer-reviewed?
Well, kind of yes, unfortunately, because I often review papers and if there is a code,
I spend a bit of time in giving some feedback that, for example, usually the typical feedback
is that the license is missing and so in my feedback I say please add the license to your
code but then on the other end I don't have the time to actually rerun unless they make
it very easy for you that it's just one docker pull whatever command that you can easily rerun
the whole pipeline and test it but even even though I would be kind of a expert to peer
review the code there's just not enough time if I have to run fan review in the paper
But of course there are journals that are actually focused on this, like the Journal
of Open Source Software, JOS, where the peer review is actually on the code. The actual
papers that come with JOS are one or two pages. We are a bit behind time, so maybe we can
continue. But a short comment that I wanted to add is it's a bit complicated on papers, because
if your repository become popular enough other people would come and do contribute to it right
so it's not exactly peer-reviewed but somehow it is right because other people are trying to
make it better but yeah maybe we can yeah then the question four is about when you find some code
you know i've seen that many are writing about the license which it seems that it's already clear that
the license might set the rules of what you can do and what you cannot do and also this type of
not just the reusability but what we will talk soon is these changes that you can do to the
code so the so-called derivative work. Do you have any comment on this? Personally I see like
the activity and the number of like when it has been updated recently or is it
deprecated already and also another thing which I usually look at is the number of
contributors that the repository had. Yeah. All right so basically the rest of this social
coding part is what we just discussed that compared to sharing papers sharing code is
somewhat different if the paper is just you know sharing your ideas and maybe winning citations
Code is a little bit more complex feature. Sometimes people will just reuse your code, sometimes it will form some sort of base in basement foundation for something else to build on top.
And so, you know, with this, of course, this makes it a bit more complicated that papers to evaluate what could be the impact, what could be the metrics.
Eventually there are some metrics through that we will also mention later when you can actually track the downloads of a package of a software for example.
And then another aspects that is covering this page is what we touched already that the journal policies are basically going towards them.
I wouldn't say forcing but at least make it clear that there should be a code availability statement attached with the with the paper similarly as we have a date availability statement
maybe sometimes you can share the code because you're working with the company or it's a dual use case or whatever is the reason that you're not allowed to share the code
But it's clear that the journals, and not just the journals, even the organizations that are
the funding organization, whether it's the European Research Council or whatever country
organization, they are clearly making it stronger that the scientific code should be published and
public. Maybe out of one last part that we can look from this page is that it's also this aspect
that we touched in the question above, that sharing software can also be scary.
And we touched a little bit on this. We didn't really cover the aspect of bugs
and mistakes. Of course, we might be scared that what I did was wrong. But on the other hand,
is it so bad? Maybe I should actually, from the perspective of science, from the perspective of
ethics, would be actually very happy that someone finds a bug in my code. And maybe, you know,
of course, it's sad for me that I need to ask for a retraction of the paper if it really,
you know, changes all the results. But in theory, if science should be, you know,
what's the word, self-fixing, maybe this publishing the code will also improve this type of…
this type of process.
True. I would say like sometimes fixing a bug requires a lot of work and it's good that we can
collaborate and help each other on that aspect. At the same time, it can be a bit overwhelming
for the publisher of the code that you kind of feel that you're responsible for fixing those
if they are just raising the bug, not a solution.
Yeah, that's a very good point. We don't have time to discuss this, but in the page,
for those who want to spend some time reading the whole page, there's also this question that,
you know, how do you feel, like, do you feel the pressure that in the moment that you put your
code online, now suddenly people will start asking, can you add this improvement? Can you make it
work on this whatever older version of this operating system maybe i actually think the
other way around that at the moment that i put it online i'm actually removing the responsibility
that i'm saying look i managed to do this i don't have time to work on this anymore
for whatever reason please continue make it better or ask for help
Basically, we're slowly moving towards the licenses and we still have now 30 minutes
to talk about that, which is basically how our work connects to the works of others.
So I'm turning page now and now it's the page dedicated to software licenses and I guess
More or less everyone is familiar with the idea of copyright there are different types of copyright there are trademarks that protect the name of a brand from it for example from impersonation.
There are patents that patents usually are not related to software as an algorithm but you can patent a system for example or in general so-called technical invention.
And then there's the copyright that is basically protecting the creative expression, and this can include a little bit of everything, whether it's music or photographs or writings and so on.
It's also nice what it says here that this copyright is practically forever because it persists for 70 years after the lifetime of the author.
But then maybe on what you will hear as a term, if copyright feels like protecting your intellectual right, I also see a point of having a copyleft.
Basically making sure that other people can actually reuse your work and build on top of your work again in a legal way.
Okay, so this brings us to the topic of derivative work, which is a term to say that from something,
let's say Osain made something and put it in the open and I want to reuse bits of it.
I want to maybe reuse some bits as they are, some Python functions, because I don't really
have any improvements to go there, or maybe I want to, you know, remix, resample, invent
my own flavor on some whatever visualization part of the script that Ossane did.
And of course I can do this, or like the question that maybe would be for myself, am I actually
able to do this?
Would Ossane work allow me to do this type of derivative work, or is it that, you know,
I can't actually even touch or run on my computer or say it works.
So this derivative work is actually, when it comes to software, it's not intuitive
at all of what constitutes derivative work and me myself, when I was attending my first
code refinery many years ago, I was actually kind of surprised that some of the options
here are considered derivative work.
So in this question file for you, please don't spy to the solution box, can you try to answer
in the notes document which of these ARC derivative works.
So derivative you understand that you are basically remixing, reusing the existing code
that you have found online.
So maybe we let some time to answer because we don't want to spoil the fun.
Yes.
And we have some questions on the note I'm trying to answer.
Is there anything to highlight?
I think two of them are coming from previous sections and copy pasted here.
It's about Docker and Kubernetes and the Conda environment, which I think we can pass.
But a question is, when you license your code, does it belong to your employer or to you?
How does it work?
Yeah.
So, as usual, what I learned from the lawyers that the best answer is it depends.
It depends on what type of agreement do you have with your employer.
Usually it's flexible in a sense that sometimes I've seen, and I'm not specifically talking
about my university, my employer, but I've seen people writing, you know, copyright,
in my case would be [name]-Alto University. At the end of the day, because software per
se cannot be turned into patent unless you build a system around it, the employer, at
least this public organization like universities, they don't really care much. But it's a different
story if you would be working for a company where you can clearly understand that you
as a coder for a company you don't own anything and the employer clearly writes in the contract
that whatever you produce.
But the same is also, and it's not intuitive, it's also for data.
And this is a discussion that I often have with our researchers that they think because
they collected the data, interviews, measurement, whatever, that it's their data.
And it's actually very rare that it's their data in the specific context of Finnish universities.
If you are on your own money, on your own grant, then it is your data.
But 99% of the time, it's actually the university owns the data.
So yeah, in this sense, it's complicated.
Yep.
I just want to add that it depends on the policy of the company that you are working.
And I know even for some companies, if you are an employee there, even if you develop
some code out of your working hours, still the code that you produce, it belongs to the
company.
So it depends on the policy.
So you can't even code as a hobby.
Unfortunately, yes, it depends on the company's policy.
Yeah, well, fair enough.
Maybe it's the same, you know, you can think of musician that if you're making music outside
of your contract with your record label, maybe the record label manager gets angry.
Yep.
All right.
But question five, there's some answers here and basically A to D, they are all to be considered
derivative works that you know, you download some code and then you donate or you change
the code and modify the code.
what kind of was surprised for me, and of course it depends, that E and F can also be considered
derivative work. So even though I'm taking our same repository, that's some Python package,
and I just rewrite it in R, I might still be doing derivative work, you know, if I follow the same
logic, the same function structure, the same. It would be different if, say, it would sit down
with me without showing any code, tell me what the package is doing, and then I would try to,
you know, code it based on the description. So it would be like that I would read O'Sane's paper
on the description of this package and just put it in the paper I try to write my own version.
And so yeah, this was a bit unintuitive for me,
but on the other hand it makes sense when things start to be kind of literal.
Well, it's also interesting, I would add another option here that, I don't know, you're using
some ChatGPT or Copilot to generate code. Is it derivative work? Because these ChatGPT
large language models, they actually have ingested lots of software from whatever open
repositories, but then they don't tell you who originally wrote a function very similar
to the one that you asked, but then again it's complicated.
Do you actually do, or saying, if you use Copilot or ChargeGPT to get help, let's say
with a function, would you start searching if that function, if bits of that function
would already exist on the internet that then you would find?
Not that you have to, because this is also the thing that when you generate something
with this large language models, you are actually become the copyright owner of what is generated,
which is counterintuitive in a way, because you feel that ethically, it's not you that
made those things, but just some machine who has read many, many code scripts.
But how do you feel as a user of, because I guess you use now sometimes these copilots
or...
Yeah.
All the time.
But I think it's something that, as a society, we still have to think about it.
What should we do?
Because it's generally a new concept that we are facing, and I think it would resolve
and we would come with a bit more macho ways on how to cite it and how to use it.
But personally, if I use something and I get some ideas or use the whole functions that
the generative AI generates, no, I don't go and search what is the original repository
that produced this one.
This is of course, I don't have an answer myself.
And if people want to give their own opinion, in my opinion, it's nice anyway, that people
discuss this use of these new tools, generative AI and how people are using them, because
maybe then we can come up with a consensus on an ethical and responsible way of using them.
We also have a question about these generative AIs. You said if you generate something like a
piece of code, you would become then the owner of the code, right? Is that correct?
Yeah, the default policy is that whatever you generate with the large language model,
you are the copyright owner.
Do you add any citations or anything that I use generative AI for these codes I created?
So, the journals have expanded on their policies on the use of generative AI, and so now publishers
like Nature or whatever, many publishers, they would now basically require you to add
a statement, how generative AI was used in the process.
I don't have, like I'm not too strong, when I teach about these things I can tell that
If you just used it for, I don't know, fixing your English grammar, maybe, there's no point.
But if it's clear that that work would have not been able without the use of generative AI,
then of course it must be mentioned. So if my level of coding is very basic for whatever reason,
because I just started, and I get help from the generative AI, and I'm basically not able to
judge myself, is this code that the generative AI made right, even though I see with the tests that
that I, you know, add that it feels right.
At least I can be transparent that, you know,
I got help or I used ChatGPT for generating the code
for this and the code is published
at this and that repository.
All right, so yeah, when it comes to software licenses,
so now we are a bit focusing on software.
I've seen some people in the notes
talking also about Creative Common.
We will touch a little bit on so-called data licensee later.
But in general, there is a taxonomy of software licenses.
This was from the European Commission, yes, so it's a publication that basically talks
about the EU public license, the European Union public license.
And so when it comes to software licenses, there are different, basically there's a continuum
of things that would basically, they are very dark green, that you could basically do whatever
you want with that type of license.
So if you find a code and with that code in, I don't know, GitHub, there is attached a
license that says MIT or BST and so on, it means that most likely you can reuse it and
you can do anything, anything you want.
You can build on it.
In some cases, you don't even maybe need to tell who was the original author.
On the other end of the spectrum, we have the so-called strong copyleft licenses.
So here, the idea is that if I find, let's say that [name] writes a package that I want
to reuse, but it comes with a strong copyleft license, it means that whatever I derive from
Ossaint work should also be released with that strong copyleft. So I need to use the same license
and in some cases, as they say, this license infects the rest of my code. So it's not just
the code that is using Ossaint's strong copyleft work that needs to be released with that license,
it might attach my whole project and now I have to also release it with the strong copyleft license.
And in between there are this more kind of share-alike. The idea of share-alike is that okay, I make this software public with this license, but I wouldn't mind that if you improve the software, you are kind of allowing me to basically get your improvement so that I can also reuse.
use. So it's kind of in between the two, the very permissive one that lets anybody else to do
whatever they want and the very strict one that forces everybody else to do as you decide to do.
What is your feeling also from a research software engineer perspective? Have you worked with the
projects that have all sorts of licenses or do you feel that in general it's more towards these
permissive licenses? Personally, I'm more of the more open licenses like MIT or Creative Common
ones. And my idea is I'm using other people's code and if I'm able to publish the code,
it's not something confidential or it's not an ongoing project that I cannot publish yet,
I would go with that more open licenses. But I can totally understand like for some of the
projects it's whether to have more copy left licenses or even a strong copy left licenses.
An interesting thing is about like this picture that we have is about
that arrows that we have. Can you also explain what are the arrows and how does it work?
Yes, so here they talk about that the arrows represent compatibility, and so that in some
cases, you know, some licenses can kind of leave, can be compatible with other licenses,
but in some other cases the compatibility, you know, when the, like for example here,
so if I remember correctly, this red block is more the proprietary licenses, and so the
the very permissive licenses are compatible
with proprietary licenses,
meaning that you can release a software
that is not going to be open source
and inside it uses some of the permissive libraries,
but then here you see there's no compatibility
between if something is released
with a very strong compi left,
then nobody can use it in a proprietary software.
There's also here for those who want to explore more,
there are this nice set of links that help you, for example,
comparing licenses and choosing licenses.
There are different, there are many nice tools that given,
you might even answer some questionnaire
or what you would like to do with your license
and then they can recommend you
that whatever type of licenses.
All right, so maybe I think we agreed
that we will not do this exercise for the sake of speed,
and we can now talk when should I add a license.
So the best of course is as early as possible,
like with everything else,
that if you agree at the beginning
that you wanna choose a certain license,
then you choose it at the beginning.
It's funny that with the GitHub interface,
you create a repository from the web interface, immediately it asks you which license do you
want to attach with it. So, you know, it's clear, you know.
And here I can see citations to myself. What I was saying also earlier that if you work
from the very beginning as if your project is already public and open, then, you know,
you can already think at the very beginning that there's a license, that there's a policy.
of course, in this social coding part, we didn't really mention this earlier, but you might also
want to recommend how people can contribute to the improvements of your code. You can create
a community around your project and tools like GitHub allow you easily to create issues,
create discussions around your code. So basically, when should you add a license? As early as
possible, and how to add a license if your work is derivative work. So basically these tools that
I mentioned earlier that could check the compatibility would allow you to see that if you
reuse some specific package that might have permissive or strong copyleft licenses, then you
can see what type of license you can basically attach to the code. In general, maybe one comment
And that, at least when I was asking you saying that you are in favor of more permissive licenses,
what I wanted to add is that sometimes you have to think that the users of your software,
those who will reuse it, they are other people like you.
So the permissive licenses, even though you might feel you are donating your code to the
Google, Microsoft, Meta, whatever, at the end of the day, you're just making it easier
for other people like you to reuse your code if you have a permissive license. With more
copyleft licenses, they're of course very ethical and it's nice that some projects are
strong copyleft and they demand that whoever uses those projects also become strong copyleft.
But when it comes to researchers like us, sometimes we might just make the life more
complicated when the researchers need to publish their code with their papers.
So at the end of the day, if you aren't sure which one to pick, go with the most permissive
licenses.
Do you have any comment on this, I was saying?
No, it was perfect coverage.
Thanks.
Yeah.
It's not an exact question on the HackMD, but I get a team that it's happening, like
let's say sorting algorithms, right?
So do someone own the sorting algorithms and have license on them, or only it depends on
the implementation and the code has been published?
Yeah I'm not a lawyer so I can't don't take my words for a legal advice but in my understanding and in my discussion with legal experts
the idea the algorithm the pseudocode is not patentable so if I write a book with pseudocode on how to do this whatever sorting method
nobody can patented but in the moment that i make an implementation as a system that is reusable kind of as a stand alone system so not just writing
the pseudo code into some code then it can be patented so let's say that i have a web application where you copy paste your
vector of numbers and then press a button and then my web application so what's your number in a very whatever fast way
then this is a system and i can't attend this web application for sorting numbers
but if i would just have the code that does the sort i would not be able to pretend that but i can still protect it with the license so that i can say ok you wanna use my short fast sort algorithm
then, I don't know, I'm going to attach a very copyleft license and you have to make everything
open if you use it. Let's see if there's any other question to bring up. It's nice that there's
many answers already so that we don't have to. Yeah, that's why I was a bit silent. I was trying
to blast the rest of my knowledge. But there are other contributors too. Thanks, everyone.
In general, there's also sometimes what could happen is that things might change in time.
So that maybe a project starts with a certain license, but then for whatever reason you realize
that I don't know you really need to adopt change the license to a more copyleft one because you
started using some software that has a more copyleft license of course license you can change
in time it's not preferable in a sense that if you would really need to apply this you would kind of
need to contact you know your user base and tell them okay you've been using my code as permissive
license, but from today, the license is not permissive anymore. It becomes copy left.
So of course, you might be familiar yourself that the terms and condition of whatever
service that you use change in time so often that nobody even reads what is the new change.
So the same would also go here.
So, changing the license is not retroactive, and if someone is still using the code, does
it apply to them, or how does it work?
Yeah, well, again, it depends, because I would hope that it's not retroactive in a sense
that if a release of a certain version of a certain tool was released with, let's say,
very open permissive license that I'm still allowed to use that open version of the software
because maybe the company decided that from version 2.0 they went full copyright.
So maybe I'm still allowed to use version 1.0 but 2.0 I need to buy whatever the license
from the company.
But then there are also some other aspects, maybe this is more related to data, that can
be changes to the license of data that can be retroactive. And the general data protection
regulation, the GDPR, is one example of this. So that if I released open personal data 10 years
ago, actually GDPR would affect the license of that data and would not allow me to keep it open
anymore. So again, it depends. But it's clear, for example, for those who really are into these legal
matters, I would really recommend reading this paper from the European Commission where they
describe this type of license, the European Union Public License. It's a bit of a, it's a
share-alike license, so it's not in the most permissive, but it's also not in the most strong
copy left. And what is interesting is then the European, whatever projects related to the
European Commission, they are being released with this license, so that it's clear that it's for the
benefit of everyone that those who will reuse this code kind of make also their code in this public
licensure like public license and then you know you can basically get what other people
made with your code and improve your code it's a little bit more work of course to
to make sure that also the new code that you release also follows this the same type of
share alike license, but this is kind of the best balance between being permissive and letting other
people to use as much as possible and also being more ethical to kind of also get back from what
you give. Yeah, we also have a comment from a user that the more open licenses cannot be closed
retroactively and also like if you have different versions or you release a new version you can
change the license but as a standard for the free software you cannot change the existing license
without changing that version or the code. Yeah, so that's what I was saying as well. Yes,
another thing that I wanted to ask is do you have any comments or thoughts on multi-licensing or
Or do you usually use one-line sentence or what is the best practice here?
Well, I mean, I see the point of having multi-licenses, dual licenses, because sometimes some businesses,
maybe in the context of academic research, maybe there's not much point.
But if some of the research turns into a business idea or if companies want to have a mixture
of copyright, private code, and public, there is a benefit that if something is used for,
I don't know, commercial purposes, then maybe you follow a certain license. But then again,
I'm also a bit conflicted with these dual licenses, because if one really looks at the
open source software licenses, it is clear that you can't really impose what people can do with
your code. One of the advantages of the open source software licenses is that
you're not liable yourself with whatever people will do, but also you can't control if people,
for example, will use your code for doing something malicious. You can't block them
with these licenses. Yeah, but I guess that the takeaway here is like you can use multiple licenses
which can be a good practice if it's suitable for your case, for your data,
for your some files. You can add a different license than the general license that you have for
for the whole repository.
All right, I guess it's time for a little break.
We can come back,
and maybe we can go back at the 14 o'clock,
or 14.01, 14.02.
Yeah, I mean, it's break.
Yeah, maybe 14.02.
All right, so let's have a little break
and we will be back in 10 minutes.
Okay.
you
Hello, everyone, and welcome back.
the social coding section. We already talked about social coding and sharing your code and also
a bit about licensing. Now we want to talk about software citations. We talked about
how code is a bit different than papers and why there are different things that you have to consider
and citation is one of the things which maybe is more similar and also a bit different than
and paper citations, I would say.
So here in the screen, you can see,
we want to talk about FAIR principles first.
So [name], what is FAIR principles?
Yeah, so we touched on this FAIR principles
also in the morning when it comes to the reproducibility.
And basically the FAIR principle is like,
the acronyms would be findable, accessible,
interoperable and reusable.
And now while this maybe is kind of easy to understand when it comes to data because of course you want your data set to be findable by whatever search system
accessible whether it's fully open or open on request so but at least there is a way to access it interoperable which means that it can work with other tools it's in a format that
other softwares can open it and read it, and reusable so that there is, like we just discussed,
a license that would give some principles on how to reuse it. To reuse it, the same
fair principles for data, they can also be extended to software. And so again, that people
can find your software, that they can access it, they can download it, interoperable so that it
works with other systems and that there is a clear way on how to reuse it with the clear
licenses attached to the software, for example.
So again, because sometimes people, you might think, okay, I put my software, my scripts
that I've done for this paper, I put them in my university homepage or they are on GitHub
and that's it. We always need to think a little bit long term and I have to mention actually that
me myself, I decided to use some GitHub repository from the university and then that repository
is not there anymore so now I have published paper that are pointed to some Git repository
hosted by a department that doesn't exist anymore and so once in a while I get questions where is
the code now, you know. So there was a mistake on my side that I didn't actually create a so-called
DOI, digital object identifier, or PID, persistent identifier, because if I would have done that,
another organization would have taken care of preserving my software for as many years as we
can think of. And so what we see here in this make your code citable and persistent, the persistent
part is exactly this. It's not enough to put it on your web page or to put it on github because
github maybe will change your account will be i don't know maybe you decide to delete your account
and with that all your repository or by accident you even delete a repository because you thought
that that was just a side project. So there are services like Zenodo which is hosted by CERN
and with Zenodo you can basically get a digital object identifier for anything digital. It can be
the software release for example or it can also be used for data sets that can be published.
And so what is nice about this Zenodo repository is that it automatically can be linked with your
open with your available GitHub repositories so that whenever you create a release on your
GitHub project repository, Zenodo can actually automatically basically pull the new release
so that you can basically have a permanent copy of your GitHub releases stored in the CERN
data center. Have you ever published this type of DOI or have you helped anyone with this type of
getting a DOI for a software? Yeah, we were helping a researcher to publish their code and
we had to use that and also explain the things that you already explained about why it's important
to just have a DOI and it's not enough to only host it on your
personal github account because in 10 years github can go down, right? We don't know.
People and researchers are already familiar with this because it's also
a very similar aspect in publishing your paper as well. It's not enough to publish your PDF or
PDF of your research on your personal website or Google Drive, you have to have a DOI
to make it persistent for the future. Yeah, it's also nice that the interface that
comes with the Zenodo website, if you see, if you search for some software, you can actually
look at some metrics. Again, we don't do this for the metrics, but sometimes the metrics help us,
us, whatever motivate our bosses, that you can look at metrics like number of downloads
and number of citations so that you can also quantify a little bit the impact that your
software or scripts might have.
What is here now, it is a checklist.
Checklists are always useful because they're practical and you can basically see what is
is needed to make your software citable.
And so assigning appropriate license,
like we mentioned before the break,
then we want to have a description of the software
so that there is appropriate metadata format,
clear version numbers, authors are credited,
we get this persistent identifier like the DOI,
And then even, you know, sometimes we won't tell
in the software which publication to cite
because in some cases, some publications might be related.
There are so-called software packages publications,
but in some other cases, the main publication is about,
let's say, some application of the software,
but still you release the software
along with the original publication.
Recently, there's also the way that through your
or on your GitHub repository,
you can also like a so-called machine-readable
software citation file,
so CFF, software citation file format.
And it basically looks something like this.
So machine-readable means that a computer,
another computer can automatically read,
and you see that these are like variables
with the names and the values,
and some can be, you know, structure.
It looks a bit like this YAML, YAML files.
And so this pre kind of fixed metadata about the software
makes it easier and makes it especially
if you have, you know, search engines
or specific publication engines
that it's easy for these other tools
to basically index your software
and make it findable and accessible and so on
with the fair principles.
GitHub now supports this citation CFF files.
So if you name the file with this, exactly like a citation.cff, it can already be automatically
interpreted by GitHub and here there's some like a video how to create it and even a web.
But in practice, if you are fine with using some text editor, you can even take just this
template and reuse it.
So anything else to add? Is there anything in the notes document worth?
No, we don't have any questions or comments till now.
All right. Well then, in general also, this is one way to get your citations with the
software, but in some cases, maybe your software, the contribution that you and your research
group add to the software can be substantial so that there can be papers that are truly
about software. So full papers that they describe the software package and then there are specific
journals that accept this type of software papers. So then if I can kind of call back
of someone was mentioning that sometimes software is not peer-reviewed with this type of work,
you can understand that it's the software even more important than the actual paper.
And so it might go to more extensive peer review and checks and compatibility and so on.
At the end of the day, like I mentioned earlier, it's maybe not the actual work of the two or three peer reviewers, but it's really the community that is around the software project.
So if these larger packages, they have a big community around, and we can all be part of that community, whether it's just fixing a typo in the documentation or working on a new release with the main developers,
So that the peer review is truly a dynamic process that basically never ends.
It's not that when this software was published in 2021, it has not been touched.
I'm sure that it has improved in the meantime and it has evolved and gotten better and better.
One note that I wanted to add is the papers that only talking about the software are becoming
more popular nowadays. And for, at least for a lot of Python libraries, all libraries, you can see
they publish the paper. And it's also good for the researchers as well, because they get
many, many citations, which is maybe not the case for your scientific papers. So consider on
publishing the paper for your code as well, which is becoming more popular nowadays.
Yeah, and it's true. And it's nice that maybe this type of metrics like, you know, maybe
right now in the CV, in some standard CV that might not yet be space for your software packages,
but these are catching up. So I can mention in Finland, there is the tank CV, which is
one format used by the Finnish grant agencies. And already they would have a section right
now they have a section right now that where one can add this type of extra non-typical
paper type of publications or like software.
All right so we still have 10 minutes left and then of course we will ask about the feedback
of the day. The last part is about sharing data. Now there are many and better and more
extensive talks online on sharing data because as you can understand when it comes we discussed a
lot about software sharing and contributing and reuse it but all the same could be said about data
that sometimes we might wanna have a data set that is truly copyrighted and so nobody else
can access and they need to ask you for a license or maybe they need to pay you but some other times
we might have a data set that you can fully release opening whether because you decide to do so with
your employer with your supervisor and of course everything in between where you might want like
we had this share alike for the software the same would be for the data that you share the data but
any derivative work done with the data should also be released with a similar license for example.
So, when it comes to this, where to actually share the data, what type of options are there,
this Zenodo repository is also mentioned in this case.
In Zenodo, it's not just about sharing the release of your software, but you can share
all sorts of data.
And it's really nice that you can also share slides and white papers or anything that you
feel like that can contribute to your scientific community. But Zenodo is not the only one and so
there are these other services. I'd like to at least mention the Open Science Framework
that allows to do this type of sharing of nice dataset. In international context,
the Open Science Framework is hosted in the United States. If I remember, Zenodo is in Switzerland.
Figshare I think now is bought by Naturespringer, Eudat is basically EOSC or European platform
and Dryad is also, I don't think it's public anymore or they might give you a non-profit
like a small, how do you call, freemium license, but here then we will not go through this
but different countries, at least in the Nordics, where most of you are right now,
there are different national services for sharing the data.
And there are also resources for the so-called data management. Now, again, we will not expand
much on here, but if you think that if Git was used for keeping versions of your code,
the same could be done with data so that you can version the version of the data set because you had version 1.0 that had some
i don't know outliers but then you have version 2.0 where you clean the data remove the outliers and so on so this type of tools like data lad data stewardship wizard
githanex that is not mentioned here but it's Prattix DataLabs so they can help you
basically keep also the versioning of the of the data and not just of the code and then when it
comes to the licensing of data sets and databases with our specific type of of data set there are
different um there are different legislation that can cover this and similarly as we had for software
we can have something that is in the full spectrum from completely open public domain to completely private copyright.
So the type of licenses that you hear about data, there's so-called creative common licenses, there are different flavors.
With the CC0 being the so-called public domain, where it's as open as possible, people can reuse it, they don't even need to cite you.
And then more kind of restrictions on the reuse of the data, which could be that people need to cite you, or people cannot do commercial work with that, or this share alike that people need to re-share what they did with the data as you are doing with the data, and basically so on.
When it comes to the machine learning and AI, things are, of course, getting a little bit more complicated.
Machine learning models are impractical data, so the model, the weights on its own, they can't really be, you can't do much with those,
unless you have a system to basically run the models
and whether you are generating data or classifying
whatever you're classifying.
But what is tricky and at least what is a bit blurred
right now here in the context of AI
and machine learning models is that sometimes
you hear things like open source models
or open source language models.
But if one really would kind of look
at the definition of open source,
are actually not open source. Sometimes people call open weights so that the models, the weights,
the actual file, you can download it and reuse it but you have no idea of how that model was done,
so everything else basically around the model is actually not open at all.
Here it mentions this Artificial Intelligence Act which was entering into force on the 1st of
August of this year and the AI act adds some basically restrictions on what the researchers
even can basically open if you're not planning to open anything related to your AI models
basically the AI act lets you do whatever you want but in the moment that you need to start
sharing your model you need to basically see if you would if your type of machine learning model
would fall inside of these so-called high-risk or prohibited AI systems. And of course there
are different, how can I say, obligations, there are different legal obligations depending
on what type of artificial intelligence systems you might be working on. In general, we have
some material on these new topics that we will expand on this page. But if you have
questions of course let them please write them down in the in the chat and then many nice links
here that would be nice to browse together but our time is soon over. I was saying do you have
any comments or is there anything to highlight from the notes? No, in the notes we don't have any
any direct question to sharing data.
We had some questions about software citations
and some about like accounts, but not about sharing data.
And yeah, it was completely good.
If you want to pick,
if you need to choose one of these further readings
and you have time to go deeper
into all this reproducible research,
opening data and opening software,
really recommend this Turing Way, which is an open book on all these topics. It's a nice read,
you can read it, it's open, you can read it on your mobile phone during your commute.
So if you really need to pick one, I recommend the first one. And in general, I mean, it's nice
that we are building a community together through CodeRefinery. If you explore our pages, you can
also get access to a chat and in the chats that we use it's called Zulip and through the Zulip
chat you can join discussions. We can continue discussions on these topics and we have all sorts
of discussions there so that is something nice. We already saw some participants from
this workshop have already joined the Code Refinery chat. All right so we still have eight minutes
which is a good moment for asking for feedback so it would be great if on the notes we could
paste the usual feedback for the day if this was too fast too slow
and i see that they are already there i could actually switch
to the notes view with my movie directory interface
And so yes, as usual, even though we give similar lessons over the years, they're never
exactly the same, the phases are changing, we might update the lesson a little bit and
of course what makes this unique is your questions and your experience, so please give us feedback
And if there's something you want to, you think that we could have covered more or less, please write it down.
Then tomorrow we have the fifth day of the workshop.
And tomorrow the topic will be documentation, which is kind of somewhat related with the topics of the day.
so because along with the license you also want to tell people not just how to use your code but also
how to maybe you know expand it contribute to it and so on and then the second part of tomorrow
will be about Jupyter notebooks maybe some of you are already familiar with this way of interacting
with code and data and hopefully for those who have never experienced this it's it's something
that you can try out.
Again, tomorrow will be like a demo day,
so you're not expected to actually run things.
But if you want to actually do and see what people are doing,
whether you want to build a documentation.
And it's not just about documentation,
because with the same system that
will be introduced tomorrow, you can also,
it's the same system that we use to build our web pages,
Our training materials, they're all built with this same system.
And so you can also learn how to create your website, for example,
under this github.io if you want.
And so if you want to test these things,
you please follow our installation instructions
if you're planning to do that.
All right.
I think I see that people are commenting.
Is there anything to highlight?
Let me have a look at the chat.
Based on the feedback, I think at least there was on track.
People were satisfied with the speed.
And although we have some comments that it was a bit too fast,
and there were many topics that we had to cover.
And unfortunately, maybe it was a bit too fast.
If you don't have the required background
or if you're not familiar with the subject,
it can be a bit overwhelming.
Yeah.
This is exactly why we decided almost a year ago
to not having exercises in this week too,
because sometimes not only there's lots of new topics
on top of those, try to run snake make locally
or building a Zenodo repository or what do you call it?
DOI, getting a DOI through the Zenodo Sandbox.
So we, hopefully this is a little bit more digestible
and useful.
And of course we provide you with all these links
and other resources that those who really have time
can try themselves and please join our Zulip chat
so that we can continue discussing there
helping you there if you want to try these things and you need further help.
All right, so hopefully this was a good day four and I can maybe add also a reminder that
day six will be more about coding related things. We will cover things like automated
testing and modular code development.
And then again, if you want to do,
or if you want to try the exercises
that the instructors are gonna show on the stream,
you can also, you should basically also install
what we recommend in our installation pages.
But then again, it's just fine
to participate through the questions.
And thank you again for the many questions.
There's almost 50 today.
so it was a great they were so active. Also thanks for the participants who are
active in answering other questions. Thanks. I see one question that is for me that is related to the
one ECT credit and so yes in this case I try to be as clear as possible on that page but if
something is not clear I'm happy to expand it. In practice this means that if you are sure that
your supervisor or study coordinator or whoever is able to accept a kind of an official paper from
me that says that this person has completed the Code Refinery workshop. There are very simple
homework to do for getting the certificate then I will give you this document and then you can
convert that into into a credit. And if you are at Aalto University you don't you just need to
to give me your student number and I will add the credit for you on our system but in
general we don't track the if you were attending you know whatever days you were attending
as long as you do the homeworks we can you know we can give you we can give you the credit
Okay, so let's see if there's any other quick question to pick.
We still have one minute and a half.
Yeah, I think you're good.
Yeah, I think most of the things are uncertain.
All right, maybe we can call it a day, one minute earlier, and thank you for watching.
The recordings will appear immediately on Twitch TV and later on the week on our YouTube
channels and so see you tomorrow for day five of Code Refinery. Thank you [name] for being
here with me and thank you everyone for watching.
Thank you everyone for joining.
Bye.
Bye bye.