and how to do that, how to do collaborative and distributed version control, and what are the
challenges there. You further have things like stabilizing your computing environment so that
others can more easily reproduce what you have done, because they know what your
environment actually looked like, and part of this is covered today.
and other ways to do this are shown in more detail tomorrow and on Thursday and
it's of course also about how you publish your research outputs,
how you publish your code, your data, your documents that you need and social
coding and open software will also be discussed later today. So, but let's jump
into reproducible research and why we want to do that. And there's a nice PhD comic about this
where Professor Smith has his PhD student in front of him and asks, well that's it. Well don't
worry, you don't have to start your code from scratch. You can reuse the software that the
previous person on the project wrote several years ago. And are there instructions for how to use it?
I doubt it.
Is the code commented?
Not likely.
And where are the files?
Who knows?
This is going to be painful, isn't it?
Just a scratch.
And
I think this is
at least to some extent
very much what a lot of people
in academia
have experienced. I myself had
a similar thing where I was told
sold. Here is code that we want to have in our library. Please connect it to the library that
we have." And there wasn't a lot of documentation and that was essentially my bachelor thesis
in the end. So this happens all the time, unfortunately. And while that's bad, there's
also the problem that's here in this anecdote where a group of researchers have obtained great
results and submitted their work to a high-profile journal. The reviewers ask for a few more figures
and some additional analysis, which is actually quite common. The researchers start working on
those revisions, generate modified figures, but find inconsistencies with their old figures.
And then the problems start because the researchers can't find some of the data they
used to generate the original results and they can't figure out which parameters they used
when running their original analysis. And well, that manuscript is likely to just end up in a
drawer and never really be published because they don't know what they actually did.
Yeah, this is actually the anecdote highlights the most, to me, the most important aspect of the
the reproducibility and things we want to do for reproducibility, which is that you
should make your own life easier, that you can reproduce your own results. And this graph
also highlights that problem.
Yeah, it's, and at least to me, it's somewhat understandable if there are some issues with
reproducibility in experimental fields where there are so many confounding factors, where
there have been examples where a changed water pipe changed the results because there was
something coming from the water pipe that wasn't expected, that they didn't test for
and that changed the results. But in a computational setting, this should not happen. Because we
can a lot better control what we are doing. And this should be a lot more reproducible.
And anything in a computational field that's not reproducible comes essentially down to
badly documented steps for the experiment. And there are different levels of reproducibility.
By the way, can we highlight that in the graph, the question that I have failed to reproduce
an experiment and my own.
And it's like...
There isn't a big difference between your own and someone else's.
Yeah, there isn't a big difference.
And there is a huge amount of percentage, like in both cases.
So yeah, and this was 2016, but basically in eight years, I don't think anything has
fundamentally changed.
One would hope that this has gone down a little bit, but yeah, I would also expect that it
hasn't gone down substantially.
And essentially, as I mentioned earlier, so you have different levels of reproducibility
and you have a kind of pyramid on what can be reproduced and of course the environment in
especially experimental settings can be something that is potentially very difficult to control
but we can control it reasonably well in a computational setting and in a computational
setting it's also we have code and data and that should be controllable because the data has been
it's there it has been generated so and it shouldn't change and the code also has been there
and shouldn't change then it comes to how has the code been used that's documentation what
parameters have been used that's documentation and only in the end once we have all this we create
we build an article and if if something below here fails then this article fails because it
can't be reproduced because if we don't know what parameters we had well nice to have the code but
how did the results actually get obtained we don't know so the whole basis of this article
crumbles essentially and we have asked you uh in the collaborative document to post a few of your
experiences with reproducibility of the things. And I actually want to highlight this first one
that was in here, because this is something that happens both to the person writing it
and to others coming there. You have stuff and you try to read it and think, well, yeah, it has
been done but I don't get anything here because it's not well documented or it's not well written
and you essentially have to redo things and that's something that's very very common.
Here this is also the typical yeah a new version of the package has been
been published and the old version doesn't work on the current system anymore, or you
have to go to great length to go through this, which is a really huge issue.
I can relate to all of these answers, and one thing I actually want to point out is
that in the question it says that a script or a figure you created a few months ago.
For me, I don't have to wait a few months, because like a day or two is completely enough.
Because like I, if I don't document stuff for myself, in two days, it's basically, I
may have to start over.
So I completely know what people are
coming from with these comments.
Yeah.
So I think all of these are really
good examples of why we need reproducible research.
And I hope we can show you a couple of things
that help you in making your reproducibility
or making your work more reproducible,
either by others or yourself.
Okay.
And so just an overview of the next two hours.
So we have four subtopics here.
So first is organizing your projects.
So files and folders, structure, basically.
The next is recording computational steps.
So what was run and when and how, then recording dependencies, which is that what is the software
or what libraries and which versions of software and libraries your code is using to get the
the results, and then recording environments, which is.
What operating system, what system libraries?
So it's actually going one step further
down the environment chain.
Yeah, one step further down the rabbit hole of reproducibility.
Yeah.
OK, yeah, sorry, go ahead.
So let's get into organizing your projects.
So yeah, it's really one of the first steps
to make your work reputable is to organize your projects well,
so to have a structure that you understand where you can
actually find things again.
Because even the finding the right function,
finding the right piece of data can become difficult
if your data and your project is not properly organized.
So first of all, of course,
have everything that belongs to a project
in a single folder,
because then you have something where you can have it
or where you know, okay, this is what it is.
And if that's not possible,
because you have, for example,
some big data that needs to be stored elsewhere,
have links or indicators where that data can be found early on.
That can be in a README or in some other way,
how this can be stored.
Use different projects in different folders.
Don't mix.
It will only lead to a mess, and you can't get out
of that mess again.
Because untangling mixed up projects
will always be a problem.
If you have things like code that you use in both projects,
set up a Git repository for the code
and clone it into both projects.
And potentially have a branch for each project
if they really do have different code in the end,
but try to get the code in a way that both can use it.
can use it. Use a consistent and informative directory structure. This, for example,
this is an example of what you can do. Have data, process data. So data is the raw information. This
is what you got from your experiments or what you got from an external partner or a partner.
this is the raw data. Process data is anything that you have pre-processed or
modified. The manuscript is everything that's connected with the with writing
the article in the end or the articles if you have multiple for the same
project. Results is essentially finished data, some tables, figures, and everything that you
want to put into the manuscript potentially. Source is your code with a license, with requirements
and information about it. And doc is the additional documentation. Your readme can already
contain some of the docs or contain information on, okay, this is where you find the documentation
for this. Also, I'd like to point out that in many, many, many cases, readme is enough.
So you shouldn't be... A well-written readme is enough.
Yeah, well-written readme is... Extensive readme is enough. But the point is that we shouldn't be
be kind of intimidated by the thought
that the documentation needs to be a whole HTML documentation
web page.
I think the simplest check is, once you've done your stuff
and you're happy with me, ask a colleague that's
not in the project, could you take this
and reproduce the figures?
And not help them by doing it.
Yeah.
One small thing, try to avoid spaces in directories and filenames.
Yes, it's uglier to read, but a lot of times there are programs that don't handle spaces well.
So not having spaces in there can make things a lot easier computational-wise.
It's not absolutely necessary, but it's, I would say, good practice.
If you need separate public and private parts, you can create a public and private Git repository.
Make sure that they are not in the same Git network. I would really create separate
repositories for it and not fork from the one to the other and then make it private.
it. If you need to separate public and secret data, in the same repository, you can use
gitignore, as was, I think, discussed last week. And having and setting up a gitignore
early on always makes sense. And yes, and the rest, I think, we already mentioned.
So about the project structure, does your project
always look like this structure?
Does it often look like this?
Does it never look like this, this example?
It looks similar.
I don't really have these parts at the moment anymore,
But I do have their source code data potential documentation.
But as you mentioned, I'm actually mainly readmes
that sometimes point to another to a second MD markdown
file for a specific setup of development systems
or something like that.
But yeah, conceptually similar.
It looks very standard.
And it's always nice to use standard practices.
Yep, so, um, sorry, um, yeah, um, the tracking, tracking your data and your project is also
important.
Well, all code should be version controlled and should be in the source code folder, have
a license in there.
You can also version control data files if they are not too large.
If they are very large, you can still version control them with systems like Git Annex or
Git LFS.
Large file system.
Where you can essentially, where the file is essentially placed somewhere else and it's
just the version that's being tracked.
GitAnnex essentially builds an additional network of repositories where it knows where
the data is residing and you can get the data, but if you don't explicitly want it, you don't
have to download it.
You can also, if they are sensitive or too large for being tracked, put them into gitignore
and provide them on a different system,
which is perfectly fine,
especially if it's research data
that doesn't really change.
So if you have all your experimental data done
and you're not going to get more experimental data,
you can essentially put this into a folder,
put it onto some data server and yeah,
and then just point to it in the README
or somewhere else.
Intermediate files don't really need to be tracked.
Commonly, there might be situations
where the pre-processing takes a long time
and you actually want to keep that data stored
and potentially tracked as well.
But in general, I would say process data
can be reproduced from the original data
or should be reproducible from the original data
and therefore doesn't need to be tracked.
Well, using git tags to mark specific versions of results is always also a good idea, because
you then know, okay, this is the version that was submitted for the thesis or for the paper,
and people can, and you can essentially in the paper point to this version, because that's
the data that was being used for the paper while your code could have developed on.
Yeah, so we have two more questions here that we can also put into the
that are already in the... Yeah, they are in the notes and everybody is welcome to.
It's mainly questions about how, the first is mainly if you use version control for academic
papers and the second is how if you do, how you handle collaborative issues.
Unfortunately, I never used version control for manuscript writing, or rather, I never
used Git for manuscript writing.
The main reason for that is that writing collaboratively on Git is painful.
There are tools like Overleaf or Google Docs or HackMD,
what we are just using, where everyone can
write in the same document.
And these things can be used to easily create
an academic paper.
And I personally prefer those tools
because they are especially suited for concurrent editing.
While Git can solve concurrent editing issues,
but depending on how many changes there are
and how much stuff two people did on an article,
you can easily end up with merging conflicts
and it can become very painful.
So personally, I have used Overleaf.
I have used Google Docs.
And HackMD is also for first draft.
And then you need to put it into a form for the journal
in the end anyways.
So would you say that the Git is like a very powerful version
control tool?
But in this case, it's a bit maybe too generic because there are tools that are specifically
designed for co-authoring papers or texts.
Yes. What I would say is that Git is very good suited for code editing, where if you work on
two different things, but you have some modifications, you then need to merge and then need to
find out, okay, what happened and what changes can we let go in and how do we need to merge that,
where you anyways need to think about this. But if you, for example, have two people who edited
a relatively final version of an article
and made spelling or changed spelling mistakes and stuff.
You will get so many lines, because GitHub essentially
goes line by line, where you have changes on both sides
that it gets really messy.
And you need to manually then select the right.
And you essentially do double the work, if not more,
when editing a document.
And that's something that is unnecessary, in my opinion,
because there are tools like Overleaf or Google Docs, which
do exactly that and are exactly for this purpose, where
can work together on a document and don't get into these kind of issues. So I would use those instead.
From the notes, we have interesting distribution between are you using version control for
academic papers. It's about 50-50, like yes or no. It is interesting.
Yeah, I have used, well, I have used version control for academic papers, no question
whatsoever, but I haven't used it for writing the manuscript.
And I think that that's also, I think.
Oh, okay.
It's a distinction there, okay.
Yeah.
depends on how people see this. There is a comment on the how to handle collaborative issues,
one author being responsible for merging everything. If they are lucky,
If they are lucky, everything goes fine.
If they are unlucky and you have concurrent edits or a lot
of concurrent edits, they will spend a lot of time
in merging them.
And it's just, yeah, as I said, to me,
writing the manuscript there is a waste of time.
Having the code under version control
and merging there, yeah, absolutely makes sense.
Okay. Should we move on?
Yes. There are other tools that help in making academic or scholarly output more reproducible.
Jupyter Notebooks can be a good way to present the flow of your code more easily.
Binder gives Jupyter notebooks and makes them available in an executable environment so
that people don't even need to install the Jupyter stuff initially.
And for R, there's also R tools or Research Compendia, which are nice tools to use to
show your results and show how your code is being used.
Okay so a key point here an organized project directory structure
helps with reproducibility and makes it a lot more easy to later on
redo what you have done.
So the next is essentially then the question
Okay, so you have your folder organized. How do we actually go about running our scripts?
So you have some steps that need to be run to do your work and how do you actually run them?
Does that rely on you remembering how you run them or is it reproducible for anyone else?
How do you communicate these steps to others or in particular future you?
And here we will also go into how we can create a reproducible workflow and
what scientific workflow management systems are and when to use them.
So as an example here we have an example project from the HPC Carpentry lessons
which is essentially a small project that
counts the frequencies of words in some books
and then plots them.
So, the example use of this is,
let me just check something.
So the example use is where you simply have Python code,
code.py, and then plot the output file into an image.
And Timo, do you want to explain
what the problems with this kind of approach are?
It is, so it's a very manual approach.
And so if we want to, I would say that if we want to have multiple books,
so let's say we have 100 or 1000 books, then we would have to
We do all of those manually, and then there is no record of what books were processed.
I think that's at least the first thing that comes to mind.
Yeah, and we also, it's not really extendable.
tendable. So if we have this, what do we do if we want to run this for 500 books? We could
even have a small GUI or something, but then we would need to click like 500 times. And
of course, you can essentially write a script that does essentially run everything, which
would be something like this. This is now on Binder on JupyterHub. No, in a JupyterHub
on Binder. And you could essentially run all of these and then you have your results. But
that doesn't really help you when you have to extend that to 500 books. So this is more
an imperative style. We tell it to do every single step in order and we can potentially
also use something like a loop for this where we just indicate the name and then we can still
run it for all of them. This is a bit better because we only have to put in the name
but we are still explicitly telling it what to do.
Yeah, and also the loop looks much better,
but there is one problem is that if we want to rerun something,
or we want to add some books and rerun the experiment,
then all the books will be processed again.
Yeah, and that's really not what we want to do, especially if the stuff that we are running
takes a little bit longer.
So if we are running something that takes half an hour for everything and we suddenly
have to rerun 500 iterations of this, yeah, we really don't want to do that.
So this scripted solution is reproducible.
Yeah, definitely.
But if we start to add more things,
it starts to get problematic, as Timo mentioned.
And that's actually the point where workflow tools come in.
Workflow tools in more complex scenarios,
so where it goes away from the simple,
I have three things that I need to run,
and I don't have more than these three things.
But I always get additional things after some time,
and I'm still producing my data, for example.
And I need to do something for every data point.
That's where workflow tools come in very handy.
And we will give an example here with Snake Make,
which is inspired by GNU Make and is a very popular tool
in bioinformatics, but also in other computational fields.
We also chose SnakeMake because it's very close to Python.
So in the SnakeMake files or snake files,
you can write code in Python essentially.
And we have a demo here.
in Binder that I will show you in a moment.
But I would first like to go through the way that SnakeMake actually writes your
or that SnakeMake files are actually created and how SnakeMake works on a logical basis.
So, SnakeMake works with rules and rules have to be fulfilled for SnakeMake.
So for a rule to be fulfilled, it needs to have all its inputs and then generates all
its outputs by the command that's being called in Shell.
And that's a bit unintuitive, because commonly what happens is you define in your rule all
the inputs which are the endpoints of what you want to create.
And in here we have in our all rule, we have, we want to create all the files in statistics
book data, where the name of the book comes from the data field, which is essentially
all file names in the data folder.
And we also want to create all the plots.
And this defines our final results.
And then Snakemake starts to look, okay, how do I get these?
Is there any other rule that creates these?
And it looks on, so there is a rule countWords, which has as inputs a script code countedPy
and a book data file txt.
And these files come, and this file is just a placeholder again, which in the end comes
from data because it knows that okay this entry comes from here then. And then you have
a Python script that says okay well from the inputs I take the script and I take the book
and I create the output and if we look back up this is exactly what we had here. So this
is the first step. That's what the count rule essentially is doing, or the count words.
And in the make plot, this is essentially the same structure, and again, as above. And
I will show you this on Binder.
So how the SnakeMech works, the rule works, is that each rule will take an input file
and then it looks that if that input file doesn't exist on the disk, it will find a
rule that has that input file as the output file.
And then, and that's why we start from the end.
It's yeah.
And one thing I need to mention here, in this binder, the results are already there.
So we already have these final results, and we also already have the statistics being
processed.
So the first thing I actually need to do is remove them, because otherwise it doesn't
do anything, because it has everything already.
So I delete all these files.
And if I then start to, as you can see on the left, the statistics stuff is now gone.
And if I then run this, what SnakeMIC does is it essentially checks, okay, what do I
have to do?
I have to create or I have to fulfill the all once.
To do that, I have to count words four times and I have to make plots four times.
So in total, I have nine things that I have to do.
The all is once for each book.
Yeah.
The all is just a final check, so that's pretty simple.
But the other code is something that needs to be changed.
And there I have my data again.
Now, the beauty of this is if I, for example,
remove this last data and run it again
it will notice that okay um i'm missing one count words
um and since i'm missing that i also have to redo the plot because
um yeah i don't know if this is if the data that
uh is being created um will really lead to the same for
the same picture or the same output here so i'm re-running this and i have to
execute the all again, because yeah, I'm missing something from there. And one more thing that I
think is very important and why we have these code pieces in our rule as inputs. If I change
the count.py here and run this again, it doesn't know what was changed, but it knows, okay,
the count has changed. Oops, this was too far up. The count has changed, so I need to rerun
everything that depended on this input count.py. That creates me the statistics data information,
which my make plot depends on. So I have to rerun the make plot because I don't know if that has
changed. And it will essentially rerun everything that's necessary to keep in sync with all the
inputs. And that's the real beauty of these things. So you can go through it and you can
make sure that only the stuff is rerun that is necessary but everything that is necessary is
rerun. And that's really something that allows you to keep all your results in sync
and allows you to run additional code or additional inputs without rerunning everything.
It also has the possibility to use containers or environments
And you can visualize the graph that is being created here as well.
Okay. Or not. At least not in this environment.
It was a good example of unreproducible.
Yep. So we would need to install the graph.
Oh, well, we can probably just install it here as well.
But I'm, that could take a bit of time.
Yeah, that can take.
So essentially, what's happening is for all,
I need to create the count words with the input of the file
Sierra.
This is also the input for the make plot.
And all needs to have make plot.
and that's the same for all the other inputs.
So all depends on all of these individual things
and only then all is fulfilled.
The reason why using SnakeMake
or why we're representing SnakeMake and not other tools,
I would say some people claim
it has a relatively gentle learning curve.
I think it depends a lot on your example
or on your use case, whether it's gentle or not
and how many features you actually need.
If you don't need too many features from it,
then yeah, it has a relatively gentle learning curve.
If you need a lot of features, then well,
like with any system, if you want to use all the features
that it offers, it has quite a bit of stuff
that you need to learn.
I think for me mainly, it's free, it's open source
and it installs pretty easily via Conda or via PIP
and you can use it on both Windows or all Windows,
Mac OS or Linux.
And that's also a beauty,
it is highly compatible with high performance computing.
You can essentially tell SnakeMake
that run these things on a cluster,
run these things with the HPC scheduler.
So don't run them on the local machine,
run them elsewhere and run them as individual jobs, which lets you parallelize all of these
parallelizable steps very easily.
Yeah, it's, as I mentioned earlier, it's possible to define software, isolate software environments
in Perlul, so essentially defining that we will now use a certain conda environment or even to
use a certain container to run these things in. We'll come to containers later and what they are,
how they work, and as we mentioned it's heavily used in bioinformatics and it's a nice functionality
to archive your workflow and to properly archive it. You could, for example, put in the parameters
that you were using in a SnakeMag file and then have everything that you were using in that
SnakeMag file. And if you want to use a new parameter set, you could create a new SnakeMag
file and keep the old one or if the SnakeMIC file is under version control you can simply
go back to that version. So that helps a lot in also remembering what was being used in the past.
There are additional similar tools like Make which is very heavily used in C compiling.
There's Nextflow, Task, and other tools that help in doing this.
And about 200 others.
Yes.
There are a lot of workflow managers.
Yeah.
And of course, computational steps can be recorded in many ways.
A script can be perfectly sufficient.
But make sure that when recording your computational steps, you also record input parameters.
You also record what was, what input parameters, what stuff was used to run the analysis.
And in snake make, I would put it in the snake file, in a bash script or any other script,
I would try to put it into the pile there as well,
because otherwise, you will forget it.
I know that I would.
Yeah.
In the notes, there is a question about parallelization.
So how does Snake make the parallelization happen?
Does it require the user to set some parameters?
The minus J, I think, is the number of jobs
that you can run in parallel.
Yes.
So if you would run minus J20, it would try to run 20 things in parallel.
So what SnakeMech does, it detects from your rules that, okay, these rules can be run in
parallel.
don't depend on each other. And then it checks from the minus J parameter or the option,
the number of workers, that how many CPUs do you have available. And if you have more
than one CPU available, then it can start running the rules in parallel. I think that's
the short of it.
Yeah, and on clusters, there is integration with Snake, MIG, and SLURM, but we won't go
go into this in detail at the moment.
If you think that you would benefit from using SnakeMake,
I would highly recommend going through the documentation.
Because what we have given here is a very small example
and a very simple example.
And like always with simple examples,
they look easy to do on the surface.
And once you actually want to use them for you,
you have to go back to the documentation.
This is mainly to show you this is something that's possible
and that's available and how to find it.
We are at the stage when we could have the break.
Yep, and I would say we have a 10-minute break
till 2 past the hour.
Yes.
Okay, keep posting your questions on the
on the collaborative document. We can keep answering them or take your break
and have a have a small walk around so that you
can come back refreshed. Okay then, bye and see you in 10 minutes.
you
Okay and welcome back. So we've talked about organizing your folders, organizing your code
and recording the recording the steps and the next thing that we want to talk about
is recording dependencies and how to communicate different versions of software dependencies.
And well our code often depends on other codes or other libraries and that in turn depends on
other codes, and so on. So for reproducibility reasons, we can version control our code with Git,
but how can we version control dependencies? How can we capture and communicate them?
And connected to that is that we can easily end up in a somewhat of a dependency hell,
where different codes that need to be run for the same analysis actually have conflicting
dependencies. The one depends on a different version of a library than the other and that
starts to get really problematic. And there's this nice xkcd comic that shows very well how
our modern computational infrastructure works and that it's a very complex pattern of libraries and
libraries and libraries depending on other libraries and this on top here that might be
your code and it depends on a lot of different things down below down to operating systems
kernels and then it probably depends on some projects some random person Nebraska has been
thanklessly maintaining since 2003 and if that piece of code breaks the whole thing tumbles down
And there is actually a very recent example that came out, that happened way after this
comic was created, where there wasn't a breakdown as such, but there almost happened to be a very,
very, very severe security issue, because someone socially engineered themselves into a maintainer
position of one of these tiny bits of codes that everything relies on and had managed to get some
backdoors into the code and that was almost shipped to the stable versions of some operating systems.
That was the XZ library which is essentially a compression library that is used in a lot of
systems as an underlying library. So this picture is very accurate and yet unfortunately it's very
accurate. So to make this whole thing a bit more understandable, a bit more tangible, we can also
think of a kitchen analogy to your code and what you're doing. And essentially your software that
you have, that's the recipe. That's the recipe on how to process the data, which are the ingredients,
to get your results, so your dish. And to do that, you normally take some libraries, which are
pots or tools. And now it's very simple to imagine that, okay, you have a recipe for a huge amount
of pasta, because that recipe is supposed to feed 40 people. And your recipe says to
take a 10 or 15 litre pot of water. Well, that wouldn't work, that whole recipe wouldn't
work if the only pot that you have is a 1 litre pot. So if you only have the 1 litre
version of that library so only the one liter pot you can't your recipe just doesn't work
because you can't fill 10 kilos of spaghetti into a one liter pot
so that's how you can think about how software data and libraries work together
and there are plenty of tools that try to help you specify what tools you actually need
and try to help you in specifying the specific library versions that are needed and handle all
the dependencies that are underlying these libraries because you might be working with
for example pandas but pandas needs other libraries to work and this kind of dependency
tree is something that you don't want to care about yourself and so defining if having a tool
that helps you there is very beneficial and common tools that have there are conda pip virtual
environments, poetry for package building, the requirement.txt which lists the
individual requirements, the environment.yaml which is the equivalent to conda and so on.
And they try to help you in defining the specific set of dependencies,
possibly with well-defined versions. They help you in installing those dependencies
because they get the underlying dependencies, they help you with recording the versions for all these dependencies,
and Virtualenv and Anaconda, for example, also help you in isolating environments,
so that you can have multiple different sets of environments on one computer,
so that if you have two pieces of code that have conflicting dependencies,
you can still run both of them, you just need to change the environment for that.
that. They even help you with changing the versions of R or Python per project or even
within the same project if you have code that needs, if you have very old code that still needs
Python 2, you can do that. If you have code that needs an R version below 4, yeah, you can do that.
So, some of these tools or approaches are Python specific, and some are more general.
So Konda, Anaconda, they are quite general.
Yeah, while virtualenv is more a Python or pyenv, while renv is more R and so on.
And one really beautiful thing with, for example, conda, yeah, mainly conda, mainly with actual
or also pyenv, virtualenv, so with these whole things is that if something goes wrong or
Or you want to try something out and it didn't work.
You can delete the environment and recreate it from the environment file.
So you can test, okay, I have found a library that seems to be solving a problem that I have.
Let's add it to the environment, test it, didn't work, okay.
Before I try to remove that library again, because there might have been other things
that came along with it, that I didn't properly record yet,
I just throw away the environment, recreate it,
because it will be the same as I had before.
And we have here five examples
of students that wrote code,
which depends on a couple of libraries.
And the code was uploaded to GitHub.
And let's assume we travel three years into the future
and find the GitHub repositories
and try to rerun the code before adapting it. There are a couple of questions in the
in the collaborative document now which we would like to have your opinions and I would give that
like three minutes or so or five minutes to read through it and answer that and just say okay well
what do you think is this reproducible or isn't that reproducible?
Okay, so see you in five minutes.
You can also, if you have comments about it, write the comments there and what the issues
So I think we will start discussing
once we have a few comments for one of them.
And you can go through it and just listen
to what we say about it in general.
Looks like A is starting to get some.
Yeah, I think A, we already have a clear tendency.
Yeah, consensus.
That this is not reproducible.
And yeah, absolutely.
you just have imports you might not even know which libraries are actually being used because
sometimes there are two libraries that provide the same imports and that essentially means that you
can either load library A or library B and or you can have a dependency on library A or library B
but in the code they have the same import statement because you have conflicting import that's
absolutely possible. So, yeah, this is anything but reproducible. And also not very nice if you
think about the workload you are putting on the next person trying to figure out. Or on yourself
rerunning it. Yeah. B, we also already have a quite clear thing that, yeah, if you have a list
of libraries that are used, that's at least helping. But if you don't have any versions,
you sometimes have breaking changes in between versions and you don't necessarily know which
version was being used. You can try to guess what version was being used, but
if this was being created somewhere in the transition between, let's say,
major version 2 and major version 3 of the same library, it's a whole lot of guesswork which
version was actually used because very often published code is already older. So it was
essentially developed a year ago or so and the version that was used back then was being used
And, yeah, we just don't know.
Yeah.
For example, so this function uses, or this class uses a function that was introduced
in version two, but was deprecated in version four, or say, deprecated in version six.
So it must be somewhere between two, three, four, five, and then the subversions.
And it's, again, it's not very nice thing to do to yourself or to the next person trying
to figure out your code.
And C, again, yeah, as people mentioned here, it's nice that you have an environment file
that already helps quite a bit, but there is, of course, still missing version numbers.
So you don't know which versions were actually being used.
Is this now Python 3 or Python 2?
and what this file is supposed to tell you.
Okay, that's actually a good question here.
So the environment YAML file is a file for Conda.
Conda is a dependence management system
that reads through this and says,
okay, well, I'll create an environment
with the following name,
and then I'm using these channels,
these channels, I'm using these sources.
And in this case, it's conda-forge.
Conda-forge is a pretty popular repository for packages.
And the dependencies are then listed as scipy.
So the scipy package, numpy, sympy, click, python, pip.
And conda also allows you to do installs with pip
because not every package is actually in conda.
And it allows you to create an environment
that has pip installations.
And here, this indicates that, okay, this is git,
this is a pip installation from this git repository
at the master branch.
And actually that's a problem in itself
because master can have changed.
There is no idea, there is no information
on what master is nowadays.
This can be completely different.
So...
And very likely is because the latest master...
Well, yeah, most likely, assuming that this is
from other users that actually still develop their code.
4D, we...
And the versions are...
Okay, so how you fix that could be like in the nodes.
In version D.
where you essentially have a specific git commit or a specific tag that this project
is being used at.
There is the comment that there might be different builds.
That's true.
There is one problem with builds.
Builds can be operating system specific.
Oh, absolute reproducibility, yes, you need the build.
But commonly, the version is sufficient.
The version is sufficient to hopefully get the same results.
If you really need to go down to the build number,
it's very likely that something fishy is happening.
And I wouldn't rely on my results too much, actually.
But yes, for complete reproducibility, the build should be in there.
For usability, I wouldn't put it in a place like that.
And I'll come to that a bit later, actually, in the next demo, where we show the differences here.
here.
Yeah.
Anything else?
This has the advantage, the E has the advantage over D that these projects that were referenced
here have now been put onto conda but actually if that is you can be happy if that isn't well
that's also something that's very common that you need some pip packages or that you need something
from a different git repository and of course there is the problem that these git repositories
could have been deleted. But if you want to make sure that you keep those git repositories
and you need a specific version from a specific git repository, fork it and use your own fork.
Because you are in control of your own fork and as long as you don't delete that fork, that stays.
So this way is perfectly fine if you make sure that the repositories don't disappear.
Okay.
And that's essentially also what's listed in the solution.
Yes.
Are there...
Yeah.
So, what about pip packages and conda packages?
Do they not disappear ever?
They can, hopefully not, but even conda packages can disappear, especially in very fast moving
fields, or if you use, let's say, more unstable channels, more developmental channels. I've
seen some PyTorch versions no longer being supplied by some of the providers because they
are too old and considered as not useful anymore. But that's, of course, a real problem for reproducibility.
Yeah. So, in general, if you use well-known and widely used channels and packages from
Conda or BIP, it is very unlikely that they will disappear.
But yeah, they can. And how to solve that problem, we can come to, well, how to switch that problem
to a different level, we'll come to in a bit.
Yeah.
So now, I will demo creating our own small time capsule for a
environment and for the future world.
Yeah, this is essentially, I have created this
environment of YAML and as explained above, I can quickly
show that this is essentially what's written in here.
So conceptually, again, it wants to create an environment
called myenv with the channels on the forge
and in this case, defaults,
which is the Anaconda environment.
One mention here, this can become a bit problematic
because Anaconda recently changed their policies
that even academic institutions now have to pay
if they have over a certain amount of users.
And it might be good not to use defaults here.
CondaForge normally has all the packages that you need
and even has more packages than default
than the Anaconda environment,
but the under-conda moment is a bit better curated.
Okay, and then it is the dependency.
So this would be something that depends on Python 3.10,
also wants to have mountain NumPy, pandas, and seaborn.
And yes, it doesn't give any,
it doesn't give any version numbers here at the moment.
So I will be using mamba instead of conda.
the reason is that otherwise conda can take quite a bit of time to actually create environments and
I want to spare us all the time. Mamba is a drop-in replacement that's just faster because
it uses C while conda is programmed entirely in Python. Okay, so this will essentially
create this environment, check the sources that I indicated and start to then download the files.
So it checks for these
And I should have them already downloaded, so there's no, oh, it actually found something
that probably has a newer version and it wants to take the newer version.
So that's something which is actually quite nice to see.
So if I had created that a little bit earlier, it would be slightly different now because
this is a different version.
So and if I then say conda activate myenv, I have my environment where in Python I can
import Seaborn and have my Seaborn library and so on.
So I can now also export this environment.
And that's essentially what was mentioned earlier in the notes,
that this lists everything, including the build number,
the build ID.
And if you look into this a bit, you
notice things like this one where libplus is linux64 so yeah i'm on a linux system and this is
a build that's specific for linux so if i would provide this this dependency file anyone who is
on a windows system will have problems installing this environment because this is not available
for Windows. That's why this kind of system where you have all the individual build numbers
might not be the best thing. It's good to have and I would put it in as for reproducibility
so that people can actually see what exact builds were being used. But for usability of your code,
So if someone wants to use that library in a different project, this is questionable.
There's the other option which is very convenient. You can say from history and if I
check into that, this is exactly what I installed. This lists exactly, even if I
later on would install something with mamba install whatever it would list exactly the
right packages here there is a third option
which is called no builds and that
is the same as the environments file but without the builds.
That can also be useful if you want to make a clearer specifications which underlying packages
were being used without providing builds, but it still has the problem that there are things like
the LD implementation in Linux. So yeah, that might still not work on a Windows system.
system.
So what is the recommendation here?
What I personally would recommend for a project
to provide is the export from history, so this.
And for reproducibility reasons, I
would put in the complete export.
Because then if someone has the same operating system
and so on, this should be really exactly the same environment
that they get when creating that.
While the FromHistory will create an environment
that is as close to what I would recreate
if I would start this now.
And it's the one that solves on all operating systems, so it's more general.
But at the same time, we have to admit that this is not a good initial environment file.
Your initial environment file should have the NumPy version, should have the Pandas
version, should have the Seaborn version that you want to use.
So to summarize, in your initial environment file do have the version numbers, but then
For completeness, it is OK to also include in your repo
the complete export with the builds.
I would even recommend it as an additional piece
of information.
Yeah.
Because it doesn't hurt.
OK, good.
OK.
We unfortunately don't have really time
to go into details with R. But essentially, you
can use Conda with R as well.
Conda does have R, does support R.
And I have created several environments with Conda
OS for R with using Conda.
So, but since we saw that an underlying library, a system library can cause problems.
And up until now, we mainly considered non-system libraries, even though Conda already does
some system library stuff.
Let's go to recording the environments.
And I think everyone has heard the, well, it works on my machine, comment from someone
at some point.
And this meme sums up the idea behind Docker or other containerization systems quite well.
That it works on my machine, well, then we'll ship your machine.
And yeah, that is how Docker was born, essentially.
So we want to ship something or give something that provides as much as possible of the operating
system to the user in the end.
And to go back to our kitchen analogy, so as we said, our code scripts are the cooking
recipes and then with containers you have container definition files and they are like
blueprint to build a kitchen with all the utensils and stuff that the recipe needs to be prepared.
The next thing is we have the container images and those are kind of showroom kitchens based
on these container based on the blueprints that we have created before and a showroom
kitchen is not connected so there there are electricity is not plugged in water is not
not plugged in, you can't really use it.
And a container is then essentially
this showroom kitchen connected to everything.
And in addition, there's a protective layer
being put on everything so that you can work with it.
And in the end, you remove this protective layer
so that you still have the original container
kind of. As we said, containers can be built to bundle all the necessary ingredients, data,
code, environment, operating system, even though including data might be problematic,
depending on your system. A container image is somewhat like, yeah, also like a piece
of paper with all the operating system on it and when you run it, you put a transparent
sheet on it to form essentially the container.
Then that container runs and you write on that transparent sheet and do all the changes
on this transparent sheet.
And when you're done, you tear off that transparent sheet and you still have your original container
and everything that was done on this transparent sheet is gone.
And the definition files are essentially text files that contain a series of instructions
on how to build these container images.
So to recap here, we have three concepts.
And first, kind of like a starting point would be the definition file.
let's say a dockerfile or a similarity definition file and we use that definition file to create
an image, a container image, or image for short, and that image and that definition
file, of course, they are persistent, but then when we create a container out of that
image, then that container is not persistent. So the container is what is actually being run,
and when that container is stopped, it stops running, then it vanishes. But the image
is still there on the disk. Then everything that was changed in the container vanishes, yes.
Okay, yeah and why would you want to use these? There are two main reasons.
One is installing a certain software is tricky or not supported on the system that you're using.
That's very common on HPC systems. HPC systems in general have a very very
minimalistic operating system with as little software installed as possible as to leave
as much computational and memory available for a user to exploit and use. But that means that
a lot of small libraries that code depends on are not there. So what you can do with a container,
you can essentially put all the stuff in that container and run your code via that container.
The other option is that you want to make sure that whoever is using the code uses it
in the same kind of environment or same environment as you.
And then you can provide them an image of your container because then you essentially
have provided the whole environment. There might be a problem if people are using different
architectures than you and there might be a problem if people are using a different
operating system than use.
There are, for, you can run Linux containers on Windows.
That works reasonably well, because Windows
has a Windows subsystem for Linux.
But you can't really run Windows containers on Linux,
unfortunately.
So one way it works, the other, unfortunately, doesn't.
Yeah, so the shipping the machine is a bit of an exaggeration.
So let's have a look at one of these container recipes.
This is a Singularity definition file and there's a link to the reference if you want to look into
more detail. Singularity commonly starts with an information on where this is coming from.
Singularity can use docker images to base your new images on. If it says a bootstrap,
essentially indicates, okay, this is where it's coming from. This comes from the docker repository
And from is the statement on what is the original image that we are using as a base for what
we are doing here.
And that's commonly some operating system or some programming language that you are
using where essentially all the packages that you need for that base operating system or
base programming language are already installed.
And then you can start to do more things with it.
And post is then essentially what happens after that basic installation.
So what changes do we need to do to our system to make it do what we want the container to
do?
And, at least on any Linux or on any Ubuntu, this commonly starts with apt-get y-update,
So just get the latest updates, which can in itself be a bit of a problem if you want
to redo that.
And then install the packages that we need.
You can set some environment variables.
You can potentially also copy over files and so on.
And then you have a run script, which is the final command that is being run when this
container is being run.
So this container would run date, pipe to kawase, pipe to loghead.
That's what this container would be doing.
It's not very useful, but it's just an example.
Yes.
And yeah.
And so does every image that we build, do they all run a script or?
No.
You don't necessarily need to run a script.
You can also have a container that essentially doesn't do anything and just provides an environment.
Or the way you need to tell it, okay, what do you want to execute in the container?
Okay.
So then it's kind of like a generic platform to run whatever script you want in that specific
environment.
Yes.
Okay.
different container platforms. There's Docker and Podman, which is more of a, which I would
say more of a single user, particularly Docker is more of a single, or a container for a
single user system, because Docker has the disadvantage that it essentially needs to
to have administrative or pseudo rights and it will run essentially as a super user so
it can do everything on your system. Singularity and Obtainer are pretty popular on high-performance
computing systems because they essentially get rid of this requirement of running it
as a super user, and you can still run these containers.
Potman is very close to Docker.
And yes, what's the default container engine
on Red Hat systems, for example?
So if you have a single machine, or like a single user,
Or if you have a single machine, yeah.
If you have a single machine, you can know super user rights.
You can use singularity obtain apartment.
If you have super user rights, you can use Docker.
If you don't have super user rights, you can't use Docker.
It's pretty simple.
Someone can add you to the Docker users,
but that would essentially give you super user rights.
So they can as well just give you administrative rights then.
So pros and cons of containers.
Well, they allow you to move workflows
across different platforms with the constraints
that we mentioned earlier.
They can definitely solve the works on my machine situation
because you essentially ship the operating system
or the underlying libraries.
For software with many dependencies,
they can offer the only way to preserve
the computational environment future of usability.
What we had previously,
where this Konda environment had things,
now we can create this image
and we can actually ship this image
because that image, regardless on whether
the repositories are no longer in the,
or the repositories no longer have these versions,
they are in the image.
If the image is created, they are in the image.
So for reproducibility, you need the image.
You don't necessarily need the definition file,
but that is very, very useful to reproduce the image.
But if you want to have it reproducible,
you need to provide that image.
It's also a mechanism to send the computer to the data
your data set is either too large to transfer or if when your data set is in a secure environment
and you just can't, you don't have an internet access so you can't just install conda packages
or whatever but you can give the image file to the system administrator and they will put that
image file onto that computer and then you can run the tools that your image provides.
It's a further set of separation where you can install software into a file, so that
image file, instead of onto your computer, separating again or essentially meaning that
you don't have to change your computer setup to install something.
There are, of course, also some drawbacks because containers can be used to hide away
software installation problems and which should normally have been solved by better development
practices. So yeah, it's too difficult to install. Yeah, we don't make the installation easier,
which would be the right thing to do. We'll just provide a docker image so that people can use it.
Yeah. You can run into the instead of works on my machine works only in this container,
container, which again leads to the same question, why does it only work in this container?
What's in this container that makes it possible?
And if that is a specific version of a normally available software, then yeah, there might
be problems with what you have actually.
They can and are difficult and are somewhat difficult to modify.
depending on what you package in there, they can become very large.
So every bit of data that you would put into a container, that's why I said
shipping the data or putting data into a container is a questionable thing,
that will make that container larger.
For example, if you have large language models, you don't really want to put
those large language models into a container because you will just increase
container size a lot and if you use that model in multiple different containers, imagine a 40
40 gigabyte model and now all your containers are 40 gigabyte in size. Instead what you can do is
you can have that image elsewhere or have the model elsewhere and load it into the container
when it's run. That makes it a bit less reproducible because you're not chipping the
data, but overall it's, I would say, the better choice.
Yeah, so then we are assuming that hopefully the language model will be distributed
in some other centralized place, for example, Hackingface or something.
Yes, so there are different places where containers can be found.
Docker Hub is very popular, Kuai is also quite popular, GitHub and GitLab container registries
can also be used, or even Zenodo.
So there was this warning about only use official and trusted images.
So what is your definition for an official and trusted image?
For me, it's the same as any other software
that I use from the internet.
If I want to use a container,
it should be coming from the essentially creators
of the software that I want to use.
Not from some third party,
whatever that provides me WinZip or whatever.
Or if I want to have PuTTY,
I'm going to the PuTTY webpage
and download it from the PuTTY webpage
and not from some third party
where I don't know if this is actually put here
or just a Trojan that's trying to,
that I've been storing on my system.
Yeah, so if I want to use an image of Ubuntu,
then I will use an image provided by the,
what is it, the Linux Foundation
or whoever is responsible for Ubuntu development.
And similar to what we had earlier
the environments or the dependencies. We also here now have a
dockerfile and I want to quickly go through the dockerfile to see what is actually
how the dockerfile can be reproduced or if there are problems with this dockerfile
or reproducibility. One mention right at the beginning if you really want
to want it to be reproducible provide the image not just the dockerfile.
because only the image is what you actually used and the Dockerfile is only the way how this image
should be generated, but we'll mention why this is a bit problematic. So we have the
or the singularity file here. So again, we have a singularity that depends on Docker and it starts
from Ubuntu latest. Is that a good idea, Timo? Yeah, that's immediately a problem that the
Ubuntu latest is dependent on when you are building the image.
Yeah, three years ago, this was Ubuntu 21 or something.
Nowadays, it's 24 or something.
So yeah, it's building on a completely, not completely,
but a different operating system.
So this would definitely not be the same
if I run this now than three years ago.
Then we start with our post, so with our installations.
we export an environment for the, or an environment variable for the installation time,
we upgrade update as we mentioned before, we upgrade install with a couple of libraries
and this already, this is where this problem also comes back in. These libraries can have
changed. Even if we have a fixed version, these can change depending on whether the default
libraries have changed over time. Then this is some cleanup, which is fine. We create a virtual
environment. We upgrade pip and, well, install some requirements.txt. That, of course, depends
now a lot on the requirements.txt, how well defined the versions are in there,
but if they are not well defined, we again can run into easy problems.
This singularity file also has an additional section with files,
which indicates what files are copied over into the image.
So it copies over the requirements.txt and I would assume that this requirements.txt
is in the same repository as this file,
the same with the app.py.
So those files we probably have.
And then it copies something from home, myself data
into app data.
Yeah, home, myself is not something that we have.
So this is stuff that is probably not even in the repository
so we don't know what that is.
In that case, it's probably the data
that is to be used by the app.
And we said that we want to reuse it with our data.
So we can probably replace it with our data here.
But yeah, that's not very helpful.
And this is then a real problem, because this
has some fancy lip where we have no idea what that is.
And yeah, puts it into the libraries of this container.
So this makes the whole image not reproducible or even
not reusable, not reproducible.
So to recap the file section here,
so I think I read the instructions again.
And yeah, it doesn't say that this singularity file
is definition file is in a repo, but yeah, we are assuming that it's in a Git repo.
And there is in the Git repo with this definition file, there is the application code,
which is the app.py. And that we have a requirements text file there in that Git repo.
But like we talked earlier, then data is not usually integrable, especially if it's big data.
And so the first requirements line and the app line are fine.
the copy data line is quite iffy, and the last line highlighted now with the fancy lip is like
a definite no-no. These are the problems that you have with Docker definition files, which means
that essentially if you want to have your Docker file reproduce or your code reproducible by
providing in Docker, provide the image. Yes, it will be potentially big, but it's the only way
how you can actually have the environment that you used saved. And not to confuse people
any more than necessary, this is a singularity definition, right? Yes, sorry. Not Docker
Definition point. So, key points here is containers can be helpful if complex setups are needed
to running a specific software and they can also be helpful for prototyping without messing up
your own computing environment or to run software that requires a different operating system than
your own. Depends a bit. Okay, so we are coming towards the end and the question is where to
go from here and what to take away from this. So I think for me we have shown you workflow tools
and how and where to use it and we have hopefully given you an idea where they will make sense in
the future. In many cases these workflow tools are probably not needed and a proper script with
all the information is sufficient but you probably want to consider using them when you are processing
many files with many steps, if your steps or files may change, if you're still collecting
your input data, or if your main script connecting your steps starts to get very long, because then
it starts to get unreadable essentially and you start to want to make different parts of it.
it. Containers seem amazing, but do I have actual use for them? Well, maybe not, but
knowing that you can use them is already pretty useful, that you can run Linux tools on your
Windows computer, you can run different versions of the same software on your computer, that
you can follow the easy installation instructions for an operating system that is not your own,
you get a fully configured environment instead of installing just a tool and that you can share
your setup and configurations with others. So yeah, they can be very beneficial, but
as with workflow tools as well, you will need some additional read up on how to use them.
This was mainly to present that they are an option. And what we think is important for every
project that you create. Have a clear structure for your project. Have a clear file structure,
clear directory so that you find things again. Record your workflow and write it down in a script
file or if it's complex enough with a workflow manager. Create a dependency list and keep it
updated. Optimally in an environment file because that makes reinstallations a lot easier and makes
it a lot easier for others to follow what you have done. So software packages and their versions.
Yes. And consider the possibility that someone, maybe you, may want to reproduce your work.
Can you do something small to make it easier? Write down some more instructions or similar
things. If you have ideas what you can do in the future but no time, you can add an issue to the
repository that you're creating your code on and maybe someone else can help or you in a few years
time notice oh well i had this idea back then maybe i maybe now i have a bit of time i can
write i can actually implement that yeah so as i have mentioned a few times not everything in
this lesson it might be useful right now but it's good to know that these things exist if you ever
get into the situation where you would require such a solution and you can come either back to
these documentation documents or you can go to the of course to the respective documentation of
the individual software to see okay how do I actually use them. And caring about reproducibility
makes work easier for the next person that's working on the project and as likely as not
but that will be you.
So that's, I think, it for us.
[name], do you want to add anything?
No, good recap there.
OK, then.
I would thank you, and.
Excellent.
So.
I think we almost still have time.
Exactly.
Thank you, [name], and thank you, [name].
And I don't think there's anything to lift.
We still have four minutes. Should we consider some of the questions in the notes, but otherwise?
I'm looking at the notes and there is a comment about the future viewpoint is really important.
And I agree that I don't think it can be emphasized too much, that it is most probably the person
looking at your code later is you, yourself or your experiment setup and all these things
that we have discussed they may seem at first that okay this is again new learning curves
they will take time to get into but they will save you time and energy in the end
and also they help the scientific community at large
because you are making things more reproducible.
Yes, so we still have a couple of minutes,
but of course we can also end it here
if there's nothing to add.
I just reminded that now we will have one hour lunch break.
And after that, we will talk about social coding.
will be me and [name] talking about basically the social aspects of coding with other people,
sharing repositories, and that comes of course with some kind of legal requirements. And
so we will talk about licenses for code and software. All this in about one hour. So I
thank you, [name] and [name], for the great discussions. And I thank everyone for the
comments on the notes. You can keep on writing comments and answers. And so we see each other
in one hour. Thank you. Bye. Bye. Bye.
you
Hello. So we are back online. Quickly check with the people in the chat if they can hear
us and see us. Excellent. So everything is working. So we still have it's still our day
day four. And we are still going to cover topics somewhat related to the reproducibility
that was covered in the morning by [name] and [name]. And now here with me there is [name]
who works with me at Aalto University. Hello, [name].
Hello everyone. I'm [name], one of the RSEs at Aalto University. Happy to be here.
Yesterday was a special RSE, Research Software Engineers Day, because basically, except me,
all the others were Alto RSEs. RSE is actually a great profession if you want to stay in research
but not exactly becoming, you know, a professor or whatever you will become. But anyway, to
To the topic of this afternoon, it will be about social coding, this lesson used to be
called licensing, software licensing specifically, as you might know when you release something
you want to attach a license and that of course doesn't even, it's not just limited to software
because honestly anything you basically create, whether you want it or not, it comes with
license and the lack of license basically means copyright but sometimes you might not even know
that let's say what you write in social media has a certain license so that the owner of the
social media platform can do almost whatever they want with your content but today we will focus on
these coding aspects. So [name], what do you feel about social coding and open software?
I think it's a very important aspect because a collaboration happens all the time and you should
be able to understand the basics of it and how to share your code and what kind of licenses to add it
and to take care of all of these things. I remember reading this blog post from
a random blog, I don't remember the name, but it was about Google Docs and about the licensing
I think that you probably agree and you are giving almost the ownership of the work that
you are doing on Google Docs to Google because you don't read the licenses and you don't
take it seriously.
So I think it's very important to know about the licenses and how to, yeah, how to manage
them.
Yeah.
I agree.
And here for some motivational example that you find some great code, but then you are
unsure, can you actually, you know, use it? Can you actually cite them? Or you need to
modify the code a little bit, as we will call it later, like remixing, maybe, even with
some data. But then what happens, especially in academic journals, that they require you
these days to also publish the code. And the reason is not just the reproducibility reason
that we heard from the first part of today's, but it's also related to basically the research
integrity, the transparency principle of research, that you should be transparent in all the
steps of the scientific, of the research process. And being transparent with the code is getting
more and more popular. So you will see these type of code availability statements that
you need to attach to your paper that you submit or data availability statements for
the data part. And when it's time to write this statement, you need to basically have
a license to your code, attached to your code and attached to your data.
Yes.
So let's, hopefully this was motivational enough, all I'm saying is keep in a look at
the notes document, so please, if there's any questions and if you feel writing any
comment related to the topic, just write to the notes and then also please let me know
if there's anything interesting to highlight.
So as I mentioned earlier, at the beginning,
this lecture used to be called software licensing,
but then it expanded into social coding.
And the reason is that coding is not just something
that happens in isolation,
that especially in the topic that we are discussing here,
especially in the topic of research,
at some point you are asked to share the code with others.
And as we've seen during the first lecture
and also during the first week,
sometimes you wanna share the code with yourself.
So the social part is not just, you know,
me collaborating with those saying on a project
and I don't know, sharing the GitHub and so on,
but then it really goes, you know,
me collaborating with the future self
and more in general me trying to share what I wrote
as a code to create an impact on other papers.
So [name], what about you?
I guess maybe that in your work
as a research software engineer, you've been helping people
kind of reaching this objective
to basically be social with their code
and sharing it and make it citable.
Yes.
Was it a easy job or was it?
To my experience, people start it a bit late, they usually come when they have to publish
the code because of the publication or a specific requirement for a journal.
So they didn't start with social coding and like trying to have it online for more collaboration.
So yeah, I think maybe if you started from scratch, it would be easier in the end.
Yeah, this is a very good point. In a way, you could even pretend from the day zero when you
start the project, when you start your Git repository, even though it's a private repository,
even though you're not already sharing it with anybody else, you could still pretend that,
you know, you are actually, that it's already live, that it's already public,
that already will improve the way you relate to the repository, because maybe you will write
meaningful messages if you know that you're being watched, if you know what I mean, even though maybe
it's still a private repository, but that will also make your life easier when it's time to
open it and share it with your paper, that you don't need to, I don't know, go through the git
history trying to delete commit messages that you were not happy about because you were very angry
with your code on the day and so on. So in this social one think about if and how you share.
There's a question that can have multiple answers and I believe you have pasted it to them
Yes.
Or can you paste it to them?
Yes, I already did.
Someone had a problem with Twitch, but now it has been resolved.
So maybe we can go to the questions.
So basically, as we did in other polls, if you are able to write a, like an O, so that
we can get this type of ASCII, ASCII, ASCII histogram.
So
So for the first question, you can answer as many as you want, but for the next ones,
you can only choose one. So Sam, I'm gonna ask you the question. Why would you want to share
your scripts, code, and data? Which one would you pick of this?
So for me, it's very good for your reputation and for your CV. If you want to change your job or
or maybe in the future, which is a good thing because you can showcase what I was doing
in my previous job.
Another thing is, at least for me, when I start to publish my code, I'm a bit more careful
on the structure and try to be more clean, which is also a good thing.
Another thing that at least I use is, because the code is more clean, it's easily more reproducible
for me at least.
So I think these three are the main aspects of why I use social coding.
What about you?
Do you have any preference?
Yeah, I agree with you, especially that you mentioned this kind of CV idea, and this also
goes with the, in my opinion, what I like about the Code Refinery workshop, that the type of
skills that you learn here are skills that are reusable in other fields outside academia.
So if the majority of the people following this workshop right now are doctoral researchers or
postdocs or whatever, but already learning it and starting with whatever, little by little sharing,
it will also open doors for maybe other jobs in the future that might not be related to academia.
Me, of the options here, I really like the reproducibility part. I'm biased. I'm a
reproducibility fanatic so that other people can truly rerun my code. But sometimes I publish
code that was really ugly, but I still thought I'm going to put it out there because no one had
that type of function in whatever language I was publishing it. And then I saw that my ugly code
was actually reused by so many publications completely in different fields. Sorry to
interrupt. Someone is mentioning that. Oh no, sorry. Go ahead. There was a comment that they
cannot hear us, but it was from the computer. Sorry, go ahead. Yeah, that's good. Yeah. If
I was muted it wouldn't be nice. But basically let's have a look at what our people online are
answering. Looks like that to my eyes at least A and B seems to be very popular. So the reproducibility
and also the trustworthiness. Exactly. It's interesting that the H doesn't get any votes,
not for this year, also for previous years it didn't get any votes either. But yeah it's
interesting it's it's nice also this that maybe the kind of social thinking of the people here
is not that we are in a competition even though the grant system makes us believe that we are all
competing with each other another thing that i wanted to add is maybe another aspect that i
think about is being part of the community so there are like a lot of codes that you can use
and they're open source so you can try them and if you try to also publish your code you become
part of this community which is very very interesting to be part of and like you can create
like collaborate with others and after some time you will be known for some of your work
although they not might be exactly your expertise for example like I have this it's not exactly a
source code on GitHub, but it's about like how to do something like more of administrative work.
And at the moment, I'm known for that work among like non-expert people for like research software,
which is an interesting thing. Yeah. Yeah, that's great. And in my opinion, it's also,
I mean, it's exactly this that it's, even though we will talk about this later,
that sometimes maybe code, you might feel that you're not recognized in citation or whatever
impact is the measure in academia. But at the end of the day, people will notice it and people will
see it. Maybe you start getting new collaborators or reaching people that you would have not just
reach with your papers.
Yes, maybe we can go to the next question.
Yeah, so it also had some downfalls a bit, right?
So when you publish your code, do you have any concerns?
Well, I would say initially I felt this kind of B, that my code is ugly.
I was never really afraid of the A, because actually by publishing it with the timestamp,
I could eventually prove that, you know, you scooped my code, I have a timestamp that shows.
But then at the end of the day, would I really see you, someone else like me, or for what?
Just, I mean, at the end of the day, I'm happy if people scooped whatever I did,
means that it was something good. But what about you out of these answers, which one?
I think for me, B, like having an ugly code was the most concern.
I never thought about like A or F, about like a lower quality copy or even F, like the code
could be stolen because you can add licenses. And it's also true about your original paper,
right? When you're publishing your idea, it can be also stolen, but it's completely okay.
You have patents and everything to have this protection. And here I think it's
the equivalent is licenses, which we will talk about.
Yeah, it looks like B is also the most popular.
Exactly. Another thing that I have some concerns about, which is not here, is like,
because no software is complete, right? And as a perfectionist, I'm always thinking about is
it complete? Is it good enough to be published? Not from being ugly or not following the clean
code structures, but just as a whole, with all of the functions and is it complete to be published
or not? Yeah. I personally like the release early, release often. And so I rather just publish
something that is even half broken but already there's an idea out there and then I will improve
it and then maybe someone will try to reuse it and I realize that I completely missed
I don't know one exception in the conditions and so on. Yeah so like based on age I can see like
other people have this perfectionist idea as well and it's good that I like I had some votes on
about the licensing which we are going to talk about in this course in this section.
Then we have question three and question four which are kind of free form so please
expand on that and now we will have a look why software often treated differently than from
papers because some people for example also have a ugly english ugly way of writing why wouldn't
you be ashamed of your ugly paper rather than your ugly software and then the fourth question
is when you find a repository with a code or with a library that you would like to reuse,
what are the things that you look at to decide whether you will use it?
So let's have a look at question three. Yeah, I like the first answer because it's this
overly fixation with citations and metrics. It's also true about one of the comments is
it's usually seen just as a tool, not a scientific product. And it's kind of true,
right? Because in my opinion, papers are more about the results and the methodology that you
used and the code is just a tool that you did it although like there are some aspects about like
optimization of the code and how fast it is how much memory does it use but in the end
it's just a tool to achieve your goal right yeah it's true
it's nice too that now this or at least i think that it's nice i'm sorry for some people maybe
this would be more work, and maybe they don't have the resources to ask for help. But this
making, or I wouldn't say forcing, but at least trying to have the code attached with the paper,
with this software availability statement, is a little bit step towards this reproducibility and
transparency, so that it's clear that maybe the method section is more meaningful if I can just
read the code rather than try to infer from a very short paragraph in the method section
which filter was actually applied or which machine learning algorithm was used.
In question three, do you agree with the last comment, not peer-reviewed?
Well, kind of yes, unfortunately, because I often review papers and if there is a code,
I spend a bit of time in giving some feedback that, for example, usually the typical feedback
is that the license is missing. And so in my feedback, I say, please add the license to your
code. But then on the other end, I don't have the time to actually rerun unless they make it very
easy for you that it's just one Docker pool, whatever command that you can easily rerun the
whole pipeline and test it. But even though I would be kind of an expert to peer review the
code, there's just not enough time if I have to run fan review in the paper. But of course,
there are journals that are actually focused on this, like the Journal of Open Source Software,
JOS, where the peer review is actually on the code. The actual papers that come with JOS are
one or two pages. We are a bit behind time, so maybe we can continue. But
But a short comment that I wanted to add is,
it's a bit complicated than papers
because if your repository become popular enough,
other people would come and do contribute to it, right?
So it's not exactly peer reviewed, but somehow it is, right?
Because other people are trying to make it better.
But yeah, maybe we can-
Yeah, then the question four is about
when you find some code, you know,
I've seen that many are writing about the license,
which it seems that it's already clear
that the license might set the rules
of what you can do and what you cannot do.
And also this type of, not just the reusability,
but what we will talk soon is these changes
that you can do to the code.
So the so-called derivative work.
Do you have any comment on this, Orsan?
Personally, I see like the activity and the number of,
like when it has been updated recently
or is it deprecated already?
And also another thing which I usually look at
is the number of contributors that the repository had.
Yeah.
All right, so basically the rest of this
social coding part is what we just discussed
that compared to sharing papers,
sharing code is somewhat different
if the paper is just, you know,
sharing your ideas and maybe winning citations.
Code is a little bit more complex feature.
Sometimes people will just reuse your code ID.
Sometimes it will form some sort of base in basement
foundation for something else to build on top.
And so, you know, with this, of course,
this makes it a little bit more complicated
that papers to evaluate what could be the impact,
what could be the metrics.
Eventually there are some metrics that we will also mention later when you can actually
track the downloads of a package of a software for example.
And then another aspect that is covering this page is what we touched already that the journal
policies are basically going towards the, I wouldn't say forcing, but at least making
it clear that there should be a code availability statement attached with the paper.
as we have a data availability statement. Maybe sometimes you can't share the code because
you're, I don't know, working with a company or it's a dual use case or whatever is the
reason that you're not allowed to share the code. But it's clear that the journals and
not just the journals, even the organizations that are the funding organization, whether
it's the European Research Council or whatever country organization, they are clearly making
it's stronger that the scientific code should be published and public.
Maybe out of one last part that we can look from this page is also this aspect that we
touched on in the question above, that sharing software can also be scary. We touched a little
bit on this. We didn't really cover the aspect of bugs and mistakes. Of course, we might
be scared that what I did was wrong. But on the other hand, is it so bad? Maybe I should actually,
from the perspective of science, from the perspective of ethics, I would actually be
very happy that someone finds a bug in my code. Of course, it's sad for me that I need to ask for a
retraction of the paper if it really changes all the results. But in theory, if science should be
be, you know, what's the word, self-fixing.
Maybe this publishing the code will also improve this type of process.
True.
I would say like sometimes fixing a bug requires a lot of work and it's good that we can collaborate
and help each other on that aspect.
At the same time, it can be a bit overwhelming for the publisher of the code, that you kind
of feel that you're responsible for fixing those if they're just raising the bug, not
a solution.
Yeah, that's a very good point.
We don't have time to discuss this, but in the page, for those who want to spend some
time reading the whole page, there's also this question that, you know, how do you feel,
do you feel the pressure that in the moment that you put your code online now suddenly people will
start asking can you have this improvement can you make it work on this whatever older version
of this operating system maybe i actually think the other way around that at the moment that i
put it online i'm actually removing the responsibility that that i'm saying look i
managed to do this i don't have time to work on this anymore for whatever reason please continue
you make it better, or ask for help.
Basically, we're slowly moving towards the licenses, and we still have now 30 minutes
to talk about that, which is basically how our work connects to the works of others.
So I'm turning page now, and now it's the page dedicated to software licenses.
And I guess more or less everyone is familiar with the idea of copyright.
There are different types of copyright.
There are trademarks that protect the name of a brand, for example, from impersonation.
There are patents that patents usually are not related to software as an algorithm, but
you can patent a system, for example, or in general, so-called technical invention.
And then there's the copyright that is basically protecting the creative expression.
And this can include a little bit of everything, whether it's music or photographs or writings
and so on.
It's also nice what it says here that this copyright is practically forever because it
persists for 70 years after the lifetime of the author.
then maybe on the what you will hear as a term if copyright feels like you know protecting
your intellectual right i also see a point of having a copy left basically making sure that
other people can actually reuse your work and build on top of your work again in a in a in a
legal way. So this brings us to the topic of derivative work, which is a term to say that
from something, let's say Osain made something and put it in the open and I want to reuse bits
of it. I want to maybe reuse some bits as they are, some Python functions, because I don't really
have any improvements to go there or maybe I want to, you know, remix, resample, invent my own flavor
on some whatever visualization part of the script that Ossane did. And of course I can do this or
like the question that maybe would be for myself, am I actually able to do this? Would Ossane work
allow me to do this type of derivative work or is it that, you know, I can't actually even touch
or run on my computer or saying works. So this derivative work is actually when it comes to
software is not intuitive at all of what constitutes derivative work and me myself when
i was attending my first code refinery many years ago i was actually kind of surprised
that some of the options here are considered derivative work. So in this question for you
please don't spy to the to the solution box can can you try to answer in the notes document
which of these are derivative works so derivative you understand that you are basically
remixing reusing the existing code that you have found you have found online
Okay, so maybe we let some time to answer because we don't want to spoil the fun.
Yes, and we have some questions on the note I'm trying to answer.
Is there anything to highlight?
I think two of them are coming from previous sections and copy pasted here.
It's about Docker and Kubernetes and the Conda environment, which I think we can pass.
But a question is, when you license your code, does it belong to your employer or to you?
How does it work?
Yeah.
So, as usual, what I learned from the lawyers that the best answer is it depends.
It depends on what type of agreement do you have with your employer.
Actually it's flexible in a sense that sometimes I've seen, and I'm not specifically talking
about my university, my employer, but I've seen people writing, you know, copyright.
In my case would be [name]-Alto University.
At the end of the day, because software per se cannot be turned into patent unless you
build a system around it. The employer, at least this public organization like universities,
they don't really care much. But it's a different story if you would be working for a company
where you can clearly understand that you as a coder for a company, you don't own anything
and the employer clearly writes in the contract that whatever you produce.
But the same is also, and it's not intuitive, it's also for data. And this is a discussion
that I often have with our researchers, that they think, because they collected the data
in their views, measurements, whatever, that it's their data. And it's actually very rare
that it's their data in the specific context of Finnish universities. If you are on your
own money, on your own grant, then it is your data. But 99% of the time, it's actually
university owns the data. So yeah, in this sense, it's complicated.
Yep. I just want to add that it depends on the policy of the company that you are working.
And I know even for some companies, if you are an employee there, even if you develop some code
out of your working hours, still the code that you produce, it belongs to the company. So it
depends on the policy. Yeah, so you can't even code as a hobby.
Unfortunately, yes, it depends on the company's policy.
Yeah, well, fair enough. Maybe it's the same, you know, you can think of musician that if you're
making music outside of your contract with your record label, maybe the record label manager gets
Alright, but question 5, there's some answers here and basically A to D, they are all to
be considered derivative works, that you know, you download some code and then you donate
or you change the code and modify the code.
Maybe what kind of was surprised for me, and of course it depends, that E and F can also
be considered derivative work. So even though I'm taking our same repository that's on Python package
and I just rewrite it in R, I might still be doing derivative work you know if I follow the
same logic, the same function structure, the same. It would be different if I say would sit down with
me without showing any code, tell me what the package is doing and then I would try to you know
code it based on the description. So it would be like that I would read O'Sane's paper
on the description of this package and just put it in the paper and try to write my own version.
And so yeah, this was a bit unintuitive for me, but on the other hand,
it makes sense when things start to be kind of literal.
It's also interesting, we don't have the... I would add another option here that,
I don't know if you're using some chat GPT or co-pilot to generate code. Is it derivative
work? Because this chat GPT, large language models, they actually have ingested lots of
software from whatever open repositories, but then they don't tell you who originally
wrote a function very similar to the one that you asked. But then again, it's complicated.
Do you actually do or saying if you if you use copilot or GPT to get help let's say with the function would you start searching if.
That function if beats of that function would already exist on the internet that you would find.
Not not that you have to because this is also the thing that when you generate something with this large language models you are actually become the copyright owner of what is generated.
which is counterintuitive in a way because you feel that ethically it's not you that made those
things, but just some machine who has read many, many code scripts. But how do you feel as a user
of course, I guess you use now sometimes these copilots or... Yeah, all the time. Yeah.
Yeah. But I think it's something that as a society, we still have to think about it,
like what should what should we do because it's generally a new concept that we are
facing and I think it would resolve and we would come with a bit more macho ways on
how to cite it and how to use it. But personally if I use something and I get some ideas or like
use the whole functions that the generative AI generates, no I don't go and search like what is
the original repository that produced this one? Yeah. This is, of course, I don't have an answer
myself. And if people want to give their own opinion, in my opinion, it's nice anyway that
people discuss this use of these new tools, generative AI, and how people are using them,
because maybe then we can come up with a consensus on an ethical and responsible way of using them.
We also have a question about these generative AIs. You said if you generate something like
piece of code, you would become the owner of the code, right?
Is that correct?
Yeah.
The default policy is that whatever you generate with the large language model, you are the
copyright owner.
Do you add any citations or anything that I use generative AI for these codes I created?
So the journals have expanded on their policies on the use of generative AI, and so now publishers
like Nature or whatever, many publishers, they would now basically require you to add
a statement, how generative AI was used in the process. I'm not too strong. When I teach
about these things, I can tell that if you just used it for, I don't know, fixing your
English grammar, maybe. There's no point. But if it's clear that that work would have
not been able without the use of generative AI, then of course it must be mentioned.
so if i if my level of coding is very basic for whatever reason because i just started
and i get help from the generative ai and i'm basically not able to judge myself is this code
that the generative made right even though i see with the tests that i you know add that it feels
right at least i can be transparent that you know i got help or i used chat gpt for generating the
code for this and the code is published at this and that repository.
All right, so yeah, when it comes to software licenses, so now we are a bit focusing on
software. I've seen some people in the notes talking also about Creative Common. We will
touch a little bit on so-called data licensing later, but in general there is a taxonomy
of software licenses, this was from the European Commission, yes, so it's a publication that
basically talks about the EU public license, the European Union public license.
And so when it comes to software licenses, there are different, basically there's a continuum
of things that would basically, they are very dark green, that you could basically do whatever
you want with that type of license, so if you find a code and with that code in, I don't know,
GitHub, there is attached a license that says MIT or BST and so on, it means that most likely
you can reuse it and you can do anything you want, you can build on it. In some cases,
you don't even maybe need to tell who was the original author. On the other end of the spectrum,
we have the so-called strong copyleft licenses, and so here the idea is that if I find, let's say
that Ausen writes a package that I want to reuse, but it comes with a strong copyleft license,
it means that whatever I derive from AusenWord should also be released with that strong copyleft.
So I need to use the same license and in some cases, as they say, this license infects the rest
of my code. So it's not just the code that is using OSINT's StrongCopyLeft work that needs to
be released with that license. It might attach my whole project and now
I have to also release it with the StrongCopyLeft license. And in between there are this more kind of
sharealike. The idea of sharealike is that, okay, I make this software public with this license,
but I wouldn't mind that if you improve the software, you are kind of allowing me to
basically get your improvement so that I can also reuse. So it's kind of in between the two,
the very permissive one that lets anybody else to do whatever they want, and the very strict one
that forces everybody else to do as you decide to do.
What is your feeling from a research software engineer perspective?
Have you worked with the projects that have all sorts of licenses or do you feel that
in general it's more towards these permissive licenses?
Personally, I'm more like of the more open licenses like MIT or Creative Commons ones.
My idea is I'm using other people's code and if I'm able to publish the code, it's not
something confidential or it's not an ongoing project that I cannot publish yet, I would
go with more open licenses.
I totally understand, for some of the projects, it's better to have more copy-left licenses
or even a strong copy-left licenses.
An interesting thing is about this picture that we have, is about that arrows that we
have.
Can you also explain what are the arrows and how does it work?
Yeah, so here they talk about that the arrows represent compatibility.
And so that in some cases, you know, some licenses can kind of leave can be can be compatible
with other licenses, but in some other cases, the compatibility, you know, when the like,
for example, here, so if I remember correctly, this red block is more the proprietary licenses.
And so the very permissive licenses are compatible with proprietary licenses, meaning that you
can release a software that it's not going to be open source.
and inside it uses some of the permissive libraries,
but then here you see there's no compatibility
between if something is released
with a very strong compileft,
then nobody can use it in a proprietary software.
There's also here for those who want to explore more,
there are this nice set of links
that help you, for example,
comparing licenses and choosing licenses.
There are different,
There are many nice tools that given you might even answer some questionnaire or what you would like to do with your license and then they can recommend you
with whatever type of licenses.
All right. So maybe I think we agreed that we will not do this exercise for the sake of speed and we can now talk when should I add a license.
So the best, of course, is as early as possible, like with everything else, that if you agree
at the beginning that you want to choose a certain license, then you choose it at the beginning.
It's funny that with the GitHub interface, when you create a repository from the web interface,
immediately it asks you, which license do you want to attach with it? So it's clear.
Any year I can see citations to myself, what I was saying also earlier that if you work from the very beginning as if your project is already public and open,
then you can already think at the very beginning that there's a license, that there's a policy,
because of course in this social coding part we didn't really mention this earlier but you might also want to recommend how people can contribute to the improvements of your code,
of your code, you can create a community around your project
and tools like GitHub allow you easily to create issues,
create discussions around your code.
So basically, when should you add a license?
As early as possible.
And how to add a license if your work is derivative work?
So basically, these tools that I mentioned earlier
that could check the compatibility
would allow you to see that if you reuse some specific package that might have permissive
or strong copyleft licenses, then you can see what type of license you can basically
attach to the code.
In general, maybe one comment that at least when I was asking you or saying that you are
in favor of more permissive licenses. What I wanted to add is that sometimes you have
to think that the users of your software, those who will reuse, is there other people
like you. So the permissive licenses, even though you might feel you are donating your
code to the Google, Microsoft, Meta, whatever, at the end of the day, you're just making
it easier for other people like you to reuse your code if you have a permissive license.
With more copyleft licenses, they're of course very ethical and it's nice that some projects
are strong copyleft and they demand that whoever uses those projects also become strong copyleft.
But when it comes to researchers like us, sometimes we might just make the life more
complicated when the researchers need to publish their code with their papers. So at the end
the day. If you aren't sure which one to pick, go with the most permissive licenses. Do you have any
comment on this? No, it was perfect coverage. Thanks. Yeah. All right. So something that I
think I got to see, like it's not an exact questions on the HackMD, but I get a team that
it's happening. Let's say sorting algorithms, right? So do someone own the sorting algorithms
and have license on them, or only it depends on the implementation and the code has been published?
Yeah. As usual, I'm not a lawyer, so I don't take my words for legal advice.
But in my understanding and in my discussion with legal experts,
add the idea of the algorithm the pseudocode is not patentable so if i write a book with pseudocode on how to do this whatever sorting method,
nobody can patented but in the moment that i make an implementation.
as a system that is reusable, kind of as a standalone system, so not just writing the pseudocode into some code,
then it can be patentable. So let's say that I have a web application where you copy-paste your vector of numbers and then press a button,
and then my web application sorts your number in a very whatever fast way then this is a system and
I can patent this web application for sorting numbers but if I would just have the code that
does the sort I would not be able to patent that but I can still protect it with the license so
that I can say okay you want to use my sort fast sort algorithm then I don't know use I'm going to
attach a very copyleft license you have to make everything open if you use it.
Yep, thanks.
Let's see if there's any other question to bring up.
It's nice that there's many answers already so that we don't have to.
Yeah, that's why I was a bit silent. I was trying to
to rest of my knowledge, but our other contributors to thanks everyone.
In general, this there's also sometimes what could happen is that things might change in
time. So that may be a project start with a certain license, but then for whatever reason
you realize that, I don't know, you really need to adopt, change the license to a more
copy-left one because you started using some software that has a more copy-left license.
Of course, licensing can change in time. It's not preferable in a sense that if you would
really need to apply this, you would kind of need to contact, you know, your user base
and tell them, okay, you've been using my code as permissive license, but from today
license is not permissive anymore, it becomes copy left. So of course, you might be familiar
yourself that the terms and conditions of whatever service that you use change in time so often that
nobody even reads what is the new change. So the same would also go here. So changing the license
is not retroactive and if someone is still using the code, does it apply to them or how
does it work?
Yeah.
Well, again, it depends because I would hope that it's not retroactive in a sense that
if a release of a certain version of a certain tool was released with, let's say, a very
open permissive license that i can still allow to use that you know open version of the software
because maybe the company decided that from version 2.0 they went full copyright you know
so maybe i'm still allowed to use version 1.0 but 2.0 i need to buy whatever the license from
the company but then there are also some other aspects maybe this is more related to data
that can be changes to the license of data that can be retroactive and the general data protection regulation the GDPR is one example of this so that if I released open personal data 10 years ago actually GDPR would affect the license of that data and would not allow me to keep it open anymore.
So, again, it depends, but it's clear, for example, for those who really are into these
legal matters, I would really recommend reading this paper from the European Commission where
they describe this type of license, the European Union Public License.
It's a bit of a, it's a share-alike license, so it's not in the most permissive, but it's
also not in the most strong copy left.
And what is interesting is that whatever projects related to the European Commission, they are
being released with this license, so that it's clear that it's for the benefit of everyone
that those who will reuse this code kind of make also their code in this public licensure
like public license.
And then you can basically get what other people made with your code and improve your
code.
work of course to to make sure that also the new code that you release also follows this
the same type of share alike license but this is kind of the best balance between you know being
permissive and letting other people to use as much as possible and also being more ethical
to kind of you know also get back from from what you give. Yeah we also we have a comment from a
user that like the more open licenses cannot be closed retroactively and also like if you have
different versions or you release a new version you can change the license but as a standard for
the free software you cannot change the existing license without changing that version or the code.
Yeah so that's what I was saying as well. Yes and one thing that I wanted to ask is
Do you have any comments or thoughts on multi-licensing, or do you usually use one-line sense, or what
is the best practice here?
Well, I mean, I see the point of having multi-licenses, dual licenses, because sometimes some businesses,
maybe in the context of academic research, maybe there's not much point, but if some
of the research turns into a business idea or, you know, if companies want to have a
mixture of copyright, private code and public, there is a benefit that, you know, if something
is used for, I don't know, commercial purposes, then maybe you follow a certain license. But
But then again, I'm also a bit conflicted with these dual licenses, because if one really
looks at the open source and open source software licenses, it is clear that you can't really
impose what people can do with your code.
One of the advantages of the open source software licenses is that you're not liable yourself
with whatever people will do, but also you can't control if people, for example, will
use your code for doing something malicious. You can't block them with these licenses.
Yeah, but I guess that the takeaway here is like you can use multiple licenses and
which is a good, which can be a good practice if it's suitable for your case, for your data,
or for yourself files. You can add a different license than the general license that you have
for the whole repository. All right, I guess it's time for a little break. We can come back
and maybe we can come back at the 14 o'clock or 14.01, 14.02. Yeah, maybe 14.02.
All right, so let's have a little break and we will be back in 10 minutes.
you
How about one on welcome back?
to the social coding section. We already talked about social coding and sharing your code and
also a bit of about licensing. Now we want to talk about software citations. We talked about
how code is a bit different than papers and why there are different things that you have to
consider and citation is one of the things which maybe is more similar and also a bit different
then paper citations, I would say. So here in the screen, you can see we want to talk about
FAIR principles first. So [name], what is FAIR principles?
Yeah, so we touched on this FAIR principles also in the morning when it comes to the reproducibility.
And basically the FAIR principle is like, you know, the acronyms would be findable,
accessible interoperable and reusable and now while this maybe is kind of easy to understand
when it comes to data because of course you want your data set to be findable by whatever search
system accessible whether it is fully open or open on request so but at least there is a way
to access it interoperable which means that you can work with other tools it's in a format that
other softwares can open it and read it and reusable so that there is like we just discussed
a license that would give some principles on how to reuse this to reuse it the same
pair principle for data they can also be extended to software and so again that people can find
your software that they can access it they can download it interoperable so that it works with
data system and that there is a clear way on how to reuse it with clear licenses attached
to the software, for example.
So again, because sometimes people you might think, okay, I put my software, my scripts
that I've done for this paper, I put them in my university homepage or they are on GitHub
and that's it.
always need to think a little bit long term. And I have to mention actually that me, myself,
I decided to use some GitHub repository from the university and then that repository is
not there anymore. So now I have published paper that are pointed to some Git repository
hosted by a department that doesn't exist anymore. And so once in a while I get questions
where is the code now, you know. So there was a mistake on my side that I didn't actually
create a so-called DOI, Digital Object Identifier, or PID, Persistent Identifier,
because if I would have done that, another organization would have taken care of preserving
my software for as many years as we can think of. And so what we see here in this make your code
citable and persistent, the persistent part is exactly this. It's not enough to put it on your
web page or to put it on github because github maybe will change your account will be i don't
know maybe you decide to delete your account and with that all your repository or by accident you
even delete a repository because you thought that that was just a side project so there are services
like zenodo which is hosted by cern and with zenodo you can basically get a digital object
identifier for anything digital it can be the software release for example or it can also be
used for for data sets that can be published. And so what is nice about this Zenodo repository
is that it automatically can be linked with your open with your available GitHub repositories
so that whenever you create a release on your GitHub project repository Zenodo can actually
automatically basically pull the new release so that you can basically have a permanent copy of
your GitHub releases stored in the CERN data center. Have you ever published this type of
DOI or have you helped anyone with this type of getting a DOI for a software or SANE?
Yeah, we were helping a researcher to publish the code and we had to use that and also explain
the things that you already explained about why it's important to just have a DOI and
it's not enough to only host it on your personal GitHub account because in 10 years GitHub can
go down, right?
We don't know.
Yeah.
And people and researchers are already familiar with this because it's also a very similar
aspect in publishing your paper as well. It's not enough to publish your PDF or
PDF of your research on your personal website or Google Drive. You have to have a DOI
to make it persistent for the future. Yeah, it's also nice that the interface that
comes with the Zenodo website. If you see, if you search for some software, you can actually
look at some metrics. Again, we don't do this for the metrics, but sometimes the metrics help us,
whatever motivate our bosses, that you can look at metrics like number of downloads and number
of citations so that, you know, you can also kind of quantify a little bit impact that your
software or scripts might have. What is here now it is a checklist. Checklists are always useful
because they're practical and you can basically see what is needed to make your software citable
and so assigning appropriate license like we mentioned before the break then we want to
to have a description of the software so that there is appropriate metadata format, clear
version numbers, authors are credited, we get this persistent identifier like the DOI,
and then even sometimes we won't tell in the software which publication to cite, because
in some cases some publications might be related, the so-called software packages publications,
some other cases the main publication is about let's say some application of the software but
still you release the software along with the original publication. Recently there's
there's also the way that through your on your github repository you can also like a so-called
machine readable software citation file so cff citation file format and it basically looks
something like this. So machine readable means that a computer, another computer can automatically
read and you see that these are like variables with the names and the values and some can be
you know structure. It looks a bit like this yaml files and so this pre kind of fixed
metadata about the software makes it easier and makes especially if you have you know search
and genes or or specific publication and genes that it's easy for these other tools to basically
index your software and make it findable and accessible and so on with the FAIR principles.
GitHub now supports this citation cff files so if you name the file with this
exactly like a citation.cff it can already be automatically interpreted by by GitHub and here
there's some like a video how to create it and even a web but in practice if you are from if
you're fine with that with using some text editor it's you can even take just this template and
and reuse it so anything else to add was is there anything in the notes document worth
uh no we don't have any questions or comments till now all right well then in general also
So this is one way to get your citations with the software.
But in some cases, maybe your software, the contribution that you and your research group
add to the software can be substantial so that there can be papers that are truly about
software.
So full papers that they describe software packets.
And then there are specific journals that accept this type of software papers.
So then if I can kind of call back of someone was mentioning that sometimes software is
not peer-reviewed, with this type of work you can understand that it's the software
even more important than the actual paper.
And so it might go to more extensive peer-review and checks and compatibility and so on.
At the end of the day, like Jose mentioned earlier, it's maybe not the actual work of
the two or three peer reviewers,
but it's really the community
that is around the software project.
So if these larger packages,
they have a big community around
and we can all be part of that community,
whether it's just fixing a typo in the documentation
or working on a new release with the main developers,
so that the peer review is truly a dynamic process
that basically never ends.
not that when this software was published in 2021, it has not been touched. I'm sure that
it has improved in the meantime and it has evolved and gotten better and better.
One note that I wanted to add is like the papers that only talking about the software are becoming
more popular nowadays. And at least for a lot of Python libraries, all libraries, you can see
they publish the paper. And it's also good for the researchers as well, because they get
many, many citations, which is maybe not the case for your scientific papers. So consider
on publishing the paper for your code as well, which is becoming more popular nowadays.
Yeah, and it's true. And it's nice that maybe this type of metrics like, you know, maybe
right now in the CV, in some standard CV that might not yet be space for your software packages,
but these are catching up. So I can mention in Finland, there is the tank CV, which is
one format used by the Finnish grant agencies. And already they would have a section right
now they have a section right now that where one can add this type of extra non-typical
paper type of publications or like software.
All right so we still have 10 minutes left and then of course we will ask about the feedback
of the day. The last part is about sharing data. Now there are many and better and more
extensive talks online on sharing data because as you can understand when it comes we discussed
a lot about software sharing and contributing and reuse it but all the same could be said
about data that sometimes we might wanna have a data set that is truly copyrighted and so
nobody else can access and they need to ask you for a license or maybe they need to pay you
you. But some other times we might have a data set that you can fully release opening
whether because you decide to do so with your employer with your supervisor and of course
everything in between where you might want like we had this share alike for the software
the same would be for the data that you share the data but any derivative work done with
and the data should also be released with a similar license, for example.
So when it comes to this, where to actually share the data,
what type of options are there, this Zenodo repository is also mentioned in this case.
In Zenodo, it's not just about sharing the release of your software,
but you can share all sorts of data and it's really nice that you can also share
slides and white papers or anything that you feel like that can contribute to your scientific
community. But Zenodo is not the only one and so there are these other services. I'd like to at
least mention the Open Science Framework that allows to do this type of sharing of nice dataset.
But in international context, the Open Science Framework is hosted in the United States,
Ferrari members, Zenodo is in Switzerland, Figshare I think now is bought by Naturespringer,
EU.is basically EOSC or European platform, and Dryad is also, I don't think it's public
anymore, or they might give you a non-profit, like a small, how do you call, freemium license.
But here then we will not go through this, but different countries, at least in the Nordics
where most of you are right now, there are different national services for sharing the
data and there are also resources for the so-called data management. Now again we will not expand
much on here but if you think that if git was using for keeping versioning versions of your code
the same could be done with data so that you can version the version of the data set because you
had version 1.0 that had some I don't know outliers but then you have version 2.0 where
where you clean the data, remove the outliers and so on.
So these type of tools like Data Lad,
Data Stewardship Wizard, Git Annex,
that is not mentioned here, but it's Prattix Data Lad,
so they can help you basically keep also the versioning
of the data and not just of the code.
And then when it comes to the licensing of data sets
and databases which are a specific type of data set,
there are different legislation that can cover this.
And similarly, as we had for software,
we can have something that is in the full spectrum
from completely open public domain
to completely private copyright.
So the type of licenses that you hear about data,
there's so-called creative common licenses.
There are different flavors
with the CC0 being the so-called public domain
where it's as open as possible,
people can reuse and they don't even need to cite you.
And then more kind of restrictions
on the reuse of the data,
which could be that people need to cite you
or people cannot do commercial work with that
or this share alike that people need to re-share
what they did with the data
as you are doing with the data and basically so on.
When it comes to the machine learning and AI,
things are of course getting a little bit more complicated.
Machine learning models are impracticed data,
so the model, the weights on its own,
they can't really be,
you can't do much with those unless you
have a system to basically run the models and whether you
are generating data or
classifying whatever you're classifying but what is tricky and at least what is
a bit blurred right now here in the context of AI and machine learning
models is that sometimes you hear things like open source models or open source
language models but if one really would kind of look at the definition of open
source they are actually not open source they sometimes people call open weights
so that the models, the weights, the actual file,
you can download it and reuse it,
but you have no idea of how that model was done.
So everything else basically around the model
is actually not open at all.
Here, it mentions this Artificial Intelligence Act,
which was became entering into force
on the 1st of August of this year.
And the AI Act adds some basically restrictions
on what the researchers even can basically open.
If you're not planning to open anything
related to your AI models,
basically the AI act lets you do whatever you want.
But in the moment that you need to start sharing your model,
you need to basically see if your type
of machine learning model would fall inside
of this so-called high risk or prohibited AI systems.
And of course, there are different, how can I say, obligations. There are different legal
obligations depending on what type of artificial intelligence systems you might be working
on. In general, we have some material on these new topics that we will expand on this page.
But if you have questions, of course, please write them down in the chat. And then many
nice links here that would be nice to browse together, but our time is soon over.
I was saying, do you have any comments or is there anything to highlight from the notes?
No. In the notes, we don't have any direct question to sharing data. We had some questions
about software citations and some about like accounts, but not about sharing data.
And yeah, it was completely good. If you want to pick, if you need to choose one of these
further readings and you have time to go deeper into all this reproducible research, opening data
and opening software, I really recommend this Turing Way, which is an open book on all these
topics. It's a nice read. You can read it. It's open. You can read it on your mobile phone during
your commute. So if you really need to pick one, I recommend the first one. And in general,
I mean, it's nice that we are building a community together through Code Refinery.
If you explore our pages, you can also get access to a chat. And in the chats that we use,
is called Zulip and through the Zulip chat you can join discussions. We can continue discussions
on these topics and we have all sorts of discussions there so that is something nice.
We already saw some participants from this workshop have already joined the Code Refinery chat.
All right, so we still have eight minutes which is a good moment for asking for feedback.
so it would be great if on the notes we could paste the usual feedback for the day
if this was too fast too slow
and i see that they are already there i could actually switch
to the notes view with my movie director interface
And so yes, as usual, even though we give similar lessons over the years, they're never
exactly the same, the phases are changing, we might update the lesson a little bit, and
of course what makes this unique is your questions and your experience, so please give us feedback
and if there's something you want to you think that we could have covered more or
less please write it down. Then tomorrow we have we have the fifth day of the
workshop and tomorrow the topic will be documentation which is kind of somewhat
related with the topics of the day so because along with the license you also want to tell
people not just how to use your code but also how to maybe you know expand it, contribute to it
and so on. And then the second part of tomorrow will be about Jupyter notebooks. Maybe some of
you are already familiar with this way of interacting with code and data and hopefully
for those who have never experienced this, it's something you can try out. Again, tomorrow
will be like a demo day, so you're not expected to actually, you know, run things, but if
you want to actually do and see what people are doing, whether you want to build the documentation,
and it's not just about documentation, because with the same system that will be introduced
Tomorrow you can also, it's the same system
that we use to build our web pages,
our training materials,
they're all built with this same system.
And so, you can also learn how to create your website,
for example, under this github.io if you want.
And so, if you wanna test these things,
you please follow our installation instructions
if you're planning to do that.
All right. I think I see that people are commenting. Is there anything to highlight? Let me have a look at the chat.
Um, based on the feedback, uh, I think a place where that was on track,
if I was satisfied with the speed and although like some, we have some
comments that, uh, it was a bit too fast and there were like many topics
that we had to cover and, uh, unfortunately maybe it was a bit too
fast if you don't have the required background or if you're not familiar
with it, with the subject, it can be a bit overwhelming.
This is exactly why we decided almost a year ago to not having exercises in this week too,
because sometimes not only there's lots of new topics, on top of those try to run snake
make locally or building a Zenodo repository or how do you call it, getting a DOI through
there's another sandbox so we hopefully this is a little bit more digestible and useful
and of course we provide you with all these links and other resources that those who really
have time can can try themselves and please join our Zulip chat so that we can continue
discussing there and helping you there if you want to try these things and you need
further help.
All right.
So hopefully this was a good day for and
I can maybe add also a reminder that day six will be more about
coding related things. We will cover things like automated testing
and modular code development and then again if you want to do or if you want to try the exercises
that the instructors are going to show on the stream you can also you should basically also
install what we recommend in our installation pages but then again it's just fine to participate
through the questions and thank you again for the many questions there's almost 50 today so
it was great that you were so active. Also, thanks for the participants who
were active in answering other questions. Thanks. I see one question that is for me that is related
to the one ECTS credit. And so, yes, in this case, I tried to be as clear as possible on that page,
but if something is not clear, I'm happy to expand it. In practice, this means that if you
you are sure that your supervisor or study coordinator or whoever is able to accept a
kind of an official paper from me that says that this person has completed the Code Refinery
workshop, there are very simple homework to do for getting the certificate, then I will
give you this document and then you can convert that into a credit.
And if you are at Aalto University, you just need to give me your student number and I
will add the credit for you on our system.
But in general, we don't track if you were attending, you know, whatever days you were
attending.
As long as you do the homeworks, we can, you know, we can give you, we can give you the
credit.
Okay, so let's see if there's any other quick question to pick.
We still have one minute and a half.
Yeah, I think most of the things are uncertain.
All right, maybe we can call it a day, one minute earlier, and thank you for watching.
The recordings will appear immediately on Twitch TV and later on the week on our YouTube
channels and so see you tomorrow for day 5 of Code Refinery.
Thank you [name] for being here with me and thank you everyone for watching.
Thank you everyone for joining.
Bye.
Bye bye.
you