CodeRefinery.org
you
Hello.
.
There we go.
So I guess if you're here today, you probably know how it works, and if not, you'll figure
out pretty soon.
So yeah, this is our shared notes, and everyone writes questions in the bottom, and we have
a bunch of people that are answering.
the suggested window layout so we have a twitch stream that's portrait mode not to be a video
short but to take off half your screen so you have half the screen to work. But let's
assume y'all know. So what do we do now? Or what's our icebreakers? Everyone can click
pencil icon at the top to edit this. So, [name] and [name], so if you had to explain your job
to someone from the year 1700, what would you say or how would you explain it?
Yeah, I don't remember how I thought about this, but I don't remember my answer.
But it depends a lot on who it is, because if it's an average Finnish person
of the 1700s, then I think I would go with like an agricultural metaphor, like taking care of
windmills maybe, like some machinery. So like you're the, ah okay, yeah. So I'm not necessarily
the one operating the windmill, but rather the person you call when it doesn't work.
Yeah. Okay. As you would expect. Makes sense.
Yeah. To me, it feels like, I mean, I don't know if electricity was invented by then, probably not.
So I'll have to say something like, I come from the future and then there are, you know,
machines which run on lightning, I guess. And they, you know, they are able to write books
and read books instead of, you know, data. And I do many things with it. Like, yeah,
that could be something. The challenging part is getting the computer part out.
Yeah. Yeah. So computers process information. Yeah. So are we like librarians or something?
Or calculators? But did people have to do calculations in the 1700s?
I mean, some, I would think.
They did build buildings and,
so probably the job of a calculator didn't exist yet,
but there were people doing some mechanical things.
Yeah.
Anyway, okay.
Oh, where are we in here?
So, yeah, please open up an answer here.
So I'll write in my answer while we're talking.
Let's see if we get some better answers than what we could come up with.
Hopefully.
So, what's the best documented project you've seen?
Should we wait for some answers?
Yeah.
I mean, I have a go-to example that I might bring up in the documentation section, and
I think we have a different example now.
I don't always have to bring up the same one, but it's NumPy, and it's mainly just that
it has all of the sections that we talk about, but it is useful.
You can actually find what you are looking for, and there are good tutorials.
describes to a complete beginner, it describes pretty well what the library is, yeah.
Can we call it predictable? Like, if you need to know something, you can both find it with a web
search, and then you find the thing, and you know whatever function you need is probably going to
have good documentation. It will definitely say what goes in, what comes out, and all.
It's relatively consistent in how it looks.
It's on the web, so it's actually available.
Yeah.
On the context of NumPy, the popularity helps with these things, because people are using it a lot.
lot. But like we were looking at the readme of Nump by that day.
So even the best libraries can have, you know, gaps when it
comes to onboarding, let's say, or getting started stuff. So,
so there might not exist a perfect project, but sometimes
good enough is all you need.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, I should actually come up with a good example of something
that only has a readme and nothing else that is where that's
good enough or where it's a good readme.
Yeah.
And then there's some projects which seem like they're pretty
good, but it's just not very user friendly.
Like, you have to already know a lot in order to navigate the docs.
So it's essentially only documentation for programmers who already use the project,
which is understandable. That's the first thing you write, because that's what you yourself need.
Yeah. Like for here, I think SQLite. So it has quite good docs, but
But, man, it seems, and like these good figures and so on and everything I know will be in
a page roughly where I know it'll look, but, man, it doesn't seem very friendly for users.
And if you don't already know how the docs are organized, you're not going to find what
you need very easily.
So yeah.
But I guess it's time to start.
So should I introduce you all?
I guess may as well.
So today we have two lessons.
First is documentation taught by [name] and [name] here.
So it's the first two hours before lunch.
And then after that, we have an hour-long lunch break, and then there's Jupyter.
So I guess many people know about Jupyter already, and for some people it's not relevant,
like if you're using the R equivalent or Julia equivalents or whatever.
But there are still some good lessons here.
So it's not only basic Jupyter, but we say how to use these kind of notebooks and to share
things using version control, and to make them a little bit more reproducible.
So some of these lessons are still going to be useful to others.
And even those that know Jupyter.
So with that, maybe I will start to disappear, and I'll leave it up to you all.
Does that sound good?
Yeah, once I've done copying.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, yeah, I'll switch to your screen once it's shared and see you later.
Um, so, actually, do you want to share your screen.
Right. I can. Yeah.
Just to show the.
the main page of the documentation lesson and
and we can
go to the demonstrations.
So
Okay. Yeah. Does that look good?
Yes.
Works for me. Yeah.
Okay. So yeah.
Let's get started. We'll talk about documentation today or in this lesson like [name] mentioned.
Let's start with a really broad question. Why do you need documentation? What's the point?
Can you take us?
Yeah.
Why do you need good documentation?
Probably the most important reason to write good documentation,
at least when you're working on your own project, when you're starting out,
It might seem that you know how everything works in your code when you're writing it,
and you probably do.
But then a month later or even a week later or sometimes even a day later, you come back
to it and it is very much not clear what is doing what.
So that is – we said about version control, one of the main reasons you need version control
is for yourself.
same goes for documentation. One of the main reasons is for yourself. Probably also a good
rule of thumb of when your documentation is good is when you think you could actually read it and
figure out what's going on. That's a big reason. Of course, another big reason is that it helps
other people use your project and therefore it helps other people then make contributions and
makes your project more useful. Shall we go into this lesson but?
Yes, I think the icebreaker is covered essentially.
Like the introduction, so let's go to motivation and wishlist.
Yeah.
Sure.
I mean, we already started talking a bit about motivation, why is it important.
So should we start, so there is now a documentation section at the bottom of the notes.
So should we start a quick question here?
I'll write down the question.
And then a lot of the lesson will
be these kind of discussions in the notes.
So I will write, why documenting code?
Or why should you document your code?
And just, yeah, please write some answers.
So write down why you think documentation is useful.
And also, what do you need for good documentation?
So what do you think would be useful for yourself
if you are working in your own code?
And what would you actually want from someone else's code,
someone else's project in their documentation.
And assuming you are working with a research group
who's using the code,
how do you motivate your colleagues
to contribute to the documentation?
That's also an important question.
So let's wait a few minutes
Before we go into this, some answers we have already given,
but these are now by no means correct answers.
Your answers will be more correct.
So please go ahead and write down in the notes.
Indeed, everyone's.
We'll wait a minute or so to see what answers come up.
Yes.
I got a video.
You
A lot of good answers.
So what do we have to make it possible for other people to use the code?
That is important.
That includes of course your colleagues.
So one option is if you have a normal average-sized research group, what would that be, five people
using your code to some extent. One option is to write down the answers to the most obvious
questions in the beginning. The other option is to tell everybody one by one, probably a couple of
times. That is a big reason to write documentation. But then also, of course, not just your
colleagues, but if you publish it, then other people might also benefit. That is, of course,
was good. To know what it's doing, what is needed, or the outputs, it needs to be sufficiently
clear so that I'm able to tweak it, yeah.
That's true.
Yeah.
Sometimes.
Yeah, so this is, I see a function, it's several lines of code, 20 lines of code. It's nice
if it has good documentation so that I don't actually have to try to read the code to figure
what it's doing. Yeah, so that it's usable. What's the point if it's not?
Yeah, if you're not only writing for yourself. I hear a bit of an echo again. Did something
change the microphone settings? Oh, well. Yeah.
Yeah, so if you're only writing for yourself,
well, even then you should document
because you will forget,
but it is your kind of in a way wasting effort
because someone else could also be using the same code
and that would be more efficient.
Remind myself what the functions did, yeah.
like putting frozen food in the freezer.
It's not labeled, it's hard to figure out what it is, right?
So you come back in a month or a year
and it is pretty much impossible to figure out
what your code is doing unless the functions
and all the parts are properly labeled and explained.
Prevent having to rewrite, yeah.
So yeah, that's true.
If you don't know what the code is doing, then you probably need to just rewrite it
later.
That happens.
Explain the code to myself and others.
people in the research group do not have the same skill levels. Essentially, either you write
documentation for the people in your research group to use your code or you end up teaching
them probably a few times before they are confident in how to use your code.
That is a big reason for documentation. That covers way more than what we had.
then what we had in our short answer. So that last point, shield your limited time, is essentially
that you don't have to keep re-explaining the same thing to your colleagues and other people.
Okay, so what is documentation and what would you actually want it to look like?
This is pretty much the same question really. There's a few different types of documentations
that are useful. There's tutorials. These show a new user how to do a thing with the code and
these are kind of like the exercises we have in these lessons for example. You have a specific
goal and then the tutorial gives you some lines of code to run. It's not necessarily the goal that
the user actually has, it's more there to show how to do things. So these are
learning oriented. Sometimes they look a lot like lecture materials.
Then, you can have how-to guides, goal-oriented, well, I just said that the tutorials kind
of usually have a specific goal, but they are doing a specific thing in order to show
you how the code works.
Goal-oriented here means how-to guides show you how you should do a specific thing that
is probably something you might want to do. A tutorial is how to train a machine learning
model to recognize handwritten digits. You wouldn't probably actually need a code that
does that because that's been written a million times. But a how-to guide would be how to
train a actual big large language model, how to fine-tune it. That's something you might actually
be doing in your real life, in your work.
Explanations, just essentially telling you what the code is
doing and how things work.
That's maybe the most straightforward.
When you say documentation, that might come to mind first.
Then there's a reference.
Something like a list of functions, a list of classes,
is and what each of those does, why they exist.
So there's a lot more here, but these are the basic parts.
If you know what these are and figure out
which ones you actually need in your project and write those,
that is a pretty good place to be at.
But it all depends on the project.
So a small project, just a readme file
that contains some explanation of what the code is
and maybe some very short example
that's basically a tutorial and how to guide in one.
That is probably enough.
Maybe some in code documentation
that kind of functions as a reference as well.
So, yeah, in a small project, you don't need much.
but in a bigger project, in something like NumPy or something big that thousands of people use,
you probably want all of those and you want to think about them separately.
Let's go back to the collaborative document and let's make a wish list.
So, what would you like to see in documentation when you open, when you go looking at a piece
of software, in research software, that you might want to use?
It sounds like a library that would do the thing you want it to do, but you don't know
yet.
What would you like to see?
Oh, maybe I'll copy this to the, to the notes.
So does it make sense to say that now the question is how do we write and maintain it,
like where do we store the documentation?
I guess this is still more about content, like what would you like to see in,
I mean, I guess someone else's work in this case, that's at least how I think about the question.
Okay.
It's talking about research software. It could be about a big library, but I guess what I have in
mind is you have a relatively obscure research problem and you do some searching and you find
a Python library or some library that sounds like it could do the job.
job. What would you want there to be in the documentation so that you would actually use
that code rather than just write it yourself? Because quite often you still end up writing
it yourself. This could be about a bigger project. It could be about something like
what would you want to see in Torch documentation or some other really big library behind us?
Do you have any comments? I think I'm talking a lot, but that's just me.
No, but here we have like very good answers from the learners.
So there are talking about assumptions of the nitty-gritty details.
And then there is someone saying that one should add a detailed way of the code so that
with examples.
So examples are often very useful.
So yeah, dependencies can help when
someone is installing the code for the first time.
Gallery with examples, yeah, sometimes
adding a lot of some images, which shows what it does.
quite useful so that it's not a lot of text. That's true. What else do we have here?
So examples, examples, yeah. Yeah, there's two big things. I mean, there's like the details of
how you use it, inputs and outputs of functions and so on. And then there's this under the hood.
code. What are the assumptions? What is it intended to do? What's the big picture? Those
should be there. Those should be easy to find. That's a good point. Where is the code? How
do you actually get the live? How do you install it? How do you get it to run? That's a very
One part of it, of course.
And yeah, dependencies kind of goes to the same thing.
Yeah.
Easy to find good points.
Good structure.
Yeah.
That's useful.
Okay.
So we have a lot of points in the answer in the lecture materials.
Um,
that are mainly taken from years of answers to this question from the notes, so that's
a good read. But I think we shouldn't go through all of this. Mostly, this is repeating what
we've said or something that we will go into later.
We will talk about licensing later, but one important point is including a license file
and making sure that people know you can actually use the code. It's not there just for show.
Actually, that is one of the answers. That is the last answer in the notes.
So, am I allowed to use it? That's a very good point.
So, okay.
Should we go to the next section?
Yes, you can do that.
License.
Oh yeah, there's a next button.
Next button at the bottom of the page usually.
Okay, so in code documentation, this is probably the easiest thing to maybe in readme file
is equally easy to add because it's just adding a file, but yeah, essentially this is writing
something into the file that the code is in, writing some comments, doc strings.
Sorry. Okay.
Okay, so what is the upside – sorry, I was coughing and then I lost my train of thought.
So the big upside is, when you look at the function,
you see the documentation.
If you're a programmer and you take
a look at what there's a function you want to run,
you can immediately see the documentation.
Then, so it's version controlled with the code itself, so you can commit it into Git.
It will then follow the code around.
And if the doc string or the comment is in the beginning of the function, it will actually
just follow the function around wherever it is in the code, so you can always find it.
But if you're a new user and you see just a bunch of code files,
then that is not the best starting point. That's the disadvantage, which is fixed by readme files.
So a readme file is something that's obvious to look at and often automatically opened
side-by-side with the code. If you look at the code on GitHub, it will display the readme file
directly, for example, and GitLab, I think, as well. Readme files are also version-controlled
in the same way. It's a file, so you have to add it and commit it separately. It doesn't
code directly with the code, but it's text, it works the same way.
So what are the disadvantages? It doesn't, essentially the opposite of in-code documentation
and also it cannot be very complicated or long because it's a single file.
It doesn't have structure in the same sense as a website might.
Okay, so we suggest that you use either RST rich text, restructured text or markdown
to write documentation. These are mostly automatically rendered by different tools.
You can use them relatively easily.
You don't have to generate anything.
And you get some nice structure that you get a good looking documentation out of it.
Some headers and subsections and so on.
And of course you are currently using Markdown to write the notes.
So, you roughly know how it works.
Okay.
So, we don't have to go much into this because we'll come back to it later.
In fact, we'll come back to everything about here.
Everything here we'll come back to in a moment.
So, here's some.
So, HTML static site generators.
generators. That's another option. So, if a README file is not enough, if you want something
bigger, so you want multiple pages or you want more structure into the documentation,
it's a big enough project that you need that. Then static site generators are a good tool.
they can turn this RST or Markdown code into nice looking websites. So we will demonstrate with
Sphinx and it can use Markdown or RST. It's well demonstrating it because we know how
to use it but also it is very general and relatively easy to use. But there are other
options too and so there's package down which is popular in our community. These often are tied to
the language for understandable reasons like it comes with the language or it's written for that
language so that it's easy to use in that language. Sphinx is very general though it's not limited
It runs on Python, but it's not limited to Python in any way.
But yeah, there's lots of good options here that you can check out.
Also, Zola is what we use to build our project website, so it's another option that we like.
At least the popular Git repositories all allow you to directly serve static HTML and
actually build your HTML sites using Sphinx or something else. You don't have to have
a web server to post your documentation pages.
But okay, so there's also wikis,
which are very similar to a static website.
The wikis would exist outside.
So a static website is written in Markdown and restructures text.
It will be in your code base and version control with your code.
So that's nice.
And wikis tend to exist separately.
But also wikis allow a kind of
collaborative editing
that doesn't require
the users to know Git. It requires
them to know wikis, so
that's a trade-off.
But they are also useful.
So yeah, the barrier
to write and edit is very low.
There's
people often use LaTeX
and PDFs.
You can also version control that with your code, it later is code.
A PDF format though is harder to share and it is not something you would probably
want to version control with your code.
Yeah, so the ODE oxygen is a way of generating API documentation which I
will demonstrate with Sphinx how to do API documentation if we have time.
time. I saw quickly, yeah, there was a point in the notes. Can you use the documentation
that's included in your code, the in-code documentation, to automatically generate this sort of API
documentation? That's what Doxygen is for. There is also a tool in Sphinx to do that.
So, yeah, I mean, one upside with using in-code documentation is that you can then automatically
also extract it into a separate website.
It's much harder to go the other way around, right, to go from a website to having documentation
that kind of links to your code.
So this is, it's a nice way of essentially getting both at once.
And the good thing is like, it's always up to date with the code.
So if you change the function or take it away, the documentation is often kept updated.
So it doesn't go old.
Yeah, so whenever you change the function, you hopefully also remember to change the
documentation because it's right there, whereas if the documentation is separate in some other
markdown file, you might forget to do it or you might not do it at the same time, and then
it will not be up-to-date.
That's a good point.
Yeah.
Okay, so we have a bit more detail in the next section about in code documentation.
So we have already talked a good bit about this and about, well, all of the other sections
I think let's do the exercise so that everybody gets to chip in but then I think we'll move
relatively quickly. So I will add a poll on the notes.
And the question is, which one of these comments is more useful documentation or is which one
of these is better?
And you can also say why.
So, info block here.
And we'll vote for either comment A. So, maybe can you share the notes so that I can
So, I will explain what I'm typing in.
So, like in the polls that we've had before,
either vote for comment A or comment B
by adding some character in there.
At least in the edit view,
it will be clear which one has more votes.
has more votes. It's kind of a bar graph.
And then I'll also add the question why, so that you get a chance to explain yourself
if you want to. I think people are pretty clear on this question, but why is the second
one better.
And I guess, what are the good, in what way is the first one good, in what way is the second one good?
Yeah, so essentially in the first one, if you know Python or if you know, I mean, it's
two lines of code is relatively clear. If you know almost any programming language,
you can figure out that these two lines are checking if the temperature is below
minus 50 and printing an error. So the comment is not giving any new information really,
unless you are completely new to coding and you don't know what this smaller than sign
of what this if statement means.
In the second one, it tells you why it's checking that the temperature is, if the temperature
is smaller than 50.
So it is actually providing useful information in that case.
It's telling, so if you are thinking of changing those two lines of code, you know what you're
doing if you read that line of comment.
So it's actually useful in that sense.
OK.
Now in the next part, a couple of ways to not use comments.
These are something that, well, OK, I'll just
say ways to not use comments.
So often you'll see someone comment out
a couple of lines of code.
You don't need that check anymore.
It's for some reason it existed in an old version of the code,
but it really shouldn't be done anymore.
You can just delete those lines of code
and use version control instead.
If you need those lines back or you
need to see what happened there in the previous version,
then you can check out the previous version of the code and actually look at what it was
doing. Whereas in this one, it often happens that then the code around those commented
outlines evolves so much that uncommenting those will just break the code. So, there's
no point in keeping them around in the later version. So, yeah, comments should not be
used instead of version control.
Another one is emulating comment messages. You are telling people why you are making a change,
which could equally well be a comment message. This might actually be slightly more akin to
documentation. You're telling people what the lines of code are doing, but
but this could be written differently to be better documentation and you could use the
comment message to have your name attached to the change and tell people when you did
it and why.
I was a bit hesitant of saying that you shouldn't do this
because sometimes you might end up making a small change
and going back, and then you know you do want to actually
comment the code later, for example.
Yeah, using comments to replace version control
is usually not a good idea.
Okay.
Then there's some examples here of docstrings.
So why should we go into this?
Because we already talked a good bit about this.
Let's just leave this to the level of an example then.
So here are examples
of how you write docstrings in different languages.
So in Python the first one is of course in each of these examples in all of these languages
the first one is a regular comment and it doesn't exactly attach to the function.
It's useful to have when you look at the code but then the second one is a doc string
docstring. That's something that will be a property of the function in a way. You can
extract it from – if you have the function, you can use some command to extract this docstring.
You can use this to build and automatically create API documentation. This is kind of
In each of these languages, this is a point about syntax.
How do you write a doc string versus a comment?
Is that clear?
I think to myself, I don't sound clear.
Maybe I can also add, when it comes to comments, it's mainly meant for the user and the programming
language, the compiler or the interpreter usually skips it. And doc strings are like special comments
which has some sort of standard attached to the programming language. So there is one way to write
it. So it tends to be useful for the user, but there might be a tool which can understand it and
process it in a way when you're writing in code documentation.
Yeah, so something like Doxygen or Sphinx or some other automated thing can pick up
this doc string and build a website that displays all the functions and all of the doc strings
for those functions, whereas the first example is a comment and, well, it doesn't have the
the same structure, it cannot be used in the same way.
So for example, in Julia,
you would write a long multi-line comment
in Markdown format,
and that is understood by the Julia's Markdown library.
Whereas let's say in Python,
there are certain formats of writing the doc strings,
and you'll have headings, which for example,
say, parameters, which refers to the input,
and the returns block, which tells you what the output is.
So there are some standards which dictate this.
And when it comes to Fortran and C++,
it has some things which has, there
are some special keywords, which are specific to Doxygen,
which is widely used for documenting such code,
Fortran and C++ codes.
OK.
I've been babbling on, and we are a bit behind schedule.
We should go get to the Read Me section
and then talk a bit about Markdown
before we get to Sphinx, maybe after the break.
But there is a good question.
Did you write the docstring entirely yourself?
I don't know, of course, who wrote this example,
but when I write code, I have an extension to my editor
that actually fills in a template almost entirely.
So it takes in the parameters and adds in.
So here, for example, in the Python docstring,
there is the temperature that's defined as a float. You could use a tool to extract that
information and write everything except this actual comment line. The temperature in Fahrenheit
is this. Something you would write yourself. There are tools that take care of the syntax.
That is true.
But at the very least, like a single sentence
is also a valid docstring.
So sometimes.
Yeah, yeah, true.
You don't have to list all the parameters, the return values.
OK, so readme files.
Oh, so yeah, OK, so in the readme files section,
we don't really talk much about syntax.
And we have talked about what you need in documentation.
So this is mostly an exercise or a discussion.
So let's quickly think, which one of these do we do?
We probably don't have time for that, multiple.
There is one.
So the first one would be a pure demonstration.
We have had some discussions.
Okay, let's just do the first one
because the other ones would require people
to pick up their own readme files
and then have a discussion probably in the notes,
but with someone.
Okay, so this is some more markdown syntax essentially,
something that you can do in readme files
most environments. Do you have a GitHub account logged in where you can easily create a new
repository or just a readme file that you can show or make edits? I guess it's probably best
just to create a new repository quickly.
So let's say readme demo, and it's me.
And I create one empty readme.
Okay.
And then we edit the readme file.
So there are a couple of effects in the notes.
So let's take a look.
So there is a note, which highlights information, I think not especially strongly, I think it's
a blue box.
Oh, preview probably works for that.
Yeah.
It's a blue box.
Then if you do essentially the same, but write important instead of note, it will be a different
color slightly more visible and warning I think is then red I think important is maybe yellow
oh it's okay um and then yeah then there's import a warning which is yellow
uh sorry warning which is red so this is something like this is meant to draw people's attention of
course. Okay, then let's try these description tags. So this is details and then summary.
So details here, these are like, if you know HTML,
the section goes from the details tag to this end of slash details.
But it contains a summary section.
So details, I guess the idea is that you don't necessarily need to read this part.
This is like extra details.
So it's not showing it by default.
And then when you click on it, you'll see.
So it could be like read more to find out kind of section, yes.
And then there are also batches that you will see in a lot of projects.
So let's just try one.
So the idea here is that a batch is an image you get from some website.
They would usually be at the top, but they show something about the current state of
the project. Actually, when you load the page, it will check a website, and that website
will return this image. It could, for example, depend on whether your tests have passed.
It might show that tests are currently failing.
and can add also hyperlinks to the bench.
Yeah.
Or, yeah.
Right, so the first one, the example,
I think you copied is with a link.
It's with a link, yeah.
Yes, so it has, in parentheses at the end,
it has a link that goes to example.org.
And you can also do the same without a link.
Yes.
Yeah, it looked the same, but then, yeah.
Yes, so those are some tricks
that you can do.
Does anybody know any more good tips and tricks on
or readme files on different systems or different
different repository websites?
Okay, let's do one more at the very bottom of the page.
There's the table of contents.
Oh, oh, sorry. So you're on GitHub. GitHub actually automatically creates a table of
contents for README.md files. You just need to add some sections and then it will have
a table of contents.
Let's try something like installation and then
contribute.
Contributing license, something here.
MIT license, let's say.
Does it show up here?
I don't know.
Maybe we need to commit this.
Yeah, I think you need to commit, and then
to the preview, it doesn't actually
generate the table of contents.
Unsafe changes?
That's strange.
Because in the preview.
OK.
That was probably a previous commit, then, or?
No, this is a new.
OK.
maybe copy everything and go back to the, so that's weird.
Yeah, maybe it's, yeah, okay.
Oh, okay, yeah, you did save.
It did save.
But yeah, this is the library.
Yeah, good.
Okay.
Okay, now we could do the break now
now and then go on to Sphinx.
Yeah.
Could you explain why one wants to use patches?
So yeah, it's mainly, so if you would want to, for example,
show on, have in your read me just a section that says,
all the tests currently pass.
so this version of the program works.
So you could do it as just something that checks a website
that returns whether tests have passed or not.
And that's essentially what we're doing here,
but what it returns is an image instead of a piece of text.
So, when you go to a project, the batches will tell you that this version that's currently in
this master branch, that should work, for example. It can also have other information,
like the digital object identifier. So, it's a link to a Zenodo, for example,
a link to some place that actually stores the object
identifier.
So that DOI is essentially for citing your code,
citing your work.
Another thing is to show the most stable latest
version of the code, which is uploaded in some index
like PyPI, for example, so that you know which
is the current version.
And because often the code on the GitHub
would be a development version.
So we are going to static site generators,
I think, after the break.
But since the section title is writing good README files,
maybe we can go back just mentally for a moment
in your mind, go back to the beginning of this hour.
And we talked about what we would
want to see in good documentation, so
the wish list.
So essentially, if all you have is a README file
and in code documentation, then a good README file
is short, but it includes all of those sections.
It includes a summary of what the code is,
like a top level headline summary
at the very top of the readme file.
This project is for x, and then it
has steps of how to use it, how to reproduce some.
So a tutorial.
This is how you install it.
this is how you run it to reproduce the results in my paper or if it's research software then
probably reproduce my paper is the first thing or a simpler example but something that gets
people running the code and shows them how to use it and then some more detailed description of
of how the whole thing works,
however much detail you want to have there.
And the rest would be in code documentation.
I think that would be a good readme file.
I mean, of course, all of this,
giving the information visually makes it nicer,
makes it quicker.
But as long as the information is there,
that's the most important thing.
Do you have anything to add before we go on break?
No, that sounds good.
Okay, so after the break we'll come back to static site generators and especially Sphinx.
Sphinx, so we will essentially be writing an example documentation website using Sphinx.
So, let's see after the break. Let's do, well, 10 minutes, but it's 57, so let's just do 11.10.
10, is that? That makes sense. So, yeah, see you back at 11.10 or whatever your time zone
is, 10 past the hour. Bye.
you
Okay, hello, welcome back.
So now we're going to static site generators and specifically a Sphinx example.
Oops, I did not scroll back up.
Okay, Sphinx and Markdown.
you can in the how to document your research software you can find this in the sidebar and
okay so let's go so yeah so the idea of this is mainly a demonstration it will be a relatively
long demonstration and the idea is to understand what these static site generators are what they
do and know how to build a documentation website with these text files that you can then
version control. And along the way, we'll create an example of Swing documentation using Markdown.
So, I'm going to assume that you're just watching essentially the demonstration,
but you can also try it yourself and I mean if it's hard to keep up then I would maybe recommend
watching first. Of course the video is also available later but the
notes and the questions are available now. Okay, so let's get into it.
it. So before we start, I will actually move this notes window out of the way to show a
terminal window. Actually resize it a little bit. There we go. And there's some unnecessary
test here that I was doing previously, so let's get rid of that. Okay,
rid of that as well. Okay, so the first thing we do is conda
activate code refinery. This is the environment you may have installed
following the installation instructions for week two.
Okay, so now we have the code refinery environment active.
we'll check the python version this is essentially checking we have python 3.12 is the latest
version and then let's check that we have sphinx build oops build okay and check the version so we
have sphinx build and the so the the notes the lecture materials have relatively older versions
but I think everything should work. We'll figure it out as we go if something
fails. So there should also be a Sphinx quick start.
And yes, it exists. Okay. Finally, we are going to use mist parser.
So what I'm doing here is I'm running some Python code that I write in the terminal. That's Python
minus c and then I'm going to import mistparser. So this checks that the library is there.
If you import something and it doesn't print anything like it didn't, then the library is
there. Okay, so we have everything we need for the demonstration. Now I'm in an empty folder.
It's my CodeRefinery folder, so I'll create a new folder called doc.example, documentation.example,
and go into it, and then run Sphinx Quickstart.
And it will ask me a bunch of questions.
So the first thing, do I want separate source and build directories within the root path?
I will say no.
So it's asking for a project name.
Let's just call it test. I'm not being, I'm not feeling creative right now.
Author's name. That's my name. Project release. So which version of the project is this?
This is 0.1. This is the first one. And project language. Let's keep English as the default
option. Okay. Now it has created a bunch of files. Let's see. There is a underscore build directory.
Underscore often in Python means that you ignore it. You don't print it and
well, you ignore it in a lot of contexts. So, it's something that Python will often not look at.
Same goes for templates and static. Sorry. Okay.
So, I think the most important ones at first are index. This is the main page of your website.
I keep mixing that up, it's in the restructured text format, RST.
So we'll see a little bit of that, but mainly we'll be working with Markdown.
Then there is this conf.py that includes the configuration for the documentation website
and for the building process.
Build is where the actual website will go when you build it.
MIG contains files, images, static files that you don't build every time and that are essentially
served with the website.
If you have done web development, then this is very familiar, but images go there mostly,
some other files.
Templates, you might want to create your own templates for these HTML files, but we probably
will not go to that here.
file is the instructions to actually build the website, which you can essentially just invoke
or make.bat for Windows. Okay, so the main things though that we will be looking at are
index.rst and conv.py. Okay, so let's take a look at index.rst first.
a second. Okay. So what do we see here? Do you see the whole page? This D, does it cut
away? Okay, good. It's cut away a little bit, but not by much. So, yeah. So this contains
a table of contents or defines a table of contents and then it defines some indices
and tables that are a default there. We will not use the indices and tables section.
So let's remove that one.
Then these top four lines here starting with two dots that's a comment.
Sorry, restructured text has this interesting syntax where dot dot means a command, but
then if it doesn't start with or doesn't have this format of a comment with these double
colons at the end, then it's a comment. So this is a comment. And then this section is
title and this is a special pre-structured text command that generates the table of contents.
Okay, so one more change that we will make is
add a section to the table of contents called somefeature.md. So this is a file name
And we don't currently have this file. We'll need to create it in a moment.
It needs to be on the same level as this caption section. Okay, it seems to be.
Okay, let's save this and go back to the command line. And in order to use markdown, we will need
to use this missed parser that we checked that it exists. So let's go to conf.py and make sure
sure that we're using that. This has essentially the information that we added in the
in the auto generation when it was asking questions. And here we have extensions. So
MistParser is an extension that allows us to use markdown files. So we will add it here.
Okay, so here we use MistParser and I think that's the only change we need to make to
the configuration, so let's go back and then we can create this sumfeature.md and add some
contents to it.
So the title, this will also be the title in the table of contents, so it will actually
get it from the file itself and not just the file name or the title will not just be the
file name. There can be subsections.
So we document some useful and exciting functionality.
Let's make a list.
You do need the empty line here for the list to work.
Item one, you can have nested items in lists.
But then you do need the, I don't think you need an empty line here, but the example has
some.
So just to make sure, I will add it.
So if you are currently typing in the notes or looking at the notes, that is also using
Markdown.
It has exactly the same syntax.
This one is using this Mist parser.
There's many flavors of Markdown.
it has some special syntax for some special things,
but mostly it has the same syntax.
OK, so now I exited the file and saved it.
And now we can build the site.
So first, let's check what files we have.
Just what we had before.
Nothing in the folders, in the build folder.
And then let's do Sphinx build dot and so dot is the current folder and that contains
this index.rst and count.py and we will place the results in the underscore build folder.
Okay. And again, let's look at, actually, nope. Okay. So, I was thinking I could make
a list of all the, like a tree structure of what is in each of the subfolders, but it's
only lists of all the names, so let's look directly at the build folder.
We have some new files in the build folder, mainly index.html and then somefeature.html.
are the pages we wrote and then there's some useful extra features that are included in this
page. So okay, let's then go ahead and open this. It should open in this
web browser when I type in the code. So let's see.
So when I type in the command so xtg open and let's go to build and find index.html.
Okay let's open that and here is the whole website. So it includes the sum feature in the table of
contents and then it actually lists the subsection as well and if you click through here you will get
you will see what we wrote it has the list and the main text so it's all there
you can so it has used a default option for what it looks like for the theme of the website
but there's multiple teams to choose from, some extensions that add additional themes.
You can also build your own if you want to, although of course that's more work.
Okay, so let's go back and continue.
Okay, so actually we have finished the first section of the exercise.
and we have one page in the documentation. So
any comments, questions so far? Let's give some time for that
and decide where we go next.
Is there a specific document generator that's used for PyPy?
I think PyPy just takes the README file, actually you need to tell it where the README file
is, and then it renders it on the main page.
So mostly you can add a link to your documentation, whichever way you generate it.
So why do you want the Sphinx page rather than just a readme file, that's a good question.
Mainly because then you can have multiple pages, if I show this again.
So I could have a second feature here, and each of these has their own page.
I only have one feature or one subpage here, but you can have a whole collection of pages
explaining different parts of the software.
So just a readme file is often enough, but if the readme file is way too long and it's
hard to find the information you want, then you can use something to build a more extensive
documentation with multiple pages that's easier to read and it's easier to find the stuff you're
looking for. It does also have a search feature. So if I search here for feature go, I find the
some feature page. I don't really have a lot of pages here so it's found the same
page twice essentially. Someone also added that things can also do API
reference so that's a good point. It's the in code documentation part which we
talked about previously using doc strings to generate documentation. Yes, so
So there's a section here with some more, essentially,
markdown syntax and misspecific syntax.
We could experiment with that.
Or we could actually do the auto-documentation section next.
That might be because people have talked about it.
Maybe we should do that.
And then we go to a different section.
let's do that next. That seems like people are interested in it. Okay, because unfortunately,
we don't have time to go through everything, but if you want to, you can do this Sphinx,
adding more Sphinx content section to learn more about mist syntax and markdown syntax.
so it's adding you can show this again just for a moment so in addition to lists and different
levels of headings and so on or you can add images links to websites and code blocks
so this is of course very useful when you're documenting code
okay
So, but now I will go through this Sphinx auto-documentation section.
So in order to generate auto-documentation, the first thing we need is some Python code
or some code that has in-code documentation.
So let's create that first, and I'll just create it directly in this folder, which is
usually not quite what you would have. You would usually have a separate documentation folder
and a separate code folder but let's keep it simple for now. So we will call this multiply.py
and it will contain a single function called multiply. It takes in a which is a float
and b which is also float and it returns a float.
Okay so this will add the docstring. First let's do the implementation
which it will multiply these two functions so a return a times b.
Okay and then the docstring. So this will be extensive for this function but this is
an example. So, I want an extensive docstring that documents all the parameters and so on.
Okay, so we multiply two numbers that tells you exactly what the function does.
We have a parameter a
which is the first number to multiply.
we have another parameter B
multiply okay and then it returns so return the product of A and B okay
That's probably enough. So I save it and exit and then I will need to add a new file called
api.md markdown file that will actually this will be the main page of the API reference.
So let's give it a title API reference.
then it will contain, oh, this is, yeah, so the module in the demonstration was called
example, but I called it multiply. This doesn't matter. This is just the title of the section
but I want it to be correct, so make it lowercase because it is the name of the module and the
name of the module is lowercase.
Then we add a command that will create this auto-documentation, so three ticks like that
to start a a command section in this mist flavored markdown
and we'll call it eval I mean the command is evaluate rst restructured text
the reason for this is that
that there is an auto-module extension to Sphinx, an auto-documentation extension, that
will actually generate this API documentation, but it needs to be invoked in restructured
text.
But as far as I know, there's still no way of directly invoking it from Markdown.
So let's write some restructured text here, auto module.
And the name of the module was multiply.
Okay.
So now it's looking for a Python module called multiply.
And then I will tell it to document all the members of this function or of this module.
Okay.
It's called multiply with a Y.
Oh, yes, it is.
Yeah.
So that would have caused an error.
Okay.
And I guess I'll fix that one as well.
It is called multiply with a Y here.
Okay.
Then we will need to add something to the configuration to
conf.py.
So we now have this missed parser extension here.
We will also add Sphinx.
It's spelled correctly, yes, .extextensions.autodoc.
So this is included in Sphinx,
but it is not automatically included in the project.
So you need to add it to the configuration here.
Another thing we'll need to do
is a trick to get it to look into this current directory,
because we added the module in the current directory.
So we will add it to the Python path.
I guess we need to import.
Import OS and system.
And then add it to path, insert.
So this gets the current path.
and then adds it to where item looks for modules.
Finally, we'll go to index.rst,
and we have some feature that markdown here in the table of contents,
we will add this API.md, API documentation.
So that's all. Now I need to run sphinx build current folder and the results go to build folder.
And the changes should be visible here. So I need to reload the page probably.
Oh I need to go to the main page. Okay.
What went wrong?
any ideas? I think we are showing the search feature but you can try to open it again.
Oh, I was looking at the search page. Yes, okay. So this is the main page, sorry. So yeah,
so now it has the API reference section and that section contains this multiply module.
so let's go there this shows the multiply module and the multiply module contains a multiply
function and it has a much more nicely structured view of this of the text that I wrote these
parameters and return value okay and you can from this link you can go directly to the multiply
module although I think we are there already oh no sorry this copies a link that um highlights
this section okay yes okay so now sorry there is also a comment on the notes that someone
pointed out that there is a mismarkdown equivalent of writing the same okay so maybe yeah maybe
there yeah maybe let's test that so in the api.markdown instead of evaluating rst here we can do
so this is a section
call author module and then we have multiply here and members.
Okay, let's see.
One thing should be intended.
Sorry?
Should not be intended.
Yeah.
And then there was.
Yeah, that looks good.
We can try that.
Okay, let's reload the page.
Seems to work.
Okay, good.
Okay, that was actually good to know.
I guess we'll update the website with that.
Now let's go to a related but somewhat different topic.
topic. GitHub pages and how to get your documentation easily visible to everyone so that they don't
have to get your code and use things to build it and then look at the website, but rather
that they can just go to a single website and take a look at the documentation.
Okay, so we've been using GitHub for a few things so far, so we'll use GitHub here, but you can also
of course do this, basically the same thing or very similar things on almost all of these,
at least all of these popular repository websites.
Okay so let's just go into it so that we have about 10 minutes to do this that should be
enough. I'm sorry not quite showing the whole because I want to also show where I'm going to
to the GitHub website. Okay, so there is this documentation example project template which
I'm opening here and this will create essentially a copy of this documentation template repository
but it will be my repository. I will call it doc example. Okay, and make it public and that's all.
So let's see what's included here.
Okay, so here we have a license, a README file, we have some example Python code.
No, actually we don't. We just have a README file on this page as well.
Here could be some source code for your project.
and then we have, in the documentation, we have some feature, another feature, and the configuration
file. So we have everything we need to build the documentation locally, but we want to actually
do it automatically on this github page. Okay, just a second because I haven't actually opened
this on the side. Okay, now I have so then so the next step is okay browse to this repository and
I showed you what the contents are so now to get this to happen automatically we need to do
a couple of things. First is we need a recipe or essentially a program that GitHub follows to build
the Sphinx website and that's called an action on GitHub. So we'll create a new file
and it needs to be in .github
and then we can give it whatever name, so documentation.yml, it needs to be a YAML file.
And then I will mainly just copy the workflow file from the lecture notes to this file.
So there are a couple of things that I will look at and possibly change, but mostly this
is just copy paste so I essentially would never write this on my own I would just copy it from
somewhere so the name obviously you want whatever the workflow name is you might want to change that
this will run every time you push to the repository every time there's a new pull request and
and also it can be, you can decide manually to rerun it.
And then well, there's some like system,
it runs on Ubuntu, it does some,
it checks out your repository,
installs Python, installs dependencies.
And here we see missed parser.
And we actually have a theme that we're using,
read-to-docs theme, which is nice.
It's a nice looking theme.
and of course swings and then we run build command and then there's an information on
how to actually deploy it how to get github to actually display it on the github pages
okay so we'll save this file commit changes
okay
So now I wonder if the workflow is actually running.
So I hit this actions here.
Yes.
So we made a new commit so it should run.
It is running.
Okay.
And you can get some more details from here.
So it is following a set of steps here.
It's actually done now.
Okay, let's do it in this order.
So what it has done is it has created a new branch called githubpages or ghpages and that
just contains the website.
So everything needed for the website is there and it will automatically update whenever
you push to the repository.
more important thing we need to actually turn github pages on so i went from here to settings
and then to pages deploy from a branch and then we select github pages here and save
okay and now it should work i think it has
somewhere here it usually tells you what the
URL to your website is. It is always the same so I know it off the top of my head but
of course you might not remember.
Oh well, I usually also add it here so there is this about section and it is actually
it is your username dot github dot io not com but io and then the repository name
doc example okay so it is always the same structure oh okay
use your github pages website is it's an option here so you can it it can automatically fill in
the URL. Okay. So slightly changed interface, but it is still at least as convenient as before.
Okay. So now I have the link here and I don't have to remember what exactly it is.
Okay. And it displays. So this is not exactly what we wrote locally because I copied it from
the template. If we had done exercise two instead of exercise four, then it would look like this.
So it has the documentation,
it has a nice sidebar here because we're using
the read-to-docs theme instead of the default theme,
and then it has the actual contents of the page here.
So this is what we wrote in the example.
So now it is online for everyone to see,
and this works as long as your repository is public.
If you have a private repository,
then I guess you probably wouldn't want it to be displayed here anyway, the documentation.
But then I don't think it's a free feature. But in any case, as long as it's public, this works.
And yeah, you can do the same thing on GitLab. The steps are different,
the interface is different, but the principle is the same.
I think we have a list here of alternatives. GitLab CI and GitLab Pages. Read-to-Docs is a
commonly used hosting alternative. This is separate from these repository websites so it will
need to have access to your repository. It needs to be able to clone it
and then it will build the documentation for you.
So, yeah, and you can, of course, build them manually or create your own workflow to build
them and host them anywhere.
Sorry.
Okay, so here's some steps for migrating to Sphinx if you already have some documentation
to migrate.
I think we should go to the wrap-up section,
to the summary.
Yeah, let's take a look at the notes quickly.
There's some questions that were answered, I think.
There are a couple of them.
Does Sphinx work with GitLab?
Of course it does.
So you can do the same approach using GitLab API.
GitHub CI is essentially the same as GitHub Actions and GitLab Pages is the same as GitHub
Pages essentially.
So you can do essentially the same thing.
And then there is this question, how do you connect or link the Sphinx documentation
you report to your repo on GitHub?
So I think there is a Sphinx setting somewhere in the conf.py, I can't collect it from the
top of my head, but it specifies where the repositories or where do you actually intend
to publish.
So then when you render it, it links to the source.
But this is very specific to the theme.
Am I right, [name]?
Yeah, so there is a setting, if you look at the config file, config.py, I think there's
a setting for the URL somewhere in here.
Oh, I guess not.
I guess you have to add it.
Okay.
Well, then I don't know off the top of my head how to do it exactly.
I wonder if that is what the question was about, though.
I guess the same, it's this edit button which comes up.
Yeah.
So one thing I did just show here is, so in one direction,
it's straightforward.
So it's straightforward to add the link from the GitHub
to these GitHub pages.
Going the other way is less straightforward.
But you can, of course, manually add this is the recommendation.
So you can manually add on the main page a link to your code.
Oh, there is a view page source.
Seems to know where it is.
I wonder, actually, where it got the information.
Yeah, Sphinx actually saves a copy of the.
That's why it comes in the generated version, so it's actually there, but there is actually a way.
You can always add it as text here, the repository is at an URL, so that's always a solution, although not automated.
Okay. Let's go to wrap up. Oh, hosting websites. So, I mean, yeah, I just, I did show you this
very quickly. There is, there's a branch called GitHub pages where it actually pushes the
new version or the most recent version of the documentation. So you can also use GitHub pages
to just directly write HTML and host it there. So if you're using GitHub anyway this is a
straightforward way of hosting a website. Same goes for GitLab and all the other alternatives.
but probably not spend more time on that unfortunately because we don't have that much
and we want to go for lunch in time so yeah just the general wrap-up for documentation
and yeah I guess the most important takeaway is you well you should have documentation
for yourself and for others in your team and for other users outside your team
him. But there is no one right way to do it. Like for a small enough project, a readme
file is enough. You probably want some in code documentation. For a bigger project,
the in code documentation should be really, especially if it's meant to be used by users.
If you're talking about a function that's meant to be used by actual users, then it
should be really well documented. And you should also have some sort of static website
at least for the documentation.
But then there's everything in between, right?
And it's really up to you to decide where you
go from one option to another.
If that readme feels too long, then it probably is too long.
But yeah, I mean, there's no one right way to do it.
So, any final thoughts?
Yeah, and then there's always progressively different ways to improve it, like adding
more user-friendly sections and yeah.
Yeah, of course, whatever decision you take, you're not stuck with it.
can always at least add more. So you can add a static website and copy stuff from the README
to the website and have a nicer structure with a table of contents.
Well, the README does have a table of contents, so you can create one.
But the main thing is that the readme shows all of it at once and you have to scroll or hyperlink
to different sections of it. On a static website you can split it into multiple pages
and it should be easier to read in that sense. Yeah another consideration is like
ask yourself who you are targeting this and is it someone who is new to the
code or is someone who is already into the code and needs to know the
nitty-gritty details so you should have something for both and it can even be a
future maintainer who should know how to publish the code and keep it updated.
To me, that's kind of the minimum. If you want the code to be usable or maintainable
in the future, then you should have at least enough documentation for the future maintainer,
which is likely, it might be you. But still, you will not remember. So, that's kind of
minimum. But then if it's really a big library and you want it to be user-friendly then you
should have a lot more than that. Is anyone rethinking how they're doing documentation
right now? Is anyone not doing documentation but is thinking of how to do it?
You could add your thoughts in the final summary section in the notes, you're very welcome
to do that.
Okay, well, there is a good amount of recap, of course, on the page that I'm showing.
So there's, we talked about readmes and static websites.
We talked about in code documentation
and how API documentation, how those two work together.
And of course, there's several options.
We didn't really talk about how to write tutorials,
but that's also a very good addition.
If you have slightly bigger program,
or just examples of how to run the code.
So yeah that is the general summary of the documentation section. So next we'll talk
about Jupyter but before that let's have a lunch break. So we will see you in one hour
on the hour and yeah, have a good break, find something to eat and see you. Bye. Bye.
you
Okay.
Welcome back, everyone.
Yeah, welcome back. Hope you all had a refreshing break.
And you are ready to continue with Jupiter.
I'm [name].
I'm going to be teaching this lesson together with [name],
which you've already heard earlier today.
We'll go through Jupyter Notebooks.
And yeah, hope you're all ready.
Yeah.
OK, so the idea is this session is, again,
a good number of demonstrations.
We'll look at Jupyter and JupyterLab
and talk about notebooks in general.
So you might already know what notebooks are,
how they are used.
They're a common way of sharing research software
and sharing the results of that software.
So they are a good way of doing,
of implementing reproducibility and collaboration
for usability of code.
Exactly. And if I may add, I mean, for those of you who are already very familiar with
Jupyter notebooks, you might find this very basic. So, [name], if you scroll down a little
bit on this page, so under optional episodes, you'll see some examples of more advanced
Jupyter features, which you may find interesting. So again, if you know a lot about Jupyter,
and you might find that still interesting enough.
But yeah, so, I mean, we'll see relatively basic usage,
but the thing, I think the main take-home message
is more about how would notebooks work,
how they are useful and how they're not useful,
like what are the caveats?
And it also, this is about Jupyter,
we'll be demonstrating with Jupyter,
But these points mostly apply to all other notebook interfaces as well.
Yeah, exactly.
So maybe, I mean, we are going to demonstrate Python codes in this lesson,
but if you're working with other programming languages,
it's still possible to use Jupyter and we'll talk a little bit about that.
And maybe one comment, so let's address the big elephant in the room.
why actually use JupyterLab instead of other codes like Visual Studio Code that we've already touched a bit upon earlier.
So, I would say it's really a matter of preference.
If you are coding in Python, then JupyterLab is fairly common.
You can use it again with other programming languages as well,
but in the end it's really up to you what you have available on your computer. You might even
like to try different tools and see which one you like the most and you find most useful.
Okay, so yeah, I'm not 100% sure this is true. I think I've heard it actually in
code refinery somewhere, so maybe it is. What I've heard is that Jupyter, the name comes from
Julia, Python, and R. So Jupyter definitely supports Julia, Python, and R.
Exactly.
So the kernels exist for those languages, and you can run any general commands in Jupyter,
but it is designed around those languages. Yeah, I mean now there are also kernels available for
Fortran and C and Mathematica, whatever. There are really like more than 100 different kernels
they may use, but some, I mean, Jupyter notebooks may be more useful for Python or in Julia,
if I may choose. But again, there are lots of different options.
Okay. So, what is Jupyter then? And what are notebooks?
So, I'm not sure how visible this is. Well, you don't need to actually see the code,
but which one is easier to follow?
Here's a description
and then example one here
that gives the code to follow this
gives the code
that does runs this example
or here another option where instead of essentially a script
script with some comments. You have some formatted text explaining each of the sections of code.
This is a rhetorical question. I mean, almost certainly, this is easier for most people
to follow, it looks nicer, it has some formatting, and the code is still displayed as code and
runnable as code, but it's interposed with these formatted text blocks that explain what's
happening.
Exactly. I mean, I like a lot the syntax highlighting. Well, now you have it in both examples, but
sometimes you need to do some additional things in order to enable code syntax highlighting in your
regular editor. So JupyterLab does already that for you and I do like that a lot. Also,
I like the fact that you can really add documentation to your code together with the
code lines and also the fact that you can break it a little bit into pieces. It makes it much
much more readable, in my opinion.
So it's great for, definitely for, well,
for shorter scripts or programs.
Okay, so that is the basic idea.
There's, it renders text and then includes your code
and the results of that code in between.
So it's like a notebook.
You write down, actually, I think, is there,
Do we have that image of the notebook?
No.
Oh, well, I mean, if you're doing this old-fashioned way,
you would be looking through a telescope, for example,
and scribbling notes in a notebook,
and then maybe drawing a picture,
and then writing some equations and so on,
like solving the equations as you go.
So this is the same idea.
You can write text, and then you can do computational stuff
and display the results of that computational stuff
in between the text.
It really looks like a notebook and behaves like a notebook.
OK, so this interface, this notebook-like interface
has been used in a lot of other places.
Jupyter doesn't have any sort of exclusive right to it
or anything.
So there's plenty of places that use that, and it really works quite nicely.
I know you can edit Jupyter Notebooks directly in VS Code, so I'm not sure if this means
that or something else.
Yeah.
So you need to install an extension, but it's easy, I would say, or it's well-documented
as well. And in principle you can do the same thing we are doing in this lesson in VS Code.
So it's again a matter of preference and what you have available to you. Because in VS Code
essentially everything works by extensions. Installing another extension is not a problem.
Okay, so there's some case examples here. You can look through these also in your own time.
but for example, is it true here, you can take a look at an existing notebook.
Here is this binder link. So we will actually have a section where we
demonstrate creating a repository and then looking at it through
binder, but here you can quickly take a look once it, not quickly because it takes a while to start
the kernel, but it will install all the requirements from the requirements.txt or
in other languages as environments and runtime.txt. Yeah, and I think this is
yeah, this is actually one of the strengths I see when it comes to working with Jupyter
notebooks, the fact that it's easily shareable to other people. You can make sure that you can
ship your code together with the requirements that you need for that to work and you can
easily show it to someone else and you don't even have to have your own computer with you.
You can just grab it from GitHub or some other place where you have your code. So that
It makes your code very accessible.
Okay, let's check back on that later.
But yeah, so they have actually, they've created these notebooks
and then they have set up a repository on GitHub
so that you can essentially, you can repeat their results
and you can read through their description
while you are repeating those results.
So that's really nice reproducibility.
Here's another example, so you can also launch this in Binder and a gallery of more examples.
There's a lot of these.
So what is Jupyter good for?
What are notebooks good for?
So if you're describing a linear workflow where you want to describe it and at the same
and demonstrate what's going on.
You want to display your results, your research results.
That's a very good showcase or a script that
reproduces your research results.
It's also really good for experimenting.
So you can go and change a piece of a part of the code
and rerun parts of it without having
to do the entire analysis from the beginning.
And yeah, it can also be an interactive development environment for code and visualization and so on.
It can also be, you can now have it running on a server, or you can run a server and then multiple people can edit at the same time, which is really nice.
So yeah, it's great for sharing your code, sharing your workflow, sharing your results,
teaching and so on.
So students can go and change the code and see what happens.
That's also really nice.
Yeah.
I especially like it when producing figures because I always find it takes a lot of time
to find good settings for a figure and the fact that it's so interactive makes it very
useful.
So now this example is done.
There is an index.ipython notebook, which I'm opening.
Yeah, so maybe you can comment a bit how you actually got to this window.
Well, I mean, once I, I mean, I clicked through here and clicked the Binder link, and once
it was done, it actually automatically went into this window.
Okay, so now you are having...
I'm on Binder now.
Okay. So, I mean, yeah, it kind of did it automatically. So, I will open my own local
version of this interface. This is JupyterLab in a moment. But now, I guess the point is to
mainly to display this, to show everybody this notebook about gravitational waves.
So, I'm not going to run anything here, but the results are already there.
So, you can have, there's some titles, some description, and then you can see the data,
the raw data, and how they progressively, they work on the data and get a final result.
So, okay, I'm leaving that.
So this is the first gravitational wave discovery, looking at the original data and the result.
So from the raw data, you can reproduce the plot in the paper, which is really nice.
Okay.
So some pitfalls.
So if you have nonlinear code flow, which basically means calling functions and for loops and
functions calling functions and so on, something complicated,
then Jupyter is probably not going to be very clear.
So I mean, you can still use Jupyter,
and you can define most of the functions
outside in a module that you import.
And I mean, we will do that, I think, in this demonstration.
So the main thing there of course is to explain what the function is doing and have a good
readable name for the function so that people reading the notebook understand what's going
on.
It doesn't really work well with large codebases.
Essentially when you're running one Jupyter notebook it does not interact with another
so you have essentially just one file and everything else you need to import as a module.
Tomorrow we'll actually have an example during the modular code development
lesson on how you actually at some point need to leave the Jupyter notebook interface and move to
something else, be it running in the command line or using other tools which make larger codes.
Yeah. So, for Jupyter notebooks specifically, they are JSON files and they include images
and so on. So, it's not straightforward to write one in a text editor. And of course,
you cannot run the cells in the pure text editor. The text editor has to support running
well, Jupyter notebooks directly. So that can be a limitation.
Notebooks can be version controlled, but if it includes images or big data files,
there are some limitations for version controlling notebooks.
And specifically for Jupyter, JupyterLab, notebooks are not named by default, you need
to remember to name them, otherwise you just have unnamed.ipython notebook, which is unclear.
So yeah, there's a bunch of, there's a bit more pitfalls listed here.
I think the biggest one though is that you can run cells out of order, which does make
development easier so if you change something in the beginning you don't necessarily have to run
all the cells but it means that the state of execution is not clear or the state of your
program is not clear from the text what that you see especially if you while you are developing it
so that can always cause problems if you run if you write a bunch of cells and then you run them
in some random order, you will get weird results. And you can do that.
Okay, so it is a good idea to, before saving your notebook and before sharing any results,
it's a good idea to run all the cells in order and then save, so that when someone else opens
the notebook and tries to run stuff, they will get the same results as you get. And if there's
a problem, you will notice. Okay, so should we go to start? Yeah, and maybe I can comment that,
I mean, this will become a bit clearer during the lesson. It's a bit hard for newcomers to
understand what cells are and so on, but we'll demonstrate this, so bear with us a little bit.
Yeah, we'll come back to it and clarify. Okay, so I will
go to the terminal and start JupyterLab. So first, let's make a new folder,
JupyterLab demo,
and then I am in the CodeRefinery environment, so I have everything installed already,
so I can run the command jupyter lab oh there's many of these okay jupyter lab
now it opened okay I do not want to receive news so it opened automatically in the browser window
that's most recently open it will do whatever your system's default is to open a browser
window. Let's look through the interface. I will get the notes to the side again because I
again forgot to do that. So here we are. JupyterLab is here displaying in the browser.
There is a notebook server that's running essentially the process that's running in
the terminal here and you can see it's printing out some information that I cannot read.
But yeah, that is not so important to understand. So the main focus is the browser interface.
Yeah, so yeah, essentially it's running on my, everything's running on my laptop here,
but yeah this you see you interact with it through the browser um okay so now what do we have here
we have a file manager we don't have any files currently but uh this it lists all the files here
there's also um a list of well i guess list of kernels maybe we'll come back to what that means
There's a tab for git, so if it's a git repository, you will see some information here.
You can initialize a git repository, or clone one into this folder.
Table of contents of the currently open notebook can be useful.
And then extensions, which we will use at some point later.
But I think the first thing to do is to create a notebook.
So let's go create a notebook.
OK, the plus button just creates a new launcher tab here.
So we already have one.
So let's then start a notebook.
OK, and this has no name.
So what would be a better name for this?
Example, demo, demo.
It's always best to rename your notebooks the first thing
you do when you open them.
Who doesn't have lots of, well, who
once the untitled file is on the computer.
Yeah, and it's easy to forget because it doesn't even
ask you for a name by default.
OK, so now we can type stuff into these cells.
So let's start with a markdown cell.
So this is a cell, first of all, and I can type stuff in.
So I'll type some markdown in.
So how do you choose whether it's Markdown or if it's a code cell?
So actually this is currently code, but I'm typing in Markdown.
So I need to go and click through here and select Markdown.
So now it is a Markdown cell.
Okay, I'm not going to repeat the entire example notebook. I think we get it from
a repository later. So I'll just write some random equations here, not random.
I'm not actually sure how to write an equation here, but it doesn't matter that much.
So, dollar signs, in between dollar signs.
Okay.
Okay, I'll just run this.
So to run this, I can press play here and it creates a new cell below.
So when you run a Markdown cell, it renders it.
It displays the result of this Markdown code.
And then I can run Python code or write Python code.
So let's do, what should I do, import a module, import random, and what should I do, random.
Let's get some results from this.
Yeah, I would copy paste from our lesson material.
I would suggest this to our participants as well if they want to play around later on.
So you don't necessarily have to understand everything that is in the code lines but just
the general idea.
Again you can use it later.
We have Markdown cells.
So yeah, there is an example of Markdown cells here and so I'm going to just paste into this
but we have already talked a good bit about Markdown.
Here's again examples of Markdown equations.
understands this format for equations, this format that is, and some more
formatting. So let's run that one. It's nice you can also include figures, I mean
images of any kind. Yeah. That's cool if you want to present something for
others and you just want to show... Well yeah, let's just do a
hello world here that's a good example okay okay so that cell is now a code
cell can you show again I mean how you change well when you create a new cell
it will by default be code so yeah you can again go from here and make it a
markdown cell, or you can make it a code cell.
Yeah, and in this case, our interpreter is Python.
If we use some other extension, then we could
write code in, I don't know, Julia or R,
but right now we are using Python as an interpreter. Yeah, so I started
this from Python, installed it from PyPI,
so it is by default, it's defaulting to Python.
But yeah, you can also have other kernels and choose other languages.
Okay, so is there anything more on this?
Anything else that's important in here?
There's a keyboard shortcuts that are, if you start using notebooks extensively, Jupyter notebooks
extensively, then these are useful shortcuts that you will probably learn sooner or later.
And then we have some tools for debugging, testing, and writing code in notebooks are useful.
Yeah, I only know a couple of shortcuts which I use all the time, and then
then many other things I do by clicking, which is not optimal, but then again, I mean, it's
maybe I don't use JupyterLab enough so that it's super useful. But yeah, creating new
cells and running things, that's good to have shortcuts for.
So, yeah, essentially, I know one shortcut, which is Ctrl-Enter to run a cell.
Yeah.
And maybe it's good to point out that this may be different on different operating systems.
Right.
So, it may be Ctrl-Enter or Shift-Enter.
Yeah, so it's...
If you don't know, you can check the settings you have on JupyterLab, and I think they will
be listed there.
At least here we have command in parenthesis, but here we don't, so I'm not sure which it
is.
But it is either control or command, depending on your system.
Okay.
But I suppose we can move forward.
So in this example, we essentially do what the notebooks are good for.
write a narrative and we get some results and then later we publish this so that everyone
else can view it and run the same code. Okay, so should we explain this or how much should
we explain this? So this is a way of calculating pi, but it is more useful as a demonstration
than it is as an actually fast way of computing pi.
So we're essentially on the computer we're throwing dice on a square and then we are
checking if they land inside the circle or not.
And use the area of the square compared to the area of the circle to figure out what
Pi is. Okay, so we start JupyterLab. We already did that. We created a notebook, which we also did.
And right, okay, so you can also start JupyterLab without automatically opening it in a browser.
and then what you would do to open it in a browser is go to this address, localhost 888.
Yeah, so the moment you add this option, no browser, then you're going to get as an output,
well, among the output lines, a line with a URL that you can then open in your favorite browser.
If you do not specify the no browser option, it's going to take your default browser,
but if you want to have control over the window in which it opens, then that's a good option to use.
Okay, but yeah, let's go in the demo. So the first thing I'll do to make things easier is
copy this iframe display, and this is the address that I'm currently looking at.
So I will basically open this current website in a Jupyter notebook. Let's get rid of this
hello world cell and also this cell oh um i guess that one test will cut let's make it a
code cell yes and then run okay so now we have a browser in jupyter lab in a browser
great and uh start recreating a cell below that so and this is where we were
Okay, so the first thing we do, well, we have a header in Markdown, so let's make a Markdown
cell.
We have a cell, but turn it into a Markdown cell.
So calculating pi using Monte Carlo methods.
Okay.
Yeah, so now you're basically copy pasting from the content of the cell above.
Yes.
Okay, so and here are some the relevant formulas, I think we can put them in the same cell if you don't mind and an image that explains the concept which we had on the website.
Yeah, I would put them in different cells, but that's just my preference.
Okay, we can do that.
I think maybe at the beginning it's better to use different cells and then if you want
to condensate a bit your...
So I made a mistake.
What was the mistake?
I'm asking more the audience.
It's actually like, this is not a very useful error message, I guess.
Well, it looks like, let's see if anyone answers actually in the notes.
Should we give them a minute so that they get the chance to tell us what the mistake is in the notes?
The error message is really not useful.
I guess this is the key.
Syntax error.
Unexpected token.
Right. Yeah, exactly. So someone did tell us it interpreted this as a code cell. So basically,
it's trying to interpret that using Python and that is... Yeah. I don't know why this is the
first error. Is this Python? Okay, fine. The first part is interpreted as comment,
right? Yeah, this is a comment, but then there's this exclamation mark and it's trying to take
darts of that explanation.
Well, okay. For some reason,
this is the first mistake it found.
That's not proper Python code.
Okay. Well, let's turn it into a Markdown cell and try again.
So here's the image.
So we're actually taking this square and then
throwing random coordinates inside the square.
If it is inside the square,
than it is in the area of this quarter of a circle and otherwise it's only in the square.
So the area of the quarter of a circle is, so the area of the quarter of a circle divided
by the area of the circle is pi over four, is that right? I think so, yeah.
Okay, now we are far enough down that I no longer see the examples. I will start
copying from the side, but I think you still know what's going on.
So I will copy some. Now this is supposed to be Python code? Yes, this is Python
code. So what we're doing is importing modules that we need. We need random
because we want random numbers, and then we also want to be plotting things.
So let's import matplotlib, and I run that.
Yes, and if you're working in the code refinery environment,
then you will have matplotlib installed as a dependency.
Yeah, okay, and then we, well, okay, we decide how many points we will create for this test
or for this example, and then we start throwing darts.
So let's, there's a comment first, we'll throw darts, which means we draw two random numbers,
an X coordinate and a Y coordinate.
So first, initial list of points and the number of hits.
Then we do a for loop that just runs the same thing as many
times as the number of points is.
We draw two random numbers, x and y.
So x and y equals random and random.
And then if it is inside the circle,
so if the sum of the squares, which
the distance from the origin is smaller than one, then it's a hit, and we append a point.
The reason for appending these points is to create this plot. So we are keeping track of
the x-coordinate, y-coordinate of the point, and also the color. So inside the circle it's red,
otherwise it's blue. If you cannot follow this, then it's not very critical. Basically, we are
copying different parts of the Python script that we have and interpreting these different cells.
The main point is not exactly what we are doing with the code, but rather how we are explaining
the code and displaying the code. So the code is divided in these cells and we are,
right now we only have these comments here between them, but we could have much more
formatted text and description between them. Yeah, exactly. I mean, I could, in principle,
add a cell at the top of this one where I exemplify more in a markdown cell what I'm
actually achieving or trying to do with these different cells.
So turn it into a markdown cell and then we could have more explanation.
So something like this comment, but much more detail or more formatting at least.
This is especially useful if I'm going to share this later on
with people that don't actually understand Python.
they still know more or less what this code does and what are the different steps.
Yeah. Okay, so yeah, I also added this that adds a blue point when it doesn't hit,
but it doesn't count it as a hit. Okay, and I run it.
And finally, we have another section that plots the results.
So we take the x, y points and colors and we create a plot and show it.
Well, actually this actually finally creates the plot.
So this will actually return a plot and that plot then will be displayed here.
Okay, so it has the points inside the circle and outside the circle.
And then one final step we haven't done yet, we haven't actually calculated the pi.
So, to do that, according to the equation above, you take the fraction of hits to the
whole number of points and multiply by 4.
Okay.
So, pi is 3.14 something, I don't know actually so many digits, but this is fairly close.
It's 3.14 at least, so close enough.
So how can I improve?
You can always rerun and see.
How could I improve on this number, for example?
Oh, you'd make it more accurate?
Yeah.
Increasing the number of points, I guess, is the best thing.
So this ran fairly quickly, so I suppose we can add a zero.
But then, well, now if I just run this, nothing happens.
So at least I need to run everything below.
So what should I do now?
And I could run all of these cells below,
and that will work, right? So now I've made a big plot,
and lots of circles. This is closer, but I don't know if it does.
But, I mean, it's a bit of oscillation
until you get this number converged, so to say.
But really I guess what I would recommend doing, if I add another zero here, is clicking on this
restart kernel and run all cells. So this will run the whole notebook from the beginning to the end.
Yeah and also it's especially useful to also restart the kernel and not just running all
the cells from the top to bottom. In case you have some variables that you have defined but
but then you remove the cells where they were defined.
They may still be kept in the memory
unless you actually restart the kernel.
So restarting means erase all variables from memory
and run the cells in order.
And it's very good practice to do this
before you share your notebook with anyone else.
Yeah, so essentially I consider this now essentially done,
although you could add a lot more story in between here
to actually explain what's going on.
But at least the code is done.
So at this point, it makes sense to rerun the entire code again
from a fresh state.
So what do we get?
What's the point?
We get the plot, so we could send that to someone, or we can send the entire notebook
as a single file to someone.
If they know how to run JupyterLab, then they know what to do with that file, and they can
reproduce everything.
They can even tweak the analysis a bit and then send us back the notebook, or even better,
use version control, and then we can edit it together to get some final result.
Exactly, and that is what we are going to be doing in the following,
see how we can actually version control our notebooks.
Yeah, so the essential point is this is the whole story, this is not just a code,
and this is not just a plot, and also it's not just a description we write in the email,
it contains all of those in one place, so that's a useful thing.
Okay, so here I have the materials open and the next section is notebooks and version control.
Okay, sorry.
Okay, so I'm guessing we will then use version control to put this notebook into version
control and then maybe put it on GitHub or similar.
Exactly, and in order to be able to show different, I mean, sorry, to show the differences among
different plots, then it's very important that we do have some packages, additional
package installed, and that is nbdime, which is a dependency in our code refinery environment,
and that is the reason why we have it, so that we can show these different
changes in the notebooks in a meaningful way. Yeah, so the notebook is stored as a JSON file.
You don't necessarily exactly need to know what that is, but it's a text file. So it is a text
file. You can version it, but let's just take this notebook and open it in a text editor.
So this is what it looks like and mostly it looks fine. It looks like something that would
go to version control, although you probably, maybe you still wouldn't want to look at this
changes in this. You would rather look at changes in this format, but this is the bad part.
This is the image. It's this image and changes here will just be one huge bunch of changes.
That makes it quite unclear. Of course, there's a lot of metadata and all of that.
Looking at changes here might look very unclear and you do want a better interface.
So, should we try the nbdime interface, or do we just look at the comparison?
So, at least I think we should show how we can initialize this directory as a git repository
in JupyterLab.
Yes, so here is JupyterLab again, and here where we have this folder view, we also have
the git section, and I guess we click initialize repository.
Exactly.
So let's see what happens.
Yes, I do.
Okay, there's a checkpoint file. I don't know what that is.
Yeah, so checkpoint is a temporary file that Jupyter Notebook uses,
and I would actually ignore that file.
So there is an option just to click on that and add it to git ignore.
So right click and add to git ignore.
Okay, that's nice.
Yes.
That's convenient.
Okay.
So, I've created a new file, because I didn't have a gitignore file before, and added it
here.
Exactly.
Okay, so that's nice.
We'll close the gitignore file for now.
Okay.
And then what we'll want is to track this change.
Yeah.
To demo.
So, now these are both untracked, so I guess, is it this one?
No.
This one.
Plus.
Button.
And also, I suppose, this one.
yes for an initial commit okay so now we can write our commit message
and the description if we want yeah i'm doing two changes at the same time but
also this is the first commit so it this is the whole repository
okay okay so now there's nothing staged nothing changed nothing untracked it's all there
Okay, so we have our very first commit on the master branch.
Yes.
It may be the main branch for you.
Yeah.
Okay.
Is that all?
I know I should make a change to the notebook.
So what should I change?
I guess like this is a big plot.
There's too many points.
Yeah.
I want to make it smaller before I...
do that. And then rerun the whole thing. You share this with someone else, you don't want
it unnecessarily heavy. Yeah. I could also remove this iframe. Let's do that too. And
I didn't change the code, but still I do want to rerun the whole thing. Yeah. Oops. It's
always a good idea before saving. Yeah, then save and yeah it looks nice. Okay, so now
I have some changes and here is div this file. So what does this look like? Maybe, okay.
So one difference is that the iframe is gone.
Yeah.
So what is this saying?
So it's the difference between your current version
to the right and then the head, which
was your previous commit.
So that is what we are doing.
I wonder if it was wider, would this look better up here?
I don't know.
Yeah, it's always tricky with narrow windows.
Yeah.
OK.
now. And then there's the change in the number of points. Everything else looks roughly the same,
but then there is this plot that has changed.
Yeah. And also the result. Exactly. So the green one is the current version and the red one,
the red labeled one is the one of our previous commit.
Because that is what we are comparing against in this case.
Yeah.
Useful, useful to have this embedime for plots.
Okay.
So now here's the Git interface.
Let's add this.
Reduce the number of points and commit.
Okay.
So yeah, now we're tracking this on Git.
and we have a nice interface for looking at the changes in the files. Okay. There's also
a point here in the notes. Well, first the point about GitHub. So, do I have a GitHub page open?
Not right now. I will open one. So, GitHub has a feature. Oh, no. Not there.
No, it's on your picture, so if you click on your picture.
And then you need to go to Feature Preview and reach Jupyter Notebook diffs.
Yeah, so this is uncommented by default. I mean, no, sorry, it is disabled by default
and then you can activate it if you have reference containing notebooks.
So if you don't have this active, it will look like a diff of the JSON file, which is
not easy to read.
If you have it enabled, then it will use the nbdime to display the difference.
So yeah, it's good to enable this one.
is also here. We have an example in our lesson material. Just higher up. I think it would
be nice to show it. So yeah. Right. Just above the Jupyter notebooks. Notebook diff.
This one. A bit higher up. A bit higher up. Yeah. So I mean you have the link there where
you have this comparison between the two. Okay. No bits, just 35% from the top. Yes. Okay.
So this goes to a GitHub, a comparison of two different notebooks
and they have changed red to orange and changed the size of the plot and then the plot does look
different. Should I demonstrate this with the rich diff off? It might look like this.
If you see a difference between notebooks looking like this and it's hard to read,
Then, this is a big one, loads of image data.
Okay.
Imagine if you had several of these fingers.
Yeah.
So I'm turning it back on.
Okay.
So that's a useful feature.
So you can turn the same thing on in Git on your command line by default or I think this
essentially applies to most places where you use Git as long as it is Git that's actually
opening the difference and displaying the difference.
So you can run this command on the command line and it will use nbdime when you do differences
of notebooks.
I will not demonstrate this, though, because I have nbdime in the code refinery environment,
but it might break git otherwise. So, you need to have nbdime installed for this to work,
and I don't. Okay.
So, yeah, there's also this git-friendly Jupyter notebooks from the nbdev, which is a nice
option, a different way of essentially achieving the same thing, and this JupyterLab extension
that records history. So that's also useful. Okay. Should we, what do you think, should
we have the break before the sharing?
Yeah, I think now it's a good time to have a break, and then we can go into sharing notebooks
and working with Binder just after the break.
So I suggest 10 minutes, and then three past the hour, then we are back with that.
So there was just a question of what is NBDIME, which I guess...
So we showed this difference in Notebooks, but we did say that it's nbdime, but most
of the time it's hidden.
So nbdime is what is actually creating this difference between the Notebooks so that it
looks like this and it looks like this rather than looking like this.
So this is nbdime.
Yeah.
So it's actually a PyPy package,
but in this case, actually, you can also install it
with Conda.
So it's one, a dependency that we have in our environment,
which allows us to show these differences in the plots
in a easy to view way.
Visually nice way of doing the differences.
Okay.
Should we say, well, let's do 10 minutes, so back at four past, or five past?
Why not five past?
11 minutes.
That's fine.
Okay then, let's give them an extra minute.
Yes.
I'll do that.
All right.
So, have a good break.
Bye.
you
I will come back hope you had a good break so anything to bring up in the notes so go
ahead.
Yes I mean we do need a couple of dependencies to make this lesson material work so as we
mentioned we have JupyterLab and also the nbdynmi package that allows us to do the diffs between
different plots and maybe you do not have that installed and then we recommend that you just
just watch this as a demo later on.
Maybe you want to set that up if you work a lot with Python,
and then you can try again on your own.
So essentially, what you might be missing
is jupyterlab-git, and then nbdime.
so you can try installing those later and then redoing the demonstration yourself.
Okay, so the next section is sharing Jupyter notebooks or sharing notebooks.
When have you shared code?
you think of situations where you have had to share some code
so have you shared code to yourself so that you can work on two different computers
that's of course a common issue
have you maybe shared to a larger audience on a website or in some other way
or to a colleague where you possibly both want to make some changes.
So, of course, last week, the whole week, we were talking about Git
and that solves exactly this problem in all of those situations, right?
And nbdime is helpful and you can use Git with Jupyter notebooks.
But one thing that Git doesn't allow you to do is editing the same file at the same time.
You will at least need to be editing on your side offline and then sharing, committing and sharing.
And yeah, there's a bunch of, a number of different ways of sharing these notebooks that might be useful in some of these situations.
So what should we say about this?
So I think there are many different options and different ways to share a notebook and
we have listed the ones we know about in the lesson material.
I would say that my preferred way is putting it on GitHub, but of course you can put it
on other platforms that you prefer. And then I would like to use that in connection to Binder
and share notebooks that way. Yeah. So we'll demonstrate Binder. That's nice.
There's also Notebook Viewer, very similar. And yeah, JupyterLab now does support this
collaborative shared editing, so you can edit the same notebook at the same time.
Yeah, that's also nice. That is useful.
But yeah, for long term, definitely a good repository with Binder is also what I do.
But yeah, there's a bunch of options that you can look through and see what works for you.
Okay. Oh, here's some other options, the commercial options that have free plans.
Okay. But let's go to Binder. So, the first thing, if you want to share your code so that
people can edit it on Binder, I think the first thing you have to do is you have to
share the code. You have to get it online. So, let's do that.
Yeah, so we'll use GitHub to create a repository and track this Jupyter Notebook, yeah.
I guess I will go, oh, there I can create a new repository, okay.
So the idea is that I share my new notebook that I wrote in the last hour.
I will share it to this repository.
Okay.
So what should I call it?
Let's just, this was called, oh, the notebook I just created was called demo.ipythonnotebook.
So.
Yeah.
But you can have binder demo or whatever.
Yeah, bind to demo makes sense, and I'll add a readme file.
I already have a gitignore file in the repository, so I don't want that one.
I'll just use MIT license. I'm not going to keep this for very long, I think, so
adding a license may be a bit extra, but I like to do it.
Okay, so then we upload the files that we already have, the notebook files, if I find here.
Yeah, so we click on that plus button next to code and upload files, because we already have
these saved on our local computers. Otherwise, you can edit it on GitHub as well. Yeah.
Yeah.
OK, then choose files.
And then I have to find source, code refinery, JupyterLab
demo, demo notebook.
It doesn't list the gitignore.
Oh, what is happening?
OK.
It's a hidden file.
Because it starts with a dot, so it's a hidden file.
So here we go.
There's also a dot git and dot.
OK.
Can I upload two files?
I think you can only do one at a time.
I'm not sure.
Yeah.
Let's try.
Okay. Very good.
Upload demo notebook.
Okay.
And now we have the two files, demo notebook and gitignore.
And a pretty empty readme file.
Okay, so what do we need?
Well, what do we need? We need a requirements file, right?
Exactly.
So that Binder knows what packages to install.
So let's create a new file.
And in this case, we'll create a normal text file and not upload.
Okay and at matplotlib the specific version for actually I don't know if this is the version I
have there. I guess in the code refinery environment I assume we have this version
because this is in the nodes but probably the exact version doesn't matter.
Oh, this needs to be called requirements.txt.
Yes, or you can also work with environment.yaml, but then the syntax is a bit different.
Yeah, so if Binder sees a requirements.txt file in the repository, it knows this is Python code,
and then it will install the libraries mentioned in the file.
In an environment of YAML, for example, you can add Python as a dependency or you can add R or whichever you want, as long as it's available on Conda.
And I'll quickly show in the notes, so for Python Jupyter Notebooks, this is what you
need or environment.yaml, but there is also R Markdown, RStudio Notebooks, and there you
have this runtime.txt instead. So otherwise it's similar. There are some different requirements
for the notebook because it would use different plotting libraries, our libraries. Okay.
This is the notebook. This is the github page. Okay, so comment changes.
okay is that all we need i think so it is so now the question is how then how can we
link this to binder or how we can use uh to show this uh this notebook in binder yeah so for that
we need to go to, I'll start opening a new browser, a new tab, and go to mybinder.org.
It's trying to fill in something, another repository, but I'll just go to mybinder.org.
Okay, and then here you can fill in your GitHub repository name or URL.
So, maybe you could show that you can actually work with other platforms.
If you click on the down arrow next to GitHub, yeah, so you can choose from different ones
where you have your notebooks.
There's another ones are nice because you also have a DOI, a digital object identifier,
that may be useful, especially if you want to refer to them in papers.
Yeah, but we'll use GitHub today. Yeah. Yeah, right. Okay. Yes. It's good that you can connect
to a lot of things. Even a general Git repository, you just need to have an HTTP server
at that point to that Git repository. Okay. So, I will use the URL from here.
Let's go to the main page first.
Okay. So then you just copy paste the main page of the repository.
Yeah.
Please make sure that you don't have the branch name.
Yeah. Right. That comes later.
Yeah. Sometimes, especially if you create a new file,
it actually goes to where I just was, which is tree slash main.
And that I think will not work.
Because that is actually defined in the next...
Right.
Yes, you can give a branch name or a tag here or even a commit ID, anything committee, anything
that points to a commit.
By default it will take whatever happens to be the default when you clone it, which is
the main branch.
Yeah, exactly.
Exactly. You can define the default branch, but in our case, it's the main branch on GitHub.
And the head is just the latest commit.
Yeah. And then you can give the path of the notebook file that you want it to open by default.
You can have multiple notebook files, and it will have a file browser.
But in this case, we have a single notebook file, so we want to open it by default.
default. So demo.ipythonnotebook. Okay. And I can launch it from here.
And then also, so exactly. So this URL that you get is very useful actually if you want
to share it with others. And I suggest that we also add it to our readme on the GitHub
repository and that way whomever is going through your code can also see an instance of this.
Let's go back to GitHub and we can edit the readme here.
Yes.
There is also a badge that does the same thing because in the previous session we were talking
about batches a little bit. So this is for Markdown.
So let's add it again. And this is a URL.
And the batch is actually a link that points to the same URL,
but it's an image.
Okay. So now it looks like this. Both of these are links, so it doesn't really matter. They
point to the same thing. This is just, this looks a bit nicer. Well, it depends on what
you prefer. But yeah, so from here you can then directly launch. So I could click the
launch button here, fill in the information, but instead I'm going to click the launch
button from here. There we go. And again, it might take a while. Now, it only has one
dependency to install, but it actually sets up the whole system. Actually, it's pretty
quick. Now, it's installing Matplotlib, so it's pretty far already.
So this will fire up a container on the cloud with the vJupyter
and vJupyterLab and the dependencies
that you have in your requirements file.
It also has a preview of the file here.
Yes, for the impatient ones.
That's very useful that you know.
I just can't run it yet.
Yeah, you know what to expect when it's going to fire up.
OK, so what do we do while we wait?
Am I also too impatient?
Well, we can check the preview.
Yeah, this one.
Yeah.
So it's basically what we had in our local notebook.
Any questions, comments?
So they are all answered, but I mean, of course, the question is when to just have the notebooks
on your own computer and when you actually want to have them on Binder.
And I think that it is always good to have your codes or notebooks saved on some other
platform.
And maybe you are not ready to share them with your colleagues yet, but it's good for
you to reference later on.
And when you are ready to share them with others, then you can do that.
Yeah.
I guess essentially, of course, I've been using these tools for a while, but at this
point I would never really have a code that's at least more than an hour old that's only
on my laptop that feels very insecure, like it might crash at any moment and I might lose
all of that hour of work. So, I will push it to some online repository.
Now, there are options for private repositories.
Many institutions will have their own GitLab instance, for example. So, it's a good option
to check that out. And GitHub does have private repositories, and so does GitLab.
So those are also options.
Or you can run a server and push your changes to that server.
That's always also an option.
Yeah, so now what's opened is a browser window
and the backbone of this is actually the cloud instance that you have on Binder.
It's just that it's using your browser interface to visualize the notebook.
So we can inspect this notebook, and what happens if we make changes to this notebook?
Let's say that one of the collaborators comes, he or she got this URL from you and wants
to make changes to the notebook or just play around, and maybe, I don't know.
So yeah, I mean, it's the big thing in Binder is that you can run the code, first of all.
So I can go through and run the process.
It's somewhere, running somewhere on the cloud, and now I'm just redoing the same thing.
Yeah, so the advantage is that they don't even need to have JupyterLab installed on
their computer.
They can just run it on the cloud.
So that's fun.
went wrong. Something went wrong in the plotting.
Could we miss dependencies?
It's complaining about NumPy infinities somehow. It happens every time though. Oh, so here
There's a deprecated thing.
So I think the dependencies we have installed are conflicting with each other, the matplotlib
and the numpy.
Yeah.
Well, we have not really listed numpy as a dependency, so we would need to go back to
our requirements file and add that.
Yeah.
So we don't really have time to do that, I think.
But this will clearly demonstrate that we did run this on the cloud.
And interestingly, it didn't actually work, but we did get the result in the end.
I can try to add something to the code.
And the advantage, what?
And then run it.
So yeah, it is actually, you can make changes to the code
and it will run the code that you see.
Exactly, and this is not going to change
your original file on GitHub.
So this is all done in this cloud instance
and you may modify it as much as you want.
But if you do want to save changes to this notebook,
how can you do that?
If I do want to save the changes.
I have a great idea and then you want to save it.
It looks like I can do something with GitHub.
I think there is a file.
If you go to file, the top menu and then save as.
Okay.
Or download.
You can also click on download.
Yes.
And that will actually save it.
almost certainly actually downloads the notebook.
Yes.
So that is one way of saving it to your computer.
And then you will still have to open that notebook in an environment which has the dependencies that you need.
Right. So I only get the notebook.
I don't get the environment when I download the notebook.
I mean, really.
Yeah.
This is restore from browser storage.
So actually, I can save it to browser storage, which means it will be saved in this web browser
and then I can get it from there.
So I can save it locally relatively easily.
Then I can reload the page, my changes are gone, but then I can pick up this one and
get the notebook.
The download option is also here.
visible so it downloads the currently visible notebook.
Although if you only store it in the browser storage and then you
clean up your browser data every once in a while then
you are going to lose that.
Yeah so it's not permanent storage. One thing that I would really like actually
is to be able to just save this to a GitHub repository but that's
not here yet. Yeah, so of course you can visit the GitHub repository and you have a link
to that from the top menu and you may clone that repository or fork it to an instance,
is to fork it to a repository in your own GitHub.
So then you can change it and version control it as you need.
OK.
Well, we are running out of time very quickly.
So I think that's all for the Jupyter lesson.
and feedback is already happening in the notes.
So let's go to outro and talk about what's up tomorrow.
Thank you all for all the questions
and sorry we didn't bring all of them up,
but we are very, very glad that you're active.
Yeah, I think this went.
[name]?
Hi, can you hear me?
Now you can hear me.
Yeah, I think this went very well.
Yeah, so hopefully you enjoyed this day.
I guess you saw a lot more ways to use version control
in different things.
So I guess the pattern here is basically
once you're using Git or really any version control,
there's all these other things you can build on top of it.
And tomorrow, this continues.
So it's sort of the capstone days, I guess you could say.
The first lesson is automated testing,
where we see how we can write things in the code,
which will automatically check the code
and see if it works for other,
like see if it works,
like basically find problems automatically,
which is really useful,
especially when we're scientists and stuff
really needs to work.
And the last one is modular code development,
where we'll basically take one of the simple toy problem,
and we'll go through a whole process
of we start with Jupyter, and then
we make it a little bit more modular with functions
and discuss why.
We do a little bit more.
We move to the command line, and so on.
Yeah, and this sort of is a summary of many of these things.
So again, tomorrow is demo-based, so I see one of the feedback things says more hands-on
things would be nice.
Unfortunately, there's so many different variables here, we can't make an exercise
that would work in a short enough time just by answering our things. But we really recommend
you take the afternoon now and go work on some of these different exercises. You can even write your
questions in the notes and we'll keep seeing it by tomorrow at least if not already today when we're
answering it. Or ask your colleagues and so on to be the mentors to do these things.
Is there anything else?
Yeah, okay. Someone's writing in the news there. Yeah, is there anything else? Or should
we call it good?
No, not really. I mean, just mentioning again that if you have another tool which is your
favorite, you can do most of it using that tool. I mean, be it Visual Studio Code or be it
Pluto, I think it is for Julia. I mean, there are many different tools and you don't have to
use our Python examples. You can work with your Fortran code or you can work with a workflow
that you want to develop, so it's very flexible in that sense when it comes to the language that
you're using. Yeah, following up on that, it's like this question number 46 down below,
are there any tutorials for these things? So we're basically inspiring you for what you can look at,
and for most of these tools they have their own tutorials, and probably other tutorials around
you can find and you can, yeah, just look and see what you find that fits your needs and all.
And exactly. So both JupyterLab and Binder have good documentation. So I would, I think
the first thing to do if you don't know something is to Google for it and see what you get and
And then, or ask your colleagues,
but Google is a very good friend most of the times.
Yeah.
Okay.
So should we call the day done?
Is there anything else we need to address here?
I think it's good.
Thank you all for being with us
and thank you for the feedback
and hopefully you're going to join us tomorrow.
Yeah.
OK, sounds good.
See you tomorrow.
Bye.
See you.
Bye-bye.
you