CodeRefinery.org
you
Hello, with more, um, hopefully you can hear us now.
Good morning everyone.
Good morning, everyone.
Yeah, hopefully you have a good day.
I see one report saying [name] is low.
Maybe let's do the proper test.
Order me, [name], [name].
One, two, three, four,
Four.
Five.
Six.
Seven.
Eight.
Nine.
Okay.
Yeah.
I hear [name] a bit lower than.
Now someone says it seems fine.
So if there's no more comments, we can.
Okay.
[name] is still a bit lower, but okay.
I'll see if I can adjust the audio.
in practice, [name] could also go lower, since I won't be around.
Yeah, he can also... I've set it to
maximum input level, so no more gain there.
I guess [name] should go down. Okay, I made it down a bit.
Okay, in the meantime, welcome everyone to the last day.
So I wonder if everyone is as excited as we are.
There's a lot going on here, or a lot going to go on.
And this is really my favorite day.
Back when we did these in person and I saw my first code refinery workshop,
once we got to the automated testing lesson, I was like
Wow.
This is some of the best exercises and demos I had seen.
Unfortunately, since we're in demo mode now,
you won't do that ourselves.
But you will be able to do it yourself later on.
So yeah.
OK.
Yeah, this is actually a good day, right, because you learned a lot about different
topics and it's more like an hands-on thing, which you can see in more like in practice
what's happening and what you should do, which is good.
Yeah.
Everything we have gone through is kind of coming together in these lessons that we will
have today.
Yeah.
Okay, should we talk about the icebreaker ourselves now? So what's the worst bug you've
seen yourself? And I guess you get to choose, is it a life form bug like someone wrote there
or software bug?
I was working on a software system, a messaging system, and where the, what's it called?
The year when you have 366 days in- Yeah, a leap year.
A leap year, yes.
So the algorithm for leap year wasn't fully, hadn't all the complexity with it.
400 wasn't implemented. So, when the messaging system were tested for the year 2000, messages
disappeared. Yeah. Okay.
For me, it was, I was part of a team working on a robotic thing and the robot has six cameras
as a feed of input and everything was working
on Friday evening, went home, be back on Monday morning,
nothing was working.
And it took us two weeks to figure out the situation
because everything was the same.
No one was like, no changes has been made on the code,
no pushes, nothing.
And it was usually like a cloudy place.
And on the weekend it was sunny and because of all the sun,
the cameras were like 0.2 degrees down.
So the feed of input was completely changed
from the robot's perspective and nothing was working.
Like 0.2 degrees.
Exactly, and nothing, yeah.
And we had to go and calibrate the cameras again.
And from that day, we installed AC in that robotic room.
Okay.
Right.
Yeah.
More like a physical bug.
with. Yeah, that's good.
Reality can be harsh.
Yeah.
When I think of this, I think there was
once I was actually teaching a.
Debugging or testing course
and I had duplicate, I got given
a test file for it and there was
like a function and then another
function and then the first function
copy and paste it again. So everyone would try to debug the first function, but there
was a second copy down below that was overriding it and no one noticed. And this is like, well,
how did I do this? It's like such a bad thing. But yeah, like when the code not doing what
I expect because of copying or something.
That's always the worst.
Oh, okay.
Yeah, someone is mentioning about that.
How the strike update and the mess in the airport
and everywhere, the ATMs, banks, and yeah.
That was a serious bug.
Yeah.
I don't know if you noticed that the tweet
of the responsible person or not,
but there was a tweet from the responsible person
who got hired, he made a picture of himself on the first day, and he did a mistake. And
a couple of days after, unfortunately, he got fired. It wasn't, yeah, it was unfortunate.
But that's really a problem in the processes more than any one person. As they say, if
a person can do that, then it's, yeah.
Yeah.
There are some practices that you can follow,
like not do any changes on Friday,
or when no one is on call on these systems.
But again, yeah, it's more about the processes
and you shouldn't blame someone for these kind of things.
Yeah.
It's almost time.
Should we get ready to start, or do
want to answer any more of these questions.
What about the last question? You just got an idea for how to change your code,
how do you make sure it keeps working after the change?
Yeah, lots of if and prints, that's typical.
But does that solve it if it's changing?
Is that more for debugging or for like, how do you use that to keep it working?
Yeah.
A lot of output to verify that the steps taken are correct.
It's like, it's like adding testing, right?
Even outputs, because you're just testing like at some level that what is the expected
output and you're trying to like test it manually.
Right.
So it's like a manual testing thing, and you're looking at it.
OK, yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
OK.
Well, with that said, I guess it is time now.
So maybe I will disappear and leave you to testing.
Is that good?
Anything else you need?
No, I think that's good.
OK.
Then I'll switch to your screen. Yeah. And see you later. See you later. Okay, bye.
Good morning, everyone. I'm [name]. I'm sitting at the Norwegian University of Technology
and Science, where I work in the HPC group. And together with me today, I have [name].
A few words about you, [name]. Yes, good morning, everyone. I was here the other day as well,
and one of the RSA's research software engineers at Aalto University. Happy to be here.
So we'll discuss automated testing from now on in the next two hours.
So you find the lesson under day six.
So my experience, first experience with testing was when I worked in a software development
company in the mid 90s and the process were very fast like we would develop
code 8 to 12 weeks and then there was four weeks of intensive testing before
we shipped the application so we were not exposed to any agile methods at that
time. Those came much later after year 2000. So what's your experience with testing, [name]?
So when I was starting, it was part of the agile and like test-driven development thing.
And so I was familiar with the concept, but when I got hands experience, it was
mainly in the industry experience that I had because sometimes in academia people think that
okay my program is not that long or it's not very complicated so I can maybe get rid of the testing
and forget about that part but when you are doing some production thing it's one of the necessary
things that you had to do before you merge anything into the production. That's right,
So have you experienced any of these problems that you change B and C and
function A doesn't work anymore? I can say all the time.
All the time, yes. Yeah, if it works, I would be more suspicious that, okay,
like, is everything working correctly? Because it shouldn't, but yeah.
Yeah, and writing tests sometimes seems like a long way
to get a solution.
So it's something that we are not always prioritize,
but hopefully we'll see it with today's lesson
is that it can be really useful to have tests
and these can be automated.
Yes, exactly.
I would say that intensive test that you mentioned at the beginning
is still a thing and some
companies still do that, especially for security and to make
sure that their application, their product is robust enough. But adding
automated testing can do a lot in time of
production and in time of software developing for the team.
That's right. And the tests are very good when you get someone else's code. And especially
code that you have written long ago. So, when you change something, you can see if things
breaks or not.
Correct. And also, like, at least for me, sometimes it really helps that when you get
someone else's code, sometimes you don't understand what does a function do. And you look at a
test and you get an idea that okay this function is supposed to do this because you can see
what is the expected result of that specific function for example. Yes that's right.
So today these lessons will discuss a little bit about motivation for tests.
We are given some motivation now but we will go deeper into that. We will then show an example
of where we test locally, just to have a local repository with some code and run tests.
We will then move to GitHub and show how we can have automated testing as a part of
doing pull requests or merges. Then we have a bunch of code where
our tests that we will discuss under test designs before we conclude and come with some
recommendations. Great, let's get into it.
Yeah. We will focus on Python and use PyTest during the day. So there are examples with
other languages, but we will not go into these. We will not demonstrate those. So those who
are interested in R or C++ can take a look for themselves after the lesson.
Okay, so let's see here about the motivation. Untested software can be compared to uncalibrated
detectors yes that's something we know from the laboratory that if you have an instrument or a
detector it should be calibrated with some known sample before being used for experiments and here
Here we have the the statement that software should be treated equally that with tests
we can use software are calibrated and then it shows that it's ready for being used for
an experiment.
There are some horror stories. We have two links to research software stories about research
software where things have gone wrong. So we have this scientist's nightmare that a scientist
had to retract papers because there was some tables
that were mixed.
And there are also this Python bug
where results of an analysis
were different on different operating system
due to how the sorting mechanism of the file system
worked. So the correction of the error was to implement a sort
function that worked equally on across all platforms.
Have you experienced anything like that [name]?
Not on top of my mind but I was thinking maybe we can also
add the CrowdStrike one that someone mentioned in the icebreaker for the future
because it's something that affected a lot of people and everyone has heard of that so yeah.
That's right. So how does a test look? Here we have a Python test, we have a function
called Fahrenheit to Celsius and we have written a test of that function.
So we have a temperature in Fahrenheit and calculate the expected is to calculate the
temperature in Celsius and compare it to an expected result and here we see that we test
for user numerical tests so that we,
so that the results are within the expected tolerance.
We will see an example later where we test
with the user numerical test and use equal signs
and then the test fails though the error is small.
Of course, you can test the whole programs.
So here is an example that we just test an application and get the message that this
is correct.
So what can head tests help you to do? It can preserve expected functionality. You check
that all things don't break. As [name] talked about, it can help users of the code that
you see that you, yeah, verify that the software is installed correctly. But also you see,
the examples of what it should do. When we have installed software on high-performance
computing systems, there is often test suites together with the software, and then we run
this test suite to verify that the installation is correct.
It can help other developers to modify the code, so that you verify that the change that
you made to the code is not breaking anything.
It can manage complexity.
If code is easy to test, it's probably easier to maintain.
So this will also be shown
in a less modular code development.
Okay, so let's have a discussion.
We can have a discussion in the shared document.
Let me add it to them.
So we'll vote in the notes and we'll discuss the results.
So, I added questions and feel free to add some O's and choose as many as you want.
And we'll give you a few minutes to answer the questions.
So what is your personal experience?
Do you like add tests all the time or?
I try to use test-driven development when I write code.
I'm not always sticking to that principle,
but mostly I try to.
So we will give an example of that later, what that is.
But then I'll write the test
before I write the function or class.
Yeah.
So when I'm finished developing, then I have a set of,
ideally, I have a set of tests
and a set of soft functions.
But it's ideally, it's not like that every time.
What about you?
I would try to like add enough tests, I would say,
But by enough, I mean I would try
to go with more complex functions that could go break
and could go wrong in a way when the program gets
more complicated.
And if I'm just having one shorter script,
I would skip doing the testings.
But yeah, I was actually mentioning on the notes
as well that these days, I'm getting
more used to using this generative AI models
to help me to write the tests.
And yeah, the experience was good enough.
Yeah.
Because in the end, it's a program that has some tests.
It's better than a program that doesn't have any.
And the more you add, the more robust your program
would be for the future changes.
And yeah.
Yeah, so let's see, take a look at the responses.
So when is it okay not to add tests?
jupyter or markdown notebook which produces a plot that can be hard to test yeah i think
you will manually verify a plot by looking at it a short obvious correct python script
which you never intend to reuse.
Well, some things that is okay not to test.
If it's very obvious and it's very short,
I think it's very good to add a test really.
What's here, once I heard that someone said,
go to the library and find ungraded thesis.
Under grad thesis, find the word obviously
and you will always find an error.
Okay.
Let's see, is there any questions here
that we should discuss?
How do you recommend people test your code
before publications?
Like to make sure each line of code
is doing what it's supposed to do.
Yeah
And we have some answers for this one, maybe we can address the second question
Which there is no answer yet for it
So the question is I mostly develop software to analyze my experiment or keep track of changes in variables in experiments
I'm not sure how I should incorporate tests when developing this software.
Would it be okay to just have a simpler check, for example, for reference samples and ensures
that it gives the proper results?
I think we will discuss it a bit in this session about a similar thing, like the factorial
functions that we have.
Yes, in the test design session, we will touch upon this. But the short answer is that you
could use mocking for handling external references.
Hm.
Correct.
Yeah.
So my experience was just to add some sample tests
that you want to make sure that the function works correctly.
And also, the rule of thumb is to take care of the,
how should I say, like the edges, like the barriers.
Yeah, right.
Yes.
So that is something to keep in mind.
And I guess if you add those ones, you are good to go.
So, there's some questions about general generative IE.
Are there any generative IE to integrate into your local computer?
Yes.
There, you often, you have to buy a license or a subscription, at least JetBrains editors
have an AI agent incorporated which you can subscribe to?
There are like some other models that you can use.
For example, like Olama supports many of the models
that you can run locally on your machine.
And there are like some IDEs like cursor or even VS code
that you can integrate these AI models
into your development environment.
So you don't have to necessarily buy a subscription,
but usually those ones are more easy and plug and play.
So if you don't afraid to get your hands a bit dirty,
you can try to the open source ones
and integrate it into your local machine, yeah.
Okay, but I guess you have to get your hands dirty.
A bit, nowadays it's more like developed,
I would say like Oldama, for example,
which I can add it here actually in the comments,
has a lot of supported models.
you can use it. Usually the problem is actually with the hardware because your personal laptop
probably doesn't have enough memory or graphical memory to run more fancy models.
But yeah, you can give it a try.
So question four here, how to test code with random inputs. We will
show an example with random numbers in the test design episode.
We will not test, how to test a GUI code, we will not touch upon that.
We are terminal based, we don't do much with the GUI.
Okay so let's go back to the lesson.
So there are a range of types of tests.
What we gave an example of early on was a unit test.
And that's typically what you develop together with your functions unit tests.
Then you have integration tests where you put the parts together and verify that it works.
end-to-end test where you see that the application
produce the expected result.
Regression tests, you collect a portfolio of old errors
and implement tests for these that they are kept out
of the, that they don't reappear in the code.
You have test-driven development, where you write a test first and then development code
to verify that the test works or breaks and then improve the code.
I'll try to give a sample of that under test design.
Continuous integration.
You have a portfolio of tests that you run on GitLab
or GitHub as a part of a merge or a pull request.
That we'll see an example of that.
You have code coverage, that's a report
that tells you which lines are run or tested
and which are not.
And there are different frameworks for running a test.
We use PyTest in these examples that we will show today.
So what should you do?
Well, not every code needs perfect test coverage.
You don't have to go for 100% coverage of the tests.
But a reasonably high coverage is good.
An interactive Jupyter notebook that we saw yesterday is hard to test.
End-to-end test is often easy.
I find it often easy to write tests for functions, to isolate functions and write unit tests.
Add tests of tricky functions, yes. And it's easy to have GitLab,
GitRub run tests. We will show this today.
Where do you start? Well start simple. Here the recommendation is start with an end-to-end
test. I would say that as you get acquainted with the code you should try to add tests
for functions that you after a while understands.
Describe in words,
how you check whether the code still works
and translate the words into scripts
and run these scripts automatically on every code change.
Anything more to add?
Or we go to local testing?
Yeah, sure.
Yeah, we can go to the next section, yeah.
Then we'll start a demonstration
of how we can have a local testing.
So I'll show my terminal here.
So, in this exercise we'll make a simple function and use pytest for testing that function.
I'll make the directory local testing example
and cd into that.
The Python code shows here that we have a function add
and in the same,
Together with the add function we have a test function, test add, which uses the add function.
So I'll copy this code.
a file example.py here we have pasted the code into the file
So I'll save it and I run this with PyTest, PyTest is if you install have installed the
code refinery conda environment, PyTest is a part of the environment and then you can
Just write PyTest example.py,
and we see that the test passed.
I'll have dash v there
for getting for more verbose feedback from PyTest.
Can you run it without the dash v and...
Yeah, I can do that.
Then there is less output it just.
But how does PyTest understand like what functions to test and how does it work?
PyTest looks for a functions that called does start with test underscore and so it understands
that test add is a function that it needs to execute.
Okay, great.
So let's add a bug to the code.
So if we modify add to do some shortcuts
subtraction instead then we have an error in our code
and PyTest will then give us a red warning
minus v example
so here we see that the test fails
And it shows where in the test function that the error pops up.
It runs assert add to command 3, supposed to be equal 5.
But the function returns minus 1. And that's not equal to 5.
the assert fails yes so so we have a question that i'm trying i'm answering on the note but
but I think it's good for everyone to hear.
Like someone asked,
when you have like several functions to test,
is it okay to put your test underscore functions
for testing the functions in a different script
so the original one is easier to read?
Yes, that is a very good thing to do.
Either have a subdirectory tests
where you have the test functions
and then import the functions from the source directory
or have a source directory with separate files
for the functions and the test of the functions.
Yes, thanks.
Okay, let's add a test which checks for being equal
a test which checks for being equal to 0.3
I'll and see how that goes
I'll correct the add function and then we assert for okay oh just add the assert here
So we have a third assert which checks for the addition of 0.1 and 0.2.
And then we see that we get a floating point error or the floating point arithmetic plays
as a puzzle.
we add 0.1 and 0.2 we get 0.3, 0.0, 0, a lot of 0.4 which and the assert is that is not
correct.
Can you can you explain a bit like why it doesn't raise an error like why that where did that
0004 api
Why it does as a given error
Uh, I mean like, uh in the function you're trying to add 0.1 and 0.2
And the results should be 0.2, right but
0.2 but 0.3
Yes, sorry, like like the assert says but
Yes
So where did the 00004
Appears out of nowhere
Where did it appear?
It comes from the presentation of the numbers. So this is how
floating point numbers are represented digitally in the computer.
We don't have a continuum of decimals or numbers. We just have
discrete numbers and adding 0.1, 0.2, then give us 0.3, 0.0, 0.4 which is not equal to
0.3. So we have to test for tolerance, numerical tolerance for this assert to go read through
them. So how do you do that? Let's see. We need to modify the test and run PyTest import
We assert that the add function approximates 0.3.
I think this will do the trick, type pytest-vexample.py, yes and now the test passes.
So there's a link there to what every programmer should know about floating point arithmetic.
so that it gives further details of why this fails happens.
Okay, so this is how we can test locally.
Each test framework has its way of collecting
and running all test functions.
like here it's PyTest selects tests starting with test underscore. Python, Julia, C++ has
better tools for automated tests than Fortran. So then you can use some of those tools for
Fortran as well if you use ISO C bonding. Okay. Any more questions or any more thing to add?
No everything is also answered in the notes. Okay. So we are good to go.
Then we'll start with today's main lesson.
Automatic testing.
How we can do use continuous integration.
So this will show how we can implement automatic testing and each time we push changes to our
repository.
And we will also use the auto-close mechanism when we commit messages.
So what does continuous integration mean in general, because we see like CICD, what does
it mean?
means that you have actions or processes that runs when you do check-in that for every change you do
to the code base that you verify that there is basic functionality or that the basic functionality
is not broken. That the code can be used for whatever purpose it has. And this is a way
to protect the main branch for instance. So that you always know that the main branch
it's a working version of your software. Yes. Okay, yeah. It's something that
in production they follow. So yeah, thanks for explaining.
Yes, so it's very important in agile development because then you can have
have continuous delivery or very short cycles for publishing or shipping your software.
So like Google for instance, they are more or less updating the software, Gmail software
continuously so you never know you don't you don't relate to any new versions of the software
really you just use the code and you use the application and and it changes us that's from
can change from time to time but you're not you're not involved in selecting the specific versions
Okay. So I'll create a code repository on GitHub. And then I'll add some code to that
repository. I will then set up a test with GitHub Actions and see how it plays out.
We'll introduce a bug in the repository and then create an issue and you will
helping me fixing the bug and we will see and how when you make all requests how the
test is then executed and to verify that your changes is correct yeah and yeah as a last
step will also introduce more tests to increase the coverage of the soft or of the function.
Yeah so I would say this is a very interesting section and this is the basics of what's happened
in collaboration when you are collaborating with others and you want to make sure that
the latest version of your code is working and still you are working on fixing a bug
or adding a new feature or adding some new experiments
to the code.
And yeah, this is the basics of what's happening
actually both in industry and academia
when you're collaborating with others.
Yes.
So yeah, let's go.
So here I'll, here's my repost, no, here's my namespace.
So I'll create a new repository
called example-ci. It's available. This is an example of continuous integration. It's
it's public. I read my file and add Python gitignore MIT license. Then I create my repository.
I'll clone the repository to my local computer, git clone and git string, so I'm cloning the
example CI. I step into the subdirectory example.CI. So what more should I do then? I'll add some
code. Let's see here. So I'll add a file functions.py which then contains four functions. Add, substring,
Subtract, multiply and convert Fahrenheit to Celsius.
Copy.
Vim-function.py.
There I added the base of the function and I save the file.
I'll do git status, so I'm on branch main,
I'll commit this to do the main branch and then push it.
Git add function.py.
Git commit message, add functions.
Git status, so I committed my changes and I have a commit add functions, git push origin
domain. So let's push the changes to my repository. So this should be now updated with function.
I added the function, but I haven't added the test function. So I need to go back and
and add that from that file as well vim test function.py
So here is the test function.
I'll copy it.
Right, right, quit, git status,
git add test function
it's staged git commit then
add test
oops
git graph, I add a test, git push origin, main, so now both test function and add function
is present yes so I'll test the that the test function works locally so I can just write
pytest and then pytest will look for the file called test underscore and then there is an
error because there's no module named functions I'll
give this function so it's called from functions import add subtract and multiply and I've
call it function so I need to rename the function. That means git move function to functions.py.
git status. If I now run PyTest. It works, it's green. So I need to commit this change.
let's commit rename function functions file
like it graph
so this become they can have more more commits than the original plan but we'll see
So git push origin main.
So now we should be set with the tests and the functions on GitHub.
next will enable automated testing. Yes. So here functions are no function are
We will now select the actions menu, it is on the upper line here.
here under github actions there is a
large set of actions but we will select the python application
where you create a test for python application
configure
And we see here now that in the example-ci repository there's created a subdirectory
called github with another subdirectory called workflows and here we have a yaml file that
we will edit so we can enable actions and this
dot github repository subdirectory was created when i pressed configure so if
you look at the repository as it was
called alone we see that there is no dot github there
Okay, so I'll copy the YAML file from the instructions, copy and I'll paste them at
the end here, then I'll remove the original code.
And so let's see here what it says.
It's given the name test.
It's runs on push and pull requests.
And here's the job description, it runs on the Ubuntu latest, the Linux Ubuntu version.
And the steps taken are checkout, it's a setup of a Python environment, it runs installation
of python packages. Then it does lint with flake 8.
Flake 8 is a python package or python application that checks for python software errors or
and python formatting. So it gives errors if there's syntax errors or deformatting of
And the Python code is not according to the standard.
This is called the linting.
After the tool lint, which was used, which was developed for C code.
After the linting, we'll run PyTest, and PyTest will also produce a coverage report, I guess.
Yes, so before you did the commit change, I just want to add something that this workflow
when we are using line 19 that you're using Ubuntu latest, it means we are creating some
hooks on every changes, as you can see on line 8 and line 10, on every changes for push
and pull request on main, there would something happening on GitHub side. And the things that
happening is it actually create a container with the latest Ubuntu so the OS is running
and it do the testing that we mentioned that. So all the things are happening on the GitHub side,
not on your computer. Yeah, please go ahead, sorry. Yeah, that's right. So
So commit the changes, create python-hub.yaml.
I'll keep that.
So I'll commit directly to the main branch.
And now let's see what's happened.
If we then go to actions,
we see there's a workflow running
and it's a kind of yellow or red there it turns to green
so if i if i go into this
uh yeah there i see that this is triggered while
it the push with the commit that i just wrote create the python app.yaml
and here we can go in and see the steps that are taken
there's the setup of the job
and there's the checkout of the source code
There's the setup of the Python environment,
installing dependencies.
That's pip and flake eight, among other things.
So there's a long list of dependencies that are installed.
In this case, I didn't have a requirements.txt file,
but if that was present,
it could then install the requirements.txt file.
So, it does the linting, check here, we see that my code is not up to the Python standard,
so I have too many blank lines, and there are functions that are imported, but unused, that's
part of the test function, so we get these error numbers from flake 8, so I have a job
to do to improve this code then.
Yes, and then we have the test itself.
It runs test function.py and there is no error message.
The test works fine.
And after the Py test,
then there is the tidying up of the job,
cleaning up Python.
post-run actions and the job is completed and the container goes out of scope or are
terminated. So this is executed on the check-in and then the results are present until there
there is a new pull request or check-in.
So it doesn't run continuously,
it just runs when there's an action
or those actions that,
under those actions that we have specified.
Okay, I think we'll take a break now.
Yes.
10 minutes break and then we'll continue
with the introducing errors and see how those are handled.
If we then comments at the 10, at 10 over.
0.8.
0.8, yeah, we'll be back at 0.8, yeah.
Yes.
Yeah, thanks.
See you.
you
Hi, and welcome back.
Welcome back.
Okay, so we have a running action on GitHub. And the tests are green.
So what happens when there is a bug or error in our code?
Yes. Let's see.
I'll update my local repository, since I have made a commit on GitHub, I committed the action
file. And this is not on my local repository. So I'll do git pull origin. I'll first do
the Git graph. So my last commit was rename functions file. And then I do git pull origin
file, my main. And I get the last commit from GitHub. And then Git graph shows that the
I've added the create Python app yaml file and if I inspect my subdirectory I'll see
that now I have the github.github subdirectory locally as well.
Okay so what's the next step?
Yep, so I'll uncomment the code in the test functions and push it to github.
test function.py. So we'll now add the test of the subtract function. And we'll see how
This goes, git status, we have the test function,
git add test function of i, git status,
git commits, commits message, add test of subtract.
And then I'll push, I'll search for the latest push command, git push origin main.
And there we go.
So I push directly to the main branch on GitHub.
And let's see what happens on actions now.
So, the GitHub has updated with the latest commit
and here's something pending.
What's happening here?
All checks have failed it tells.
Then we can go into details.
I could also log on into actions and see the same thing,
but the code view gives me the same information.
Details.
And we see that the test with, our test now fails.
This test, I also get an email to my mailbox
my mailbox that tells that the continuous integration job now fails.
So GitHub do take actively steps to inform me that there is errors.
Okay.
So I'll create a issue.
First issue, subtract test.
Test of subtract fails.
There is an error.
Error somewhere
Submit issue
So then
So now
We have a broken software what do we do next
Can you help me uh, yeah, so this is actually a very good demonstration of how collaboration works so when usually there's a
uh
There is a bug in open source software. Other people collaborating on that software can come and help and we want to demonstrate that.
So, uh, let me maybe I can share my screen and I'll stop the share. Yeah, sure.
And try to try to demonstrate that.
that. Yes, give me a second and sharing. Yes, let me just resize this one. I hope now you
I can see my Chrome browser without any issue.
Okay.
This is good.
So let me first find the repository that you created.
So this is the repository and I go and see, okay,
there is an active issue.
I will go and check and see, yeah,
there's a problem with the subtraction test,
and probably the subtraction function that it fails the test.
So usually when I want to contribute this,
contribute to solve this issue or add a feature,
I would go and, because this repository is not mine,
so I would go and fork the repository,
which means some kind of cloning the repository online
getting a new branch of it and then try to work it on my own. So I would go and create a fork out of
it. Oh no, this is the branches. To get a fork I would go here with the forks or maybe here to get
a new fork and then I'm the owner I would let it let it the example ci the name and everything is
fine so I would create the fork so everything would be copied into my namespace and my github
account and you can see this is under my name now and it also mentions that it has been forked
from the original repository.
It also shows you some banners
that is it updated with the original repository or not.
So if I try to change it and add some commits,
this would be changed.
And also if the original repository changes,
this would be changes as well.
Sometimes I can sync it with the original fork
without any issues,
but it depends on what kind of files I have changed
and what kind of commits that I have.
Sometimes there are some conflicts that you have to solve.
But yeah, let's maybe continue from here.
So I would go ahead and fork this repository
on my local computer.
Let's go to my local computer and let me,
is the font okay?
Yeah, the font is okay.
Okay, so I would clone this repository
and I would go to the, this is my VS code
And you can see that the repository has been cloned here.
So I know there is a problem probably in the function.
So I would try to go and see either the problem is
with the function, with the test, which the test is OK.
So probably the problem is not coming from the test.
I would go to the functions file and try
to see if I can handle the bug or not.
And I see that this is the bug coming from.
So I would try to fix the bug, right?
I want to fix the bug.
But usually the best practice to do this
is to create a branch
and then try to do all the commits there.
So I would go back to my terminal
and I would do a branch, for example,
let's call, usually to start with a name
or username or something
and then fix subtraction bug.
You're not in the Git repository.
Oh, yes.
Sorry, I have to go to the Git repository first
and then try to do it again.
So I would create a new branch called my username
and then name of the branch.
So you can see that I'm currently in the new branch.
If you're using VS Code,
you can also see it here that I'm on the new branch.
So in the new branch,
I would go ahead and fix this issue and save the file.
So if I now get a get a status,
you can see in the new branch,
this function has been changed.
So I would go ahead and add this file, so the functions,
and then create a commit.
Usually, when you are fixing a bug,
it's a good practice to mention the issue number
that you fixed.
So when you are trying to merge it
and the owner wants to look at the pull request,
it has a better understanding of how it results.
But you can also mention it in the description.
But let me mention the issue number here as well.
So fix these subtraction bug on address on issue number one.
Oh, I forgot the message command, the message.
black okay so now everything is
good and I can go with uh push it from origin
to origin from the branch which was fix subtraction
back
OK, great.
So if I go to the GitHub, you can see, if I refresh the page,
you can see that there is a new branch has been created,
which I pushed from my local machine.
And if I go to that branch, you can
see that this branch is one commit ahead,
as I described before, from the original fork.
And here you can see that we can create a pull request.
And the pull request is to merge everything that we changed
back to the original fork that we got
from the original repository, which is a great thing.
So we would go with compare and pull request.
From GitHub site, there would be an automated,
not testing, but automatic checkup.
So if this commit and if this branch is easy to merge
and you can see that it's very easy to merge because I only replace a file, but sometimes it's very hard.
And you have to do a lot of different changes and solve the conflicts before the merge can happen.
But GitHub would also help you with that and raise an issue that it raised an error that if it is not easy to merge.
I think you need to have fixes in the in the description there, but I'm not sure it is enough to have it in the title.
Yeah, I would add a description as well, that in this pull request, I solve the subtraction
error address in issue number one.
I think you need to add your word fixes.
There are other words as well, but I don't think...
The fixes, what do you mean?
That it needs the word fixes, for instance.
There are other word fixes as well.
Okay, here you mean.
No, I mean in front of the pull request.
No, in front of the hash number one there,
addressed in the description,
In the body, not in the title, but in the body.
Okay.
Add fixes in front of the hash number one there.
Okay, so.
There, yes.
You mean here?
Yes.
So you mean fixes, right?
Like this, yes.
Okay.
So, okay.
So this pull request, I would say, this pull request fixes,
let me rephrase it, fixes number one on the subtraction error.
Yeah, something like it, yes.
And the error was caused from a bug in the function.
So actions.py file, let me also add it like this, so it will be, okay.
So I had it add a description, it's when you are usually contributing to an open source
repository, there are some guidelines on how to contribute, you have to go read that because
usually there are like some things that you have to check and you have to mention the
number of the issues or the files that you had changed and you have to follow the guidelines.
we don't have a guideline here and just want to demonstrate.
So I would create the pull request.
What it does, if we go back to
the original repository that has been created from V-Run,
you can see there is a tab on pull requests,
and my pull request has been created here with
the title and also with the description.
This has not been merged,
so the original repository has not changed yet.
You can see the pull request is still open.
You can create pull requests on a draft mode to
showcase that I'm working on an issue,
which is also a good practice.
I'm still waiting for the original repository owner or
for other editors that the original repository should
had to review the case, and if they got an approval,
they can manage it.
Also, they can add some comments and everything,
but I think [name] can showcase that.
So maybe it's good to give the screen back to you,
and you can continue from here.
Yes.
OK, so let me stop sharing, and we can continue.
So there, now, let's look at the state of the, my repository.
So now I have a pull request, listed on the pull request, picks this abstraction bug addressed
in the number one.
So let's have a look at what this is.
And here, now you see
[name] have written a pull request,
stating that it fixes the error.
And
GitHub have now queued up a workflow
waiting for,
waiting for being run and this is our test of the of the software so I'll approve this
and then the tests are running so it's yellow while it builds up the container and the environment
and we can go to details and see
So something, yes, so it doesn't, and there's a change here in GitHub as a part of the pull
requested the coverage report is not created so this gives an error.
So that was a little bit surprising but we'll go back.
So the check did fail due to creating of the coverage report.
Yeah.
What was that?
Yeah, I'm not sure whether there's permission we think
that or why it's fails as a part of the coverage report.
you know, part of the, what does it say here?
Okay.
For HTTP error, we search not accessible.
Okay, then we'll learn something new today as well.
So, it was supposed to run and be green, but that will, it will turn green when I'll merge.
Confirm the merge.
Um, yeah, maybe something that it's also good to showcase is, like, if you go to the files changed and tab, you can see all of the changes that has been made and you can also make comments before approving and, like, add, uh, maybe some comments to change some of the functions or some of the changes that there has been made so you can comment that there isn't like a more like a collaborative way before making the approval.
making the approval.
That's right.
I'll I didn't do that now it's completely fine.
How's actions now?
So the merge goes green.
So the build now works.
I think the coverage error was coming from the fact that
it was trying to create it on my repo probably
or something like that.
And that was the, it was a person.
Which is strange, really.
Yeah.
Okay.
Any questions to what we have done so far?
No, the notes are good.
So yeah, I think everything is good to go.
So we accepted the pull requests.
So now we'll increase the coverage.
So I'll write a test for the multiply function
and create a pull request.
So we'll see how of this. Let's see if I can find a coverage report.
Action.
I'll pull requests.
So here.
No there's no coverage reporting either here.
No, but if you go to the workflow and see the actions here on the build, you can see
the coverage later.
Coverage.
Yes.
So if you open the result, yeah, and if you go to the details of the build, and it create
coverage if you open it.
But I don't get the coverage XML.
Okay.
Okay, let's see, you search, because I, okay, let me see for the failed build one. I can see the coverage, but it doesn't create the, the file.
Oh, okay. So, for example, if you open the failed one, we can see that it, it mentions the coverage of the, yeah.
Yeah, but it just gives the error message.
If on line 14, if you open the results.
Okay.
Yes.
Results.
Yeah.
So you can see.
Yeah, there it gives a report of coverage of 88%.
We will see with the next pull request that I get the coverage as a part of the pull request
when the test has been executed.
Okay.
So let's go back to the code.
I'll implement the,
I'll do git pull.
So we get the latest changes, git graph.
And then I'll add a test of the multiply function to the test function.
If testMultiply
assertMultiply
5 and 5 equal 25
Save
Git starters, git add test function, git commit minus m, add, multiply, git graph, oh, I should
have should have made this in a branch really. Oh it's fine. Yeah but now it will commit
directly to git push, see if we get the, can we get a new test, new.
Mm-hmm
So it failed
So I get a chance to correct this
Okay
We are also a bit behind the schedule. So we have to wrap this up, but maybe you can see uh, where it fell and
So why did it fail?
Uh, it was coming from the lint with flocate
Okay, yeah, there's an l missing
Did check out must be
Um
Then I created a branch, test function.py, multiply.
That's what's there.
Yeah.
git add text function, git status, git commit mysql,
It says git push setup stream origin [name]fix, so I'll copy that and paste it in here.
Like this, and now we'll have, now we can compare and write pull requests.
So that was my intention.
pull requests so we say
this branch has no conflicts but it's running
the action and we will see that we get a coverage report as a part of the pull
requests yeah here it is yes and if you remember
from the details that we looked at we had a coverage report of 88 percent
before and now we have a overall coverage of 94 percent
so we improved the coverage of the of the code
so i'll merge this confirm merge
Yes, so this was automated testing. It can really protect your code from being
broken. And as a code, but of course, as a code grows
and you add more and more tests,
these actions will take more and more time.
We said, here's a simple test
and it takes a while to complete.
So if you get a large portfolio of tests,
Apple request or check-in
will then take several minutes to complete.
Yeah, so you have to structure balance
between how many tests you add to these actions.
Yes, I hope you find it interesting
and you can then redo the example
from there as an exercise after the lesson.
Anything more to add?
No, everything was good.
Maybe we can start the next section to be a bit, because we're a bit on behind the schedule.
Yeah.
We showed Python, but this can be done for other languages as well.
Great.
Yeah.
Then we'll go to test design.
And there's a lot of examples here.
So we'll dive into different tests and see how these are.
So let's get started with the first one.
We have the function factorial.
How would you test this one, [name]?
So it was also a bit, I think that the question was also asked in the beginning of the session
that if we have a function that it depends on the input what you want to do and what
do usually is to create some test cases, and usually take care of the edges or the barriers.
For example, if the number is too large or something like that.
Yeah, but for this I would like add some small number, some medium number probably,
and a large number to see if the function is working.
Well, here the numbers grow rapidly with small input. So you can easily get an
an overflow or.
Yes.
So let's see, we'll take a look at the solution here.
So here it's tested for zero, one and two.
There are no large values, simple values really.
And as I said, this is a pure function.
So it has, it's quite easy to test it.
In Python, Python has the pipe long.
So if you get really, you can get really large,
test really large numbers with Python.
The challenge is really to calculate a large factorial and have it ready for inserting
into a test.
Design a test for a function that receives two strings and returns a number.
This seems simple as well.
You can really add the documentation here as a test.
So if you step out of,
Step into a new subdirectory.
So we could create a function log pi, in the insert code, and in test function log pi.
It doesn't be from function import and the name of the function was countered occurrence.
There is thing.
There are two double R's in the occurrence.
So define test count word. Assert. And if we then say count word of currents in string
1, 2, 1, 2, 3, 4 and the argument, second argument would be 1, then assert that this
This is equal number two, take a join there, write quit, our PyTests work now.
So yes.
Yes, then we'd have tested the docstring really.
Under solutions, there are other strings
which could add this test to see how it may phase
with several, this is like, I don't know, border case.
And here, we get an error. So, either we have to change the test, or we have to change the
function. So, we are not sure here what's wrong here, whether we our specification of
the function is wrong or whether the test is wrong.
But the function returns zero and we have expected it to return one.
Okay, here is a design, something similar, we count the words occurrences in a file.
But here we're getting a more complex function, which are doing several things.
So one approach here could be that we didn't implement the opening of the file as a part
of the counting function.
But we rather used, had the file opening in a function for itself.
Which then could return a data object, like a list for instance.
And then we use the count word occurrence in string from the previous example instead.
As it is very similar to the previous example that we did, maybe it's better to bypass it
and then talk about how do we want to check if there is a dependency for the next one.
And we also have the question about that earlier today.
Exactly.
So here we have an external dependency
from reactor input to import max underscore temperature.
And how would you approach this function?
So usually when it's dependent on an external factor,
it can come in from a physical board or another library.
If that specific number is not available or it changes,
it's usually good to mark it,
which means you give it an arbitrary number and
then try it with that arbitrary number
instead of getting the actual number from the external source.
Yes, so let's see what's written under the solution here.
Here it says describes monkey patching that you then set the temperature from the external
to some, to a specific value.
Mocking is also doing the same thing.
Yes.
I'll skip the next,
I'll skip the design five
and we'll go to test-driven development.
I'll think I'll spend five minutes on that
And then, and we'll also touch upon testing randomness.
Okay.
So, in test-driven development,
you develop the test first.
So here, we have a function that takes an integer
and it returns this on three and five on bus.
And multiples of five returns bus.
And for arguments that are multiples of both three
and five returns fizz and bus together.
Fails in case of non-integral arguments
or arguments are negative or arguments zero or negative
or otherwise it returns the integral itself.
So that's the specification of the
So, I would then go on and create the, create the test first, test function.py.
So I'll write from function import.
This doesn't exist yet, but I'll write my function files as functions, I'll write import
FizzBuzz and then the final test of FizzBuzz
assert FizzBuzz3 equals Fizz
assert this bus five equal bus. So then I've written a simple test. So if I run this of
course now I'll get an error. So import the import statement false. So this is getting
Getting red, getting the state red is called under test tree development.
But I want to get to the state of green.
And I'll do that as fast as possible.
So how do I do that?
So I'll implement FizzBuzz in the function.py, FizzBuzz, and as a simple step, I'll just say
if and there's a number here should be number
if
if number number equals three return
Return this, else if number equal five, oops, return bus.
else return number okay so if I run pytest now it was wrong in the function
Yeah, with the else, yeah.
There was a column missing.
I test.
So now, the time has gotten to the state green.
But we know that the function that I've written is too simple for the specification.
But it's a first iteration of the function relayed.
So, as soon as I add more tests to the test function now, this function I have written
will fail. That's okay. Then I'll go another iteration and implement a new, a more complex
for fizzbuzz function. But I have started and I have got my feel of how the function
is used, how it's called, what the arguments are, so it's the an easy first step really.
Yes, so the solution then points to a complex solution which raises exceptions and
can enhance all border cases. So then after several iterations, I will gradually reach
something similar. Okay. I think that's what we will have time
for during test design, that will touch upon randomness. How would you test randomness?
So with the randomness, because the random generators are working with a seed, it's usually
good to set the seed and based on that seed you would get, it's not random anymore your program
because the seed is fixed, so the randomness would be some statistic again, like static,
so you don't have any randomness anymore.
So for testing a function that has some randomness,
set the seed, and then you have a static number,
and it would be very similar to what we already covered.
Yes.
So here there's two functions, rollDice and Yatsy.
And we will see that when you test these functions,
you set the random seed.
One and then you get a series of numbers that are equal each time.
Okay, I think we'll go to the checkout and really over to some conclusions and recommendations.
Yes. Learn one test framework well enough for the basics. For Python it's PyTest is
really simple. You have unit tests as well, but it's more complex. And that's my experience.
and use the good tools that exists.
Start with some basics, some simple things to test.
I think it's a good thing to automate these tests.
So add them to your Git repository.
Strike a healthy balance between unit tests
and integration tests.
As you grow your code, then tests should also should increase.
And as the example with test development, the test development cycle shows that you
can you can add tests as you add new functionality.
So when you fix a bug, it's a good thing to add a test against the bug.
So you get a volume of regression tests that can be used to verify your code.
And use code coverage to analyze what part of the code that are not executed.
Yes.
Yeah.
I mean, if you make your code easier to test, it becomes also more modular.
And we'll see in the next lesson how to create code more modular.
Ways to start.
Perfect is the enemy of good.
So just start for something that's good, good enough.
There's always probably something you can isolate a test as a part of a function or
split the function in more in two or if you have data analysis or simulation of some sort
end-to-end tests with sample data and use local and testing frameworks and GitHub actions?
Yeah, I think one of the takeaways here is, as you said, the perfect is
the enemy of good. So doing a test-driven development and adding like a
test for all of your functions and getting a 100% test coverage can be a bit overwhelming,
but a code that has some tests is better than a code that doesn't have any. So start adding
tests to your most important functions and the things that really could go wrong, and
then in the future maybe you would get the habits of adding more tests and more tests.
Yes, so that was automated testing. Now we'll go for lunch and we will resume in an hour.
Okay.
Yes.
Thanks everyone for joining and yeah, see you after lunch break.
Yeah, bye bye.
Bye bye.
you
Hello, we are back and hopefully you can hear us out there.
Should we do an audio test?
One.
Yes.
Two.
Three.
Four.
Five.
Six.
Okay, let us know if the audio sounds okay.
So we are resuming now for the last lesson of the day with what is called modular code
development.
So this is sort of an example that puts together a lot of the topics of the workshop.
We'll see us using GIT and who knows, maybe some testing, but in particular, how we evolve
some code from being this small, what do you say, how we would actually evolve some code
from being this small, how do I say this?
have prepared a small script doing some typical scientific data analysis for us.
Yeah, let's see. We'll start from there, and let's see how it will evolve.
Yeah, exactly. Okay, so it's like the real or a realistic example of it.
In the meantime, we have some links here in the notes or some questions here in the notes
that you can start filling out while we begin our discussion. So please think
about that. In the meantime, [name], do you have the lesson opened or should I
open it? I can share my screen. Okay.
Can you see it?
That's the questions we put in the notes.
Yeah.
There we go.
Yes.
So when we start off, I guess we can discuss these questions ourselves.
So [name], what does modular code development mean for you?
Well, as a person with some medical education background,
to me modular is something that actually exists in the nature.
We humans are modular ourselves, I would say.
Because if you look at our body,
there are multiple systems like circulatory system,
the nervous system, and the respiratory system.
Each system actually performs its unique function,
and together they form our body.
At the same time, if you look at the microscopic level,
one single cell is also composed of various tiny,
tiny components, and those components
are all performing their own functions,
and together they will form a functional cell.
So it's not just about code,
it's in the nature.
Yeah, I never thought of that.
So I guess there's two types.
One is there's, from what you said,
there's different systems doing
different things and they're separate,
so they can be understood and, well,
I won't say developed about humans, but can be understood and function separately.
And then there's the hierarchy.
Yes, exactly.
And, you know, that matches up with what I think about code also.
And whenever the systems start interfering with each other is that when stuff goes bad.
the really difficult diseases start happening.
Yes, I think that's true for both human and the code.
Yeah. Okay. What does
modular code development mean for you then?
Well, I would say that's also a hierarchical concept.
In the lower level, I would split a functional block of code into functions or I will create classes for them.
If you look at a little bit upper level, then I will organize functions or classes that are related with each other to a single module.
module. The module could be reused in different projects. That's how I understand. How about
you?
Yeah, I mean, I guess it depends on the kind of project. But basically, I start off with
something and then usually it starts off a bit chaotic. But once I get parts that I think
are self-contained, I'll start splitting them off,
whether it's functions or other files or classes
or something like that.
But yeah, basically, like picking off
little bits that are standalone and other things
can use as an interface.
Yeah, I guess that has partially answered
a very natural second question, which
is why do we want modular code instead of a block of code
line after line to do our tasks?
So is there any other reasons we want
to develop modular code?
So let's see.
Well, the first thing comes to my mind is
If I want to share my code with the other person or put it to my paper,
I would like it's well-organized.
Then the other people can use part of it or use the,
if I make a whole Python package,
then they can import it or they can install it.
I would like a code in the package module.
Okay. We have seen some answers,
so please fill out the questions with your comments.
Maybe we can come back to this later and have a look at the material first.
Good idea. So what's next? Let's check out this. Okay, the learning outcomes.
So should we discuss this now or come back? Maybe we do some hands-on stuff and then come back to
this when we have a deeper understanding. Yeah, sounds good. Yeah, I guess the main
thing we might bring up is this first point about pure functions. So basically
we'll see which of our functions have side effects and don't. So basically if a
function is only evaluated by its arguments then that makes it easy to
write, and test, and understand. And we'll maybe get there. But okay.
Let me go back to the notes. Yeah, another thing I would like to emphasize is that
in this session, the main idea will be we will do the typing together. It's kind
of like a live tapping demo.
I will be using the keyboard, and [name] will be helping me,
giving me guides.
And also, you will participate via the notes,
giving us comments, suggestions, or questions in the notes.
So we will do this coding together,
but I'm the one using the keyboard.
OK.
Yes.
Sounds good.
So what is our task?
Let's have a look.
OK.
So this is our task.
We will use some data downloaded from FMIs open database.
It's some records of temperatures in year 2022.
It's the temperature measurements
from the observation station in Wanda Airport.
Yeah, FMI has the observation station there.
That's the data we are going to use.
And as I mentioned before, we have prepared some scripts
for our task. So we will use this as a starting point and try to make it more modular.
Yeah. So what does it do?
Should we move to a Jupyter notebook first?
Yeah, sure. I guess we can look at it as we copy it there.
Yeah. Or maybe while you're getting it set up I can talk about it some. So it's
a simple analysis that reads in data from the CSV file. It computes the
average temperature over the specified range and then makes some plots. So it's
a fairly typical, well, little analysis. So it starts off like it has the read, analyze,
write out results sections. So even though it's simple, it provides some good stuff that we can
use as a good example of the whole analysis workflow.
So, while we're doing this, we'll basically be doing it live.
So you can, and please do, write in the notes and make suggestions on what we should be
doing next.
So we won't really do stuff until someone suggests it.
And we'll just see where it goes.
So do you want to see if it runs first?
I guess that's the first step, right?
Yes, let's try it out.
I have already imported this package,
so I can run directly this one.
Oh, we got some fail not found.
Oh, I haven't downloaded the data.
It should be in this repo.
Yeah, we can see, we can have a glance here.
We can see that the record is there's
one record for each hour from 0, 1, 2.
We will download from here.
So you copied the link.
Yeah, I will use a Jupyter magic command.
That's clever.
So basically from the terminal you're using the wget program which downloads the file and saves it,
I guess. Yes, I think yes. Okay. It's running. And the exclamation mark there is the shell magic,
so it runs something. And yeah, we see it saved temperatures.csv.
All right, let's run this again. Okay, it works, so I will delete this.
You know, this is a question that's come up some past days, like how do you include data
along with an analysis? So there could be something that says if the data doesn't exist,
it runs this command to download and saves it. So just an idea.
Yeah, especially when you're working with a Jupyter Notebook, it's very convenient.
Yeah, okay.
And it works.
Yeah, should we go through this line by line?
Yes, please.
What do the parts mean?
Okay, so the first line is kind of a hard code.
It's number of measurements we want to analyze and visualize.
And then by using appenders, we read some data from a CSV file and then extract the one column.
We have done some computation, which is the mean of these temperatures and then some plot.
So very simple, but typical process.
But also, sorry.
In the notes, I put a question to the audience,
how is this not modular?
But there's no answers yet.
So maybe I can ask you, how is this not modular?
Well, we can see there's a file reading, data extracting,
and the calculation and the visualization,
all stuff together.
If next time I want to use just the plot,
what should I do?
I copy and paste?
That doesn't sound like a good idea.
So I would like some single functional unit.
of code that I can reuse. I don't need to copy-paste, just call that function.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, I guess that's right. So one of the first tasks suggested in the
workshop is to create plots for 25, 50, and 500 measurements. So if you want it
be very unmodular, you'd copy and paste the code block three times and then rerun it,
and that makes a lot of code duplication.
So you can just copy the cells. Yeah. So if we want to be slightly better than that,
how would we make three different plots? I will use a for loop that I don't need to
to repeat all this stuff, so three times, should we try that?
Yes, let's do it.
Okay, I will say, well, number of measurements in the list.
in the list. So 25, 100, and 500. Okay, let me run it. Okay, it works. It's better than
than three cells.
Yeah, OK.
But since it's not modular, we forgot
to change the file name it was saving to.
So this is always a risk.
So should we fix that first?
Maybe we can either define unique names for them
or we can use some other variable to generate the file name automatically.
Maybe we can use the number of measurements. That's exactly what is being used here, 25.
Yeah, makes sense.
Yeah, okay. Let's do that.
Okay, yes. So, use string formatting in the variable, make defining out file. And this
is also good because in the future when we need to, if we make it more modular, we have
variable already defined, so it's good. Yes. Okay, so what should we do next?
I'm waiting for chat messages. Let's see. Let's see if anyone suggests something.
Is there anything we should extract out and pull from here?
Well, I don't like the visualization and the calculations together.
So would you like to pull one of them out? Yeah, at least I would like to pull
the plot part out. Yeah, makes sense. And it really makes sense that once we have
all the plots working well, so we define all the axis labels and format and stuff
like that, we'd want to be able to use the same plot format in multiple cases.
Someone says we need an underscore and out file.
Oh, yes. Thank you so much.
So I will move this out.
Yes. Okay.
See, I will define a function for this.
It will be plot and temperatures.
So do we need some input? Yeah, so what should the inputs be? Well, outfail should be here, I guess.
I guess.
Should the temperatures be an input?
Yes.
And the mean, I guess.
Oh, right.
Yeah.
Should we give alt file some default value?
Yeah, why not?
So default to none.
Then we can use the number of measurements
as the output file name, or a different idea.
Yeah, what should or could it just
be something like plot.png, so not take any stand
and it basically always, like, it minimally works,
but always needs to be something.
Or maybe we should just call it good enough
and accept you need an output.
Otherwise, it doesn't make sense.
So we will use the out file.
What if the default was none, and then the save fig only
ran if there's a given out file.
Yes, yes.
If out file, then we save.
So now the function is usable both for interactive kind
of work, and then if you want to save stuff later.
Although there are still some problems with that,
But we can get there later.
Yes.
OK.
And now we need to put this back into num measurements.
Yes, we will.
Or we just this.
Okay.
Yeah.
And mean.
Oh, but it should specify the outfile.
Yeah.
If we want, then.
Oh, yeah.
But we could also not give it right now.
Yeah.
Yeah, we could comment this out.
Okay.
Should we try without saving firstly?
Yeah, let's try.
Then we don't need to specify this.
Okay.
It won't be saved.
Should I run it again?
Yeah, let's go.
Okay.
It's still working.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, what's next? Should we extract more functions out? So, something, one of the
files says one of these suggestions is to remove the compute statistics and
reading data functions out to set yeah move these two separate functions yeah
that sounds quite reasonable to me yeah okay so this part will go to another
function which will be let me name it get get data maybe so should we make the
input file we can we can flexibly use different input file yeah so the
function shouldn't, should be able to work on different inputs. Yep, okay. Yeah, see, then this
will be an input fail. Yeah. Number of measurements, maybe a second argument. Okay, yeah, I guess
that has to be specified from outside. Yes. So what if we didn't have it as an argument?
So I think the code would still work because of how Python goes, but is that
good? You mean, well, if we don't specify this number of rows, I think
it will read all the rows. Yeah. But if we leave it like this, then
And we probably will get an error.
Yeah.
So yeah.
OK.
That's good.
So we've got that.
So I'll put it back.
It runs successfully.
Is that the file name?
I think so, yes. Okay, is it still working? Okay, yeah, okay, good. Now we have two functions.
Is there too much data being plotted? Did it read the whole thing if you scroll down?
Sounds weird. What I would do usually is to restart the kernel because there might be some
variable names polluted. Good point, yeah.
Okay, there are some typos, I think.
Okay. Oh, yeah.
Yeah, okay, so we need to store the output of the getData function.
Yeah, we need to return.
Nasty. Okay, now it looks okay. Yeah, okay, this looks like it looked okay.
And then should we extract out the statistics function?
Yeah, I would love to do that in case I want to do something different.
So that means we will have a third function. I'll call it getName.
Someone points out that infile isn't specified.
Why do you specify it?
Oh no, it is specified, yeah, in git data.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think it is specified here.
I mean, it worked, so it had to be there.
When the question came up, though, I got confused.
So I wondered, how is this working?
Yeah, so the input will be temperatures.
But do we want to use this number of measurements,
or we can get it from the input temperatures.
Yeah, it should probably come from the input temperatures.
So we could pass it as an argument,
but then we have to basically pass redundant information
because the column knows how many rows are there, right?
Yeah, and there might be some risk
that we input a wrong number.
So this might be better, I think.
Yeah.
OK.
Let me rerun this.
OK, still working.
Yeah, OK, good.
So let's talk about which of these are pure functions
or not.
So is there any parameters other than the arguments?
And does it have any side effects?
So plotTemperatures, it's based only on the input arguments,
but it does have side effects, but only saving files.
So is this function easy to test?
I think, yes, at least for getMean,
we can easily test it by using test.
Oh, git mean, oh, it's talking about plot temperatures.
So let's start with git mean.
That's the easier one.
So for git mean, this is the easiest thing
to test because there's no side effects.
The only input is the, the only thing that affects
the output is the input.
Should we make a test now for it or later?
would like to, well, I usually test, I usually do unit tests in the Python script other than
Jupyter Notebook. Yeah, you're right. Like, if we did the test, then how would we know if it even
worked? Yeah. Okay, so let's not test it yet. But git main is easy to test. Is the function
get data easy to test?
Get data, I think there are several things we can test.
For example, we can test the size of data.
Is it matching with the number of measurements?
Something like that.
Can you say that again?
was reading the stats. I mean because the input is number of measurements and we pass that to the
read CSV method, we want to verify that the extracted data has the exact the same number of
records we want. That could be something we can test. That's a good idea. So start with like
Yeah, so include some sample data, like this one, and then we can, well, there's not that
much that can go wrong, but test that, okay, yeah.
Yeah, usually for computation functions, I would do some tests, like getMin.
Yeah, okay.
a question. Maybe it's better to put the get mean function call inside the plot
temperatures function. So should we compute the mean outside or inside the
plotting function? Well, usually I would make them stand alone instead of...
yeah it depends yeah like like what do you want the plot temperatures to only
plot means or maybe it could plot other statistics too like it's yeah right now
basically a general function that plots the temperatures and a line and the line
can be different things yeah let's imagine that we define a force function
that we'll get not an arithmetic mean, but a geometric mean, then we can plot a different thing.
Yeah. There's also a good suggestion, why not use statistics.mean instead of creating a custom
function? And yeah, I guess that would make sense, but this is a demo and this is an example of
something that would be more complex. So yeah, yeah, we want to go to a very,
very complex Python stuff. We want to make it more general. Yeah, someone suggests testing
if the column for air temperatures is numeric, and that sometimes they've done things and it
writes it as a different type of data. Yeah, yeah, yeah, true, true. Let's get to that later.
Okay, so we have the loop, we have means. So how modular is it now? So what benefit have we achieved so far?
I think so far we have split the whole block of code into three single purpose functions. All of them could be reused.
Yeah, you can
Well, if it's a Python script then you can import them to a different Python script or a different notebook
Yeah, that's I would say we have improved the code
Yeah
Okay, what should we do now
Should we
make it a Python script or is there anything else?
Yeah, I would like to make a Python script.
When I come to this point of coding,
I have done some interactive work.
I have seen some visualization of data.
A Python script will make it more convenient to
to do more exploration.
Yeah.
OK.
How do you make a Jupyter Notebook to a Python script
usually?
Hmm.
I haven't done it that many times.
I think you can use nbconvert or export it.
Or maybe in the end, I would just
copy what I need over since usually whenever I do something,
There's like, it's too messy for me to want to do everything.
This seems a bit cleaner.
So what do you recommend?
Yeah, this one is not very long.
So maybe we can use the simple way,
because Jupyter Notebook has this save and export
Notebook as executable script function.
So yeah, we can do this, I think.
Okay, I will save it.
Okay, temp visual.py, yep, okay.
Okay, let's see. I think it's here. Yes.
Yeah, okay. So, it looks like Python code.
So, yeah, how do we start fixing it up?
Well, I will remove this redundant stuff from Jupyter Notebook.
Then maybe we can simply run it to see if things go wrong.
Good idea. Yeah, so yeah. Yeah, I suppose it could work. Yeah, I mean, probably. So maybe
this is the first time, well, we've seen examples of command-line usage before,
but can you explain what it means to be running it on the command line now? Well,
it means you will use Python. You will use Python and specify the name of the py file, which is a
script. Then the Python interpreter will run the program. Yeah, okay, so we give it the program
name. And right now there's no argument, so it just runs it from top to bottom.
Yeah, everything is entered in the script itself. Let's see.
Okay, the importing will take time. Okay.
Okay, we are supposed to have...
It's showing. Okay, so now here the command line program is opening a graphical window.
Is this what we want? It depends. If we are working on HPC,
we don't want it to show because there's no display. But if it's locally, I don't quite
demanded to see it show.
Should we make it where, this is what we said before, right?
So if it, maybe we could say if you give it a file name,
it saves the file name.
If you don't give it a file name,
then it shows it with plot.show.
Yes.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, I think if we don't want it to be shown,
then we probably want to save it.
Yeah.
So that would be around line 10 we adjust.
Yes.
So we can comment out this line.
Then it won't be shown.
But instead, we would like to input output file name.
Then it will be saved.
Should we say under the if out file then else
And then do plot dot show if there's nothing.
Oh, yeah, that's a good idea.
Yeah, I see.
OK.
So is it good that it does two different things
depending on the argument?
I guess.
It's good, I think.
Yeah, it's a reasonable compromise for now.
It's a pattern people might want.
Like, if the plotting function was actually
relatively difficult, then maybe this
would be a good way to use it two different ways.
Yeah.
OK, so if you run it now, does it show anything graphically?
Yeah, because we didn't input any output first.
So it goes to the else.
Right.
OK, so we need to give it the output file again.
OK.
Then we need to modify the script.
Yeah.
Is that something you want to do?
Yeah, should we give it a way to specify,
should we hard code the output file,
or should we make it a full script with arguments now?
Well, I'd like the argument idea.
OK.
don't want to touch the script that much. Yeah, okay, good idea. And someone here
suggests disconnecting the loop, so maybe we can do this at the same time. So before
the script would run it for all these measurements, now the number of
measurements should be an argument. Yes. Okay, so do we make a main function here?
is it? Yes. Okay. Let's make a main function that can take a number of
measurements as an input. Okay, yeah. Okay. And what other inputs should we give it?
Info, I would say. Yeah. The output file? Output file. Are those the three main
things I guess yeah yeah okay so whenever you make a command line program
what do you use for parsing the arguments there are several different
And tools, they are pretty much similar, like arg parse or click.
Well, the example solution says using click, so maybe we should do that.
Okay.
I can't remember all the commands, but...
Well, I'm reading here, so I can tell you.
So, okay, above death equals main, then at sign click dot command with parentheses.
I remember it's a click option.
Dot option, yeah.
And then dash dash the measurements.
Does the order matter? Should we specify infile firstly?
Oh, maybe we do infile first. I often do that also, so sort of go the input arguments first,
then the analysis ones, then the output ones, but it parses it in any order.
Yes, so it's required, I guess.
Ah, there's a good point here.
Is an infile an argument and not an option?
So it should be an argument.
So maybe we can say what's the difference here.
So option is usually something with the two dashes on it, and is optional.
But positional arguments don't need the dashed things, and you are just taking the first
one on the command line as the first one, and second one as the second one.
But our example we're following has everything as options, so maybe we should follow the
example rather than make things ourselves.
Okay.
But we should specify it's required, right?
Yes.
There's no default, but definitely some help.
Yeah, okay.
it's the input file name. Yes. So a second one is number of measurements. I think the
convention is dash instead of underscore.
This is also required and it must be a int.
Yes, okay.
And also when you specify the type like this,
it will automatically convert it to that type.
Yes.
And give a warning if it's not.
So help, that would be the number of methods to use.
Then, another one will be the output.
This is not required.
Okay, yeah. In the example it says it's required, but I guess we can leave it as
not required and it will show it on the screen, which is possibly nice.
Yes. So not required, right? Yeah, not required.
Okay, output file name, okay.
Yeah, but in the main function, we didn't reflect anything about the output file.
Okay, yeah, so we should add that to plotTemperatures, I guess. Is it the last
argument? Yes, I think so. Yes, it's the last argument.
So, it should be like this, I guess.
Yes.
Okay.
Do you think it will work?
We need to specify the namespace.
Yeah, it has to actually run main.
So what you're about to see is the typical pattern you see at the bottom of Python files.
So this means if it's imported, then it just imports it, and all the functions can be used.
But if it's run as a script from a command line, then name is equal to this main value
here, and then it should run the function.
So this is just basically the pattern you use all the time.
So let's see.
Does it work?
I think I forgot to import.
Yes, we have to import click.
Yes.
I'll guess you have it installed from the Code Refinery.
Oh, yeah. I haven't activated the environment.
I guess everyone has created this content environment for the workshop.
I also created it myself.
Activate. Yeah, but it worked before.
Yeah. Let's see.
Okay.
Yeah, it should be better now.
Yeah. What if we run without arguments?
Can we see help text or something?
Yeah. Missing option, yeah.
Okay, so it basically will guide us through everything that's needed.
Yeah, but let's check out this.
Yeah.
Oh, we need Python on it. Yes. Yeah. Okay.
Yeah, we can see this help message reflects what we specified by using click.
Yeah, okay. So let's see, can we then run it with all the options?
Let's see, we give it an input file which is
temperatures.csv, if I remember that correctly. Yeah, I think so.
So number of measurements, that will be, let's say, 25.
Let's try without output file.
It's supposed to show.
Yes.
And if we change the number of measurements, does it do more?
Let's see.
Great.
That looks correct.
Yes.
OK.
Good.
And if we give an out file, does it save it to somewhere?
Let's have a look.
Out.
Let me see.
Just an example.
.png.
It won't show, I think.
Yeah, okay. Let's see if it's saved. Okay, it's saved here. Maybe I can open it. Okay.
Yeah, and it's there. Okay. Yeah, that looks good. Should we summarize and then go to the
break and then we can do a little bit more when we come back? Yeah, I think it's a good
point to break. Okay so what did we just accomplish and what's the benefit of what we've done? Also
people can comment in the notes about what you think. So there's a lot more code but
also to do different analyses we don't have to edit the code at all. The code is basically
Basically just that.
And if we save these command line lines we run, then we can reproduce our analysis in
different ways.
If we want to run this automatically, for example with what we learned for SnakeMake
on Tuesday, we could easily plug this
into a SnakeMake workflow that does things.
We can script it to run many, many times on the cluster.
We can send it to someone else, and we can tell them,
use these options.
And they don't have to understand the code.
They only have to understand the help text here.
So by making this more modular, do we call this modular?
Yeah, I would definitely call this modular.
It could be reused.
It could be reproduced.
It can be easily scaled up.
So it's modular.
Yeah.
And the outsider using it has this clear defined interface
for it.
So I guess let's take a break.
Please keep suggesting what to do next.
I can think of a few things, like adding the test to it.
And we can see what we do then.
So there will be maybe 15 or 20 more minutes of working
on this.
And then we'll have a quick wrap-up of the whole workshop.
Okay. When should we come back?
I guess four past hour.
Okay.
So 10 minutes break.
Okay. Thank you.
Okay.
See you soon.
Thank you. See you soon. Bye.
you
Hello. We're back. So, the last half an hour. In the notes, we had votes for, the most votes
were for adding tests. So, we're thinking of doing that next. And that really does seem
to be about the right time to do it. But before you do that, would you like to make it a
Git repository, so we have some record before we start changing a lot of stuff and risk breaking.
Yes, yes, when it comes to this point, when you have a script like this,
we would like to do some check. You have learned in last week, so I guess we all have Git installed,
so and yeah okay so it's not yet a git repo so I will initialize it
so git init I usually will specify the branch name so okay now it's initialized
and so we can check out with the most commonly used command git status so we
can see all the files are unchecked okay yeah but we don't want to check all of
them. I will check the code, of course. So, git add temp pool.
Yes, it's frozen. Okay, that one has been added. Do we want to add the notebook?
Maybe.
Yeah.
Well, yeah.
Why not?
I mean, I guess maybe it's being replaced now, but for a development project, we may
as well keep track of it and we can do something different with it later if it was ever needed.
Yes.
Okay.
So I won't track the plot.
Yeah, because you probably will have plenty of them.
Maybe at some point, I'll track the most important ones.
That depends.
But the idea is to show how we use Git
for the version control.
So I will commit to the...
Yeah.
OK.
So this is, well, usually I will,
it's the initial commit.
Or you can use some other meaningful commit message.
Okay, now we have checked the files we want to check.
So that's a version control you have learned in last week.
Yeah.
Okay.
So what else we can try?
Should we add a gitignore for the things we don't want?
yes yes that's a good idea yeah if you list if you list the hidden files you
will see there's a .git but typically we will add a gitignore file it's also a
hidden file, gitignore. And we add in all the stuff we don't want, like should we
add asterisk.png? Yes. And what else things like the pycache and the ipynbcache?
Yes, pycache, is that correct? And dot ipy. What's the ipynb cache? I forgot it, but let's
check it. It's the ipy and b checkpoints. Checkpoints, yes. Okay, yeah. So ipy, checkpoints.
Okay, with this git ignore, if we run git status again.
Yeah, gitignore itself. But I guess we'll add gitignore. Yes. Yes. Okay. How about the data?
Yeah, should this data be included? Since it's open data, not something sensitive,
and it's a small data we use as an example, so I would say it's fine to add it.
It would be good data for our tests, basically.
Yeah, yeah.
OK, sounds good.
So let's add it.
Yeah.
OK.
Now everything should be there.
Yes, but we needed to make another commit.
Yeah.
Let's see. Add the test data. Okay. Now it should be clean.
Yes. Yes. Okay, great. Okay, but now tests. So, which of these three functions would you
like to test, or which do we test things that aren't in a function?
I would test a function, like, well, if the first function I want to test is getMin.
I don't want the calculation wrong.
Yeah, yeah.
That seems like the most likely to go wrong without us noticing it, so.
Okay, should we add the test to this file or another file?
If there's only one test and the file is not very long,
I will add it here.
Otherwise, I will use a separate file for multiple tests.
Yeah.
So should we use a separate one?
Yeah, I mean, whenever I start with one really small thing
like this, I'll also often start just
inside of the like yeah just inside because yeah yeah it's small enough yeah yeah okay okay then i
will, uh, we need to import pet test. Yes, okay. Yes, so test min,
so min will be something calculated by using this function. Yeah, okay, so we basically run
the function. Yeah, maybe just a list of floats? Yeah, that's a good idea. So we basically give
it some of our very own data, and we know what the mean should be, so we can see what it is.
And this is sort of the best possible case, so we write in some values.
maybe another one yeah and then we could do yeah there and then for pi test we
would write assert mean equals 3 I guess 3.0 yes okay and then to run it how do
do we do this? We use pytest. So pytest. And since this file isn't named test, we
need to give it the file name. So temp visual. Yes. Yeah. Let's see. Importing syntax error.
Ah, yeah. Is it saved?
Dev, lantern, table.
What's wrong with this? Maybe it needs to be saved.
Okay. Oh, yeah.
That's something Jupyter Notebook doesn't do for you.
Okay. Sometimes. Yeah. So now it says
there was
one test collected, so we know it actually found it. If it said zero tests collected,
we'd be a bit worried. And it worked. And this time it happened to work, and there wasn't any
floating point error, which caused it to make problems. So that is good. If there was this
floating point error, it would say error 3.0 is not equal to 3.0000 something.
PetTest has this proxy method to avoid this kind of accuracy problem. Maybe we can use that.
Ah, good idea.
Like this.
Yeah, good to demo anyway.
Let's see. I'm sure this will work.
because it's less strict than before. Okay, yes, okay.
Yeah, do we want to test some other things? Like should we test if it works with negative numbers?
Would we test if it worked with no inputs at all?
Would we test that it works with one input? Or maybe this is a good stopping point.
What do you think?
Yeah, there is something else we can test.
Oh.
But we're also almost out of time, so.
Oh, yes.
We can talk about how we would test other things.
So how would we test the getData function?
GetDataFunction, as I mentioned,
we can test if the size is correct.
As it's mentioned in the notes that we can
test the data type of temperatures.
We want it to be float.
Right. Yeah.
But sometimes from CSP file,
it might be stored as a string.
Yeah.
That's also something we can test.
And since we have some test data included,
it's easy to run or do test data or test test data
because we just give it this thing we have already.
Yes.
What about plot temperatures?
Is this easy to test?
I mean, I guess we can test if it runs and makes a file.
Yes, if the file exists.
Is it worth testing to see if the file is correct, or is that trying too hard?
That's not something I usually do, but it's definitely doable.
And yeah, it's valid, depends.
Like same for me, so I would usually not test the plot temperatures unless I know I really need it
to. I think there are things for testing matplotlib plotting, like you would define
what you expect it to have and can test it without saving the file. But I would usually
try to do all the stuff that needs testing outside of the plot function to make it easy
and plot just does the bare minimum.
Yes. Okay, should we move to the outro and wrap-up of the workshop, so people can keep asking questions here and we'll keep answering after the outro part?
Do you want to have a look at the learning outcomes?
Yes, yes, this one.
Let's go back there.
I think we have achieved most of them.
Yeah, so we talked some about pure functions,
not as much as some instances of the course.
But basically, when it doesn't have these side effects,
then it's easier to test.
The second one we didn't talk about too much.
A single-purpose function we talked about a bit.
So split apply combine is a different kind
of thing, which we haven't talked about.
It's another way of basically dividing and conquer.
The command line interface we did extensively talk about
And to me, that's when the code really starts getting reusable
and I start becoming proud of sharing it.
It becomes actually like a thing.
So, yeah.
And I think we saw how this connects to the other lessons.
So we did the tests, didn't really do documentation.
We talked about version control.
We talked about how the scripts, making the command line
interfaces lets us make it more reproducible later on.
So yeah.
Yeah, we have there's something we haven't covered,
but we can continue the discussion in the notes.
Yeah, and also I see some suggestions
regarding the code script.
Yeah, we use it as a demo.
It's not perfect, but the idea is the modular coding.
Yeah.
OK.
So I'm going to switch to my screen if I can.
Yes, it worked.
So we're going to the concluding remarks.
and where to go from here, also known as the workshop outro.
So thanks to everyone who was attending. This was a fun course to give. We had
a lot of new people and new instructors and we're getting closer to the sustainability
point of view. Thanks to everyone who attended. I don't know how many people were working in
teams here, so basically had people in an organized group together attending. But anyone
who was able to do that, thank you for coming. That's really good, exactly what we want.
We would like to thank all of the instructors who are listed on the workshop webpage.
I won't say their names again here, so I don't have to remove them from the videos. But yeah,
I mean, instructors have put in a lot of work to go and make this happen.
We also had a bunch of people answering questions in the notes, as you may have seen and found.
These people took a lot of time to do that, and the local partners who organized
any possible in-person things and so on.
We'd like you to keep giving us feedback, so in the notes, you can keep adding things.
It is in there now.
We see it's here, please keep adding stuff.
You can send us by email or you can join our chat if you wanted and say some things.
So you can always use Git itself by making issues or pull requests to help update our
lesson materials.
In fact, you could say that our whole course is a way, our whole course is a way, is teaching
you how to update our materials, because everything we use, we teach in the course.
And we keep developing based on your feedback, so let us know.
In about six months, you may get a post-workshop survey, which will basically ask how your
work has been changed and updated based on what you learned in this course.
is really important to fill out because it really provides the best indicator to
the people that fund us that we've done something useful and they will keep
funding it. So I'd really encourage you to keep studying and asking for support.
So this is a starting course but these are very applied and not theoretical
topics so most of what you'll learn will be on your own after this. So I would
say, starting off, you have the course and it gives you some ideas, lets you do some things.
But the next step is to work on things along with someone else. So someone who can be there
and help you answer your questions locally. We have these partners below we can talk about,
but even if it's just another colleague, do talk about the things you've learned here and
ask for help because it's new. And then, even after that's done, there's still plenty more
you'll be learning yourself. Never start doing web searches or whatever to find
new things that you can use based on what you've seen here.
We have these things called bring your own code sessions. And it's basically a way you can bring
your code or well I guess other questions and come talk to us instructors and we'll look at
things together with you and it's basically like a follow-up Q&A mentoring kind of session.
So this is a way we can help with the follow-up ourselves.
You can continue to review everything that we have here. The lessons stay available
indefinitely and get updates. As you know we have videos published. The main point of these videos
is for you, our learners now, to go and re-review things during yourself, afterwards. And you can
reuse these materials as much as you'd want. So there's a bunch of different partners that are
are part of the Code Refinery project.
I think, yeah, did we have, yeah,
I think we had people from all of these here.
Maybe not Denmark this time.
But anyway, the point is that locally in your country,
you have people that hopefully want
to answer questions about these things
and then help you follow up.
If you're at Aalto University, we have plenty of things.
basically come to our daily sessions anytime and we can follow up and help you do these
things.
And I think probably is the same for more of the stuff.
We just have listed the Nordic countries here because we're a Nordic project, but there's
more in other countries that you need to find yourself.
If you want a certificate, that's on the course webpage.
I don't really know much more other than what is there.
So please read it yourself if you're interested.
Tell people about us.
So let people know that it's a good workshop and they should come in the future.
Or even recommend to your institution or yourself, join us as either a team leader or become
part of a team, an instructor in the future, a supporter.
There's all kinds of people doing stuff in the background, which we need help with to
keep stuff working.
So, yeah.
We already talked about these things.
The newsletter is a good way to hear of what's going on, other interesting tidbits, and so
on.
And if you really like the kind of things that we're talking about now, you can look
into this thing called research software engineers,
which is basically people that are researchers,
but they're focused more on the technology.
So they're more interested
in making the research technology better
rather than getting as many citations
as they can for themselves.
So it's a different kind of career path
that has a different kind of focus.
So it's still sort of a new thing in some places
but it's something that would be worth reading about.
Okay.
Any other comments or things from the notes?
I will switch there.
Let's see.
Please give feedback.
This is not much feedback and we need more
in order to see how it went.
Yeah, okay, there's a question here.
Are there any good AI tools which can automatically generate a test code?
I think there are probably some, but I don't know them myself.
I think someone will probably come in and fill in the answer later.
Yeah. Is there anything else?
Are there any other instructors around who want to
join the studio and say any final words?
Yeah, I'm very happy I'm here today.
It's a very good time to learn from each other.
I saw quite good answers and comments,
suggestions in the notes.
I will read them through later.
Yeah. I think today went quite well overall.
So we had some good sessions.
And, yeah, the most sincere thanks to everyone who stuck with us all this time.
And yeah, I really hope that this will improve your work and that you can reteach these to
other people later on.
Okay. So, I guess I will turn it off for now.
Is there any final news? So, I think most of the news was in this outro session.
And there's no future session. So, yeah, that's that.
Okay. Thank you, everyone. Bye.
Bye.
Thank you.
you