Hello, hello and welcome to
Python for Scientific Computing
edition year 2025.
I am very happy that we
managed to do again this
hopefully useful course and we
have many people online that
are watching us and interacting with
us but we have of course a
few people here in the room with me.
How are you, everyone here?
So do you want to
briefly introduce yourself?
I see my list first, [name].
Yeah.
Hi, this is [name].
I'm working at the University
of Iceland in Reykjavik, and
it's really nice to have you here.
Iman will be teaching in
the morning with [name] about
kind of the introduction on how
to work with Python specifically
for scientific computing for data analysis.
So [name], do you want
to mention something about yourself?
Yeah.
Hi, everyone.
I'm [name].
I'm working at Uppsala University
and also for NICE.
Very happy to be a part
of this great course that
Aalto University is leading.
And I hope you'll enjoy it.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.
And since Aalto was mentioned,
I'm actually from Aalto University
and we also have another Aaltonian here.
[name], do you want to
say something about yourself?
Hi everyone.
Yeah, I'm [name].
I'll be teaching, well, the
first time you'll see me
is when we're teaching NumPy in
about an hour, I think.
But you'll be seeing me,
I think, throughout the course
this time around.
I'm an RSE at R2 and try and do two
trying to teach as much as
I know about computing to as
many people as possible.
Yes.
So the page that we are
sharing right now is the
so-called notes document.
You should all have received
it in the email.
And the idea of the notes
document, I will explain it soon at the clock.
The idea is that we can
all edit this document.
But as you can understand,
since there are almost 500
people watching this, if you
don't need to write anything, you
can stay into this view mode.
But in general, since we're
talking about languages, many of us,
we are now using English,
but I believe none here, nobody
of us here is mother tongue English.
So I'm Italian myself, and the
rest of us here is from other countries.
So if we think of
this metaphor in programming languages,
and if the first language you
learn is your mother
tongue programming language,
What did you start with, [name]?
What was your first programming language?
I first learned C, and then
a little bit after that it was Fortran.
It took a couple of years
to start getting into Python as
well, as it became more popular.
So now Python is the
language that you speak daily, basically?
Yeah, yeah, that's true.
I do speak the other one still,
but yes, Python is very
common in the day-to-day work.
was a little bit the same for me
that I also started with C and C++
and then which was maybe painful
is not the right word but let's say not
as fun as other languages and
then I had a detour with MATLAB actually
for many years I've just
been using MATLAB but then
in recent years Python and R
are the languages that I speak
today apart from Finnish
I'm still learning.
What about you, [name]?
What was your mother tongue
in programming language?
I started actually similar, like
I started with C, C++ mostly,
and then shifted to Fortran because
most of the community is focusing
on Fortran at the time.
And then more recently, like
Python, like this kind of thing.
So yeah, it's like a kind of a mixture
when a new language comes
and becoming popular, I started
diving into it.
Interesting.
So it looks like that C is winning.
What about you, Suza?
What was your first programming language?
So I would argue that
my actual first programming language isn't
what would be my programming
mother tongue, because the first
thing I did programming in was BASIC.
And then I learned Dr. Scheme,
which is a list dialect,
if anyone knows what that is.
It's basically a scripting language.
It's how complicated.
And I hate it.
I would call my actual
native programming language would be Java.
That's what we used when
I started studying computer science
the second time.
But then I've been doing lots
and lots and lots of
other programming languages.
I did MATLAB for quite a while.
I did Python a lot.
I do R, though I don't like it.
But I've also done things in
C. There's a dialect of
C basically called small devices C compiler.
So yeah, my programming
language experience is very, very broad.
Yeah.
Excellent.
So as you can see, for
those watching us in the
streaming, you might learn Python today,
you might switch to something
else in one year or 10 years.
In the end, what matters
is that you're able to transfer your ideas
and wishes from your brain to
a device that is then going to
do what you ask it to do.
Basically, yes.
So we have still a few seconds
before we officially start the
course at 10 o'clock Finnish
time, 9 o'clock Central European time.
Let me just have a look.
So right now in this
notes document, there's 152 people using it.
Let's hope we don't
crash the server.
Just to give you an idea,
a Google Doc would limit
100 edits, 100 concurrent users.
So we are now beating Google
Docs with the server, but
hopefully everything will be fine.
so let's just start hello everyone
and welcome to python
for scientific computing 2025
i'm [name] and i'm
the organizer of this course
along with a multitude of
people behind the scenes who are
taking care of the streaming
and installations and course materials
and so on
in this course we are
basically using two main tools
which is the twitch tv
stream that you're watching right
now and this notes document that
we are seeing in the stream
here you can see that we recommend
for those at least to just
have a laptop screen that you
can arrange your windows so
that the web browser with the
twitch tv stream takes let's say
the left hand side of your
of your laptop screen and then
you can have the python window
and then another browser window for example
with this document where you
can ask questions of course
if you have multiple screens
you can rearrange the screens as you wish
but this is why basically
we do this vertical screen
sharing so that those with a
laptop have a little bit of
free space around it
So what you see right now
is this so-called notes document.
And I will ask Iman now
if you scroll up into
this document, there should be a pencil.
Sometimes it's on the, yeah, there it is.
So if you click the
pencil, this document turns into an editor.
And so the first block
here, we basically would like
you that you don't edit it because it's useful.
They are the links that
we need throughout the course.
But in the bottom, there
are some icebreakers so that people can write.
And I can see that
people are already writing where they're from.
And I wrote a couple of silly questions.
How much have you used Python before?
And how much have you used Jupyter before?
And where do you store your files?
So it's interesting to see, you know,
how diverse we are some
people are experienced python
users some people might be you
know the first day today
that they started jupiter and we let it
and i think one powerful
thing of this course is that we
try to give a little bit
of everything there's some
take-home messages and learning
out outcomes for the truly
beginner but there's also insights
for for those who have
been working with python for for many years
then when you don't need
to edit this document because
as I mentioned earlier there's
many people editing it's good to
switch to the view mode so
like it's doing now by clicking
on the eye and now in the
very top there there is this
program link would you mind clicking it
So here, if we scroll down to the schedule,
we see the schedule for today
and the two following days.
And so this morning we will
start with the basics of
Python and specifically a little
bit of Jupyter.
We will not really go
into the Python syntax.
It's kind of learn by doing.
So if you have syntax errors,
error messages hopefully are
clear enough to correct you
with the syntax after we will
have then a lunch break at
around 12 Finnish time so
11 Norwegian Swedish time and after
that we will talk about pandas
which is a framework for
working with tabular data and
x-arrays which kind of adds how
can I say extra power to
working with tabular data and this
will be our first day
I will not spoil the fun for the second
and the third day but if
you could click on this intro
bit that we have already started
So I already mentioned the
course content, so we can scroll
a bit more down.
And so how to attend this course?
Instead of using Zoom and
having people in the Zoom
window and basically trying to avoid names,
because what we really want
is that we would like to record
this workshop and publish the videos
and if people are on the zoom
and they want to ask
questions becomes difficult with
the practicalities so by using
twitch tv we can allow immediate recordings
and immediate publishing of
the recordings and also people
can just watch from whatever
device they are without you know
need to be in zoom
So the live stream is like watching TV
and some of you might
be watching TV together with
their colleagues in some rooms.
Some of you might be at home.
And then if you want,
there's also the possibility to do exercises.
But in general, you can
just watch the stream and
eventually ask questions.
so when it comes to
asking question this chat
communication we already gave you a
kind of a demo of how
it works and it's interesting to
see that almost 200 of you
are right now editing the
document which is great
and so the notes are very useful
and in the very bottom we
don't need to show the notes right now
but in the very bottom I
also included the questions that
were sent earlier through the
registration so you can already
see some answers there
Screen arrangement, I've already
mentioned this, but here you get a good,
how can I say, screenshot of
how it can look like on a laptop.
Maybe something important that
I should mention is that the
Twitch TV tends to save bandwidth,
which basically means that
sometimes the stream might look
pixelated and the sound might look robotic.
And this is because Twitch TV
is trying to use less internet bandwidth.
so it's important that you
set the source quality of the
twitch tv stream to source
so that basically you will
never get pixelated images and
and robotic sounds
so what else where do you
focus well in general if you are lost
and we are all lost once in a
while it's good to focus on
the on the on the lecture
on what our instructors are saying
and and just watch the stream
when there will be exercises
that will be clearly mentioned
in the notes document what is
the task that you need to do
if you're able to do it is great if you
are not able to do it
because maybe the installation
didn't go successfully.
You can do it later.
There's no pressure.
Maybe we don't need to go
through the list of what can go wrong,
but in general, we use
the notes document to communicate.
So if the internet collapses
or which can happen.
Last week, there was
just Cloudflare collapsed that
blocked large part of the internet.
So if something is extremely
wrong, you will hear from us.
And finally, of course, we
follow the code of conduct of Code Refinery,
which is our umbrella organization
for all these trainings.
So we just like people to
be respectful and helpful.
And we all come from
multiple different countries with
very different backgrounds so there's
no you know best or worst of
us we are just all learners
including us warrior teaching and
so let's just enjoy this
these three days together
Final note, it is possible
to get certificates and in the
webpage of the course it clearly
says how to obtain those.
For those at Aalto University
there's a little bit special way
of doing it, but you will
receive an email from me.
Otherwise, enjoy the course.
It's 8 minutes past 10 in Finland.
I think I've talked enough
and let's just start.
So I pass the microphone
to [name] and see you
later and enjoy the course.
Thank you, [name].
So now we are going
to continue with Jupyter.
And Herman is going to or
is sharing the screen right now.
I will just mention that
if you've been using Jupyter for
a while, then this is going to
be a very easy lesson for you.
So go to the notes document
and check the questions that we
have added at the bottom of
it and share your experience with it.
and the best practices.
What would you like others
to know about Jupyter?
Pros and cons, favorite ideas
that you may have.
And also, if you do not
want to do things in Jupyter
for this workshop, that's perfectly fine.
Use your favorite IDE or
your favorite IDE with
Jupyter notebooks, that's perfectly fine.
But now we'll start with Jupyter.
So, Hemal, I'm giving the word to you now.
Yeah.
Hi.
Thanks, [name] and [name].
So, yeah, in the next 30 minutes,
what we will be doing is
mostly like going through the
Jupyter, like and like basically
try to focus on like
what the Jupyter kernel looks
like and what are the pros and cons of Jupyter.
So the Jupyter, like basically it has,
you can build up a
computational narrative using this Jupyter.
It is a kind of a fun, like doing that,
And maybe if you want to
share the kernel with others, it
is also a very interactive way of doing it.
So in the rest of the course, basically,
if you are already familiar
with Jupyter, what you can do
is there are some exercises below.
So if you scroll down a
bit below, you can see exercise 1, 2, and 3.
So if you are already
familiar with Jupyter, you can
jump to exercise 3 and try to edit the node.
Basically, it's like collaborative
nodes where you can add your experiences.
So otherwise, just relax and
then follow the lecture today.
okay so uh why jupiter what
is jupiter like and what are
you going to use it for like basically
so jupiter is mostly used
for like a teaching purpose like
or also like for doing data exploration
and the kind of interactive
work [name] could you share
your experience with the jupiter like
Yeah, so the way I use
Jupyter, actually I use either JupyterLab
or I use it in VS
Code with extensions for Jupyter notebooks.
It's mostly for data visualization,
or sometimes I just want
to inspect different data.
I use it for teaching.
And especially if I want
to combine some code
together with documentation.
So if I want to show someone, okay,
how does this script like,
what does this script do and
how you should use it, then
I would prefer to show that in a notebook.
So early stages of development as well.
And then once things get
too long, then once the script gets too long,
too complex and I will
jump into scripts and we are
going to cover that later in
the workshop as well.
Okay, great.
So let's start JupyterLab.
So you already might
receive the installation instructions.
Otherwise, when you are
doing the exercises, you can
follow the installation instructions.
it is pretty easy to set up the jupiter
and for the day one and
the next coming days you will
be using the jupiter for uh the python
for scientific computing so i
recommend you to like uh in
case if you haven't installed try
to follow the installation instructions
So there are different ways of installing.
I choose miniforge basically.
Otherwise you can also choose
Anaconda or your favorite setup.
So I will just copy these
lines because I already installed
it in my laptop.
So I will switch here.
So let's make scroll a bit.
Okay.
So just
I'm copying these lines.
So I'm just source-ing my miniforge.
And then activating my conda.
And then starting my Jupyter Lab.
So just copy and paste and.
It will basically then redirect
you to the Jupyter.
OK.
So now I will hide this
terminal for a while.
OK, so.
So then this way it starts
in your default browser, basically.
Yes.
Let me close this.
OK, when you start the kernel.
So what you can see here is
like a kind of a you have
the menu bar here on the top
file edit, which is a typical
menu bars you see in Doc or
any of the other tools and.
Here you have like a kind
of if you're starting new, you
can start a new launcher here
and it will open this.
Basically, you can start a
new Python notebook by clicking
on this Python 3, or else in case
if you want to use other consoles
and terminal, you can scroll
down and see you can use
a terminal and other things.
Let's go back.
In case if you're already using it,
you might see a multiple
Python kernels since I was using
a lot, so I have a bunch of other stuff.
But if you are starting
from scratch, you will only see
a couple of them, like only this kernel.
So it's nice to see
JupyterLab actually picked up
all the environments that you
have installed on your computer.
Yeah, that's interesting.
So then, okay, it's like...
The first thing you will be
doing is, first of all, try to save the file.
By default, when you open
this Jupyter Notebook, it will not save.
You have to save by going to the file.
Actually, you can right-click here
and you can rename the
notebook and say, okay, like a demo.
Okay, and you can see here
on this sidebar that the file
name has been changed.
Okay, so let's walk through
like what are the different icons here.
Like here you have a save button
and basically it's like this
scissor is like if you want
to cut the cell, let's try to create some cells.
and what you can do is like
you can cut the cell or you
can paste the cells okay so
these are different icons here so
and then if you go here
you can find like jupiter
has two different cells like cell
types one is a code cell and
the other one is a markdown
cell so the markdown cell if
you change here like a
this is the same thing what
you are using when you
are writing the collaborative notebooks okay
so for suppose uh you can use
uh this is a heading for suppose
so this is the biggest heading
you can find like uh and you
can uh double click and edit
basically that cell for suppose
this is a heading to like this
okay so and in case if
you want to change like you
can change the cell type okay
from markdown to code or
code to markdown because
accidentally sometimes you try when
you create a cell it will
create by default the code cell
and you want to change it
into markdown you can do that one
So yeah.
Sorry.
I just want to say that
it's great that you can either
choose code or markdown.
Markdown is great if you want
to document a certain part of your code
so that the documentation is
close to the code snippet that
you want to emphasize.
Nice.
So let's do just a print command.
I'm using a different
Icelandic keyboard, so I need
to find the right keys.
This is how you try to
use the print command.
What you can see is by
default, we have here, if you
scroll a bit, by default, it is a Python kernel.
And when you execute the
cell, it will print this print command.
You can also try to create a list
let's look at some code
examples here okay what you can see is like
if you do this one it
will print all the numbers up
to three okay three is excluded
so we see only zero one and two okay
Let's try some more examples.
For suppose if you want
to like some numbers from zero to three,
what you can do is like,
I think I missed one closing bracket.
Yeah.
Now, when you execute it, you
can see that you can do
the summation up to three.
You don't need to use print command.
You can actually, let's suppose
I copy this cell,
from sum and when you execute it.
The way you execute is you
can use a shift and enter.
Then you can use the print command
or you can directly run the
command you are using it.
The reason we recommend using
a print command is for suppose
if I add here, instead of sum
up to three, let's say sum up to five,
what you see is you can
only see the second line which is executed.
You can only see the output
of the second one.
In case if you want to
see the outcome of the first one,
you try to use the print command.
In that way, you can see both the outputs.
That's the kind of it.
So then let's go to the magic comments.
[name], do you have any magic comments?
What is magic comments?
What is your favorite magic?
ls ls nice although you can do
that in other ways as well but uh
but yeah i mean one can also
uh time it is uh it's a nice
one as well so what we show
here yeah indeed it's uh so yeah useful
agree yeah let's try time it okay
so basically it's like uh when
you're uh we call it magic commands
because it's like uh these
are outside the python uh commands okay
so for suppose uh if you
are using a bash or anything then
you can use uh an inline commands
or it can be a multi-line commands okay so
Here what we are looking is
when you type %ls, what you
see is all the files which are listed here.
You can also see onto
your left whatever the files I
have in that particular folder.
Let's also look at the time it command.
Let me create a new cell
and I'm not sure whether the
PWD works for everyone.
Since I was using Linux,
it might be working for me.
But in case if you're using Windows
or some other operating system,
some of the commands might not
be native, so no need to worry about it.
Suzanne's favorite command is timeit.
Let's try the timeit.
Oops, I need to enter because
it's a time it requires some input.
Basically what the time it does
is like it tries to time
the execution of that particular cell.
So it runs multiple times
and gives you like how much
time did it spend to execute this.
so here what we are doing
is like we are just doing for
up to range 100 okay trying to see like
what is x square okay and
what you can see is like it
runs for 100 000 loops the same command like
and then each loop is taking, sorry,
100 into 1,000, and that
is 100,000, and each loop is
taking about 3.5 microseconds, okay?
So this, you can use
the collaborator notebook to write
how much time does it send.
It's the first exercise you're
going to do later, first or second, I think.
So then let's look at
some more commands here.
let's take a bash for suppose
and if I want to like
change let's see what I have here in
Okay.
So what I have, what I
was doing here is like you
can have multiple commands like LS,
and you can change the path
and see what is there already
in the two parent directories before.
Okay, so, and
let's uh do one more thing
let's create one more cells more cells
and you can create more
cells by pressing this plus button
so let's take another bash and
i was taking uh this uh
commands from the notebook itself like uh
I was just copying it from, uh,
if you scroll down, you can
see some of the, uh, what we
are doing is like, uh, we
are copying these lines.
Okay.
Let's copy this one, this bash
and try to execute it here.
So, yep.
So this is all about cell
magic and line magic.
The cell magic starts with
two percentages and the line
magic starts with one percentage.
And it is like a kind of,
what we have is like whether we
want to apply it to the whole
cell or one cell, okay?
so after this uh so [name]
like uh you have like shall
we go to the exercise then
Yeah, I think that's a good idea.
So just one comment that I mean,
if some of these line magics
don't work for you, don't worry about that.
If you find them useful
for your workflow, use them.
Otherwise, I mean, you can ignore it.
It's not something that you
need to learn here or now,
but we find them useful.
So I thought we thought
we'd share them with you.
But now I think it's time
you try out these exercises 1 to 3.
If you find number 1 too
easy, then just skip.
And if you are experienced,
try exercise 2, for example,
for a larger number.
in the Fibonacci sequence and
try different ways, maybe parallelize
it if you really want to.
So try out your best and
time your little code.
And then we come back in,
let's say, how much time should we give them?
maybe 15 20 minutes i don't know
and then write please write
in the notes document when you are done
so that we know if uh if
it's a good time to get back
otherwise we say uh we are back
here so back in 15 minutes
in 15 minutes yeah bye
hello welcome back so i hope
uh you tried uh these exercises
which are here uh in the
break like basically it's like uh
so the first one is
basically it's like let's uh
walk through some of these exercises and uh
Okay, the first task is
basically it's like in case
if you haven't installed, like try
to run some basic commands
like opening a Python notebook
and creating new cells and saving it.
I hope you tried it.
And then in the next exercise,
it is mostly like writing
your own Fibonacci numbers.
Like basically it's like
a Fibonacci sequence and printing
out the Fibonacci numbers.
and timing it out so let
me quick take a quick look i
hope i see that a lot
of people tried the exercise one and two so yes
So yeah, this is basically, you
can see the solution also in case
if you want to compare the
solutions, it is also available
on the course page.
So here, basically what we are
doing is we are printing
the Fibonacci numbers, which is the
sum of the previous two numbers.
and later timing it out for
the first 10 numbers.
So you can see that it
took about 238 nanoseconds for
running this range 10.
And the next task is
like increasing the numbers from 10
to like say bigger, I think
it's about million or so.
and try to time it out.
Then you can actually speed
up your algorithms.
There are different ways of
speeding up your algorithms.
This is one way, but you
might come across your own favorite way.
Try to write it in
the shared collaborative notebooks,
how much time you got.
It's interesting to see people
might have different approaches for
the same problem.
Then,
uh yeah there is one thing
which is like uh when now
so far you have created the cells you know
how to write like execute the
cells like uh and uh you know
how to also uh add a markdown
okay and then like uh write
your own notes narrative notes
for this markdown okay
so then on the top here
like basically it's like what you
can do is like you can restart the kernels
and uh basically clear all
the outputs in case if you
want to share these files to
to your friends or anyone then
you can choose this uh like option
So there is a, yeah.
And when you are executing
the cells, it matters like
how you are executing.
Like for suppose, in case
in the previous couple of minutes back,
we looked at this, how to
print this, the for loop basically.
And this is the first
cell which I executed.
And then later I tried
to create another cell on the
top, which is now I is equal to three, okay?
If I execute this cell now,
the number will change from 20
to the new number 23, which you
can see in the square brackets.
This square brackets tells you
that the order of execution.
So it really matters.
And now if you say that print i,
what happens is it takes
the number 3 instead of 2 if
you go by sequence order from top to bottom.
so it really like you
should be very careful when
you are creating the jupiter
like notebooks try to keep it in the order
and yeah so that's about this exercises
so always always restart the
kernel run all cells before
you share a notebook with other
people yeah and are there any
reasons when one should not restart the kernel
Sometimes it really depends.
I suppose if you have it too,
I see most of the people,
if they're in the machine
learning or deep learning, like
they want to train their models.
So sometimes the training might
take a longer time.
So in that case, it's
better avoid, like you can save
a lot of time in case
not restarting the kernels unless
it is needed, you know.
So restarting the kernel
actually means removing all
variables from memory, all
initialization of functions, and
then basically all data which
has not been saved to a file is lost.
Yes.
So if you have a time-consuming notebook,
then you might think
twice before restarting.
Or else it would be nice to save the files.
And then if there is
a possibility of reopening and
loading the weights, it would
be also another way of just in
case if you want to restart.
Yeah.
So, okay.
Then that's all about the exercises.
And let's go back.
Why Jupyter?
Yeah.
Why do you want to use Jupyter?
What are the pros and
cons of using Jupyter?
[name], like... Yeah, so I mean,
I think I mean, Jupyter is really great
for interactive work and
for notebooks which are not that complex.
I think once you get the workflow settled,
then what I typically like to
do is to transform it into
a Python script and run that as...
We run that in production mode.
And also what I dislike a
little bit about Jupyter is that
it's not so trivial to version control.
I mean, as we do mention,
there is the nbdime package, which
can help you with that.
But I think it is much
easier to version control
Python scripts instead.
So that's a little bit of a bottleneck.
But yeah.
For me, it's like I
use Jupyter for teaching mostly.
It's really nice for supposing this course.
A lot of people might
be using different systems like
Windows or Linux or something.
Once you confine them to
a particular environment,
It's nice to share, like,
teaching the Jupyter.
Like, what you will be seeing later is,
like, Python for scientific
computing, like, in different ways,
NumPy and other things.
So, it's, like, it's nice
when you are sharing the notebooks, okay?
I also use for mostly for,
yeah, most of my teaching.
It's nice for the students
to try, basically.
Then, why not Jupyter?
Okay, I mean...
So it's always good to know
what is good and bad about any tools we use.
So [name], in case if you
want to find another alternative
or what is your preference?
Yeah, then I think, yeah,
I'll go to scripting after a while.
So, and especially, I mean, if
I don't want to, if I, as I said,
if I have my, if I already know
what I want to achieve
with my workflow, everything is set
up, then I would just run that as a script.
Then I don't have to
babysit that notebook all the time.
And I can just run four
hours or whatever it needs.
And then I can check the results later.
But for visualizing data, for
doing things interactively, tweaking,
maybe a notebook that I got
from a friend and using my
own data, Jupyter is great for that.
Yeah, I completely agree.
So what do we have then?
I think it's actually the
end of our lesson.
I would just like to say
that please do check the notes document
and see how other people
have been using Jupyter and
other ideas that they prefer.
And thank you for those of
you that have been sharing
your experiences with us.
And we will post these Q&As
on the workshop page so you
can refer to them later.
Yep.
Thanks.
Thank you all.
And then we will now take a break
until 10 o'clock if you're in
Sweden or 11 in Finland.
So take some time to stretch
your legs and get something to drink.
And we'll see you back in nine minutes.
Yep.
Bye.
Right, and welcome back from
the break to the lesson about NumPy.
I've got [name]
here with me, who's a
real NumPy wizard, actually.
So I'll ask stupid questions,
and hopefully [name] will be
able to answer them all.
I will do my best.
Yeah, thank you, and welcome,
everyone, to NumPy.
It's the first scientific
package we're going to discuss
during this course, and we're
going to discuss many of them.
And we're going to start
with NumPy because it's the OG.
It's the foundation package.
It's the thing that
makes scientific computing possible
with Python.
It is super useful just by
itself to learn about and to know.
But it's also the basis of
many of the other packages we
will talk about today and
tomorrow, like Pandas and X-Ray
and things like that.
They're built on top of NumPy.
So...
Well, what is NumPy?
NumPy allows us to work with
data, with a huge grid of numbers.
If we are doing astrophysics
and we are looking at the
stars, in the end, it's going to
be a grid of data.
If we're looking at
brains and neuroscience, our brain
signal is going to be huge amounts of numbers.
temperatures across the globe,
they're all numbers.
And that's what NumPy is going to do.
And the main data structure for
that is an array.
So we should first talk about arrays.
So you might think if we
want to work with a huge
amount of numbers, we have something for that.
We have Python lists.
And Python has as list, and
these lists are very useful
and they're very flexible because
you can put anything you want in a list.
We can have lists with
like integer values, floating
point numbers, strings.
We can put lists inside of
other lists and objects that
makes them very flexible.
It's very good, but it also
makes them very slow.
If we put all of our
numbers in a Python list and
we want to do something with
them, say we want to add one
to every element in the list.
then a normal Python list, we
need to go element by element
because, well, it could be anything.
So for each element, we have to check,
like, what does adding one
to this thing actually mean?
If we have a number and
a string, they mean different things,
so we have to go step by step.
And it just goes slow.
This is not good for science.
We want fast operation.
We want to be able to
do the same operation on a
huge amount of data all at once.
And that's where an array comes in.
So to demonstrate this, so
in this claim about speed,
maybe we can showcase this a little bit, [name].
So let's create just a Python
list with a bunch of numbers
and then do something to those numbers.
Okay, well, maybe we've got
an example here in our, so
I'll just maybe copy this.
And then go to my Jupyter.
I'll just make a new cell
and paste this in here.
So what does this do, this code?
It does nothing in the
nothing obvious because it
doesn't print anything.
But I guess we could say print.
B or something, right?
Oh, we could.
Oh, that's a lot of numbers.
Okay, yeah.
It's a long number.
We created two Python lists.
Okay, maybe we get rid of this first.
Okay, so we have A and B.
And we have a list of the
numbers 0 to 10,000 minus 1.
And a bunch of zeros.
Okay, let's do something to this list.
So...
For example, can we square every number?
So we have A and raise
all those numbers to the power of 2.
Let's square them.
OK, so we've got A. And we
want to do A. I don't know.
And maybe assign them to B.
So we now have a list B,
which is all zeros at the moment.
But it's the same size as list A. Yes.
So let's make it so that we loop over A,
over all the elements, we
square them and write them to B. So, yeah.
B. Do we want to append them or?
Just create a for i in
range length of a. Just create an i iterator.
OK.
Or just copy it from the materials.
I guess I could copy it.
Or you can.
But this already demonstrates.
OK, so we want to do something.
We want to square the numbers.
Look how long it takes us
already to do this.
Wait, we have to write a for loop.
Yes.
How do we want to do it?
Do we want to, like, enumerate over them?
Do we want to make an index?
And, I mean, this is not
that bad in terms of how it works in Python.
I mean, this is still quite readable.
But it could be better, right?
Yeah.
I mean, if I do this now, it runs, right?
It runs.
Okay, yeah, it runs pretty quick.
So this is how you do it.
And hopefully now B contains,
like, the same as A,
but everything is squared.
Well, you can just print B or
just put B in there.
And do we have it?
We do.
OK.
Whoa, the numbers go very, very big.
But Python is good.
That one is good with Python.
Hey, but now let's do it in NumPy.
So that was a little bit painful.
We maybe want to know how
long it takes because we have
this time magic, right?
Oh, but to be fair, let's add
it to cell 10 and not this
time because this is the setup.
Ah, true.
If you want to be really fair about it,
you should only time the for
loop that does the squaring of the values.
True.
Time it like this, right?
Yeah.
OK.
Yeah, we can have that.
Let's run that.
I mean, it looked pretty fast.
Well, it's only 10,000.
Python is not that slow.
So it takes about, what is it?
Nine, almost 10 milliseconds.
Not a bad $10,000.
But let's see how this
works, how this would work in NumPy.
So the big difference in
NumPy is that we're not going
to create a Python list.
We're going to create a NumPy array.
So can you now create a NumPy array?
Hang on.
There's like a million ways
to create a NumPy array, aren't there?
We had a lot of them.
That's true.
There are a million ways.
Yeah.
And the first way is actually
if we have a Python list
with the numbers that we want.
Yeah.
If you want to make a
NumPy array with that, that's
like the first way to do it.
The first way to create a
NumPy array is that if you
have a Python list, you can
change it into a NumPy array.
Maybe you can show it at work.
So you can do np.array.
And then as first argument, you
give it the Python list.
That will create a NumPy array
for you with the same
contents as that Python list.
So let's create, let's do A. Well.
Okay, maybe, yeah, call it A
array or an A NumPy.
Yeah, that's good.
That's good.
Okay.
And then do we want to make
a copy of B as well as an array?
Why not?
Okay.
But let's, just to demonstrate
this, do it differently.
So with A, we're just going
to copy the... Yeah.
When B, maybe use another function.
So let's use the zeros function of NumPy.
So it should be all zeros.
This is a second way to
create a NumPy array.
We need to give it a size, right?
Yes.
Was it like this?
No, you just give it as
a, actually, I actually don't know.
It's just the first, it's
just the first parameter of zeros.
We want a 10,000 of them.
Okay.
So we want 10,000.
We want them just flat.
For this example, yes, because
we want to replicate what we
did with the Python list.
So then we just run this.
It won't do any.
This is a little tip.
You can use underscores in
your numbers to separate.
Like this?
Yes.
So now you see that we wanted 10,000.
But you only wrote 1,000 there.
Ah.
And this is why it's there.
So underscores and the little Python thing,
if you write numbers in Python,
you can put underscores inside
your numbers, and Python will ignore them.
But it's very useful for us
humans to read the number.
And now it's easier to see.
Yeah, this is 10,000.
Much easier to read.
OK.
And then we want a new cell to do this.
And we'll start with the time at r.
If we want to raise them, now let's do it.
And then we want to just.
OK, so now we want B and
P. We want that to be A and P squared, right?
Yeah.
So it was, was it like this?
No, it's two stars.
Two stars.
Too many different programs.
Yes, it's a MATLAB.
It's an R, I think.
Yeah.
But you're going to crash.
So we don't need to write
any for loop for this, which
is a main NumPy thing.
So a NumPy array is an object,
and it supports many of these things,
like adding things to
it, subtracting things, and
now squaring things.
Is this it already?
Like, this is?
This is it.
We don't need anything else.
OK, let's try this.
That's all we need.
This?
It takes longer because it
ran the loop 10,000 times because
it was so fast.
So now we're at 63
microseconds instead of 9.7.
Okay.
We're an order of a magnitude faster.
And this is just 10,000
numbers, not that big.
But imagine if you have
like your astronomer, you have
like gigabytes of data loaded up
and you just want to, I
don't know, remove a value from
it or like do something to that data.
This is why we need NumPy.
We like to use NumPy for
these sort of things.
For one, we don't have to write for loops.
And second, it's way faster.
Okay, well, what's next in the lesson?
Let's see.
So we already looked a little
bit on how to create arrays.
We saw two ways we can create from a list.
We can use NumPy functions.
Okay, give me a bunch of zeros.
I think that, yeah, there are a bunch here.
I think A range is good
to mention because I use that
one personally a lot.
So very often I want an
array with the numbers zeroed up to a number.
And that's a range.
You also have linspace.
Maybe interesting to point out.
So with linspace, you can create, like,
increasing numbers, but it's more flexible.
So with linspace, you could
say... Wasn't there an exercise
about it, actually?
Yeah, there is.
We have, yes.
Okay, so, okay, we'll leave
it to the exercise.
But before we go, yeah,
we should talk about...
saving and loading.
So if we have, once we have
our data in a nice NumPy array,
we can save it and save
it with the save function.
So maybe we can demonstrate that quick.
Yes, we can.
Maybe save our array and
load it back again.
Is it mp.save, or is
it... Oh, it's mp.save.
And then you give it whatever
you want to save.
Say we want to save the B array.
Yeah.
And then you presumably need to
give it a filename, right?
Yeah, but the other way around.
So we do first the filename.
I just had to look it up.
I always have to look this up.
Is it filename first or variable first?
It's first the filename, and
then the variable you want to save.
and yeah and i like to use the npi
as an extension yeah i like to use
that let's see okay that saved
it to disk so now yeah now
you should have it there you
should have it there somewhere
you called it test save
I did.
Oh, there it is.
There it is.
Can you actually see that
on my shared screen?
I hope you do.
I think so, yeah.
Check with the… It's all the
way in the bottom, but yeah, we can.
Yeah, because I named the test.
Good.
And to load it, it's the np.load… function.
So if we wanted to do
np.load, then... You just give it a file name.
Now it's easier.
We probably want to save
it to some variable if we load it as well.
True.
We have A and B. Let's do C. Sure.
And then...
Maybe just try that.
Okay, it's loaded.
Okay, one bonus thing.
Can you quickly create a new cell?
I want to show you another NumPy function.
So now I want to know whether this works.
So if this works, then B
and C, they should be exactly the same matrix.
Yep.
And there's a function for that.
It's called np.array underscore equal.
And you give two arrays.
So in this case, B and C.
And then it will tell us,
are they the same array?
Or do they contain the same numbers?
And it is.
So it will very quickly go
over all the elements and
check if they're equal.
And they are.
So this worked.
Okay.
I think it's time to
let our participants now play
around with NumPy a bit.
Yep.
All right.
Ah, but before we do that,
we need to explain a little
bit about data types.
So now we've been enjoying
NumPy and it's like amazing speed.
But the reason why NumPy is so fast is
that all our elements in
our array, they need to have
the same data type.
And so if you're familiar
with computer science, you might know
what I talk about, but if
you're super new to Python, this
may be a new thing, that
variables in Python can have different types.
Like we have an int type,
and int means a whole number.
We have a float type, which
means a number that can have
a decimal dot inside.
Pi 3.14, that would be a floating point.
We have strings, which are
these things in quotation marks
that we keep writing with this
like a bit of text.
These are different data
types, different types of data.
Inside a NumPy array, all
the elements, they need to be the same type.
And it's relevant in NumPy.
So each array...
keeps track of what date data
type it is what and as yeah
it's stored in in in D type
um so maybe we can quickly check
for one of our list in
our notebook like what's the D
type of this what's the data
type of this data it's
probably floating maybe check it
for A and check it for
B because they might actually be different
We created, I think when we created a,
we created a bunch of
integer values in like this.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's an integer.
It's even relevant that it's
a 64-bit integer, which is
something in normal Python you
absolutely never have to deal with.
But in NumPy, these things are relevant.
Hey, and our b now is
a floating point of 64.
That's probably because we
started squaring very huge numbers.
Likely.
Likely, yeah.
Okay, but so that's the thing.
And it comes up in the
exercise as well, that you
have different data types.
That's why I want to mention it.
All right, it's high time to
go to our first exercise now, I think.
Yeah.
Okay, so to you, all
the participants, we have our first exercise.
It's an exercise in creating
NumPy arrays in various ways.
So go check that out.
I think we will give them
Given that it's relatively
late already, maybe we try to
keep it to five minutes.
One reminder, what you absolutely
have to do, as always in Python,
if you want to use
something that's not base Python,
you need to import it.
So for anything that we,
for the solutions, we always
assume you imported NumPy as np.
Yes.
Very good.
All right.
Good luck.
We will see you back in five minutes.
We're not actually back yet.
Now we're back.
Welcome back, everybody.
OK, I hope you did well with the exercise.
[name], maybe we can go
through the solutions really quick.
Yeah, right.
So we wanted first to
do some arrays, basically.
creating them with arrange
and with linspace.
And I mean, I run this.
What's different?
There's little dots here.
There's dots there.
Yeah, that means that the
second one, they're floating point numbers.
They're numbers with decimal point inside.
So we talked about D type.
Can I just do this and then
tell it to do ints?
Yes, you can.
And now they're integers, yeah.
Yeah, okay.
And with the A range as well.
With the A range, you can
tell it, I need them as floats, if you want to.
Yeah.
This will sometimes come up.
So when you try to add
float to integers another way
around, it may, at some
point, NumPy may complain.
Let's see, the second one
was creating some random numbers.
yeah okay so so when this is relevant
so say if we if we create
um uh can you create a three
by two array of random float numbers
so it's NumPy dot random dot random
and then you give it the shape
as a tuple so we need
another pair of round brackets yeah
so a three by two array three
by two yeah so if you just do that yes yeah
If we execute that, we
get floating point numbers, okay?
But what if I now were to
say, no, I don't want them as floats.
I want them as integer.
But maybe at the end, do .stype.
Yeah, you can also do it like that.
But maybe show a different way of doing it.
All right, this works, okay.
And then the other one would be asType?
Yeah, at the end you do .asType.
So if you already have an existing array,
and now we want to convert
it to some different type, you can use .asType.
Integers, yeah.
Exactly, you can write it like that.
So now I've created random
numbers as integer values, but
now they're all zero.
Because they were between 0 and
1, we now convert them to integers.
Integers only store like whole numbers.
So they all get rounded down
to the nearest whole number,
which in this case, they're
always rounded down to 0.
Is it if I do this with a d-type int?
You should get the same thing, I think.
Oh, it doesn't actually do it.
So random, I guess.
Random doesn't do it.
But can we make random
give us, like, integers?
With a different function, we can.
So there is a function called randint.
I mean, can we...
The thing is, how do I
remember all of these different options?
That is a good question.
Well, the first answer would be
is to check out the
great NumPy API documentation.
So in this course material,
every time we mention a function,
these are all links.
So you can click on them.
And it will take you in
a new tab, probably.
It will take you straight
to the NumPy documentation about
what this does.
And now in the NumPy
documentation, okay, these are random numbers.
So how do we create integers now?
We can, well, yeah, it's already there.
We can also go up one
level in the API documentation.
Okay.
There it is, breadcrumbs.
You can go to random
sampling, for example, and it will.
Like that one?
Yeah.
And it will, you can scroll
and it will give you all
the, like, different functions
for, like, computing random numbers
and other things.
There are so many functions.
So that's one way.
Another way I would like to
show you is inside the notebook itself.
Okay.
Give me a second to get
back to my notebook.
Yeah.
Because it's a bit difficult
with the... Now with the things...
Yes.
No, now our screen share is a bit wonky.
Yeah, that's because my screen
is off work entirely.
I'll put this aside and redo it.
Let's get back to the notebook.
Right, so how do I do it?
Inside the notebook, of course,
we have our big friend, tab completion.
So if we just have NumPy.random
and you just pause for a
bit and we press tab, it will
show you all the different
functions that start with random.
So there's our friend random
integers if we want to
generate random integers.
It's right there.
Then if you want to know how to use
that function, what you can do
is now just append a question
mark to what you have now.
Like this?
And then execute.
And then execute that.
Ah.
It will give you the
documentation for that function
right inside your notebook.
This also works in an
IPython terminal, by the way.
That's nice.
So that's useful.
Okay.
Hey, but we need to keep going.
Yes.
Okay, so with random integers,
we can create like numbers
between, like random numbers between
one and 20 or something, if we want them.
All right.
Yeah, we already showed how
the IO works and, well, maybe
quickly show how to reshape an array.
I think we haven't talked
about, actually, we haven't talked about that.
So right now, all the
arrays we've been creating
were one-dimensional arrays, basically
just long lists of numbers.
But a really useful feature
of these arrays is that
we can create two-dimensional grids
or three-dimensional grids or
like 12-dimensional grids.
Let's see, so now you give it
as a two, yeah, you have
one pair of round brackets too many there.
I think it's just... No, I don't.
Oh, no.
It's just that it's... Let's just
go to a random... Yeah.
Let's just do floats.
Let's do random floats.
And then we had three and two, right?
Yeah.
And then we want it to reshape.
So we can reshape that to other shapes.
So what can we do?
Well, we can reshape it as a 1 by 6.
That works.
Or... So, yeah, you need to assign it to X.
So X equals X dot vision.
Yeah, so now it's a flat list.
So this is, yeah, things we
can do, three to two, one to six.
Can we reshape this as a
four by three array?
That was like the exercise.
Four by three.
But there's not enough.
No, it's not.
Yeah, it's not going to work, right?
So it needs to be.
There's not enough data there.
We have six numbers.
They need to remain six numbers.
So we can put them in different shapes.
But they need to be six numbers.
OK.
Yeah.
OK, let's go and change topics
and do a bit of math on these arrays.
We've now seen many different
ways of creating them and
shaping them and that they have data types.
But now, what if we actually
want to do some science on
them, at least some math on them?
So can you maybe copy
from the lesson materials and just create?
Yeah, let me get the
lesson materials back to the
shape that people can see.
So like this one, yes?
Yeah, let's copy that.
So that piece of code gives
us two little arrays to work with.
A and B. And then we add them.
So, yeah, basics first.
Like, basics first.
So we can erase, we can
add them together with plus.
Or...
with the add function of NumPy.
They do the same thing.
We can multiply them together
in different ways.
And like if we want
proper mathematical matrix multiplication,
we use this add sign that
you also use in email addresses.
Or you use the NumPy dot function.
Yeah.
It doesn't do anything because
it doesn't print.
Well, it does something, but
it doesn't print anything.
You can add some prints there or.
So maybe print A and then.
What was it?
B. Yeah.
So maybe show the matrix multiplication.
So maybe print A, print B,
and then also print E, which was
a, or F, which was a matrix multiplication.
Okay, well, it's a bit hard to read.
It'll print them right after each other.
But we have two, two by
two matrices, and we can matrix multiply them.
We could do other things.
We can subtract them.
We can multiply things.
We can divide.
We can compute square roots.
But rather than us showing
that, I think it's better
for the participants to try
that out for themselves.
Yeah.
Oh, this is way better.
That sounds like a very good idea.
Okay, so let's go to the second exercise.
We will give you five minutes again.
To create, to...
yeah, to create some arrays
and play around a bit
with matrix multiplication, doing
things like computing the sum
along some dimension.
We will let you play with it first,
and then we will cover
the solution, what we will see.
Okay, we will see you.
So it is 11.36 now, so meet
you back at 40, I would say.
Yes.
Let's be quick about this.
And bye for now.
See you later.
See you.
Okay, and welcome back.
So at the moment, you have
had a look at the exercise
two, looking at these
different matrix multiplication functions.
So multiply, it sounds like
multiply should do what we want
if we want a matrix multiplication, right?
But does it?
It doesn't.
Multiply does element-wise multiplication.
And if you actually want
proper matrix multiplication, you want
to use the dot function.
Okay.
I generally advise to just use
star and the at sign.
Yeah.
Uh, which do the same thing
as these, uh, NumPy functions.
So we could, we also, we
could also say they're syntactic sugar.
Uh, so they, they just look
nicer in your code, uh, and a bit more clear.
Yeah, because we're, we're used from,
from our school math to have
this sort of infix notation, right?
Like where the, the, the
operators in the middle.
Exactly.
And then there was
something about specifying the axis.
Yeah.
Are we doing dance now or something?
No, it's okay.
Yeah.
So, well, when you use the NumPy functions,
a benefit of that is
that these functions have loads
of different parameters that you can set.
So if you want to compute
the sum of an array, there's
a function for that.
It's called sum.
And by default, sum will just
sum all the values in your
array together and give you
a single number back, like complete total.
But what if you want
to compute the row-wise sum?
So for each row, we want the sum.
Or for each column, we want the sum.
So this is where the
axis parameter comes in.
When you specify axes, you can...
You can tell it.
So rows is axis 0, columns is axis 1.
And then you can do
the same for three-dimensional,
four-dimensional, five-dimensional matrices,
and the axis just increases.
It's a very useful thing to do.
That brings us a little bit
to how do we index and slice up arrays.
So now we've been working
all the time with, like, we
create an array and did something
to the entire array.
What if we want to do
something to part of an array?
Like only the first row.
Yeah.
So then we need to select that first row.
So this is an important NumPy thing to do.
And you can already see
now from the materials, it uses
the same syntax as Python lists do.
So NumPy arrays try to be
a little bit like Python
lists, only they're much more powerful,
because for one, they're
multidimensional, so we can do things as...
take the first three rows
and then also take the first three columns.
And you can even do
complexing, and maybe we can show
that in a notebook.
We can index this really
specific elements from an array
from multiple dimensions by giving
it two tuples.
But maybe you can copy that.
I'll just copy the whole bit
and go to my, oh, my Jupyter.
Let's put this here.
And then paste it.
So we're making a matrix named
A that is four by four.
Yeah.
And then we want the first
row, the first column.
But that final one is interesting.
The final one, it selects two values.
We can select specific elements
from a multidimensional array by
giving two tuples.
we give one tuple for each
dimension in the array.
There's a two-dimensional array, so
we give it two tuples.
And the first tuple contains the values,
not the values, the indexes
along the first dimension, and
then the second tuple gives
the indexes across the second dimension.
So, in that we say, okay, we want,
value at index zero alongs
the first dimension and one
alongs the second dimension and then
as a second value we want the value
that is index one along
the first dimension and one
amongst the second dimension so
it's it's difficult to wrap
your head around but it's a
really powerful way of let's see
what we get if you need
arbitrary unit uh this is great
yeah if you if you want arbitrary things
The original is 0, 1, 2, 3,
4, 5, 6, 7, up to 15.
And then we want the, we say
we want of the first row, the second element.
No, no, that's not how it works.
So, so the,
What is it?
The first tuple tells you we
want from the first... We want
from the first row.
So the first tuple deals with dimension 0.
Ah, so it's the first row.
And the second tuple deals
with dimension 1.
So it's just... We want the
first row and the second row.
And we want from those
the first, the second element
and the second element again.
Yes.
pairwise.
So it's a little bit difficult
to wrap your head around.
Oh, yes.
So if I wanted like the third row
as well, and the same, I
would want I would go like,
and which element in a third row do you want?
The first again?
Or the second?
Second again?
Okay, so that should be the right?
Yeah.
So what if you wanted to?
What if you wanted to select the 11?
The 11, then I would have to
go not one in a second,
but three, I think, right?
Yeah.
11 is the last one.
Yes, you got it.
So, okay.
I think this example is...
If you mastered this, you
have mastered indexing in NumPy.
Compared to this one, all
the other ones are easy because
they behave a little bit like
you would index a Python list.
It's in the same way.
Okay.
Yeah.
Um, so, okay.
One other really powerful way
we should definitely show is,
uh, Boolean, uh, indexing.
So what if we, if we take this matrix A,
which is a nice, nice example,
what if you want all the
elements that are larger than five?
C equals A. Is it A?
Yeah.
A is larger than five like this.
That would work.
And now the question is,
why does that work?
I guess what we could also
do is just a larger five.
Yeah, print that.
Because that would get.
That won't.
Let's remove these other prints.
We already know what a looks like.
And we're not really interested in
B at the moment.
Maybe first print, what does that do?
That's a Python statement.
A is larger than 5.
What does that do?
It does something to our array.
Yeah.
So it turns it into a Boolean.
So a larger than five will
give us a new array.
Now it's a data type Boolean
and will give for each
element, whether it's true or
false, that that element is larger than five.
And we can use that
to index an array.
This is called Boolean indexing.
So if you have an array
with values true and false, depicting
which elements you want to select, yes
or no, for each element, if
you have such an array, you can
use that as an index into another array.
They have to be the same size.
They would have to be exactly the same.
If I want to use... If I
want to be a bit...
more complex than I need to be.
And say I wanted to select
the first five elements.
Could I just give it make
an array that is true?
No, you don't make them string values.
Yeah, true.
Not string value, true.
OK, so true, true.
Let's keep it at three.
OK.
And then I want to select a.
I want to do that.
Maybe get rid of the printc
then at the end.
Yes.
On it.
Yeah.
What happens?
Well, you're going to error.
So it needs to match at
least one of the dimensions.
So if you just.
If I did.
If you add two falses to that.
It's four by four.
So four should be fine.
Oh, sorry.
It's four by four.
Yeah.
So four is fine.
So now it's all true.
So now you can turn like rows off and on.
Okay.
Okay, so yeah, it's high time.
We have 10 minutes left.
Yep.
But for our lesson plan,
it's important that you guys
try exercise three.
And after exercise three, we'll
get to our final point of our lesson.
So I would invite all
the participants to play around
a bit with indexing, which
is what exercise three is all about.
But exercise three will also
be uh give you a surprising result
so go try it um and
get your surprising result and
we'll be right back so we
will give you again four minutes
to do this we'll be back at
55. um to reveal the surprise
and talk about our final point okay good luck
And we are back.
Welcome, everybody.
I hoped you had some fun slicing arrays
and maybe found something
interesting that we create in
the first line here in the exercise.
We create an identity matrix.
of four by four.
And then in the second line,
we use this slicing thing, we
select a single column from our array.
And we assign it to B. Okay,
so now we have array A and B.
And then we modify a value in another way.
We didn't really talk about it yet,
how that works, but you can
see now in the exercise, you
can assign values to slices and things.
But let's quickly run that in the notebook.
So can you quickly run that,
[name], and see what happens?
What happens to matrices A and B?
Let's see.
When we do this.
brand new cell.
What's the history before, but
let's ignore that.
Okay, do that, and then show
us what A and B look like afterwards.
So A, I'll actually, I'll
add some print statements.
Print A here, and print.
So can you print A and B
both, like, at the end?
And that's for clarity add just a line up.
Oh, yeah.
This is perfect.
Yeah.
Right.
Let's see.
So A is an identity matrix.
One is on the diagonal.
Zero is everywhere else.
And then we do some… We
assign something to B. Mm-hmm.
And now we print A. This is A, actually.
Yeah.
And this is B. We
didn't change anything about A, though.
Yeah, but it has changed.
So this is an important thing to note.
When we selected a single column
out of A and we assigned it
to B, what we did is create
what is known as a view.
So NumPy is designed to do...
NumPy is designed to deal
with huge grids of data.
And if it can avoid it,
it will not copy all the data all of the time.
So it's super fast in
selecting a single column.
And the way why it is that fast is
that it will not actually
create in memory a duplicate
copy of that column, just
that column, and assign it to B. No, it will...
keep the same underlying memory
in your computer memory.
And we'll just like create,
well, we have now a new made
array B and it just uses this column.
Um, but it will not actually
copy, uh, copy any data.
So now array A and array
B, they use the same bit of
memory in, uh, in your bigger computer memory.
How does it know where the column is?
Ah, so it's the data pointer.
So if you go to array A
or array B, they have a dot data attribute.
Is that your question?
Well, actually, like, how does it?
I mean, if it wants,
you can select anything from an array.
How does it?
not how does it know where those
that data is, but not have
to make a copy so we can
do things know where it is fast.
Okay, well for that it's so For
that an array it contains
three things it contains one a
pointer To the big data array in memory
and that should be for a and b
that should now be this like
point to the same memory And
then it has an attribute called
size it has an attribute called
shape and it has an
attribute called strides which
tell that array, OK, which part of
that big block of memory, which
part is my data array, and
what kind of shapes do we have,
and where do we find all the data?
So those are just attributes of the array.
So basically, it relies on
it being always the same size, all the rows
and the columns being a fixed
size so that it knows where is what.
But if not necessary,
so reshaping, transposing, or just
selecting a row of a column,
it will not create a new
copy of the data, something to be aware of.
So then if you modify one
array, it may also modify the other array,
like the data in that,
because they share the same memory.
It's now 12 o'clock, so
our final message here is if
you do not want that to happen,
There is a copy function.
So NumPy has a copy.
You can just say, create a copy of 8.
That will actually create a
memory, like a whole new chunk
of memory it will assign, and
it will copy the data there.
So now you actually have
two independent copies that you can work on.
So that's a caveat to do.
Now, we just skimmed really the
tip of the iceberg here.
NumPy is a huge, huge package.
We covered some of the basics for you.
What we did not cover
is the absolutely enormous library
of functions that NumPy has.
If there's anything you want to
do to a bunch of numbers or
a vector or a matrix,
There's probably a NumPy function
to do it for you.
This includes things like linear algebra,
if you want to do
an eigenvalue decomposition, if you
need to invert a matrix, if you
do need to do a linear
regression with that, there's tons
and tons of functions in the NumPy library.
With that, we will end this session.
Is there something like closing
remarks you want to do, [name], before we end?
Well, if you want to get more of an
a structured teaching-like intro to
a bit more detailed NumPy topic.
You can continue reading this lesson
and then there's also an
advanced NumPy lesson that we
will not be teaching this year,
but it is still there.
The materials are still quite good to use.
Yeah, they go really, the
advanced tutorial really goes into
the nitty gritty details of
NumPy, how it works.
So that's one of the, I
would say it's recommended reading
for the interested reader.
Right, but that said, now we've
got an hour lunch break.
We will be back at 1
o'clock here in Finland, which
is accordingly 12 o'clock in Central Europe.
Central European time zones anyway,
also in the Nordics.
I'm subbing in for [name] for a little bit.
But yeah, just essentially saying that.
So we're going on a lunch break.
And after that, we have
in the afternoon, we have pandas and X-array.
First with [name] and then with [name].
So I guess...
uh you can maybe advertise just
uh like 10 seconds what is
x-ray what is pandas oh with with
x-ray is i was just talking
about that with with suza so if
we we showed we have this
dimension like we we take
the sum along dimension zero
or along dimension one what if
we did not have to use
these confusing numbers and we
can just give names to
dimensions and give names to our
rows and our columns our life
will be a lot easier and
that's what we're going to
talk about in excellent
Well, and, um, well, to me, pandas is
if you want anything that looks
a bit like a database, but
isn't a fully fledged database,
um, operating on, on larger amounts of data,
merging them, um, joining
or whatever things you would,
might be doing in Excel or might
be doing in an actual database
and you want to do it in Python.
That's what pandas does for me at least.
All right.
But yeah, let's, uh, let's
go have some lunch.
and see you at the hour,
depending on the time zone.
All right, bye.
Okay.
Hello.
We should be live.
Welcome back from the lunch break.
I'm looking at the wrong camera.
Okay.
Welcome back from the lunch break.
I hope you had a had
enough time to well get lunch
and stretch your legs and it's
going to be a couple
of interesting lessons still.
So I guess I shouldn't spend
too much time here.
I just go
go into it so that we don't go over time.
So first we have Pandas and then XArray.
Go ahead.
Yeah.
So it'll be me with you today again.
And with me, I've got [name].
[name], do you maybe want
to introduce yourself?
I've done that in the morning,
so I'm not going to bore everyone else again.
Hello, that.
So my name is [name].
I'm a researcher in rice in
Sweden, and I work at the memory factory.
So let's get started, I guess.
So in this episode, we
will be introducing a new
package in the morning is so not by already.
So now you'll be looking
at another package pandas.
pandas is a package which can be used to
read data structures which look
like a table or a spreadsheet.
In general, one can say
it's a tabular data.
And we'll see like how we
can use that to make use of in your research.
If your research revolves
around with dealing with such
tabular data in formal spreadsheets
or CSV files, but even
databases for that matter, you
might find something useful.
So there are a lot
of utilities inside pandas.
We won't go through all of them,
but the idea is to give you
a taste of what can be done.
And the best way to
find more information is from
the pandas documentation.
So here we have handpicked
the selected few tutorials from
the pandas documentation itself.
And also they have
the extensive, well-documented functions
and methods that you get from Pandas.
Also, then like an API
documentation, just like you had for NumPy.
Yeah.
I'll try opening this documentation
in the new window so you
can just quickly see it.
Takes a while to load.
Yes.
So you've got all sorts of,
you can get, get us started.
If you want something on
a specific function, um, the
API reference is your friend.
Um, but, and that gives
you, it's fairly similar to the,
um, to the NumPy reference,
um, gets you information
on basically everything you could want to do.
Yeah.
So just as a quick
excursion, let's get back to the lesson.
And then, of course, there
are other ways like the cheat
sheet can be like a one pager.
So if you're getting lost
and you don't know what to
do, you can also take a look
at the cheat sheet and that
should give you a quick recap
of what we have been talking about.
Okay, so without further ado,
let's try to explain things
while going through an example.
So the way you import pandas,
and you should have that
in your condas environment already,
is to write this statement,
import pandas as mpd.
So what we're doing here
is we're putting it into
our current Python interpreter,
and we're giving it a short name.
So we don't have to write
pandas all the time.
I guess you could call it X, Y,
or Z if you wanted to,
but then these are usually variables.
And PD is, I think,
the most common shorthand for pandas.
So if you find code on
the internet on Stack Overflow,
they usually use pandas as PD.
Exactly, yes.
So this is some sort
of convention people use.
uh and what we are going to use
as example data is uh is
a csv file provided in the
pandas source code itself uh
and pandas comes with a lot
of read utilities everything
starts with pd.read underscore something
so if it's a csv file
you do pd.read underscore csv shall we
actually executes this.
So I've already executed this
import panels as PD.
And now if I read this
in, it'll take a while, but now it's executed.
And then we can, I mean,
I've already done this, but we can do it again.
And then we've got the start
of the CSV file, the stuff
with the table of passengers on the Titanic.
Right.
If you go back to the
read operation, let me try to
explain what is going on.
I mean, you can be in the notebook as well.
It's fine.
Yeah, I'm just... Hello.
No worries.
Trying to... Hello.
Hello.
Sorry for the, yeah, I know
my computer was frozen.
I'm sorry.
If you scroll back up a bit.
I scroll back up a bit.
Yeah, so what we're giving as
input to lead CSV is a web address, a URL.
So Pandas makes it easier
for you to download it on the fly.
and it recognizes that from
the HTTPS in the beginning of the string.
But this is not the only
way, like it could be a file
path in your hard disk.
So instead, if you download it yourself
and give it instead of URL string,
which points to the file path,
either related to the current notebook
or an absolute file path, it
should do the right thing, exactly the same.
and you see an argument called index call.
So this is something which
is particular to pandas.
So if you notice the
output below, I'll tell you what
head does in a moment.
You see the first column is marked in bold.
So pandas has a way to
do indexing based on human readable names by
setting the name column as
the index column, it gives it
some, it gives some special powers
so that if you can access
in terms of name any row in
this CSV file, which is loaded as a data frame.
And in the same way, any
column can also be accessed by
the headers in the CSV file.
So the first row is
treated specially usually, if you
want it, that's the default.
and those get assigned as columns.
So if you remember your
episodes from NumPy, every time
we wanted to index a row or
column, you had to use an
integer, that of course is
possible, we'll come to that in a while.
But here, indexes is the name
of the first column and column
names are on the top.
And then,
Typically, you don't want to
see all the rows in the
column, unless you want to.
So that's why we use the head method.
And you can choose to see the default,
which is five rows, but you
can also to see 10 rows as well, or three.
Yeah.
So that's right.
You still get the whole columns, right?
Yeah, you do, you do.
And if it's like 1000
columns, I think it'll try to truncate it,
it'll write dot dot dot and
then try to fight the whole issue overload.
Right.
So, um,
What do we do with this
data, this Pandas data frame now?
Because this is actually, it
is a data frame, right?
Yes.
What is a data frame?
So a data frame is a
representation of this tabular data
in the memory.
And it's a unified format.
So if you read from an Excel file,
which is also possible in
Pandas, they get loaded as a
data frame as well.
So there is no conflict
depending on what format it's coming from.
And also there are some special properties.
For example, if we write
titanic.info, it will see
how they are stored in memory.
Yes, exactly.
So we see that it's a data frame
and it contains a certain
number of columns, 10, 11
columns, actually, if you exclude a name.
And each column, like pandas
being smart, it gets assigned some data type.
So these are from the NumPy,
data types that you saw before.
So if it detects that all
the column values are integers,
it tries to assign it on its own.
But if it's unable to guess
what it is, it will give
a universal type of this object.
So some ticket or camera.
Yeah, exactly.
So maybe it contains some special
Yeah, a combination of letters and numbers.
Right, yeah.
It was unsure, and there
was some missing value, so it was unsure
if it's a float or it's
a string, so that made it second-guess things.
Another way to get an overview
of a data frame is to type the describe method.
So this is very common to do.
And it also give in
some sort of statistical overview
of the data frame.
For example, for every column,
how many values are there?
You see that, for example, in age,
there are some missing
values, probably 714.
And you also see some like
the probability distribution of things,
what is the mean, what is the min,
max, and all percentiles in
between this distribution, the
standard deviation as well, if
you understand that.
We can get maybe some guesses like how,
what was the age distribution,
like the average is around 29 and the 50%
Percentile is 28 and so on.
The 50th percentile is
basically the median, right?
I think so, unless I'm awfully wrong.
I was unsure, so I didn't
say that out loud.
Yeah, well, so the maximum is 80,
so the maximum age of any
passenger on the Titanic was 80.
Right, yeah.
So this is now some simple analysis
that you can do, but now we
can also try to do something like a group buy,
So we can try to
combine two different columns and
to get something much more useful.
So we'll try to do it.
Yes, titanic.groupby.
And if you choose the... Is
it uppercase or is it lowercase?
I think it's lowercase, right?
Lowercase, yes.
And we can choose the
survived column for this example.
And right, so this will.
This was selected, right?
Yes.
So just to give a
understanding like survive column here
has two different values, zero and one.
That will group into two
different groups and we can
choose the age column out of this group by.
So if you do square brackets,
And then we can do a mean, I suppose,
so that we don't see
the whole distribution of ages.
Yeah.
Is this printed automatically?
I think that should do it.
Yeah.
Okay.
So we see that in a
very condensed form, like, if you
were alive, you were probably
younger of the average age of 28,
but you're slightly older, 30s,
you get unlucky in the Titanic.
You can also get the same
thing out in histogram fashion.
So that's an example code
in the lesson, which is Titanic.hist.
Let's take a look at that.
I'll just copy that from
the lesson material.
Paste it in here.
So this should get a
histogram over ages grouped by
the survived column.
And then we're telling it
that it should split it into 25 pins.
So when you do a histogram,
you put things in pins
that are relatively similar, and
then it will actually should
create us a figure.
Yes.
Yeah.
And at this point, maybe
which may be useful to if you go to
near titanic.hist and press shift tab,
you can get the inline
documentation, I think.
Shift and tab.
Yeah.
So you get a clue what
kind of parameters are there
if you're feeling lost.
And that's one way to get help in Jupyter.
Another way is to do
titanic.hist question mark and pressing enter.
That's also awesome.
Yes, that is something that
we looked at when we were
looking at NumPy functions.
But shift and thumb also helps.
That's nice.
Let's take a look at what we get.
Yeah, it's compute.
Yes.
It takes a while to plot
and make a distribution of these things.
So when it's done, you might
be able to see two distributions,
each for the values zero and one.
And we'll see the one
with survived equal to one
being peaking at around 28, I suppose.
I mean, we have done some binning here,
but I guess the same as
the group by that we just did.
Yeah.
So for some 25 bins, what do you think?
Will we see a difference in
where the peak is?
If the bins are like three
or five, then you'll definitely
see a difference.
Yeah, somewhat.
You've got the
The peak for the Right.
So it's distribution is not symmetric.
So maybe mean is not the right.
So you also see something
better from visualization.
Maybe mean is not the right metric.
You might need to go
for the median instead.
Right.
We can actually try this.
I mean, it's all built in anyway, right?
I guess so.
If we get the median.
And we have the median is
pretty much the same.
Okay, so there was no real bias.
No real bias.
How we survived or how old
the people that were survived.
Right.
Shall we take a look at a
recap of what we saw so far in the lesson?
Yes.
I will...
the lesson document.
So we have done these bits.
Right.
The group by on the histogram.
And then we saw how to get the column.
Yeah, right.
I didn't think we I think it comes later.
Maybe we should.
Yeah.
This is a nice view.
So a data frame is, just
to recap things, it's composed
of rows and columns.
And it has a special
column called an index.
And the top thing is the column names.
And you can get some information about
how the columns are used by
doing .info or .describe.
And each column of this data frame,
which is a 2D structure, is
stored as the pandas.series object inside.
So every time you access
a special column on its own,
you will see that it's a .series, pandas.series.
object, how to access the column is
even below, like you can
either use square brackets and
type in the column name.
And we just did.
Yes, but sometimes it can conflict.
Suppose if you have a
column name called describe
then it will get confused,
are you asking for the method?
If you're using the titanic.h
without the square brackets syntax.
So that's why this square
brackets and the string notation exists.
You can also look at what
the data types are using,
the type built-in function.
It's universal in Python.
You can use it outside of Pandas as well.
Yeah.
And as we already saw earlier,
you can also see the data
type in the series with the info function.
Exactly.
and we saw that columns can be accessed
and index can be accessed like
as shown here and this we
already saw like what those are
what is an index and what
are columns another way to
access a particular value is using
the lock and the at method special
special methods called lock and add.
So this will are quite similar in sense,
in sense that we that you can
when you compare that to
NumPy, like when you do slices of NumPy.
So
the previous example where you
just put square brackets, that's
a short form for the lock, I think.
And you can also do ranges.
So should we look at some
of these examples in the notebook?
Yeah, we can do that.
So let's add a cell and
then we want to maybe do the
from the Titanic data set.
Maybe we want to get the first row.
So I would go, if I don't know
which row is the first row,
what the index is of that row,
but I know that I want the
first row, I could go ilot, right?
Yes.
And then that would be,
not square brackets, but round parentheses?
In square brackets, yeah.
In square brackets, is it?
Yes, yeah.
And then we want the first
row and all the columns.
And all the columns.
Yeah.
That should give you a slice, I think.
Let's see.
of course it doesn't print it now
because no you give it a
name right right and then it's got
so you will get the first
row also as a series actually
because it gets it's a one-dimensional thing
No, it's not a series.
It's a data type object.
Can you check that, maybe,
type of first row?
At least I think.
Maybe I'm mistaken.
Oh, it is a series.
Okay.
You're right.
But maybe if you ask for more
than just the first row,
maybe the first three rows.
I guess I could.
0, 2, 3.
That would be the first two rows.
That would be first.
Yeah.
Now it's the first three rows.
That's actually the first four rows.
Yeah.
And now it cannot become pressed into.
Yes.
Then it is a data frame again.
Right.
Yes.
Yeah, if you use a
print function, you'll get
a text-friendly representation.
If it's just first rows that
you give, then you get
a more Jupyter-friendly one.
But that's something Jupyter does for you.
It's along with Pandas.
So the loc and iloc comes in pairs.
If you use loc instead, you
need to know what the names
of these people are in the
first row and the third row.
because that is the index.
Right, which depending on the
data can be useful or not useful.
Usually like the column names
are very descriptive.
And you can also do
ranges with these string based names.
One difference is that the
at operator because it's newer,
And it doesn't do a lot of checks.
It's supposed to be a bit more faster.
That's maybe not so much
difference that you'll see because
it's a small CSV file.
But if it's a very large data frame,
which looks very similar, it'll
be slightly faster.
So how does that go?
I haven't ever used that one.
It's exactly the same syntax.
So if it's integer, then it
will be I at instead of at.
Integer indexing, yeah.
And then that gives us?
Like it says, same thing, I think.
or not wasn't app actually the one
where you um all right so
you cannot do ranges then you
can only get a scalar yeah sorry yeah
that is a small difference
there too yeah so if you're
only interested in one element
like the very very first element yeah
Maybe that is not very useful
in this case because we don't
know what we're doing.
But if you do it with the
at, you then give it the name.
Right.
Yeah.
That can be more nicer to look at.
And then the age.
Let's see what his age was exactly.
So that's more descriptive.
Let's see.
Let's try to see how you
can do Boolean indexing.
Now we saw strings and integers.
We can try to see who are
older than the age of 70, for example.
So that we do that.
Do it with the with
just the square brackets.
Yeah.
And it's the same as a NumPy.
Basically, you create a mask.
Yeah, a Boolean array, basically,
or a Boolean representation of
the data frame.
Or in this case, I think
it's of the time series, like all the rows.
And then it will select
based on that Boolean array.
Right, it will get back
all the indices where this is true.
And then that serves as a
mask for getting a sub slice
of the state of thing.
It satisfies this Boolean condition.
So the condition can be
something like greater than, but
you can also look for a
string based Boolean indexes.
And for that, there is the
example in the lesson.
It could be useful if you
deal with a lot of strings.
There are other useful things
when we deal with missing data.
Data is often very messy and
you need to be careful
can fill with empty, it
might be filled with like missing data,
which gets represented as NA
or not available in pandas.
This is a generalization of
the NumPy, not a number.
It can include not a number values.
if you are dealing with just floats.
But if it's a generic thing,
pandas call it NA.
And you can either get a
Boolean mask of this NA values
using the isNA method.
You can choose to drop every
row if any of the column values are NA.
So the whole row will be dropped.
Yeah, and then there are other
ways to do that too.
You can also fill it if you want.
So there are some useful methods.
I think it's time that
you get your intuition with
it by exploring through an exercise.
So let's take an exercise for 10 minutes.
Here you'll be using the same data set
and try to do two tasks
and any of the methods mentioned above.
So exercise till 43 past the clock.
Okay, all right.
We have a note to help with the time.
We want to stop the exercise.
It's 43 past the clock.
And we're going to be saying bye for now.
See you in 10 minutes.
Yes.
Bye.
Hello, welcome back.
I hope you got some time
to look at the small exercise.
If not, we'll show it to
you anyway, like demonstrated.
So in the last two points of the exercise,
the first task is to compute
the mean age of the first
10 passengers, the first 10
rows, the data frame.
So the way to do that, you can,
as shown in the solution
below, you can either use
the iLock based indexing with
integers or the lock indexing.
It's string based.
So we chose the first one
because it makes sense.
If you know the first 10,
you want the first 10, then
it makes sense to not look
up their ages, like their names,
and just say, I want the first 10.
Exactly.
And it's...
And we get average.
Right.
And the other task was to find
who are older than the mean average age
or who are younger over
and under the average age and
get their the mean of the
survived column, if they were more
likely to be survived or not.
uh so we chose the one
for the older people titanic age greater
than but i mean um the
younger would just be inverting
this this relationship and then
you get well so the older
ones were slightly less likely
to survive maybe so i would say
Not so good.
Yeah, right.
So this was just a repetition of
what we saw so far,
indexing and creating Boolean masks
and doing small statistics like me.
So now we take a look
at how data gets represented.
So this is borrowed a lot
from the R tidyverse theory
of representing data.
uh i saw briefly in the notes
that some people were comparing
this to sql and our data frames so
so it is true that this
pandas package was very much
inspired from these two
libraries which pre-existed at pandas
i think uh so in
If you talk about tidy data,
like the best way to represent
data is to have every variable
in its own columns and each row
is an entry or an observation.
So what would be the
inverse of untidy data?
Like here, there is a
synthetic data of some runners,
runner one, runner two, runner
three, and what we record
is given below uh even over there
and if you print that run
us how does it look like [name]
fee i guess i have to print
it well just run us it's good
it looks nicer i think without
the print well then you don't see
it you mean i like that just
like that yeah so what we are seeing here is uh
all the distances that they run
as columns and the runner names
as the first column and
the timings get represented in
the interior of the data frame.
So suppose you want to
do something very simple, like
calculate their speed, then you
want to do distance divided
by the times, right?
The operation gets really messy
and you will get a new data frame.
You don't have any place to put that here.
And it's also difficult to
access the distance from the
column names like this.
So the way to make this
into a tidy format is to
use, for example, the pandas.melt function.
What it takes as input is
the untidy data frame from this.
We tell them what is the
unique index, I think, ID values.
and then ask it to pick
what are actually values and
should be represented in its
own columns, value words.
And we give it a name
for this, these values, these are distances.
And whatever is inside also
gets its own columns, its own column.
Those are the time.
So if you do that instead, what do you get?
I need to repeat it
so it's actually offensive.
Right.
It's a sort of longest data frame.
Right, exactly.
So each are observation in its own rule.
And it's very easy right
now to compute something like
speed distance by time.
And it gets fast and easy
to do other statistics on top of it.
Let's...
Yeah, one more thing like
tidy data tends to be very
long, like very tall.
And if it's untidy, it has
this side effect of becoming very wide.
So you could go back from
the long format to the short wide format.
I think it's called pivot.
Yeah, it is called Pivot.
And I think there is an
example of that later on or
in one of the exercises, I think.
Take a look at them.
Another thing that you want to do is to
Sorry.
To get data from different
data sources, right?
Exactly.
Yeah.
So then suppose you were
reading part of the data is in a CSV file,
part of it is in a
JSON or an XS spreadsheet, then
you can use Pandas.
But then what you get is
you get different data frame objects.
And then they are supposed
to be together for your analysis.
What would you do then?
Like the one way to illustrate
is to, uh, by example.
So here, so you can,
you can create manually data frames
or something else, but you can
also have a different set of
data frames or have various
data frames that have something in common.
Like for, for example, here,
the, the runner column.
And then you can do what's called merging.
Right.
Before you merge it, can you
print the age data frame so
we know how it looks like?
Yep.
If I manage to type it correctly.
Then I think you need a
print function if it's in the middle.
Yeah.
It should be okay.
It's a very small one.
Right.
So we are creating a small data
which should be merged into
the previous data frame.
So some observations on what the ages are.
And so as you see here,
yeah, that's a good observation as well.
Like when you call such
operations, they don't change
what the original data set is
unless you pass it back.
Yes.
So if I do it now, there
is a new column age, and it
has for each of the runner rows
in the first data frame, it
has added the correct age from
the second data frame.
Right.
And that it knows through
the on argument in merge.
Yes.
You can actually specify
different columns if they
have different names, but you
know they are the same data, essentially.
You can specify different names in the,
they're called right and left
data frames in Pandas.
So you can specify different columns.
But here we were lucky that
it was called runner in both of them.
And a lot of the time it is.
I mean, same data, right?
Right.
Then what else is there?
There are, of course, other
methods to combine things.
For example, there is CONCAT data frame.
But for CONCAT to work, you
need the data frames to be of
the same size, I think.
We'll not look at this
example in the interest of time, but it exists.
So as I said before, a
lot of this is inspired from SQL.
So SQL also has this
concept of merging joins, right
join, left join, all that.
And also to make a selection
based on some condition and
Group by we have already seen.
We saw previously group by
based on just one column name,
but you can also group by
based on multiple column names as shown below.
Right.
Yeah, we can take a look at that.
Some other ways to manipulate data.
So we're,
looking at the grouping by
the gender of the person and
whether it's how we need to
first include this child column.
Oh yeah, sorry.
I skipped that.
So you cannot use the
Boolean index to create new
columns of your own.
That's also possible.
So we are creating a new
column named child that includes all the people
um that that's true for
all the people whose age is below 12
and then we can group by that column
and compute the means exactly
and then you'll see for
the survived column for these
two combinations what was the average
split into gender as well.
So you get two levels of grouping.
The first grouping is based
on male and female.
The next grouping is based on
if they are a child or not.
So you can do that too.
And what we can conclude from this,
I think, is that indeed
the women and children were sent first.
And more of them survived,
much more of them survived than the male.
Yes, right.
Women are children first.
So they actually followed
through with those males.
So now I think we have...
room to do some repetition
on this exercise.
In this exercise, you will
be looking at the same Titanic data frame
and you're asked to compute
the family sizes based on
a particular SP column.
It stands for the family size.
And then there are other
questions and there is an
advanced question as well.
so we'll give you another 10
minutes to do this exercise and
we'll come back after that so
actually um right maybe after this right
after this exercise it would
be good to take a little bit
of a break so we will um
we convene at it's not two
o'clock um 15 minutes past
15 minutes past sounds good.
Yeah.
So try to give the exercise
five to 10 minutes.
If you get stuck, don't worry about it.
Don't forget to take a break too.
And yeah, don't forget to take a break.
We'll be back at 15 past.
Okay.
So bye for now.
Bye.
I think it's time.
Yep.
I think we should be back.
OK.
And we are back with looking at pandas.
And well, so we've seen what
a panda's data frame is and how to handle it.
And we've seen that pandas
does everything in series objects.
But it can also do special things.
Because a lot of data
is actually dates, right?
It's when something happened,
how old someone is.
So Pandas has special logic
for handling dates.
If you ever try to read
in dates manually from different sources,
potentially from different countries,
you will know that it becomes a nightmare.
But luckily for us, Pandas
has ways to understand the date data.
And we will explore that a
bit with a new data set the
that is about the Nobel Prize winners.
And yeah, there's a bit
of special things you have to do
to to get the data actually, but
We have it because you cannot
load it from the original source.
So we also have put it on GitHub
if you want to access it from there,
or you can just download
it yourself from the Nobel
Laureate, Nobel Committee and work
with it there.
And if you want to, yeah.
Shall we take a look at how it looks like?
Yeah, do.
Have you got it on your machine there?
So let's see.
So it has a data frame
containing the names of Nobel
laureates when they were
born and then they died and when
even the day when they
actually got the Nobel Prize.
So there are a couple
of columns which deals with dates.
Yes.
So maybe if we were
interested in specifically these dates,
it won't necessarily read them in
as dates automatically if you
just read it in from CSV,
because there is a bit of computing involved.
And if you don't really need it as a date,
There's no point in doing that.
So you have to tell pandas
that it actually is a date.
You can do that by using
the to date time function.
So if you
Yeah, exactly these.
So if you run these, it
will reaffine the born, died
and year columns as a date.
Can you actually run these and
then look at the info again?
At the info?
Or the D type for the born column?
Yeah, I did it wrong.
I think it's...
was easier.
So you see before it was object
and year was assumed to be
an integer, but now it
was reassigned as daytime.
NumPyDateTime is 64.
So now we told pandas that
it is actually a date, and
then we can do through this
.dt, we can get different parts of the date.
So maybe you can run what
we see, like the dt.day and
year and weekday to see what...
So we will get the days
for when they were born.
Some, not a number.
Some are not a number.
For some, the format might
not have been recognized.
For some, it might have
also been missing in the first place.
Could be an organization, so
there was no birth.
Maybe.
We don't know that without
looking at the data, but I
don't think we have the time for that now.
And then do we want to try to compute
how long they lived, all
these Nobel Prize winners?
Maybe.
Yeah, so I think for that
we use the diet column and the
bone column get a difference of butylase.
Yes, get the difference between
the days they died and the
days they were born.
We're using days because if we used years,
I mean, we could do that,
but it would be very, very
inexact because the year is
just the year number.
And this way, if we use the day
and then divide by 365, that
will give us a much more exact time length.
Also, I think in this data
set, the year is the Nobel
Prize when they were awarded the Nobel Prize.
So that's another analysis, I think.
No, no.
But if you get the Nobel
diet minus Nobel born dot DT dot year.
Right.
That would work, but it
would give you potentially ages that
are half a year off.
It would be an exception.
Got it.
Very, very inexact.
So the days and then dividing
by 365 is exact enough, at
least for our purposes here.
Again, so here we build that as a column.
And then we can plot it as a histogram.
How are they?
They live a happy life in
the 80s, so it's not too bad.
Most of them?
Yeah.
We can also do other
kinds of plotting, combining two columns.
So we do a simplified
span divided group across subjects
or category, as it's called here.
Yeah.
Yeah, nothing to see here.
Well, it works the same as
with the data, with the normal data frame.
It's just that handling dates
is quite a pain if you're doing it manually.
So having this facility of
Pandas is really, really, really helpful.
If you ever...
have the the honor and joy
to work with data exactly right um
but since it is already uh 23 past
and the next topic will start
at half past i think it would be good if we
maybe quickly discuss the
third exercise that didn't actually...
You can do the exercise, of
course, on your own time later if you want to.
But maybe we can just show
what it would be.
Yeah.
So I have it prepared as
a demo, at least for the
first three we will show.
And you can explore the rest later.
Yes.
So yeah, the first question
is, given this...
data set, which I have loaded here,
noble, what will be the
which country has received the most.
And to that, we use the
book column, which is called born country code.
And we use the describe
function, which gives you along
with the list of how many
data entries are there.
We also see how many
unique countries, but also the
top appearing country, which is US.
So we see that the US
has received the most number of
double prices so far.
And here is some repetition
on using the histogram.
So here we create a
histogram based on when they
were awarded the Nobel prizes,
at what age they were awarded.
So to do that, we combine
the Nobel born and year columns.
We ensure that those are daytime types.
We take a difference of these two.
Do exactly the same as
before to compute the lifespan,
but here it's the age.
So we see that most of
them got their Nobel Prize once
they were close to retirement at
the age of 60, I suppose.
And you can also list
Nobel laureates from your own country.
I chose Sweden because I live here.
But so what we are doing
here is this country column can
do a Boolean mask based on equality.
And you can
two other indexing after this mask is done.
So let's check for Finland.
I think it's correct, or is it just one?
Maybe so, at least according
to the dataset.
There are other advanced steps
which you can follow through.
The code is given here,
but we'll leave that as an exercise later.
And you can also do
some fancy visualization
on your own time.
With that, there is some
extra knowledge that you can do
if you feel that Pandas is becoming slow.
While doing some operations, there
is a NumExpert optional
dependency, optional library.
which evaluates certain operations
as strings instead.
If you pass them as strings,
they will give you back
exactly the same result, but it'll be faster.
You can also do custom creation of columns.
We saw like Boolean indexes,
we can create columns, but
if you want something really fancy,
there is a pandas.apply.
So you choose your inputs,
you keep passive function, which
accepts one element at a time,
and then gives back another
column by using this apply method.
There are much more that you can explore.
There are some tips for extra reading here.
And also in the
in the notes that we
saw some discussion, like some
people were asking about Polus.
So yes, Polus is a rewrite
of this approach based on
basing every thing that they work
with from a library called Apache Arrow.
Whereas Pandas was originally
designed on top of NumPy.
Although like Pandas recently has added
some support for task, sorry,
some support for PyArrow.
It's very limited because they
wanted to keep compatibility.
So unless you're very careful,
you usually end up getting
NumPy as the working engine in Pandas.
Whereas in Polar, it ends
up getting really fast because it's
as other properties, including
being written and using PyArrow.
There are other libraries also,
if it's very large data
that you're using with, Dask
is one such example.
So which parallelizes such analysis
on top of data frames.
Yx is also another library
which is very similar to Pandas.
Written in C++, I think.
Do you want to round up things, [name]?
No, I think that as much
as we have time for now, there's, of course,
lots and lots of topics
we could discuss about pandas.
But there's a few other
very interesting things that you're
going to learn in this course.
And let's give those people
the time they deserve as well.
So next up will be a lesson on pandas.
X array.
If I am not entirely wrong,
that will be by [name]
again and [name].
Do we actually have these
people on stream already?
Hello.
Right.
So we'll hand over to you
guys and see you all at another time.
This is slightly better.
Oh, man.
It's already getting dark.
What's wrong with Finland?
Hello, everyone.
And welcome, [name].
Uh, welcome for joining us
here and exploring x-ray.
Uh, I was reading during the, uh,
during the pandas, uh, uh, lesson, I was,
I was reading the, the,
the shared document a little bit
and it was one, uh,
user who sort of desperately asked like,
wait, we have NumPy, we have normal lists,
we have data frames, now
we're gonna teach you about
X-Array, and later on we're gonna
see even more packages.
How do I make sense of this?
When do I use what?
I think this might be a
good place to start here about X-Array.
So,
These packages are created for
people who are using NumPy.
That's sort of the default.
So first learn how to use
NumPy and get comfortable in that.
But then there were people
who were using that for years, and
for their specific use case,
they were thinking like, okay, but what if
What if NumPy could be even better?
I have data that has
many different dimensions, and I have rows
and columns and fourth dimensions
and fifth dimensions, and I
keep losing track of all of that.
What if we could make it even better?
And then they created X-Array.
And I'm pretty sure a
very much driving factor of this is also
having this small tiny bit
that's annoying every time you're
using it and that you just want
to not have to use.
Yeah, I want to find
something how my specific problem
can be solved better.
Yes, exactly.
So for people getting confused,
I would say, like, first
learn how NumPy works.
But then when you're comfortable
with NumPy and you're asking
yourself, wait, is there a better way?
Then your answer is yes.
And then we start talking
about things like pandas and
things like X-Array.
So let's get into it.
What is X-Array?
Or what do you want to say?
I just want to interject that.
You always at the same time
have to keep in mind that
for its purposes, NumPy is really good.
It's just that it's designed
for a certain target.
And in a lot of
cases, different scientific fields
have slightly different requirements to
how they need to handle the
data and how they want to manipulate the data.
And that's why all of
these additional packages arrive
and why people essentially
design these additional packages.
Most of them are somewhat
solving one particular problem or solve
or aiming at it from
a specific perspective of a field of research.
Yeah.
Yeah, for example, XArray was
created, I think by by
people doing climate science and
it's it's very well suited for that.
Although also in very like in other fields,
I think will be useful
across other fields as well.
But it was originally created
by climate scientists to help their analysis.
So what is XArray?
Let's get to it.
So the problem that XArray solves is
that what if you have a
NumPy array, but it has three,
four, five, six dimensions to it?
If you start doing operations
and saying, well, give me
the mean value across the
third dimension, that is quite unintuitive.
What is the third dimension?
You have to look up,
what are my dimensions?
And so they developed x-ray as
a way to give names to
the various dimensions the rows
the columns of a NumPy array
So we're gonna start naming the dimensions.
We're gonna start naming all the rows
and naming all the columns
We're gonna assign units to it.
So if if something is in
terms of location then like is
this in meters or kilometers
or That we're gonna take a look at
Or degrees.
Yeah, or degrees.
So...
Just to give an example, say
we have a NumPy array, and
we have a three-dimensional one,
and that NumPy array, it contains temperature.
This is temperature data.
We're going to record
temperature at different locations
across Earth, and also at different heights.
If you take a look
at the entire atmosphere, you have an
X and a Y coordinate, but you also have height.
So it's going to be
a three-dimensional matrix,
um and uh recording all
these temperatures and if we
now have questions like okay
can you tell myself give me
uh the temperature uh at kilometer
50 uh yeah yeah 50 kilometers
to the right 100 kilometers straight ahead
and then 50 meters straight up
um you would have no idea uh
wait wait wait let me let me check the uh the
definitions that we have put
in there because I can't remember them.
Yeah.
Like which row, which column do you need?
So enter X array.
We're going to name everything.
In order to do this,
let's actually load some real climate data.
It's a good example for this
half an hour that we have.
Let's work on this.
Let's work on temperature data.
And in the lesson materials, we
have a nice example data set
that we can just load in.
and we can see x-ray in action.
All right, so yeah, we're gonna use it.
Oh yeah, you can ignore that warning.
It's some recent change in
how the package resources,
package wants things.
We can save it.
We are fetching this dataset
and let's see that essentially
Tells us now that we have
this at a certain file path.
So yeah, we quickly use
this Pia dataset package just
to download the data.
Right.
We could, we could have like
went to the website and downloaded from there,
but this was just a quick way
to do it for this particular dataset.
But now we have it, um, on our, on,
uh, on [name]'s hard drive
and [name] can load it.
It is, uh, let's see what we have in there.
So a lot we have in there,
and we have to go through it a little bit.
What this file contains, I
already told you it contains temperature data,
which we'll look at, but
it contains other things as well.
But if you go from top
to bottom, what we have here
is an X-array data set.
And an X-array data set
is actually a collection of
multiple NumPy arrays that all describe
In this case, the same piece
of the earth, but they're all
related to each other.
They describe the same thing.
And in the data set,
we have different coordinates.
These coordinates are essentially
the different axes or
the different dimensions of our NumPy arrays.
You can see most of our
NumPy arrays will be four-dimensional arrays.
And these coordinates, they
specify what each of those
four dimensions mean.
So we have actually gonna
discuss them bottom to top
because it's more intuitive.
We have the x and y
position on the Earth where we're
gonna have the temperature.
We have the isobaric pressure,
which is like the way
that climate scientists like
to indicate height.
So they indicate height not in meters,
but in like pressure,
well, isobaric pressure of the air.
That's, I guess, more intuitive to them.
And in addition to
that, temperature changes over time.
So we also have a time dimension.
So we have recordings there
across time even.
So a four-dimensional data race we have.
Even though I think we just
have one time point.
We only have one time point, yes.
But we could have multiple
time points here as well.
Yes.
With this example data, it's been cropped.
So the original data set
had thousands of time points.
We cropped it down to only
one time point to fit into our puny memory.
But the dimension is still there.
Okay, now I said that an
XArray data set contains multiple NumPy arrays.
So we don't have a single
one, we actually have multiple ones.
And those are the data variables.
So the most intuitive one here
is, again, I go from bottom to top.
The temperature one is like
the last data variable there in the data set.
So the temperature contains,
it's a four-dimensional array, you can see it,
where the first dimension is
time, the second dimension is
the isobaric pressure, third dimension
is the y-location, and fourth
dimension is the x-location.
And it contains the temperature.
But we have other arrays as
well, we have one for the
v-component of the wind, we have
one for the u-component of the wind,
We have the geopotential.
I don't even know what it
is because I'm not a climate scientist.
I don't even know what it is.
These are all things
that are four-dimensional arrays.
I can see from there, and
they have four dimensions defined.
Now, in addition to that,
we have two NumPy arrays which are two-dimensional.
So that's the latitude
and longitude values of at the
X and Y positions in this data set.
So they're only two dimensional,
but the dimensions correspond to the X
and the Y dimensions of
these larger four dimensional arrays.
Are you still following, [name]?
So we have different arrays
Essentially, you have multiple
different types of data in the same data set.
And for example, they decided
they don't want to have
the latitude and longitude as
their own variables or coordinates.
But they want to keep
this information alongside so that
you don't need to recalculate
it whenever you actually want to
see, where am I actually?
Because as you can see here,
the x and y, they have minus and plus.
Yeah, kilometers, like in a
nice square grid.
But what's the zero point?
Without having this latitude
longitude information, you wouldn't
have the zero point.
So you wouldn't know where
this actually is.
So we want all this data together.
So X-array is really a convenience thing.
We could have had these
as separate NumPy arrays and
just loaded them one by one.
We could.
But with X-array, we can have
them all in one data set object.
And as the data said
it's really powerful We can we
can slice up this data and
situated all the arrays get
sliced in exactly the same way all at
once So if we yeah, let's
if you visualize this At one time point
so if we now like discuss
only one time point our
data is three-dimensional we have X
and Y and height and the
temperature there So now we
by specifying these dimensions in
the data set.
So we don't longer have to
talk about the first dimension
or the second dimension.
We can talk about the X
dimension and the Y dimension.
Okay, that's not really much better, is it?
But we could talk about
the isobaric pressure dimension.
We can talk about the time dimension.
Dimensions have names now.
And then each row and
each column, each item along
that dimension, we can also give it a label.
So if we look across the X dimension,
It's not like row 1 and 2 and 3.
We have actual, like in
kilometers, we have, so we have
one that is like 895 kilometers that way.
And we have another that's
1025 kilometers that way.
Or if we go up, we could say, okay,
we're going to up with like
100 units in hectopascal of isobaric pressure.
So instead of just having
abstract numbers, we're talking
about concrete real things.
And you can also use these
as kind of indices to
these different dimensions.
Exactly.
And that's how we're going
to work with this data now.
So in order to make things
a little bit easier for us,
let's just focus on the
temperature variable now.
So let's see from this data set.
[name], can you just pull
out the temperature data?
Yeah.
So in a way, this is
a little bit similar as what
we saw in Pandas, right?
We have these different variables in there,
and we can pull out a
variable by indexing our data set
this way, as if it was a Python dictionary.
So we can essentially extract
this data variable here, and
that's where we get this information from.
Yeah, the DS is our entire data set.
We're now just gonna grab
the temperature data from it.
So now it's a bit more manageable.
It's just a single variable now.
It's no longer an entire
data set, single variable.
It still has our four dimensions, right?
And with my little different attributes.
Yeah.
There's also attributes.
Yeah, I haven't talked about,
so attributes are just
like freestyle annotations to the data.
They're key values.
So just annotations to say, well,
What's the actual unit of
this piece of information?
Yeah.
What temperature are we looking at?
Exactly.
And these are like, you can
define your own attributes.
So these attributes are
completely defined by the people
who collected this data, just to annotate it.
And they can put in
there whatever they wanted.
Um, and it's, it's really helpful.
So now we just don't only have the numbers.
We have like a lot
of description about what this data
is, what it represents, and it's
all in one file.
So it's very, that was the wrong.
That was the wrong thing.
Okay.
What to make what to take the, um,
just tripped a bit, uh, to the side
so that we can see what
we are actually using here as
well, so that we can stay in sync with the.
Well, yeah.
If you want to get to the actual data,
we... Well, yeah, if you
actually want to get the actual
data back, it's just like in pandas.
It's .values.
So you see that these packages
look at each other.
What are they doing?
So in pandas, if you want
to roll NumPy array, it's .values.
And then x-rays say, okay,
let's do the same thing.
uh you know you know
overwriting things that don't answer
that we still need no oh
no it's no you're not okay sorry
no no it's not over what
you're doing you know what you're
doing yeah now we have a plain NumPy array
so you can always get it
out i'm not sure if i know
what i'm doing but uh i'm
not overwriting it not yet okay so um
Well, obviously now that we
have given names to all our dimensions.
So if you now want the data
at a certain X location, for
example, can you give me the temperature?
And I want the X location
of minus, well, the certain value 3,292.
Uh, I wonder as a specific location,
so you can say, okay,
I want the temperature and you
can use this dot, uh, cell, uh, method.
Now let's select some data and
we can say, okay, the X should be this value.
Um, just noticing something here.
Um, what is, uh, what would actually.
what would actually happen if
we take the value here and
not the string oh yeah well you can i think
that should still work that
should still work and yeah makes
that actually makes more sense
you should maybe update that and
uh i think i agree this makes
more sense but are you uh
are you happy with that [name] or
Well, I'm not really happy because
if I look at this, I
have no idea where this
number actually comes from.
Yeah, it's specific, right?
It's a specific x location.
It's kind of annoying.
And we would like to indeed say, well,
we want a location at
the x coordinate that's roughly 3,292, right?
In fact, it's like...
but yeah but that's not
that's not the specific like in
our data that's not how we
called it we called it zero zero two um
but we uh so this is where
we have uh we can tell x-ray
well just give me the closest
row right just the nearest
that is quite powerful because
that allows you to essentially
that we have essentially what we
had before we have it back and
This allows you to just
take whatever index, essentially,
as long as it's a numeric dimension,
and go to the closest thing
and find things that are
closest to this location, which,
yeah, that's quite convenient.
Yeah, if things are overly
specific, like our x and y coordinates, right?
Yeah.
So, yeah, that's the usual thing.
Of course, I mean, we
should maybe quickly show that, of course,
you can still can index
your data with integer indexes.
And then again, they borrow
a convention from pandas.
So we we're now showing
you sell for select.
But we also have I sell for.
index sure it's like so now
x is no longer like it's one or zero
or like so this would be
the second value along the
x dimension example so that
which is some number something else
and which is admittedly uh this
is the kind of thing where
you very often get typos that
lead to problems because you select
Well, I sell, sell close enough.
And given that you can just
give the same dimension name, that
can lead to inconveniences.
Yeah.
But in many ways, these
X-array things, they behave like NumPy arrays.
They're just a little bit more convenient.
So, for example, [name], can
you just give us the
average temperature, like for this
entire data set?
Yep.
So that would be the
temperature, average, mean, right?
Just like you would do in... Now,
if you just do mean, you
will get the average temperature
across the entire thing.
Okay, but yeah, now I want
the mean along a certain dimension.
So I want the mean, but I
want the mean at each isobaric
pressure, so its height across the atmosphere.
So in NumPy, I would have to do, well,
that's the mean along the second dimension,
I think it was, but with
X-array, we can name the dimension
by its name, so.
So that was isobaric one,
which we have here as this coordinate.
Yeah.
And that just reads a lot
nicer in your code.
It's much more obvious what you're doing,
that we're taking the mean
along the isobaric dimension.
It makes the code a lot more understandable.
You don't have a number in there, and
Well, what people often do with NumPy
or similar things, you define
a variable that is called
isobaric equals one or something like
that to fix the dimension so
that you can write code
that is still understandable.
Because in fact, if this is just,
if this is, let's say, if
this would be two, one, you
have no idea what this means.
No.
That's, yeah.
pretty much useless code or
extremely, not useless, but
very, very difficult to debug code.
It can be, unless you
commented it properly.
So if you do this in
NumPy, you definitely can.
But then you need to comment it
and explain, like, this is
this dimension, and we're doing
this, and it's absolutely fine.
But if you want XArray, it
just makes it a little bit more convenient.
Or, as I mentioned, you
can just say isobaric equals 1
temperature equals two or something,
and just use then these
variables instead of the actual values.
Oh yeah, that you can also do, yeah.
That's a useful one.
Which would be what I would be doing
if I would want to use
NumPy for something like this.
Another way where this is
really convenient is when we want
to plot the data.
So for example, let's make
a plot, again, of the temperature.
And let's see, how do we do it in example?
So I want to plot, but I
want it at one of the x coordinates.
And I just want to look,
give me the height and the temperature.
Let's see how the temperature
changes as we go further up in the atmosphere.
so that would be um select
so maybe now we don't really care about
which exit is just give me
the third like the third row
along the x dimension okay so that's isl
so at this moment i don't care
um so we can just yeah do
plot um and we'll give us
a surprisingly detailed plot
Because we've named all the dimensions
and we also given the
coordinates along all the dimensions,
if we just plot something, look
at how much information XArray
can already annotate in the plot.
So we see here the
temperature at different Y positions,
which are in kilometers.
We have the height there now
in terms of isobaric surface
pressure, which is again in hectopascals.
And we have the temperature
there in Kelvin.
Essentially, we see a slice
going, I would assume, north to south.
No, east to west.
And to the top.
I think north to south.
North to south?
East to west?
Yeah.
You would think bottom to top, but aha, no.
Pressure increases when we get
closer to the Earth.
Yeah, true.
XArray is not psychic, so
it doesn't know that.
So ideally, we would plot
this isobaric surface dimension.
We would flip it, which we can quickly do.
I mean, if you know matplotlib commands.
So this plot function, it
also takes matplotlib keywords.
So can you give it yincrease as one thing?
yincrease.
and then set it to false, is equals false.
So with a capital F, yeah.
So the Y thing in our
plot should not be increased repetition.
Okay, so then it flipped.
But it's a matplotlib thing,
just to show that that works.
Now it's more intuitive.
We see higher temperatures at the ground,
and then as we go higher
up, things gets colder, yeah.
Definitely.
Okay.
So that's the...
That's the 3D kind of view of things.
You could also just look at, well,
one specific point on the map
yeah we can do but we
actually don't have time for
that because we only have five
minutes left oh yeah we're gonna skip ahead
but um we're gonna skip ahead
to um uh to creating our own x-ray data set
so that we loaded one from the file
that somebody else has created
so what if you have a
bunch of NumPy arrays yourself and
you want to like put that into
an x-ray uh a data set
so if you look a little bit
at the code i would highly
recommend we just copy paste
this uh [name] because it's it's
a bit it's a bit for both
because we have to uh tell
x array all these things so we
have our uh NumPy arrays say
we have pressure data and humidity
data um we um this is how
you put it together um
So we need for each of
our dimensions, we need a label
for that, so now we have time and location.
But then for the time dimension,
we need to specify, okay, what time?
It's not time zero, one,
two, three, no, it's in actual dates.
And if we have location,
what are these locations?
So now in this example,
we named them somewhat unhelpfully.
Location one, two, three.
Maybe this could be like Helsinki, Oslo.
Helsinki.
Stockholm.
Otherwise, they'd feel left out.
You could give them meaningful things.
Yeah.
So, yeah, so we have
two arrays, a different coordinates, right?
We can give it some attributes, right?
Give it a nice description.
This is weather data and the
author, we are like data
science, real data scientists
created this, whatever we want.
And we have a really
nice like XArray dataset object
that contains a lot of information.
And once we have that, maybe
show them how to save it.
Do we do that?
That would be nice.
maybe to uh uh 20 or something
so um with X-array by uh
one of the um best ways to
save this is into a file
format called netcdf, so netcdf is
created for, yeah, to contain
this sort of data where you
have multiple NumPy arrays and
they describe the same piece of
land of the same object.
It's really nice data format to save it to.
And this is also sort of
the default in X-Array.
In X-Array, you're sort of
expected to save the data in
this net CDF format and load it, load from it.
All right.
And you can then essentially
do something like this to get
the data in Helsinki for pressure.
Yes, exactly.
Which is, yeah, some random
numbers, so don't worry too much,
but you can get it.
So that's our quick, super
quick overview of XArray.
The main takeaway is you can
give names to your dimensions and
names to all the rows and the columns,
and then you can use them
to make your code a bit
more readable if you need.
All right.
Thank you so much.
This was super interesting and
there were relevant questions in the notes,
but our time is out for today
so we can keep on
answering to the questions in the notes later.
If you can briefly switch to
the notes view and scroll to
the bottom, there is, I've added
a section for the feedback of the day.
so it's like again just a
simple type of feedback questionnaire
so that you can mark with the o
if it was too fast or too slow
or if the speed was good
this is very important because
we can quickly adapt for
example already for for the next
day if this was too fast or too slow and so on
and then it's usually it's
important to mention you know
one good thing about today
but also something that could
be improved we are improving
these courses every year i think
this is maybe the fourth
time that we're running this or
fifth i don't know i lost account
but so you know what you
see is the improvement of
thousands of comments from previous
runs and previous learners
all right do you have any
final words to mention maran
or [name] anything else go take
a break become overwhelmed we
were throwing a lot of stuff at
you uh this uh this three days
so it will take it will take
a while to to sink in and go back uh
for the there are so
many packages things in general um
i think what we want to
provide you is mainly an
overview of what's around
what you can use and
probably whatever you will use,
you will have to read a
bit more in the documentations
because your specific problem will
be very special.
And we just want to give you hints
as to where to start looking
and give you a couple of
general basic ideas because all
of this is very,
On this, on the surface of,
of the things and rarely goes
into extreme low details because
those low details are in
my experience, at least always
very, very project specific and
would probably be useless to 90%
of the other people that are here.
So yeah.
We just want to give you
a general overview of what,
what is around, what you can use, how you can.
how you can approach things.
Yeah.
And in general, if something was too fast,
as soon as the streaming
stops, the video will be
there immediately available on the
same Twitch TV page.
And later we will upload
them to our YouTube channels.
All right.
But thanks a lot for all the listeners
and watchers and people online
and for the great instructors for today.
We meet again tomorrow morning at 10 a.m.
Finnish time, 9 a.m.
Central European time.
Until then, bye-bye.
See you then.
See you.