hello hello and welcome to
day two of python for
scientific computing edition 2025 i
hope day one was exciting i
understand that it might have
been overwhelming for some of you but
We try to give you as much
as we can in three days, and
then later you can rewatch
the recordings, go through the
Python code examples.
But today with me here, we
start with some icebreakers.
We have [name] and [name]
from Aalto University.
[name], do you want to
say briefly something about yourself?
Yeah, hello.
So my name is [name].
I'm a research software engineer
in the altoscientific computing.
I've been part of teaching
this course for as long as
the course has been here.
So back in the back in the olden days.
But yeah, so we'll be talking
about a lot of subjects today and
I'm a seasoned Python, like
yesterday there was a question
of what languages we're using.
Like my first summer job
was converting Python numeric to NumPy.
So it's like a long history
with NumPy and Python.
So it's good to follow up
or keep going with that.
And then with us today, also
[name], do you want to
mention something about yourself,
although you were already
Yeah, but I did actually
introduce myself yesterday.
So I'm also a research
software engineer at Data
Science and Computing.
I've been teaching here now
also for the last four years or so.
I'm originally from a
bioinformatics background.
So using MATLAB very, very way
back when I actually started with Java.
So Python only came later in my career.
But nowadays, since a lot
of things are working in Python,
I'm also doing stuff in there
and doing quite a lot
of actually web development things.
So more TypeScript, JavaScript,
but backend stuff in Python.
So [name] is sharing the
screen now and [name] is
showing this notes document.
You all have received a
reminder from me via email from
the link of this notes document.
And there I wrote a
couple of icebreakers that I'm going
to ask to our instructors
of the day, especially the one
how do you make figures for reports
or articles or in even
in general maybe even figures
you know let's say that today
for the teaching materials you need
to make a figure so I start
with [name] how do you usually
make figures or plots
Yeah, that's a good question.
Like I often do use
different kinds of tools.
So back in the day, I
used to use Matplotlib a lot.
Nowadays, it's much more like
Vega Altair that we'll be talking about today.
But of course, there's like
other mentions there like ggplot2.
I've been using that as well.
other other tools that are better
for like diagrams and and teaching stuff
so yeah just yesterday i made
like a change change to the material
and i used geodebra to
create one figure and um and
sometimes i use this graph tool
called y ed y edit i don't
know how to pronounce it but y
ed which makes it easy to
create diagrams and uml diagrams
and that sort of stuff uh
There's also this Excalidraw
that is nowadays really nice if
you want to do a quick dirty
figure so you can demonstrate
something for people in the web.
But there's plenty of tools.
Yeah, I know less than half
of the tools you mentioned, so
if you can please add them to the list there.
And what about you, [name]?
Which tools do you use?
When I still used to
actually create scientific...
lots of things.
It was mostly at the time
in MATLAB itself, so just
the MATLAB plotting things.
Nowadays, I'm mostly doing diagrams
and things with partly
DrawIO, sometimes Inkscape if stuff
needs to be, if I need to
have a bit more control over details and things.
and actually rarely do these
kind of standard plots anymore
yeah have you when you were making plots
for for papers and things like
that did you try to make everything
as much as possible with
the code basically with the plot or did you
and your colleagues maybe you
know after the initial plot
lots of whatever illustrator or
inkscape or photoshop or
I try to avoid post-processing figures
as much as possible because
it only messes things up
and the figure actually gets less usable.
At the same time, I try
to normally just provide the raw data
for whatever figure I created anyways,
so that people don't need
to extract data from figures, which
is, in my opinion, really,
really painful to do.
Yeah.
What about you, [name]?
Do you try to avoid these manual tools?
Although I believe some of
the tools you mentioned earlier,
some of them are just manual
in a sense that you draw with the mouse.
Yeah, because I would say
there's two kinds of diagrams.
There's diagrams that are like
figures that you want to
create to illustrate a point or an idea,
and they are not necessarily published,
but they are like tools
for aiding discussion and that sort of stuff,
like the diagrams of how
your program works or diagrams
of what's going to happen with
the data or whatever, like
creating flow charts and stuff like that.
And that's never going to
be published because it's just
something you use to refine your ideas.
And for those things, like
like what you see is what
you get kind of tools are very nice
because then you can just like drag
and drop stuff and it doesn't matter
if it looks nice because
it's never going to be in a paper
or something and and when you
get to the like point where
you want to actually like have something that
is publishable ready or whatever,
then you need usually to just
pick one tool that you
can programmatically create the stuff
and then tune everything.
Then it becomes like a
hell of microtuning where you
tune every small bit and everything.
But that's not feasible if
you try to create a
quick demonstration or quick graph
for somebody else.
So there's use cases for
both kinds of tools.
Final question for both of you.
Do you always label your axis?
Or do you forget sometimes
to label the axis?
I would answer in a similar way
as what [name] said about
the building of figures.
If it's something for a quick sketch
for some internal presentation
or things where you just
want to show what's the general situation.
Yeah, a
can happen very, very often that
there is a missing access label or something.
For papers, I think I, for
the stuff that I published, I
had all access labeled.
I hope so, at least.
But yeah.
four internal preview things just so, yeah.
I was quoting this XKCD.
I added the link there
that some people, I'm very strict.
If I see a paper that
doesn't have labels on the axis,
I will reject if I'm the
reviewer of that paper.
You're absolutely right about that.
yeah all right so it's
almost o'clock let me check the
exact number of seconds so 15 seconds still
and it's great that people
are already editing the document
and basically we can actually
start so maybe if you zoom a bit
into this yeah hello everybody
and welcome to day two of python
for scientific computing yesterday we
had a look kind of how to run python
for example using jupyter and
what's under the hood when
it comes about loading data so
we talked about numpy and pandas and x-ray
Today we continue with the
more kind of data science workflow, like
for example, plotting the data
and more in general, we will
also cover a little bit more
with working the data.
In the afternoon, we go a little bit more
advanced maybe if you want to
think it like that meaning that
we try to remove the human
from the interface that we
can actually run Python without
you know clicking cells on Jupyter
and basically that means scripting
and scripts are very useful
for many different things especially
when you move your Python code
and data to larger system
like high performance computing clusters
And so that will be very interesting.
So again, there will be a little bit
for those of you who are starting,
but also something interesting
and useful for those of you
who have been using Python for many years.
Now, just a reminder, we
use this, what's the name?
Collaborative notes document.
So [name], if you could
switch to the collaborative notes.
and so if you scroll yeah
at the very top there is this pencil
that [name] is clicking and so
when you click the pencil
you switch to this edit mode and so
for example here [name] could
answer one of these icebreakers on
okay he was he used to use MATLAB
and Inkscape before making figures
and so you can do the
same you can already test this
they are able to edit it
and answer your your questions
a little bit more above from
today's i left the feedback from yesterday
so if you were around yesterday
and you didn't have time
to write some feedback from
yesterday's episode you can still
add it at the top of this notes document
what else the videos from
yesterday are already available in
our twitch tv channel basically
the same twitch tv link
that you're using today
and at the end of the
week we will upload the videos
to our youtube channel so that
you know you can watch them again and again
and again but now maybe
[name] can also show how to go
back to the view mode
because there's many hundreds of
people editing in parallel and
our poor server sometimes needs a
rest so when you click on the
eye icon it goes back to this view mode
But maybe one last reminder that
if you use Twitch TV, remember
to set the quality of the stream to source.
Otherwise, Twitch TV will
pixelate the image and it's
not nice when you're looking at text or code.
But basically, after this very
short intro, I will leave the
stage to [name] and [name].
And so enjoy your morning
with Python and talk to you later.
Yes.
So hello.
And before going to the
plotting, let's talk quickly, a
recap, like previously in
the previous episode, what we did yesterday.
So yesterday, the question was, okay,
introduction to the NumPy ecosystem
as a whole.
And there was a lot of stuff there.
Like for many people, it's
probably a first introduction to
Python in general or scientific Python.
So there was a lot of stuff.
So a quick recap before
we start the plotting, because
it's important to remember where
we came from and how we
utilize those tools now for new things.
So first off, NumPy.
So the idea behind NumPy was to...
We take, instead of using
like the Python basic types,
like integers and numbers, we use arrays.
So we collect a lot of
these numbers into one big block.
So then we can do
like collective operations on these numbers.
So, and we can calculate sums
for a huge number of numbers at a time,
or we can calculate various
like additions or multiplications or whatever.
over a large number of data
all at once, which brings speed
back into the question.
So that's basically the idea of NumPy.
And NumPy is underneath all
of the Python scientific computing.
Everything in scientific computing
is NumPy.
like built upon NumPy and the NumPy API.
So because NumPy provides these
kind of like basic tools of
like, okay, here's the idea of lots of numbers.
and that have a certain data
type and we can do some
collective operation on them.
Then we can build other tools
on top of this.
So one of these tools was
Pandas that we went through.
So Pandas was a tool and library
and framework for working with
lots of these arrays organized
into this data frame.
And in the data frame, we
had lots of these arrays as columns.
So each column was one array.
And we had this representation
of like this tidy data representation
where each column is a
variable and each row is an observation.
And because now we had this kind of like
mental model or organization for our data,
we could have lots of
data organized into one data frame.
Instead of figuring out individual arrays,
we had lots of these
collected into one data frame,
and then we could search in
the data frame and do all
sorts of operations with these columns.
Then we had the question of X-array,
which was, okay, like what
if your data isn't just
one dimensional array, but you
still want to collect them together somewhere.
So that was the idea of
X-array that we had multidimensional
data, like a
like a grid or something,
like a multidimensional grid.
And we put that into X-array data set.
So we collect all of
that together into this kind
of like a collection so that
we can then do operations on those
and keep our like sanity when
we have to operate with lots
of different data and try to,
want to figure out certain subset
of the data that we want to operate on.
So basically, it's all like
NumPy at the bottom is the
kind of like workhorse that speeds things up.
And Pandas is a way of
speeding our work up.
So it's a way of making our...
data organization and make it
easier to create workflows and
create code that makes us
able to answer questions with that data.
Instead of having million
arrays floating around, we
collect everything into the data frame.
And X-array does the same
kind of thing, but for multidimensional data.
So basically this was the whole
day here in five minutes.
But of course, there's lots
here, which is like
Skipped over.
Yeah, skipped.
But basically, that's the basic idea.
And the basic idea is that,
like, why does this matter?
Like, why can't I do whatever I want to do?
Like, the reason is that
if you have... Because there
is this NumPy ecosystem, like,
every other package and every
other framework can build upon
the, like, chosen types or,
like, build upon...
the way that the previous
ones did, like previous packages did.
So they can reuse the same ideas
and they can add more
functionality that you can achieve.
And that only works if
there's a common truth or common standards.
And NumPy is basically the
standard for Python.
That is the standard for how to represent
numbers and data in in like
close to the machine level speed like
so that you don't like run stuff slowly
and and pandas is a
way of representing this kind
of like tabular data and that
is basically a standard there's
like extensions or other packages that
do similar stuff to pandas,
but basically pandas and data
frame is the kind of
like standard for organizing this
kind of like tabular data.
So basically here's where we
can jump into the plotting.
So, so because like, why,
okay, what does this matter?
Like the reason is that when
we use now plotting, we want to plot stuff.
We can do it with multiple ways,
but the tool we are going
to be talking about, the Vega
Altair, is a tool that builds upon Pandas,
or the structure that Pandas provides,
and it can do lots of
beautiful plots very easily because
it knows that, okay, stuff is in data frames.
But there's other, of
course, other plotting tools
that we're skipping over.
So one of the biggest is Matplotlib.
So that's basically originally started
as Matlab's, like, plotting
interface made into Python.
Because, like, NumPy is
heavily influenced by Matlab.
Like, the underlying thing is heavily,
back in the day at least,
it was heavily influenced by Matlab.
So then...
they wanted to do a plotting library
that was similar to Matlab,
and that's Matplotlib, which is
a great plotting library, and
it's used widely, and it's a
very good thing to use.
But it's not... Well, it
has its own complications, but
there are previous lessons in
this course, previous years, that
you can find in...
in our YouTube channel that
you can check if you want to
have a good lesson on it, and
you can check the materials.
But we are going to be
focusing on Vega Altair this lesson.
And Vega Altair is a library
that is more heavily influenced by ggplot,
which is a library from
our ecosystem, which is this
kind of declarative plotting.
There are many other
plotting tools mentioned here.
So there's no, like already
mentioned in the icebreaker,
There's lots of tools.
None of them are wrong if
you get good plots out of them.
But Vega Alt here plays
nicely with the data frame.
So Vega Alt, like if you
have your data in this kind
of like format that Pandas provides,
so stuff is in columns.
you have columns of data, each stuff,
your data is in columns and
each row is an observation.
Then Vega Altair can read this in
and make easy, beautiful
pictures with minimal amount of code
and with this kind of
like declarative language so that you can like
You don't have to wonder
why certain things look the way they are.
You don't have to figure out, okay,
what is this axis I need
to modify or whatever it is.
These kind of low-level details
of the library.
So that's basically the test
that we are going to go through today.
So should we just start doing examples?
I would add just one
thing that's mentioned here as well
and why we are doing
the plotting in libraries and stuff
at all and not just use some
where some GUI interface to
draw lines like Excel stuff.
What we want to have is we
want to have a script that
reproduces the figure because that's
also part of reproducibility.
Because then we have a clear view of
how this is, how the final
plot relates to our actual data.
How, what is what, where does
the data come from?
And we want to have as little,
post-processing of these plots as possible.
Because if you do post-processing
of a plot, it's so easy
that something gets in the
wrong, gets slightly moved and
you don't even notice it.
And it messes up the whole,
this is the actual data that
is being plotted here.
So we want to have something
where we can click and this
produces the plot from the raw data.
And you can check, okay, what,
went where and you can
understand what is happening.
And I think that's an
important reason why we actually
use all these plotting libraries.
Yeah, that's an excellent point.
Like very, very good point.
My main reason is that I
don't want to figure out how
to make good plots if somebody
else has created a better way of doing it.
But that's a more ethical way
of looking at the thing.
Okay, so let's start with
Vega Altair and let's start
plotting some things.
But before we can start...
plotting anything, we need data.
So in this example, maybe
[name], can you make the Jupiter a bit bigger?
Yes.
Nice.
So in this example, we'll
use this temperature data set
from like from wherever, I don't know.
From Tromsø and I think it is Oslo.
Yeah.
So like, I don't know where
the data is collected, but
it doesn't really matter.
It shows like data from different stations,
weather stations, temperatures for
each month.
So we have this sort of
a data frame that we have over here.
Like usually when we have
this sort of data, like yesterday,
There was already talk about
what sort of modifications you might
do to a data when you get it.
In this case, the date is
in a weird format, so it's not an actual date.
It's a month year date format.
So it's just a string at this point,
but we want to make it
into an actual like date.
So, so like all of the
columns can have data in a
certain data type and we have
a data type for dates, which
is date time in Python.
So if we use this date
time, we can then like tell
that, okay, like this is now a date.
So we can strip out the
date from the bad string date time
and then make it into an
actual date that we store in a new column.
So now we can start the actual plotting.
So let's run this plotting code
and I'll then explain what
each of these pieces mean.
Do you want to, [name],
close the Jupyter news at the bottom?
It's driving me crazy.
Sorry.
Yeah, no problem.
So, okay.
What we have here, so if
you want to show the code at the top screen.
Yeah, yes.
And then we have a plot in the bottom.
So yeah, so then we here
have now a nice plot.
Like what happened?
Like what did we do to create this?
And let's go through the
whole thing, what Altair does.
So Vega Altair is like
you import it usually with this
import Altair as alt so
because nobody wants to write Altair over
and over again so many packages
when you import them they
have like a preference or like small alias
that you use to to use
them for Altair it's usually called
alt so if you see a
documentation or whatever it's usually
like alt something
And then we need to take
the data and give it to the plotting library.
And this in Altair, this
works with this chart object.
So everything is chart in Altair.
And chart basically defines all
the pieces of your plot.
And when we create a new
chart, the first thing we do is
that we give it the data
that it needs to operate on.
So in this case, we just
give it the data frame.
And it usually expects the data
to be in this data frame format.
It can also accept data.
like csv files and or
jasons or whatever but usually what
you want to do is to give it a data frame
after that we have this mark bar
so so when we have a chart
we often we want to modify that
and we do it by by calling
an attribute of of that chart and
then we can we can specify these um
can specify how do we want
to plot our stuff and this
is called these markings so the
for bar charts this is called
mark bar they're also like mark point
and mark line and all
sorts of like different markings
that we can use to represent
different kinds of data but we
tell it like okay how do we
how do we want to represent the
data in the plot so we declare
Like we want the bar chart over here.
And then comes the important
part, which is this encode, which sounds weird.
It might remind you of
like text encodings or something,
but it's not that.
The thing with the encode is
that when we have an encoding,
We convert, basically say to
the library that, hey, in
the chart, this thing in
the data should represent this...
this thing in the chart.
Like this thing in the
data should represent this thing in the chart.
And this is done via
these channels, these visual channels.
So in this plot, for example,
if you [name] want to keep it there.
So we have the X, Y
and color there mentioned.
So these are basically like we
say that X channel, so X direction.
So this is the visual channel
for the X direction.
We want
to put the date here, like
put date, use date to represent X direction.
And then for the Y channel, we say that,
hey, let's put the precipitation
to the Y channel.
So represent that in the Y direction.
But there's other channels as well.
There's huge amounts of
different channels that we can
do in Vega Altair.
So here we use color.
So we just put the name
to the color and Vega
Altair will automatically be like, okay,
I will now colorize based
on the name column of the data.
And because the data is in these columns,
Vega Altair, for example, if
you look at the X axis,
we have these dates over there.
It's no longer like in this
kind of like daytime look of the data.
It's actually represented as
text because Vega Altair based
on the column type,
It can now know that, okay,
I will want to represent this
as months, month names, the x-axis range.
It will automatically know that
the user wants to get this sort of like
representation.
If it would be like
nominal data, like names, like strings
or something like that, it would know that,
okay, I will represent this
as just like different categories.
Or if it would be like a continuous data,
it would know that, okay,
I will represent this as a continuous x-axis.
So it will determine what is the
what is the channel, like how
do it best represent the channel
based on the data type of
that channel or that like column over there?
So if we look at the
bit below, we can check the
next plot which illustrates this further.
So if we go and do the next plot.
So over here, we do a new plot where we
now tell the we set the
x-axis to be this year month
and then we have this colon and
t and the t here again tells
that it's a temporal data but
then we call it this year month
so we can say that okay like
give me year and a month over here
and use that representation.
We will talk a little
about transforms later, but it's
basically a transform where we say that,
hey, make the data into
years and months and put those
into the X categories.
With the colon,
After that, in the channel
name, we can describe what is
the data type of this channel.
What is the data?
How do we want to represent it?
Often, Altair recognizes
this automatically, but you
can overwrite them if you have something
that is floating point numbers,
but you want to represent this
as integers or something.
And these channels are quite
common in statistical languages.
So quantitative, it's basically
like it's categories.
So it's like strings or
something like that.
Ordinal is like these numbers
that are increasing in order.
So like from the...
scale of one to five, how
likely are you going to
recommend this course to your
friend, like that sort of like ordinal data.
Nominal data is
Sorry, I misspoke.
Quantitative is like a continuous data.
Yeah, my mistake.
Quantitative is continuous number data.
And nominal data is something with naming.
Like this is statistics talk.
Like if you have ever used like SPSS
or other these kind of
like things, they use these categories a lot.
Then there's temporal data, which
is, well, time.
And then there's the geostation,
which is like, if you have
a shape, there's other things
you can represent.
But that's for geoinformatics people.
There's lots of support for
these sorts of special things in
Vega Altair as well.
But this basically tells, how do
we want to view in the channel?
How do we want to encode
the data into the channel?
Like, how do we want to
represent it in the visual channel?
So basically the whole idea is
that we switch around these
channels and we put our data into the chart.
Then we decide, okay, how do
we want to view, what sort of
plot do we want to create
with the mark statement?
And then we play around with the channels
Well, get the kind of plot we want to do.
So let's try another kind of plot.
Let's add another column.
So instead of doing like subfigure
or something like that, or
adding figure, we can just add
a new channel for column.
And now Vega Altair will
automatically know that, okay, you
want two columns of plots and let's put...
the data from name, like
separate it based on the name category.
So in this case, the name
was the name of the station.
So we get two plots for
one for each station.
So you can also use this as
a row for if you want to
do multiple rows of plots,
And it basically what, what
Vega Altair under the hood does
is that it does group wise.
So it, it, because the data
is a data frame, it will
group the data based on the value of the,
of the, um, like in this case, the column,
uh, the column name, and it
will, it will then like for
each of those data, it will do a separate plot.
Uh,
We can then do, like, if we want to,
we didn't like that, like,
we didn't want to, like, use
so much space in our figure.
We can also do something like x offset,
which basically, like, makes all
of the bars, like, offset from each other.
So this is, like, common way
of doing plots as well.
So we can get, like,
different... It's actually bars side
by side instead of on top of each other.
Yeah.
And we can also do like,
uh, like in the next example,
we can, we can, uh, for example, plot ranges.
Just as I mentioned, the
X offset is particularly important
if you have more than two things.
With two, it's commonly not that
big of an issue because you
see the higher bar, you always
see it in the back, but, um, you could also.
could end up with something
with not seeing something and
x offset essentially allows you
to have them side by side yeah
and then then we can do
all sorts of plotting like we can
plot uh we can plot areas so
in the example uh we can we
can tell that we want to plot an area with uh
with, uh, X and Y, uh, like
if, if you go bit down in
the, in the page, uh, yeah.
Like if you look at the
code, code for that.
Yes.
So we can, we can do stuff like plot areas.
So here we mark areas and
for the area, we, we want to
have like an, like an X and Y, uh,
like X ranges or Y ranges.
So for that, we can use this Y2.
So in this case, we encode,
we have still the X axis is
the same, but now we highlight
an area with like maximum
temperature, minimum temperature.
So we have two different columns
that define these like top
and bottom of the area.
And where they overlap, we
can see this shaded region.
So we can create plots such
as this quite easily.
To ensure that it's not...
canceling each other out, you
have this opacity, which you cannot,
which if we set this to,
you wouldn't see where the,
well, except for this tiny
bit here, you wouldn't see where things are.
Yes.
So there are many, like,
for the mark statements, so for
the data, like, how do we
want to represent data?
There's lots of
changes we can do, like if we plot points,
we can decide how big the
points are and that sort of stuff.
If we plot bars, we can
make the bars rounded if we want.
there's a huge number of
these examples of these different, uh,
ways of encoding the data, uh,
in the, in the documentation.
The documentation is really clear
and the examples are like super, super nice.
So what I usually do is
that if I want something, I
will look at the examples and
then, uh, then check, okay,
what, what are they?
So there's huge number, huge
number of these, uh,
different ways of representing the data
and so basically what is
the core tenet here or core
idea the core idea is that like
if you want to plot something
like anyways you need to plot
it in like a paper like you have a 2D paper
that you want to plot something into
so your data will have some
sort of like XY axis somewhere
and if you have your like if
you anyways need to have it
in this sort of a, like, way.
Like, you can't plot, like, like,
13 dimensional data or something
like you can't plot like an X array.
You have to take some slice of it,
or you have to take like
some, uh, some average over it or something.
So when you have this sort of, like,
you want to plot something, if
you can take your data, let's
say you take your average temperatures or your.
your um like your like house
price at at a certain time
or whatever like you have different exits
that you want to have you can then
if you have it in the
data frame in the tidy format
you can then easily tell a
vega alter that hey here's my data
But here are all of the
columns that are here.
I want you to take
these columns and convert those
into like things in the graph.
Like I want to take stuff
in those columns and make
it into something that is a graph.
So then that's basically the whole idea.
So let's play around with this.
So let's have exercises.
let's have exercises and let's go
through them so that you
have enough time to like
actually familiarize with the ecosystem.
So first off, well, you
can read the exercise over here,
but try to reproduce what we
have over here and check what you get out of it.
And there's a good question,
like, should you format your
data in Pandas first before using Vega Alter?
And usually, like, data preprocessing
and stuff like that is a
large chunk of everyday work
when you're doing, like, scientific work.
So usually you want to process it into a...
way where you can then
tell Vega-Altair to plot whatever
you want it to plot.
We'll talk later about how
Vega-Altair can also make like,
how you can modify the plots
and how you can modify the
data while you're plotting it, but
But yeah, usually you want to
have it at least in the
format, the tidy format, so
that you can represent all
of the different channels
with different columns.
But yeah, let's go to
exercises, I would say.
So should we return at... In 10 minutes?
Or maybe 15.
Okay, so 48 then.
Yes, yeah.
See you then.
Bye.
Hello again.
So we are back from the exercises.
So hopefully you managed to do them.
We are going now for a break.
So just like a reminder to
get some steps in and get some water
or coffee or whatever the
beverage of your choice and relax for a bit.
You can, of course, do
the exercises while the break is going.
But after that, we'll talk
more about like what sort of
things you can do in Vega Altair.
There were good questions in
the notes, but we'll put more there.
Like if you encounter problems,
if you figure out something nice,
if you have, I'll add a
poll there of did you complete
any of the exercises, add to
that poll and we'll be back in,
11 or 11 in Finnish time.
Other times for like, at the
hour at the hour, we'll be back at the hour.
So have a nice, quick break
and then let's continue.
So, hello, we're back from the break.
Hopefully you managed to run
some of the exercises and see
what, what came out of them.
So now we are going to
be looking at various other
like features and things that Begaltech can do.
We'll talk, we'll check more,
more fancy plots and stuff like that.
In the notes, there were a
lot of good chatting.
So first off, I will say
there was a question of whether
Vega Altair is better than others.
Not really, like nothing is,
like the end result matters, right?
Like if the plot is nice, if
it was nice to make it, that's what matters.
If you want to use
something like Matplotlib, that's
great as well.
Like Vegalta has some extra
features that Matplotlib doesn't have.
Matplotlib has like lower
level control that you can do,
but it's all about like whether
you get your plots done.
And Vega Altair is designed
for this kind of data
visualization when you have your data in order.
So if your data is in a complete disarray,
that might be also... It might
be hard to get it into
Vega Altair, but that might be
the least of the problems at that point.
But yeah, there's no best tool.
Whatever floats your boat, that's the...
Um, that's the thing you want to use.
Uh, so, so, but, but
I prefer Vega-Altea before, because
I feel like I'm more in
control of what's happening because
I tell it what I want to
happen and then it does it.
And if it doesn't do it, I
will modify it a bit, but usually
I look at the examples and choose
a plot I want to use and then go forward.
Um.
Yeah, so let's continue with
the plottings and let's look at other things.
So [name], if we check first,
like how do we modify our plots?
Like the previous plots, they
were nice, but they weren't
like publication nice.
So often what we want to do
is we want to customize the channels.
And in Vega Altair, all
of the channels that we
specify, by default, you give
them these shorthands.
Or usually, when you start
at least plotting, you give
them these shorthands of what data
you want to encode into a
channel, like what data column you
want to put into whatever feature of the plot.
But at some point you want
to make certain that like
everything looks nice and like
is organized neatly and whatever
has a nice title or something.
And for this, you can use
these, you can use the channels directly.
So what Vega Altair does under the hood,
that if it gets a string as a channel,
it will create the channel
with defaults, like sensible defaults,
and it will use those.
But you can...
you can create the
channel objects directly.
So in this example, instead
of just using the channels as they are,
we create the channels ourselves
and we set reasonable titles for them.
so so we get better namings
so instead of having this like
in the plot below you can
see that the these are
these auto-generated uh channel names
like year month and whatever date
and they might not look pretty
because they are basically taken
from the data frame uh like
the names so so instead of
using those let's just give
the channels different titles
And it's very simple how it usually works.
So if you have a channel,
you usually have an alt and
then with a capital, the
channel, and that's the class
of the channel that you want to use.
So for example, X and Y
and color and that sort of
stuff, like you can...
You don't have to be
Sherlock Holmes to have a
detective sense of like, okay,
what would be the name of this channel?
But if you're unsure, it's
good to check the documentation.
There's a whole list of
the channels named and whatever
channels you want to modify,
they're listed there.
And you can check for each
of these channel classes, there's
huge number of parameters that you
can use to modify the plots.
So you can change titles,
you can change placements, you
can change rotations and all
sorts of stuff that you want to use.
You can optimize your plots
in various different ways.
And this makes it already like
a bit nicer of a picture
when like the small details are set up.
But usually like when you're
still working on a plot,
like the most important thing
is the graph itself.
And then later on you like
need to pick all of the
small details at the edges.
Like you can change,
change the ranges of X, Y
axis and that sort of stuff.
Like you can do all sorts
of like, you can set the
limits, like, yeah, whatever you can think.
Basically you can set them in the channels.
Yeah.
Was that not the correct one?
According to the axis, that
should be a option.
Let me check.
Oh, dict float.
Wait, no, float.
It is a float.
Okay.
Let me check the actual encoding.
So, alt y. So...
It's not a part of, it's
not for why, but it's for something else.
But you need to give it
a different, like, let's not figure
it out on the fly probably.
But yeah, you can do all sorts of stuff,
but it's best to look at
the, like the reference in the guide
or check one of the, like
the examples and copy paste
code from there, what usually people do.
Then, like, once you have
your nice plot that you have,
you can save them, of course.
And it's very easy.
You just call this save.
And then what you get is the plot.
Yeah.
And you can view it.
Well, if you're saving it as like a PNG,
which is like a rasterized image,
so it's like the raw image data there,
you usually want to specify
the pixels per inch, like
what is the resolution of the image.
By default, it can look a bit blurry,
but often you want to save it
as SVG or like as a
vector format or like to make it
crisp or PDF or something.
And
And Vega Altair supports various different,
like it supports SVG, PNG, and PDF outputs.
So you can use all
of these different outputs to create your plot.
There's also like nice support
in Vega Altair for web like web things.
So if you notice in the
already in the plots we were doing, we had this
like in the Jupyter Notebook,
we had these like
interactive, like semi-interactive things.
That's because like it renders
it as HTML and it shows that straight up there.
So you can do HTML saving and
and JSON saving, and then
you can embed those JSONs to different places.
What you can also do is that you can
even create this shareable link,
which basically just creates a
huge link that then you can
send to somebody, and they can
open the link with this URL thing.
And because, like, Vega
Altair underneath it, it uses
this, yeah, like, you will get
this sort of a link.
And if you open that
link without the quotes,
Yeah, you will get this.
You can view this in this Vega editor.
A reminder that when you send
this sort of a link, it
encodes some of the data needed
to plotting the data into the link itself.
It encodes all of the data
that it needs to plot this.
So everything that's in the plot
is in the link.
So basically, if you...
have some, I don't know, private data
or whatever, like make certain
that like, yeah, nothing.
Don't use that.
Yeah, yeah.
But if you want to send something
for your friend, like you
can just send them a massive
link and that will, they can view the plot.
Okay, there's other things you can do.
So let's look at some fun
new, let's do some fun things
with the visual channels.
So here we have like daily
data now of snowfall in Tromsø and Oslo.
And we'll do the usual like
kind of like date conversions and
limit us to a certain date range.
And then we can plot the data.
here we have like now we have the date
and there's no depth as x
and y channels and then we
have the column as name but
what if we now colorize this
based on another another
column like max maximum temperature
so what we get is this
so now the color corresponds so
we have like 3d plot in a
sense of course like it's 2d
but the color represents another
piece of data so we see
that okay there's like some warm
days some some cold days and we
can see that if there's a
warm day usually like the the
like if it's a dark
After the dark band in
the snow data, usually the snow
starts to go down.
Like, well, it's hotter.
The maximum temperature is higher than,
well, the snow melts and
otherwise, like, it might increase.
So we can represent this sort
of stuff over here.
We can also change the colorings.
Like over here, we would
change the color channel so we
can change the scale.
Do you know that when
you're using these colorings and
stuff like that, you usually want to...
there's a whole subject
of like perceptually, perceptually
like correct colorings.
And many of these, like you
want to check Matplotlib and for Altera
and various other libraries, like
there are these colorings that
are designed for plotting
scientific data where the idea is
that like certain, like
human eye recognizes certain
like brightness differences
changes or color changes differently.
So you might want to use
plotting like this to make certain
that the actual luminosity or
intensity of the color
represents actual ranges in the data.
like if you have a
data that, like otherwise you
might see artifacts, like for
example, in this rainbow coloring,
it's pretty like, like I'm
pretty certain the changes aren't
that drastic, but it looks
very drastic to our eyes that
like, hey, like the days
are completely different, but
like actually they might be,
very similar in the data values.
So when you're playing
with these colorings, don't only look
for the coloring that looks
pleasing to the eye, but also
check that the coloring is
like this perceptually neutral.
There's also the question
of like accessibility of can,
does the coloring have colorblind like...
like taken into account and
that sort of stuff, but
there's like whole books on this.
So I won't go too far into this detour,
but when playing around
with colorings, it's good to reminder
that like sometimes choosing a
coloring is more than just the looks.
It's also like, does it
represent the data correctly?
Okay.
Let's do another plot with,
but this time with circles.
So let's try this one.
So over here, now we, instead
of mark bars, we use mark circles so we can do
stuff like this, like we can,
we can, uh, plot things like this.
We can, uh, in like, it's
not in the material, but in
Altair, you can also like
add multiple layers to the plots.
Like, um, like you can plot
lines over dots and stuff like
that, if that makes the
coloring, uh, easier for you.
But let's not go to that
because we want to go to
the other, other things as well.
Um.
Okay, so we have talked
about the visual channels a lot,
but can you... When you're taking
the data into Altair, like, there
was a good question in the
notes that should you, like,
first... Like, what format should
the data be in?
Like, should you do all
of the data transformations before
you plot them?
And that's usually a good idea.
Like, if you know what you're
going to be plotting, it might
be a good idea to...
like to pre-calculate the data
as far as possible and then just plot it.
As long as it's in this
tidy format, you can like do
that sort of things.
But sometimes, especially when
you're exploring the data, you
might not know what is the,
like, what are you going to be plotting?
Are you going to be
plotting like monthly data or
weekly data or daily data or whatever?
And in Vega Altair, there's
this powerful data transformations
that you can use.
So these data transformations,
basically they take the initial data
and then based on the
channels, like whatever transformations
you do to the channels, it will modify
the visual channels with
those transformations.
So for example, in this
transformation, in the original data,
we had daily values, but let's
say we want weekly values.
So in here, we can take
the original code and instead
of using the original code,
So this is what the original
gave, which is just for the
few days from December to May.
And this is the transformation
where you actually look over
the whole year, because you do it by week.
And yeah, get a yearly picture.
I would actually say it all.
It's, it's not just if you
want to play around.
It's also this is some
kind of visualization question.
This is not a data question.
So the pre processing that I
think we said we answered in
the in the document is most
because if you actually need to
modify data in some way or form.
not how you visualize this and
this is uh more the how
is the data actually being visualized
in the end yeah the the
only reason why i mentioned
that like sometimes you might want
to do it beforehand is that like
if you do the data like
let's say averaging over a week
or something in pandas or
in other frameworks such as that
you can get a more like physical
feeling of of like okay
this has been calculated correctly
like with the with the
alter transformations of course
it's it's calculated correctly but
with any kind of like system that that um
that is like a library
or something, you usually want
to make certain that the results are correct.
So it's actually plotting the
right data or the right thing you're doing.
And I'm not saying it's not
doing it over here, but the
more complex the system is, it's
easier to not be certain
that you actually calculated
the averages correctly.
So that's why I was saying that usually...
the in the exploration time
you you would do this and
sometimes you would calculate
the weekly averages yourself to verify
that these are actually the
correct numbers but um how
these aggregations work so
all these transformations is that
uh in these transformations you if
you want to show the code
for that generated the the plot yeah so
We have data transformations,
like there's multiple of these, but
in here we use a data
transformation for the date, so the
X axis, and we tell it to take weeks.
So we want to convert it into weeks.
And what it does, basically it
does it at this point, it does
a group by like it groups
the data into weekly bins.
And, and then for those bins,
we can do aggregations.
So like a mean value, like
it means node ref, instead of
like, um, just plotting everything
in that, uh, in that, uh,
bin so we calculate the average of
that bin the weekly thing
the weekly mean snow death so
yeah I just would say in this
case there is not the weekly average is
because we have the daily values
and it's not an average
over multiple different years which
this could also that's kind of the one of the
um risks with a plot like
this this could also be something
that is visualizing the average
things over multiple years yeah
yeah sure sure yeah like it's a
bit uh from the plot itself it's unclear
what exactly yeah yeah but but
in this case we have had data
from one year so yeah i'm
i'm just saying that this is
the kind of thing where um you
Probably with access labeling
and things, you should make
clear what is actually in the blog there.
Of course, yes.
You might use something like
yearweek or something.
I think there might be... I
don't know if there's such a channel there.
Let's continue.
Yeah, but basically the idea is
that you can use these
transformations to quickly convert
the data into a format where...
like you can plot it in
various kinds of like ranges and things
and automatically do some
aggregation there's also like
the possibility of using different
like modes like yeah so it's
I think it's alter theme now
there's yeah don't have to update that that one
I think it's Altair theme dark.
Yeah.
And then we actually get
to our final exercise.
Yes.
So now you can pick, you can pick
and choose what, what looks good
to you in the, in the, in
the examples for Vega Altair.
And then, yeah, check some of
those and try to implement those.
There's other things that we
don't have time to go through.
So, for example, I use
nowadays Vega-Alte quite often.
I do interactive plots with
selections and whatever.
Like you can do interactive...
plots with with uh selections
and stuff like that but
that goes way deeper so if
you want to like visualize data
and have like clickable elements
in the plots for notebooks and stuff like
that you can do that in vegalter
as well because it has this web support
but but let's not go there
let's uh that's something for that
you can look for later maybe
in the examples if you want to
look at one of those examples
but now let's have an exercises
uh until uh well 11 35 let's have 15
so you have time to go
through so 11 35 let's return them bye
Welcome back.
Hello.
So yeah, so now we
have gone through plotting.
So we have a quick session
here about we talk about a
bit about like data handling
with and working with data with
pandas and all of the different frameworks.
The reason why we want to
mention this is that this is
like, like there were a lot
of questions there, for example, like,
where you should do the
data transformations and do you
do it with pandas or whatever.
And usually like getting the
stuff into the right format and getting
that stuff right, like
for whatever simulation you want to do
or code you want to run
or something like the data
part is usually where
like people, well, everybody has
the most trouble or uses the most time.
There's been talk that like
in the field that like 80%
of time with data analysts or
whatever they use like for
data pre-processing and data handling
and data kind of like cleaning
up and that sort of stuff.
So it's very important subject
to be mindful of.
It's not the fun part.
Like the fun part is
the actual, like writing the
actual model or simulation or
or the actual science that does it.
But in order to do that,
you usually need to have the
data in a correct way that you
can then do some sort of analysis
from it and at the end, do
some plotting from it and then
do some papers with it.
But for all of this, the
important thing is that at the
start, you need to have the
data in a correct way.
And unfortunately, it's also not
something that you can say,
okay, you always do pre-processing
like this because the pre-processing
and the data wrangling is
very much topic specific.
So we can't go into
any details here because it would
just not be applicable to 90%
of the people, each individual bit.
And that's why we are in
this working with data focused
on a larger picture of things.
Yeah, and there's no, like,
this section is small.
It doesn't have exercises, so
you can just focus on what
we're saying and no need to,
like, check on the Jupiter that much.
But so when we are talking
with data, what [name] just said was,
was like, there are million
of these formats.
And whenever somebody thinks that, okay,
I have one tool to
solve everything, they just
create another format.
So this XKCD highlights this perfectly.
So if there is like a
thing that needs to be like represented somehow,
like somebody creates a standard
around it and suddenly there's
yet another standard around it.
So that happens.
So there's no like one way
to represent data, but there's
usually like ways that, well,
there's, there's better ways and
less, less good ways.
And we'll, we'll talk about them later,
but usually like, but there's no
one way of doing it that
there's like, there's so many
different ways of doing it.
But what is important is
to recognize that, okay, like
there's the question of, okay,
what sort of data are you dealing with?
What is your data structure?
And recognizing that is important
before you start picking up
any sort of data formats.
So for example, if you're
dealing with tabular data,
like the tidy data format
is the most common way of representing that,
both for the computer, like
when you're doing stuff with pandas,
but also like when you have
a table or something, you want
to have it like represented like that.
Or when you start plotting,
you want to have it represented like that.
And even if you're not
doing like, let's say you're
doing physics simulations or something,
and you think that, okay,
like my data isn't in tabular
format, I don't care about this.
But
But let's say you want
to calculate something, like you
want to represent an average
of the temperature of the
system state over time or something,
or how it scales or something like that.
You have an X and Y axis.
Well, again, you have something
that is like a tabular data
or like how many simulations you did.
what simulations you did
with which parameters or whatever.
It's tabular data.
So even if your simulation
data isn't like that, the end
result is usually represented in
a tabular format.
And if you're doing like
these big simulations, you often
use like this kind of like
block way of representing data.
So you have arrays then.
So for example, NumPy arrays
are usually like multidimensional.
They can be one
dimensional, two dimensional,
three dimensional arrays.
And you can have them stored
in a different way.
But if your data is this
kind of block data, that's
different to this kind of tabular data.
So it's good to recognize what
sort of data are you dealing with.
And so do you have this sort of like...
blocky data, like let's say
3D simulations or something,
3D space represented as a
big block of numbers, or do
you have like economics data that
is like lots of lots of tables?
So, and for these different
tools, like you wouldn't use an
Excel to store whether like
weather simulation data and
you wouldn't use weather simulation
data to store like Excel spreadsheets.
So there's like a tool for
each one of these purposes.
And [name], maybe you can explain
what do you look for when
you now need to pick a tool?
So you need to pick a
file format for your data.
So I'm looking at it from
a couple of different angles.
I'm looking at what is a
good way to represent it.
And at the same time, also
what is actually being used
currently in the field that I'm working in.
Because there is a bit of a trade-off.
You could have a perfect tool
for something, but if no
one uses that perfect tool, whatever you do,
it will be extremely
incompatible to whatever anyone else is doing.
And you can try to get this now
as a new standard, but
yeah, maybe it's just not worth
it because the tools that
are currently being used are fine.
And then better don't
have another standard.
That's this XKCD.
And apart from that, yeah,
really looking into what is a
good tool to be used or what
how can I represent my data
in a usable fashion?
And also what's my target audience?
Is my target to create data
that a human can quickly inspect
and have a look at to
figure things out themselves?
Then I would like to
have something that's human
readable, that could be a CSV,
that could be a JSON file.
If I want something that is
only to be processed by a
computer, I would definitely want
to go into some kind of
binary format because it doesn't
need any parsing anymore and it's
a lot more precise.
For example, with CSVs, if
you have floating point data
or any non-integer numeric data,
you have cutoffs, you
have certain precision cutoffs.
And that means that if you do a simulation,
store it in CSV and load
it again, the values have changed.
Not a lot, very minimal,
but depending on your simulation,
that can cause a lot of problems.
Yeah, like the double
precision floating point number has
like 15 to 16 precision
points of like precision.
So like if you have a CSV file,
either you need to have
like huge numbers there, like
huge strings of text to represent everything,
or you truncate it somewhere
and now you introduce like an
error that can propagate throughout
your like analysis pipeline.
So it would be better to
store it in a binary format that
stores it as a floating point number.
So then you can keep the precision.
And in most cases, you also,
when you store this text, you're
blowing up the size of it.
Because the precision in a
floating point is as compact as it gets.
And if you put that into a string, yeah,
even if it's less precise,
it takes more data.
So you're wasting data and
that becomes a particular problem
if your amounts of data start to get large.
Yeah, and when data comes large,
what often happens is that the question of,
do I actually need all of
my data with me to answer
a question, it becomes important.
So when you have to answer
a question based on data, whatever it is,
the question you have to
answer, it becomes more important
to not load everything into memory.
The more data you have, if you just...
load all of your data into memory then
but then decide that actually i
i just want this one one
column like like the rest of
it just like i don't i don't
care about it there usually what happens is
that the rest of the data
is still stored in memory like
you you you have allocated
into memory and suddenly your
code requires a lot more resources
and a lot more well power uh than um
than is necessary.
And even if you would really discard
and purge the memory again,
you will need this short time
where you need all the memory.
So yeah, having a format
that from the format itself can tell, okay,
if you want column 10, I
go to this position in the
file and just read that.
and just read this bit of the file
and give you that bit of
the file, that will help a lot
or it will make it a lot more sufficient.
And many of the data formats,
like the more advanced data
formats, they also make it
possible to like pick what data
you want from the data.
Like you don't necessarily have
to load everything all at once.
Like with a CSV file, you
usually have to load the whole file at once.
But with many of the advanced formats,
you can tell it that, okay,
like I just want this column
and it will only load that column.
There are so many of these formats
that we don't possibly have
like capability of going through them.
So we have this kind of
like not exhaustive list, but
quick list of like explaining
various kinds of like data formats
that you can use.
Like if you load raw
data from the internet, it's often
like CSV or JSON.
Yeah.
Especially in web communications,
if you have APIs, it's
very, very often that you get
some kind of JSON responses that
you then need to process.
You can also get files,
of course, so binary files,
but it really depends.
Yeah.
For example, going a bit in this list,
So there are advantages,
disadvantages to most formats, and
it really depends what your specific topic is.
For example, if we take, let's say,
pickle, so the Python
export functionality, that's great
because it essentially can store
any data, any data that a Python object has.
However, it comes with its own problems.
Like you need the right
versions loaded when you actually
load the data, because if the data format,
the internal data format of
a library has somewhat changed,
then suddenly the pickle data
file is corrupt because it
can't be interpreted anymore because
it doesn't know what it is.
So pickle is something where,
yeah, it can be really powerful
because it can store anything,
but you need to make sure
that this, but it's not a
format to transfer information.
Yeah.
It's usually also not recommended
for sharing information because it
has its own, like you can
put arbitrary code in pixels.
So it's not something you
want to like load, like you
don't want to execute a
random code that somebody else
has like given to you.
So it's not,
the kind of a format that
you would want to use for long term.
But if you have like
a situation, like often, like we
think of this like analysis kind of things
that we start from the data
and we have the original data
and then we just like
keep it along the way and
we just do everything with that
until we get to the end.
But often in a simulation
or research problem that you're
trying to solve, you need
to create an intermediate representation
of the data.
You take the original data, you pick
you clean it up, like
do some pre-processing for it,
and you may store it into
some format that is easy to
use for your actual analysis code.
And then the results you store again,
like in some way that makes
it easy to share with other researchers.
But there's this kind of
like intermediate step where usually
you want to pick
something like you can store
the state of your system
temporarily like just like okay like this is
A checkpoint, or this is like the,
after pre-processing the data
looks like this and, and stuff like that.
And usually you will want to do this,
um, to, to make your code more efficient,
but also, um, like, like
separate the different stages of
your code and, and make, like,
make it certain that, okay,
like after your pre-processing, you
don't have to do the pre-processing again.
It's done.
Now you have the intermediate
step and then you can continue on your way.
Yeah.
There is this huge
distinction between binary and
textual formats.
And I think it's good to
kind of remember what the things are for this.
Yeah.
What are the good and bad things with it?
And it's pretty clear that
on binary file formats, they
are a tendency more efficient if
they are being used by a
computer, if they are being used by a program.
they can store data more
compact they can more easily
access individual pieces of the
data within the file and so
on but of course the disadvantage
is they are more specific so
you need to have something that
can parse them because a human
looking at this yeah sees ones
and zeros or hex code or
however the editor that they are
looking at it and then yeah
It's more prone to not be compatible.
Textual formats have exactly
the opposite of that.
Yeah, you can read them
quite easily because they are just text,
but they are prone to
imprecisions, as mentioned before.
They can be or they can
very often are relatively slow
to read right because yeah you
can't just hop into a certain position.
And you need to read
essentially all data to get to a certain point.
And it's almost impossible in
texture data or not impossible
but quite difficult to get
really multi dimensional data in
a textual format.
you can get, it leads to
a very, very strange replication of
a lot of elements.
You can do something like that in JSON,
but it's blowing up the amount of data
that you need to store
because you essentially need to,
for every dimension, you need
to replicate the identifiers every time.
Because yeah, you can just think about it.
You can't really put,
multidimensional data on a piece
of paper you can write it
down but then you replicate things
or you need to you need
to know additional information and
at some point like like the
data becomes like basically like
once you have enough like json files
or whatever you anyways need
to use computers to to read
them like you won't go through
it by hand yourself like csv you can read it
if you look at it.
But for many complex data formats,
once you get complex enough
data, you eventually will use
computers to read them anyway.
So it becomes important
to understand what's in your
data and what's the format there.
There's also the whole question of...
Like we already mentioned
that it's important to pick a
data type in your field.
So like as a general like consideration
or kind of like things that
you like good things to check
is that is somebody else like...
else using this so for
example like previously there was
this geo json mentioned so
if you're doing like map data
if you're trying to do like like if you
if you're dealing with map data
or something like that you
there's like geopandas there's
this whole ecosystem of like how
do you deal with with
different coordinate systems and
mapping data and stuff like
that if you're doing physics
simulation there's different formats
for that and like usually you want to
to pick out what is
important for your field.
Like what I usually do
is whenever there's a new tool
that needs to be used, I look
at what are the import and
export functions of that and
check, okay, what does this need?
What does this tool use?
What does this, what
representation it wants from me to
be able to use this tool?
And then try to wrangle my
data into a format that the
tool uses so that it can utilize that.
And it becomes very important also
for like replicability of your like,
like how do you, how can
you reproduce your results?
Like if nobody else can
reproduce your data or like
wrangle your data into the
same format, it's very hard for people to,
replicate your results or reuse
your code like if you have a code
that does an analysis but
the input needs to be in a format
that is like you need
to have it specifically tailor made
for this kind of like
weird format then suddenly like
nobody will want to use that
so if you want others to be
able to use your tools and
what you have created you really
want to pick something that well
others can use and others can utilize.
Even if that is maybe
not the most efficient for
your particular case, because
it's a trade-off.
It's something that might be
the lowest common denominator for
all the different types of
analysis that are done in this field is
this format.
Yeah, it has disadvantages, but
we can do everything with it.
So yeah, each subfield in
the field might have a perfect thing
for them, but yeah, then
it's not transferable or
it's extremely difficult to transfer.
And when we started today
already like talking about, okay, like
how these different tools
played together, like NumPy is
the building block at the start.
Then Pandas is the representation of like,
okay, how do I represent
multiple of these arrays into
like a cohesive data set?
How do I get the
different formats again together?
Yeah.
Because...
x x array one x sorry numpy
is this is one data type and yeah we we
but we often need these
multiple data types in one set
of data yeah and that is
something that numpy can't do
Yeah, and we often want to transfer
that information to the next
piece in our tool set.
So when we have NumPy arrays,
we put those into Pandas.
When we have Pandas, we put
that into Vega Altair to get plots out of it.
So we often have this kind
of like a situation where
like somebody, some framework
or something decides that, okay,
like this is a good decision.
And it's not like...
decision by VR or just because
we say it's that.
I often think of it is
that all of the decisions made
to create these frameworks are
paved with problems that have been solved.
There's this saying that
like workplace regulations are
written by blood so that like every
if there's an accident like
some regulation comes out of it
and there is some reason
why this regulation has been created and with
with kind of like frameworks
it happens the same kind of
way like people have tried
to figure out solutions to
answer their questions and eventually
you only see the end point
you see the regulation you
see the framework that okay like
why does this require me to
give it in this sort of
format the reason is somewhere there
but it's it can be like 10 years ago like like
somebody realized that this is
a better solution for the problem.
And I personally appreciate it a lot
so that we can like
build upon the shoulders of giants,
like we can build upon like
the work done by previous people.
And that's why I often like
to use these tools.
And this is also important because like
if you want to go further,
like if you want to, like we are now going
Like we are looking from NumPy to Pandas,
but there's stuff further away
there as well.
Like there's like the big
data analysis pipelines.
And we don't have time in
this course to go through like Polars
and IBIS and other like this
kind of like tools that can
like leverage, like if you have
a big data warehouse or something
in a company, or if you have
a lot of big databases that you need to analyze.
In those cases, it's mandatory
to use their way of
doing stuff because otherwise you
can't like really analyze
access even that data.
You can't just ask, if
you're working in Google and ask
for a huge number of data,
your computer would explode.
You would want to be very precise on
what sort of data you want
to request from these big data warehouses.
And in those cases, it
becomes even more crucial to
pick the way that is
designed to solve these questions.
And it limits what you can
do, but at the same time,
it gives you more power.
And so it's not a trade off of liberty.
You give up some liberty to get more done.
But I think with that, we
are reaching the end of this session.
thank you so much [name] and [name]
it is now time for a lunch
break some people in the
comments yesterday were suggesting to
skip the lunch break i believe
we need to eat and it's important to eat
so we will be back in
one hour you can still use the notes document
if you have any other questions
and i will not steal any
more time from your lunch so see
you in one hour bye bye bye
Hello, hello and welcome back
from the lunch.
So you've been active with the notes.
There are very interesting
discussion, especially when working
with the large data sets.
We try to answer it a
bit, but feel free to, you
know, ask more and discuss more.
But now for something
completely different, or is
it completely different?
I don't know.
Well, first of all, I want
to introduce a new instructor with us today.
It's [name].
[name], do you want to
say something about yourself?
Sure.
Hello, everyone.
I'm [name].
I'm RSE at Aalto.
And I will be talking
about this lesson about scripting
in a few seconds.
yes and in my opinion this
is just my personal opinion this
is the most beautiful and
most important lesson out of
the whole course because you
will really realize that Jupyter is
just a way to prototype
and familiarize with Python and
with data science but when you
need to scale up when you
need to consider reproducibility
using remote systems like
high performance computing clusters
this next hour is you know
you you will go back to
this to the materials from this next hour on
how to write python scripts so
i will not steal any more
time from our instructors and i
let you go with the
python scripting production for the
pressure of delivering the
most beautiful lesson according to you
So hello everyone.
Now we're talking about scripting.
So why do we want to create a script?
So why aren't we not, are
we not happy with Jupyter Notebook so far?
Well, Jupyter notebooks are great
for exploring, for prototyping,
which is what we do a lot when we do science.
You know, we do research,
we generally don't know what we are doing,
we want to try, we want
to get instant feedback, maybe we
want to blend our math notes
with our code, with pictures, to
get a gist of what we
are doing, of our research, our work.
Then now we are slowly
moving towards the next step where we know
what we are doing and
we have found actually something that works.
So we have developed a nice
tool for doing some analysis.
We have tried with some
parameters, with some values, with some data,
but now we want to generalize
it to make more generic.
We want to make sure that
everyone can use it with
different data, with different settings
and so on and so on.
And we wanted to make
this process of tweaking
the different settings, tweaking
different values as easy as possible.
And the limitation with Jupyter
Notebook is that it's this
blended text of code, pictures, text,
where if we want to
change values, we should edit
the notebook directly.
So open it, go through the
code, find the right place,
change the value, and so on.
And this is not very ergonomic.
So we want to find a
more dynamic way of doing this.
And I'm also, I'm not alone here.
I have my great co-teacher, [name],
who will also deliver questions
from the interactive notes system.
So whenever you have questions,
you can interrupt me, ask
questions, and we will address it together.
[name], do you want to add
something so far to this introduction?
Not a lot.
The other thing to me,
moving away from notebooks
to scripts essentially allows you
to build the actual
the actual final script in some way
that then lets you go through
all of your processing steps and
allows you to also separate
your code into different parts.
It's something that we are
not covering here.
But for example, in the
Code Refinery Tools workshop, there
is a lecture about
code modularity, and that allows
you to reuse things a lot more easily.
Smaller things.
At the moment, we are
mainly looking into the, well,
reproducing the large run and
avoiding the problems that sometimes
come with Jupyter, as in you
don't, you are not entirely
sure about the execution order and things.
Yeah, exactly.
So cool.
So first of all, maybe
I should clarify what does it
mean to convert to a script?
Maybe it's not obvious to everyone.
What does it mean in the
first place for something to be a script?
Well, for now we can think of
a script as a simple plain text file.
So like Python file, which we
can run from the terminal.
Yeah.
And the first step now,
if we're using Jupyter, it's
actually pretty cool because we
can very easily convert our
Jupyter notebook to a script.
The Jupyter lab, Jupyter offers
us a very compact command line,
a command to convert the Jupyter
notebook to a plain Python text,
which we will call script.
But then we can add all the bells
and like cool features for
more interactive usage.
And if you have Jupyter
installed, this is the command that
you can use running from the terminal.
So Jupyter nbconvert dash dash two
and script and the name
of your Jupyter notebook that
you want to convert to script.
And let's try to break it
down a bit like why it's
written like this, what does each part mean?
So Jupyter, well, Jupyter is
what we're using so far, what
we have been using to write the notebook.
And we convert, so convert a
notebook to a script.
And then we tell it what
is the notebook that we want to convert.
And what this will do,
it will basically take the
file, convert all the text or
like the markdown cells into comments,
if memory serves, and put like
a strip the code cells from
being cell and just put them as plain text.
And this then something that
can be opened in a plain editor.
So without further ado, yeah?
If you could quickly, so how to run
that command in the terminal,
there's also a simple way to
just run from within JupyterLab.
Yeah, totally.
So if you go to the
JupyterLab tab that you have.
Totally.
So I'm going to give a bit of like,
let's say, spoiler for the next exercise,
that if you have a
JupyterLab open, what you want to
do, you want to
but click new and the terminal,
and this will open the
terminal for you from which you
can run the command.
And maybe one important thing
to clarify is that you probably
want to make sure that you
are already in the right folder.
So when we will get to
the exercise, you will see like
how to download the notebook
and the recommended to start
the terminal from the same
folder where your notebook is.
And then you can, you are
able to run the command from here.
And don't worry, your shell
or your terminal will probably
look slightly different to what [name] has here,
because it's essentially using
the terminal of your operating
systems or whatever you have configured there.
Yeah, I have slightly
customized appearances, so yeah.
Okay.
And I think with that we-
So I think actually in this
session, we start with the
first exercise, which is setting
up the conversion to script, and
then we can start talking,
looking at the notebook together and
see how we make it a nice script.
So I would say we can
go to the first exercise, which
you can find in the teaching material,
which requires you to
download the notebook, open it in JupyterLab,
launch the terminal as we
just saw, and convert it to script.
And then you can try running
it also from the same terminal
with Python or Python 3 and
the name of this new script.
OK.
And I think we are giving
a good five minutes for
this because it's relatively small
and should hopefully run without any problems.
But if you have problems,
just write them in the collaborative document.
See you back in five minutes.
Yeah.
Bye.
Hello, welcome back everyone.
Now we are going through
the solution of the first exercise
and we will create the first
version of our script from
the Jupyter notebook.
So first let's open the notebook
and have a look at it.
So I hope you managed
to download this weather observations notebook.
And let's have a quick look at it.
As you can see, it has like a simple,
like a typical structure of a typical,
I would say, like, you
know, data analysis or
analysis research application.
So we are downloading some
data, we are doing some
filtering, extracting some data and
doing some plotting.
So would be kind of, you
know, the first step of your analysis
where you just, you know, have
a look at the data, what data
you have, what do they look like?
And you prepare to think what to do next.
And this is now as a notebook.
And as we were hinting
before, a notebook can have some limitations
if you want to reuse the
code in slightly different setups.
So now we have hard-coded what
data we use, what dates we
use for the plotting.
And this is a very rigid structure.
And we wanted to make it
a bit more flexible, a bit
more reusable in different setups.
And converting a notebook to
script is the magic word to make something,
or well, the first magic
step to make something more
reproducible and more dynamic, more scalable.
And yeah, I mentioned that now
this is very rigid.
So maybe if you want to
use in different setups, it might
be a bit painful.
What do you think, [name]?
If I gave you this notebook, I told you,
hey, I have this very
cool data analysis pipeline for weather data.
Here is my notebook.
And you want to try
it with different setups.
What would be your pain points?
What would you find painful
in this notebook?
One thing that I would find
a bit painful is that we
always have to essentially do
the whole pre-processing again and
again, or at least run the
whole cell again and again each time.
So even if we just want
to change the start dates that
are being used, if you just
want to have a different time range.
I will assume that, yeah,
taking a different source for the data
[name]- Is okay that's Okay,
for me, at least at the moment,
because this is for this is something
for for these weather
observations that come from these
this data lots of yeah fine but yeah.
[name]- Having to having
to rerun the whole thing when
I would just want to change
the dates is something that's
a bit annoying um.
One thing, if I look at
this, one thing I would find painful
or dangerous is that now, you know,
I need to read carefully
through everything to find where is where.
And something, a mistake that
I can very easily imagine
myself making is that, oh, I
want to change the dates.
I find, OK, let me see.
Here is start date.
Here is end date.
I change it.
But oops, here is the name of the picture.
And I forget to change that.
And so when I rerun it
again, I change the dates.
But actually, it overwrites
the previous picture.
And now my picture is not
with the older dates.
It's with the new dates.
And this sounds very scary
if I'm preparing pictures for paper.
I can actually imagine something
more that is problematic.
So you change the dates.
And you change the output and
then you run the second cell
again, but you haven't actually
run the first cell again.
So you still have the old data.
And that's where this
becomes really dangerous because then
you have a new file with a
new name for the supposedly new
data, but it's the old data.
So it's just the wrong
data that you're presenting there.
And that's also, to me, why
I'm not a huge fan of
Jupyter Notebooks for final scientific work.
For prototyping, fine.
For testing things out, perfectly fine.
But if I want to run
my analysis in the end, they
are too prone to these kind
of, I forgot to execute one cell problems.
Or I run the cell again
and it actually changed data in
a way that I didn't expect.
Yeah, working on behalf of a
friend, it's a very common mistake
to forget to run some cells.
So I think we have bashed Jupiter enough.
Maybe let's start to make it better.
As I was mentioning, we
can open the terminal from JupyterLab,
but now we'll do it again
so that people who didn't see
before are able to follow.
So now we want to
start converting this notebook into a script.
And like one way we could do it is
that we manually create a new file
and copy paste the text, but
that's a bit like, you know, maybe clumsy.
So what we will do, we
will open a new terminal.
So if you're in JupyterLab from file, new.
terminal and now it will
look a bit different for you
this is like my custom terminal
but now we want to make sure that we have
that we are in the right folder
so that we have our notebook
and then we can run the
command so jupiter nb convert dash dash two
script and the name of the
file weather obs observations dot e
let's do it whoa something
happened let's see and now we
have a new file so now
we have converted the notebook to script
We can open the file and have a look at it.
So you see from JupyterLab, now
I have this new file,
which is weather observations.py.
So it's like a plain Python text file.
Let's open it.
And now we can see what happened.
And now we can see
what our command actually did.
It actually did what we
could have done manually, nothing much more.
It took the text and copy
pasted them into a new Python file.
And one thing to highlight is
that what was before text,
that markdown cell, now it
has become a comment in the script.
So what do you think, [name]?
Is this a good script?
Are you happy?
Well, personally, I'm happier
than before, because now I
don't forget to run certain cells.
But I would still need to
modify the script every time I
want to change things like the
start date or the end date.
So having something where, because
you can run this script by
just saying Python and script.
Yeah, maybe we can try that.
So it could be Python or
Python 3, in my case, Python 3.
And then we want to run the weather
script script so now it's
important we choose the dot pi
the script one so with python
we run the script and this is a warning
and this generates the output
image at least it should yeah
at least it should now we
can check later okay yeah
But yeah, we could run it.
But what do you think?
It's a bit annoying now.
Well, as I said, I would
personally like to be able
to switch to different time ranges
or change the output file name
so that I'm not always writing
the same output file name.
Yeah.
So for example, you would be
able to do something like
Python 3, whether observations.py.
And then pass the dates from here,
for example, so that we
wouldn't have to open the file.
Yeah.
So I guess we can start doing it.
And the cool thing is that
Python makes it very easy for us to do.
It allows to have this, um, we have these,
um, sys library, like built
in, in Python to pass a
simply the information general system
to get system information.
Part of the system information
is the arguments that you're
script got, which is a
bit unintuitive from a
Python perspective, because the
first argument that your script
got is actually the script
itself, because it's not, the
arguments are not the arguments
for the script.
The arguments are the arguments for Python.
And Python gets us the
first argument, the script file.
Yeah.
So maybe we can take a
shorter demo for it to demo.
So what...
So you want to import sys?
Mm-hmm.
Import sys.
And now, for example, here,
instead of having the hard-coded
data, we would use this syntax of sys.argv1.
Yeah.
And this is what you
were referring to, that in
Python it starts from zero.
The one and not the zero here,
which coming from a Python
where it's zero-based is a bit unintuitive.
Yeah.
And then we want to
maybe also parametrize the end date.
And should we parametrize also the...
The name of the image.
Well, it definitely makes sense
to do that, because that.
I also realized I was on the wrong file.
Yeah, you were in the.
Yeah.
And here we can add the.
So maybe we can make
a variable, output file name.
And this would be sush.argv3.
And here we would save
the picture as output file name.
OK.
Let's see.
Should we try it?
Yes.
So what we did now is
that we used load this library SUSE.
And what this library allows us is
that after we write the
Python three weather observations.py,
like we did before, now we
can pass some inputs to the script.
And here, when we say one,
this is like the first argument
after the file name.
So the first thing we pass.
The second argument after the
file name, so the second
additional thing we pass.
And this is the third thing,
so the third thing after the
file name that we pass.
So this is suce.argv and the
number is like the nth thing
we pass after the file name
that we can pass from the terminal.
So the system argument.
Now we can.
Yeah.
0, 1, 0, 3, 2021.
3, 1, 0, 5, 2021 and spring in tabula.png.
Let's run it.
And now we have a
spring in tabula.png image appeared.
Here it is.
And if you compare this
with the weather.png that we
had before, this is different.
Because we have a set
of different time range for it.
Yeah.
Are you happy with this solution?
I have a few comments.
Well, at least what I can do
now is I can essentially
select different points from the data.
Overall, yeah, it's okay.
It feels a bit like, okay,
I need to remember the order
of the arguments when calling it.
I need to make sure that,
okay, is it actually the right order?
And so it would be nice if
I could give it a bit more specific things
so that I can see from
the command call what's the
start date, what's the end
date, what's the final date.
Yeah.
Because like this, this is
prone to someone thinking, okay,
the first is the end, the
second is the start or something similar.
And that's where I would
personally not be that happy about it.
But it's definitely a lot
more reusable than it was
before because I don't have to touch the code.
without changing what I want to plot.
Yeah.
I also have a couple of
other issues with the current
setup, which is much better.
So first of all, you
remember, first I complained that
if I want to change from
the notebook, I need to
read everything and find where to change.
Now, I still have to read everything.
I still need to read the
whole script to know what to pass.
So if I just send you the script,
if you just send me this
script, maybe I say, OK, it's a script.
But now, suppose I don't know
that I need to pass these parameters as input.
And I say, OK, it's a script.
Let me just run it as
we did the first time, weather observations.py.
Now it gives error, least out of range.
And I'm not super happy with
having to open the file, figure
out it's a bit annoying.
Yeah.
And also w what if I only want to change,
uh, for example, the picture
name, but I don't want to change the dates.
I don't want to type again,
the dates I want to use
some, maybe the full values or, or
if I have a lot, I don't
want to remember in what order to pass.
Like, is it a picture name,
a start date and date?
Is it started and date picture name?
I guess I can assume it's
for start and end.
So yeah.
So what we want to do
now to generalize the workflow,
to increase our ergonomicity, I
would say ergonomicity of the
scripting, is that we have
seen this library SUS, which
is pretty simple, pretty backbone,
but it's also a bit limited in what it can do.
So what we want to do
now, we want to upgrade, level
up our scripting workflow to
use a library called arg-parse.
There's a few other options,
but I would say we use
it here arg-parse because it's
built-in in Python.
It's nice, simple to use,
gives enough functionalities then in
life one can ever go fancier and fancier.
Yeah.
So just to take a quick
anchor point of where we are
now from the notes, we discussed
the use of this Swiss library,
which is this very simple
backbone library to accept inputs
from the terminal.
Now we are moving to
the second session here, I mean
to the second part, where we
want to discuss the usage
of this library argparse.
How exactly is that?
How exactly does ArcPars
run these arguments, or how
do you define what's coming in there?
Is that the argument I
see down there, right?
Yeah, so there's a short
example that we can use to like this.
So here we have a shorter script
that we can use as an
example to get to know arg
parts before using in our weather observations.
Do you think we should type
this or just go through it?
I think you can just copy
paste it over and... Yeah.
Yeah, and if you do copy-paste,
one thing I would like to highlight is
that there's a shorter typo
here where it says type equals string.
This should be str.
I have actually opened pr to
them and asked for your review
of that, but yeah.
But yeah, so now we want
to get to know this arg-parse library,
and before we use it in production,
so to speak, with our
weather library, we will take
this toy example to get to know our new friend.
So now what I will do here is
that I will copy this text from the notes,
go back to JupyterLab, create
a new Python file, so file,
new, Python file, and paste this text.
And now, as I was mentioning
at line seven, where it
says type equals string,
I want to fix the typo so
that it should be type equal str.
Let this be a proof that
I actually checked the material
before starting teaching.
Yeah.
OK.
So let's comment a bit the
structure of our file.
Here we are loading the library.
So import arg parse.
And here we are creating
this parser object with this
arg parse dot argument parser.
So we are creating a class
here, but it's not important.
And now what we want to
do, this parser is like this
enhanced SUS to read the
inputs from the command line.
And now we want to tell
this like super SUS, this
enhanced SUS, what are the
arguments that we are accepting.
And here we have two ways of doing it.
Defining a positional argument or
define an optional named argument.
So when we define positional
arguments, we are doing something
very similar to what SUS was doing.
So we define first, second,
third, and they need to be passed in order.
One, two, three positional arguments.
Now, so here we add this
argument, which we call name.
We are telling it it's a string.
So str stands from string
as the previous type was hinting.
And this meta var, well, we
will see in a second what it means.
It's kind of like imagining
it's a variable name.
I mean, it's a variable name.
It's like giving a name, like
as if it were a variable.
And then something very nice
that connects to what we were
saying before is that now we can actually
help people without having to
read the whole script.
Like before I was complaining,
I still have to open the
script, go through everything.
I still need to open
the script, read through everything
to find out what I need to pass.
With arg parse, we can
make some automatic documentation
so that lazy people like me
can get some help and instructions
how to use it without reading everything.
So this was the first one.
Then optional arguments are useful
for two reasons.
They make it position independent.
So I don't need to remember the order.
And the issue with like
position arguments and even if
I give default value, if I
want to only change the third,
Sorry.
If I finally want to change the third
and use first and second,
the same default ones, I still
need to repeat them.
Whereas here, I kind of fix this problem.
And now the syntax is slightly different.
This dash d or dash dash
date will become maybe a bit
more obvious in a second when we run the script,
but basically means that
these argument comes after the
short flag dash d or the
more verbose flag dash dash date.
So when we will run it in the terminal,
these will have to be prefixed
by dash dash date or dash d.
And the nice thing is
they can essentially appear anywhere
in the command call.
So the positional arguments, they
can come before positional arguments,
after the positional arguments, as
long as they are specified with the flags.
Yeah.
Yeah, so it makes it more
robust for people with short memory like me.
Where was it?
Where do I put it?
I can put it anywhere.
Yeah.
And then the last, let's say
like a static line.
Yep.
Arcs equal parser dot parseArcs.
This makes the magic happen.
So, so far we have only
specified that we have created our parser.
We have told it what to accept,
and here we are actually
making the action happen.
So we're saying, okay, now when
I run the script, actually parse the argument.
So, you know, do something actually.
And then the,
It's where argparse essentially
calls SUS and gets the arguments
and then processes what we have
told it to do with the arguments.
Yeah.
And then the nice thing is that now
that I have this argument
parsed, before, remember, we had
this SUS.argv 1, 2, 3.
They're not very informative.
Now I can access those by name.
So I said that this parameter
is called the name.
I can access, use it doing args.name.
I've said that this parameter
is called the date.
So I can access this with args.date.
So it makes also the text
a bit more readable because then
if I see suess.argsv1, I'm like, what is that?
Like, how do I know what that means?
So without further ado, I
will save this file.
and call it the birthday.
And now we can run it.
Now a cool thing about this
arg parse is that it also
gives me this nice Easter egg that
if I now do Python three,
birthday.py dash dash help,
It actually prints me
some documentation for the script
which was automatically generated
from the specifications when we
listed all the arguments.
And that's why it's important
to use the help keyword, to
print these nice instructions.
So, okay, now I say,
okay, position argument, the
name, optional argument, the date.
So it's optional, I don't have to do it.
So let's go with the minimum first.
Python three, birthday.py.
So one position argument, it
needs, I need to pass it after the script.
Name, I guess I'll tell it my name.
Now [name] was, it says [name]
was born on the 1st of January, 2000.
That's not quite true.
So I will now modify the date.
So Python three,
birthday.py lookup.
And now I want to
highlight that this difference
between optional and positional
argument is that now if I only do a date,
I'll use a random one,
it actually fails because now the
date is not a positional argument.
And being an optional argument,
it needs to be prefixed
by the appropriate flag.
So for example, the appropriate
flag is a scene from the documentation, "-d".
So let's go back, which we can do by arroa.
And now before here, "-d", space.
So I said prefixed, but
prefixed means also with space.
And now the date is different.
[name] was born on 1st
of January, 1999, which is still
not true, but it's okay.
And you can, you could now
also put the [name] in the end instead of,
so move [name] to the end
because it will, it will still work.
Um, being that [name] is
the positional argument and the minus
D is an optional argument.
You could say minus minus
date instead of minus D and it would work.
And yeah, it's overall a
lot more robust and flexible.
Yeah.
Okay.
So having seen that, I think
we can go to the next
exercise, which has you actually
do this change to the
weather observations script, where
we would like to have the start date
and the end date being
changeable along with the name
of the input file and the
name of the output file.
Because then we can actually
test different things.
Yes.
So what we want to do, we
want to go to our script, which
I think I lost, this weather.py.
And now we have this
cryptic suce.argv1, suce.argv2.
We want to replace those.
the name of the picture and the input file.
And we want to do this
in a nice user-friendly way
using arg parse that we just demoed.
So this is the exercise in the nutshell.
Make [name] and me happy with this script.
I would say maybe we can
give 10 minutes that leaves us
enough time to go through
the solution after that, or should
we just do like?
Um, I would, I would say till 55 and,
um, the solution is also in the,
and we'll just discuss the
solution and what we can do then with it.
Yeah.
Cool.
Okay.
See you back at 55 and goodbye.
Welcome back, everyone.
Now we will go through the
solution of the exercise.
And if you didn't manage
to do everything, that's fine.
The solution can also be
found from the teaching material.
So everything will be available afterwards.
No worries about that.
So what we want to do,
we want to upgrade our script
from using SUSE to use
argparse for better usability.
So I will replace the user
source with the import, sorry,
the importer source with the
importer arg parse.
And now, as we saw, the
first thing we want to do is create the parser.
we initialize the parser.
So parser equal argparse.argumentParser.
And then we want to pass
all the arguments to it.
We want to define all the
arguments that we want to
accept from the command line.
And now in the interest of
time, I'll just copy paste
this and briefly comment on those.
So as we discussed,
We want to parameterize input,
so the link here, output, so
the name of the picture we
generate, and the start date and end date.
Now, input and output, we
are making them positional
arguments, which we're calling
input and output.
They are string, so text
literals, and we are adding
a short description.
Then we are defining two
optional arguments which are
the startDate called start and
endDate called end.
We can see they're positional
because of this dash syntax when defined.
And also by the presence
of the default value if
not, sorry, they're optional,
not positional, the presence of
the default value if not specified.
Then as we saw,
We want to make the action happen.
So what we want to
do, args equal parser.parseArgs.
And this will make sure
that we actually parse those
arguments when we call the script.
And now what we can start
doing, we can now replace
the hard-coded constants with
the parametrics call.
So now we don't need
this URL anymore because this
will be the input.
So here, when we build
the weather variable, this will be args.input.
And this we can delete.
Similar here for startDate
and endDate before we were using SUSE.
Now we use our upgraded version, argParser.
They're called start and end.
So I will replace these with args.start
and this with the args.end.
And then finally, the last
update we wanted to do is
that we wanted to have the
picture name also being a parameter.
So I will delete this line here.
And now the name of the
picture will be our args.output.
So I think we are now
ready to test our script.
So we can go from the
terminal to the terminal.
Now, Python 3, weather observations.py.
And now, first, the thing we
can do is that we can ask
for help, since we use a hard parser.
And now we get this
nice description that we have
two position arguments.
the input, which is the input data file,
the output, and two optional
arguments, the start date, the end date,
which can be passed with the
flag dash S and dash E, respectively.
And now we can briefly test.
So if we go back to
the material, in the discussion
session, we have a few usage
examples, and we can try running
a few of those.
So this we ran already, we
can try the second one.
So I'll copy this and go
back to the terminal and paste it.
And now we see we're only
passing the two position arguments,
the input and the output.
And when we run it, pardon,
I need to use Python 3.
When we run it, we get
the picture, this temperature tabula.
We can verify.
We have now a new
picture called the temperature tabula,
which we can open.
And now, since we didn't pass, sorry, yeah?
I would add one more thing.
By changing all of this, we
also have now the opportunity
to just download the file
and not always download it
again, and just provide the
file itself because the
Because if there's no URL,
Pandas will look in the local folder.
So that's something that came
on top without us actually
having any additional work to do.
It just made Pandas a lot more flexible.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's a very good point.
If we had the CSV file
downloaded, then we could point
to that directly and it
would be there, usable.
Yeah.
Okay, so there is another
part about larger option lists that
we will not be covering today.
It's mostly concerning if you have
a lot of different arguments for your program,
then it starts to make
sense to really write configuration files
that are being loaded at
the beginning of the program and
that you don't provide as,
arguments, because even with
labeled arguments, it just becomes
messy at some point.
Even this web URL call
is already somewhat messy again.
So at some point, you just
want to put all of these
into a configuration file and
then just provide the configuration
file from which the arguments are then loaded.
So you have a couple
of different configuration files.
Yes.
And with that being said, I
think we are going to go to a break again.
And after that, we have
[name] and [name] talking about profiling, I think.
Okay, then.
See you in about 10 minutes at 10 past.
Goodbye.
Hello, welcome back from the break.
So now we are going to
be talking about profiling and
we have [name] here as well.
Hello.
Yeah.
So first off, like profiling, why
do we do profiling?
Well, usually we want stuff to be done.
So we want to get stuff done fast.
So we want to optimize our stuff.
So in this
mandatory xkcd you can see
like a good example of how long
does it take to like how
long should you spend optimizing a task
before you spend more time
optimizing the task like the
optimizing the task than actually
like saving by doing
the optimizations optimization so
[name] when should we optimize
Well, I generally think it's a
good idea to try to optimize
if you do something regularly.
Like if you do it once a
day and you can improve it
a bit, that's potentially likely
fairly good savings if you do
something once a year.
Actually, I wouldn't even...
consider it worth optimizing if they
if there's a task that is
you know you're going to do
it two times yeah just just
do it yeah often like yeah if
you do it a hundred times even if it's just
It will just take you a day
to do these 100 times.
If you can spend an hour
on making it be half a
day, there'll be some time savings there.
Yeah, like, I think everybody
has an experience of that they
need to do something and they
need to get it done.
And then they're like, okay,
I don't have time to spend
on trying to figure out how,
what's the best way of doing it.
I will just do it
manually, copy pasting stuff from
one place to another, or, or
doing some sort of like running
the same script over and over
again until your keyboard is, um,
is melting because you're gonna
press enter so many times, but
that's one way of doing it.
And not everything needs to be optimized,
but often like when you
have some problem and you want
it to get done and you
realized, okay, like this is
not happening as fast as I was hoping.
So I feel like there's
something to be gained here.
Like there's something that
can be optimized.
So then the question comes to, okay,
What should I do?
And the key steps for
optimization is like three points
here is first measure.
So if we have an analogy
of like, if you're doing
If you go to a doctor,
like the doctors will do tests on you.
They will like determine what
is the sickness.
Are you even sick?
Like they will do tests, blood tests,
x-rays and whatever to determine
are you sick?
And that's basically what we
are going to be talking
about today, the profiling part.
Then after that, once you figure out,
okay, like this is sick,
this piece is, something is wrong here.
The question is like...
uh, okay, can you, can you diagnose it?
Can you figure out what is, what is wrong?
Like, and that's actually a
harder question often than, than, um,
like a hard question to often
start to like figure out
because often the first instinct
is like, okay, I will just
throw stuff at the wall and see what sticks.
Like I will, I see that this is slow.
I will just start
modifications, whatever, maybe that it
will be faster somehow.
But usually it's a better
idea to actually figure out, okay,
why is this part slow?
What causes it to be slow?
Is it some coding thing?
Well, of course, it's most
likely a coding thing.
Or is it just that it's
slow because it's doing a lot of stuff?
Sometimes things can be slow
because it's a heavy calculation or something.
So this is like creating
a treatment plan for your
sickness, like doctor giving you a
like a treatment plan.
And the last step, once you know
what you're going to be
treating, is to actually treat it.
So to actually give them medications
or surgery that actually helps
you with the sickness.
So for metalheads, I would
also call this like searching,
seek and destroy.
So you can like...
figure out what is the
problem, figure out where the
problem is, what is the
problem, and then destroy it.
So how do you figure this out?
So the first step, of course,
is to add something into your
code that tells you what the code is doing.
So timers are the simplest approach.
So you add some timing
things into your code and you
print out what is the timing.
Maybe, like, a better way
for long-term health of your program
is to use logging.
Like, Python logging module, you
can set it so that
it prints timestamps whenever
it's doing something.
And if you add these to the, like, major,
like, breakpoints of your code, like,
okay, now I'm going to
the next iteration, now I'm
starting data loading, now I'm doing whatever.
then you know that, okay,
like, you can calculate from
the timestamps that, like, this
period took awfully long.
Like, I don't know what
happened here, but something is off.
But this is kind of, like, this kind of,
like, a very... not
very descriptive approach to...
like figuring out what is
the problem like you're just
measuring like very like okay am
I do I feel like I have a
hot head like do I have a
fever like this kind of like
it's not very accurate so for
better way is to use dedicated profiling tools
So here's a list of some
of these profiling tools.
It's by no means exhaustive
again, but it has some shown here.
Some of these are already
included in Python, like Cprofile
and Profile, and TraceMalloc.
They are part of Python itself.
But then there's others that
are provided by various...
And some of these profilers
are so-called like tracing profilers.
So basically tracing profilers,
they check each line when
you execute, they will check
what's being done, what changed
between each line.
And this gives you very
accurate results of what's being done,
but it creates a slowdown
to the code because now it
has to measure everything.
So you don't get realistic run times
if you're using trace profiling,
but you will get a lot more accurate results.
But then there's also sampling profilers.
We'll be looking at Scaleen
today on sampling profiler side.
That basically every now and
then they ask the program, hey,
what are you doing?
What are you doing?
And then they create a picture out of that.
So they don't have such an
overhead as the tracing profiler.
But they can, of course, miss something
if something happens between
the sampling periods.
But often, like, there's some... Like,
you can use the sampling
profilers to profile, like, most of the stuff.
But it really depends.
Do you know of the ones
we listed, which ones are
sampling and which ones are tracing?
I mean, you said Scalene
is a sampling profiler.
Yeah.
C-profile and profile are...
are tracing profilers.
I think line profilers as well.
I think PyInstrument is maybe
sampling, I think.
And PyMpler, I don't know
how to pronounce it.
It definitely is probably a
sampler because it uses the
wordplay over there.
Yeah, and then TracerML Unlock
is probably a tracer.
Yeah, so it does the tracing.
So usually you want to check on this
and usually the whole field
is called instrumentation.
You basically put these
instruments into play and then
you measure small nitty-gritty details
of your program runtime.
And the best way of
probably, like, demonstrating is
to actually have a demo.
So we are going to have a
demo now here of an example case.
So...
This example case is this kind
of like a traditional Monte
Carlo method example of like
throwing darts at a dart
board and calculating pi from that.
So how it works is that
basically like the area, the
ratio of the areas, so between
the dart board and the square is like...
like you can calculate the
probability of hitting the dartboard
and like the probability
distribution of that is the same as like
Yeah, I'm really bad at
explaining this right now, but
yeah, basically like the area
of the dartboard is pi and
the area of the square is 4
because it's like 2 to either direction.
Uh, like two squared.
So, so basically if you
throw dice like random, random
dots to the dartboard and see where they land,
you can calculate how many,
like what is the pie based on
the ratio of hits to throws.
So that will like go towards pie.
And this is like a, like
a commonly used example.
So here we have like a
small piece of code that runs this.
So, uh, let's switch into
like a Jupyter environment and let's see.
what it does so basically
yeah remember to time it because
we do want to measure it yes
so do you have the profiler already
in place um i will i will set it up yeah
so so what we have in
the code is that basically
we calculate the number of hits
so we throw like n dots
And then for each dart, we
see where it lands.
We take two random numbers,
like I coordinate and J coordinate,
might be X and Y. I don't
know why I called them I and J, actually.
And then we calculate the
distance from the center.
And if it's in the
circle, in the dartboard, the
radius is less than one.
So then we calculate it's a hit.
Otherwise, it's not a hit.
And then the pi is...
pi is the result.
So if we like quickly
demonstrate what it does, let's
throw like a million darts.
So we get a bad estimate of pi,
but an estimate nonetheless,
it's getting closer.
So let's now time it.
So let's add here, time it,
and let's add, let's say one,
let's calculate for 10 million
throws, so it will take a bit longer.
So this is, of course, already
a good way of getting some baseline numbers.
Before doing any optimization,
you usually want to determine
what is the baseline speed.
Is there something to be gained?
And of course, this is a
toy example, but it would
apply for many situations.
So in this case, we get
that, okay, it's about two seconds to run this.
So let's try to profile it
and see where the problem really lies.
And for that, we can like
take the original code.
I will actually, well, I
will organize the bit.
I will throw the imports
into a separate cell and
let's have the original code over here.
Because for the profiling, it
needs to know what code to profile.
It's good to have the same
code in the same cell so
that it doesn't go across
many cell boundaries and it will
give us the correct answer.
So over here, let's do like now...
And what I have added here is this magic.
You can do this from the
command line as well.
The C profile has a command line
and it has also like a
Python, like you can do it
in Python as well, this instrumentation.
But we basically say here
that like profile run this, sort
it by the total number of
time used by some part of
the code and then limit it to top five.
And let's run it.
So now the profiler will run
the code and it will give us an output.
And this output, like let's,
let's look at what we have here.
So we have 30 million
function calls, give or take
like some, some over that.
And it took like seven seconds to run it.
So we can see that it's
slower with the profiling because
this is a trace profile.
It's, it's slower to run.
And over here we can see that.
Okay.
Like now we can see the
number of calls is 20 million
calls to the random, method
random, and 10 million calls
to built-in method math square root.
And we can see that the
total time, most of the total
time is used by these ones.
So it's used by this.
This is an artifact.
The sleep method is an
artifact of the Jupyter environment.
So we can ignore that.
But we can already see what
can be the problem.
So basically in the for
loop, we currently have like, we do lots of,
function calls to these functions
and those take time.
So, okay, let's, let's try
making them faster.
Like, like maybe we, we
could make this faster by using numpy to do it.
So let's, let's do like a
naive approach of like, let's
make this faster and let's use numpy to...
to make it faster.
So let's put… let's use
numpy random and numpy square root
to do the thing.
Let's do this sort of a…
Did we lose the stream?
Looks a bit like it, yep.
Yeah, just a second.
We have some technical troubles.
Yeah, now we're back.
Yes.
Yeah.
So let's just use numpy
functions there and let's see
if it works better.
Spoiler alert, it won't.
So I will actually reduce
the number over here to
million because, oh, actually, well,
let's go with the 10 million.
But it won't make it faster.
And you might think that,
hey, what's the problem?
Wasn't NumPy supposed to be
this fast thing that makes stuff faster?
NumPy is fast, but it is fast
if you've got arrays and
you're calculating on arrays.
So can we do this in an array fashion?
Yeah, so now we are at the point
where like, okay, we have figured out
what is the problematic part
and the problematic part are
the function calls.
We have so many function calls
and now we have sought
out and discovered like, what is the problem?
And now we can try to
remedy that problem by doing
what [name] exactly said, like making
it into an array fashion.
So instead of having this long
list of like numbers,
like for doing this for loop across these,
all of these numbers, we can
just get rid of the for loop
and then just let numpy give
us lots of random numbers.
So now we create like a
lot of random numbers with one function call.
And then we can do
the same radius calculation we can do again.
And now for the heats, like
how do we actually calculate the heats?
Well, let's, we can, we can
check where the value R is, is less than one.
We can check where it's less than one.
And we get an array of
true or false values.
And we can check how many are these.
So we can just modify this to
be a sum of true or false.
And then...
This is basically a code.
So now it's vectorized code
and it's working in this array fashion.
And now if we profile it,
well, it's 0.3 seconds.
So it's a lot faster.
So this is like a good example of like,
we get rid of one for
loop because we turn something
into these big blocks of numbers
that can be worked together.
Okay.
And as an ending thing, we can look...
at the scaling.
So we were now using the C profile thing,
but there was the sampling
profile called scaling.
And this is a very nice
tool that gives you like
line by line information of
the stuff you're going to calculating.
Let's take the original code
and then I will
I mean, to me, the main
throw of using scalene over
using something a bit more built-in is
that you get memory and
CPU and everything, and you get quite nice.
A quite nice overview with just one run.
So if you don't know where
is the problem, really, that's...
Yeah, it will...
It will, instead of like,
previously we had to interpret
the output to see where the
function calls were being made.
With scaling, we will get... Oh, sorry.
I forgot.
We have to load scaling first.
With scaling, we will get
this... This monitoring data.
Uh, that, that looks a lot nicer.
So in your output, you might
get an error because there was
a, there was a, like the version of, uh, the
Version of the IPython was changed.
So scaling version might be a bit outdated.
I have already made like
a pull request upstream to
scale and developers that they
should update the versions.
But you can view the output
also with this profile HTML if
you can't see it in the Jupyter.
If you want to try this out yourself
and you can't see it
in the Jupyter interface, you can
also view the output in this HTML format.
And if you're viewing it
with this HTML format, you need
to click this trust HTML.
And what you will see is
this sort of an output.
So what scaling provides, it
provides you a report of the
whole code and it will show where time was used.
And it will like show you
that these lines were using most of the time.
And this was the, like, this
was the part that used most of the time.
And you can straight up,
like, look at various things over here.
It can do memory profiling
and GP profiling and all sorts of stuff.
But I think this is like
a good place to stop.
Like, try this out.
And usually these tools work best
if you have some pieces of code
that are like a function
or whatever that you can independently measure.
But sometimes you can also
measure the whole program and see what sort of
output you get.
So this is like a good
way of checking that.
But now I think it's time
to switch over to [name] and
[name] about library ecosystem in Python.
Thanks for that overview of profiling.
That can be quite useful.
Um, I think we need to check this.
Yeah.
Okay.
The screenshot is working.
Yeah.
So, um, after this small
course in profiling, we will
come to something that underlies,
I would say most, if not all of our work,
um, in scientific computing
and that's essentially the library ecosystem.
So the, the, all the libraries
that we have been talking about, like
scipy, numpy, matplotlib, xarray, scalene.
All of these things give
us, give Python this kind of
potency to address so many
different problems relatively
effectively, because if we need
to implement all of the
features that these libraries give
us, we wouldn't start working.
So.
One thing that we kind of
have to keep in mind is
we can't do everything ourselves.
You don't want to reinvent the wheel.
You want to use tools
that other people have generated.
Also, to some extent, you have to,
at the same time, trust that
what they have built is useful.
It's the same as in science where, well,
we have to somewhat trust
that the published papers have
solid science underlying them,
because otherwise all we build
and all we proceed from there wouldn't work.
And luckily, it most of the time works.
And it's the same in computation and in
libraries that yet,
most of the time it
works, sometimes there are things
that don't work, and then you
can find a bug report and be fine so.
But if we
are talking about libraries, what is,
what is it in general,
so libraries are collections of code
used by a program.
Um, a package is something
that is more Python specific.
It's one part of a library.
It's something that has been,
or just the library itself.
Um, something that has been
made easily installable and
reusable within Python.
It's sometimes interchanged or yeah.
Used in the same way as
the word library and, uh,
the packages are often
published on repositories such
as the Python Package Index
or Conda so that you can easily install them.
And dependencies are, well,
what these packages again depend
on, what they need as underlying tech.
So in the ecosystem that we
are working in, this is one
part of the Python ecosystem.
We are mostly working
with scientific Python things,
like NumPy, Matplotlib.
And these are the most basic libraries
that are underlying almost
anything, any other library that
we are working with, any
data analysis library and so on.
And there are these core numeric libraries,
NumPy, SciPy, and a lot
of different plotting libraries.
We have talked about Vega Altair.
plenty of different data
analysis libraries and packages like Pandas,
X-Array, well, with one R2
or any, Network X for networking analysis.
And all of them have
their specific target problems that
they aim at solving.
And you can't just, we
can't go into details of all
of them because there's just too many.
And this list here is mostly
for you to have a look at and see, OK,
one of these things is
something that I might be able to use.
These are packages that have
been used by one or another
of the instructors in this course over time.
So what's listed here is
probably quite robust in what it
is doing and quite useful.
There are a lot of things
that are listed here as well
that have more to do in
how we interact with Python, how
we build our Python programs.
And that includes things like IPython,
which is, well, essentially
an interactive interpreter that's a
little bit nicer than the
Python interpreter itself.
We have Jupyter.
which we have been using here
quite a lot because it makes
it quite easy to start
building your Python code.
But there are other editors like Spider,
Visual Studio Code, PyCharm,
which all provide features and
are popular in their respective communities.
There are things like Binder
where you can essentially set
up a completely online work environment,
which allows you to already
have the environments set up and
so on online, but sometimes with
a bit of limited resources.
But they are great to
add as a demonstration
demonstration portal for
scientific results, where you can
just put it onto a binder
and someone else can rerun
the code without having to
install anything on their machine.
They just do it online
and can rerun things.
And you don't have to actually
build a lot of additional things there.
You can give it an environment
and the code and just run on that.
There are things like testing libraries,
which can become very useful
once you want to build
something that is supposed to become a library.
When you find that, okay,
I've now coded these
40 different functionalities, and
I would actually like to share them.
I would like to make
them available to others.
And that's the point where
you can think about, maybe it
would be good to write a couple of tests,
whether the things actually do
what I expect them to do and, um,
whether you can, uh, can
kind of reliably also handle
things that are not the
expected inputs that they are
throwing nice, uh, error messages and so on.
And also writing documentation
that for example, Sphinx, but
there are plenty of other, um,
other tools as well.
Here, these whole lecture nodes,
they are created with Sphinx.
And yeah, I think that's
a relatively simple way to
get something into a nice form
that can also be deployed
on GitHub, for example.
There are lots and lots
of data format support things
like Pillow, H5Py, PyTables for
for different more complex data types
that allow you to read, write files
or large files or more
complex structured files in an efficient way.
There are libraries for
parallelism and code speed up like MPI number,
Joblib, just to name a few,
or to make C extensions, because on Tendency,
for example, NumPy is based a lot on,
well, we are actually running
the code itself in C and
not in Python, because it's a lot faster,
and we are just providing
an interface to the compiled
C things, and Cython makes it
easy to do just that.
There are
machine learning and deep
learning libraries like XGBoost,
Scikit-learn or PyTorch and TensorFlow
or JAX that has become more popular recently.
And all of these packages help
you in not having to reinvent the wheel.
They provide a lot of
additional resources, a lot
of additional information
and just make life a lot easier.
[name], what's your take on this?
What kind of packages do you
think are the most important things
that you do use, or do you actually use them?
Yeah, I use a lot of packages.
Working wheels are the best wheels.
Yeah, I mean, I would
say like generic ones, like
Matplotlib, I would mention for
plotting, like Pandas for data libraries,
for data management, NumPy, of
course, most people, generic ones.
Then I guess it gets
like very field-specific, like
everyone has their importance in my field.
Thinking to my background from my PhD,
I would definitely highlight
SumPy for symbolic computation.
That's, I think, pretty close
to my heart, but for a lot
of people might not be relevant.
Yeah, then generic ones like
plotting, data managing.
Yeah, probably the more field agnostics.
What's your favorite?
Personally, I'm actually using
something not in the
scientific programming range at all,
which is fast API for
web development, which makes
it extremely simple to write
a small web server that can
very simply be spun up
and provide data that could, for
example, be an endpoint that
you just provide that can run
your code and allows other people
to use what you have developed.
Something that comes from my
times back in science was CobraPy,
which is constraint-based
analysis, reconstruction analysis, which
is a library that
It's quite popular in that field.
But yeah, I think the most
important bit is that there
are very, very, very many packages around.
And if you have a specific
problem, have a look around.
Maybe it's already solved.
And when looking around,
check if the libraries and
things are actually what they say they are.
Because especially recently, it
has become more and more common
that due to AI inventing
packages, people have started
to essentially try to inject
wrong package names into
to things like Stack Overflow,
and the AIs are starting to spoo out,
yeah, package names that don't
exist and essentially are viruses.
And those then having been
loaded onto PyPi with something
that sounds roughly right, and
the AI being happy with just
saying, yeah, this is how it works.
And yeah, that has or is
becoming more and more of a problem.
Also, typos, especially with
AI-generated code.
Be careful that the packages
that are suggested and that it
tells you to install are actually the packages.
Check the PyPy pages for it.
Look around whether it's
actually something that has been in use.
particular for very recent things, yeah,
be sure that it actually
is a proper package and not
something that was just spun
up to, yeah, inject stuff.
Because it's unfortunately
happening nowadays.
Another thing about libraries is
that it's good, maybe it's
often like over thought, over seen,
but a lot of the
popular open source libraries,
they're not backed by like
some corporate with people hired to develop it.
A lot of popular libraries
start with like some person doing
it for fun and others finding it useful.
So if you find an issue
with the library and open an
issue, remember to be nice.
Remember, it's probably someone
who is doing that on their free time.
And, you know, don't assume
someone is like, there's like money
and people paid to fix the issues
because a lot of the
cool libraries start as a
hobby projects from people kind
enough to share.
So I think that's often
a very overseen side of
libraries that people take for granted.
Yeah.
Yeah, I would agree.
At the same time, I would say
if you find bugs in
libraries, most people are happy
if bug reports are being written.
It might take a bit of time
for them to be corrected.
And the optimal bit is
if you understand the library
well enough to actually be able
to provide a bug fix.
And yeah, the whole ecosystem
here is something that is based on
a two-way method.
You are the users, but at the same time,
you are also probably the people
who can correct things that are wrong
and are the ones that,
yeah, most likely figure out that
this is not correct.
And especially if it's a
package that's very field-specific.
You will be the people who
have, in the end, most
knowledge about whether this is correct or not.
It's this, use tools that
have been established for things
that have not yet been kind of established.
Check them, try them out, see
if they do what they claim to do.
And if possible, yeah, walk a bit
through the code to see if
this is actual useful or if
this is very strange.
And it's also having a look
into code is quite often
a reasonable approach to say
whether this is something that I want to use.
Because if the code is so bad
that I'm starting to read it
and then say, no, I don't get anything here.
I might not want to use this code
because if I can't at
least understand the general concept, is
that even trustworthy that this
is actually producing what it's
supposed to produce?
And yeah, essentially every project
can be turned into something that
can be reused as long
as it's reproducible and
relatively well created.
Well maintained would be optimal,
but if it's at least well created, yeah,
this can even be some code
that was just published once.
If it's solid, yeah, there might
need to be some updates
if Python really changes enough
that the code doesn't work anymore.
But Python is,
In contrast to a lot of other languages,
very robust when it comes
to backwards compatibility.
So old code will normally run
as long as it doesn't rely
on too many additional libraries,
because those might not
be backward compatible.
But the base Python libraries,
they are quite good there.
So, um, I think it would
be interesting to see, um, maybe
you could just start writing down a bit,
what kind of libraries you
are using in your work,
because that is something that
other people can, can make use of as well.
And we can talk a bit
more about what's, uh, what we
think is good here.
Uh, let's put this here.
It's not a break.
Yeah, if you could just write
down in the collaborative document
what kind of libraries you are using,
that might help extending this
page at some point, and or
it might help others to see
what is around, what can be
used, what is useful.
And if you could point
library that you're using
that's not yet on the list,
write a little bit, maybe a
couple of words, what the library does.
I think that would be
really, really useful for others to see,
okay, oh, I'm in a similar
field and I should have a look at this.
It's something that I
often notice listening to these
kind of software talks that, oh,
okay, I never actually heard of that library.
Maybe I should have a look.
So [name], do you have anything else
that you want to say
here or considerations when using a library,
what to look for, what to
check before just adopting and running it?
Yeah, I can measure what
I generally look at if I need
to start a new library.
I try not to give too
much weight of who wrote that.
In some open source
communities are relatively small,
and everyone knows everyone.
But it can serve a bit of a bias.
I try not to pay attention to that.
But how well it's maintained.
When was the recent most
time it was updated?
Is it still actively?
maintained and developed.
Although I will mention this
sometimes a bit tricky, because
there are stable algorithms that
have been developed in the
70s and never needed any update.
So if something is working,
we're changing it.
So that's also something I would mention.
Don't say, hey, this hasn't
been updated in 10 years, so
it's not working anymore.
Well, the algorithm implemented
hasn't been updated in 100
years, so what would you update there?
I would add to that.
are there issues that are open
and are not addressed in some way?
That's the more important bit
to me, at least.
Because, yeah, I completely agree.
Not updating.
If there isn't anything to
update, why update?
So why change your running system?
But if there are a bunch
of issues that are not addressed or
or not interacted with at all
that's more a sign that okay um and
but but at the same time
it also it also depends a
lot on the issues themselves so
don't just say oh there are
50 open issues um yeah maybe not
and because i i have seen
issues where i was like okay um uh
I could close this now
because it's completely irrelevant,
but it feels wrong to just close it.
So there are oftentimes things
where issues stay open because,
yeah, this would be a nice feature to have.
But it's, yeah, there's no
one doing that feature.
There's no one who has the time to do it.
And that's not something
that speaks against the library
because that's additional functionality
that, yep, isn't yet implemented.
And if it's exactly the feature
that you need, then okay, maybe
this is not the library
or alternatively, you could implement
that and actually close the
issue with your pull requests.
Yeah.
That's the beauty of open source.
You can just do it.
You don't need permission.
That would be the optimal solution.
If the library is otherwise something
where you think, okay, well,
this is actually really useful to me.
Yeah.
So what do we have in
the color which document now?
Let's see.
We have a lot of NumPy pandas.
DuckDB is mentioned here.
And yeah, DuckDB is quite useful
as a data library for
big data analysis without, well,
at a stage where you don't
yet want to install your own database service.
There, DuckDB becomes really useful.
Qlik is an alternative service
for ArcPars is definitely more powerful,
but its own library is another dependency.
So if you want to have
a really nice interface or
command line interface at least,
yeah, Qlik is definitely nice.
If you want to have something basic,
I would personally probably
stick with ArcPars.
We have PyTorch here, which
is probably still the most popular library
for any GPU machine learning, oh,
well, deep learning machine
learning model training approach.
I personally would, yeah, also,
maybe add VLLM, which is a hosting library for
large language models, which can become,
it's a very simple way to
just run a model if you
want to test specific models.
Yeah, we have MNE or MNE
Python for EEG and
general neurobiology analysis.
What else?
I think I have to look at SIGNOC.
Additional workflow management.
I know a bit of snake
make, but well, let's see if
that could become interesting.
I'm wondering whether the
Python call.jl comes from my co-teacher.
Yeah, guilty.
Yeah.
Okay, so we have a couple
of minutes left in the day.
There is a feedback section for
day two at the end.
I would be very grateful if
you can fill in your feedback about today.
So just as a reminder,
we covered plotting in the
morning and data management.
And then now in the
afternoon, we've covered scripting,
profiling, and then this
section, selected libraries.
So those are the sections,
I guess, that the feedback would be about.
But I mean, feel free
to write anything also about yesterday.
Then tomorrow, we'll go into, first of all,
more high-performance computing kind
of stuff.
parallel programming and integrating
C code into Python with Cyton in the morning.
And then in the afternoon,
we'll talk about how you can
make your own Python packages from your code.
So how you can make
it installable easily on other
systems and how to manage dependencies.
And add your code to this list.
Yeah, add your code to the list, right.
Yeah, so it will be an interesting day.
It will definitely go a bit
into slightly more advanced topics.
I see that people think
today's speed was better.
Yesterday, it was a bit fast.
I have to admit, and
today, there's more votes on
right speed, which is nice.
But yeah, also, it's
It's nice to get good feedback,
but it's also important to get
to know what actually, what
we can improve, right?
So that we can do better next time.
So yeah, thanks to
everyone for participating and thanks
for the feedback.
I hope it was a useful day.
See you potentially tomorrow then.
Hopefully tomorrow.
Yeah, we'll see if anyone else
pops up in the last 30 seconds or not.
I don't think I've
actually introduced myself at any point.
Hey, I'm [name].
I guess you can see my name there.
I was subbing in for [name]
yesterday for a few seconds,
and today I'm doing the outro.
Otherwise, I've been in the
background all the time.
[name] is one of the people
who keep this whole...
thing running and making sure
that we are actually going into breaks,
having the notes up and so
on and not messing up too much.
But, well, all right.
Again, thanks for the feedback
and see you tomorrow.
See you tomorrow.
Bye.
So usually we are still live, actually.
The sound from instructors is still on.
Hello, you can still hear me maybe.
So if you click break, it
will turn off the sound.
That's what I always do.