Hello, hello.
Welcome to day three
of Scientific Computing.
We have 10 minutes together
to break the ice.
Today we have a couple of new instructors.
Good morning.
Good morning, [name].
[name], you know her already.
But we have some new
faces, [name] and [name].
So, [name], do you want
to briefly say something about yourself?
Yes, hi everyone.
I'm [name].
I work at CSC Finland, which
is the Center for Scientific Computing.
We host supercomputers for Finland
and also some Europe projects.
I have a background in
physics, so hello there.
And yeah, nice to meet everyone.
And with us, there's also
[name], directly from Sweden.
Hello, [name].
Hello, good morning everyone.
So my name is [name].
I work at the CDC
Center for High Performance Computing
at KTH in Stockholm.
And there we operate
the supercomputer Dadel, which is
a smaller sibling computer to
Lumi, which I have in Finland.
And I also have a background in physics.
And yeah, with that comes that I'm
often using some other
compiled languages, Fortran, it might
feel is common.
Now more and more, and we will come to
that in this lesson also,
I'm also combining it with Python.
excellent and today so you
can already feel uh hpc
high performance computing class
that have already been mentioned twice
so some of the topics that
we covered today especially in
the morning they are very
useful when you really need
to scale your analysis that you
need kind of you know
parallel parallel computers parallel
processes to analyze large amount of data
so what you see right now
on the screen are the notes
document just have received an
email from me with this link
if [name] could you scroll down
a little bit i left there
the feedback from yesterday so
you can still you know if
you didn't have time to
write something yesterday something nice
and of course something also
that could be improved as
you might have noticed we are
trying to improve as fast as
we can based on your feedback
But if you scroll a little bit more down,
there's a couple of
icebreaker questions for today.
And I'm going to ask
the second question, starting from [name].
So what's the most surprising
thing you have learned in your career?
I think the most surprising thing
that I've learned in my
career keeps surprising me is how
how difficult it is or how
scary it is to share your code,
like put it on GitHub and
have other people see it.
I mean, everyone struggles with this
and everyone has unclean, not
so nice looking code, but
still people think, no, it's only
my code that looks so bad.
And I get that sometimes myself.
I think this isn't good code really.
Do I really want to show it to someone?
But yeah.
I work with many RSCs, so
many people who share their code.
And it never came to my
mind to read their code in a way like, look,
I would have not written
this variable name in that way
or things like that.
So in the end, it doesn't really matter.
But it's true.
Maybe we are more self-critical.
then like critical towards others
you know it never happened to me
that i have to give comments
to one of you on your and so same question
for [name] what's the most
surprising thing you have learned
in your career yes so um one
thing um is this we we
talk about uh sometimes um yeah
also in this code refinery
workshop about this that when you the aspect of
reproducibility in science.
And it can often, one aspect is this,
that sometimes the person that
is to reproduce can be yourself.
And that has led to
some comical situations where I
have been running some simulations
with some program.
And after a few days, I
realized, oh, this seems very familiar.
And what then has happened is
that I've simply been
running something that I ran
Let's say a half years ago.
It's just that I had it
somewhere else in my file system hierarchy,
and I didn't have like
the I've forgotten simply that I've done it.
So yeah, I find it quite interesting.
Exactly.
I wouldn't call it a daily struggle,
but sometimes even remembering
which subfolder was I using.
That analysis.
And what about you, [name]?
What's some surprising thing
you've learned?
Yeah, so this definitely not
the most surprising because I
couldn't think of a better one
since I don't have 10 minutes
to think about this.
But so one thing that's also relevant
for today is that I'm always surprised
how much Python is actually
used in high performance
supercomputing environment.
And it also makes sense if you think about
the needs of today's kind
of computing clusters, because a
lot of the work is actually offloaded to GPUs,
And Python is just doing the
kind of CPU side logic that
tells what the GPU should do.
And in that sense, it
makes perfect sense that Python is
now a very good language
actually, despite the Python
being inherently slow.
It doesn't really matter if
the GPU is doing that most of the workloads.
So that was something that I'm always,
I'm still quite impressed by
and also surprised by.
And I think this will
actually become even more common in the future.
I agree.
And what you said just
connects perfectly with the topic
of the morning, where under
the Python code, there is C
and C++ and or CUDA.
There are other languages that
are called to gain the speed.
You kind of saw this already
when we were mentioning when
we were talking about NumPy
and X-Ray, how under the hood,
it's not just pure Python.
Well, we still have a couple of minutes.
Maybe I can answer the icebreaker myself.
What's the most surprising
thing I've learned in my career?
And I think it's what I
wrote there first, planning ahead.
And planning ahead can mean, you know,
not just when you start a
project, you have a long-term
plan for the project.
But even when you start a
script, I usually start from
writing the comments.
I just write all the comments
down so that I know first I need to do this.
Then I need to, I
don't know, pre-process what I
loaded and so on.
After I've written all the
comments, then I actually start
writing the code.
It makes it much easier and especially
if you get interrupted, you
know what you were doing and
what you were thinking.
And sometimes even pen and paper
or pencil and paper, it's even
the best to start planning a script.
But yes, so we still have
one minute before starting.
I can see that people
are already editing this notes document.
Anything else you wanna add,
[name], [name], [name]?
Nothing comes to mind.
So maybe I can briefly say
that this is our last day together.
You've been very active.
We have now 500 people registered.
So 500, round number.
And you will still have more
days for going through the videos.
And for those of you on
the credit, do the simple homeworks.
And in general, if you
have questions, you can always reach out
so that we can answer
your questions and hopefully
improve this course for next year.
There were already good
suggestions there in the top.
Someone was asking for an
extra hour every day.
So maybe next year it will
be five hours per day course.
But otherwise, it's now 10
o'clock in Helsinki, so we can actually start.
welcome to the third and last
day of this run of
python for scientific computing today
for day three we will cover
enough a little bit more
advanced topics compared to the
previous two days or well i'm not sure
if they should be called
advanced but at least they
relate to those cases when the
analysis need to scale up a lot
So in the morning, we
will talk about parallel programming
and Cyton, which is basically
what's under the hood of
the Python scripts that you might be running.
And in the afternoon, we
will cover packaging.
So when you want to
create your own library, when you
want to reuse your code easily.
And of course, something that
you have already experienced, when
you need to install all the
right versions of Python libraries,
which is dependency management.
Just a quick reminder for asking questions,
we use this notes document
that we see right now on screen.
So [name], if you can scroll
up to the very top, you
see that there's a pencil on top.
When you click on the
pencil, the document turns into
an editor and then you're
able to write something.
So for example, [name], you
can scroll to the very bottom
and tell us what would be your favorite
holiday winter holiday activity
for me was asleep yeah um
one thing i hope to do this
coming weekend is to go ice
skating okay on a lake nearby okay
so it's already frozen enough
safely enough frozen yes one
one decimeter already well i
wouldn't i wouldn't yet try to
go skate on a lake at least
not here in the air thinking
But so you got the idea.
If you don't need this
document, there is another icon in the top,
which is the eye so that
we can basically get less load
on the server that is hosting this.
And final reminder, when you
look at the Twitch TV stream,
please set the quality to source.
Otherwise, at some point you
will start seeing big pixels
and that's not nice.
But that's enough with me talking,
so I'm happy to pass the
stage to [name] and [name].
Enjoy the last day of
Python for Scientific Computing and
see you later.
Yes.
Hello from me as well.
Thanks for joining us again.
We are going to start by
talking about our programming.
So maybe to...
And to get started, what is parallelism?
What is parallel programming and
why and when should I be using it, [name]?
Yes.
So to start with a bit
of a historical account.
So in history of computing,
the early computers were essentially serial.
So it was the processors
would run one execution thread and that was it.
Probably many of you have
seen these graphs where you
show the evolution of hardware
over multiple decades.
And this started to flatten out
as regards clock frequency around
20 years ago when we
reached around three gigahertz.
So essentially, most of the
speed up which has happened since
then is in form of
running things not faster
per execution thread but to
run them in parallel and
parallel nowadays often is
in multiple execution threads on
one single chip and this affects very much
how you how you write programs
and how you execute programs and
python has has its own
way of doing it.
And this is the topic for this morning.
So one of the first things
that you need to do when
you have a morning competition is
that you need to find where
is the program spending most of the time.
So where do you have a
good opening for redesigning it?
So do you have any
experience of doing that, [name]?
Sorry?
Yeah, I was thinking, have
you analyzed a program to see
where it spends time?
Well, yes.
Well, actually, I was just
teaching about profiling code
yesterday together with Seymour.
So what I used in the past is to use Glean.
The thing is, the most
important bit about profiling is
you need to know whether you want to profile.
So you...
want to see whether your
program spends more time than
it should or than you can afford really.
And then you want to see
where it spends that time and
you can use a profiler for
that as we talked about yesterday.
Or maybe you want to look
at how much memory it uses.
But I think for the
parallelism, it's mostly the time
that you can speed up
with going parallel, right?
I mean, you can't really do much about
about the memory consumption?
Or can you actually?
What do you think?
Well, that depends in part in
what kind of parallelism that you implement.
So actually that comes here.
We can highlight what you have
here in the lesson material.
So some different modes of parallelism.
So there's one concept which
is called embarrassing parallel.
And that is when you
have a compute workflow where you
need to run multiple instances
of a calculation or an analysis.
Let's say you have 200 data
sets and you have them in form of
200 files, then you can write a script
that just loops over this
whole set of files and everything
is then run in parallel and
needs not to be synchronous.
Yeah, that's something that happens.
So I'm from, from neuroimaging originally,
and this is something that
happens so often in neuroimaging.
Like you have to, you have 50 subjects
and you need to pre-process them all,
but they are not really,
they don't depend on each other.
So you can just show that
off to 50 different computers if
you have the amount of computers.
Yes, yes.
Coming here to when you want
to do things a little bit
in parallel for one single calculation.
Then we have the concept
of multi threading and that is where you are.
It's a thread memory mode parallel
where you let multiple threads
in the execution of a program
work in parallel on the data.
And as you'll see here.
So hang on, hang on, what's a thread here?
A thread is, so logically
in the execution of the
program is doing something sequentially.
And you can then have typically have
as many up to as many
threads as your physical cores
in the processor.
That's a typical thing that
you would like to have.
In Python, however, what is
more natural to use is so-called multiprocessing.
And that is when you
launch multiple instances of
the program execution and they
will then work with their own memory segments.
And that means that one
such process cannot automatically
access the memory of the other um
or the other processes so you
need them to have some
communications going in between there
and this is called message passing um
and one important protocol for
this is the so-called mpi
message passing interface which is
a bit more than 30 years old
and here in python we will
work with a packet which
is called multi-processing
So I think we will make
here first a little bit a
notion here about multi-threading and
then we will come into multi-processing.
So by design in Python,
there is something which is
called the Global Interpreter Lock, GIL.
And that restricts the program
execution to use only one thread at a time.
And I'm going to say that
this is possibly a limitation.
However, in practice, it's so
that if you invoke some
library underneath that can be
done libraries such as NumPy,
SciPy or Pandas that you
have encountered earlier in this course.
They're written in C language
and within them, this lock can be released.
You can run multiple threads.
And
It's also so that if you
link your program to some other library,
that could be, for instance,
some logpack libraries for linear algebra,
which is external to Python,
then also there you can
run things in parallel.
So we will here make a
Just to showcase here how
this is working with a
code snippeter for NumPy.
We can take this code here
that will invert a symmetrical matrix.
And this code here is using NumPy.
So we set up a random
matrix A, which is sized 4,000 by 4,000.
And use then the NumPy
Invert function to invert it.
So I take this code snippet here.
And I put it in my Jupyter notebook.
And OK, actually this I could
run in the in the tunnel.
So I do that installed.
Yes, I already have the code here.
Run it.
That was 3.79 seconds.
that is with multi multiple
threads right because numpy uses
c in the background yes yes exactly
what happens if you turn
the multi-threading off basically yes
we can do some experiments here so here um i'm
Okay, it actually by default
it uses one thread and now I
increase it to use say four threads.
Ah, you see, and this
is something, yeah, now it cut
the time with a factor of two.
Potentially it could have cut
the time with a factor as
large as four, but here it
achieved only a speed up of two.
What do you think?
So in general,
parallelism, the speed up is
typically the ideal speed up will be
if you increase the amount
of hardware available with a factor of X,
then the tentative speed up
you could foresee is up to a
factor of X. So in this time, a factor of four.
So that is also the natural target
when you implement and
optimize parallel code you would
like to strive to come as close up to
that so-called ideal scaling
as possible but for many reasons
this can be more or less
challenging to achieve one reason
why it sometimes is slow can simply be that
that the progress the the calculation
that you want to perform is
a little bit small so then
there's not enough workload to to distribute
so then simply going to
larger workloads you will you
will for that reason achieve better performance
or invertedly, if you just have
that small workload, it doesn't
pay to add the additional threads to it.
Yes, yes.
Because usually you have a problem
that you want to solve
and you can't necessarily scale
it up infinitely to make it
more sensible to use multiple
threads or multiple processes.
Yes, indeed.
So we will now come to
a main functionality for
paralleling spin Python, which
is the so-called multiprocessing flow.
And we have an example of how to do
that for a simple
mathematical function here, which
is calculating the square of a number.
So we have here the
definition of this function here.
It's defined as a square
that takes an input argument X
and returns it square.
If you want to, I mean, you
can use the map function here
to apply the square function
to every element in the list.
if you invoke the square
function nested in with map.
If we execute this snippet
here, things will be done in a serial.
If we use this
here so-called multiprocessing packet,
We import it, we imported
the pool function.
Then we can use pool and
then we distribute the calls
to the square function over the
set of elements here in this
list, and this will then be run in parallel.
This is still a very small
program, so for this example here, we have
only six elements in the
list, there will not be any.
I mean, this is quasi
instantaneous in any case.
There's not much to parallelize here.
So one important thing here,
because we are primarily
using Jupyter notebooks here, is
that this multiprocessing
Packets might not always work
in the notebook, but then there's
a fork of this which
is called multiprocess that one
can run instead.
So you will now have in an exercise
that we will get going to in a minute
that have the chance to
explore the functionality of multiprocessing.
So we can introduce what
this exercise is about.
So perhaps if someone can
share the direct link here to
the exercise in the collaborative document.
So the code snippet here is
a method called sample, which
is calculating an approximation to pi.
And it's doing this with
a Monte Carlo algorithm.
when it is generating random
numbers within a square.
And then there's an if statement
that checks do these random
numbers fall within a circle
which is inscribed within this square.
And this suits itself very
naturally to parallelism.
So for this exercise, you
will then... So this code in here is serial.
And what you will explore here is
how you can speed this up
by using the multiprocessing
pool functionality.
So are there any more
instructions that we could mention?
Uh, no, basically I think, well, the,
the exercise description is in,
in the exercise.
Um, you will have 10
minutes to explore this exercise.
Um, and then, yeah, we'll put
a link also to the exercise
in the notes document.
Yes.
Good.
So it's basically 20 parts now.
So exercise will be until half past.
Good.
So see you in ten minutes.
Okay, I think we are back.
So welcome back.
I think the sharing is
probably not correct.
Yeah, I think you're at
the moment, unfortunately seeing
Yeah, well, you can see my notes.
A little more than you should be seeing.
But yeah, instead, you can't read anything.
We'll try to fix that thing.
All right, it's starting to look better.
Yeah, OK.
Good, good.
And this should be readable, I hope.
Yeah.
All right, so.
We saw some very nice
discussion in the notes during the exercise.
I hope you got on with
the exercise all right.
There were some good questions
here about the latest version of Python
and the release of the
global interpreter lock, which
is now implemented.
And that's a good thing to bring up.
And I have so lovely.
Have you explored this newest version of
Right, so we discussed this a
bit over the exercise session
in the private room also, but
we don't have direct experience
with this new Python version that
does not use the GIL global interpreter lock.
But in principle, it is
there in the standard now,
it should be working.
But I personally would be
a bit cautious about using it
of building your application
with the assumption that you
can now ignore the kill
completely because it's such a new feature.
So I think it's a
promising new feature, but maybe
not for production yet, just yet.
And one thing about the GIL
in general is that it's very easy to bypass
if you write the code
that does multi-threading in
some other language and then
bind it to Python, which will
be discussed in a moment in more detail.
Someone on the notes highlighted that
in the exercise, using it,
running it with multiprocessing
is actually slower.
And yeah, it is because
what we're doing there is
we're kind of misusing it a bit.
It's a pure Python code
and it's a relatively small example.
So adding the
So when you're adding threads
or multiple processes, what you're
doing is you're telling your
computer to create different processes.
But these processes all need to be handled.
And that means you're adding overhead.
The computer needs to do more
to do the same thing.
And because it's a
relatively small example, and it's...
code that doesn't really
like multiple threads, multiple processings.
Actually, the overhead that
you're adding is more than the
time gain you get.
So in the end, it is slower.
What we, I think, show with this is
that it doesn't always make sense
to go to complicated multiple
pool kind of things if your
problem actually is easier to
solve in other ways.
One of them is the
embarrassingly parallel cases.
Well, this is something that
I come across all the time in neuroimaging.
If you can separate the
problems, you don't have to
handle pools, you don't have
to handle the overhead.
You just run your program
for each instance separately.
That is an easy speed
up without adding overhead.
So yeah, that's I think the
point of the this exercise.
Yeah, and I should add that
if you can do it in
a way that's empirically parallel,
so you're just running
independent processes, then that's
always the best option because
there are no overhead associated
with kind of spawning threads
or spawning multiple processes
within one process.
But of course, that's always not possible.
And should we move on to NPI already?
Or is there something else you
want to say about this?
No, I think we're good.
There wasn't anything else in
the notes specifically to the exercise.
And we will keep answering
questions in the notes as usual.
Yes, so let's talk about MPI.
So as mentioned already, MPI
stands for Message Passing Interface.
It's a kind of protocol or
a standard that allows you
to launch multiple processes that
can also communicate with each other.
And this is very useful if you want to,
say, utilize a large computing cluster,
because you can launch one
large job with MPI, which
essentially then launches many copies
of a program.
And then those can start
communicating with each other so
that you can implement things like,
divide a large simulation
into smaller simulations that
then communicate just the data
that they need to communicate
between each other and this is
the main method or main
way that most scientific
simulation programs scale themselves to
so they can run on let's
say extreme case full
supercomputer just running one simulation
So this is a very
typical approach in high-performance computing.
So what NPI does is that
you run a command called NPI
exec or NPI run, and that
will take care of spawning the processes.
And it will also assign
a unique integer number called
the rank to each process.
And of course the operating
system will usually assign these processes
so that each process runs
in an independent CPU core so
that it's like you get
the max possible performance.
There's no competition of
resources within the processes,
assuming you have a large
enough computer, of course.
And
Yes.
Yeah, it's a comment.
So sometimes it's also perfectly
fine to run more ranks than
you have physical cores.
And that could be also
depending on what algorithm you have.
So perhaps it is so
that algorithmically you would like to run,
let's say, as many as 4000
ranks of the program, simply
because your problem size is that large.
and you might then not have
that many cores available, then
you can have less, run with
this many lot number ranks.
Yeah, and just to reiterate, MPI
is a form of multiprocessing,
but it differs from Python's,
this built-in multiprocessing package.
by the fact that you
can actually communicate it
with the processes.
And the MPI is also
implemented usually in C or Fortran.
And then this Python implementation
that we're looking at today
is a thin wrapper around the C implementation.
So yeah, the communication
between processes is the main part here.
And this is not multi-threading.
So the big difference
with multi-threading is of course
that the memory space of
each process is independent.
There's no shared memory like that.
But you can actually combine
NPR with multi-threading so that
so that inside an MPI
process, those processes will
then launch multiple threads
and do multi-threading that way,
which is also quite common
in real world applications.
Okay, so I thought that we
could do a short demo of
just doing a hello world printing in MPI.
So let's try to do that.
So here I have an empty
Python file called mpi-demo and
I will write the code here in my editor.
And the reason I'm not
doing this inside Jupyter is
that I'm not really not sure
how well Jupyter handles the
spawning of multiple mpi processes.
So I'm going to do
this the traditional way.
Okay.
So we're going to start by importing
from the mpi4py package and now
I need to cheat is it capital
or not it's not capital okay
mpi4py import mpi and yeah
here's the example code I'm going
to copy parts of this that
you see in the browser
Let's just start by printing
a string from each process that MPI launches.
So for that, we need to denote the,
or we don't need, but I
want to print the ranks,
the identifiers that MPI assigns
to the processes.
So I'm going to get the
rank of my processes.
So I do this by first
getting what is called a communicator.
So communicator in MPI is
an object that contains information about
a group of processes and
how they can communicate between each other
and world communicator in
particular refers to all processes
started by this mpi mpi start command
which i'll show in a
moment but anyway let's get
the word communicator looks like this
and by the way this is very
similar in c or fortran if
you've already used mpi there
but by because this python so
we get it's a slightly shorter
which is nice.
So we can ask for a property called size.
Size refers to the number
of processes that were launched.
And then the rank is the
identifier of my process.
like this.
And now if I run this code with MPI,
then remember that all the
processes will execute this, but
the number they get out from
this rank is different because MPI
just gives a unique identifier to each process.
And let's print that out to
see it in action.
Hello world from rank or process.
It's called task, MPI task.
All right.
And now I'm going to go
to my terminal, go to the right directory.
And the way to start an
MPI program, at least on your
laptop, is to use the MPI
exec or MPI run command.
On supercomputers, this can
be different because they have
their own task managers.
job systems whatever like slurm
uses srun but you can find that
in your in the user manual
of your supercomputer so
that's always something to check
on caseback is basis but yes
let's run two processes and the
file is called mpidemo.py and now
we get two prints and you can
see that the rank or the
test number is different
And just for comparison, if
I run this without MPI, like
just Python, usual thing, they
will just have one process.
And the magic argument in
here is the number of processes
that is going to be spawned by MPI.
So I can do four and now I get four prints.
I can do it again, just
to illustrate one thing.
which is that the order of
this print is not deterministic.
You can see the order is different.
And this is because the
execution, there's kind of a
race in which process gets to
do the first printing.
And that's the order you
end up seeing here.
So just something to keep in mind
if you print out stuff
in the standard output from NPI.
Now, my laptop has six CPU
cores, if I remember right.
So I can do this, which is still fine.
So every process gets now a
unique CPU core to work with.
So there's no competition of resources.
Of course, in this example,
it doesn't really matter because
this runs instantly.
But I can also do, let's say, 12.
which hopefully runs, yes.
It runs, but now it means
that there are two processes per
one CPU core, which is not
ideal in a real computing environment.
Yeah, and at least I noticed
that it took quite a bit
longer until it started printing things.
So that's probably the overhead
from having to switch
It's hard to say because this runs so fast.
Indeed.
We will need the proper example.
Let's do 100.
Now it's taking a long time to even start.
Yeah, because it doesn't know
what it's supposed to do first.
It needs to decide that.
Yeah, but this still runs.
Some MPI implementations may not
even allow you to start the program
if there are not enough cores
to kind of have running independently.
I guess it depends also
on how it's configured.
But anyway, here it does work.
Yeah, that's a good point.
So indeed that can be
dependent on the configuration
and on supercomputers, which I
mean, they're shared between many, many users.
then typically the setting is
that it is not possible to
over scribe the physical course.
But you will get a clean
error message then if you try to do that.
Yes.
So now should we move on to the exercise?
And the exercise is doing the same thing
as for the multiprocessing,
which is calculating pi.
but now do it with MPI instead.
And the main difference is going to be
that there's a communication
between the processes.
There's what's called a
collective communication.
So every process participates
to communicate some data.
So message in MPI means some data always.
So you're sending numbers
between processes or bytes to be specific.
So the exercise is here.
Do we have any comments before we start?
We don't have any new comments
on the notes docs.
I don't think we have, at
least from my side, I don't have any comments.
I think we planned 15
minutes for this exercise.
And after that, since it's already 47,
let's make it exercise until
the full hour, and then we will
have a break of 10 minutes.
All right, sounds good.
um add to the notes document
so see you again in well
25 minutes don't forget to
take your actually take your break
and get up and search a
little and well with that bye
and see you later see you in a bit
Hello, everyone.
Welcome back.
So I hope you managed to
do something at least with this exercise.
Now, from reading the notes,
there have been some
installation issues regarding MPI,
which is completely understandable
because installing MPI or
using MPI libraries is not
always entirely trivial.
And the reason in this case is that
uh even if you download mpr
for pi the python package with
let's say pip then you may
still not get the the actual
mpr runtime library needed to to use it
and this is made this
on purpose because you usually
don't want to download just any
implementation of mpi you want
to use the one that's been configured
and made available on your
your hpc system but now of course
if you're doing this on your
own laptop it would be nice
to have it available and the solution
for that is the to
use the conda environment which
is really the recommended way
for for this course here because
it turns out that the
that conda is able to
download a working MPI runtime library for you.
It may not be the most optimal one,
but just for running things on your laptop,
it doesn't necessarily need to
be the most optimal version available.
So in short, if you had issues using MPI,
try doing this in the
conda environment as instructed on
the course page.
All right, so now do
the actual exercise and let's
look at the solution.
Actually before that, let me run
it a few times.
So I have the exercise code
here, just the same code copied from the page.
And now I'm going to run it
a few times to see what
the output should look like.
So NPI exec number of processes.
Let's do, let's start with one.
So no parallelization whatsoever.
And the file is called mprxs.py.
So I noticed here that in
the Python code that you have
increased n to 10 raised to 8.
Let's try again.
Yeah, sorry, I had to
increase the number of tries
that the program or number of random
numbers that it generates.
I had increased it by
order of magnitude for testing.
So now it's back to seven,
which is on the example.
So now we get that it
through this many darts, so 10
to seven, it gets an estimate
for pi, which looks pretty good.
And the time spent was 2.5 seconds.
And now just to compare,
let's do two processes.
and we expect the speed up
to be roughly two times, 1.4.
It's not exactly two times faster
because of, well, it is
just measuring it once, so there's deviation.
And the other reason is
that communications are overhead,
always in MPI.
And in this case, so what
is going on is that it's
running this function many times,
in well, this many times
generating these two random numbers
and then checking if you end
up inside a circle.
And it's doing this now
in each process independently.
And then in the end,
there is something called a gather.
So gather operation in MPI
means that we're gathering data
from all processes inside the
communicator to one process.
And the one process is
called the root process of the gatherer.
And here we specify root zero.
So we're gathering to the
process whose rank is zero.
And then it calculates the
usual sum of this to estimate the pi.
And there's also if statement
for checking if the rank is zero.
And if yes, then it does
this summation and prints the pi.
And this is because we don't
want to print this thing
out from all processes.
We could, but it's redundant.
And the corresponding prints are, well,
there is the final print
showing the result and the timing.
And then there's these two
kind of testing demonstration prints
that show the number of
hits inside the circle before and after gather.
And now, interesting, you can
see that in, let's say, rank zero,
After gather, the data array
is actually really an array here.
It has two elements, and
these are gathered from the two processes.
This is just the number of
hits in the original rank
zero process, which just gets
gathered like this.
And the other number is
from the other process, gets gathered here.
After the gather process in
the process that's not the
root process, there's no data left.
So gather kind of removes the
data in that case.
And we can repeat this
with other processes as well,
other number of processes.
So now with four processes,
it's again faster.
It's not faster by a factor
of two, but close enough.
And let's do six as well.
Now this time the speedup was
a bit less impressive.
Final demonstration.
What happens if I run
this with many processes, like
way more processes than I
have CPU resources on my laptop?
Then we expect it to be slow.
So let's try 20.
And this should be much
slower than running, let's say, six processes.
Yeah, 0.8 seconds, which was
slower than with the six processes.
It's because there's no
competition between CPU resources
or competition of CPU resources
among these processes.
OK.
And again, there was also
a question about why is the
order of prints kind of random.
And it's just because NPI
starts as many processes as you tell it to.
And then each of those
processes will execute independently.
the kind of actual speed
at which they execute it may
not be the same for all the processes
because of things like
operating system assigning resources
to other processes also on
the operating system so it's just
how it goes it's not
deterministic yeah and that's it
is like that also for
for efficiency, because if you
would have it deterministic, then
you would need to somehow implement
or the operating system would
need to monitor then that,
okay, first rank zero does its
thing, then rank one and then
rank three and so forth.
And every now and in an MPI program,
You need to have this kind of
either like things are sequential
or you need to do some kind of synchronization.
But this also costs a little
bit of time because then the ranks
which are perhaps finished
with their tasks, they need them
to wait for the other ranks.
Yes, that's a very good point
that we can enforce the
order of things that happen in
MPI by using synchronization.
There's a function called MPI barrier,
for example, which synchronizes
everything in the communicator.
But that is usually not what
you want to do because then
that means that all the processes
would have to wait.
until everyone, like all
the other processes also are at
the same point of execution.
So that's, in most
cases, that's unnecessarily waiting.
But of course, in some cases,
you just have to synchronize
depending on your algorithm, on
what you're computing.
Yes, indeed.
And an example here in
this particular code is that
towards the very end here, you
need to add up the
I mean, individual contributions
from each and every rank here
before you then get the
best possible approximate for Pi
here, which is to combine from all of them.
Yes.
So indeed, we cannot really
Jan-Willem Wasmann, proceed beyond
this gather function call until
all the brothers have actually
finished their computations and have
sent the the results, the root node,
so there is actually
an implicit synchronization here
in this gather call.
Jan-Willem Wasmann, Yes.
Okay.
Any other comments or questions about MPI?
[name], maybe?
I'm just trying to look
whether there's anything in the
notes that we should discuss, but
I don't see anything.
Well, people have been problems
with MPI not being
being there.
I think this is something
that happens quite commonly that you have,
it might be working on the
one system, but then on
a different system because the MPI
needs some other installation steps,
it won't be working on that
system with the same sort
of installation script, especially
common when switching from Windows
to Linux or vice versa.
Yes, that's unfortunately, because
MPI is relatively close to
the hardware, it's kind of
unavoidable, isn't it?
Yeah, and I think for
Windows in particular, MPI is not, let's say,
it's not very relevant for
Windows because there are no
super computers running Windows these days.
So it's really like implementing
and maintaining MPI for Windows
systems is not something Microsoft
is proud to putting tons of resources into.
MPI is mostly just a
kind of high-performance computing library.
It's not used really outside HPC.
So I said that, but I need
to say that it's used a lot in HPC.
like all the supercomputers have
some NPI implementation available
as the main method of
parallelization in modern clusters,
modern supercomputers.
And it's also where a lot
of kind of technical issues show
up because, I mean, NPI has to
kind of communicate.
It has to work across
a full supercomputer, which
supercomputers are essentially many
smaller computers linked together.
And MPI is one software
side thing that lets this
linking to be possible for users.
And if something breaks, it's
very often actually MPI, at
least from my experience.
Which is also why supercomputers are
like often they have a
one recommended mpi library that
you should use on that system
and uh meaning that do not use the mpi
that you would download from
from let's say i don't know
pip or something like that try
to use the system mpi as
much as possible if it's available
There's actually an interesting
question in the notes document asking,
if you're forced to use Windows
because your company or
university wants you to, does it
make sense to work on
VSL, Windows Subsystem for Linux,
i.e.
running Linux on a Windows machine,
for the people who didn't know,
if you want to go to
supercomputing, or if you want to
run your code on a cluster later on.
What do you think, Valerie?
So I think, so here I'm assuming
that the cluster or
supercomputer itself will not be Windows,
so it will be a
sub-linux computer, like they always are.
As you just said, I don't
think there are any actually.
Yeah, but for developing and
testing your code on a
Windows system, then using, let's say,
this Linux subsystem for Windows
with NPI is a perfectly valid approach.
Anything that lets you...
compile your code, run your
code and test it with an if
it needs NPI, then great.
Even on Windows.
Yeah, Windows subsystem for
Linux is overall very stable.
So there's still, I mean, after all,
it's not native Linux, but
it has almost everything is in place.
So yeah, I could recommend it.
And I also have some
own experience from running it
and including also running with MPI.
And that works nice on
the one machine where I've tried it.
Great.
Yeah.
And final comment on MPI
is that usually you will know
if your program needs
should or would benefit from MPI.
It's when you have complicated, let's say,
parallelization needs and you need
to pass messages around, pass
data around, things like this.
And if you're simulating anything
that needs to scale up to
very large node counts, CPU
counts, then usually MPI is the way to go.
But the other side is that
if you don't need MPI, then
don't force your program to use it.
because if you can do it
in an inversely parallel way, then that's
even better because then
there's no communication overhead.
Okay, I think we should move on.
The next topic is a short discussion of
coupling Python with other languages.
And this is something that
I will discuss more in detail
in the next episode, which is on Cython.
But just to give a very
short overview of what's in
this section is that there are, let's say,
three main reasons you may
want to combine Python with
other programming languages like
C, Fortran, C++, things that
either run faster or are
convenient for other reasons.
The reason something like C
may be more convenient than Python
is that it doesn't have
the global interpreter lock.
So you can do multi-threading
there without worrying about this
kill in Python.
The other reason
It might be that you
have this library implemented in,
let's say C, and you want
to call that library from Python.
So what do you do is
that you usually write a thin
wrapper code that exposes this
library to Python.
And this is called extending
Python with usually C. The third reason that I
want to mention is that
sometimes Python is just too
slow to execute some particular
algorithm that you need to do.
Like you have some specific
computation, it doesn't really work
well in Python because Python
is inherently a slow language.
Then what you can do is you write just
that part in a faster language
and then expose it to Python
so that you can still have
your main program written in Python.
You just call that
function that's not written
in another another language you call
that from your main python program
and this is very common
in scientific codes um how do
you actually do this well
there are good libraries for handling this
for handling the let's say
most of the painful stuff for
you um just to pick a few or highlight a few
There's a package called cffi,
which lets you expose C code
to Python or vice versa.
There's also ctypes, which is
built into the Python standard library.
It's similar to cffi, but it's
a bit more, let's say, elementary.
It has less features.
For C++, there's a very
good library called pybind11.
But it is really just for
C++, it doesn't work in C. For Fortran,
what you usually do is
you would expose first the
C, expose your Fortran first to
C, and then expose that C code to Python.
So there's a deal by process there.
And then for us, there's
also library code by O3.
Rust is not very popular
in scientific course yet, at least not yet.
Maybe it will be in the future.
And the point here is that
these are all faster languages
that do not suffer from kind
of this slowness that's inherent
to Python, which is an interpreted language.
More on that in just a few minutes.
So I could add on here.
So you mentioned many reasons
why you would like to
combine languages and many of them
have to do with performance.
Another aspect naturally is when
it comes to different
features and functionality.
So for scientific code, it's
very common that you get some
some kind of numerical output
or raw output that you
would further like to analyze or visualize.
And if you have the bindings to
that program and to Python,
you can then get going
with using Matplotlib and
or you can work with pandas you can
or work with any of
the other visualization packages that
can be very powerful
Yeah.
Then just a very brief comment
that there are also other,
like many other libraries that can
do kind of parallel computations inside Python.
Dask, for example, is something
that you can use for dividing
a NumPy array work or kind
of array-like work to many processes.
It's a Python library.
You can have a look at
it if it sounds interesting.
will chunk the array into smaller parts
and divide those parts to
the many processes then then
there are something called task queues
and these are essentially
helper programs for launching
multiple processes
Jan-Willem Wasmann, might be
a bit redundant in actual
super computing environments, because
they usually have their own job systems
for doing this kind of
things, but if you're interested
this link you're going to have a look.
Right.
So the next topic would be Cython,
which is an example of
actually combining Python with C code.
But before we get into that,
do we have any final
comments about this section?
I think we could highlight
that we have added a few
examples of scientific codes
that combine Python with C++.
as well as with the CUDE
and HIP code for running on GPUs.
So this one link here
to the numerical toolkit Runco
for simulating astrophysical plasmas.
And then there's also code
VeloxCAM for quantum chemistry.
And for the latter,
I know from the developers
that they use very much a workflow
and modality of using the
code based on Jupyter notebooks.
And that scales then very well.
So you can run on your
own laptop to poke around and
you could use it for
teaching and demonstrations and
still staying on the laptop.
But you can then offload,
if you have bigger calculations,
you can then offload it to the supercomputer.
So that's, I mean, at least
for the context of teaching chemistry here,
I've heard that it's been
rather successful because then you can
showcase and let the students
make use of the code, which
is run for the really heavy calculations.
So it's the real tool, so to say.
Yeah.
Python is very commonly used as
a kind of glue to stitch
many packages written in
other languages together.
And Python is very good at that.
Yeah, indeed.
Okay, but now in the interest of time.
Yeah, I would maybe quickly, as a summary,
add that hopefully we've shown
you today in this lesson
that parallel programming is a tool.
It's not always the tool you need,
even if your code is
running slightly slower than you
would like it.
Profile it first.
see if you can speed it
up in other ways first.
And if you cannot speed it
up in other ways, then it is
the time to look at a parallel programming.
And we've shown you a few ways to do it.
So now we'll think a bit
more about using other languages
than Python to do actual programming.
baseline parallel things.
And yeah, that's about what
I wanted to summarize.
And I'll say goodbye for now.
Okay, so thank you and goodbye.
Thanks.
Okay, so we're a bit uh,
bit behind the schedule because
I've been rambling so much.
So [name] is now joining me
for the next section, next
topic, which is Cython.
So this is in the
section called Extending Python
with Cython here on the course page.
We're going to discuss one
quite popular approach for
combining Python with C code
and also improving performance of it.
Let me get rid of the sidebar real quick.
Exactly, so... Yeah, okay.
Hello, everyone.
So yes, Python can be
slow, as [name] rightfully put it,
and Cython is one possible
approach to compile and
make performance benefits.
yeah so lori like how what
is cython like how does it
do things cython is uh well
it's a python package and it's
also kind of tool for producing
c code from python code
and compiling that using a
standard c compiler so that the
the generated code has all
the necessary boilerplate that Python
needs in order to call this
a compiled code from Python.
So Cython is one way of doing that.
And now the real selling point
of Cython is that it allows you to add
static type declarations to your code
which can drastically speed
the execution because python doesn't
need to then interpret the types
all the time right and so
maybe you should actually discuss
that because i have here an
example of why why exactly is
python slow in let's say most
cases and the reason is that
Python is a strongly typed
language and it's also
dynamically typed language.
What this means that the
strongly typed means that all
variables have a type and
this type is important for
what operations can be performed
on that variable.
So the type needs to be
known in order to do anything with the variable.
And Python will figure this out
figure this type out at
runtime and check it all the time.
And this is the part about dynamic typing.
So a type can change at runtime.
And so just an example
of what actually happens or
what Python needs to do in
order to add two integers in this example here.
Let's say we're adding seven to six.
variable names are a and b then
what happens on this line
is that python needs to
do what's called unboxing of variables
or unboxing of the type so
it needs to check first that
okay we have an integer sorry
we have one we have variable
called a and now let's check
the type okay the type is
an integer that so that takes
time to do that check
And everything, just to
reiterate, everything is an object,
even integers, they just have
a number associated with them,
but they have other data as
well as shown in this box here.
Now the same thing for
the other variable, we have
variable B, okay, it's an integer.
And now the next thing it checks is that,
okay, is there an operation
implemented for this called addition
with this addition symbol?
So Python has to check that also.
And then it finds that,
okay, yes, integers can be added together.
Now let's do the actual addition.
And this is where it
would then call something on
the, some additional thing on the CPU.
But that's not everything, because
then it needs to put the types
back in in the result.
So it gets a result.
It's number 13.
But in order to pass this
number back to Python, it needs
to do boxing of the variable type.
So that also takes time.
It creates a new Python
object that's of the integer type.
And this happens all the time in Python.
And a large part of why
Python really is a slow language
is because of this kind of
boxing and non-boxing of variables.
The other reason Python is slow
has to do with interpreting
itself because it's an interpreted language.
But [name], is this always the case?
Do we have examples like
NumPy where this is circumvented?
Yes, very good.
Very good.
NumPy, what happens when you
call some function of NumPy array from NumPy?
is that it actually calls
the C function where the
routine is implemented in a
faster compiled language like C
or Fortran usually in the
case of NumPy actually.
So in that case, because
the types are known for
NumPy arrays, the arrays have
only one fixed type.
They're either integers, they're
either floating point numbers or something.
else that is known so numpy
can do very fast operations on that
as well so the speed is
going to be similar to
compiled language like co4 so
it's actually like certain
libraries actually makes use of
this uh compiler which is
cyton to enhance their performance
Yeah, so, sorry, NumPy doesn't
actually use Cython very much as
far as I know.
Maybe SciPy does, at least.
I think so.
QPy?
SciPy.
SciPy maybe does, I don't know.
I know that QPy, which is
a kind of GPU version of
NumPy, that's all written in Cython.
Okay.
So then we know like what performance
for pitfalls you can have, at
least one of them is this unboxing.
And how do we
Maybe we can mention that
this episode is also going to be a demo.
So we don't expect everyone
to follow along.
So sit back.
Yes.
So indeed, because we will
be compiling C code here.
And having that kind of
working compilation environment for
that goes beyond what is
required for this course.
So we don't really have exercises here.
And we will be demoing this.
You can follow along if you want.
you can try running this
command here in your conda environment.
It will install cython and it
will add them to get the C
compiler as well, if you don't have one already.
All right, so now, so
we established that Python is
indeed a slow language.
So it's not just a joke
that Python is slow, it's actually slow.
But the good thing is that in many cases,
Like many libraries that we use in Python,
they actually written in a
faster language under the hood.
So the slowness is not as big of deal.
Except that if you have your own code
that needs to do something
that NumPy is not good at,
for example, the code that
doesn't vectorize well, then you
may have to write your own
code in a faster language and
then expose that to Python.
And this is called,
kind of extending, writing
Python extension modules.
And usually it's done in C.
There are many ways of doing this.
You can use some of
those libraries described in
the earlier section.
And these are very useful
if you already have a working
C code or Fortran code or C++ code.
If you don't, then this
is where Cython comes in.
So Cython is a way
of writing Python-like code
but that also can be compiled to C code
and you can optimize it
by adding static pipe declarations.
So Cython extends the Python
language with a bit more new
stuff that can be useful for optimizing.
So if I understood correctly,
you don't have to learn C
to create extensions and we can
stay with the python like syntax
and still generate extensions right yes
and uh we can demonstrate this yes
so let's look at the the
demo here you first cite the module
and i should actually open
my code editor and open a new
file here so i'm going to
create a file called my
module.py just let's start with
the normal python
And I'm going to add a
function that just adds two numbers.
Very simple.
So it will take in what
are assumed to be numbers, X and
Y, and add them together and
then return the result.
So that's the module.
And now you know how to
use this from Python.
You import this into another
Python module and call the
function from there.
But with Cython, what we can do
is we use a command line
tool called Cythonize to compile it.
So this will compile the code
and do it in place.
So this dash I means in place.
it will produce a what's
called a python extension module
it's a compiled binary containing
this uh this function that we have okay
and uh so what happened is
that we have the original module
here then we have a c
code like file file containing
c code let's actually have a
quick look at it although it's
not ready so that this is
what cyton generated from our python function
It's a long file with a
lot of kind of Python API
usage, and it's not very readable.
It's mostly just preprocessor stuff.
And it has a,
Well, the line numbers are
not visible here, but it
has almost 8,000 lines just
for adding two numbers.
So point being, these are not
meant to be human readable, but
it's valid C code that a
C compiler can then compile for you.
And the compilation was done
by Cython when I run this cythonize-i command.
It produced a file
called mymodule.cpython something,
something, something.so.
So so means it's a shared library.
And this is called the
Python extension module.
It contains the, the compiled
version of our function, and
we can import this to Python.
So let me demonstrate.
I can do from my module
and I get, apparently I get
this, this hints already.
I can do this and this.
is now getting the function
compile add function from my module.
I'm gonna call it with some
numbers and I get five.
Nice, so now we compile Python to C code.
I think it's worth pointing out
that although the binary and
the Python file are called my module,
so the name is the same,
but it will give preference to
the binary if it exists.
Yes, that is a good point.
In this case, I still have
the original .py module as well, as well
as the compiled version, but
it will give priority to the compiled one.
Okay, and now to make life
a bit more convenient, let's move
on to Jupyter Notebook, because
we can actually use Cython
from Jupyter, which is actually
very useful for debugging.
But unfortunately, there is a
bug in Jupyter, or at
least in JupyterLab, that makes
some parts of this Cython
helper functions not as useful
as they should be.
So I'm going to use
the old classic interface to Jupyter notebooks.
because it should work here
and let's pray that it actually works.
Even if it doesn't, then
what you're losing is just
some color highlighting.
So it's not that big of a deal,
but just to demonstrate what
it should look like, I'm going
to use the old interface.
So now I have here a new Jupyter notebook.
Cython is implemented as an
extension, so I need to load it.
Load extension Cython, and now
it should be available.
I can create the same function as before.
result x plus y and return the result.
And now to tell Cython
that it should compile this
function, we're going to use magic.Sython.
And that should do it.
And we can call the function.
And the reason I started
using this classic notebook
instead of JupyterLab is because
there's a useful magic called
annotate or dash A, or
just two dashes, annotate.
And this will show you the
generated C code by Cython.
And there's color highlighting
that shows how much
Python interaction there is in the code.
And this is useful because with Cython,
we commonly want to minimize
the amount of Python interaction
because that's the slow part, and
we want to get rid of that.
Now here, everything is yellow,
which means that there's
Python interaction on every line.
And the reason is that we
have not really added any
kind of Cython extension features
that could help Cython remove
this Python interaction part, which
will be the next topic.
just we can here inspect
the code it's again not very readable
but at least it's only
showing the the relevant lines these are
so this c code written
using macros from python header
it can be useful for
some debugging purposes but
not necessarily like this is
not very useful for example right
So yellow means that it's
interacting with the Python interpreter a lot.
How do we get rid of it now?
Are there ways in Cython to
get rid of this?
Yes, and that is the topic next,
which is adding static type
information to Cython.
So...
As we discussed, there's a
lot of boxing and unboxing
of Python types going on because
Python has to figure out, it
has to check what type this
variable is at any specific time.
So if we can actually tell Python,
or in this case, tell
the Cython compiler that, okay,
this variable is going to
be integer always, then it can optimize a lot.
And this is also how C or Fortran
or any compiled language with
static typing gets there, kind of.
manages to be so fast.
So with Cython, we can actually add that.
Cython extends Python with a
few keywords that we can add to code,
which makes the code not
valid Python anymore, but it
will be valid Cython.
So usually what happens in
Cython projects is that we
have files specifically with Cython code,
which we compile ahead of
execution to the machine code
and then call those from
the main Python program.
So in the case of just adding two integers,
we can add this keyword int
to a function to tell
Cython that these variables are
going to be integers.
like this.
And let's look at the annotate.
Okay, this is very good.
So what happened?
I told Cython that, okay,
this input variables are integers,
and now it doesn't show
any Python interaction on this
line where it does the addition anymore.
So that means there's no
type unboxing or boxing going on here.
There is still boxing going on
on the last line,
where it has to convert the
result to a Python type.
I can also do this.
I can define the result
parabola as an integer with
a keyword called cdef.
But in this case, it
doesn't really help much because
it still has to convert the
result to Python type.
So that's a bit redundant here.
good so now if this was
a real function that had to
do some really heavy workloads
then this would be a lot
faster than a standard python function
but they of course just
adding two numbers is fast also
in python so it's not that big
of a deal one thing that uh
which is the downside of static typing,
of course, is that types really
need to be integers.
So what happens if I
call this function with something
that's not an integer?
Let's call it with floating point numbers.
We see that it's still
returning 4 instead of what it should be.
It should be 4.8.
And the reason is that
when you're passing floating point
numbers to your compile function,
the function is forced to
reinterpret the inputs as integers.
So it converts the floating
point numbers to integers,
which means dropping everything
after the decimal point.
So in the end, it's just saying, okay,
I'm getting one and I'm getting
three as an input, and it
adds those up and returns an integer.
To make this work with
floating point numbers, you would
instead have to add something like float here,
remove that and then read on
and now it's actually giving
you a floating point addition and uh
if you've done any programming
in a static type language like
c then this of course not not
news but uh just something to
keep in mind with cython that the price to pay
for performance in this case is
that you really lose some
of the dynamic nature of Python.
But at least it will
prevent something very silly like
passing a string to this add function, right?
Yeah.
It will complain.
Let's actually try that.
So we have a function that
wants to take two floating point numbers.
So what happens if I call it with a string?
Yeah, it gives a runtime error.
Must be a real number, not a string.
Meanwhile, if this was a
Python function with no typing,
then it will pass the string to the function.
It will try to perform this
addition of an integer and a string,
and it will fail at
this point because integer plus string
is not a valid operation in Python.
Right, yeah.
And even like adding two strings
is a valid operation in Python,
but even that will fail here.
Yes, that will fail because
it's failing already in the
stage where it's trying to pass the variable.
Yeah, let's add some other string.
So adding two strings is
valid in Python, but it is
not valid for this function.
because this function has no
types fixed it needs to have
a floating point number as an input
as both inputs all right
yeah that's nice and so we saw like
how to compile with some
small scalar inputs how can we
do the same with numpy arrays
Yeah.
This was, of course, a
very trivial example.
A function like this is not something
that you would want to in
real world usage because it's
not the bottleneck.
If it is, then your
program is very interesting.
But what you can or what
you may have to actually
is something involving NumPy arrays
that does not vectorize.
So NumPy is good for vectorized operations.
But if the algorithm you want
to do does not vectorize, then
you're out of luck.
You have to loop over the
NumPy array and index it at different indices.
And that's all very slow.
So we can take this example here from the
from the nodes.
And I'm just going to copy
it in the interest of time and
paste it to my Jupyter notebook.
So what's going on is that
we have a function called slowLooper.
It's slow because it is very slow.
It's looping over a
two-dimensional NumPy array.
We have a double loop here.
And then it's assigning
a number to every element of
the of the array so every
array element gets a different number
so just just to demonstrate this
and i can um time it i can measure
how long it takes to to
calculate this slow loop error
let's use how much 500 maybe
Yeah, it takes 40 milliseconds
to do that loop when the
array size is 500 times 500.
Now let's do the same thing with Cython.
So Cython has a support for numpy arrays.
And to do that, I'm first
going to copy the same function.
I'm going to change the name
to, let's say, Cython looper.
And then I need to
to do what's called the C import.
So C import is a keyword added by Cython,
and this tells Cython to
import something at compile time already.
So in this case, we need
to import the NumPy C headers.
Otherwise it won't know how
to deal with NumPy arrays.
And now I need to cheat
and check what the syntax was.
yeah okay so it's just numpy
so c import numpy to get the numpy c api
as c numpy and we're going to import it
as a different symbol so
this is python numpy and this
is numpy c api and um so
what we can do first let's add some pipe hints
So the input is going to be integer.
It's going to be the size
of the array, or square of the size.
And I'm going to add the
magic to side them as this cell.
Can VUC NP to declare the data array?
Is that correct?
Yes, I should.
So I'm creating the data
array with the standard NumPy,
which is still valid.
Oops, sorry.
But I need to declare the type.
I need to tell Cython that,
okay, this is going to be
a NumPy array of specific data type.
And I need to cheat again
and check the syntax because
it's not quite trivial.
Syntax looks like this.
Use the cdef declaration keyword
to declare type.
The type that we're going
to declare is going to be CNUMBY NDArray.
So NDArray is the usual
kind of actual array of NUMBY.
And then the type is specified here.
In this case, I'm going to
create an array of 32-bit integers.
And the dimension also of the array.
Dimension is going to be 2.
So I'm going to copy this
and paste it here.
And for some reason, that's broken.
We are in the wrong cell.
Ah, true.
So copy that here.
And now we call it int32.
So maybe the array should
also match numpy.int32, right?
Yeah, just to be on the
same side, let's use the same
data type here because the integer
type I think in Python is 64-bit by default.
So now that should have cythonized.
And then I'm going to call our new looper.
It's called cython looper with
the 500 times 500 array.
and you can see that from the timing
that the same loop was
10 times faster which is
pretty nice compared to the
the python loop like pure python loop
even though with uh so we
did not test actually if we
just cythonize this pure function
without any any type hints
So that could help a bit,
but the main issue is that
indexing of a NumPy array is rather slow.
So the indexing happens here,
and this is a rather slow operation,
which is why the usual rule
of thumb with NumPy arrays is
that you want to avoid
manually looping over them.
and doing indexing like this.
But with Cython, you can
actually do it because Cython
can optimize this indexing away.
And it can also optimize
the overhead of interpreting a
loop that Python does.
So that gets optimized away
when you, when you Cythonize.
So we get rid of things
like safety guards for going out
of bounds from the NumPy array, right?
When you do indexing.
It actually does not get
rid of that automatically.
So yes, that's a good point.
So what happens when you're
indexing a numpy array?
So you access a numpy array and some index,
it will check, like it does
some checks on the indexes.
It checks if the index is
valid in the sense that it's
not too large for the array.
and it will also check the
sign of the of the index
because numpy wants to support
syntax like this like minus
minus indexing in order to
wrap around the array so it
does checks like that um you
can disable them with cyton
so that the decorators for
those are here bounce check and
wrap around and i can add them here
And now it failed, because I
forgot to do something.
Oh, yeah.
I need to import site then.
So that now disables the
index checking, which may or
may not improve performance.
If it does not improve
performance, there's a write-up about
that here, which has to
do with branch prediction in CPUs.
So this might not always
be actually beneficial.
And if you do disable these
checks, then be very careful
because then it's really not
doing any checks and you
can crash your program.
So if I add a line
here that tries to access data,
let's say minus something, something
that should crash because it's
not checking the indices anymore.
Oh, well, it did not crash.
Why?
Maybe if you go, like, more
than n plus 1, something.
Yeah.
Yeah, let's try a very large index.
OK.
I have crushed my Jupiter kernel.
And with that, I think it's
a good time to end.
I have successfully broken my
program by disabling NumPy
safety checks because I wanted
to improve performance, but I
was very careless, very reckless
in doing that.
So lesson learned, be very careful
if you actually disable these
checks that Cyton allows you to do.
So to shut things up,
yeah, we don't sitonize everything.
We choose only the slowest
parts, slowest functions.
Yeah.
Yeah, absolutely.
And also like, usually it's
not like the siton works
the best with elementary data
types, like integers, floating point numbers.
Strings, but it's not that great
for heterogeneous containers like
Python dictionaries, because those
can really contain any type, so
it's just hard to optimize those.
And same for Python lists.
Okay, sorry for going a bit over time.
Yeah, it is time for lunch break,
so I don't want to stay
very long and chat here, so...
I'm just trying to decide if
we are going to meet back at
10 past or, but I guess, uh, let's meet in time.
So at, uh, well at the
hour, which is one o'clock
finished time, central European time
should be about 12.
And, um, otherwise it's whenever,
um, it's the exact hour.
Right.
Um, all right.
Well, have a good break.
Um,
if it's an appropriate time
have something to eat and we'll
see you in 50 minutes bye yeah bye bye
hello hello and welcome back
hopefully you had a little bit of time
for eating some food and relaxing a bit
so briefly before i introduce
the speakers for the last part
of the course which again
is after the scripting is
my second favorite part because
it really goes to the core of uh
reproducibility by making, for example,
your own code reusable
through packaging and by reusing
other people code with version
control and or dependency management.
Just a reminder about the credits
since this is the last session
that you can read the required
tasks at the link that is written there.
And remember to send homework
from your university email because
that's a requirement that we would like to.
Basically, we want to give
the credit to those who are students.
And if you are a master's
student, you need to also
verify that your study program
actually accepts credit.
But I don't want to
steal any more important time
from [name] and [name].
You've actually already seen them
before in the past days.
So the stage is yours.
And I guess we can go
to [name]'s screen share.
Yes.
So hello, everyone.
Welcome back.
So now that we have gone
through a lot together already, like
if you remember, we have
gone from first creating the environment
that you have been using
throughout the course to learning
about how to do scientific computing.
And now becomes the interesting
part of like, okay, you have
learned how to do your
own scientific programs, hopefully,
and now you want to share
them with other people.
So for that, we need to
first talk about how do we
package that stuff and then how do you
make it reproducible and stuff
like that for installation.
And we'll have two sessions on this.
And this first session is
about the packaging stuff.
And so [name], hello.
What could you tell me about packaging?
How should we package our projects?
Right.
So packaging is an interesting topic.
It's also important to think
like, when do we decide how to
when a piece of code
becomes a package, like when it
deserves to be a package, right?
So it could be very simple.
It could be one file.
And it can also mean
that like you're doing, writing
a couple of functions within that file
and you start to reuse
it in different places, different computers.
Your friend starts to like it.
They want it.
They always email you.
That's one reason maybe packaging
is useful for you and your colleagues.
So what packaging does is it
puts all the Python code,
if you're talking packaging in
Python, into a zip file or
something similar to the zip file.
It has some special extensions.
And you upload it into a special server.
The most popular server we will
see soon is called PyPI.
and that's how you create
and publish a package in short.
Yeah, like these special
files, they're often called
wheels, Python wheels.
So this is like Monty
Python jokes all around, like
the Python is named after the
Monty Python and the wheels are
for the wheels from the G sketches.
So like weird naming
conventions all around, but that's all fine.
So how do we...
Is there a preferred way
how should we organize our stuff
when we have this sort of
like we want to package our stuff together?
How should we organize it?
Right.
So the first thing you should
do is you should have a couple of files
which will become modules because
they will be made importable by
the process of making it a package.
So we need some files.
That's the first thing that you need.
And then, and PD also
needs some metadata to go along.
For example, a license is important
that makes it legally possible
for other people to download
it and install it in their own systems.
Without a license, it
doesn't mean anything.
It's supposed to be a private package.
People may not use it as you want.
And then of course, every
package usually comes with
the readme describing what it
does so that people can read
about it before they install it.
So these are the main components and
We will do a simple package
in this episode and we will try to go slow.
Yeah.
So let's go, let's get started.
So I'll have a new folder
here and let's, let's get started on this.
Maybe I'll make it a bit bigger.
Exactly.
So what we're going to do
is we open Jupyter lab and
we create an empty folder and
The first thing is to choose a name.
Choosing the name is sometimes
the most hardest problem for any project.
So before we go to the
step, maybe we could check PyPI.org
if this name actually exists.
Yeah.
In all cases, if you have a new company,
you want to start a new
company, the first thing you do
is you Google the name of the
company and is it already taken?
Or do you have the webpage already present?
Has somebody else already taken that?
Because if they have taken all of the
the space, all the search
engines point to them, or you
just get confused with that project.
That's not a good thing.
There's also in these packaging indexes,
there can be a problem
of like cybersquatting or this
kind of like security attacks by
like, if you install like numpy or something,
with two Ms or something like that.
People have done these kind
of attacks where they
publish vulnerable packages with
small name differences.
So usually you want to pick
a name that is like...
uh not something uh generic so
of course in this example we'll
pick like a calculator as
a non very non-generic name but
let's call it like let's i will
call it like my own calculator
and maybe maybe i'll put even
the year after that so let's
call that our project yeah does
that look fine nothing yeah
In a practical sense, I
wouldn't put something like an ear,
but just to make sure that
this thing is unique, we can
assume that this is a fine name.
Yeah.
In an actual situation, you
would, of course, want to
put something that is more... Descriptive.
Yeah, more descriptive and unique
and that sort of stuff.
Findable when you search it
in Google or something similar.
Yes.
So then you need, what do we do now?
The XML, the files, or?
Yeah, like we should probably
have the files there, but if
we want to use them in
Python, we probably want to have
them in a way that we can
import them in Python, right?
Right.
So then we need to give the package a name.
So we call that package
something really short and useful.
Yeah.
So something we want, when we
do an import in Python, like we
want to give a Python module
name that is like something that
we can import easily, like
for example, NumPy or something.
And this can be different,
but to the project name or what
is in the PyPy index.
But of course, like in best
cases, it would be the same.
So, but let's put a different one
for now, because we don't
want to import this kind of a monstrosity.
Exactly.
Yeah.
And it's also done in the wild.
For example, you might have
heard of this package called scikit-learn.
If you install, it's called scikit-learn.
But when you're launching a
Python and importing it, you
will write sklearn.
So it's a very short name.
It could be the same
name, but sometimes you can.
Short is good, right?
Yeah.
Less typing.
And then we put these
functions in small files, which
will become the module.
The module is called adding.py,
and the function here is called add.
All of this is from the page?
So if you want to do
this later on, you don't have
to write it really fast.
You can look at the page after the fact.
Yeah.
There'll be time in the exercise
for you to catch up.
We create a subtracting node
pi with a subtract function.
Finally, the third module, we
call it integrating.
In that, we actually
import another dependency from SciPy
and reuse it to make
our own integral function.
So your package doesn't have
to be standalone.
It can rely on other packages
to get help from.
Now it's also a good
practice to tie everything up so
that you don't want to write calculator.adding.
So we create init.py it's called,
and this is supposed to be
the top level of your package.
And this is like a chosen name in Python.
This underscore is like
internal Python information.
It has this specific format of underscore,
underscore, init, underscore, underscore.
exactly and we will soon
see when we install this
package that this makes things
easier to access this one
we also here mentioned this kind
of like a version string of
what is the version of this module
that we are creating so this
is again like this kind of
like meta meta things for python
and this is again like a
chosen word right exactly yes
well done practice
And then finally, like we
said before, we need to give some description.
So we'll write that
as readme.markdown file, readme.md.
Yeah, quite often, like, of
course, this thing would be
like in a repository somewhere,
like you could probably use
version control and you would
put this repository somewhere.
So we would have probably
pre-created the markdown already,
but let's now create it
because we're missing it.
Exactly.
Yeah.
This is meant for humans, of course.
And now our, most of the
main contents are ready, but we
are missing a key piece,
which is the packaging, like
the machine readable part of it.
So we will use at this
stage, a tool which comes
in your conda environment already.
It's pre-installed.
It's called Flit.
And if you run Flit in it,
it goes into a flow where
you can type in some names.
Like here, we can give the
name of the package.
It's calculator C mode 25, the author name.
We can give an email.
You don't have to reveal
your personal email.
Could be something.
Yeah.
Let's promote all of them.
And the home page, yeah, it
could be your university name
or the GitHub repository.
That's usually done.
And there are some good
options that Flit does for you.
Like you can choose which
kind of licensing you have if
you are familiar with this.
But here we keep it simple.
Yeah.
And you notice that the
module name here is, it was different to
what demos, like by default,
did want to give the same
name for the module as the file here.
But like we can, we'll fix this afterwards,
like because our project name
that we put into PyPy is
going to be a different one.
So what we get out of the
flit, we get this kind of a file, right?
Yeah.
So it pre-fills all these questions
and writes into a project.toml
file, where all this metadata goes.
So before we go into
installing, actually installing, we
will show like, even at this
stage, you can import it, provided
you are in the right directory, right?
So let's see how it's done.
Yeah, let's try it.
So I'm here, like, I have
a terminal open here.
Of course, I could use, like,
a notebook as well.
But let's use the
interactive Python terminal for fun.
And I will just start Python here.
Let's try something fun.
So there's an example code in the...
in the examples, that runs some, like,
complicated mathematics with this
new package that we have.
Very complicated.
Yes, and then we see that,
okay, it managed to import.
So you notice that, like, we
got this from calculator kind of a thing,
and how Python recognized this
is it looked at these init files, right?
Mm-hmm.
So it knew what to import.
And there's like a whole thing
of how do you do this kind of imports.
And there's other things like
you can have an all there as
well that you can do a
wildcard imports and that sort of stuff.
But let's leave that as an
exercise for the home viewer.
Yeah.
Okay.
So how do we install this?
Are we ready?
Like, is this already ready
for install or do we miss something still?
I mean, we have, we
are using, assuming that this
package requires scipy, right?
So we need to mention that somewhere.
Yeah.
And the previous, we also,
well, let's first fix the scipy thing.
So let's, for the project,
we can set dependencies, right?
Yeah.
So the way to do that
is to write in something which
looks like a list of strings
and it can have more
dependencies comma separated as a list.
And scipy is what we choose.
The other thing we need to tell
and the build tool that we
are using flit is what the
module is called, the top
level module, which is calculate.
So this is different from
the package name that we chose,
which is right now calculator.
Let's go same with 2025.
Yeah, so, so we are
now using, there's multiple of
these build systems that you can use.
There's multiple of these
initialization things you can use.
We are just using flit
because it's easy and it asks,
asks those nice questions.
So to create the
PyProject.toml, but there's others as well.
And, and you, they have, you
can give them their own options.
So in this case, we are telling it that,
Hey, look for this folder
for the Python files, not.
like this is the folder name and
and but there are other tools
as well for this build system
but for this case we'll use
this one yeah so are we now
ready i think it looks ready so
now we can there is also a
note we can mention that like
it's possible to uh hide dependencies from git
Yeah.
Yes.
But that's also possible.
And there is a small comment on that.
Yes.
So we could add something like,
for example, if we would want
to use a repository from Git,
we could do something like this.
Or any kind of like bit packages
or something we would want to
use, like we could use it.
But in this case, we don't need X-arrays.
So let's not add
additional dependencies that are not needed.
Yeah.
Exactly.
And also, since we are mentioning this,
for development, like for
local installations, this is fine.
But if you're going to upload this,
PyPI will probably complain
that you're using something
which doesn't exist in PyPI.
So be careful there.
So with that, I think now
we can describe the exercise,
give an overview of what you
are supposed to do.
Yes.
So in the exercise, you should
do the same kind of project
like what we were doing,
like basically follow the
instructions over here to create
a similar kind of project.
And now you can try to
do a local pip installation of that project.
And in the exercise, there's
a hint over here that we are
going to go to the package dependencies
and environment management and stuff
in the next section, but
we haven't gone through there yet.
So for now, there's a hint here on
how you can create your
own virtual environment that you
can test out the installation.
But yeah, test out creating
this package first and then
creating a new folder, creating
this virtual environment and trying
to install that package into
that virtual environment and see how it goes.
And we should probably have
around 15 minutes for this.
I would say so, yeah.
So 35 minutes past the clock,
we will come back and discuss this exercise.
Yes.
And ask any questions in the notes
as well, like about the
package management or package creation,
if you have any.
Yeah, absolutely.
See you.
Bye.
Hello.
We are back, hopefully.
Welcome back.
So hopefully you managed to
try out the thing.
There's lots of copy pasting needed.
Sorry if there was too much
in this time frame, but we
can quickly demo what was the
result or what you could have experienced.
So first off, like for
this installation, like when we
are trying it in a different
place, we probably want to do
it in a place that is not inside here.
So we want to do the
testing in somewhere that
is completely different folder, right?
So let's create a new folder
over here, and then I'll open
a new terminal over here.
So yes, I have a new terminal here.
And now let's do the steps
to get a new virtual environment for us.
So I'll just copy this over here.
Okay, so we now have
a virtual environment and let's
do the pip install command.
I will type the path as a relative path.
So with tab, pressing tab,
I can autocomplete.
So I will install from
the relative path over here.
And it's the folder with
the PyProject.toml, right?
So that's what the pip
install is looking for, the PyProject.toml.
Exactly, yeah.
And to note while we're doing this,
virtual environment is some
sort of simplified version of
a content environment.
It shields the Python from
seeing other dependencies which
are pre-installed.
Yes.
In your system.
Yeah, so we noticed that
now it's installing NumPy, SciPy
and our calculator over here.
So now we have it, so
we can now try opening a
Python interpreter and try the test code.
I'll just copy paste this one over here.
Yeah, notice that it works.
So by magic, we have
installed it over here.
And when we did the
installation, we used this editable flag.
So [name], can you quickly
explain why the editable?
That sounds like.
So what PIP tries to do is
not to copy over files when
it's trying to install it.
It creates something like a symlink.
If you understand Linux language, symlink,
it's like a shortcut pointing
to the package folder, calculator
symbol in this case, right?
So every time you make a
change in your modules,
then it's immediately reflected
once you open a new Python interpreter.
You will have to close
the Python interpreter to make
those changes appear.
So let's try to make some
change in the subtract function.
Yeah, let's add there like
maybe a print statement or something.
Yeah, let's say.
so writing yeah x and y
from from x yeah yeah yeah all right
and then now we skip
the pip install because it's just
uh it's an editable install right
and now we run the same uh
command that we did before
yeah let's just run that
well actually let's let's run
the whole thing because it's
easier to copy paste yeah yeah
and then we notice like
while calling the subtract function
it managed to print something
So this editable is really useful
if you're doing like a
development thing, right?
Like if you want to test out things.
But of course, like in an actual, like
if you want to use your
code, you probably want to have
it in a lockdown version state so
that you can like be
certain that what version you
have installed and so forth.
But if you want to do
this kind of like development work
and test out how it looks
like the imports work and
everything, you can do this.
exactly so for that you
can skip the editable flag yeah
all right okay so should we
now publish this package and
probably we don't want to publish
it uh like we don't want to
like mess up uh the first
step of publishing is probably
like uh testing it out we
don't want to like necessarily
mess up the python registry
with more package names than needed right
Exactly.
Yeah.
So for that reason, we
will avoid the PyPI.org website.
Instead, we go for the test
PyPI, which is like a test version of it.
Just a note to all of you who are watching,
we don't expect you to follow
along at this point.
We'll be going slightly faster,
but good enough that you can follow.
So first step is to log into PyPI and log
What should we do?
Is that what we do?
Like we make sure?
Yeah, so if we want to log into PyPI,
yeah, we have to get our
account and then we have to
figure out this API key from PyPI.
So do you want me to show it?
Yeah.
Yeah, but maybe we build
the package first, so we... Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, like, first off, yeah, we
need to do an account for the
place we want to push it.
But then once we have
those created, first we need
to, like, build the package, yes?
So that it's ready to be sent there.
And so we want to put
it into this wheel, wheel of cheese.
And for this, we use this command, right?
Exactly, yeah.
So this, again, should come pre-installed.
If not, the way to install
it is pip install build.
And the way to work with this
is to go to the package
folder, where your pyproject.toml
sits, and then to run
this command, python-m build.
What it does is... Yeah, what it does.
Yeah.
What it does is try to
create a isolated virtual environment
for you on the fly.
Make sure things like flat core,
which is the tool that
we choose is installed and
then wraps everything under a
tar.gc file and also a wheel file.
So these are two different
special formats and you'll find
them in the dist directory,
dist for distribution.
So we are supposed to
distribute this somewhere.
And that somewhere is going
to be our testbybi.org.
Yeah, and for this, just again, a reminder,
if you want to try this
out, you can create an account
in TestPyPI and then push it there.
But yeah, don't go messing
the PyPI registry if you don't need it.
Of course, for your
actual projects, publishing them
in PyPI, that's the place to do it.
But for this kind of
messing around, we don't want to...
cause problem for them so the
test by pi is meant for that
where you can like you can
put like arbitrary crap in there
and then try it out like your projects
so so for that we use
a different tool right yeah so
here we are using twine it used
to be the tool and we are
gonna just do that so twine
has a sub command called upload and
When you write that, you give
the list of files that you want to upload.
Here it's dist slash star,
meaning these two files that we created.
And then it asks for
something called an API token.
It doesn't ask for the password.
So this is something you
need to create from the website.
Can you show how to get that?
Yeah, sure.
Let me just have it somewhere open here.
Yes, so if you... If you
log into... Are you... Yeah, just a second.
Yeah.
So... Yes, so if you go to TestPyPI
and log in there, you can
then, in your account settings,
Okay, it wants me to put
my password in, but no.
Yes, so once you have the
account, you can then, in
your account settings, ask for this API key.
I won't be showing it because
I don't want to dox my
emails and stuff, but it's underneath there.
Yeah, you can create an
API token over here.
Exactly.
Yes.
So while creating a package
for the first time, it makes
sense to give the API token
access to all your projects?
But if you're running something specific,
maybe it makes sense to
create a token later on after
you upload your first release and
do a token specific for this package.
And this makes sense in things
when you're doing this packaging
in an automated way in GitHub
and so on, which we won't show, unfortunately.
But so I will now...
Well, there goes my token.
Well, I have to delete it, but
that this happens, like this
is a good example of, of like, uh, yeah.
Like when, how do you revoke an API token?
Like you, you post it into
the internet and then you revoke it.
So, but, uh, okay.
This already exists because I
already did, uh, did an upload.
Let's do a quick change over here.
So let's me.
In my calculator, I will
change the version.
I will upload the new version
and then have to do the build again.
Yeah, clean the dist first though.
Oh yeah, yeah, that's true.
Yeah, so I cleared the dist
and now I will build again.
So this is how you create a new version.
Yeah, bonus lesson.
And then I will upload it
and maybe publish my API key again.
But this is why you use the test pipe here.
So it doesn't matter that much
if your API keys are leaked.
Yeah.
So, yeah.
So now it gave a response
that it was successfully published.
And I can maybe show it over here.
Let's see.
In the test pipe.
Yeah.
Python Packaging Index, it's now there
and it probably has, yeah,
it has the README over there
and it has a release history.
So I have two versions over here.
Two versions.
Absolutely.
Yeah.
Should we now quickly try how
to install it from there and then... Exactly.
So that we create a
virtual environment, another one, fresh one.
So yes, let's go to, I'll
create a new folder over here.
So let's, uh, pi pi test.
And I'll open a new terminal
in this, uh, folder.
Yeah.
So then let's create a
new virtual environment.
Uh, this over here.
Right.
So in this snippet of code,
what we are trying to do
is create a virtual environment.
Try to... These parts.
Yeah.
Go right ahead.
So create a virtual
environment, activate it.
And so the PIP from now on
will be the one inside the virtual environment.
And then we tell PIP to
actually look for this package in test by BI.
That's what the flags are.
I needed to cancel
the previous installation because I
need to give it the name of my package.
Ah, yes.
All right.
So now things are more clear.
And the extra index URL is
to fetch scipy from.
Yes.
Unless scipy is already in
test by bi, which maybe it is.
Yeah.
So I think this is a good
place to wrap it up.
We need to have a break
before the next session.
But before going there, maybe
we can mention that there
is good extra information in the page, like
if you want to look later,
about how to do a conda
package and also about the
whole ecosystem, right?
If you need to do
something like C compiling for
your Python package.
Exactly.
So FLIT is the most simplest
of the build tools of all
five that we have listed here.
And here is a small decision
tree where you can choose depending
on what you need.
If you're doing something more complicated,
you might need something
equally capable when you're releasing to PyPI.
If you're releasing to Conda,
then we have listed some
instructions for that too.
But typically people don't upload
a package to Konda themselves.
They rely on something which
is called Konda Forge.
It's an automated GitHub-based
organization where you upload
small recipes, as it's called.
We also show how to build
your own Konda recipe in this episode.
So you can take a look
later on after this episode.
Yeah.
And with that, I think it's
good to have a break.
So thank you, [name].
And we'll return at the hour
and talk about dependencies
and virtual environments and that
sort of stuff.
So yeah, 10-minute break.
So see you at the hour.
And keep your questions coming.
See you then.
Bye.
Hello.
We're back.
Hopefully you had a nice break.
So we have a new instructor here as well.
[name], do you want to introduce yourself?
Yes.
Hello, everybody, and hope you're
having a nice time today and
learning so many things.
So my name is [name] and I'm joining from
uh oslo no way uh i'm not
i'm not i mean i do python programming
but i'm more in the system
level uh support so i'm hoping
to learn some things how [name] behaves
when he install packages and
and maybe we'll see some
opportunities to learn more things
from each other
Yeah, that sounds nice.
So, okay, let's... At the
start of the course, we
started, of course, with creating...
our environments that we have
been using throughout the whole course.
So it might feel a bit strange
that at the last lecture, we
are going to be talking about
how do you manage these dependencies.
But yeah, this will become
more important for you when you
want to have your next project,
you want to start your
own project, you suddenly have
to work with these dependencies.
So we had done the work for creating
that environment and putting
the instructions on how to do it.
But now we are going to
be telling you how you can do
that as well for your project.
So what is a dependency?
Well, in general, it's like some package,
like a Python package or a
thing that your code needs.
But like we have been
talking throughout the course that
like many of the last
scientific Python packages, they are
not only Python.
They're not only Python,
they're underneath it is a layer
of like lower level codes,
lower level code like C code
or Fortran or something else
that makes the thing fast.
And nowadays with deep learning
and stuff, often people have
to do GPU stuff as well.
They need to use GPUs
or graphical processing units to
speed up their codes.
And for these, you
need additional libraries that
make those codes work.
And there's also people are
using Python to do user interfaces like...
they're using it to create
their editors and whatever.
So you might need all
sorts of like graphical libraries as well.
So there's huge bunch of stuff
that can be in these packages.
And how they are usually like,
how is this handled usually?
In the lesson before, you
mentioned several times about packages
and you also made a package.
Now we are talking about
additional things we need to run our packages.
Is that correct?
Yes.
If we have something, we
create our own package and
we have something that it depends on.
For example, in the previous
lesson, we had a package
that depended on SciPy.
So
if we have our own piece of code
and it it needs imports
from a python module or
python package these are what
we want to install and
what what for efficiency's sake
uh these are like usually
pre-compiled or pre-created somewhere
like we download them somewhere
like somebody of
Like some nice person has
already created us usually these packages
and provides them in the internet
so we can download them
without having to compile the code ourselves
or do all of the necessary
thing that we just did, like
the building of a package and
that sort of stuff.
So without writing NumPy ourselves,
we can use NumPy and develop from that place.
Yes, exactly.
And for these, there's basically
like a big ecosystem around Python.
And this is like why Python is
so popular for scientific
computing, because it's so easy to extend it.
Or in general, why Python is so popular.
It's easy to extend it with
other pieces of code.
Well, relatively easy at least,
but easier than, let's
say, extending Fortran or something.
So there's like big ecosystem
of these packages available.
And there's basically two
major providers, at least in
the open source world.
There's probably others as well,
but two major ways that
scientific codes are often provided.
So we have already been talking about PyPy.
So this is Python Packaging Index.
So this is basically the
go-to place for Python codes.
So there's a huge number
of different packages there, and
you usually use pip to
install stuff from there.
Nowadays, there's been a new
tool, like rocking the boat,
called uv, which is really fast,
like this PyPI installer.
But there's others as well, like poetry
There's a lot of different
things, tools that can install
from the Python packaging index, but
PP is the most common one.
UV is this kind of like a new player
that is getting very popular,
but basically PyPI provides a
lot of Python packages.
And the thing with PyPy is that
if you have like code there, like
if you have pure Python
code, that rolls very nicely there.
But if you have something
that has external library needs.
So for example, if you
download NumPy from PyPy, what you
also get is open blast libraries.
So these are like linear
algebra libraries that are...
embedded into the wheel, like
it's inside the wheel, there's
these libraries that make NumPy work.
So if you need something that,
that has like external
requirements that needs to be
put into the package.
And that's why often in
PyPI, you find things like,
well, pure Python code packages,
but other packages, but those
have been like embedded with
the requirements needed for those,
like those library requirements.
Yeah, but we're talking
about some limitations, right?
Later on, we'll talk about Conda
where you can integrate more
system level packages.
But now maybe you're talking
about because NumPy might use C underneath.
It might need some dependencies
and then some linked libraries.
Yes.
And you mentioned the word wheel.
So wheel is like a pre-compiled,
like a tar file or a
collection of things, but it
comes for your operating system, isn't it?
So is there a better way
to explain a wheel?
No, that's exactly right.
It's basically like a compressed file
that has all of the stuff
in it needed for it to work.
Of course, packages can
have dependencies to other packages
and so forth.
For your code that uses
NumPy, it doesn't need to
package NumPy inside of it.
It can depend on NumPy
And NumPy then can package
whatever it wants inside of it.
But basically PyPy is this sort
of like big ecosystem.
It has huge number of packages, like,
I don't know, probably millions
at this point, but it's a huge ecosystem.
And the other big questions coming up.
So we'll talk a little
bit later about dependency and config.
So good questions.
Keep them coming up.
We'll talk them a little later.
Take them a little later.
Go on, [name].
Yes.
Yeah.
Do ask questions.
The other big ecosystem is Conda,
which is like, that was
already mentioned by [name].
And this is basically, like
Conda is this kind of like,
it goes one level deeper.
So what it does is
that basically people were noticing
that there's a lot of
these lower level libraries that
are common to many other packages.
And what if people want
to have different versions of
these lower level libraries or
different things like that, or
they want to use...
the same like they don't want
to put the same like plus library
for every package so what
if they would just use the same one
and this basically like there
was this company Anaconda Incorporated
that created these tools
but nowadays there's a big
open source ecosystem providing
these packages and conda is
basically like almost like an
operating system kind of like
package manager thing
where it can provide like all
sorts of like tools.
There's all sorts of like
graphics tools and weird stuff
and lower level like compilers
and build systems and all sorts
of like tools provided in the Conda ecosystem.
And we are talking about
like, again, like tens of
thousands of packages.
of different tools so if your
case is like you need a
much more like base level
of of like installation you need
you need to have like some libraries
for your code let's say you
need to compile something or if
you need to make certain
that everything plays nicely and
there's lots of these like
complicated library things, then
conda is your friend.
So conda basically like takes
it one level, like ups the ante a bit.
So PyPy provides mainly
like Python packages that then
you can import and dependencies for those.
Conda provides like basically
an operating system, like lots
of packages inside of there.
Yeah, so this OS level dependent,
so people do use a lot
of machine learning stuff these days, right?
So if you think about Python,
if you want to install
this PyTorch library, for example,
it'll come with PyTorch and
the Python APIs and the maybe
C code, but it will not come with CUDA.
But if you CUDA or OCHEM or whatever
that additional things you need
to interact with the operating
system level access.
But the conduct would also
pull in the OpenSSL libraries
and CUDA and other stuff.
Yes.
And there has been like,
there's this kind of like push
and pull between these two ecosystems.
Like they are not incompatible
with each other.
But it used to be that
installing CUDA was like, like
PyPy couldn't install CUDA.
So Conda was very popular
with stuff that used GPUs.
But nowadays, like...
Nvidia has started to actually
publish CUDA in PyPy.
So people have switched back towards PyPy.
But they're not like... There
are different ecosystems, but
there's interplay for all of these.
And one is not better than the other,
but it might... Certain
environments or certain...
tools that you want to use
might be more supported in one ecosystem
than the other so it depends
really on the use case that you're doing uh
and where like which is
the better solution for you
i'll quickly explain like yeah yeah
so sorry um could you
explain about this anaconda and
miniconda and you know there
are so many versions before you go further
Yes, yes.
So I was going to explain like the,
the conda ecosystem, because
like, like this is something that,
that sometimes can get
quite confusing because whereas in PyPI,
it's basically like you have a
pip and then you have a
PyPI and then it's like, that's
the, the thing that you usually
need to remember, like you have the PyPI,
which is the stuff where
the stuff comes from, the index,
and then you have the PIP
that is the installation tool.
But in Conda, you have this
kind of like this bunch
of different things because it
was originally created by
this Anaconda incorporated.
So they have their own
like repository, their own
like proprietary channels, and
they provide this mini Conda
installation and this Anaconda distribution.
And these are not free by default.
Like there's licensing, like you
can look below, there's like
links to the terms and conditions and whatever.
And it's free for certain
academic users, but not for every.
So if you're going to be
using these, do check that
if your licenses apply.
But in most cases, we recommend that...
use the open source alternatives.
So there's like a wide
community around this CondaForge channel.
So this CondaForge provides like
tens of thousands of packages
and it's maintained by open
source community and it contains
like open source packages.
So they are free and
they provide this miniForge installer
that you can use to
create your environments and
your Conda environment.
So if you're going to be using Conda,
Do be mindful of what
you're using to install the stuff
and whether you are allowed to
use the free version or not.
So check the licensing.
But in the condo community,
there's this free side and
it's very well-maintained.
So what, okay, so we
have been talking about what
are these like ecosystem, there's the PyPI
and then there's the Conda, but
how do you actually like
do something with these?
Like, how do you actually,
Like they manage your project.
How do you get stuff into it?
And the real question is,
there was a question previously
on the previous session, like
why are we creating virtual environments?
And the reason is that
Well, if you want others to
use your tools or your code,
it's best to provide them with something
that they can like,
like installation instructions that
make it possible for them to use those.
And for that, Python uses
these virtual environments.
So virtual environments are
basically like you do
a self-contained installation of Python
and all of the packages you
want to have and you put them
in a nice area where they
play nicely with each other and
they don't mess up
stuff outside so it's like basically
if you go to a zoo if
you take all of the cages
out like suddenly all of the
animals are running around and it's
going to be a horrible mess but
if you put like the cages like
If you like Zeus or don't
like Zeus, that's a different question.
But if you have the cages
there, then the lions won't eat the gazelles.
And this happens with Python environments.
If you have one code
that wants certain things and another code
that wants another thing, then
it's not usually possible to
satisfy both of these requests.
So you want to have these
kind of like gardens, like
walled gardens for each of these Python codes.
So these separated environments.
So you put your lions in
one place and you put the
gazelles into another one.
Another one.
And then that's a good analogy
because there was a question
about like conflicting dependencies.
So the Python doesn't just fail
because of conflicting dependencies
if you use the environment.
For example, as you said,
gazelles and lions, they should not
be in the same cage.
You could have two cages.
So that's a good way
to explain that scenario.
So you could keep the
compatible stuff together.
And when you need an incompatible thing,
try not to force it inside
that, but create a new environment.
And for these virtual
environments, there's multiple ways
of doing them.
You can use like the Python by default,
it has this VN of a
module, which you can use
to create virtual environments.
Then the UV that we also
mentioned that can do those.
Konda and Mamba can
create these environments.
And then there's this
package called Virtual N in PIP
that can do those.
And there's plenty more like this.
There's a list of non-exhaustive
list at the bottom of the
article or the lesson, if you
want to look at those.
But there's lots of different
tools that you can use to
create Virtual N ones.
But the main thing to capture
is that if you have a virtual environment,
you don't mess up other stuff.
If you have it there, it
doesn't spill out to other places.
It doesn't mess up your...
The lions won't eat the gazelles
if they are in the same enclosure.
And
You can have the specific things
that those animals or packages
need in that enclosure and environment.
And if somebody else wants
to create the same kind of
environment, you can just tell
them, hey, this is what I did.
Like this is the things needed
and they can create it as well.
So it's very important if you
want to share your code and
you want other people to use your code as well.
So there's a question about when
you have a conda environment and
if you do a pip install,
it'll be installed in that environment.
But if you do an apt-get
install, like a system level
installation, like on Ubuntu
system, it'll install on the system level.
So you said that it's
like operating system, but that
was just like a reference.
So the conda does not
create an operating system itself,
but it's even less than a container.
But if you install something system level,
and if you install the same
thing on the Conda, then
the Conda will override.
So don't try to, like if
you get into this rabbit hole
where you have to fix something,
you try so many things.
If you have a system level library
and a Conda library, and then
when you activate the Conda,
Conda became the prominent library.
yeah so basically what we want
to we want to when we have
some code we want to step into a realm
where that code works and
that's basically we don't want
to like think about okay what's
in the wider world like we
don't want to think about
the global python installations
or anything like that we want
to just have the stuff that we
need and that's what
the environments basically do like
we just put the stuff we
need and then we switch to that realm of
that place where we have
the packages uh that that our code needs
and and just those those packages
and like it used to be like
back in the day like 10
years ago or something that
whenever people were doing
their installations they were
using like installing system level
things and suddenly the operating system was
crashing because like the
operating system also depends on python
and if you change the
version python version or
whatever suddenly you you break
your computer and and suddenly
people realize that hey actually
it might be really nice if
we could do these separately so
we wouldn't like always have
to reinstall our computers when we
do a wrong installation so
that's why virtual environments exist
and this is same for all
sorts of programming languages this
is not a python specific thing like this is
Every language nowadays has its
own idea of virtual environments.
Zoom example, for example,
somebody asking whether it's only
for Conda, but it's also
relevant for Python environment that
you want to show us.
Both Python and Conda
environments, it's relevant example.
Go ahead.
Jone Peter Reistadler, yeah so
let's lots of talk, we have
done lots of talking less less coding
so let's actually like look
at something that can something that.
Jone Peter Reistadler, assembles
like an actual example.
Jone Peter Reistadler, So how
do you create these example
these environments so let's first
look at conda.
Jone Peter Reistadler, So in conda.
we highly recommend that you
create these environment.yamls.
So this basically is a
specification of what your thing
needs, what your environment needs.
And in this case, it's like
you give it a name,
You tell where do you want
the packages to come from.
So these are the so-called
channels of where the packages come from.
And then you specify what
sort of dependencies you want there.
And once you have this, you
can create your environment.
So let me try this out.
So do you want our learners to follow?
We have an exercise coming
where learners can do the same thing.
So I will create a
new file, environment.yaml here.
And I will copy this stuff here.
And then I will do conda env create.
And then the file name with
the dash if, and then the environment.yaml.
Well, that won't work because
there's no conda in this environment.
Well, that's fun.
Do we have Mambo?
No.
Okay.
Let's not do the conda example then.
Let's do the virtual environment
one so we can jump straight to the next one.
So if you want to do
a virtual environment with pip, you can
you can write stuff
into this requirements.txt.
So this is another standard
and it's like just the packages that you need.
And you write that, you create
a new file called requirements.txt.
So now this is a text
file and the earlier one is a YAML file.
So you saw some structure.
So if you have created here,
you can just write text.
But in the YAML, you need to maintain
that structure, mentioning the
channel, for example.
Yes.
And in the case of
virtual environments, I will have
to first create, like Conda
will create the environment
like for me, but in the
case of virtual environment, I
first have to create the environment.
And then whenever there's
these environments, we need to activate them.
So I have now here the virtual environment.
Could you explain the command a little bit?
You try Python and the dash
M for some modules and then... Yes.
So in this case, we are
using the module of VN and then
we tell it to create a
version of the environment.
So in Python, there's this...
self, like it provides this
module called venv.
And when we call it like
this, it will create a sub-virtual environment.
And what it has over here inside of it,
it's basically like a, like a mini Python,
mini operating system installation
that only has like, like
Python installed inside of it.
And when we run this
source, activate, bin activate from that.
So we run this, we, we run the script.
What happens is that we
activate this environment.
So we get into that environment.
We go into that environment.
So now it's active.
So basically our Python version
has changed and where the
packages come from has changed.
So you can see that
the version has changed.
So now I'm in that environment
and I'm in the world.
I'm in the liar's cage now, like over here.
So over here, I can do
the installations I want.
So I can run the pip install
dash R and the requirements txt.
to install the packages mentioned
in the requirements.txt.
Yeah.
So until that installs, [name],
so now you use the
requirement file, but you didn't do
like a pip install numpy.
By instance, you collected them
in a file and you're installing it.
So what are the advantage of doing that?
Yeah, and this is a
really great question, a really great point.
So why are we talking about these files?
Like, why can't we just install stuff here?
And the reason is that, like,
if somebody wants to
recreate this environment, like, you
need to have instructions on that.
And if you want to recreate it, like,
you do something and you
don't, like, later on remember what you did...
like if you haven't logged it anywhere,
you don't remember it and you
don't get the same result.
So that's why we always recommend
that you use these environment YAMLs
and requirement TXTs to log
down what versions you're using.
And it's not only for you,
but it's also for the tools as well.
So what these
tools do, like Gonda, what UV,
what PIP, all of these different tools do,
they have a solver inside of
it, and they try to, like,
figure out what packages to get.
Because, like I mentioned,
these packaging indexes have, like,
Not only do they have millions of packages,
but for each of those
packages, there can be hundreds
of different versions.
So if your code needs certain versions,
we'll talk about version
numbering and stuff a bit later.
But if you have certain
versions for the code, you need to...
you need to let Solver
decide what versions to install.
And if you give it
partial information, like if it
give the information that, hey,
like here's a package I want you to install.
And then later on you
say that, hey, install this package now.
Like it doesn't know about
the previous packages.
So it will try to do what
you asked it to do.
Like if you first say that,
hey, like paint this wall green.
And then next you say that,
hey, actually I want this...
this wall to be red and
these other walls to be red
as well, then suddenly everything is red.
so it's well that's a bad analogy
but but basically like if
you install one package and
you install then another package
that has a stricter requirement
suddenly it cannot like remove
the previous package and it
can like overwrite stuff yeah
here the the similar numpy
matplot and pandas the the
solver would check all these
three packages so it will install compatible
Three packages.
But if you start with NumPy,
it will not check that compatibility.
And when you're installing Matplotlib,
if the earlier NumPy is
not compatible, then it takes time.
And also, you know, there
might be conflicts.
And the UV tool that you mentioned earlier,
it has a faster solver,
isn't it, than regular people?
Yes, yes.
The UV has been written
with Rust, which is, again, like,
like testament to how extensible
Python is that like the solver
is written in Rust and it's
much faster and more compatible
than pip solver.
So that's why it's quite popular
and so it can do the installation faster.
But yeah, basically once we have done,
like we see now the
installation happening here and we
can see like what's been
downloaded, what's been installed.
And now we have our environment
and we can use something like
pip list to list what packages
we have in that environment.
So we have now this environment.
And let's say I want
to recreate this environment.
I can use the same requirements
txt to do it again.
So it's very easy to keep
track of what your program
needs while you're doing this.
And I think with this, it
would be good to have you try it out and create
quick environment yourself.
So we can have like a
small example or small test.
So for example, try with the VE-Env.
That should definitely work
if you're missing the conda like I did.
But if you have the conda,
you can try the conda version as well.
But try creating this
virtual environment and we'll be
back in five minutes.
So 35 minutes.
And then we will talk about
all of the complexities that
go into these environments like
versioning and stuff like that.
Okay.
So is that that we break
for five minutes for everybody to
try it out, right?
Yes.
Try out creating, let's say,
this virtual environment here.
Okay.
Hello.
Yeah, this was a short exercise break.
We didn't have that much time
and there's so much discussion
happening in the chat.
So it's good to address
all of the questions because like
this is a major question
for Python situations often.
So first off, I want to
clarify a few things about
the terminology in Konda ecosystem.
So first off, there is this
concept of a channel
in conda like and channel
is basically the place where we
get the stuff and there's
multiple of these like different
projects have their own channels
as well that provide like
extra packages and stuff but
but conda forge is the main
channel for open source places
and then there's this kind
of like anaconda channels
They are listed in the document over here.
So there's this package
repositories and these software
channels mentioned here.
So you can check on these,
but we highly recommend you use
the Conda Forge because it has
most of the stuff you need
and it's the open source alternative.
And then there's this lots
of like these different ways
of getting these tools
and then they often contain like
either the conda or the
mamba installers that you can
use to create the environments.
There was also a question about like,
can we have multiple
like environments loaded at the same time?
And this is not a good idea.
Like the idea behind an
environment is basically like you
have Python there, you have
whatever that your program needs
and that stuff.
And once you start to get
to this kind of like
if you try to like
merge stuff from different places
it breaks the idea of an
environment right like you want
everything you need in that one environment
if you have stuff coming
from outside it's basically like
you have a cage and the cage door is open
so is it really a cage
anymore like it doesn't anymore
like have the same effect that
it's supposed to have and that's
why we want to have a cage
and the lion's cage with a
tunnel yeah yeah basically and it's like
suddenly it doesn't serve
the purpose anymore that much.
But workflows, [name], like
some workflows in React scenarios,
you might need different versions
of package workflows.
So you could activate
and deactivate environment.
So next time when you're in
a terminal, you could also
show how to deactivate it.
So you could activate another
terminal if you have time later.
Yes.
For example, I usually have
maybe 20 different environments going
for all of the different
projects and tools I want to use.
It's so much easier to
have a separate environment.
than trying to figure out
one big environment that serves
all of the things I want to do.
And around this topic, we
could talk quickly about what
is the best practice of
working with environments?
So how do you add, for example, packages?
You create an environment, you notice
that I actually need to
import these packages as well.
How do you add it to the environment?
So if you want to create
problems in the long run for
yourself, you can just try to
install it into the environment
and then you forgot that you
installed it into the environment
and now your environment
YAML or requirements.txt no
longer represents what's in the environment.
So this is not usually a good idea.
And it also creates the
solver problems that we mentioned.
So the better solution is to
try to add it to the
environment, YAML, order requirements,
TXT, and then update your environment.
Try to do the installation again.
And often if you're like suddenly you...
You have a very, if you have a package
that has a very different needs
than the other already existing packages,
it can create all sorts
of like deadlocks in the solver side,
or you can see that,
okay, like something is being
removed and then something is
being installed and something like
weird is happening here.
And then you notice that,
okay, like maybe like at this
point you should like notice or
you should like be careful and notice that,
okay, like something, this new
addition to this thing suddenly
upended the whole thing completely.
So maybe it's a better
idea to just recreate the environment.
And that's usually the best approach.
Just like take the new
requirements TXT that you have
and just create a new environment out of it.
Because it usually doesn't take
as long to create a new
environment and try to fix
an environment that is getting broken.
So it's better to just
start afresh because it doesn't
take that long to install.
That's very good advice, [name].
Thank you.
And in addition to this,
what the command we see is
that we expect the environment.yaml
file to have the same
environmental name inside for this
update and also the same channels.
So let's say if you
have a different channel, it
might bring out different versions
because depending on the
channel, the default version might
change and it might actually
create more conflicts and rabbit holes.
If you follow your advice as
create a new one, if you
need it, that might save a lot of time.
Yes, yes.
So it's like, like, when the
lions are in already in the
cage, it's bad idea to
start renovating the cage.
Like, like, it's basically like
stuff can get wrong and the
lions can escape and stuff
can like, like trying to
fit out different, like, things
there like it doesn't necessarily go well.
So it's better idea to like
create a new cage and then
move the lions there and then
like, live with that situation.
Uh, but okay, so we talked
about like this version, like this, uh,
environments, but often like often
the best idea is to give a very wide, uh,
version ranges, because that means
that like, when you create
an environment, you of course
create the environment in that time.
When you create the environment,
it doesn't update automatically.
It doesn't magically keep up
to date of what the
ecosystem is moving forward.
So it's now something that
is actual realization of that
environment YAML or requirements TXT.
But as time moves onwards,
the packages upstream will change.
And that's usually a good thing
because you want new features
and you want your things to
be up to date with those things upstream.
Like you want your thing
to be installed with the
current versions that are there.
Can you show some details
of what you mentioned about
these versions in the slide?
Can you show some?
Yes, yes.
So sometimes you want to
lock down versions.
Maybe your code needs certain versions.
There was a question in
the chat about Python 2.
That's like a really old thing already.
But some codes still use Python 2.
So for those, it can be
quite difficult to get...
the versions installed.
In some cases, you might need
to use other tools like containers
and stuff like that to
make certain that you have
these really old environments installed.
But in many cases, you
might have a situation where
You want certain versions, maybe
a code is written with a
certain package and now the
package has updated their whole style.
So for example, NumPy updated
recently from version, well, not
that recently, but a few
years ago, they updated to version two.
And some codes, of course,
broke because of that.
So some codes only run on Python NumPy 1.
So then you might want
to specify something like this
in your package if you don't
have time to update your code
to work with version 2.
So, of course, the better, like,
if you want your code,
like, Rolling Stone gathers no moss, right?
Like, if you have your code
and you want it to be usable
in the future, the best option
is to update it when the future comes.
Like, when the package is
updated, it's to update your code.
But sometimes you don't have
the time or you want it to be, like, well...
want it to be working, but
you don't care about the
longevity of the project.
So then it might be a
better idea to lock it down to certain versions.
So here, [name], you have this,
for example, the Matplotlib, it
has three numbers, like 382.
So the major version and
like, you know, two as a patch version.
So do we have to be this specific?
And which of these numbers,
changing these numbers could break your code?
Yeah, so usually like these
numbers are called, this
is semantic versioning that
is usually followed by most people
or most projects, where the
first number is kind of a major number that
that is like major changes to the apis
and stuff like that the
second version is minor number
so that's often like new additions
but nothing will be deprecated
uh often sometimes there can
be deprecated functions as well
and the last one is like a patch number
that is like if something
if it doesn't matter at all
then the like patch number is
increased but but different projects
have a different versioning scheme
often uh but but in most
cases you don't have to like
put your version to be
this specific patch version or
something like that.
You can put stuff like this
as well that is compatible
with a certain version.
Then it can give you...
like versions that are higher
than like 2.1 but still
compatible with 2.1 so this is
a good idea because then it
gives the solver leeway on how
to solve the environment like
if there's another package that
requires a newer version and you
have an old you want like you
force it to be too strict then
you can like make the solver's
life hard for yourself hard for it
And you might get like
really old version of a software suddenly.
So it's usually a good
idea, like put requirements or
this kind of version locks when
you need them and when you want these.
when you want certain things
to be stable or working, but
only for those ones that can cause problems.
And usually like the version
locks start appearing later, like
the longer the time was
when the requirements.txt was created
to the time when, well,
you're now installing it.
Like the longer the time,
the more likely is that you
have to version lock something.
So here, [name], we have
mentioned the Python version as well.
So because we are
creating the environmental file
according to your advice in
the beginning, we might not
know all the versions.
But in this file, if you
mentioned 3.11 as Python and
NumPy as this version,
would it automatically, if we
don't mention the version of
Matplotlib, would the solver figure
out the Matplotlib version, or it
would try to install the
latest version and just break
everything before that?
Yeah, so it would try to find, like,
basically, like, what these do
under the hood.
There's, like, SAT solvers there,
so they basically, like, at
least UV and Mamba and Conda use those.
I think Peep uses a similar
kind of thing as well.
But basically, they, like, they...
create this kind of like a
huge list of like rules that
needs to be followed.
And then they try to figure
out a solution, like a proof
for that, that huge list of rules.
So if you have this
version, Matplotlib needs to be
higher than this.
And there are some versions
of Matplotlib that require numbers
that are like numpy two,
they require numpy two.
Then those are like out
of the question because like
this other rule suddenly forces it.
So it basically tries to find you the,
like the solution for this
kind of like multi-dimensional problem
of like these different conditions
that need to be satisfied.
And if you give it more leeway, like
if some package version doesn't matter,
it gives the solver more
leeway of finding possible solutions.
When you do these things,
the packages get installed and
we didn't mention anything about
where do they get placed,
but there's a question about how
do we place a package in a specific place?
For example, on HPC systems, for example,
we don't want to do that
on our home directory.
Sometimes it's limited when you
work on a shared computer.
Yes, I will address that just in a minute.
I will quickly mention that
if you are working with...
Like, if you want to
get the version numbers
for existing environments that you have,
you can, or what's in
your existing environment, you can
use these export functionalities to get those.
We don't have time to go through them,
unfortunately, but you can check
them over there.
And if you want to, like,
the best case or best place
to put these kind of, like,
requirements, if you have like a paper
or something, like you usually
want to have a requirements TXT that is
applicable for that paper.
So these were the versions that were used.
So in those cases, it makes
a lot of sense to lock down all of the versions.
But often, if you have the
code still being developed
after the publication has been
done, you want to have it
in a separate requirements.txt file.
So these are the exact
versions that you can use
to replicate the paper.
But then if you still
want to continue developing, then
you have another requirements.txt
or an environment that doesn't
have these lockdown versions.
But I will quickly address
the excellent point that [name] raised.
It was a question actually from
one of our very curious followers.
So thank you for that question.
I'm just going to transfer
the thanks to that person who asked it.
Yeah.
So that is exactly like a good question.
And you can, with virtual
environments, you can create them
all over the place, like where
you want to put them.
With Conda and with...
UV, they do things a bit differently.
So UV wants to like put
stuff into the current folder
where you're working on.
And then Conda has this
like central repository of a
central place where it puts
all of the environments.
So everything is in that environment place.
But what all of these tools do is that
they download a lot of files.
Like that's the thing.
Like whenever you do installation,
you can get like gigabytes
of files depending on what
sort of libraries you're using.
And the important thing is
that where those files end up.
And most of those end up
into your home folder by default.
Like all of these tools, they use...
home folder by default to cache
all of the downloaded files.
And then they unpack them
to different places.
And Gonda and UV try to
reuse the packages as much as possible.
So they create this kind
of like package cache where all
of the packages have been like unpacked.
And then every new environment
that you're going to create,
it's going to link, create a
shortcut to those packages so
that as little space is used as possible.
And usually you want this cache
to be in the same file
system as where your environment is
so that like it doesn't have
to go across the file
system boundary to another file system.
Might be too technical here, but
what you want to do is
like place the caches into
the same file system.
So if you're doing...
running stuff on the HPC system
or something, you want the caches
to be in the same file
system where your environment is
going to be eventually.
PIP doesn't do this.
So PIP just copies the files there.
So it uses a lot of extra space.
So yeah, you can put
those environments wherever you want
to place them, but they will
use a lot of space.
So you can...
quickly run into like quota issues.
And there's also the question
that like many of these tools, like
if you use Python,
like virtual environments, Oconda
or UV or whatever, they will
create a huge number of files usually.
So in an HPC system, you
might want to check your
like system administrators guides on
how to like maybe
containerize these environments.
So to put them into
yet more strict enclosures so that
you use less files to do that.
Unfortunately, we don't have time
to go through containers here.
But the environmental file you created,
you could also use it
to construct containers.
If people know what a Docker file is,
for example, container files, you
could use this same container
files to create it.
And the, I think we follow, we finished,
like, I mean, we went through
most of the basic concepts and
I think it's a good point
to discuss a little bit about
before we end some problems as well.
So when you install packages,
if there's an error, try to
read the error a little bit.
Sometimes you misspell it and packages
that you downloaded, they
downloaded the wheel file.
That means it will not be
compiled on your system.
But some packages, they might be compiled,
especially if you're on a unique system
and reading the error a
little bit closer or using
some large language model to
sort of help interpret the
error messages would help rather
than just trying the same thing
over and again and then
going through rabbit holes and
messing up things.
Start with the environment,
create a requirement file, as you said.
And if it fails, try to
read the error messages a little bit more.
And then you could even
delete those folders.
That's the advantage of
having environments.
Yes.
The advantage of having
environments is that if
something doesn't work, you can
try to recreate it from scratch.
And it's the same as restarting a computer.
It suddenly works better when
you restart it.
You don't know what it
solved, but something was solved
around the way.
And it's similar to
the environments that...
If something doesn't seem to work, like
if the environment doesn't seem
to install correctly or something,
and if you just do it
from scratch, it usually works better.
One thing I will also mention
that is like a super
annoying thing, that this is
legacy stuff from the really past.
Like I mentioned that it used to be
that people were breaking
their own computers for when
they were installing Python code.
Like using the system Python
and stuff like that.
So back then, the people were
using a lot of these pip
install dash dash user.
So they install, they would
install it for the user, like some package.
But this is a really
complicated, like really, like...
dangerous thing to do because
if you install some packages
with this pip install user those
are now your packages like like
those are the packages those
will overwrite whatever environment
you're using so those will
be always the first option
that python picks and and
this is super annoying because like
Like suddenly, like you
create an environment, you start your Python,
you try to do something,
stuff breaks and you don't know
what is the problem.
And later on, you realize that, okay,
I had like a conflicting
version of a package installed
in my home directory with
this pip install user, and it's usually hidden,
like those installed packages
are usually hidden so that
you don't immediately see those
packages and you have to go and look for them.
And then you notice that, hey, like,
here's a package that was
taken, like Python took this
package instead of the packages I
wanted it to use.
And like, there was this kind of like,
there was this lion with a
master key to all of the cages
and it was going and eating
all of the gazelles and it's like,
I didn't know that this
could even happen, but this happened.
So this is the kind of
situation you want to avoid.
So if you see instructions
of pip install user somewhere,
I would highly recommend thinking about it
and instead creating an
environment and using pip install
to install it into that environment.
Great advice.
I think [name] is getting ready
now as well for the outreach outro.
And also the home directory that you said,
especially if you want to
distribute your code, you might
not know exactly what to
send because there's something
always overriding.
And also in a shared system,
when you ask for support, you
don't ship your home directory
to your support staff.
So it will be difficult
to explain your problems.
So how are you feeling [name]?
Is everything good?
Yeah, this is super good.
I want to thank you so much [name]
and [name] for going again
through something that is fundamental
when it comes to reproducibility.
In the last three minutes that we have
for this course, I'm going
to cover a little bit of
output or outro, sorry.
So [name], since you're sharing the screen,
if you are able to browse
to the list, to the program,
kind of to the... Yes.
You know.
You mean the main page?
Maybe even there, there might be,
or I can give you the link.
This one.
It's in the program page.
Yeah, this one here.
So if you scroll to the
end of day three, there is this outro.
And in practice, I'm not going
to keep it long, but just
a reminder that you can get a credit.
for those of you who need credits.
So the description of what to
do is written in the webpage.
And if it's not clear, just
get in touch, really.
Maybe something that I want
to mention is that I think
all of the teachers that were
involved in this course are
actually involved with Code Refinery.
Code Refinery is an organization
that spans across multiple universities
and other type of research
organization in the Nordics.
And the Code Refinery workshop
runs twice a year and we
cover these type of topics
like you basically saw today at the end.
So reproducibility, opening your
code, open licensing and things like that.
So definitely that would be
the next step for those of you
We want to go deeper into
some of the topics that you've seen today.
But Code Refinery also
covers version control.
So the first week is all
related to Git and GitHub
and collaborating via Git and so on.
So that was about future events.
The next Code Refinery will
be around March.
We also run other open events.
For example, at Aalto, we
will have this intro to HPC
and it's designed so that even
if you are not at Aalto,
you can still learn something
about Slurm and things like that.
If you scroll a little bit
more down, see more on the outro page.
Yeah, how to stay in touch.
So we have both Scott
Refinery and other scientific computing.
We have mailing lists.
So if you want to be
added to those mailing lists, I guess
that if you register to
this course, there was a question
if you want to be added.
So if you click this, you
will receive more advertisement
for future courses.
Nothing else.
It's a very low, low traffic mailing list.
and you can also join us
and work together with us and
the barrier again is extremely slow
so that let's say that you find a typo
or you have an idea
to improve some examples or you
want to add a package that
we didn't cover during the course
or our lessons are stored on
github you can open an issue
to a specific topic or
start the conversation by getting
in touch with us
And we are one minute over time.
I can just mention that I
will now paste in the notes
document a Zoom link.
So we will have the
famous Zoom after party.
I don't know if people
are excited about Zoom after parties.
But anyway, if you want to
come to the Zoom after party,
some of the instructors will be
there and we can chit chat about the workshop.
The Zoom after party will
not be recorded or streamed or anything.
So it's a safe space.
All right.
Thank you again, [name] and [name]
and [name] and [name] and
[name] and all the others
that have been involved.
I guess we can close the stream
and let's keep in touch
and have a beautiful November and December.
See you.
Bye bye.