So today, our research software engineer at Jarno will demonstrate taking some code and extracting it out from another library and publishing it on PyPI, the Python Package Index.
So this is basically a common-ish thing we do.
It's also common to do most of the steps but not publish it, but it can be installed through a repository directly.
but anyway this is hopefully a quick demo of something that basically works so you can follow
the steps along later is that a correct introduction so that's what we'll be
doing and it's essentially all the steps in um creating an open source publication in python
except writing the actual code so I thought it's a pretty good example because
So it shows everything you need to know, except the stuff that I cannot know.
Should we get started?
I will share my screen.
Here we go.
Okay, that's the right desktop.
Okay, so I'm sharing my whole screen. So let me know if the font is too small. Can I even increase the font in this?
Oh, well. So I made a really rough plan and you can add questions and add things into the plan as we go, but it's not going to be visible most of the time.
the time. I will maybe take a quick look. But the first part is to quickly take a look at the code
that we already have and then from there decide what we're going to do. So I will go to the actual
Repository. Did you see my screen before this moment? No, now I first see it. Okay, so it took
a while to share it. I'll actually show the thing I told you I was showing because I guess you didn't
see it. So I mean it's not a very detailed plan but there's some notes here and we can add stuff
as I already explained quickly the plan I guess so actually
let's follow the plan and look so the first thing is a quick look at the code and then
what do we actually need to publish it so we can think through the steps and start a repository
and add what we need. So I'll use VS Code to open this folder and it opens on the wrong screen.
Here we are. And the file that was added, there are a lot of files here. This is a big project
that has a specific purpose. And the specific purpose importantly is not handling email and
and handling this big email inbox files.
So one thing we want to do with this project
is though to be able to open specifically email inbox files
that are exported from Google and do some processing,
create some sort of condensed view of email activity
activity from that file. And for that, we need to be able to read the email inbox. That's not
at all core functionality here in this project, but it is a useful thing you can do. There is
a Python package called email, which we're using, but there's some things that we need to do that
go beyond what email can do directly. So this is this small bit of code, this one single file that
does what we need. Some passing email addresses in a list. So this is a string that is a comma
separated list of email addresses. And we want the actual email address, not the name, for example,
that often is contained in the string. And this is just for opening and reading specifically the
Google's version of a mailbox file.
So there is a standard, but the standard is very open
and there's differences between inbox files.
So basically this one file is what you'd like to split out to another package
because it's useful alone.
So this is kind of generally possibly useful for others
and it is definitely not core functionality for this software
that we are looking at.
Okay, so to do that, what's the first thing, so we need to publish it somewhere, of course,
we need to put the code somewhere.
This is already on GitHub, this code.
So we're using GitHub.
So that it just the code itself will be public somewhere.
And we'll need a license and we'll need some documentation or at least a readme.
It's a very short, relatively small package.
readme is enough. What else do we need? We can of course see what comes to mind
as we go. Probably dependencies, right? Dependencies, all the project metadata.
Yes, citations.cff file. I think these are the most important part.
They didn't show it, but we do have tests for this email reader.
So we will include those in the repository.
Okay, well, let's go ahead and let's go to GitHub.
And for the recording, I hope I don't need to log in.
I don't.
And so this is the way I would now recommend actually starting.
So you go to whatever online thing you want to publish your code in and create a new repository.
rather than creating a repository on your laptop
and then pushing it to this online thing
because now you don't have to worry
about initializing an empty repository.
So what should we call it?
Because email is already a Python package
and this is more specific than that.
It's something like email utilities or...
Google take out email or something.
Well, whatever.
I guess this can be changed later until it's published.
Read around some utilities for the email inbox in.
Now I'm actually starting to think.
Google takeout so Google takeout comes as a zip file and we do read the zip file in the code but
not in this file that I'm thinking of exporting so this is for reading files directly or files
that have already been opened with zip file but it would actually be good a good idea to add the
ability to read the email directly from this Google takeout zip file but we're not doing it
now so it's missing a feature that I think is useful. Let's add a gitignore template for
Python. This is super useful if you don't have to worry about files. And already here it's asking
for or you can choose a license and I want to use the MIT license. I wrote the whole thing so
So it's not, I don't need to think that much about what the license is.
But let me still just quickly check what the license is in this original.
It is MIT.
So definitely taking something from published in MIT and publishing it as MIT is fine.
So let's go create a report story.
Okay.
So here we have a very small initial repository. I'll create a new
terminal and clone it. So this is the address. Here we are. And open it. So now
I will be copying a bunch of stuff from one place to another. So I'll have two
windows side-by-side. Start with the README. We have this little bit of
a comment text here that explains what this file does and since the file will
be the entire package. This is now essentially the contents of the readme file. Oh, I don't
actually want to edit the original repository here. Okay. And probably I want to take out
these underscores here and make it a proper title. Let's say this is enough for now. It
could contain examples of how to use it and it could tell you how to there's nothing specific
about installing it but how to run tests for example but that's also just pytest so
we'll get to that but let's say that the readme is enough for now now in this file itself I will
create a new file so this is a python package that only contains one file so you could still
create a new folder and create an init file and create the put the contents in
well you need a separate files or a single file the simplest way is to just create a file
a python file like this and now when you install this package this python file can be imported
directly okay so whoops I did not copy this so close that okay so we'll need two packages
email and regular expressions and I think neither one needs to be installed both of them are in the
so that would be you can find out from looking at requirements yeah so both
packages exist by our in the default Python installation so we don't actually have any
requirements any dependencies for this and then I'll just pick up the code from here
at least I think that it doesn't have any dependencies
but we'll see
there is at least one dependency that we will add in a moment
and that's pytest
but that's only for development
so that's the main package
now
what else do we need to do here
I guess let's go to the tests
Oh, let's actually first add the README commit to TurboStory.
Sorry?
Yeah.
Making the initial commit.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, there is an initial commit because it came from GitHub.
Yeah.
Okay.
So first you're committing the README update.
Yeah.
And then I'm, oh, it shows, interesting, okay, this is new for me, it's just incoming and
outgoing, so you can, I have changes that are not in the online repository, okay.
So Google take out email, and this is just the entire file, so, yeah.
And I guess you've made this entire file yourself, so there's no other licensing.
It is published as MIT, so that's not actually a concern here anyway, but I did write the
whole file myself.
I mean, of course, often that can be an important thing to check.
You need to ask all the authors before publishing stuff.
Okay.
so now we have
all the basics
we can import this
and we should probably check
that all of those imports are real
so that they are
actually in this
the base Python package
so to do that
what I will do, and you can do this in many ways
in fact there are probably these days
better ways that I haven't learned yet
I will use conda
to create a new
environment. Let's just use the name of the folder, activate it and what I will
need to install is pip because I want to install dependencies through pip. In the
end we will be publishing this on PyPy. So just to be sort of self-contained everything,
all the dependencies come from PyPy. PyPy is the tool for installing things from PyPy.
And PyPy is the Python package index. But we'll get to that. So now we have PyPy.
I'm on one hand assuming that most of these things are familiar to anyone using Python,
but on the other hand, it's always good to mention. So we are using the right pip. This
is something that you have to do with conda. You have to check that you actually have pip
in the conda environment. I don't have any dependencies listed, so I'm not going to use
pip to install anything. I will just run Python and try to import. Tab completion doesn't work
because I'm not using IPython. Okay. It seems to work.
So you're basically testing it interactively.
Yeah.
So can you...
mailbox reader actually started of course it's google take out email dot mailbox reader
and it's a class yeah and you would initialize it yeah so you need to give
it actually a file handle to a mailbox file or a string that is file name
test file doesn't exist so it will give me an error okay
Um, right. That's good. Then the next thing is that we need to create these tests. So
I get, I will put them in a separate folder, even though there is only one test file. So
tests. So in this original code, there is a folder called tests with a bunch of sub
folders. And here's the test email.
Uh-huh. And you are, so you already have the tests also.
Yes.
Okay.
That's good.
Screen new file, test, Google take out email.py.
Here we're importing OS.
So this config file, the NIMBY is the package that this comes from.
So this just tells where the test mailbox file is.
So we'll need to change that.
Yeah.
I guess you need to embed the test data.
So we need to also move the test data into the package.
This is a complication I didn't actually properly prepare for,
but we'll have something to refer to.
So the main thing I guess here is most of these things,
I don't know how to do by heart.
I will actually refer to something.
Okay, yeah.
Just like me.
Yes, that's the way you should be doing it.
Almost every time I make a new project,
I find a recent one that is similar
and copy it from myself.
So now if I directly import Google Takeout email,
that assumes that I have used pip
to install it on my system before I run the tests.
So another option would be to actually do,
well, you could go down a level and import it from there,
but I think this is common practice and it works.
It just requires that you have it actually,
pip installed this package.
Okay, so we actually do need a new folder called data
or test data.
Should it be in the test folder?
I guess that makes sense.
Kind of makes sense.
It's also easier to write out the path.
Yeah.
Oh, that's okay.
So I will simplify the name.
So this is actually the name of the mailbox file
in the Google takeout.
So, I will slightly simplify it.
So, we actually need OS.join.
Oh, we are using OS.join.
This is the function we are calling here is OS.join to get the path correctly.
So, the folder is testdata and the file is test.mbox.
Here, on the other hand, where is this test?
mailbox file here so this is this is a test file this is what a mailbox file
looks like there's the content of the body of the message and here's some
metadata fields like sender and who is it from who is it to when was it
received all of that yes it looks a lot like standard email stuff yeah and it's
just text. Okay, so now we have the mailbox file and we have the test. And it will try to read
from that file. Now we do need to install some a dependency, but this is a development dependency.
so I guess I will call it requirements-dev.txt. Just write down the dependencies. It is always
useful to write down all the dependencies anyway. So this is pytest. Here is a dependency and here
we find the terminal window. So we in fact should install pytest into this environment.
And whoops, pip install, pytest, not just pip pytest. Okay, here we are. And now I
think if I just run pytestings and things will not work because I haven't installed
this package. Right. I also cannot install it yet because I didn't make it a Python package
yet. So let's go there next. Actually, yeah, commit this stuff first. Okay, tests and test
data. Just push them already. Okay, so again, I guess, why not use this as reference? In
In fact, this is something I didn't write, I will tell you, because this is something
Richard wrote.
But I will not copy this directly because this is not actually quite exactly what we
want to do.
I will just use it as reference.
So to make a Python package, should we actually do it the modern way and not use setup.py,
but use a toml file?
Yeah, I can find... Do you have an example to copy from?
I have written those.
While you're looking, I can explain the background.
So what we saw in the old code was a setup.py file, which is probably many years old.
It's the old way of storing or of declaring package metadata.
data, it's executable Python code, which makes problems because you can't execute it until
you have stuff installed already.
The new method is a file called pyproject.toml, and it declaratively defines all the same
things you see as here.
So basically what you need, like, both declares what the build system is and the properties
of the project.
Okay. I'm unfortunately still looking. I guess I should just find the documentation
rather than an example.
I have a copy I can paste into the Zoom chat.
Okay. Thanks.
Okay. There.
That's the chat. Now it's open on my shared screen. Oh, okay. So I guess I'll directly
copy this and make changes. Yeah, it's made as a
Oh, it is an example. Okay. Yeah, it's from my own templates.
Okay, so we need to create a PI project dot tumble and I've made
spelling error here. Hi project, but that's correct. Okay, so let's just look through this.
So this is using flit to actually build the package.
Our module name, I guess we have now started using Google take out email, which is fine.
Is pip name the same?
So I guess I'm assuming this is what you, so you type pip install and this name.
So I prefer if it's the same, but people sometimes use a different name.
So this is what you import or is it?
And this is the name that you install.
will also be auto detected. But anyway, yeah. It's better. Okay. Okay. Authors. And you
can also give an email in there. But I've never done that. I generally do. But would
be an email field like oh it's okay this is I'll check giving my work email here
is not a problem because I'm already using it in the example or in the test
data yes so it is email just like that yeah read me.md so the way the pyproject file works
is it automatically get or the way flit works is it automatically gets most of the metadata
data from the repository itself.
Okay, so I guess we don't need most of these fields dependent.
So I wonder if it finds dependencies directly, but we
don't have dependencies. It's an empty list. Right now. We will
actually require zip file once I've changed it so that it can
open the zip file directly but i'm not doing that now so so right now it's 33 minutes past the hour
so maybe yeah okay so yeah we will not do that today I mean in any case the point is not to
write the code here the point is to publish the package yeah so this is we don't have a script
here so we'll just get rid of that part but here you could you could add a script that you can
execute directly from the terminal so that you don't have to import in Python. So that's a
useful thing to take a look at. Yeah, option dependencies test, and then a PyTest.
We don't have, well, we have a repository URL, I guess, not the separate documentation URL.
and the repository URL is
somewhere here
okay
here we are
did I close it?
Okay. That was the quickest way to find it.
Okay. So it's github.com, but this is not how it works.
It's name and then...
Yeah. Within...
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay. Then there's some information here of how to build it and how to push it.
Or how to publish it.
Yeah. That's...
We will need that in a moment.
But now, since we have this, we should be able to pip install dot.
The dot is this folder.
Okay, that did not work.
No docstring.
Can you go down?
I thought I saw.
Please add a docstring to the module.
So it automatically gets something from the module.
Okay.
Okay, so I guess copy the same thing from before.
Okay, so this is the module.
Yeah, it needs a docstring.
It needs a docstring, and I guess it should be on top of the file.
Probably, I guess.
If it's automatically detecting it, then I'm assuming it needs to be in a standard place.
Let's try this way.
no
need version
so
so version is not defined anywhere
right now
and it should be defined
somewhere so is there a place
it should be defined in the module
itself so in google.txt
email.py
so it needs to be
version
so we define a variable directly
in this
and we will call it 0.0.1
Yeah, like I usually do
Okay, so now we have it installed
Great
I guess we can point out that where we are now
this is even useful if you never publish it to PyPI
so you have something which is now self-contained
and you can install it yourself
and you can install it from GitHub
which makes it easier to use things across different projects
without setting Python paths and so on.
So just, there is one more, one small step before that.
So add .string and version to the module.
So, I mean, we need to push it to GitHub
before we can install it from GitHub, but yeah.
okay so now we have synced changes now everything's in on github and now in yeah in
principle we could instead of pip install dot we could write the repository url here
I think it's git plus the url with https yes and then it will install it from the repository so
So you don't actually need to put it on PyPy
to install it from a remote.
And really most of the time,
I don't, if it's just for me
or I don't expect it to have a big audience.
Yeah.
So I guess in this case,
I don't really expect it to have a huge audience,
but still, why not?
Like pushing stuff to PyPy is also not a big step.
It might be useful,
but it's true also
often I would not do this next step
unless I want someone to be able to conveniently install the package
without having to type in a long URL
or copy it from somewhere
so that is the main purpose of PyPy
the package index
you can just type pip install package name
and you get the package
yeah
okay
so I have actually not
used flit before but
your
yeah
this template had
instructions
on how to do it
we could even open
the
and actually with pyproject.toml
I've hardly ever used
flit directly no oh okay I basically always installed it and it's happened in the background
and the uploading I haven't done that much yeah okay if you don't upload then you don't need to
run flit yeah okay so but in order to build it do we actually need to install flit
I suppose we do because I cannot just run it from here yeah if you
I could use apt to install it.
Or it's probably available from pip.
Yeah, I mean, I guess it must be in flip or in pip.
It's not a built-in library.
But neither is twine, which is the previous option
for pushing to PyPi.
So this is just not a thing that's built into Python
itself.
You need to install it separately.
But now we have it.
so we can it tells us conveniently what we can do with it so we can flip build
okay oh it doesn't so the url I wrote here doesn't start with https or http
so it's not an actual url yeah oh that should be better oh https let's try again
Okay, so now Fleet agrees with me and everything is fine.
So it actually checks the metadata in this TOML file, which is great.
So it just checks that you didn't make weird spelling mistakes and things make sense.
Okay, so what do we have now?
We have this dist folder in our project, and this folder contains, essentially, in this case, a wheel file, which is the way you install Python packages, and then a TART version of basically the Python code.
Because we only have Python code, we are not actually building any C code or anything.
This is relatively straightforward.
So this will work with any Python tree, basically.
Okay, I didn't actually, yeah, I didn't require any specific Python version here, but it actually does only work with Python tree, I think.
Okay, but yeah, so now we have a built version of it.
And we can push that, publish that on PyPy.
so this command will push it to test
PyPy. Most likely this will fail because I'm not
logged in. Okay so it's looking
for how to log in
and there is no
test PyPy logging information. So now I have
to remind myself how to do this.
Okay, so this there should be a pi pi RC file that stores your username and password.
Although it didn't ask me, so I guess I have that file.
Maybe I should check for that file without showing you the username and password I have.
Oh, but I don't have one.
Okay, so I'm slightly confused about why it's failing instead of just asking me for the
username and password.
I can, whoops, I don't want to click that one.
So I can set a username and password here.
Can you give it the URL on the command line
instead of the test PI instead of the name?
So the full URL to the, to test PiPi.
Okay, so it's here.
Oh, actually, here's an example of the PiPi RC.
so it should give you
you should
add your username and
the URL there
and
I've somehow always
remembered it prompting me
directly so
okay so it does want
the
it will prompt you for a password
in any case but
you I guess you need to
create a PyPyRC
file
and it needs to list all possible servers
then it needs to define
the username defined here is of course not my username
so I will quickly check it on the other screen
also copying the password in case so the username is what I often use it's my
github username as well. So it's not exactly private information. Test PyPi
directly. I didn't want to copy this because I had already copied the
password to PyPi but fine. Okay.
I'm not used to how vim works because I've been using code for a while.
Okay let's save it.
So now it knows where testpypy is and also where no more pypy is.
And we should be able to call it this way.
And now it asks for the password.
I'm not sure that I have a password for TestPyPy, let's see if this, no, this doesn't work.
Username password authentication is no longer supported.
Migrate to API tokens.
Maybe we can stop here and leave it as like, okay, so you would be here.
You could upload it to PyPy following different things.
You've made the package yourself.
Yeah.
And I do this rarely enough that I always have to check.
But I kind of did want to show it until the end
or to get the package on PyPy,
although that's not the most important part.
so here's instructions
on uploading packages
from PyPy itself
and this is what we should
follow to actually
get it to work
or Flit
probably has updated instructions
but these instructions
don't seem to work
so to figure that part out
will take a bit more although I think
actually doing it with
just uploading with wine is just one command
if we can figure out how the API keys work
but before we go there
there was a change in the
PyProject. So fix URL in pyproject.toml.
We are running out of time when we did all the important parts.
So I guess one more important thing is to take a look at the repository again on GitHub.
to my repositories or okay let's look for it so no oh come on
Okay, here we are. So here is my new package. And yeah, this
contains everything we need to install the package and to run
the tests. So I guess we didn't quite do that yet. Okay, so we
can run the tests. So yeah, they don't quite work, which is
understandable.
so I mean i'm wondering should we summarize now there's a lot more debugging to do but we've got
10 minutes so let's not forget the main like or what someone would be most interested in
so here we did the license documentation dependencies this is all somehow linked
through both in the repository and also declared in the pyproject.toml file
citations you want to comment on the citations some okay we didn't create a citations file yet
so this is a way especially so and also this is maybe not this is more of a utility project
but if someone uses your code specifically to, I mean to in some scientific publication for
example they should be able to cite your code right because it is a it is a scientific output
kind of like a paper.
So the citation.cff file
tells how you cite a project.
I can show an example of one
relatively quickly.
So this would be...
Now I find the rest of RepoStories.
Somehow I didn't previously find it.
Did we move it?
Okay, sorry.
How did I? Okay. How did I not find it? Right. So here's an example of a citation.cff file.
This is also a Python project. And it lists essentially a message, please cite this software
below and then lists the authors and you can add a DOI which you have from Zenodo
and a URL to the publication the software and importantly you can also cite things here so
if you if you use something if you use a scientific publication or software that you can cite
you can then list them below in this file.
And there's tools for tracking citations using this, including in GitHub itself.
So that's just useful for you, of course, to track citations to your project,
but also it's important for others when they use your code for doing some science.
they can then actually cite your work.
It kind of allows them to use it in a scientific publication.
Okay, so we didn't quite get it on PyPI, but that only makes it slightly easier to install.
So do you want to demonstrate installing from GitHub with the URL?
Yeah.
And maybe that's a good ending point.
I actually just thought about something.
We didn't quite add the data file into the package yet,
and that is why the tests are not working.
So adding a data file to the package is something that you sometimes need to do, but most of the time not, and that's a separate issue.
So this is a Google takeout email.
So what I'm looking for is the correct URL to the repository.
And now we can install it from pip, using install it with pip.
So pip install as usual.
And then we say git plus and then the HTTPS address.
I often make a mistake here, but I think this is correct.
Let's see.
Looks good.
Okay, so it clones.
Okay, so yeah.
So it first clones the Git repository.
Okay, it says cloning.
and then it does some filtering of the branches
and also it doesn't want all of the data
but the important thing that is
it's getting the repository from online
and then it's following as usual
to installing dependencies
getting requirements to building a wheel file
and then installing it and getting metadata
so this is exactly the same thing that happens
if you install from PyPy
so if you type pip install numpy
it just gets
the file from a different location
and you have to specify the full URL
here too so that it knows
the location
okay well
is there anything
else to comment before we go
it would be nice to
get it to
PyPy and to get the data stuff to work
but that would have taken more than an hour
so
So, I mean, we focused on the important part.
We can have the, people can look at the repo later
for the full thing.
Yeah.
So I have shown the URL, but let's actually
copy the URL here.
And this is basically, like basically this is not that hard.
So if you-
Yeah, that's the main thing.
the code yourself you can easily find a pyproject.toml file copy it make it semi-installable
and add stuff later and I really do this for most of my projects these days yeah so for license we
just selected it when creating the repository and there's some differences but it's they're
not huge, anyway. Well, read me a documentation is a part that
you have to write yourself, but it is only it is a description
of the project of you just describe what you're doing. Some
examples are nice, of course. Listing dependencies is maybe
the well, it's something you should do anyway, because it is
very useful but it is kind of also the thing that that is non-trivial here
then citations which I showed so you can copy a template again from anywhere
and tests are in their python functions so there's nothing that nothing especially
intimidating here and it only took us an hour to do the main steps maybe in another 10 minutes
or so we could add the data file to correct place and in another 10 minutes or so we could figure
out how pi pi has changed so that the fleet no longer works as instructed but yeah that stuff
happened so okay yeah so that those are the important parts yeah well thanks for watching and
yeah thanks for watching thanks we'll update the repository and video description with
anything that's been missing okay with that bye bye
hello so we are back uh later in the afternoon and we will finish the demo now that we've figured
it out it wasn't that hard anyway Jarno so now we will try to complete the publishing to test
pi pi yeah so there were two issues one was the data file and the other one was that uh publishing
didn't work as it seemed from the documentation. So I figured both things out. So for the data
file, we don't actually need to have it in the package because we will only use it for testing.
And when you're running the tests, you will clone to repository. So we will just have the data file
in the repository. The problem was that this is not the correct path depending on where you're
running the test from. This is not the path to the data file if you're running it from the
main folder of the repository. But we'll make it even better than that
because we can get the full path to the test folder. So I just copied this from my notes,
but I will quickly explain. So this file means, well, this current file, the file containing these
test functions. We take the absolute path to it, and then we take the directory name of that,
which gives us the full path to the folder where the tests are. And then we just join it here in
the beginning. So now we have the directory where the tests are, and from there we go to
test data folder, and there we take the mailbox file. So yeah, a little bit complicated, but
we always get the correct file, no matter where we are in the file system.
And that, in fact, did work the last time I tried. So the tests run correctly now. I run
pytest, and there's three tests that it runs, and they all work. So that's one thing.
the other one is then publishing it so right okay so that is a example of what the
pi pi rc file should look like so what uh what I needed to do is go to the
pi pi.org and test.pi.org separately and for both of them create a an api token
and then authentication happens
so that the password is the token that you generate
and the username is underscore token.
So it looks similar to before,
but really what you need is this authentication token.
I'm not 100% sure what the purpose of the change is,
but it is more secure with the token.
it just, you could change the structure of the file to make it clearer. But in any case, this
is what it looks like. So let's just close that example. That was of course an example because
I'm not showing my actual token here. So otherwise there's no change and we can go to the terminal
and run
flit publish
so in fact
let's find the
yes
so flit publish repository test
pi pi
oh great
a new one
so flit wants you to
have everything tracked with git so there's no risk of unintended stuff being published
okay so what is it what is it saying it's not tracked the bottom one can you do git status
maybe okay oh it is actually complaining probably about this example file that I created this pi
so this is not the real pi pi rc file this is the example I just showed you so let's just remove it
Okay, so now it works.
So we already ran flit build.
So I will come back to that error in a second.
We already ran flit build, everything's fine.
And then you run flit publish.
It is now complaining because the file already exists.
I have already uploaded it.
I can probably get around this and demonstrate this by updating the version number.
So let's do flit build, okay, fine, flit build, publish, okay.
And now to publish in actual PyPy, you just remove this part.
So just flit publish, and it goes to the actual Python package index.
Here we go.
Okay.
And now that it's in the actual Python package index, you can install it with...
So pip install package name, and it worked.
So now we upgraded from, oh, already satisfied point also.
So yeah, I didn't ask it to upgrade, it just, it is already installed.
Yeah.
All right.
So that is everything.
Now the project does have its own page on PyPy if you want to take a look.
This is maybe the last interesting thing to demonstrate.
So all of this information comes from the toml file and readme.
So it found the readme in the repository.
And in the TAMO file, it has the URL to the GitHub page.
Well, this is my PyPy account, but authors are listed here.
License is here.
So it found the license file and so on.
So yeah, it's relatively smart.
It found a lot of things just from the files in the project.
But yeah, so there it is.
People can now install this package and use it.
Yeah, and I guess all our other talking was done before, so thanks a lot.
Yeah.
Thanks.
Bye.