CodeRefinery.org
you
I
example online, and then it's going to have it as,
oh, this works very nicely.
This works.
So what we see here on the right side is all the code.
And on the left side,
we see exactly when each line of code was last edited.
So this is a file that has been opened,
one file in this repository called NetworkX.
Yeah, I mean, what you see in the code
doesn't matter right now.
So this is just an example.
We're gonna go into more depth
for all of these things later on.
Who's ever wanted to send someone a bit of code
so they can see it, but it's annoying to attach it
an email and tell them where to look or copy and paste. With GitHub, we can do things like paste a
link that highlights a certain bit of code. How do we use Git? What do we use it for?
So, obviously, there's code and software. There's other scripts. There's documents.
For example, if you're writing paper in LaTeX, it works really well there.
but even other files that aren't plain text files you can in theory track with
version control. Configuration file, website sources, this lesson itself
that you're reading now is itself tracked in version control so you could
say that the whole workshop is a lesson in how to use the teaching tools in the
workshop if you want to be recursive about it.
One question.
So what would be the advantage of actually using version
control like it instead of using different zip
files which are dated?
Yeah.
So yeah, you could always go and make a backup copy manually
like this where you basically, well,
are archiving different things. But with all these archives, you can go back to a certain time.
But what if you want to see what the differences are? That's sort of hard.
What if you want to compare over time? What if you want to see what's in each of these?
What if you want to search for a certain change you've made, and so on? That's more difficult.
So this is better than nothing, but compared to being able to run one command and save all your work in the same place, it's not quite so convenient.
Yeah, and one thing I would add, if you actually have a project which is quite large in size, you don't want to make all these different copies of your project.
project, Git actually is going to save only one version of one change to a file.
So it's going to keep, so it's going to ensure that your tracked project is actually lighting
size.
Yeah.
So one big advantage, especially for big projects.
this provides nothing with the branching and merging
and things like that.
If I send someone a zip archive and they work on it,
now I have two zip archives and that's a bigger problem.
So, yeah.
But we know that not everything is perfect.
So there are difficulties.
And the point of our lesson here
is to try to make it easier.
So it's another thing to learn,
but I think everyone here would agree
that it's well worth the time spent to learn it, especially if you want to do anything
else in your career with code and so on. It's better to learn quickly.
If you have collaborators that don't want to use version control, well,
I'm sorry, but that is a pretty common thing. When I was doing my academic work,
it was always hard to find someone that wanted to take the time to do it. But, I mean, if you
help them, maybe they will begin working. I've often done a thing where I've had version control
of a manuscript, and I would send my advisor a copy by email, but I would track locally
what version they last got so I can merge it myself on my end.
And this last point here about advanced things being difficult is definitely a bit of a problem
somehow. But I think that our philosophy here is that the basic things should be easy and don't
worry about the advanced things. Even if you use Git in the most basic way, it will save you time
compared to other things and you don't need to worry about advanced stuff. So we are really
trying to make this a user-friendly and practical starting course. And to be honest, when you need
to do something advanced and you don't know, you can ask someone else or learn it when you need to.
There's no need for everyone to know everything. Yeah, exactly. I think, I mean, Git is so beneficial
if you just, even if you use it in a very basic way. So you don't have to know all the commands.
I don't know all the commands. You can just take it slow, learn to do some things, and then you'll
grow from there. So there is no need to learn everything from the beginning. Yeah, yeah.
And there are other things besides Git for version control, but we focus on Git because
it's the most popular one, which means that it's in the most places already. And, well,
in the end, teaching the more common thing is more useful because that's what you're
more likely to use. We want to be practical and not pedantic. But it does have some good features,
like the distributed nature, although it's not the only one that's distributed now.
So, with that being said, should we check the notes and see if there's any questions?
Yes.
There should have been a motivation section here.
Most of these... Is there a limit to the size of files and documents? No, not really.
Really, I mean, there's only the practical limit
of how big of stuff you want to control.
Yeah, maybe.
So one good point is that if you have the repository
on your laptop, then it's not really a size limit.
But if you put things on a different platform,
like on GitHub or GitLab or anywhere else,
there may be a limit for private repository.
private repository, so that is something that you may want to consider. There is no limit as I know
for public ones, but if you are not ready to share it with the world yet, then there may be some
limits there. And there is actually one link in the answer there, so you may check. And this also,
so this limit actually changes over time. So I think, well, one is more and more,
I mean, this usually goes higher and higher over time, so.
Yeah.
Storage.
There's a really good question here, number nine.
Can I use Git for Word and PowerPoint?
So it's, I wouldn't even,
it's designed for code and text files,
but you can store any kind of files in there.
So Git would look at the Word and PowerPoint things
as just binary documents.
And you don't get things like the differences
and merging to look so good.
But I've done this before,
when I've worked with people who want to write a paper
and they're only using Word,
I have my own private repository where I'm tracking things.
And you can also use extensions that let you
show differences between versions and things like that.
So the difference between GitHub and GitLab, I think that's probably being answered there
and we'll answer it later.
So maybe we should go on.
Yeah, so I think everyone wants to know how they actually get to work with Git.
So maybe I'm going to get the screen share from you and let's look further into a repository.
And we are going to start with a repository on GitHub.
So I hope you can all see my screen here.
So you'll find this lesson.
So we are going to continue with modifying an existing project.
And I'm going to now zoom this in.
And the very first thing is copy and browse an existing project.
And as I said, we are going to look at something which is stored on GitHub.
And what we will be doing is to make a copy of an existing one that we have prepared for
you.
And in GitHub terms, when I say making a copy, what I mean is making a so-called fork of
is a repository.
And the one note here, so usually
when we refer to a repository, so a copy of our project
on a cloud platform like GitHub, we usually
refer to it as a remote.
So if you see remote, then think of it
as a repository in the cloud.
So what we're doing now, are we looking at GitHub
to see something that exists,
and we make our own copy, which is the fork.
Exactly.
And we will share exactly which repository we look at.
And throughout these lessons on Git,
there'll be different ways that you can follow this along.
Some parts can only be done on GitHub,
but other times you can do this via the command line
or using other IDEs like VS Code or other IDEs
which have Git integrated.
But what we'll do in this first lesson
is to show you how you can do it on GitHub.
And throughout the lesson, I'll let you know
if other options are actually more suitable
for the things that we do.
But again, now we'll be focusing on GitHub.
So the first thing we will do is to create a copy
of an existing repository.
So create a fork of this repository.
And so think of, again, I mean,
as there is a repository as copies,
different copies taken at different times of our project.
And the project we will be working with
is called Recipe Book.
And it's under a GitHub user organization,
which is called cr-workshop-exercises on GitHub.
And so what we'll do by forking
is to make another copy of this repository.
So with all of these different commits and branches
that it may have, but not residing in this user space,
but in our own user space.
And so we'll copy this under our own repository.
organization, or what user space on GitHub.
So which is the repository that we are going to copy
or fork?
So it's this one here.
So github.comcrworkshopexerciserecipe.book.
So you may just open this in a browser
And for the sake of, so I will be working with this repository instead,
which at this point is identical with Recipebook.
And the reason is because, well, I don't want some other usernames to show up
as we are now streaming this.
But no worries, these two repositories are identical at this point.
point. So, I am going to open this in a new tab and go to that tab. It's a bit tricky.
Yes. So, I have CR Workshop Exercises Resume Book recorded, and I'm going to just check a
little bit what this repository is all about. So, I will just decrease the font size a bit
so that you see that this looks a little bit,
I mean, being zoomed out,
you lose some of the information that is on the page.
But basically, we have a content of the repository.
So all the files and directories that we are tracking with Git.
Then we have some information about the repository.
By default, GitHub is actually going to
show the content of the readme file and it's usually nice to have a readme file for your
repository so that people know oh what is this all about. So this is just a repository that
tracks different recipes and it's categorized, well they are all stored into different
directories and I can see that if I go to these different directories then I may
find different files. So what we are going to do now is actually not to work in this
repository. And why wouldn't I want to work on this repository?
Yeah, so this reminds me, what you're showing here seems like something I do quite often. So
there's some new project, new code, and I want to see, okay, do I want to use this person's project
in my own work. So I go there, and first I'll browse it and see what's in there,
and then I decide, yes, okay, I want to try using this myself, and maybe I want to modify it.
But I guess I can't modify someone else's work on GitHub, so I make my own copy.
Yeah, exactly.
And that's what is going to happen here.
So, what we are going to do is to fork this repository, so make our own copy of this repository.
And actually GitHub is very smart in showing what different tabs do, if you just hover
over with the mouse over them.
So I'm going to click on this fork.
So I click on fork, and again, I mean, you should not use this recipe book recorded,
you should use the recipe book. So then I am prompted to choosing an owner. So under which
user space do I want to have this copy of the repository? And I'm going to choose mine.
Oh, okay. First, I'm going to, let's see, rename this because I already have
a copy of this repository. I'm going to call it 25. And so let's choose... Oh, I cannot fork
twice. Okay, maybe I should remove my other fork.
So bear with me. So what I'm going to do, I'm going to delete my other fork.
So basically what happens is when you were practicing, you've already made a copy.
Exactly.
And that's, I wanted to do that because I, um, you know, I, uh, pushed something.
So then you know how to actually move.
I'm going to click on, uh, settings, no, this is a bit, uh, these settings and, uh, somewhere
here there should be a danger zone and then I'm going to click delete this repository and you
should be certain this is what you want to do because there is no going back and then
so this is a bit more advanced than
than we intended at this step
You really need to be sure you want to remove repositories.
So yes. So sorry for this.
Then let's go back to this original repository.
Sorry for this. I have. So yes.
So now I'm going to fork this from CR workshop exercises,
and I have the owner selected,
a repository name, which I may keep the same
or I may change.
And then the description is taken
from the original repository.
And I'm going to keep that, I think it's a good one.
And then I'm going to deselect this.
And the reason why I do this,
because I want to copy all the branches
that this repository had.
And then click on creating work.
So what happens is I'm going to have this recipe book
in my, under my GitHub username,
and then it looks exactly the same.
I even get an information that this is a repository
which has been forked from another one,
but the content is exactly the same.
The advantage is that I actually have control
over this repository, I can change this as I want,
do any modifications I may wish and share them back
as we'll see later, so.
Yeah, and this is possible because it's on GitHub
and because it's public.
Could I do this with a private repository?
So you cannot do this with a private repository
unless you have permission to fork from that one.
fork from that one. So you have to be, you may need to be added actually as a member to that
repository before being able to fork. Yeah, yeah. So you still have the permission
things going on here. Okay. Yeah. Okay. Okay then. So by the way, I'd like to say
there's a emergency update of the notes document so it's offline right now I've
been watching this in another chat so don't don't panic if you can't ask
questions right now but hopefully we will be back in five or ten minutes
yeah so then so now that we have our fork what we are going to do is to
investigate this repository that we have forked.
And one thing before we do that,
so this copy,
so no, this repository that we have copied from,
we usually call it the upstream repository.
So it's just another fancy name,
GitHub term for, or a Git term actually,
for repositories that we have copied from, so upstream.
And then, so the exercise that we'll be doing in the following is to browse through this fork that
we have copied, investigate the commit history, check, I mean, how we can find different terms
in different files, check, I mean,
who has modified what in this repository.
And we are going to do this for 20 minutes, I think.
20 minutes and hopefully the collaborative document
is going to be back online fast
so that you can get to ask us questions.
So, is it also time for a break? Should we say maybe break plus exercise time? And then…
Yes. So, let's say that. So, break and exercise until 15 past? Or no, that's a bit short.
Until 20 past.
20. So that's 10 minutes break and 15 minutes exercise. I guess we can start with that.
Ah, but the notes is working again. Okay, great. It works. Okay, cool.
If at any point you don't know what to do, please ask us in a collaborative document.
And yeah, hopefully you will enjoy this first exercise.
Yeah. Okay, so we sent the notes and you can read further instructions there. See you in
a little bit. Bye.
you
I'm sure it has been a bit tricky, especially for those of you that are new to the GitHub
interface, but I was thinking that actually in the following minutes I'm going to walk you through
the solution. And so I am now in this repository again that I have forked,
the recipe book recorded, and you are working with the recipe book one. That's okay. So the
first thing that you were asked to do is to browse the commit history. So then one way to browse
the history is to, well, simply look at the, looks a bit different, look at the commit. So I'm going
to make this a bit larger. So here I have, for example, the latest commit that has been
done by Rust. And [name], I have lost the commits. Where were they? It was supposed to be
somewhere here. So... The history, could it be the clock icon? Yes, sorry. It's because whenever I
I have the window smaller than it just doesn't show everything.
So I have the latest commit,
which was done seven months back.
Then clicking on this clock,
then I can actually go and see not only the latest one,
but all the commits that have been done for this repository.
Let me scroll this back.
So then if you remember from the motivation part,
So I see the commit message,
so this is actually what is shown in bold here,
the time of the commit and the committer,
and also a hash,
and actually it's only part of the hash that each command has.
So it's like a unique identifiable for a commit,
which is, think of it like a snapshot
of the state of the repository at that particular time, so September 1st, and then I can see the
whole history from the latest, the first commits. I can also change the branch, so there are different
branches for this particular repository. There is a lasagna branch, which again, I mean, has
its own history of commits. So this is one way of looking at the history. There is another feature
that GitHub has in order to see the history of a repository. If you go here, so the top menu,
and then click on insights, and then network, then there is a graphical visualization of the
repository. So we have forked the repository, so today, 25th of March. So this whole history of
commits is actually the one that has been on the original upstream repository, so the one we forked
from. And then there are some new commits that I have introduced and we'll talk about them
in the next episode. But so all these lines, so the black one with the different circles,
it's like one line of commits, one branch in this repository. And time is going, so from left to
right is increasing time and then there is another branch here shown in blue,
a branch which is called Alex Fruit Salad which has a couple of commits.
So it's a branch which has been formed at some point in time and then it got merged back
in, unfortunately it doesn't say the time, I think I have to zoom in a bit,
but we'll show you exactly how you can actually form these branches and then
merge them together in the main one. So that's another way of looking at the history.
So how can I actually find out when a recipe was last modified? So I go back to code
and let's pick up one recipe.
So I go into one of the directories.
Let's see this vegetarian lasagna.
So then, sorry, let's get back.
So I see that this particular file has been last modified.
So on the last commit date, sometime last year,
if I do open it and I can also get a hash
of the commit. So it has been modified by [name] which will tell you all about
collaborative git the third day. So and then, well, these are the contents. I can see the history
which will tell me all the different commits that actually modify this file. So it's not only the
the one on the fifth, it's not only this commit, but there has been some other changes before.
So let's quickly see the guacamole recipe. So I go back to the,
so I go back to code. So let's see, I actually do not know where the guacamole recipe is. Then
And I can click on this button, go to file, and start typing guacamole.
And then GitHub is going to search for this repository and open this file for
that, well, in this case, it's the guacamole MD file.
So what we were to do here is to see how many changes this file had.
And then again, as for the previous one, I'm going to click this history button and I see
there are several different commits by different committers.
So both [name] and Jamie Garcia [<- this as a fake name for artificial data] that has committed to, that has introduced changes to this guacamole
recipe and committed it.
So step number five, which recipes include the ingredient salt?
So of course, if you don't...
Many people had problems with this indexing thing.
Yes, exactly.
So there is a search button at the very top, towards the right of the page.
So if you one-click that button,
then I can search actually in many different repositories.
By default, GitHub is going to suggest
that I search within this particular repository,
but I can search through the entire GitHub,
but by default, again, it's this particular one.
And then I'm instructed to search for recipes
that include ingredient salt.
So this is, so GitHub actually needs to index the repository
before it can actually search for it.
So the very first time you do the search,
it might take a couple of minutes.
So as it does have to index this repository.
So if I look for search,
I see that actually there are many recipes
that include this term.
So in salads mixed and sides and so on.
So that is one way to search the contents of the files.
So if you remember before,
clicking that button go to,
clicking the button go to file,
which sometimes actually shows like a search button.
It doesn't check the content,
but it actually checks the name of the files
which match a certain syntax.
So it is different.
So, number six, again, we are going to go to the guacamole recipe, which I remember
now it is in Sides, Guacamole.
So let's say that I want actually to know who has edited this file.
So we remember that if we check the history,
then we got the name of the committers for this file
and when they have committed.
But let's say that I actually want to know
which changes they have introduced.
So one way of doing that is by clicking on this name,
sorry, on this tab called blame.
And this comes from the git blame command,
which is actually similar to the git annotate command.
So what it actually does is to break this GuacamoleMD file
into different lines and showing which lines have
been modified by whom.
So the top of the file has been changed by [name].
And then it also what says when.
And then again, I mean, there are different changes which
have been introduced at different times.
So it's going to show by default. So
when a certain line or a group of lines
have been modified last.
OK, then.
So can you actually use these recipes yourself?
And this is something that we'll talk a lot about next week.
So licensing.
What can you actually do with a repository
that you have formed?
So the important thing is to look at the license
and you can see this either
on the right part of the repository
or you can also find it close to the readme file.
So if the repository has a license file,
which is recommended,
then you can check what you are allowed to do
with a repository. What changes can you do and how you can share them. So I'm going to click on the
license file and let's say that I actually don't know what this Creative Commons license actually
means. So GitHub does provide a very nice summary if you open the license file. So this is a,
so the Creative Commons 0 is a very permissive license. You can use it commercially,
you can modify it and distribute it. And yeah, so basically you can do almost anything. It's not
so suitable if you actually want to use this in a patent. So depending what is the ultimate goal of
your project, then you may think of different licenses. And then again, in next week, we are
going to have one lesson which discusses different licensing. So the very final thing to show before
we go further is to browse issues and pull requests in the upstream repository. So remember
the upstream repository is the one that we have forked from, the one we have copied from. So
So, let's see, I don't remember what that link was.
So if I go to my main page of the repository,
then I can see that, okay,
it has been forked from this repository.
So I'm going to click on that,
and then I'm going to see,
so the top menu shows the issues.
There are two issues to this repository.
And well, the recipe book repository,
I'm sure has many more issues,
but this one in particular has two.
And issues, you can see issues as like,
let's say that you have some questions
about this particular repositories,
maybe some features that you think
that you would like to introduce.
Opening an issue is one way of starting a discussion
on a project.
Then there are some pull requests as well.
And how to actually create these pull requests
and why they are useful,
we will be doing that in the first episode.
So [name], anything else that we should discuss before?
Actually, yeah, seeing how we can do commits
now that we browse through the repository.
There's a lot of good questions in the notes
that we're monitoring, I don't see anything that,
maybe it's better to go to commit
because some of the questions are starting to be
about how you commit and messages and so on.
So if we go to that, we can start answering them.
Exactly.
So permitting changes, how do we actually permit changes?
commit changes. So we have started from this existing repository on GitHub, but let's assume
that now we actually want to introduce our own changes. In this case, we want to add some new
recipes or modify existing ones. So, we can do that. So, I'm going to
scroll down a little bit as we have discussed that already. So, let's say that we have
have an existing repository with different commits, let's say we have a series of commits
on the main branch, so the main line of development, and then we want to create a new branch.
So let's say that we have some features that we want to introduce and we do not want to
do it on the main branch because maybe, well, we still want to ensure that this main branch
produces results that we want.
And we just want to introduce some experimentation
to our project.
So then we can create a new branch
that we refer to in this case as your branch.
And so our repository is going to look like this.
So we have a series of commits that we add.
on this branch, your branch, but at any point in time we can actually
go back to the main branch and do further, further commits on this main branch. So then
what we'll have is, so except the initial commits that we had, we have the new ones on your branch
And then we have additional commits on main.
So this is what we want to do in this repository recipe book.
And again, there are different ways that one can do that.
One can use GitHub.
And that's what we'll demonstrate.
but one can also use the command line
or work in IDE as well.
So it's up to you, but again,
we'll show how you can do this on GitHub.
So we will continue with the same repository,
the recipe book one.
And then what you need to make sure
to make sure is that you work on your fork.
So you work in your username, recipe book,
and then what you will do is to create a branch
and add a recipe in that branch,
and then modify that recipe
on that particular branch that you created,
and further on, switch to the main branch
and add yet another commit.
So [name], so let's say,
how long time should we say for this particular exercise?
So we have 20 minutes until the scheduled lunch break.
Should we say 20 minutes and then go to lunch
and we don't say anything else?
Or should we say we come back for a brief wrap-up?
So let's do a brief wrap-up before the lunch.
I think that would be good.
Or we do the wrap-up just after the lunch when we come back.
That's also an option.
Yeah, let's do that.
Maybe if we do wrap-up after lunch,
people can go to lunch early and beat the queues and so on
if they want.
Yeah.
Yeah, so exercise, lunch, and then we are back in one hour and 20 minutes.
Yes, okay.
So I'm adding the info to the note doc where the exercise is.
We will keep answering questions, as usual. Keep asking. Yeah. Any final stuff? Summary
is now we're adding commits to something. And, yeah. Okay. So, see you after lunch.
See you. Bye.
you
Okay, welcome back everyone, I hope you had a good break.
So just before this longer break,
we're supposed to do an exercise on GitHub for
this recipe book repository and I
will quickly walk you through a solution.
So I will go back to my fork,
and the first thing that we were to do is,
but to make sure that we are on the fork,
and that is correct.
So I can see my username there,
so I'm not under the CR workshop exercises.
And then I should create a branch
and add a recipe to that branch.
So how can I create a branch?
So it's important actually that you are signed in,
that is the case.
So here in the left,
just under the repository info,
you can see the name,
sorry, the word main,
which actually is the name of our default branch.
And I can switch to a new branch,
sorry, to another branch,
or I can actually create a new branch
by just typing the name of it in the search one.
So I will call, how should I call this new branch?
I will just call it new branch,
which is a very bad name for a new branch.
But I will, I'll give you this bad name
so that I can show you later how you can rename.
So that's what we have.
I'm now on this new branch.
And then what I am to do next is to add a recipe.
So this seemed to be a common question in the notes, so something about making the new branch and then committing on it and getting the commit to show up in the right place.
And I know this is also often a problem with doing it other ways.
So, it's important that before you add changes, you do check on which branch you are.
So, if you are working on GitHub, then you see this just under the repo info.
So, in the code menu, and then this is the name of the branch, under this source control
symbol that you may also recognize in other IDs.
It's like having this, well, it's a symbol for actually merge the branches.
So yes, do make sure that this name corresponds to the branch where you actually want to introduce
changes.
That's important.
Just because you created the branch doesn't mean that you are on the wrong branch.
But on GitHub, the moment you do create a branch, it will switch to it directly.
And oh, and now it happens all the time.
When I click, it just goes to, I don't know,
it goes bananas.
So now I'm on the main branch, actually.
That's not what I want.
So let me switch to this new branch.
You see, I mean, sometimes GitHub behaves funnily.
So it happened previously as well.
well. That's why sometimes I don't like to work with the web interface because it just does what
it wants. So here I switch to the branch I actually want, new branch, and then I want to
add some changes there. So I will follow the instructions in the exercise. So I was to,
actually I should have created a new recipe branch. So sorry for that, but the name is
It's not super important.
So, but I should do, let's see, create a site recipe.
And so, yes, I am now in these sub-directory sites.
I'm going to add a file.
So I find it just under the menu, add file.
And what can I see?
I can click the plus to create a new file
or I can actually upload a file.
If I have one, I don't.
I'm going to edit it on GitHub,
which is okay for short files,
but for longer ones, I mean, of course,
it's more convenient to upload,
but it really depends on what you want to do.
Here, I should also name my files,
so I'm going to use mixed nuts,
and I'm going to give you the same extension
as the other files in my repository have,
so a markdown file.
In short, it has an empty extension.
And then I'm going to enter a recipe.
So let's see.
I do have a template somewhere there, but let's call it,
let's give it a title, Mixed Nuts.
And what should we have?
So I should have some ingredients.
And maybe some of you actually notice
that unless I have this line, there
are some GitHub actions which will fail.
we'll see that later. So what to add here? What's your favorite nut? Cashews, pecan, walnuts.
Yeah, walnuts. And then let's add some instructions.
Let's see. I think it's adding extra, yeah, those bullet points there.
Yeah, nice and simple.
And typos, as always.
So now I have my file here.
So the next thing to do is to commit this change.
and I click on this red button here.
And what I'm prompted is with a pop-up window
asking for a commit message.
And I get the default,
but I can also write my own commit message.
So let's say add recipe for mixed nuts.
for mixed notes. Yeah okay so you're and there was a question about what
or how to write it and this is a common one it's like imperative you are adding this. Yeah yeah
so this is a short change to our repository so it does not necessarily need an extended
description but for example if you do a lot of changes in your file then you might want to
explain actually why you've done those changes and what those changes are. So one can add an
extended description here but it is important to have a commit message which will identify
in short the summary of your changes so that you can more easily find a certain commit in
your history of commits. So this also shows as a top line in the commit message when you display
the history of your repository. So it's important you have something concise and suitable for these
changes. And then I'm going to check that the branch that this should be committed to is the
the one that I actually want.
So the default is the one that we had under code,
but I can also create a new one.
That is not the case.
I do want to commit under this one.
And then I just click Commit Changes.
Yeah.
Okay.
So then I'm actually,
I get this interesting message saying that
my branch is ahead of the upstream repository.
So the one I copied from.
This is a nice way to see, I mean,
how does your repository stand
with respect to the upstream, do you?
And yeah, so now we are one commit ahead.
That means that I have one extra commit
compared to this repository.
And as you have forked from recipe book,
you may actually get a different message here.
Okay then.
Yeah.
Now I should modify this recipe with a new commit
on the same branch.
So I'm going to open this file again
and I'm going to edit it.
So I click on this edit.
I don't want to add a new file,
I just want to improve it.
So let's see.
Seasoning, I'm going to say that we should have
some seasoning, like salt or, and chili.
What do you say?
Yeah, sure.
I would like both of those.
Okay, so I like that. I'm going to commit this, and then I'm going to say,
actually, update is not very useful, so I'm going to say add seasoning.
Okay, so on the same branch, commit changes. So now what do I have? I have two new commits,
right on my new branch. And then step four is to switch back to the main branch and modify
a recipe there as well. So basically introduce a new commit there. So I am going to click on
code, go back to the main branch. So select the main branch. Here it is. And what should I do here?
here. Let's open a recipe. Let's see what we have for salads here. Fruit salad. I'm
going to edit this file. And let's say I actually don't want fresh beans. I'm going to take
some whipped cream instead. And commit changes. And then remove it. Okay. And then again,
sure I'm on the right branch that I am. So what do I have now? I have one new branch,
sorry, one new commit on main. Actually, it's not very easy to see here, but let's go to
this history view that we looked at before. So I have this new commit, remove mint, add
cream on the main one, while on this new branch, I had added two commits.
Actually, there was a branch which was called a new branch before, but I have two new commits
here at seasoning and at recipe for mixed nuts. So what do I want to do now? I want to actually
compare the changes I have introduced to the change on the main branch. So in the repo and
I'm going to scroll down a bit here so you can see. So I'm going to go to code. So here
where I have the name of my main page of my repository, I'm going to
to take that back and actually click and edit,
sorry, write compare.
So GitHub, my username,
the name of the repository,
and then the important name compare.
So this, as we'll see,
works a little bit like the git diff command.
So it will allow us to compare
different commits that we have in our repository.
And I can choose either a branch
or a commit from the left here.
So let's say that I want to compare.
Oh, how did you get here?
You got to-
So the way I did here, so-
Is this making the pool?
The main page of the, so from the main page
of the repository, I am in the wrong one.
It's the-
I should have, it's because it swaps
between the fork and upstream a bit widely.
But so under my username and the name of the repository,
name and the name of the repository.
So recipe book recorded and then compare.
So yeah, this is what one should get.
Then I am prompted with what I would like to compare,
either compare against the upstream.
So this CR workshop exercises and I can
choose which branch in particular I want to compare from there,
or yeah, and what I want to compare with.
So by default, it took my own repository,
my own fork, and then the branch name.
So actually I can see that compared to the upstream,
so the main branch has a change,
and that change is in this fruit salad file,
a file and the changes.
So in red is shown what is missing in my main branch,
and in red shows what I have added to my commit.
So I added this line and I removed the other one.
So this is what is different.
I can also use it together with hashes.
So I can compare certain commits.
Then in order to do that,
I'm going to go to the history view again.
So let's say I want to compare two different commits
from my repository.
So I have copied, so I clicked on this copy, full hash.
And then again, so let's see,
I have to make sure that I type the right thing here.
And this is what I find a little bit annoying with GitHub,
because I can't see everything, first of all, compare.
This is so annoying.
So then actually, you know what I'm going to do
so that you all see what I am typing.
I'm just going to type it here.
Oh, let's see, no.
Bear with me for one second.
Okay, I see you opened a notepad here.
I'm going to open a text editor so that I can actually see what I am typing.
So compare, and then I'm going to copy this hash, for example.
Let's see.
And then you don't see everything.
But I see.
So now compare.
Slash compare.
So I add the full hash and I'll add two dots and then copy another hash.
So let's see actually what is in my.
So this is upstream.
So this is the upstream.
So this is, the problem is that this always changes back automatically whenever, whenever
I am, whenever GitHub doesn't find the link that, that you are trying to edit and it kind
of figures out for you what you should be typing.
So, let's edit the right thing.
So, this is very annoying.
Maybe you experienced this as well.
So, let's go back to the end and add the other hash.
Okay, so let's go to the new branch and the latest commit on that.
Okay, I see your two commits.
Yes, and now I'm going to copy paste this.
This is not elegant, I should say.
I don't like this a lot, but it's a way to show that you can compare two commits on GitHub.
So here we have it. We have a change between that commit specifies first, and that was
on the main branch. And then we have another hash, which stands for the latest commit on the new
branch. And what is different is this new file makes nuts with this content. So again, it's,
yeah, it is a little bit troublesome to actually add all these hashes, so I don't find it ideal,
but it is one way of doing differences. And the final thing is renaming a branch,
so let's see how we can actually do that. So going back to the history of my commits,
I see, oh actually I should see all, view all branches, let's do that. View all branches,
so then I have a list of all the branches for my repository. So let's assume that
that this new branch actually had a bad name.
It's not actually, it is very, very bad
because it's not representative for what it includes.
And I have to scroll a little bit here
so that I get to the most right part with these three dots,
which if I click on that allows me to rename the branch.
So I'm going to give it another name, `[name]/hummus` [our name, slash, a branch name].
It's not, it's quite common actually that a branch,
especially for a repository that has several collaborators,
that the branch contains the name of the person
that initiated that branch,
especially if you are the only person
working on that particular branch.
Okay, so that was it.
I can also have tags and then again, going to code.
So you'll see me going back to the main code a few many times.
So I can add tags, for example,
there and there are no tags right now.
So what is a tag?
Tag is like adding another identifier to a certain commit.
So let's see, I can choose a new tag.
Let's see, version 0.1.
And then I have to specify which branch
do I actually want to tag.
And then also the commit that I want to take.
So I'm going to take the, no, it doesn't matter, this one.
And I will describe this as first draft of my recipe book.
then publish release. Okay. So, but now what do I have? So I have this new branch, the
anahomos, which I may actually merge into the main branch if I wish. And then if I am
on GitHub, I see that I am prompted with a compare and pull request tab. So what happens if I
click on that? So I can then incorporate the changes that I have in the hummus branch
into the main one.
So I merged these two lines of work
into one branch again.
So what I have to do, yeah.
Is what we're doing part of the exercise right now
or is it going further?
No, it's not part of the exercise.
So we are now moving further into,
so let me show you.
So we are moving now into
of merging changes and contributing to the project.
Okay, so should we, so is this a demo right now
of this part?
Yeah, you can follow longer, you can better just watch
and then you can get to do this as an exercise.
Okay.
So what you need to be careful,
especially when you're doing this on GitHub,
is to specify which repository
you want to have a pull request against.
So, because GitHub knows that this,
this repository is a fork
of the AppStream1-cr-workshop-exercises recipe book,
then it's going to have a pull request
against this repository by default.
But I actually do not want that.
I want to do a pull request against my repository,
the main branch on my repository.
So now you see that by selecting that,
I got back to my main one.
And then, the branch that I want to merge into this one,
so do the, is the `[name]/hummus` branch, so that was correct.
And then, it tells me, so GitHub tells me that it's able to merge this automatically.
I can add a title,
so merging humus into main, for example.
I can give it a description and create a pull request.
There are different options.
If I click on this triangle,
I can see that I can choose the default,
create pull request, but I can also create a draft.
This is if you still want to work on your branch before the final merge.
That is not what we want right now. We want to ask for a pull request.
So this is what I'm going to click on.
So again, what this means is that I want to merge the hummus branch into the main one.
Okay, so then it tells me that, okay, everything is ready to be merged, but I actually have
to confirm the merge.
And because I am the only person that is actually working on this repository, I get to do this
merge myself.
But when you are working on a shared repository with several people, usually the person that
does the pull request is not the one that is merging.
It's just a practice.
But for repositories that you are working on yourself,
you can do the PR and the merging yourself.
So then I click on this.
And then I can provide the commit message.
So I'm happy with that.
and I click on ''Commit Merge''.
So then let's check actually our network graph,
see how that looks and then I'll listen to your comments.
One second. So we're Insights.
Sorry, I clicked on ''Settings'' instead.
So Insights Network.
It takes a bit of time when there are many new commits.
Oh, it's, yeah, going to show up quickly.
So what I have is this blue branch.
It was my `[name]/hummus` branch.
And then what I did in this last commit
is to merge it into main.
So GitHub is going to show it like, okay,
there is an arrow from the `[name]/hummus` branch
into the main one.
And it also prompts me with the commit message
for that merge.
And now you may wonder why there are so many other things
under the main one.
So these are simply different forks
that exists for the upstream repository.
So GitHub is going to collect all that information
and put it all in the network graph.
Yeah.
Okay.
So where are we now?
So let's see.
So what we did was to show how a merge can be done on GitHub.
So then what you can do now, so you also had your several commits on a branch
and some possibly some newer commits on main. So your task is now to attempt to merge these branches.
So merge your branch into the main one. So everything you just did with the pull request
and the merge is now the exercise where people do it themselves, following the instructions.
Okay. Yes. And you can do it as I have done it using GitHub. That's one solution.
And if you're comfortable with the command line and you've worked a little bit with Git before,
then you may attempt this solution as well. But I recommend that you try GitHub.
There's a good question, number 61. Can we make a pull request from the new branch
to the main branch of the original repository?
Yes.
And I think that... Go ahead.
Yes, you can. Yes, you can do that. And that is actually very common.
you usually do a pull request against the upstream and that is the whole reason why
you actually do a fork. For repositories you do not have the right to modify, you do some line of
work in your own fork and then you may ask for a pull request and have your changes integrated
in the upstream repository. So yes, that is possible and very common.
Yeah, and this is done as part of step seven of the... it's an advanced step, optional.
You can do it, but also on day three we do this a lot. But I recommend starting with doing it in
your own repository because then you can merge it. Today we're not going to be merging stuff into the
public repository. No, we'll show that more on day three. Yeah. Okay, so then exercise time until
10-2. Is that a good time [name]? Until for 20 minutes
or how long did you say? Until... Yes, 20 minutes. Okay, so until... yeah. Okay,
sounds good. I'm setting it up, and so the exercise is this here, and our goal
is to do everything except the optional step and after that we have more
discussion and stuff while you wrap up I think okay great see you in a little bit
bye
you
Okay, welcome back from the break, well, the exercise break.
So I'm going to show this very final step,
which was optional on how to
actually handle pull requests to the upstream branch.
So for that, I am going to go to
CR Workshop Exercises recipe book and click on pull requests.
Please know that this is the recorded version,
so I will not see all the pull requests that you have done.
But in this case, there are three pull requests.
So let's take this one from [name].
So what do I get to see here?
I get to see the committer and also let's see.
What I want to see is which files have been changed in this version that he has.
So there is a new recipe for burritos.
So this is the file that has been changed.
There are several commits in this branch,
And I assume, well, one of them has,
well, two of them have failed.
So then he actually proposed a new commit
that solved some of the errors that were in the project.
So let's just see why I'm actually happy.
I am happy with this proposed change.
So then what I can do is to merge the pull request
that [name] proposed.
So, I can also add a comment, so it's especially nice to write comments, especially if you don't
need these committers and you only get to communicate with them via GitHub. So,
So, thank you for your contribution.
And also I can comment to a pull request
even before I merge and actually say,
okay, I would like you to change a certain file
or improve on a feature.
so I don't have to necessarily accept the merge
in its current state.
So maybe I want [name] to do some changes before that.
But in this case, I am happy, so I'm going to merge it
and I can write another commit message for the merge.
Going to take that and confirm the merge.
So, then his recipe for the burritos is going to be in the main branch.
So, if I go now to mains, then I can see that I have his recipe incorporated here.
I see.
Yeah.
So, anything else [name] that we should add?
Let's see, there's a question number 68, contributing to the original repository
with pull request. Normally it's the other person, so if you're contributing to someone
else's repository, it's the other person that will do the merge, but you don't need to have
it in your main branch or anything. It can be in your own branch or whatever.
There's git switch versus git checkout. There's an older form of basically the same command. So
yeah, git switch is the modern word for it that's been made a bit less confusing.
Should we go to our break now, we can keep with the questions and then we can do some final demos and discussion afterwards.
Yeah, let's take a break and then we come back at 10 past. Is that a good time?
Yeah, sounds good.
So, back in 10 minutes.
So, sounds good. See you then. Bye.
you
Okay, welcome back from the break.
So, before we show a final demo, [name], is there anything that we should bring from
the collaborative doc?
There was a question about restoring branches and all, and how long can you restore things.
I don't know how long the GitHub button for restoring branches is still there.
if you make other changes, that wouldn't work. But all the history is in the repositories.
And if you do a normal merge, you can always go backwards. So maybe that's the more important
lesson there. Once you have the history, even if you don't have the button, you can go backwards.
Yeah, you can always see the closed pull requests. And if you get to your closed
pull request, you can see that you may restore your deleted branch.
And you usually want to do that if you want to add some additional commits to that branch.
And also, the moment you do a new pull request with the same name,
then that will be restored by default.
And there's some of these other questions about pull requests versus pushing and so
on. These are good questions, but maybe we'll go into them more later when we do some more
other demos and so on. I think there's some reasonable answers there.
Yeah, it is a bit confusing. Also, it's, well, different, well, all terminology that GitHub
has, GitHub developers have been using, and it's a bit tricky to understand sometimes
the punctuation, pull or pull.
Yeah.
Okay, let's go to actually introducing a conflict in our merge. And how do we get to do that?
So I'm going to go to my own fork and-
So first off, what is a conflict?
So-
And is this something that we need to go into now? Like where will, I mean, we want to go
into it now, but when does it become important? So a conflict appears when you are changing
the same portion of the file in two different branches, and then you want to merge those two
branches. And then either you merge it via the command line or on GitHub. It doesn't know,
Git doesn't know, okay, how do you actually, which changes do you want to keep from these
two branches? Because I'm having contradicting modifications to the same part of the file,
and I have no idea how to resolve those. So that's what we mean by the conflict. I am unsure,
Git is unsure about how to merge these different changes, because they appear in the same file,
in the same portion of the file into different commits
that we want to merge,
to different branches we want to merge.
So I think it's gonna be clearer if I demo it.
So again, I'm going to do that on GitHub.
So I will create a new branch.
Let's call it, what should I call it, [name]?
I call it creatures? Good question. Well, I'm going to make it. I'm going to call it soup.
Because my plan is to take some. Are you modifying the recipe? Yeah, I'm going to take an existing
recipe, this mushroom soup recipe, and I'm going to modify it and then commit these modifications.
So I am, yes, I am in the branch `[name]/soup` [we use our name + `/` + branchname to keep it organized.  It doesn't have to be like this.]. And then I assume, let's assume that, yeah, let's see
Let's see, that, what did I want to change?
Here, that I want to have two cups of cream.
Okay, yeah.
And then I'm going to save this changes into a new commit.
So more cream.
And then commit this to `[name]/soup`, okay?
And then what I will do is,
I'm going to go to the main branch now
and change exactly the same file.
Where was the main branch?
Here.
I'm going to change the same file again,
actually the same portion of the file,
but I'm going to introduce a different change.
So soup, mushroom soup, edit,
it. And then I'll say that, okay, I actually only want half a cup of heavy cream. And then
commit this change again. Well, now I am on the main branch, so commit this. So I'll call it less
cream, this commit message, and commit. So what do I have now? I have two different modifications
to this soup recipe in two different branches,
and it's the same line which is modified in different ways. So now let's go to...
let's try to merge this.
So I have this branch, `[name]/soup`, that I want to merge into the main branch,
So I click compare and pull requests.
And again, I should be careful what I want to merge.
So I don't want to merge against the upstream.
I actually want to choose my repository.
And I want to merge the branch called `[name]/soup`.
And what does it tell me?
Oh, you cannot automatically merge.
And the reason is because there is this conflict.
Git cannot automatically decide which of these changes I want to keep in my merged commit.
I guess this is a common thing to happen if it's a project with multiple people.
Hopefully you're not doing two similar things, but you might touch the same line and
a human has to decide what to do.
Exactly. So then I could still create a pull request or a merge request, but then it told
me that, okay, you have to resolve the conflicts before this can be merged. So then what I
do is to click on this resolve conflicts. So GitHub is going to open this file, Mushroom
which has the conflict, and it's going to introduce these delimiters to indicate where the conflict is.
Usually when one resolves the conflict, actually one should remove these delimiters.
So I will remove them, and it's the same if one does it on the command line, these delimiters will show up.
But then I have to decide which of these lines, or well, how do I want this line to look like?
So what do you think?
I'm actually going to go for half a cup.
And-
So this is mostly human deciding which one is the-
Exactly, exactly.
More useful one right now.
Yes.
So I am going to scroll down.
Oh.
Oh, where?
And then mark, yes, it was actually up here.
So mark as resolved.
And then click on commit to merge.
So Mark has resolved, it means that actually
I have accepted this change,
but I still have to instruct GitHub
that I want to merge these two branches.
So merge the `[name]/soup` branch into the main one.
And I can add more comments.
Okay.
I don't want to add more comments
and then just confirm this merge.
Yeah.
So yeah, that's one way a conflict can emerge.
And of course it's undesirable,
especially if there are two different people
that have introduced changes
and you don't know how to resolve them,
then you might actually need to sit together
or have some email communication or GitHub communication
to see how is best to resolve that conflict.
Yeah, so this is actually pretty useful because normally if two people were modifying the
same thing, you might have to get a human to open them both and figure out what's what
and do a lot of manual work.
Here you still had to do manual work, but it showed you exactly what the problem was
and was much easier than some of the manual merges
in my past when I've sent someone code
and had to get it back.
Yeah, I think this also makes us realize
that if you have a branch you've been working on a long time
and you're waiting for too long
before you actually try to merge it into the main one,
it's more likely that you are going to encounter conflicts
when you try to merge.
So it's good to think,
well, it's good not to wait too long
before attempting a merge.
Because otherwise it's gonna,
well, it might take many days to resolve some of the conflicts.
So it's of course very dependent
from repository to repository,
but yeah, it's something to keep in mind.
it's one person, then, well, you get to decide how these conflicts should be resolved. But
the more people involved, the more opinions. So, yeah.
Okay. So, what now? Should we go to the notes and for a final discussion,
looking at different questions and so on? Yeah, maybe just the final thing is like,
Like, so we showed most of the things on GitHub.
While we did say that, okay, you can do all these
using either the command line or using BS code
or another ID.
But what is your preference, [name]?
When should we use what?
So I definitely do use GitHub sometimes,
times, especially for small updates and things like that,
and for reviewing and merging things
that are relatively clear.
I don't often go making new files
and doing serious changes.
So adding a recipe like we've done,
yeah, I might as well copy and paste there
if I don't have it locally.
But for all the real work, it's always
done via my local copy of the repository,
which is what we will get to tomorrow.
But still being able to merge both of them together
is very useful because one is easier short-term,
one is easier long-term.
Yeah, it's the same for me.
If I have one change per commit,
then yeah, I'll do that on GitHub.
And also if I'm working on a different computer
and I don't have a clone of that repository,
so a copy of that repository on my local machine,
then I'll just work on GitHub instead.
But the moment I have many changes to different files,
then I think that using the command line is better.
But then there is also a threshold
until you get comfortable enough
and you know enough commands
actually get to do these things on the command line. Although I think that, yeah, you can do a
lot with just 10 GIT commands. So there are definitely pros and cons to these different
ways. And I think that GitHub and the features that actually GitHub has evolved a lot in the
last years, there are many things that you can do using the GUI interface compared or the web
interface compared to how it was five years back. And I think it's still going to evolve. So at
some point maybe you don't need to do things in the command line unless you prefer that.
Yeah, but okay, let's see.
Did I already say at the bottom there's a feedback section, so we'll keep answering
questions, but you can tell us if today was too fast, too slow, a good speed, and so on.
And then something to improve, something good about today, any other feedback, and well,
you can keep asking questions. In the meantime, I want to talk about this question number 74
for a conflict to arise there. Sorry, I'm making sure my cat isn't eating some cables or something.
So the conflict to arise, so if it's the same line it's a definite conflict.
Does anyone know is it the case if there's something that's on several adjacent lines?
I think there has to be at least a line in between so that it's not interpreted as a conflict.
Okay, yeah, makes sense because, yeah, so basically it tries to be safer rather than
risk messing thing up.
But of course you can change code so that Git doesn't detect a conflict, but the final
code doesn't work together with the two different changes.
And for that, the way to detect it is with automatic software tests, which GitHub and
Git can run automatically.
but that's something we cover on day six,
and that's really sort of the capstone part of it.
Yeah, so we haven't really showed how to compare commits.
Well, we did show how to compare commits on GitHub a bit,
but I would say actually before every single merge,
you should check what you are trying to merge.
What are the changes that I introduced on this branch
and the branch, and what are the changes in the,
and what is different on the branch
I'm trying to merge into.
That is, I would say a must before attempting any merge.
In this case, it was a simple example.
I knew exactly what is different on those two branches,
but usually, well, you do want to check.
I mean, what have people been modifying on the main branch?
I know the changes I made,
or I can recheck the changes I made.
And then once I compare that,
either on GitHub or using git diff, then I know,
OK, this is what I expect from the merge.
And maybe you may even actually anticipate
some of the conflicts before you are attempting the merge.
So definitely test how the commits are
different between merging.
Yeah.
This is a common pattern we'll see in future days.
So it's really easy to, in VS Code command line
or even GitHub, you get to a place
like you're on a branch you aren't expecting
and you start doing something
and things get messed up somehow underneath.
So we'll really emphasize before you do anything,
you stop, understand where you are
and then you do the next part.
Yeah.
So before we take any other questions,
Should our participants prepare for anything in particular
before tomorrow?
Yes, actually, there is this news here
that's related to this question.
Do we recommend VS Code or shell-based?
So for the news, so we have the recordings available.
Twitch will have them immediately.
And probably, I will have them on YouTube
by midnight, finish time.
Let's see how well it actually goes.
So since tomorrow is more local work,
so not from the GitHub web interface.
Today you didn't need anything installed on your computer,
but tomorrow you need something installed.
So we have two main tracks.
One is with the command line
and one is with Visual Studio Code.
And you can choose either of them.
I'm not sure which one we will demonstrate with,
but it does require stuff to be installed and set up.
So definitely look at the installation instructions.
And either way, watching the shell crash course
will be useful because it will prepare for today.
No matter what you do,
you're gonna need to type some things in a command line
and it's better to have a little bit of familiarity
with it first.
Yeah, so if you're not used to the command line,
then feel free to watch the shared course.
Yeah.
And in day three, there will be even more set up.
You'll need to join a team and request access
to a repository before you can do a certain part.
And as for what we recommend.
Yeah, sorry.
We will email you about the steps
that you need to do before day three, so no worries.
Yeah.
And as for the, do we recommend the shell or VS Code?
Really, I'd probably recommend whatever you're already using.
If you're using VS Code a lot, use that,
because that's what you're more likely to use later.
If you don't know, well, you can try
both tracks of the exercises.
Do it in VS Code, and then do it in command line, or vice versa.
and then you see how they relate and will learn even more because even though I use both of them
sometimes, well I use the shell more and it's important to be able to put them together.
Yeah and also if you have another IDE that you prefer that's also okay to use,
although we will not be demonstrating that. But you can still get help from all the other
persons behind the scenes which are helping us answer all these questions.
Yeah. Is there anything else? I guess the preparations for the next day is the
most important part. I know I heard rumors of there being a install help session
via Zoom an hour before we start tomorrow.
I'm not sure if that's happening,
but I guess you will get an email about it if it does.
Yes, and also many of the news and important information
is also on the course website
or will be on the course website shortly.
So we want to, or actually maybe I can show
where to find all this.
Of course, I don't have the page open.
So yeah, just go to Code Refinery.
Okay, I don't fancy a thing.
What is it, 25?
So, news are going to be here and also you may find the past communication under this
tab, communication, so then all the communication, all the previous emails are going to be there.
But most important things will be under the news here.
Okay.
Good to know.
Yeah, I think that's about it for today, and hopefully you found this useful, and you'll
join us tomorrow, and we'll continue with it.
Yes.
So good.
So see you tomorrow.
See you.
Bye.
you