Thank you.
you
Test, test, can anyone out there hear us?
So I think you should be able to.
assume so until we hear otherwise so this is our notes as usual so registered participants
have them we can scroll down and as usual there's some icebreakers which include what do you want
to be when you grow up how would you explain your current job to someone from 1700 and what's the
best documented project you've seen. And in the meantime, while we're waiting, we have a guest
for the icebreaker. This is something we've been doing some years in the past. We have Matteo with
us. So [name], can you tell us a little bit about yourself, where you work, what you do now, and so
on? Yeah, sure. Hi, everybody. My name is [name]. I'm a research engineer at the Gothenburg
university uh here in sweden research engineer is very often people with screwdrivers or working in
the wet lab but i'm more like a research software engineer in that sense it's just that my title
doesn't contain the software part but i basically do software for humanities uh technically i work
in digital humanities you can count that as 50 in archaeology probably and the other 50
doing infrastructural stuff for um project of cultural heritage uh a history of ideas
things like sounds analysis for um documentary studies things like that yeah cool i didn't
realize your title was research engineer i think it really is pretty appropriate i mean we're the
equivalent of people who go to the labs with screwdrivers but with code instead so yeah i i
agree it's a bit of a swedish thing i know at chalmers which is the the technical university
here they have this i think it's like research digital engineer or something like that but here
in sweden very often fortunately engineer so a research engineer means screwdriver or pipettes
yeah yeah but i mean that's fine i mean we can put them together yeah so how did you get where you
are like what did you study and what was your path that led you to this job i i took the long road
uh which uh i didn't study software at all until basically my phd i have a master in theoretical
physics that's my start and when i was looking for a phd i was looking for something where i
could use pen and paper and do proper modeling but then during my phd after my master i switched to
theoretical biology because many of the methods were were in common and i was very interested in
the living beings because they're more stochastic but when you say stochastic very often means that
analytical solutions can be difficult to come by and so all of a sudden you start doing computers
so that's that was my entry point and i realized i actually enjoyed it a lot
even though i thought i didn't and i specialized in both modeling population genetics but also
individual population-based modeling so which is generally called agent-based and then i did two
postdocs in there. I went through all the stuff for the normal career in academia and I basically
burned out when I was looking for more money after my second postdoc. I was ready to move out of
academia to my sorrow, but they opened this position in digital humanities and they were
looking for someone specialized in agent-based modeling. So, you know, I jumped on it and I was
right profile a bit of a mix of good good fortune and yeah and and good skills i guess yeah and so
i've been here for two years and a half now yeah okay cool um it's um just a little bit of
reflection there so i heard um you mentioned that early in your education you were studying
theoretical physics and it was essentially with pen and paper and it's a bit interesting because
i also started theoretical physics in the start however from us in the other undergraduate
education there's a lot of scientific computing and programming um and also in in the master's
level um yeah okay then it was more like you could choose the courses but but naturally you would
come a lot also to scientific computing yeah we we had courses of programming uh it's always
surprises people that my first course was in c plus plus which is not surprising that i didn't
like coding at the time yeah but i did i also had courses in matlab and then in another software
that was for uh statistical analysis it was called igor i don't think it's very much used outside of
physics i never heard it ever again but uh there is still this very strong part of classical
theoretical physics like cosmologists that like like equations i that was my favorite part my
My favorite course in statistics was analytical mechanics, which is studying the movement of objects just through theorems.
And it's amazingly funny, but we never saw a computer in those courses.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think most of most code refinery people have somehow studied some like physical science and some computer science, but most physical science.
and then now support computers with lots of stuff so but i will also say that the reason i didn't
like coding is that nobody taught me to do it properly and that's when you realize that your
code is not good it's full of errors very often you don't know if it's full of errors but you
kind of feel it you you start developing that kind of instinct of like i know this is wrong
but I don't know where yeah yeah yeah and and what happened is that during my PhD
I started to follow these courses of good practices in programming and those opened
the world for me and all of a sudden I realized wait first of all I like this I even like the
bugging now but second of all like I can code and be sure of what I'm coding and now do you teach
this to people you work with um i i try to uh i think it's 50 50 there are the people that are
still spaghetti code but are very efficient at that yeah and there are people who are even better
than me at cicd processes testing you know all those things and i'm learning a lot and i'm trying
to teach a lot especially when we have share code we have a lot of share code um and we we yeah we
some short code that is over complicated but it's kind of understandable yeah and so we're trying to
simplify it and then there is code that is just too complicated nobody understands it because the
person has left and you know like like every enterprise i think yeah yeah yeah okay cool
so we've got just a few minutes left um don't forget the icebreakers we have here um
Well, first, before we go on, I want to ask [name] the standard question.
What advice, what do you know now that you wish someone had told you when you started your career or studies or sometime a while ago?
Related to coding, I wish they taught me to code properly from the start.
that's because it took years to really get into that that mind space okay uh but in general uh
life doesn't end with academia and this is something that i'm still learning myself but
you know you never know if funding expires in a couple of years and even my permanent job is not
that permanent anymore there is stuff outside that is really interesting and sometimes it's
enough to just go google something software engineer on linkedin to find out how many
interesting and cool ideas that are out there of jobs so i think that's something i wish
someone told me before yeah yeah academia is not everything and you don't have to
to stay hooked on it yeah yeah and i say this as someone who loves academia
for everything that it's giving me yeah yeah yeah good to have the balance um [name] or
[name], do you have
any thoughts on any of these
questions?
Well, they touch a lot of
aspects of
what we do
I guess
so I would talk for
four hours perhaps
I think when it comes to
with i mean to learn to code properly and so or let's say early on then i've been over the years
often active in in environments where you're a little bit understaffed when it comes to
doing what you're doing yeah so in practice then that means that you devote most of the time and
effort to let's say the science part of the projects and then for let's say coding you do
what is necessary and yeah in computational physics working with let's say mbi and open
mp threading that's manageable let's say to do for a skilled 50 student but i think nowadays
we see this that that let's say you're in territorial chemistry or something and
and you need to keep track of the chemistry
and also learn, let's say, how to write code for GPUs.
And that's a lot.
That's really not really.
Typically, for one person to get a grip on that, it's a lot.
So then you need to work differently to be effective.
Yeah, I completely agree.
That's actually the typical U skill profile,
meaning that you have two main skills that need to be very deeply developed.
That is common to basically everything, research, software, engineering, I would say.
I think this adds to another thing which I learned before,
is that in STEM, at least, there is a feeling that you have to learn everything on your own.
When you have a publication, even if you have co-authors,
from A to Z, you have to know every nitty-gritty of the paper.
you have to know how to code you have to know how to test you have to know how to do a literary
review and that is just not true a literature a literary review you go to the library and you
ask for help they will help you they know how to do those things better than you do and for
software is the same thing you go to a good coder and you can do some some pair programming you're
going to learn much more than trying to go through a youtube video that is badly badly made and this
is a stem thing we want to do everything on our own learn everything on books and and youtube
videos alone and that's that's just the wrong approach yeah speaking of learning with other
people don't forget we have some bring your own code sessions which are precisely this kind of
thing you can come to the instructors and bring whatever you're doing whether you already have
code or not um but then get one-on-one advice from some of the instructors usually there's not
many people attending these so yeah come if like there's plenty of space for people
but with that being said should we carry on now so the first lesson of the day is documentation
and that's taught by [name] and [name] but first i guess we should thank [name] from coming this is
something we've wanted to try more like inviting some of our broader community people to come and
introduce themselves and talk about their careers we should we really should have done it more but
basically i didn't have time to ask people so you only get one anyway thanks mateo and see you around
no problem thanks thank you for having me bye goodbye okay and now i will hide myself and
switch to your screen. So see you all later. I'll be around in
the background if you need me. Thanks. Bye.
So yeah, thank you, [name]. And thank you, [name]. So,
[name], we're going to talk about how to document your
research software.
Yeah, very interesting, very important thing, I would say.
Yeah, very important topic.
Yeah, so this will be a two hour lesson that runs up until depending on the time
zone here for us, it's up until 11 o'clock and in the first hour it will be mainly
that we'll go through things here based on our lesson material on the web page.
And then it will be a little bit more hands on in the second hour.
But there will be a lot of discussions also over the shared document now during the first hour.
So we could just give a little bit of an overview.
So we'll talk about documentation in general for a project, for a code, and also then touch upon some specifics, as for instance, how to write a good reading file.
What we'll be talking about will be independent of programming languages.
Some of the examples will be in Python, but it's essentially transferable to other programming
languages.
We will learn about a documentation generator, Sphinx.
It is often combined with an online service, Read the Docs.
And we will also then, towards the end, talk about how to get documentation up online on
a service like, for instance, GitHub pages.
It's quite a lot of things to go through.
Yeah.
There are a few things, but I think we have time to cover things here.
um so yeah perhaps we could first just start a little bit on see what people have written
in the icebreaker question in the shared document
like good yeah it's it's always funny to yeah these are typically very funny questions and
people come without come up with very funny answers i think yeah sorry so i'll
brought this over here to the screen share and okay what do you want to be when you grow up
yeah i like become a scientist i like that this is that it also applies to me this is being
a software engineer means that i'm always between you know doing software and doing science and
And yeah, I want to do both of both, both things,
let's say, more of both things.
And so become a scientist
and I would say also a software engineer,
but I like that.
Yeah, I can relate.
Oh, here's one, a funny one, streamer.
The stream is teaching and mentoring kind of stuff.
Well, join Code Refinery, I guess.
So, for reference, I'm the one that wrote that one.
I see, I see.
Ah, okay.
How to explain your account job from someone from the year 1700.
across the future yeah i can always try um okay so moving down here a bit becomes a little bit closer
to to the to the to the topic here of the lesson so what's the best documented project you have seen
and the highlight lighted here are for instance numpy and scipy which are
automatic libraries implemented with api for the python programming languages
I think we will see how to write documentation that looks a bit like that.
So at least we cannot teach you today all the good practices, but at least we can teach you the tools
or show you the tools at least to do something that looks like it at least.
Yes, so okay there are the placeholders. So let's move now to the lesson material here.
so the idea is here that yeah we will start to be interactive here right away
so we would like to bring up this I mean why would you like to document a code
and why it is important so you can see here these questions and we would now
ask you to please contribute with your input in the shared document and here
have here some starting questions for discussion so questions are is product
documentation important and why is that so how would you describe a useful
documentation and the third thing how can you motivate your colleagues to
contribute to the documentation.
So I can start saying a bit of my opinions here, perhaps, I
don't want to stimulate the discussion. Well, of course, I'm
seeing already some interesting answers there. So I will try to
say something else is not there. So I actually, for myself, I
want to document the code also, because I do, I typically do
many things at once. And maybe there are some projects that I
need to stop for a moment and then pick pick them up later.
And if I have good documentation written, at least I can, I can
get back to it. But of course, if I want someone else to use
code then yeah but then it becomes more complicated i would say but still uh yeah that's a very
important uh aspect of it so yeah uh yeah and actually there's a comment which is interesting
for no one is going to use it not even yourself perhaps not but yeah so it's true a throwaway
code exists uh but yeah we throw away code is throw away code is awesome because you can do
whatever you want with it and you don't pay for your sins uh but uh but yeah we are talking about
here i think we are talking about code that that where you don't have this luxury let's say yeah
throwing everything away and um it could also be that even if it's a code you write it and perhaps
just for use over a shorter time or so then I mean to document it can also guide you in
the development of the code itself and perhaps you come to think about some constructions which are
not so good and you then while describing them in text in documentation you
then come to think about these shortcomings and you then improve in the code itself
So, yeah, we could highlight here what you have contributed with here in the document.
Yeah, here, important here, we need at least a bare minimal documentation, like a README.
I think that that's a very important point.
And there are so many steps in the project
that are stored only in your head initially,
and you need to get them down on paper before you step out away from a project.
Yeah.
I think we should try to comment a bit on the third question.
how can you motivate your colleagues
to contribute to the documentation?
But I think even before asking this too
about your colleagues,
but how can I myself,
how can I motivate myself to write documentation?
And I think that, yeah,
so getting familiar with the habit, it's important,
and also with the tools that are available for that.
So I think, yeah,
habit is more important than the than the tools but uh but yeah we'll i think that that's the way
you structure our lesson basically talking about simple tools first and describing the
yeah or the the things you need to think about when you write documentation and then talk a
bit more about the tools later right um yeah but yeah i think that uh someone's writing an
interesting comment here like learn to do a little bit at the right stages it doesn't seem
like an artificial yes so the point is that you you can always learn a bit improve your practices
while you also do some some some like important work at the same like like the the fundamental
work of writing the code and right doing your research at the same time you you know then you
stop for a moment you learn a bit more about how to do things better and go on so in this iterative
cycle and i think that this is a key to the practice it applies here but to the documentation
but also to other to best practices in general how do you learn how to apply best practices in general
yeah yeah um i think yeah we can perhaps see here there are some things which we had here
uh in the lesson material let's see that we had thought of up beforehand so to say
um and this perhaps complement here and
yeah there are some some points here that that complement actually what we have on the
on the shared document so you may want others to contribute to the code
and yeah to that and having a documentation can be helpful because that can get persons to
have a more smooth entry to the code and to the product and the fourth point here is yeah that's
actually a very important point because feel your limited time and let the documentation answer
are frequently asked questions and i mean the scale of things here matters a lot so if you are
working let's say three four persons perhaps you even sit in the same corridor and you have lunch
every day that then clearly a lot of let's say keeping track of things can be very informal
perhaps only in voice and you don't need to write it on in paper if you start to share a scientific
code with people who are not at the same physical location as you and also the numbers go up to
let's say hundreds of users can be tens of developers then clearly you need to do it in
writing and also this with let's say the efficiency of things namely this that things would be
possible to grasp for newcomers to the code and then be the users or be the developers
that is helpful for them and also quite helpful for people who are already on board
because then you don't need to answer the same question over and over again
But then the question, I guess, is, what would you like to have in a documentation, right?
So what are the things you would put in your documentation?
So that's why we have this question about the wish list, right?
So what is your wish list regarding what you have there?
Yeah, so one important thing here is that documentation can come in many different forms.
One way of categorizing them, which has gained a lot of traction, is to distinguish in the four categories of tutorials,
how-to guides, explanation and reference.
So we have here also a few reference material for this and we could perhaps
just move quickly to this page here.
Yeah, so here you have like a nice box here with these four different kinds of documentation.
So a tutorial, that would be something which is learning oriented.
So that could be like an entry point to get started with the code.
How to guides, more like you have something very specific.
have a specific thing you would like to do with the program and you would like to go in and then get
a suggestion on how to do a certain task for a specific purpose
that relates also then i mean tutorials and how to guides i would say both of them will interrelate
quite a lot to more like explanation material which could be material which are
a i mean explaining the program and the code itself it could also go let's say beyond
to the code itself in a sense that could give let's say an overview of i mean the scientific
field and put it into context when you're using the code. And fourthly here you have the category
reference information and that is yet another category which is that can be then very let's say
technical instance could be like an application programming interface and complete description
of the api which then is important for you as a developer of a code to have available
but it can also be done for users that you sometimes need to be able to just find sort
of like in a dictionary style complete listing of all of the let's say keywords if it is a keyword
based program or if it's a graphical user interface program that that you have let's say
um a little bit of an overview of here are all all the entry points and work modalities in the
program
and we will come in in a little bit later into the lesson we'll talk about
readme files which i think is probably something that you all are familiar with
But before we do so, we have here a little bit of a task here to come up with ideas for
what would be points, I mean suggestions on points to have on a wish list for good documentation.
So we have these three questions here to start the discussion.
And please then work in the collaborative document.
The three questions are, let us create a wishlist for how we would like the competition to be.
We do have some of our ideas, but please don't look on them yet, but come up with your own.
And also, you'll probably come to think about some things that we did not think about earlier.
Yeah, how does documentation need to be in order to be useful, in order to be, like, yeah, useful to different people?
And also, well, I don't want to give away too much.
I don't want to stimulate the discussion by creating some kind of bias.
but yeah okay but I see that comments are coming in yeah yeah so yeah working
examples like examples on how to use the code great I think this I think we she's
really reasonable a table of content yes we'll discuss how to get a table of
content. This can be typically automated, actually. So, we see
that. Yeah. Yeah, I think that template input idea is similar
to like an example of usage, right? So, it falls in the same
category, I would say, possibly in the category of, of how to
guides, perhaps or tutorials. I mean, that is there. I mean, a
template input would be possibly part of a and how to or a
tutorial, right? Think there's a comment coming through about
language i guess one should try to be as possible as unambiguous as possible i guess
if i understand correctly the intention of the writer
yeah that's obviously very important to avoid any let's say confusion
to the extent possible because I think it's inherently so that for larger programs
or could be like program packages where you have let's say one main program and you have
a number of libraries that you're also using then there is a lot of complexity
which you can try to shield the user from it up a point but
But I mean, there are often situations where you need to get under the hood and really
know what is going on in the code.
And then there will be details for sure.
I see very interesting comments here, but I'm also curious to see what's the reaction
to our suggestions.
So, would you go to our – should we start discussing our suggestions?
Yeah, let's do so.
Yeah, so I think the reason why this documentation,
this is part of this workshop and we spend so much time on virtual control
is because I think that documentation should be virtual controlled.
It's easy for your code to change in a way that it's not synchronized
with your documentation.
So if you put the documentation and the source code in the same repository, then it's more likely, it's still possible to have some kind of, you know, issues with synchronization that, you know, your documentation describes an old version of the code and the code has progressed.
But it's harder for this to happen, or at least it's easier to see that in a sense, right?
Yeah, so I think, well, so yeah, so the idea is version, so your documentation should be version control because it will change over time because the software will change over time.
I think also it will change because, so documentation can change because you may find ways to rephrase some sentences or to, you will find more fitting examples and you would, so there are different ways, different reasons why documentation may change.
so you want to keep that under virtual control i would think hey and so it should be close to
the code i think then yeah what about a standard macro language what the what what is what is this
about yes these are something we just a lot for rendering of contents of texts
and documents often in the context of web publishing but also for documents
you have offline um and these are the market language is something which can be when you read
it in source in in its raw form it is pure text which means it suits itself to version control
at the same time you can then on the fly in your in your in an editor for instance
visual studio code or or other programs on your local machine you can also render it very swiftly
often on the fly and we will hear in this lesson we will see two examples
namely restructured text rst and also the so-called markdown mark up and and
and it is sort of a play with the markup as in HTML.
Yeah, so it's a kind of, it's very simple.
The thing is, who doesn't love markdown?
It's very simple to use and yeah.
And it was created with that intent.
Restructure text instead is a bit more complex,
but it's more powerful.
Yes, yes.
Okay, what more do we have here? We have copy-pasteable. That's very practical, I would say. You have
let's say some suggested sequence of commands and you can take them directly from the documentation
and then you just paste it in let's say your terminal window or other application interface
and things get running.
Yeah, and the problem is that if you use PDF
or even some slides, when you have some,
some codes written slides,
if you copy that and paste it, it doesn't work.
Even if it, you know,
even if it looks good when you pasted it.
So it's the weird things happening sometimes.
So, yeah.
Okay, I think we should go over these things here
a little bit swiftly
so that we can come to read new files.
So installation instructions,
that's very relevant.
Code licensing, that's...
That's a big thing.
Yeah, that's a big thing.
The last point here, information for contributors.
That's also something that lowers the hurdle
for newcomers and also a means to where you can,
means to where you can, let's say, make clear that you welcome
contributions. And I mean, that also depends where you stand in
a project, perhaps in the beginning, it is, let's say,
essentially closed shop, you work with your team of close
collaborators, and you're not really ready to let in other
people, and that's perfectly fine. But then you could also
perhaps be transparent about this, so that there are no
misunderstandings. And what I do myself sometimes is that I simply reach out over
email to people to check first, like, okay, is here something you would like people to
contribute? It might be better to have that kind of conversation offline rather than to
to have that in, let's say, discussion on issues in GitHub.
I actually have something to add to the wishlist,
which is not on this list
because it's a bit hard to achieve,
but I think it can be nice.
So I think that there's some kind of documentation,
there are some formats that allow you to check
at least part of it automatically.
And so if you write documentations using a notebook approach, like a literal programming approach,
there are some tools that actually can verify that your tutorial that you write in, like, a Jupyter notebook in this way,
when you mix text and code.
So if you use that format, there are tools that can validate your documentation, in a sense,
so that you can actually run them automatically
and see if something has changed.
And I think it's nice to have something like this
because it allows you to basically maintain your documentation
with less effort or to at least detect problems,
incompatibilities between documentation and your code quicker.
And so we are going to talk about Jupyter Notebooks this afternoon,
and we're going to talk about automated testing tomorrow.
So I think this is a good way to connect the dots of all this.
I have a narrative, overarching narrative in this huge workshop.
Yes, indeed.
And you mentioned, [name], that there are different tools and frameworks.
So that brings us naturally over to a little bit
um that particular topic namely so what what popular i mean what tools and solutions are out
there so um when you do commenting in in documentation in code there are um
things that you can do um which could be like pure comments you can use function doc strings
And I mean, actually, the in-code documentation is a primary concern for the developers of a code.
It can also be of high importance for users of the code, if it's so that you have something which is,
let's say it's something um yeah a big simulation software with a lot of
let's say detail details in implementation and where you as an end user need to know precisely
what is happening sometimes looking directly into the source code is the adequate thing to do
And then having the in-code documentation is important because then you can, as a guide
for the eye, so that you find...
Yeah, especially if you're talking about the kind of functions that stay a bit on top of
everything.
So the more, the general, the functions that the user may call, then I think these are
comments there uh and are going to be pretty useful because that's i think these are the
most likely to be looked at by by uh by a user right yeah yeah
i want to say one thing about commenting your code uh there's uh there's a a number of people
like a discipline called the clean code where they say oh cold comments are not great because
they are hard to fight to to um to verify you should actually name your functions and your
your variables in a way so that it's obvious what they do and they think that it's good advice but
it's quite hard to get to get right so yeah um yes we need we need also comments in the code i think
yeah but i think there's also people that say no you shouldn't comment your code you should make
your functions and your your variable uh named in a way that you don't need comments maybe it's
possible i don't think it's always possible but yeah yeah it depends a little bit also on which
language you you're using because i mean some languages are more verbose and and let's say
human language like it and whereas others a bit more a bit more compact and keyword like it so
that you need to decorate it or you could naturally decorate it with normal text okay
so we had mentioned here earlier um already this with restructured text and markdown so
So, [name], what are these formats?
So yeah, here in the notes you see,
so basically there are two formats
that allow you to write.
They are really already readable as they are,
especially Markdown, I think.
That was the design goal of Markdown,
was you don't have to render this to HTML.
You don't have to render this to a webpage.
You cannot re-read as it is.
And yeah, so you see that you have different features here.
You can make some parts bold.
You can emphasize some parts.
You can have lists.
You can have images, tables, links.
Yeah, and they are equivalent in the basic functionality, at least.
right uh yeah so restructured text is a bit more feature featureful uh the markdown markdown has
actually different flavors so github for example can render markdown files it will do that in a
different way than the github for example um at least on the more like niche features um
well instead restructured text is more standardized and it can also be uh expanded if you want you
add if you want to do something fancy you can create new directives and new roles and there's
a mechanism to do that with markdown alone it's a bit more complicated but markdown is simple
and people don't need to be taught how to use markdown while people may need to be taught how
to use uh restructuring text yeah yeah that's a good point um i know indeed markdown is very
lightweight essentially you can um i mean copy paste some paragraphs and then a starting point
and then you already have the syntax there for everything and and just write your content yeah
and actually in what follows later when we are going to talk about sphinx we are going to use
like um something which is the best of both worlds which is my st which is like a markedly structured
text which is a flavor like a markdown flavor which is a expanded in a way that you can also
you have also the restructured text features so you see here in in the middle here of this panel
that have some references here where you can find them more details on on markdown and on
restructured text um html static site generators that is something that we will try out in the
second hour and as you can see here there are many options available here um so
So, yeah, we have Sphinx here, [name].
Yeah, so Sphinx is like the main tool
that is used to document the official Python projects.
And that's what we're going to use here.
So we said that at the beginning
that this part is like language agnostic.
And it is because you can write any documentation
for any project of any language.
But yeah, I mean, this is actually Python.
This is a Python tool, okay?
But this is only for the Sphinx part.
What we're going to talk about in the first hour
applies to basically every software project in any language.
And yeah, so there's really many of them.
I think the MKDocs is becoming more and more popular.
and uh yeah the cool thing about um sphinx and mkdocs and also others is that they can do
things which are really interesting not just generate html uh so web pages but they can also
they have plugins where for example they can produce pdf or latex or they can um parse your
code and extract the doc strings from it, okay, so that they can generate an API documentation,
reference API documentation. And so this is about Sphinx and MKDocs and many others which
are a bit more language specific because they need to read things from your code. So they need
understand your code um yeah and the thing is that after you have used this tool to create a web page
you can host it you can put it on the internet so it can be seen uh from from from everywhere
in the world um and we'll discuss about how to do this on github pages later and i think that uh
Do you want to add anything here?
Is it anything I'm missing?
No, I think that was a good overview.
You could briefly highlight some other frameworks here.
So the wikis, as pioneered by the wikipedia.org website.
Those are solutions where you have, I mean, then you can produce contents a bit dynamically
with having people to jump in and contribute.
And essentially the editing of wikis is done on a web browser, so you don't really need
to just need to go to from view mode to edit mode and then you can contribute um
so that's not advantage um but i would say my personal reference from wikipedia
from wiki is sort of that they i mean in order for them to to become good you also need to have
a lot of let's say you need to have some editors and some moderators of content because otherwise
it's a little bit uncontrolled how they develop over time
yeah but the problem with wikis i think uh that it doesn't fit with the first one of the first
i the first item in our wish list that they are not version controlled yeah so they are to an
extent version control but they're not version control with the code because it's a typically
a different repository um actually it's like a yeah it's like a different repository so that's
That's why I think they are easy to use, typically,
but it's not what a research software engineer
or a software engineer would use to document their code, I think.
Yeah, I agree with that.
Yeah, it's not like that was for me,
that would not be, let's say, a primary choice.
But certainly, wikis can be a very good complement.
Latesh and PDF, those I would say are a little bit old school, which can be perfectly relevant.
In particular, if you are working with a lot of equations, LaTeX is the best tool.
But, yeah, the rendering, the contents can be a little bit, it's not always so smooth
to work with for, let's say, live documents on the web.
Yeah, and write your papers in LaTeX, but please give us something else to understand your
code.
Yeah, yeah.
That's my opinion.
in yeah yes i agree okay doc cdn and we will not look further into it here but this is a
tool which is very popular in the c++ community where you can decorate your code with
some some keywords and you can then from from that source like in the source code
decorated with this document keywords you can then generate documentation for
the classes and and objects for your code and like the programming interface
yeah it's i think it's uh one of the oldest tools that does api document api reference generation
like as i mentioned sphinx can do it for python code for example doxygen can do this for c++
for c++ and c and other languages yeah yeah i want to say that if you're using c++ or the
thing that you you possibly need to use doxygen to generate this but you can still use sphinx as
well because doxygen can actually talk to sphinx with a plugin a sphinx plugin called breathe
So, yeah, if you are a C++ developer and you want to, you like Sphinx, but you need to use Doxygen, then you can also put these things together if you like.
Yeah, that's a very nice opportunity that one can do this.
So, there are, yeah, Doxygen is popular for C++, but also for some other languages.
is you can find here some specific frameworks which are of relevance for Fortran and for Julia.
There's also an interesting tool Quarto to convert Markdown to various document types.
so let's move over here to the topic of encode documentation and here so now I mean we are
doing this this lesson here in streaming but we will not have any separate exercise sessions
in between but yeah so we will highlight a few things here and then we very much
encourage you to to sit down at another time so to say and and then work through these
exercises and you will then find also some template solutions
so in particular in this particular uh episode we are i think it's more discussions right
so but yeah yes that that's uh yeah you're right um but but nevertheless if you have time
uh i mean later today or so then then please go ahead also to do the exercises um
so here we have some examples here um this is about an if statement
has something to do with temperature and uh yeah [name] so so
so yeah basically if you see so there's a check uh so if the temperature is less than minus 50
um then we do something and now if you look at comment a i think okay now we check if temperature
is below minus 50. okay if i didn't know python then i would i would really okay this comment
would be would be have really helpful but if i could read python already i thought okay so that's
exactly what that if statement says right so it's not it doesn't give me more information if i know
what python syntax is okay actually it's it's also good that we use the temperature so that the
variable temperature is called temperature because then we know what it is and there are some codes
where things all variables are called a and b and then in that case yeah that comment would have
been helpful but yeah in in general i would say that comment b like we regard temperatures below
minus 50 degrees as measurement errors um yeah i think it's uh it's uh it's a more i like more
that comment uh although i would really love to be honest to have an error like in the print
statement error is temper temperature too low i would possibly put that so i would write in
that printf in this print uh string i would say it's a measurement error something like this
but yeah
that's at least
my opinion here
yes
very good points
I think that writing
comments and making readable code is
a bit of an art and
I'm not I don't think I'm good
at it so
my suggestion is always
iterate, right?
Try it, write something, and then go back
to your code after a while when you have time
and see, ah, maybe, you know, you first
start with version
A, and then you realize, oh,
but, I mean, this comment says something which is
obvious. Maybe I can change that to
version B to C. But, yeah, so
you can do it, like, incrementally.
You don't have to start and do things
perfect on the first time. But I think that, yeah.
To me, it's a reason,
so this example, comment A and comment B, are
like a realistic progression of like how to how you can improve code if and in
comments if you if you iterate on that if you go back to your code and I could
also think that perhaps this the comment or the type a is like now we check if
temperatures is below 50 let's say you have a year from now that you revise this if statement and
let's say you check also is it below a temperature or is it also above a temperature something like
that then i would say it could easily happen that you do that the code and the comment becomes
out of sync a comment or the type of b is more like um okay so here's like minus 50
degree check but you could also then let's say this is about defining
what intervals are could come and could be considered to be reasonable in the first place
So here is an interesting comment here in the lesson about the so-called zombie code
that you have some old implementation or some functionality and you comment it out and then
you replace it with some new code and the advice is here that you should strive then
to remove the out commented code and then I mean you retain it by means of the version control
but it's good to hide it away to avoid clutter.
I must say that I find this a little bit difficult in practice
because I somehow feel more confident if I have the zombie stuff in the code.
I mean within reason I think it depends so if I'm doing some quick changes yes
then I will keep the zombie codes just to but if not I would I mean if it's
something more long-term yeah then I would use version control maybe maybe
you can even say I will you know I can do like patch staging so get add minus
p and choose only you know the not basically i can say i want to add only the the parts which
don't contain this zombie code so there are there are options there so version control
gives you a lot of options there if you want to be like clean let's say um yeah yeah
So, here is something which is called Doxygen that we could say a few words about and that's
it's that, I mean, various languages support, I mean, having good constructions for self-documentation
or features so if you look here on this python snippet here we have it here described first as
like a pure comment in the code but
you could also put like description on what this function is doing
in this more like API documenting style and this connects a little bit to the kind of output that
you can get if you have a like a program that you are you're executing it by long by typing
the name in in a terminal window you then offer they have some flags to steer the execution of
command and one of the standard flags is dash dash help and if you don't have the command name
that's just help then the contents which you have like in docstrings is what then will be shown
yeah and also sphinx and doxygen can actually you know take this extract this docstrings and create
the api so yeah yeah api documentation so i'm looking here on the clock here uh [name] and
i think perhaps we could do like this that that we we spend some three four minutes here on
reading files yep and and then we will be at another point where we go for a break
and then after break we can then start with the sphinx yep okay
So writing good README files.
So what can we say about this?
So what's your experience, [name], what would you like to see from a good README file?
um so as people have mentioned uh so well i think a good readme file uh well it's a part of the
documentation right so but i think it shouldn't contain the whole documentation sometimes it's
like um it's nice to split it into different files if possible there is there is a catch there
but yeah so uh for example having links in a in a i think you know as a feature of markdown or
you know of general uh technology that you can use when you use when you write uh ring me files um
so and it's also nice to have some kind of um markup that says for example this important part
um so it's nice to have like uh so it's mentioned here in the in the first exercise which is walk
through like you can actually specify some uh like some you know that some parts are more important
than others uh yeah and uh yeah you can have images and you can also have like badges uh like
like the one that is shown if you scroll a little down in the in the notes yeah um yeah it can be
useful to have some badges to to signal like uh okay my code has passed the the the all the tests
and you can have a badge there let's say that is red if not if the test failed or you know uh can
show also the license right away what kind of license is there so there's many different badges
you can put there um it's a bit eye candy and i think people some people find it a bit of a gimmick
to have these kind of things but it's nice i think it's a it's a way to signal things and actually
the readme the readme file you have in your repository on your github repository github
whatever it's like the the entrance of like like your the front your front door right so that's how
what the first thing that people have as the people see when when they look at your repository
so yeah i was from my experience uh i prefer a lot where the readme files stand on their own
so certainly i mean you can have links you can have badges but it's also good if i mean
you have to really file in itself without following the links or without clicking the
badges if that can tell you upfront and that will also be sometimes let's say you work on on a
on the login node of a supercomputer then could even be that you cannot really click the link
because you don't have a web browser on that login node yeah true true true yeah but it can
tell you for example a link to to other files in the repository for example the contributing guide
can be actually linked in the the readme although maybe it doesn't need to be linked because
typically it's written in a in a file which has a like it's called contributing.md or the installation
guide yeah you can link it from the readme if you wish but it's usually called install so you
can actually yeah so that is this kind of um standard file names for different kind of
documentation the readme is one of them of course and it's the most important in this case and you
you could you could put links to those if you if you wish if it's relevant yeah and certainly this
with having different file names like you can read me you can have install you can have contributing
that's i mean these standards are quite useful because that makes the reader find
the specific content very quickly and that's something i appreciate from a readme or from
an install file is this if if it can get a grip on it within i mean really like 30 seconds or one
minute because could be on some days that you have you're looking into five readmes for five
different programs. And the more clarity you can have upfront, the better.
Yeah. And it's actually interesting here, if you have detailed descriptions, you can actually
use these details tags, where you can actually hide some long things, some long descriptions,
and just show a short summary in this case and it's actually interesting because this is an
example of a feature of markdown which is that you can actually put in line in in the code in
your markdown code let's say but it's document you can put html code this is actually html if
you look at this uh so there are html tags and yeah you can use that in a markdown file as well
and it should be rendered as as expected as if we have it as if it was html
so um
if you are on on this page of the lesson um you can just so this first block here was actually um
we had it labeled as an exercise and you can also find two other exercises here
in the section of the lesson. I think that we will now shortly go for a
break and I'd say that this exercise number two and exercise three
that you could come back to this on your own later and there are good template solutions
here and now after break we will start the topic of documentation with swings and markdown.
Just one thing about this readme exercises well there's going to be a bring your code
session they are going to be bring your code sessions in the next weeks so maybe that's
thing that one could discuss in those sessions. That's a very good suggestion.
So let's just very quickly move over to the shared document to see what we have here.
Let's have 10 minutes of a break.
So shall we go in at 12 past the hour?
Yes, that sounds good.
So yeah, see you all at 12 past the full hour.
Bye.
you
Hello, we are back.
okay so did you have a refreshing break [name] yes yes I was filling up with
coffee coffee like yeah yeah a lot of jokes about coffee I don't remember any
at the moment but yeah we need coffee coffee so so we do more hands-on ish
part of the lesson at the moment right so now we are switching to how to use
Sphinx and Markdown so I'm showing the notes now there's a link in the note we
should show we should point to the parts we're going to talk about now and so I
will since this is a hands-on part I will show a lot my shell my terminal
Okay. I'm going to switch to my terminal now. Okay. Okay. So you can see the terminal in
his all, it's all glory. So for this part, for this hands-on, we are going to use a conda
environment. I think, I don't know if anybody has used it before during the workshop, but
yeah, so in the installation instructions for the workshop,
it was written how it was discussed how to set up a conda
environment. It's, it's a couple of commands, but you need to
have conda or like the conda package manager installed on
your system, at least. Okay. So the cool thing is actually that
with this setup, if you if you're not ready, now we can
still watch the stream later after you have set up
conda if you haven't done that. But let's assume you have done
that. Then you can follow what we are doing now. So what I'm
going to do now is to show you how to use Sphinx. Sphinx is one
of the documentation generators that we have discussed before.
okay it takes markdown files structure text files and then generates
different kinds of documentation out of it we are going to focus today on the html
kind of generation of the web pages kind of output because it's the thing that we can publish on the
web you see that most easily um yeah so um sphinx is a python package which is actually present in
the conda environment for code refinery so i'm going to activate the the environment of code
yep now it's up it's active you can see that my
I didn't want to do this.
You can see that my prompt has changed and now
the environment which was previously the base one,
it's now switched to code refinery.
Just to check, what kind of version do I have here of Python?
Now I have 3.12.9, it's correct.
For you, it could be slightly different,
but it's still fine as long as it's like 3.11, 3.9.
I think up to 3.9 should be okay.
Okay.
One thing we need is Sphinx build.
Build.
Okay.
And let's check the version.
The version I have is 7.2.6.
It's okay.
At least this command has run without errors.
And the other thing we want to use is the quick start tool.
Sphinx quick.
Okay.
and let's check the version yeah so similar to the previous one and we also want to check um
if the parser we're going to use uh so it's it's if we can use the so-called um my sd so the
markedly structured text parser so because that's the this format we want to use to write our
documentation okay and in order to check that you can use python minus c so if you use python minus
c it's um it's it's going to execute the problem that follows in in the double quotes in this case
import import uh mysd rsr okay it's a the shortest python program ever just one line which imports
this and if there's no errors it's fine so and i have no errors okay so like yeah yes 15 years so
um if you want it um you're very much encouraged to type along with [name] but if you for some
reason do not have the content environment available then you could also just i mean
relax and listen in yeah i will try to be entertaining and funny um so that at least
you won't follow you won't fall asleep um yeah at least try to keep up the discussion is last
um as we did in the last uh in the previous part in the first part so now we have verified the
it up okay and we can start hacking at our documentation so i will create a directory
and seed into it doc example okay and now i can do sphinx quick start so
So quick start, and this command now will ask me a couple of questions.
So here it will ask me if I want to separate source and build directory, I will go for
the default answers.
So yes, project name, I will say test documentation.
Okay, so you choose no, so you will have them in the same directories?
Yeah, at the moment should be okay, which was the recommended thing.
Yeah, yeah, no, no, it's perfectly fine.
And yeah, so actually I don't have a lot of experience with Sphinx.
I have some, but I know that [name] has more.
So I think that [name] may correct me if I'm doing something wrong, please do.
approach release 0.1 it's a okay and then the project language is english let's try that even
if it's not my uh my native language so now you can look at um yeah at the content of the
let's clear here shall i clear should i clear maybe i don't have to uh you can see what how
what has been created you you remember that this was actually an empty directory
And now Sphinx Quickstart has created all this stuff for me, okay?
And there's some things we could talk about,
but the most important are actually this, like, I think this is this index.rst, okay?
Rst is the extension that stands for restructured text.
So let's have a look at it.
In order to look at it, I will use Vim, okay?
So, if you don't know how to exit Vim, ask in the notes and if you get dropped.
But maybe you can use anything else.
I use Vim because I'm comfortable with it.
But you can use Nano, for example, or Cat.
Cat is not an editor, but you can still see.
So, what does it say here?
Well, it says, yeah, it gives us like a comment at the beginning.
This is not going to be printed out.
Then there's a heading.
Then actually this is a directive in restarted text that tells the Sphinx
to create a table of content there, TOC, table of content.
and uh yeah so what we actually want to do now okay is to remove for the moment this indices
and table section because we don't care about that okay um thank you very much swings quick
start but we don't need that um so how do we add content to our um to our documentation well
we need to here add file names
in this case so i'm going to to create a file uh so here i mentioned a file name i need to create
a file with the that name in my home directory to make sure that you know in my home there in
the directory of the the project uh and as things will look at it and will render it okay so uh yeah
So we will go to this.
There's one comment I want to do.
As you may be familiar with, if you're using Python,
you know that in Python, white space is important,
so that the indentation level is important.
Here, the indentation level is important as well.
So in this case, I need to make sure that some feature.md
is at the same indentation level as this other block.
So now I can save it, but I need to still do one thing.
So in order for Sphinx to be able to parse this kind of markdown files,
I need to edit the configuration of it.
So I open conf.py.
Conf.py is Python.
It's a Python code that tells, it's a file made up of Python code that tells Sphinx how to configure itself.
So the syntax here is Python.
And here, what I'm going to do is to add my st, my st underscore parser to the list of extensions.
And then I can save and exit.
okay and now i need to uh add uh some this some feature dot md file
and um for the in the interest of time i will uh copy uh and paste it here
the con the content which we should have you can see there are some some markdown features we are
using so we are um have it we have a level one heading then we have a subsection which is level
two heading then we have some items in lists and we have nested items and that's nested lists right
and you see that actually we have these empty surrounding lines which are required i don't
know if it is a thing which is needed also for markdown i think it's also not just the this
this particular flavor of Markdown, but also generally Markdown, you may need
these empty sounding lines around. I'm not sure, do you know?
I don't know all of this by heart, but it's very important to be aware of this, that both, I mean,
like as in general in Python, that I mean spacing as tabulated spacing are important, and then also
here for the generation of the html contents that spacing matters sometimes yeah so horizontal
spacing here that this you can see the yeah the indentation but also vertical spacing let's say
yeah so that that's very common error if the rendered contents do not display properly
spacing is one of the first things to check yeah so i'll save that and then let's have a look
at what we have in the repository you should see let's say ls minus one so that we see everything
in a in a in a column and yeah okay so if it looks like this in your directory then it should be fine
okay and uh yeah so now how do we build uh the documentation um let's do this uh sphinx
build dot meaning the current directory so we want to build the commutation which is in the
current directory and um we wanted the the the produced documentation the the render
documentation to be in the underscore build directory common uh common choice so if i now
run this command with enter uh you see that it uh tells me okay so the html pages are in build
everything looks green uh no errors okay good so now if we look at um um build uh we see that
there's some stuff there the most important thing in the generated documentation is this index.html
okay this index.html is the like the rendered version of index.rst
yeah so we have we can have a look at how it looks like right so let's do now open
i mean in i'm on a linux machine on ubuntu so i can use open build index index index.html
now we have many windows open many browser windows open so where will this go
So these HTML files that you render now, these are a set of static HTML files. That means
for previewing locally on your machine, you can simply just open them in a web browser.
It didn't work for me. Let's try again. Okay. It doesn't like it. Wait, it's interesting.
so I'll go to a browser and show you
so this is notes but if I do in file
I don't understand why it can't work
let me see
I
so wait a moment so i mean having the static html files is
they are rather smooth to work with because you do not need a web
server to to host them so i need to do some magic sorry
I need to do because now the problem is that I'm using a training so that there's some things
possibly I shouldn't tell you I shouldn't have I don't have to tell you so if [name] can host
the show for the next 30 seconds I may actually fix this and show you finally how our Sphinx
documentation looks like. Yes, so I'm looking now here on the shared document
and there's a question here. So why do you name the directory with a leading
underscore build with a dash? Someone has answered here. So it's a convention.
and so it's not something that is required for any syntaxic reason or so but it is a convention
so when [name] used this swings start command to initiate this swings document
there was this question here about
Let me just go to it myself.
Yeah, the question about separating source and build directories where
and is the default and so one thing within general is good if you are working with
rendered content from some set of source files indeed right now we're talking about
strings document but it could also be let's say doc cdn rendered contents is this that typically
what you do want is to have
the source contents in the git repository
but you typically would like to avoid
to add and commit the rendered
contents to the git repository and that
that's rather natural in a way because otherwise you have a bit of redundancy of
having both source and rendered contents
which after all contain the same contents just it's in raw form or in so to say readable form
and this in particular is important in case you are including
figures in your document and if you have let's say in figures that you pull in from outside of your
core repository i mean you do not want to do that in the repository i can show you now i think
wait a moment i have managed to find a workaround yeah so that's how our first
um our first documentation project looks like um yeah so
So you can see that this is the index, yeah?
So we have some feature.
This some feature is actually the, let's look at index.rsc.
So this is what comes out of this file, somefeatures.md.
Then if I open somefeature.md, you see that I have this heading and subsection.
and these two things these two headings match what I have here and if I click on some feature then I
I show here I I see here something familiar that looks a bit like a rendering of what I
have here okay this is plain text and this instead HTML right yeah if you go over with the mouse here
in the document what happens then do you see some links yeah so yeah here yeah you have some feature
and then you have subsection right yeah so you have you know when you're at subsection if you
right click here yeah yeah link to this heading uh you can you can copy the link yeah so that's
extremely useful feature that you get for free with uh swing stocks so you get like the the
direct the direct links to individual sections and paragraphs are available
which are typically the page the web page itself plus this hash and then a little something which
follows the hash which is uh typically the subheading the the like the the link in the
page so to say yeah yeah the section yeah yeah okay so uh shall we continue with the
yeah so um now there's uh actually an interesting uh list of things you can add to the uh to your
um uh i'll actually show the because there's a lot of things you can do right so uh for example
we can have additional kind of levels of heading.
You can go up to level four, I think, which is a lot.
I think you should just try to stay as like level one, level two, or level three.
If you want, you can get to level four of nested headings.
You can also have links, as we mentioned before.
like and the the links are written like this so if you need to type here like
the text that you want to be shown and then and then in instead in the round
brackets you type the the proper link the proper address yeah URL you want to
connect uh so for example in this case you will see um a link where the text is a link and then
it will link to this to this website okay um you can also have images um i don't have an image to
show you at the moment but um so here for example i can show you how to do this so it works in a
similar way you have um square brackets there you need to type an alt text and which is like
the text which will be shown if the image is not available so um and then you have like the
the link to where to to the image file yeah you can also have things like numbered lists
and numbered lists are
they start with a number, so the items on the list
start with a number, item 1 is item 1
item 2 is item 2, but actually
this is a funny feature of Markdown, that actually
if you start going on with one dot
these items will be actually
renumbered for you. Item 3
and item 4. And so I think you understood
what I mean here. And you can have simple tables
and so you can
have
simple tables written like this. Let's
make a bit of
like that.
It's important to get this heading
right, I think, and then
you can say,
let's have a little thing here.
So, have a
little table that tells if a number is
prime or not.
One is not prime,
and then, I mean, I think
it's debatable, right? But then
you can have
two is actually prime,
So let's, yes, and then also three is prime, and so on.
And most importantly, now come to code blocks.
So the following is a Python code block.
And then how do you do that?
So you start with three backticks, then you type the programming language you want to use,
in this case python and then you can say dev hello and then
and then you can go like that and then when you are done with writing your
code block you can add another three ticks and yeah you can do the same with c
you can also include files i mean in the in the in the notes it's written the notes in the
in the material and uh yeah it's written how to add actually literally file from somewhere else
and you can also use jupiter notebooks actually so um you can have a file of the jupiter notebook
and you can include it in in your documentation if you need um so uh yeah so um so what happens
here i mean when you label it here with python or you label it with c is that i mean you would
then have this nice i mean syntax highlighting in the rendered html yeah and one thing it's
quite important for audio audience i think is that you can have equations yeah yeah so for example
you can have an um math so here it's a bit different you have this uh uh these braces
here but you can have something like a squared plus b squared equal c squared okay you can have
much more complicated things like that you can also have uh wait a moment um yeah you can also
have that in line uh yeah so there's a lot of things you can do with it and i think everything
which is reasonable uh reasonable i think um is quite it's covered by sphinx so let's see how it
looks like. So if I do things, build, I will build again. So
yeah, it tells me, for example, that this image file that I have
added didn't, it was not found. But let's see how it looks like.
I need to do a little trick again.
Yeah. So in the meanwhile, I commented about equations. So
this can be written in LaTeX format and that's quite useful because if you for instance have
some old documents which are written in as LaTeX documents then you can migrate over directly the
equations and then you put it put them here into to the Sphinx document and then they will be
I mean, not the postscript file, but it will be rendered to HTML.
This is LaTeX.
Yeah. And yeah.
So I build it, then go back to my browser.
I think, oh, but this doesn't show. Why?
Because I need to press F5.
It didn't show it.
Ah, yeah, because I need to do another little step before,
which you don't have to do.
But if I do F5 now, this latex will appear.
Okay, so I think...
So I'm curious, so what happens if you have some syntactic error in the file?
I mean, if you, by mistake, if you change from no to yes in the table,
but you then get it, let's say,
so that the alignment of the vertical bars is incorrect.
What happens then?
So if I do something like this, let's break this down.
Yeah, you break it and then you're sure.
Let's see what happens.
Will it work anyway?
So I got no additional wordings, so maybe it worked.
Let's look now at the rendered version here.
So, yeah, it worked.
Okay, interesting.
Then it was tolerated here.
This was in Markdown, okay.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, okay.
Then, well, with RST, I think it would not have worked.
I don't...
But you would then...
The point I wanted to make is this,
that this swing stocks is rather user-friendly,
So if you break things, you sort of get like a warning message or you get like an error message.
And one thing I wanted to show you to attract your attention to is I said that the number list will be numbered automatically.
Even if I wrote 1.2.2 dot, 1 dot, et cetera, it will show as 1, 2, 3, 4 instead.
OK, so, yeah, it does. Yeah, there are some convenience features.
also this you don't have to align your tables perfectly because they will be rendered instead
by your browser in in a correct way uh yes there are some um some yeah it it's it's it's nice you
don't have to be really so a lot a lot of so as things understand what you want to do in some
cases and will will do it for you right so another thing i want to possibly just show because i'm not
sure if we have time is that um but i think it would be nice to show this right uh auto generating
documentation from python dot strings right i think maybe i can i can show you briefly how to
do this so let's say we have a multiply dot pi uh file which is which contains some some python code
which i will now paste here okay and save okay so if i now uh want um to add
the this uh this function to my documentation uh how can we do that um well
i need to do some steps first so i need to change my configuration uh and i need to make it so that
the among the extensions i also mentioned a thing called auto doc auto doc two okay so this is uh
it was essential to auto generate documentation and in addition to that i also need to say
doc two packages wait a moment
and then i can say um yeah the file that i want to to process with autodoc
multiply.py, okay?
Yeah, because I want to tell Autodoc,
hey, please, Autodoc,
parse this multiply.py file, okay?
And then this is the first thing I need to change.
Then I need to change index.rst
because I want to,
things to say, okay,
so now after some features,
some feature.md,
I would like you to add
call, like the API documentation.
So apdoc index.
So basically, this autodoc will create a file directory
called apidox and there's going to be an index in it
and I want Sphinx to include it.
So now, if I do Sphinx build,
Sphinx build, yeah, wait, it doesn't like that.
sphinx build dot build okay do that okay so with this command sphinx build dot i rebuild
the documentation i need to do my little trick here and then i should be able to show you
again this so let's go to the to the main page yeah i click here and then you can see that
there's a new thing that's popped up which is the api reference okay and the api reference of
multiply and if i look into this multiply so then you see that i get something which looks
very similar to the doc string that i had here so which i will open now and yeah wait a moment so
yeah yeah multiply two numbers parameters a parameter b and return and that's what i see
here right so we have the parameters and returns and this is uh similar i mean yeah it's similar
to what you have in the numpy documentation for example okay which may be the fastest thing say
uses that is used to to uh to document a lot of python projects you were saying yeah so so it's
clear here that if you would like to render in the way that [name] did here, contents of this type,
I mean doing it, auto-generating it from the source code itself from a doc screen, I mean
that's really the way to do it because if you run, I mean if you edit this material a little bit
it out of sync with the source code.
Yeah, well, it typically would get out of sync.
So the take home message is to strive to have it
like integrated here with the source code itself.
Yeah, so that it would be easier for you to write it
and easier for your colleagues to write.
So yeah, write doc strings
and then there will be other documentation automatically
is something the docs can do for you for other languages and julia i mean a lot of languages
they have similar things so if you're not using python use another language i'm sure that there
is a packet that gives you this if this this um this uh capabilities feature so yeah indeed yeah
i think that maybe yeah maybe we also mentioned here in the in the in our uh notes in there in
the less lecture notes it is anyway um i think i would like to move now quickly to um to the next
bit unless we have some questions if there are questions we should always
uh spend a bit of time talking about those if there's anything specific
Okay. So one thing I want to talk about is this. I will open the material, the teaching
material here. So it goes with the Deploying Sphinx Documentation to GitHub Pages. So here
It's a quick exercise which I can show you directly on GitHub.
So you don't need to have followed what we've done before.
I can just go from here.
So we have a documentation example,
which is a project template on GitHub.
And we can use that to show how to publish things on using GitHub Pages.
GitHub Pages is a feature of GitHub that allows you to show the kind of websites that are composed, that Sphinx creates.
So static web pages.
Static web pages are pages which do not require the web server to actually do anything fancy.
They just require the web server to give them.
okay so to give it to the browser that that wants to to see them okay uh so how to do that there's
a documentation example uh repository i will uh click on the link uh so and uh i can do i like test
gh pages okay um create the repository and then what do i have here
the the yeah everything is being generated for me and uh yeah so i have some some content already so
So the thing I need to do, actually, here, is to add an action.
So GitHub has not just the pages feature, but there's a thing which is called actions,
which is a way to do a lot of things, actually, but in an automatic way.
So we can tell now GitHub to perform some operations on this repository.
so what we can do now is actually we don't have to
start to click here you can go to the code and then
I can create a file that is
that will contain the workflow
the actions that GitHub needs to perform in this repository
so these GitHub actions files are
contained in GitHub
then
workflows
this is the standard
path where GitHub is going to look for
when he
looks for actions and then the
name of the file would be
documentation.yaml
so this is
the file I want to create
and the content of the file will
be copied from
the material, oh wait, I need to copy
and paste, yeah, and
so, we are saying
I will just quickly comment on what are these things, so we are saying, okay, so
there's a workflow called documentation, which will be run when there's
when someone pushes to the repository, when there's a pull request, and
when someone wants to run this workflow manually
and this job, this
workflow is made out of jobs, a list of jobs, in this case there's only one
job called docs, which runs on a container
it needs a container to start, and the containers were mentioned yesterday
it's a container that is based on Ubuntu
and then there are some steps here, first
we are going to check out the repository, and to do so we are going to
use an action that has been written by someone else.
Then there's another action that is made to set up Python,
and this action has been written by someone else as well.
Then we had another step,
which is the installation of our dependencies.
We have our pip command here to store everything we need.
Then we have the build command to build everything,
the sphinx build command okay and then we have eventually our last action last our last step
which does some magic here which means um some trying to simplify uh take whatever we have
created in the underscore build directory and uh put it on a new branch called gh pages okay
and this gith pages is also an orphan branch
which means that it has no parent
and so on.
So I can commit the changes now
and say
create the commutation.yaml
I would never do this, I would never leave
the default commit message
but that's what we need to do here.
And now I have this
actions, this action defined
the next thing I need to do is
to enable
GitHub pages for this repository. So, how do I do that? I go
to the settings of the repository, go to pages,
and then I say, okay, deploy from a branch. That's okay.
Then I need to choose the branch. But first, I need to actually
I need the branch to be created. So, let's go to actions
first. Okay. I need to, okay, so create documentation on YML.
This has actually run. So, I should see
here and if i go to code i should see a gh page gh pages branch appearing okay then i can go back
to the settings and pages and then i should be able to select here gh pages which was not available
before so if i do that and save then if i go back to actions then a new workflow will restart which
will take what I have on the branch.ghpages, which is my
render documentation, and actually publish that on GitHub pages. And you see
that there's a new
workflow here that is happening. See, the build took five seconds,
build status took three seconds, and now it's deploying.
So, it doesn't take very long
technically. And we are almost out of time.
so but let me show you this okay so now i have some documentation which is an empty project
here and it's shown on our github pages so it's visible to everybody so if you go to this
if you go to this to this address on your on your browser you will see what i have just created yeah
Yeah, so this is really neat. And so, I mean, all of these steps that you showed here with this
YAML file and the actions, I mean, the things that you're activating on GitHub here,
these are things which are, so to say, living on GitHub.
They are corresponding things on GitLab and on Bitbucket and so forth.
uh and unfortunately the syntax is different actually on gitlab is much simpler uh and
there's also a uh guided procedure if you have a repository on gitlab but anyway uh yeah you get
the idea i guess i hope that the idea that the whole the hope here is that you get the idea that
you know you can yeah this platforms github and gitlab give you this opportunity to host static
websites, which you can generate with things or other projects
or other other or other tools. So shall we go to the notes and
see if there's anything we need to discuss or anything that we
can? Yeah, we have like three minutes for conversation.
there is okay starting with the last question here so are the limitations to being able to
use this with private repositories and i think you can't i think you cannot on github
uh not not for free not for free yeah but if you pay for it enterprise and so on then yes
if you are an academic user
do you qualify for
pro anyway so I guess it depends
if you register with an academic
it used to be that if you registered with an academic
email address then you would
be automatically
considering the pro
tier so you would be able to have that
yeah I'm not really up to
speed what was currently
the offering from github
but in general I mean you get
some of it a little bit
for free and and if you want more capacity you need to pay for it which is rather reasonable
and and that's something actually that we will come to tomorrow in the testing lesson because
the the rendering of this fengs document that [name]l has set up here to run on github
that that's rather lightweight this is sort of you only need a little bit of hardware on the
the server side here on GitHub to render the HTML and then also toast it.
When you come to things like testing and the so-called continuous development
workflows, where you might then run big tests,
then more hardware is booked for longer time.
And there you will also have this
situation where you get a little bit of capacity for free
but if you do want to do more heavy stuff you need to start pay for it monthly
there are ways out of this but uh yeah they can be a bit harder to to set up
but yeah it will be discussed tomorrow yeah yeah so
So now we showed it here on how to get it up on GitHub pages and you find in the lesson
material that you can do similar things then on GitLab and also on Bitbucket.
Yeah, I never used Bitbucket.
I have quite some experience with GitLab.
The only thing is that GitLab allows you to have private, let's say, pages,
but they need to be activated centrally.
So your GitLab instance may or may not have the pages feature activated.
So, yeah, some of the servers they have.
So GitLab.com for sure, but if your institution has their own GitLab server,
well you need to check if the page is available there. Yes indeed so many institutions do have
their own instances of GitHub or GitHub servers and then you can work with them within let's say
I mean within all of your organization and perhaps also with some partner organizations.
good good good um so now we are going to have a lunch break um and we'll be back
uh with uh with the i will be back with [name] talking about jupiter notebooks if you have
questions you can still ask uh in the in the notes in the collaborative document
but we'll try to answer them anyway.
And well, I mean, if you want to join
the bring your own code sessions in the future,
well, I think documentation is also something
that can be discussed there.
So with you personally, I'd say.
Yeah.
So what can I say?
Yeah, yeah, good.
So thank you, [name], and bye, everyone.
Thank you.
you
One.
Hello.
So, welcome back.
Hello, [name].
Thanks.
Good afternoon.
So, I was here yesterday, so I guess I don't need to do much of an introduction.
I just go into Jupyter Notebooks.
And also, you were here in the morning.
Yeah.
If someone is just joining us now, hello, and let's get started.
So, what are we talking about?
We're talking about Jupyter Notebooks and, well, talk a bit about various things.
So, motivations for using Jupyter Notebooks.
Then we will discuss how to launch a notebook.
We'll look at the interface, some of the shortcuts, how to basically make your life easier, at
least when working with notebooks.
And we'll have a look at the first show here, a first computational notebook, so an example
of it.
Then we will have a break.
And then after that, [name] will talk to us, tell us about how to do version control with
notebooks, which is an important thing, I would say.
So it actually matches the content of the previous week, at least.
And then talking about how to share notebooks, right?
So this is also, the sharing notebooks is also a response to one of the questions that
came up yesterday.
What do you do when all of your code is in a notebook and it's not actually
runnable as a program in that way?
Well, let's see.
I think, yeah, so writing code in proper code, like in text files or in
notebooks, well, I mean, it's a thing that we're going to discuss now, I
would say.
So what are the motivations for using Jupyter, Jupyter Notebooks?
And Notebooks in general, there's not just Jupyter, but there's many other kinds.
I think that Jupyter was one of the first widely used implementation of this paradigm called literate programming,
where you mix code with text, with explanations in prose, let's say.
And, but not only, okay, so in the case of Jupyter Notebooks, I think they are used nowadays for like data science-y workflows, I would say, and where you need to, you have some code that produces some pictures, some plots.
So, you want to show the plots, you want to show the code that has produced the plots
for context, and you want also to add some context that you can write, maybe some shows,
some equations and so on.
So, in a sense, you are documenting your code in yet another way compared to what we saw
this morning.
Right?
Yeah.
So, it's like, instead of writing just code, you'd write a lot of documentation with a
code.
so um i mean so Jupyter is also notebooks in general is also a great way of documenting
a library so you can have your documentation written as notebooks and then you have
like examples of calls to your program that produce some result that then the user can just
go and modify and see what happens yeah yeah and i think that as we mentioned you can have Jupyter
notebooks in your documentation your web uh documentation and those notebooks are runnable
so you can even validate them so it's a you can have so it's a it's a way you can basically write
a tutorial make it make sure with jupiter make sure that it runs as it should and yeah so that's
a way you can have actually automated tested documentation so stay tuned for automated
testing for tomorrow uh but yeah so that's why i actually like jupiter notebooks that's what i
the promise that they have yeah and but in general um i think the important
more general uh i think more more general use of that is when you have like a
computational narrative that you want to show so yeah you do some data analysis let's say and you
want to show uh the results with the code and so on and yeah it's uh it's it's great for that
especially if you need to communicate with other people that may not exactly know the code uh or
know maybe not even know how to code but at least they can see the plot and and
yeah and and get insight with from that yeah so there are some there please please yeah so they
The two things below, I guess, are actually pretty much examples of something that's very useful.
You can essentially reproduce or recreate your paper with a notebook and include the code to produce the plots and all of that.
So I could tell the whole story by doing the math as you go.
To connect ourselves with the topics of yesterday, so like reproducible science.
uh yeah that's that's a uh quite a quite a boost to that i would say yep so um yeah so for example
here we have some uh examples of uh some notebooks uh that uh you can uh load in in binder binder
it's a platform that allows you to run some notebooks on the web without actually having
to install anything on your on your site so we will see this later so [name] will show us
how to use binder and yeah so i will not go into into the details here but here yeah to wet your
appetite let's say we have some some different some example of the uh of jupiter notebooks
coming from different uh domains different scientific domains um yeah one about the
gravitational wave discovery nobel prize and other things uh you know so something related to
humanities i would say yes so um there are some use cases that work really well for for us uh for
for jupiter notebooks for example uh yeah so we have a really uh linear workflow okay with the
uh where you need to read data to filter it then to some statistic and plot okay and then you want
You want to experiment with new ideas, testing new libraries and maybe databases or whatever.
And they're also interactive.
So that's one of the great reasons to use it.
I mean, there are also alternatives typically with high-level languages where you can just turn on like the Python interpreter and see something.
But actually, with Jupyter, it's nicer because you can plot in the notebook.
so it's it's a bit it's a easier and more user-friendly um environment to actually do
interactive work in uh yeah and you can share explain code to colleagues for teaching for
teaching i've used jupiter jupiter notebooks a lot um yeah and keeping track of interactive
sessions like a digital lab notebook um and yeah so also yeah when you publish articles you can
actually supplement some information for that to those but there are also some pitfalls right so
these are very nice use cases but there are some some issues there so for example if you don't have
a very um very simple flow of code so if it's not linear um then it can be difficult
if you have a large code base you you may actually use jupyter notebooks as like at the top of this
code base right so you could um you may have some functions that are written in some other
in some files and in some proper source files and then you can import those uh like use those
in the in the notebook but you cannot write your whole code base in uh in jupiter i would say i
mean you can try but it's very difficult and clunky yeah i mean people often go a bit too far
with how much they include in a notebook but yeah um when you start including functions for example
then it's probably already a good idea to start moving those functions into a separate file
So anything that the viewer doesn't need to see probably should not be in the notebook is basically my recommendation, but just personally, basically.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I think that one should safeguard themselves from doing this by making, okay, so you're going to use notebooks, good.
but consider whenever you start a notebook
also to have basically a background infrastructure
where you have a properly set up project for your own language.
Then again, of course,
one thing that notebooks are really good for
is kind of fiddling around with stuff,
trying different things.
Then you might in fact have some cells that you don't run
and some cells that you run in a random order
to get things to work and so on.
So like all of these pitfalls happen for a reason
and sometimes there's a good reason for it.
So it's just that when you publish it
or when you try, when it gets big,
when you start sharing it with someone else,
it is a good idea to clean it up
and make it more presentable.
Yeah, yeah, definitely, definitely.
But yeah, the cool thing is that
they lend themselves for for rapid prototyping. And yeah, so
that's actually quite, quite good. So I would say, let's go
to, to the next episode in the lesson, I think I hope we have
made the case for Jupyter notebooks. And so we can show
the how to use them, let's say, you know, a bit. So it's a bit
the basics but just like everybody um on you know on the same page um i will now switch um to
uh switch my share to to the um to the the terminal okay for a moment okay and yeah so
So here I have a terminal, and here, what should I do here?
So I will create a director called JupyterLabDemo.
LabDemo.
Yeah, create that.
And then what should I do next?
cd JupyterLabDemo.
LabDemo.
And then I will use the conda environment that we discussed about in the previous episodes to start it.
So I first of all activate conda, the right environment, and activate code.
That's how I call that.
And then I should be able just to invoke JupyterLab.
Okay, yep, and now JupyterLab should be after this huge blurb.
So it will open it in the browser window if it finds the browser.
Or you can also, it tells you how to open it in a browser if it doesn't pop up immediately,
but it's a little bit hidden in all of that text that you just saw.
so it's the part that says
starts with HTTP and has this token
equals something
yeah I could copy that
but fortunately in my case
there's no need for that and I have this
beautiful interface
that shows me
some different things
so let me just
copy
the notes
okay
JupyterLab
so how actually does it work so you have seen that in my terminal i have actually started
jupyter lab the server of jupyter lab okay there's a web server attached to it okay
and yeah let's show here i think it's clear from the notes so this is the program i have started
in my in my terminal then in the browser i'm able to to talk to this to interact with the server
and of course there's a user here and then the notebook server
is able to interact with the
file, the notebook file, also with the file system, with everything which is in the
folder where you started the JupyterLab
server and in addition
the notebook server itself will talk to a kernel. The kernel is
not your operating system kernel
But it's like the thing that actually runs the code
that was written in the notebook.
So the kernel is actually running code.
It's interpreting the code.
So in Jupyter, the name actually comes from Julia, Python, and R.
So there's default kernels for Julia, Python, and R.
And there's different kernels.
Well, yeah, there's kernels for those three languages,
but also other languages.
so you could have multiple kernels open at the same time
but I guess we'll just have one for Python
Yeah, so for example
in my case I have a Python 3 kernel
but since I'm a bit weird I have also
a kernel for Bash
which is why I could do this
I'm not going to do this
I guess not
Yeah, so well you have
two different kernels then
And there's also for C++ for example
if some of you is interested in
having c++ developed in a in a in a notebook then you can also use c++ there why not yeah
so um other things we can let's have a look at the interface so um it's better to do this here
because it's a bit uh there's more stuff here i can show so here there's ways to actually create
a new they have a file browser you have a way to create new files uh then here on the
if you want to can actually collapse this this uh um navigation bar on the left
um then here on the right you have uh you have the notebook and you can see the notebook has
different things so you can have like two kinds of cells so the the content of a of a notebook
is organizing cells you have markdown cells which are your pros your content your comments
that contain also formulas for example then you have uh cells uh code cells here for example you
have a cursor and then uh you have also input the the output right so if you're pointing at
something with the mouse and maybe we don't or i don't see your mouse oh okay um yes unfortunately
no my mouse is not visible it's interesting um well but there is um so the gray light gray areas
are code and the um the white areas with text are markdown cells and i guess we can show how
that works yeah so wait a moment uh can i get back to that okay good yes i will show that um
there will be plenty of time to show this and uh yeah so the control here two kinds of cells so
there are markdown cells and uh yeah you have all the features of markdown there so you you can
create headings you can create links you can have um bold italics strike through and also code which
is in line can you see this um so we can if you need to type code but uh in in a in a not in its
own cell but in in the you can do that uh you can have lists with the bullet points or um yeah or
number of the lists equations and so on so these are all the things we discussed
previously we showed previously in you know when you use markdown and then you have code cells
yeah so yeah code cells um and yeah and you you create these two can do kind of things
called cells have also outputs and it goes on like that um yeah so um
so the interface has
the JupyterLab interface has
a little
some shortcuts, something we'll discuss
now about this.
Yeah, those are the kinds of things that it's better
to check when you
when you have
used it for a moment.
But don't wait too long though.
So
okay, so what should we do next?
Should we start this demonstration,
the first computational notebook?
Yes.
So here in the notes,
you have a discussion
on what are the shortcuts.
But yeah, so I'll start
a first computational notebook.
And I think I can get rid of this
so that everything fits.
But yeah, if you want to back your navigation,
you can just click on...
Yeah, so that's a file view.
So it shows the folder that you started Jupyter in.
And, well, I mean, it is very similar to a lot of other file system processes.
But, yeah.
So one thing is you created a new notebook, and the name is untitled by default.
So it's usually a good idea to change that.
Yeah.
So how do I name that?
Let's see if there's an idea in the notes.
Let's say, my first notebook, or how do I do that?
Let's call it, well, we want to call,
so the example here wants to calculate pi
using Monte Carlo method.
So what would be a good name?
Like, wait, F2, pi Monte Carlo?
Yeah, that's fine.
Good.
And now I can close this, so we have space.
Okay.
so um what do i do first of all i want to add a so i change the i want to a markdown cell here
uh so i will press m so that actually that the uh the kind of the cell turns to markdown
so i can type in header so if you don't remember the shortcut there's also this um
there's multiple layers of user interface,
but just outside the notebook,
there is a menu bar that has this save icon
and then a few other icons,
and it includes this text markdown.
So it's currently markdown
because it's showing that the current cell is markdown
and you can change it to code or raw.
Raw is just text.
So it's pure text.
It will not get changed when you run it.
so okay okay um so monte carlo method yeah and now i want to create a new cell
um so i i press usually press shift enter okay so should i maybe i mean i can draw here can you um
or not
wait
can you see
let's go back to the preview
I think you cannot really
I cannot try that
it's all black
yes
we have some weird
issues with the screen share
yeah it's weird sometimes
so do we try
maybe I'll click this again
it sometimes comes back
Do I start sharing?
Do we try resharing?
Maybe it's 25 past already.
I suggested I start sharing.
Okay, well, it's gone again.
It's back.
I suggested I start sharing.
I'll stop sharing then.
Yeah, not quite yet, I guess.
Now I'm sharing something.
Yep. Okay, so I'll stop my share then.
And now the Zoom thing is in the way. Okay, sorry about this, but stuff happens. So is
that okay? So I have activated the CodeDefiner environment and I'm going to run JupyterLab.
there we are so it started in the browser window okay now let's pretend
that I don't have this file already here I'm going to create a new file here okay
why do I have an untitled folder here let's delete that one okay so and I'll
I'll call this pi dot i pi np.
OK.
And we had already the markdown cell.
So I'll just very quickly write some title there.
This, I made a mistake now because I was going to excel.
So this is now a code cell.
And it's actually, it's a comment
because it starts with a hash.
But I want this to be a markdown cell.
So I will go here and change it into markdown.
and then press play to run it okay and the other option to run it is to play press uh control and
enter or at least that's one other option there's other shortcuts as well okay so that inserted
shift shift enter doesn't and control enter maybe create a cell okay shift enter creates a cell
below it okay so uh what do we do then so um and i'm i'm guessing we do want to actually make some
calculations well first we have a list of relevant formulas for this calculation
so that people can follow along what we're doing
I wonder if I should
just
you can reopen the cell by double clicking
you can show some formulas there
which can be useful
I'll just copy paste
so that I don't spend too much time
writing it out
but it's Markdown
which you have already used
in the notes
and in the documentation session.
Okay, so here we are.
Beautiful rendered.
We also have an image visualizing the content.
So this is kind of fun.
You can include an image either from the file system.
So I'm going to go create another Markdown cell.
But here we are actually including it from GitHub.
just the
you can navigate to the file in GitHub
and get the raw
open the raw image
and then get the link
to get something like this
okay
so that's fun
but let's get to coding
so
first we need to
import some things
And I keep pressing Shift-Enter to get a new line,
but that doesn't work.
I just keep creating new cells.
I need to get used to this again.
So import random.
We're going to need random for random numbers.
Just enter, not Shift-Enter.
Okay.
And for plotting, we're going to need matplotlib.
Iplot, actually.
From matplotlib.
um we probably shouldn't spend too much time on the code itself it's uh i mean the basic idea
yes but um like the code is in python and uh you like the language shouldn't be necessary
it shouldn't be necessary to understand the language or use python specifically there's uh
yeah so the idea is that the idea is that you compute pi because pi is going to be
close to pi divided by four is going to be the probability that a dart thrown in a square is
also in the uh in the circle circle yeah or yeah similar or equivalent multiplied by some number i
think yeah yeah yeah so we were
calculating the area of the circle by
randomly throwing randomly picking
numbers and deciding if they are inside
the circle or not so first let's pick a
number of throws
it says num points equal 1000
okay and run that and then we can write a function that
throws the dots which means picks two random numbers an x
coordinate and a y coordinate okay so
actually the function
throws a dot
right
okay
instead of okay
so
initialize well actually yeah we
throw dots because we are
we're not doing a function
we're doing a follow up at this point
yeah I was reading
incorrectly so
um here we go so we make a list of points um and we'll count how many times it hits inside the
circle so at the start this is zero then we'll do a for loop for and we don't really care about
the index but we want um
do it number of points times so this is a follow-up if you know a different language
don't worry about the syntax it is a bit weird python okay but we'll get an x coordinate and
y coordinate from random so that means if there is a random contains a function called random
we will be calling it twice
okay, to get two random numbers
and then
we need to check if they are inside
the
so how do you check if it's inside
a circle
the Pythagorean
theorem
so we'll do x squared
plus y squared
and the size of the circle
is one
so we're picking, here we're picking
from between zero and one
So the square is from 0 to 1.
I'm checking quickly if people can actually see me.
And so the square is between 0 and 1.
And so the radius of the circle is also 1.
And 1 squared is 1.
So we don't even have to square it.
So if it is inside the circle, then we say hits.
Add 1 to hits.
and in any case
we actually want to keep track of the points
so we'll append
the x y coordinate
and
we'll want to mark
whether it hit or not
so we could say
true or false here but actually
just for the plot
we want the points inside to be red
and points outside to be blue
so
So I'll go a bit fast here
and immediately mark it as red.
Because we've already stored the number of hits here.
Okay.
And then if it didn't hit,
we'll want to still add the point,
but we will make it blue.
Yeah.
I think you need another bracket there.
Yes, I do.
Yeah.
Because you are appending a tuple to the points.
Yeah, it's a tuple.
Okay.
So we have already run that.
Now, if I want to check what happened,
I could just say hits.
So hits, there were 765 hits.
I could say points, and that would be a long list.
Okay.
So...
Wow.
Yeah.
So it's nice. You can just check what the variables contain. This is why it's useful
for rapid development. But let's actually make it more of a narrative. So let's see
what the result looks like. So we'll make a plot. So we'll take the x and y coordinates and colors
and extract that from this. So this is again, don't mind syntax. It's weird.
it's though let's say what it's actually doing so extract the coordinates and
colors in this case up you're getting a it's a single list for all the X the X's
or another list for all the Y's and then at least for the colors yeah exactly
okay and then we define the figure dimension so define what the figure
looks like and this is also plots this is just how matplotlib works so
So again, I'll just skim past it.
What is important here is that you
can do this plotting thing inside JupyterLab
or inside Jupyter, and it will work out.
0 is not a good size.
I want to go with 6, I think.
OK, inches and, yeah, 6 inches.
I don't know why we use inches here, just standard.
Okay. I mean, in general, in plotting, why do people use inches?
Well, that's just the standard.
So we plot the results.
We did get this x variable here.
Axes.
Not an axe for chopping, but axes.
We'll make a scatter plot with the x coordinates and the y coordinates listed
and then C for colors.
So we need to set C equals colors here.
Okay.
And this should now, instead of this long list, produce a plot.
Let's see if it's pretty.
Okay.
There's an error.
That's a little.
Yeah.
So you called fix.
So if you go a line above, you.
There's a fix.
Okay.
So it's not a fix.
It's a figure.
Okay.
All right.
So here we have a plot.
So we have some points outside and some points inside the circle.
Okay.
Now, that's not the actual result, though.
This shows the method we used, but the actual result is the value of pi.
So that's, if you look at the equation here, it's the number of hits divided by the area,
which in this case, the area of the square is actually two times r squared.
so it's 4
and
that's
not, is that correct?
Well I mean
the area of this square is 1
so I guess this S actually means the area
of this square
and the C is the number of
the fraction of the hits
Yeah I think
this applies for the quadrant
or for the full
Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Well, I mean, we'll do it correctly here. Anyway, I'm sure if I'm reading that correctly. So the number of hits divided by the number of points is the fraction of hits. And then the pi actually is just four times the fraction, which I guess is what was written down there.
so I'm just somehow confused
fractions does not exist because
I added an extra s there
okay
you see here how errors happen right
so
how errors are displayed
yeah that's maybe I should
do that again just for a moment
yeah so I mean
the colors make it actually easier to
figure out what's going on but it's on line
two of the previous
cell 13
input cell 13, which is this one.
This is an output cell, or this is actually an error.
This is an output, this image here.
And, well, there's also markdown cells,
which I think also count as input.
Okay, well, let's get rid of the error.
So 3.06, I mean, it's three, it's close enough.
We can get some more points if we want to, and run again.
so one thing I do want to show because it was something at least I use very often if you're
making a narrative from top to bottom you probably want to run the cell from top to bottom
so here's restart the kernel and run all cells this is also useful to do before publishing
if I just make sure that if you run everything in the original or in the written down order
then it should work okay so it is running all of the cells now this is so many points uh the image
is just an image of a circle at this point and we have slightly uh a slightly better estimate of pi
here okay yeah but important here that if you change one parameter you need to i mean uh yeah
you need to run all the cells again, to be safe. You can be clever, try to be clever,
and rerun only the ones that are, but yeah. So what I could do is change this here,
run here, and then just try to go to this one, but now I get a completely incorrect result,
because I didn't change the stuff in the middle, I just changed this variable.
this didn't run and this didn't run um so if i run that one now i think i will get the correct
result but the image is not quite correct so at this point i'm confused i'm going to rerun
everything it's uh often better to rerun everything often than it is to like try to figure things out
yeah
okay
that's the example
anything else we want to
bring up here
check if there are
any questions in the notes
but it doesn't seem so
yeah but yeah I think one
comment in the notes is about
Marimo notebooks
and yeah so there's a number
of other
like jupiter alternatives that for example marimo i think it's for python but also pluto for julia
instead and these are a kind of notebook that is that compared to jupiter they have something
more so they are reactive so if you change for example in in those notebooks if you change one
cell if you change like uh num points then all the other cells that depend on that would actually
run. And this is, I think, can be useful. Of course, if you have cells that take very long
to run, you may be careful about doing that. But still, it's like a little improvement over
Jupyter from the point of view of reactivity. From other things, I think there's a lot of tooling
around Jupyter Notebooks
that we are going to briefly
skim over.
Which is...
Yeah.
Which unfortunately doesn't apply to
other kinds of notebooks.
So, yeah. But
that's why I think we teach Jupyter Notebooks.
I don't know.
Should we have a break now?
Yeah. So, I mean,
R has its own
sort of infrastructure
and R Markdown has
most of the features
so you can do
things like well I mean
it has most of the same features that we haven't
actually talked about yet and Pluto
is also kind of designed to work well
with
version control and stuff like that
but Jupiter still has
the most mature environment
because it is the oldest of
these examples
yeah the validation
tools there's a lot of stuff there
which is cool
anyway shall we have a break now
let's take a break now
so we'll do
10 minutes until
13.52
we'll write that in the notes
are you writing it down
someone is doing it
the invisible hand
thanks okay so see you at 53 past or 7 to right bye bye
you
Okay. Hello. Welcome back. I hope you had a good break and took some time to walk around.
so
next we'll go
into how you
share notebooks
how you include them
in your software
and just have other people
use them as well
and that starts with
version control
so
the notebooks
themselves especially
maybe I'll just show the notebook again
so this one includes an image
so it can be
it's not actually text content
and git is designed for text
so if you use it with just the default stuff
it can get a bit weird
but I mean it's not that bad
it does work
so there's a few different ways
of making it look better
so
there's the
nbdime extension for
jupiter and jupiter lab which is very
useful it allows you to
more directly compare
and merge notebooks
so
so it
is aware of the cell structure
here and it can tell you
what has actually changed in the cells
in the notebook
and doesn't
doesn't point out every change in
outputs necessarily
and so on so
that's useful
there's also other options
also for images if you have plots
then they're
saved in like a blob or text
base64 in the
notebook file and yeah
with nbdime you can actually have a nicer
yeah so we have
people show that in a moment
well maybe it's better to
just list the options from here.
So, I mean, there is also this JupyterLab Git
and JupyterLab GitHub extensions,
which are useful depending on what you use.
Here we'll show nbdime
and also show some things on GitHub.
So, yeah, so the first thing, I guess,
we'll just show what happens when things go wrong.
So here's an image I can actually open this pull request
or a comparison between two different versions
of a code in GitHub.
Let's see what it looks like.
Well, it doesn't even want to show it to me.
It's a large diff.
So we've changed some things in the notebook
and then there's this huge blob of text.
which is actually the image and the image is a bit different in some part of the image
somewhere is a bit different and it's very hard to see what's going on there's also this
text output cell here that's slightly changed so there is an option in github that you can enable
It's been a, what do they actually call them, feature preview.
I think it's been a feature preview for several years now.
But you go to the feature preview from this preferences section and enable rich Jupyter notebook diffs.
Okay.
And then if you reload the page, it should look very different.
let's see if it works okay so this line in the cell has changed this line has
changed and this image has changed so that is a lot better and well this
output has changed here you can also go back to the original source code which
is for this part it works but for the image it's not very useful okay so maybe
I will close this one okay and there is a similar well there is an interface for git in
JupyterLab itself and that is this nbdime extension it's already installed in the code
refinery environment but if you're creating a new python environment that includes Jupyter then
or well any other environment that includes Jupyter you'll have to include it for it to
work. Okay so we already I think kind of showed the the actual text that the notebook contains
maybe we should do that again. So here's the the file browser view and I think I should be able to
open it from here yeah open so this is actually a json file which is a text file that contains these
cells this is even a bit too stylized maybe the maybe i can open it with the
text editor so this is the actual text content of this file that we just wrote here
so it is text and it is something that you can handle with git but well here's the image again
um yeah and all of these outputs get uh gets changed every time you run the cell so
i mean there's just a nicer way of doing it it's not it's not that bad to start with the image
part is pretty bad but so here's the nbdime extension this is the button that gets added
when you install nbdime and there you can first of all i need to initialize the repost a repository
here because i haven't done that yet i don't have a git repository so i will initialize a
a Git repository in this. And now I have some untracked files, which is...
I don't actually know what these checkpoint files are. I assume it's because I have
JupyterLab open. But this is the actual file, pi.ipynb. And this is the example I downloaded
previously because um i wasn't planning to actually demonstrate this part so so now you stage you
stage the the yeah so i staged the pi dot ipy nb by clicking the plus button so what happens if you
change uh if you change the that file pi dot wine so if you change that because now it's staged
right so if you change that yeah i was planning to make a change so now it shows up in changed
I can view the diff. Maybe I should write this view here. So it's mostly the same.
It should show me the...
So this is the line that I changed. What is going on? Maybe it's showing me the diff to the commit.
that would be a bit annoying
leave this file
have you changed the file?
have you saved it?
I changed this and saved it
so now it's back to the original
and now it's showing some changes
I guess you need to save it
because if you don't save it
then the kit doesn't see it at all
but yeah
I think we found
an issue
with np time. I've never actually tried to do that. So if I just stage the file and commit
first and then try it, maybe that will work. Let's see. Okay. So I'll just call this an initial
commit. Traditional commit message. And then what should we change? Let's change this color
from red to orange okay now you already see that there's some change and we can go see a diff maybe
it will work this time okay so now okay a bit more space for it so you see that the line has changed
but actually um i have only changed this line i haven't changed the the actual color so let's go
and you need to rerun so now we change the image as well
and we can now again go here and see what the difference is
okay did i save it no i did not let's go and save it okay yeah
okay and
okay so it didn't show any new differences but now
that i click this button again now it shows some differences um so i had to close it and reopen
and now it's showing a difference in this image and in the outputs outputs uh let's remove that
there so um the outputs have changed because i re-ran the code and it's random so it's going
to be different every time okay so now yeah we can kind of nicely see the difference here
I haven't enabled this in the command line so if you are using git in the command line
I will need to activate whoops activate the code refinery repository
I should have thought about this before I started okay contact with code refinery all right here we
And now if I do git diff here, it's going to show me that the JSON file, so this, it's
relatively structured, relatively nice to read. I don't really care about the execution counts
for the cells or this, whatever this is. I do care about the image being different, but
this is not what I want to see. So you can also go to, well, I mean, go to the notes and
copy paste this or get it in some different way. So it's, you change the git config and
include nbdime in there. Okay, that looked weird.
i was moving to a different window um to get the terminal window back and that looked a little bit
weird on the screen share okay so now i can do a git diff again and let's see what it looks like
is it different it is a bit different so now it's um it's not really showing me the image
showing me that it's different which is better right that's like um how much can you do in a
terminal. But it is definitely better this way. Okay,
much less, much less use less information in the difficulty.
Yeah. Okay, so but we should really move on actually. I will
commit this. Okay, orange, change the orange. Oh, I will
need to first stage this one
and commit. Okay,
so let's move to
sharing notebooks now.
So we talked about
version control, and
again, there's different ways of sharing a notebook.
So there's
some
free, some commercial alternatives
where you can...
Let me back up a second.
The big thing here is
if you share
something online, just as a web
page that people can see they will not be able to run the code but there's plenty of ways to do
that so you can take this notebook and turn it into a essentially a text that includes this
website that includes the text and then includes also these code blocks and images and that's
really nice that's really good for generating documentation for example but you won't be able
to run the code from inside that website.
Then there's plenty of options
for creating a runnable shared document in some way.
And that does mean that you need a server
that actually runs the code.
So we'll show you how Binder works as a demonstration.
It's a really nice way of doing it.
And that allows people to actually run the code.
But there's other options.
And this NB viewer, this renderer, NB Sphinx, they allow you to turn the notebook into a
website. So not run the code, but otherwise great. So one option, save and export as
HTML, later markdown, all kinds of options. And then there's these platforms that allow you to
actually run it on the cloud and well and there's binder okay so first let's
ah sorry okay yes i was confused for a moment this is the next part
so uh let's go into the binder section but to do that we'll need to get the
notebook actually online so now it is only here only locally on my my laptop
up. So I think we'll actually need to create a new GitHub repository. That is actually
the first step in the exercise. So that's good. So here's a nice link, github.com slash
new, and that will create a new repository. I didn't want to actually close the website.
Okay. Yeah. All right. So we will not use a template. What should we call it? CR demo
PyCalc is written correctly. Okay, so this is a it's not actually in short
and memorable in any way but it is very descriptive of what this is and
something I will delete after sometime after this this course. So I'm going to
make it public so that everybody can access it. And importantly, I'm not going to generate a
readme file. No, I am going to generate a readme file. And then I'm going to, I guess, clone and
add the notebook. Okay, let's see where this goes. So I will add a readme file. It is a nice thing to
it's just that I already have a GitHub repository. No, I already have a Git repository, so
I'm not going to use the same one, I suppose. Okay, so let's do that. Why not? Let's also
add a license since we're at it. Make it MIT, for example. We talked about licenses yesterday.
It's good to have a license early, right? Okay, and you can make it more restrictive
later if you want to um here we are so we have a license and a readme file the readme file is
pretty much empty okay so so now you need to add your your code somehow right yeah so now i'm going
to actually just add the notebook and not push from the repository and i guess that the reason
for that is that in the first demonstration we did not make it a git repository but I did
actually make it a git repository already so well anyway let's go with the exercise as it's described
so I will go from here upload files
and I guess choose files then is good. Where is it? Okay I'm going to have
to move my windows a little bit just to see. Source, Code Refinery, Jupyter, here we go.
So, okay, there's pi.ipinb, okay.
And then now I need to give a commit message to add the notebook.
Okay, commit directly to the main branch, yes.
Okay, now there is another thing that I will need to do.
before the requirements yeah so in order for so we're going to run this on binder but in order
for it to know or to be able to run it it needs to know what what other python packages i need
so i'm going to add another file i'm going to call it requirements dot txt
and do we have a list of this if this is so if you switch to the plot lib 3.4.1
um yeah what i was going for is um so if you use python it will recognize it from this requirements
or txt file if you want r it will you will need to add a runtime runtime.txt and it will recognize
that you are using r if you have this file you can even have both at the same time
so what i'm going to do is add a requirements.txt and add matplotlib
and i'm going to use a specific version just because it is the version that i know it works with
Is it good for reproducibility?
Yeah. So in a moment, you will see that Binder actually creates a container to run this code in.
So this will work pretty well. Okay, create requirements of TXT actually is very descriptive
here. It's pretty much, I mean, I could say, describe dependencies or something, but
This is good. Okay. Now the next thing we want to do is go to mybinder.org and it opens this website.
And actually I'm going to switch over back to the repository and just copy the name of the repository.
So that's my GitHub username and then the repository's specific name. And that goes here.
Now, the name of the notebook is pi.i.pi.nb.
Okay, I'll just put that there.
pi.i.pi.nb.
Okay, so IPython notebook and from the main branch.
So this is a file that it opens to the user by default,
but you can leave it empty and then it will just open a file browser instead.
Okay so this actually constructs a web address you need to go to to launch the
launch the website. So we could click launch here but actually let's add a batch to the readme file.
So we'll have a markdown file and it has this address to this binder logo
and then the address that opens the binder as a link. So I'll just copy that.
This button is for copying and change the readme file.
Okay, so this will add an image that allows people to quickly
recognize that this repository works in Binder and that you can open it. So
Let's save that file. I should do it with the mouse. So commit changes. Add
binder button to readme. Okay and let's again commit directly to the main branch.
And there we are. So actually let's go back to the main page of the repository.
So now we can actually launch the binder page from here.
So I will go and close this one and hope that this works.
Okay.
It takes a while to build a new container.
It's actually waiting is done.
So we already have a virtual machine that we are running stuff on,
but we are now waiting for the container to finish building so that we can actually run
JupyterLab inside that container. Okay.
What else should we go through while we wait?
So I did all of these instructions I think.
Yeah, so people can now go and look at my work in the cloud.
If this finishes correctly, if it doesn't, then we'll fix it.
Yeah, well, let's go on while it's doing its thing.
So yeah, you can go even better, of course, get a DOI and launch a full version of your software.
Should we, how much time do we have and how much stuff do we have to go?
So, oh, we have plenty of time, I think.
so this exercise is about
sharing
doing it yourself
which you can definitely do
after this session
and this is about playing around
with this inequality repository
which we
we talked about in the first
section
if I was
this fast, then what did I skip over? And so if anything is
unclear, please ask questions. And if you want to do this
yourself, you can follow the steps, try to do the same steps
that I did. And feel free to ask questions then later. I mean,
yeah, a good amount of the time usually in this exercise is
waiting for binder so we can have a chat about other stuff as we wait
i have actually a remark so regarding tooling for for jupiter uh so i there's one one uh like
one python program called nb val which can be used to validate your jupyter notebook so if you
have a jupyter notebook and you want to make sure that you have run all the cells and you want to
test it for example test if the output is the same in different environments or you know even
after you have changed some underlying code that sits somewhere else you can use this tool and be
well and and get the you know just an idea whether or not anything has changed and of course in this
particular case with the calculation of pi it would always give you an error
because it's random yeah if you are comparing the value of pi to the correct value of pi then
it will not be or if you yeah or if you are correcting comparing two random values of pi
you may have a problem yeah so here possibly for reproducibility you would have to set to set the
seed of the random number generator oh right okay so if it's yeah yeah but in any case yeah so
comparing two notebooks maybe um you know maybe so you need to be careful there because there
There are some things that perhaps there can be some differences
you don't actually care about.
Some differences instead are significant
and may mean that there is a problem.
Some instead not.
So, yeah.
But I think it's a valuable tool.
Anyway, finally.
Yeah, that sounds useful.
And, I mean, tomorrow we'll...
Testing is tomorrow, right?
But finally loaded.
We'll also talk about how you compare, for example, random values.
That's one of the things.
and automated testing in general.
So, okay.
Yeah, it's loaded and it shows exactly the same.
It should be the lab interface.
Oh, except without the Git interface.
And I can run everything in here.
I can also change the numbers and run them.
So I get a different result.
Ooh, that's a problem.
Okay, let's finish running.
So yeah, with 100 points, you don't get very close.
We have a two new version of NumPy compared to Matplotlib.
So Matplotlib is trying to use something from NumPy 2.
so either I need to set a newer version of NumPy
a newer version of Matplotlib or a different version
or I need to
use a different version of NumPy
I will not have time to demonstrate that now
I'm almost sure
Is there a possibility in Binder
to set up a container and tell it
use this container
instead of just saying a requirement file?
Oh, I don't know.
I mean, I would assume so, but I don't know.
That also sounds like specialized enough that it's,
well, we can figure that out later,
and if somebody else wants to know, just ask.
There's also often when you can run some terminal commands,
bash commands, for example,
Okay, so can I do pip install upgrade matplotlib?
Oh, oh right, okay, there's a space there.
There shouldn't be a space.
Yeah, so this is one thing you can do in Jupyter.
You can try to get it to work.
And I guess I need to restart the kernel.
So is that something I can do from here?
oh actually that is this button, restart the kernel and rerun all cells.
So we'll see if the error goes away, this is just trying to fix some small thing.
Okay all right here we are, now it runs. So to fix this I would go to the repository then and
tell it to use a newer version of Matplotlib.
Okay. Next, we have the feedback section again in the notes. Let's see, where do I have the
notes open? Yeah. So let's go there. Unless you have more ideas. So I think I'm for feedback.
so yeah please fill in any feedback you have
and
ask if you have any questions
we have a few more minutes
in the schedule
so we can respond to any questions
but otherwise just
have a nice day
So, maybe there are some questions we can go back to and try to go on.
Hello.
Hey.
so i think the question about jupyter notebooks and uh uh version control uh yeah i think we
recover that i hope i hope that the person who wrote that is satisfied
um i think that sometimes uh if a jupyter notebook is too long it doesn't show on gitlab
but you may actually so it may take time but if you if you press on the button show anyway
it should show it although it could be that if if it contains images and the images are
are too large and the notebook is displayed as like literally so not as image but as a as a
json file then yeah you get very large large uh files and and there won't be any interesting
information for you to visualize there and yeah i think there's a question about reactive notebooks
and so what do people think about reactive notebooks i think we mentioned this already
uh the one thing about this uh about reactive notebooks is that they do not contain the output
so for example uh marimo and also bruto do not contain the output and they are just playing
python files so they are easier to version control but on the other hand yeah you you miss the
computational narrative there so you don't have the the outputs so it's like a very different
kind of
tool I
would say
what are
your opinions
on this
I mean
you can
with
reactive
notebooks
for example
with Pluto
you can
still export
it as
an HTML
file
export it
as a
website
and then
it will
contain the
outputs as
well
it essentially
is just
running the
notebook and
including the
outputs
but the
source code
for the
notebook
doesn't
contain the
outputs like in um the source code for a uh a jupiter notebook is well it is this change in
file that i showed and it did contain like the full image as this huge blob of text um so it
contains all of the outputs there so it's a different philosophy yeah one could take this
this note this kind of reactive notebooks and execute them and add a like a generate add those
the content of that to your documentation site or to your GitHub pages, let's say.
One could do that to make sure that content is visible somehow, so that the results are visible.
There's a question about the Git connection in JupyterLab,
is it whether it's similar to git in vs code uh yeah looks like it it looks very similar
um we saw a couple of glitches maybe that wouldn't happen in vs code but um yeah i mean
the nbdime thing is just meant for working with jupyterlab and jupyter notebooks
so the version control system
that's included in VS Code
or essentially it is a user interface for Git
it is fully general
Yeah, I think there's possibly a distinction
that if I remember correctly
the Git source control for VS Code
looks at the state of the files you have in your editor
not at the state of the files you have saved on disk so this is yet another problem so sometimes
that there can be some some issues there because git in vs code looks at uh the code you have in
your editor and it can be different from the one that you have on disk so if i understand correctly
here nbdime and the extension on in jupyter lab looks at the state of the notebook as it is saved
on disk. So then
there was that problem.
It should always look at what's saved
on disk.
Okay, I have to try that.
At least there's a way
of getting VS Code to look only
at what's saved on disk.
But yeah, it depends
on what you're used to.
What is more useful?
Yeah, just saying. This kind of
git extensions uh git integrations they they can get a little uh weird in when because of this
additional state that they have the state of the fight in the editor or and the state of the file
and this plus all the other things that that git has so all the you know the stage version and so
one so it's you know it gets better it is already uh complicated enough with the um
separate staged committed and on this version and well then you do also have the version in
your that you have currently open if you haven't saved it so yeah there's a comment for the days
lesson that it's missing hands-on activities and yeah we know of this problem so in previous years
we did like all the exercises you would see here we actually did together but since people have
different backgrounds like we have mostly them in python some in other languages but
it was basically too much and if we gave enough time for everyone to do the exercises
we basically spend all the time on the exercises so instead we can look at it like this so we have
the demos and the exercises are there for you to do later on your own time if you would like
and maybe someday we can go back to trying the exercises but with the difficulties of
installing stuff and managing everything, it hasn't worked that well.
Yeah.
I mean, if you do want to try the exercises, we do have the notes as a way of asking questions.
So if you have problems when you try them, you can always ask questions in the notes.
And yeah, you don't exactly have to follow us when we do it.
you can just go ahead and start doing them
and turn off the stream or do it now after the stream.
But the, would the, so I think for the documentation,
I see how the bring your own code sessions
would actually work because yeah, you have maybe some,
but possibly also for Jupyter Notebooks,
maybe if you're interested in this
and how to integrate Jupyter Notebooks
with your documentation or so,
So the bring your own code sessions may be useful there.
So you would apply what you've seen today,
but directly to what you're working on
instead of some artificial exercises,
which still would be nice,
but maybe you can make a longer jump
and go directly to applying these things to something new.
Because it's also nice that people are saying,
okay i will use what i learned today that's quite yeah uh that's quite a number of o's there
which is pleasant i think
yeah um and if you have anyone locally you can talk to you can basically show them exercises
exercises and say i would like to do this can you be my mentor and they can give you the starting
advice like let you know if it's the right thing to do for your own environment you do it and you
ask them for help and if you're at any of the organizations where any instructor of this
workshop has been we're around to help you unfortunately we can't help everyone in the
world because well you know we're a few people and this is an open course but
yeah i guess you know how that works
let's see
and tomorrow yes if you can scroll up a little bit there's some news for tomorrow there yeah
so tomorrow we have two lessons one is testing which is a very practical thing so it would have
some really nice exercises if we were giving you time to do them but we sort of combine the version
control the github and many other things and show you how you can use github to test your code on
every push you do and integrate that with pull requests and so on so it's really cool it's a
quite good um thing to do and i think that if you're just following along you can still get
a lot of it even without the exercises that's easy to do later and then after that is modular
code development and this used to be a sort of discussion thing now you get to see two instructors
come together and they will start with a basic idea make a code in a jupyter notebook and slowly
make it more and more modular add function split it to files and eventually end up with a program
that can be run from a command line and there's a lot of general discussion here
so to say like it's really how would you say it
it is
if you ask me it really puts everything together and shows a realistic process
from chaotic initial scientific scripts to something that's reusable
yeah okay any other news for tomorrow
or should we get going
yeah looking forward to tomorrow actually we've been in the background
yeah okay great so see you all later then please keep filling out the feedback
at all thanks so all right see you later bye see you
you
Thank you.