Thank you.
you
Test.
Can anyone see people out there?
I see us on screen.
Yep.
So do I.
Okay.
Yeah.
It's like we have a classical icebreaker question there.
What's your programming language are you normally working with?
So how about you, [name]?
I think the answers in there that are currently set, that's mine.
Okay.
Yeah.
So yeah, I'm mainly working with Python, JavaScript, TypeScript at the moment, sometimes MATLAB,
Sometimes Java, a little bit of R, but really rarely for me.
And that's about it.
And yourself?
Yeah, that would be C++ and Fortran as well as Python, but yeah, writing code is primarily
Fortran and then in combination with a bit of CUDA and then you have, that's a little
bit of a setup because the way we are using it in one program that I'm working with, then
need C++ as an interface. So, yeah, it's working, but it's, well, I would say,
if I would start a program from scratch, writing with CUDA backends or perhaps some other
GPU backends, then, I mean, among the traditional compiled languages, then
then if you go with C++, you can then
work with fewer languages.
Because if you work with Fortran,
you would need C++ also most of the time.
Not necessarily, but it's rather common.
That's true.
I like that answer.
Natural language, let GPT code for you.
yeah what do you think about gpt coding in general
yeah on my side my experience is um i didn't really try it myself um
i had to sort of say be aware of it and deal with it in the autumn because we were um
a few within the team for one code development project we were recruiting new team members
and we then had the code exercises as part of the of the interview process
and yeah up front we were a little bit undecided so okay we invite a few persons into you and and
And what do we say about, like, AI-assisted coding?
Would we say that, oh, please do not use it here in this context for this exercise?
Or, well, you can use it if you want, but then be transparent and please explain how we're using it.
And somehow we naturally landed in the latter.
so now
the people who we then were in contact
with, they would
use primarily
writing the code by themselves
but also some of them did it with
AI-supported coding
My take is that
I personally do use
GPT to help me with things
definitely
but my impression is that
one of the most important bits about
AI-assisted coding is that
you still know what the code
is actually doing
and you have an understanding of the code
because yes, nowadays
just a few
days ago I had a discussion with someone
GPT or
larger
agent frameworks can
essentially write whole
applications for you.
The problem starts
when you then want to
maintain that application.
So you have an application that works,
that does exactly what you want it to do,
but it's barely maintainable
because there is no real concept behind the code
and no one understands what it does.
It's essentially, yeah, like the LLM itself internally,
there are loads and loads of weights,
but why it does something is really, really difficult to determine.
Yeah.
And that's my main argument why I wouldn't, at least for anything in research, rely on just have GPT code for me.
Because I would never be able to maintain that.
And that essentially means that whatever results I,
or whatever things I get from this application,
if it's anything that I have to explain at some point,
this application is useless.
Because I can't.
Because I don't know what the application actually does.
If it's just for presenting your resource,
so you had to build a application
that essentially takes in a couple of values
and then uses your self-coded algorithm
to present something in a nice fashion
to a user or something,
that might work.
That can be perfectly fine.
But if it's something fundamental
where you want to also be able to maintain
what the application itself does,
it becomes difficult.
I would say in general with many machine learning methods,
explainability is something of a challenge. So your algorithms are doing something for you and
perhaps they do it right on the spot and very fast and helpful but if you want to understand
what they have done and how they've done it then sometimes you're a bit at loss it's essential
to me it's a bit the you can try with enough data you can train models to detect
well a lot of things but if then ask so and what is it they are actually detecting
the kind of the kind of the why is this marked as that and this marked as the other
then it becomes really difficult to explain okay uh what's the what's the feature that this is
actually detecting what's the feature that we could potentially work on to to change something
or to build something
So, let's see here. We have now the... I could perhaps take over the screen share, [name].
Mm hmm. Sure.
Okay. So yeah, let's start.
So we are here about automated testing.
Yeah, it's still one minute to the full hour.
now we need to yeah so good good morning everyone um for those of you who haven't already seen it
Please see here the iceberg questions that they have put in the collaborative document and we have three questions here.
So first is what programming languages are you normally working with?
So we have some 10 languages here and please add if something is missing.
And the weather seems to be very good here in Northern Europe overall and also in Taipei. It's sunny. Nice. Sunny in Bergen. That sounds to me just a little bit unexpected because I thought it was always raining in Bergen.
okay yeah let's start yeah let's start
so we are here essentially for automated testing
yes so good morning everyone so today in the first lesson we're going to talk about automated
testing and this will will will be taught by by [name] fow from uh from from finland and uh from
me you want to take who yeah yesterday i was sitting in stockholm and today i'm sitting in
upsala so automated testing what what this is about so we can start by illustrating with some
examples here typical situations so you have a code you're working with it and
for over a few months it's stable and to implement from the new feature b
or you change the feature c and then all of a sudden the feature a which was there in your code
for a few years it's not working anymore and i mean that can cause a lot of disruption
and you need them to figure out why this happens and and how it could be prevented
so i presume that many of you have experienced this at some point and and if this happens
you you need to know some some good tricks and techniques and and and it's can be worth to get
some good habits with testing because you can save a lot of time with it and i can quickly i
can quickly mention here um the bnc can be something that is your code um or actually
code from a library like in matlab the different matlab version so suddenly your matlab version
changes and something in your code doesn't work anymore as it did in the past that's i think one
of the most common situations at least that i have encountered that you rely on some library
and some library changes um suddenly make things not work or work differently
yes indeed that that's a very common situation actually so it's very much so that the errors
or the source of errors can be in a code itself or it could be in the environment
or simply in the matching between the code and the environment
because out of the box they might not click together
okay so like the other lessons given on tuesday and on yesterday on wednesday we will do the
the examples we will do them all like in demo mode and also highlight some of the material
which is in the lesson presenters exercises we will do them then live on the screen
we very much encourage you to then at later point get back to do some of these exercises yourself
prerequisites are what you probably are up and running with already so you need pi test
with this port of python and you need to have your git i mean
have git and also your account with github or git lab
so coming here to the first
second giving giving here some some motivations so
So I mean the consequences from software malfunctioning or functioning in a way which is not intended
can be of different severity.
So the common thing is that something breaks and you need to fix it, perhaps you need to
spend a few hours or half day, that's not the end of the word obviously.
But in the context of scientific research, one of the more severe scenarios would be
if you pursue some work on your own or with colleagues, and even if you complete it, you
communicate it in scientific journals, and perhaps two years later, you figure out or
someone else figure out that, oh, something here in the code that you used for simulations
calculations within this project some features were not functioning as intended and therefore
the raw data perhaps the post-processal data simply is not correct and you can find here some
some articles here about this so here is some cases where people even have to retract
published work semester is so too much did you did something like that happen
to you or have you been spared from luckily not but I would also want to
mention that depending on the type of testing you're using you might not
protect yourself against mistake miss mistakes in your code that you didn't
in anticipate you um because of depending on the complexity of what you're what you have there
there might be issues in the code that you just don't realize um even with testing so um it's more
at least to me the the major thing is that uh you have something you code on and a bit back
a bit later someone asks for well someone asks for changes and stuff doesn't work as it used to be
that's more that's more what i was what i'm commonly concerned with that you
essentially get suddenly different results from the from the same functionality
or that
some functions just
don't
do anything anymore
that's more where
testing can help you with
or that
testing kind of
prevents
yes
I could, I will not do it now
but I've actually myself had
some rather, yeah, I would say, most of the fun experiences were programs that broke.
And fortunately, this was discovered in, let's say, manuscript review phase.
So of course, it was a referee who requested some additional simulations.
And while we were getting on the board to do these simulations to complement the original
results then we found out oh we had done something wrong and we then had to redo it and then had to
also be transparent in in the community getting back to the journal that okay we had made the
mistake as of a half year ago we spotted it we corrected it and to the best of our knowledge
this is now to say the sound results and i would very much encourage uh transparency in this so
mistakes can happen and and um one should not wipe this under the carpet
also let's say in in communication with the journals also
okay so how can testing look um in in practice so um
here we have an example this is in python code and and uh we will shortly we'll get to some
hands-on exercises on this. So what do we have here? This is about
a temperature conversion from Fahrenheit to Celsius temperature scale. So this here
is the function in Python. And [name], what do we have here?
so um we essentially try to see if the if um what we put into this function gives us the
result that we expect uh the function to give so we give it one example um
um often uh for basic for relative basic ones you might even get a couple of different
values that you want to pass in and out so that you make sure that this is not a hard-coded
337.7777
returning
which would also pass
this test
but
more of a general
does this function
behave as we expect it to behave
so does it
return the right values
and we already see in here
we have this
absolute
smaller than a certain
so it's an
epsilon kind of assertion
and that's
something especially with floating
point numbers that in tests
you will see relatively often
where
well
floating point numbers are not exact
in computers so
you always try
to say
it has to be almost
correct because correct
doesn't work yes yes certainly and one aspect here is when it comes to numerical computation
so nowadays i mean even if you on your your local laptop or desktop computer
you often go beyond serial execution of the code but you have perhaps some some kind of threading
or some multiple rank computation and yeah particularly threading over cpu cores then
that can very well be so to say non-deterministic execution because you then if you have let's say
eight real numbers and you sum them using eight fiscal cores depending on in which order the
estimation is made the rounding errors might come about it's slightly different
and what we what we see here is essentially a so-called unit test this is testing one atomic
unit of the of the code so this fahrenheit celsius function does not have any side effects there is
nothing this depends on besides the basic language functions and that means that we are just testing
our code and as soon as you have function calls from within the function you start it's
if it's your own functions that are being called then
this goes into a bit of a different type of testing
sometimes it's still unit tests but yeah it depends a lot on the side effects of your function
I think that's also what we are going to see next.
So here, yeah, you can find, so in this lesson is rather long, so we will not have the chance
to cover all of it.
I think we can here and now actually we can go come here to a little bit of definitions
of what are different kind of tests that we can deal with so [name] you mentioned this
that there is something which is called unit tests yeah unit tests essentially are testing
that the individual small unit so an individual function does what you expect it to do that under
that different kind of inputs that you get always produce what you expect it to produce
that's what a unit test is doing then you have integration tests that's where yeah if you have
larger parts if you have um one element depending on another element and how how they work together
um that's and you test that you would still write one function that does this test but
you would have an essentially an integration test between the two
components if they work together as you expect them to work together
Yeah. There are two types here. End-to-end tests, which sort of relates quite a bit to integration
tests. But here it's really like the complete program. And if it is, let's say, for a file-based
user interface program, you work with input files and the program produces output files.
then that lends itself rather naturally for testing because you then have as
your test for end-to-end testing or essentially a set of input files and then you have stored
then the selected output complete also with some specification about what would be let's say
the tolerance for the output if there is any if yeah exactly so so real numbers are sort of
one case but but they can of course be other categories also
and then you have uh what's called regression tests which especially for um i think academic
work is quite important because it's essentially that if you do changes the results don't change
um so that would be uh yeah i'm using uh i'm using different versions of matlab
to test that under all the versions of matlab i still get the same results i'm using different
versions of a solver for whatever problems i have and i'm getting the same at least conceptual the
same the same results um i can change it essentially helps you to be able to change and
update code and make code faster and make sure that even if even if something changed inside
the results that i'm getting out of it are still the same and if they are not there should be a
good reason why they are not and maybe you then well
need to see if the original was correct or if something has something substantial has changed
yes um one thing which is important to keep in mind here with interest and 10 tests and
regression test is that let's say you have you've engineered your regression tests
and you start to deploy them let's say you run your program
first on a local computer then you run it on three for other servers
and then it's all good for extended time over many months
that is tells you then okay things are now stable over time but it's very important to
to remember also that at some point there's a base case that needs to be sound
that means at some point early on in the program development you need them
to think like okay is the program now doing what it is supposed to do
so yeah in example from my field of science computational material science then it's
yeah i mean it's essentially about doing simulations for differential equations you
get a lot of numbers and often let's say the models that are implemented they are sort of old
can be 100 years old 200 years old and you do have let's say for the small problem size you
have the analytical solution or you can work it out yourself and and that's something which is
very useful because if you can establish let's say the analytical solution for some let's say
a differential equation um and or you have it in a textbook or whatever then you have a base case
and if you then do for that small computation you do it then with your program and you get
right results then you have sort of like a base case then probably the typical thing is obviously
that in on the computer your program will run something which is bigger and you want to be
done faster and so forth uh if you can do it a little bit inductively so that you work from the
base case to say like okay the machinery in the code is is is correct here with regard to a and b
and then like okay then we can sort of presume that results are coming out here
for c and d have a good let's say probability for being correct
so if you can build such things into to the what it then becomes regression sets
that can can be a value but those those can also be unit tests
if you if you have if you have clear solutions for uh for something this is exactly what a unit
test could also be working or before a regression test would be most likely more the and now i have
a more complex example that i don't have an analytical solution for and i want to i want
that to be stable even if my code if my code is changing yeah very good point
you're completely right there so often when you look at the components the units
for them it can often be more tractable to come up with like the base case result
so you can establish them that you have a good reference data for your unit tests
so i think we can do a little bit of an interlude here with
the discussion on what's easy and hard to test so i put that question up in in the notes
so here towards the end of the collaborative document so if you could perhaps
tell us a little bit about your experience is on what's easy and what is hard to test
i would quickly go to the what you should do and what you or what's kind of good practice i think
not every bit of code yeah needs to be tested um there are some basic things that
yeah okay we trust that they work as they should um there's the thing with uh code that's really
difficult to test
like what's mentioned
in the motivation
with Jupyter Notebooks
and I would argue that
if you can move
functional code
out of the Jupyter Notebook into its
own functions then it's a lot easier
to test these
bits to have actual functions
that you can then import back into the
Jupyter Notebook. Then you can test
the code.
Yes. Yeah, that's good to be aware of.
In the Jupyter Notebook, which are, depending on how you interact with them,
they are having the whole execution flow is depending on your interactive input.
But that's a little bit more, a bit like a moving target for testing.
I think here now in this lesson, I mean, we will keep it to like this execution program from the beginning to the end.
So we will avoid this.
There's one more thing that to me is a good motivation in writing tests.
if you write tests for the functions that you expect users to use they already have an example
of how to run your function so your tests can to some extent also just work for us documentation
essentially how is this supposed to be used what kind of things can you do with it so
testing can be integrated in yeah writing documentation to some extent
and you can reuse things that you use there yeah indeed so this is actually a way to to be
efficient with working on this process as you said [name] your examples and your input files
if it's a text-based program and and also like documentation and test cases all of that sort of
naturally can be combined and reused as appropriate
so let's just we can briefly highlight here some points before we move over to the
to the next hands-on, so to say.
So what are you writing?
Yeah, so getting an up to high code coverage
can be difficult on a complex and legacy code,
like 95% code coverage.
Yeah, that's very ambitious, probably.
Yeah, the problem with that is especially
if you handle some kind of exception,
if you do some exception handling and things,
then it becomes really difficult because you essentially need to write tests for every
possibility that where things can go wrong and where and how that is then handled so
yeah i completely agree on that
yeah last point here generally hard if you do not have modular code yeah certainly it's
very much so which to me is a reason why try to have modular code and don't try to have one huge
script that does everything try to put it into sub routines that you can test
yeah so to some extent essentially testing also helps you improving your code quality
in my opinion. Yeah, yes, so when you design functions or subroutines
that's, and we'll talk more about that in the second hour, so the design of a function can
be guided by its tentative testability. So if you know upfront that, oh what I'm writing now,
it will not be possible to make a unit test for it in in any kind of let's say straightforward manner
then yeah okay perhaps you you can then have a good reason to reconsider how you are designing
that function and perhaps like it is not a function that might very well be let's say
what makes it difficult okay so
So let's here move over to the next episode here, which is testing locally.
And then I think perhaps, [name], you would like to take over the screen share?
Yes.
Yeah.
Okay.
So essentially in this exercise, we will quickly
show how to set up a test and how tests work in Python. There are examples in other languages as
well so if your preferred language is one of the others you can go through those exercises
afterwards but here we'll just show the Python example. So the minimal example that we can create
is we can essentially create a folder for our test things. Go in there and then take your favorite
editor and take this code. So this code conceptually consists of a function
which is a simple add and a test function for this which is
very Pythonian because of the untyped language and you can use integers or floating numbers
or whatever and add them and the plus operator is defined for multiple things.
So we actually want this add function to also be able to add strings
and therefore we want to
test this for strings
and then
in Python
always pytest which is part of
the code refinery environment that
you hopefully have installed
it's relatively simple
to run these
tests by
simply calling
pytest with the
file name
that you want
want to run the tests in or from and PyTest will automatically find everything that
every function name that starts with a test underscore. I want to quickly mention that
sorry I want to quickly mention that this is if you use four folders
PyTest actually looks for all for all files with test underscore starting so you could also
create two files one with test underscore example and the test in it and the other with
example which is called example and then import the function that you want to test from example
into your test but now let's see what happens if we actually break the test so if the test doesn't
work and well one simple option is to just remove the or just change the plus into a minus
and if we run the test again we get a failure here and this failure essentially tells us that
um it tried to assert so um i try to assert that minus one is five because the result of this
at two three now is minus one well two minus three is minus one and this is not five
so yeah it tells us what went wrong and where the so what kind of assertion was um wrong and
it even tells us where this minus one came from that it came from this at two plus uh two comma
three because this could be a bit could be more complex and then it really helps to see okay which
which side or which part um led to a wrong result um now we have uh we have already mentioned that
in the introduction um there is a problem that if you have for example floating numbers
and try to do
no wait
sorry and try to add those
you might end up with something that's not correct
or you might end up with some problems
because if you run this
well
now we see that our addition
of 0.1 and 0.2
is not exactly 0.3
and that's what we were
talking about with these tolerances earlier
and
the problem here is that
due to numerics
these are not presented as
0.1 and 0.2
but they have additional
additional
information way way
I don't know how
which digit um and you often for floating numbers have to do this
uh kind of correction where you take an absolute of oops not of this
an absolute of this
minus 0.3 uh no
wait uh yeah
yes and define that this is smaller than one
smaller than whatever epsilon you want to choose um
don't choose something too large and don't choose something too small
yeah this
1 and then
10 raised to minus 6 is
yeah I mean
take something that's
appropriate
it's rather commonly used tolerance I would say
like if you have no specific reason
for choosing a
given tolerance then this
1 minus 6 or 1 minus 9
you might
even have if you have more
complex programs some some programs especially some optimizers allow you to set tolerances
for optimal solutions and things and if you if you are setting a tolerance
you should make sure that your assertion for something is also within that tolerance even
if you know the correct result because you just allowed the the the program to be not exact
and that might lead to essentially going into the documentation
and see what is the default tolerance for this.
So if you have an optimization problem
and the optimization says, yeah, up to 1 to the minus 9,
you shouldn't assume that your optimal solution,
even if you know what it is, is exactly that
but could be up to minus nine worse than what you expect.
So yeah, each test framework has its own way
of collecting the tests.
For PyTest, it's relatively simple.
If you have a function, I can actually quickly show that.
oh this would be done
so and if i now
just say please run this on this folder it will collect
the from the test example pi will collect test add which we had defined that okay we import
the add function from example and then have the test function here so it will look into all files
that have test underscore select collect all functions that start with test underscore and
run those and it does not run the test underscore from example.py because example.py doesn't start
with a test underscore yeah okay this much for the local testing were there any questions [name]
yes let me check
No, not at this point.
Okay, then let's go on to automated testing, which is actually really a convenient feature
of GitHub, but also GitLab.
So to make sure that your code stays correct or that your tests are still running, you
You could, of course, always, before pushing something, run PyTest or whatever testing framework you have.
But on tendency, at least I tend to forget these kind of things.
So having someone else automatically do it for you is really, really convenient.
And that's where something called continuous integration or continuous development comes in.
so continuous integration essentially makes sure that even if you change something the tests are
still working this is of course under the assumption that the tests haven't changed
haven't changed um so if you change your tests um things can fail and sometimes you unfortunately
have to have to change tests if uh the preconditions for the test change but
on a normal assumption
tests should be
as static as possible and not
change
so
in this example we will essentially
run
a small
example for a continuous integration
test with GitHub
and
the assumption is
you have
you have your git login and everything and we'll begin with just creating a new repository
so this is from your uh from yeah from github if you
click on new repository you end up in here
we don't want to have a template name but we want to call it example ci
and want to add a read me so that we can make this relatively easily so let's
clone this and have it in here so we have a example ci with a readme okay
now we want to have we want to do exactly this split into functions and test functions here
so we have
a file called
functions.py
and we want
to add this code
and
there are some
mistakes in here
this is also something that you could call
test-driven development
because we are
To some extent, we have tests before we actually do the final coding here.
Even though our tests are currently not yet active.
But these are the two tests, the two files that we have.
And we need to add them with a small comment and push it to our
push it to our remote so if we run our tests locally they seem to work
because we haven't activated the subject tests and the car the Fahrenheit tests yet
because if we would activate them they wouldn't work so to add automated testing it's actually
relatively easy if we are in our repository and click on actions we have
this get started with github actions and we want to use this Python application
and configure this Python application so I'm you and did we talk about github
actions in uh last week i think so um yeah but you you i think it's good if you walk it through
in general
how can i we spoke about it yesterday when it comes to deploying uh documentation with uh
in general um github action is something that is run every time um something happens on your
branch so in this case we tell it that it should do something on push
and it should do something on pull requests and we also um one
yeah i'll just copy that um and we give it certain permissions uh as to the contents of the of uh the
of the repository and the main permission here is sorry is read permission so that it can see what's
happening in there and um for our for our action we also want to give it a write access to pull
requests because what we want to do is we want to write something in the end into the
pull request that's concerning coverage because we want to see what our tests actually cover
and to be able to do that we need to allow it to write into pull requests
then I go over in here
then it essentially is telling it what
sorry
then it's telling it what kind of basic image to use
and then there are the steps into what it should do
so it uses a checkout action, that's a different action that
checks out the repository
action that
sets up Python and this
is where we
want to add
our
instead of just
pytest we also want to add
the pytest cuff package
which essentially allows us to
add this coverage
report in the end
then it does
some linting with Flake so that
our code style is
better or that it at least complains if the code style is not good
and then
we want to
run pytest and in pytest we want to create
a coverage report
and the coverage report can come
in different formats
and we want to have it in an XML
format because the XML format is what
is going to be used
in the
next stage
or in the next step
and we want to create the coverage report
for the whole folder
and this create coverage
is another action
that was it was implemented and that is a very simplistic coverage report that's
being put into pull requests okay and now how do I get rid of this sidebar
here seemingly can't which is really annoying because it covers half of my
okay then we want to commit these changes and they will be in the dot
github workflows folder and let's call this at CI CD and commit directly to the
main branch yes so now this has been added and now we have an action that
says CI CD and builds this Python app. This will take a little bit of time and at some point
this is done.
So let's see what this has actually done. Okay, so this has run a setup the job,
done the different steps, but it didn't create coverage. The reason why it didn't create coverage
is that we restricted this to only create coverages on pull requests, because
it doesn't, for this specific action, make sense to create these coverage reports during a push or
or in this case, a direct commit,
which is essentially a push,
because it doesn't have anything
to put the coverage report into.
So let's see, they have been run,
and we can go back here and let's pull what we have.
Yeah, Git pull origin main is essentially the same as just Git pull in this instance, because I'm on the main branch, which is tracking the remote or the origins main.
Now, we want to update our test functions to actually.
run the test subtraction check and yeah because we've noticed that there is an
issue with the CI CD there was the subtraction we create a new issue
This is not something that you need to do, but this is the assumption that someone else
has created this issue, because they noticed that something is wrong.
Actually, I forgot to actually add this and push it.
So and if you now look into the actions, there's the test for subtract that has been added
and the action is being run again.
So [name], as mentioned, so it was the question here on the document, whether this is type
along or pure demo and what we're doing now is pure demonstrations.
please follow along and and then you you can do the exercise on your own later
yeah um
okay uh so
let's see and we actually far have a this build failed because in the tests the tests indicated
that 5 is not minus 1, and 5 is what comes out of subtract 2 and 3.
So seemingly our function is wrong. Well, you might have seen that right in the beginning.
So, we need to fix this.
And add the functions.
Yeah, this is now a bit the wrong way around, but I forgot to create the branch.
So now I've fixed this issue.
And we'll create a pull request to change this.
And there are no conflicts, but there is an action that's being run.
And let's see if this fixed our problem.
So actually, and now we see what this coverage bot does, or this coverage report does.
So there is a current status, there were no new files added, functions.py has a coverage
of 75%
and it essentially tells us
okay, this is the coverage of the code
that we have at the moment, 75%
and all the tests
worked. So
that's
quite
okay. So let's
merge this.
Let's see if I completely screw up.
No. Okay. So, I could pull this back to my main branch here.
Okay. So, what's the next? Next, we do have more tests
that we already had
well
the optimal that we could have
is that we get 100% coverage
but this is
not something that you
commonly manage to get
but
for this simple thing we can
probably try to do this
so we also
uncomment this test
for the for the fahrenheit check and and here it's a bit more it's a bit more
complicated um and i'll quickly go over what this is doing so
this is actually the pi test version of um of having this absolute and this is probably what
you should be doing under normal circumstances so this is approximating
um that this number that the reset from here should be approximately 50
given some tolerance and in this case the pi test default tolerance and there's also um a function a
uh an additional yeah there's an additional um statement here which is sometimes functions do uh
are expected to raise errors if they get inputs that are wrong or that are unexpected.
And we can test this by having this with PyTest.Raises assertion error.
If this does not raise the assertion error, then it will fail.
So let's see.
Let's see what happens if we run the pytest here.
Okay, so there is definitely an issue with what we have here.
And we need to fix our Fahrenheit code.
and I let's do this now and and now I admit let's see we had a working
fahrenheit functions um fahrenheit function in the start and the motivation because my stuff is ah
it's just the nine of the five divided by nine
and this is working so okay and if you run the part it's still um we have still an issue because
it doesn't raise an error and that's uh well actually correct because uh or
it's actually good that air that we have this because
um we would expect that we can't convert something that's below zero kelvin
so a value of minus 600 celsius of minus 600 front right just doesn't make any sense
so what's the
what's the
actual
let's see
what's the minimum Fahrenheit
Minimum well-defined number of Fahrenheit.
Something like this.
Yeah.
Could be.
Yes.
I never thought about it.
That's zero Kelvin.
Yes.
At least according to Google.
And if it has this, that works.
And we can, of course, also just, I won't, let's.
So, edit, put it on, put it to the repository, and then
we also see that the issue has been closed
because we had a fix in this
one per request
don't really need further descriptions
but let's see what
the coverage report
will tell us in a second
I think this is a good
finish of the first of this
lecture here or of the first
part here
and then
so we have 100% coverage
reached even with a test
that even having a test
that
uses or that checks for
errors being thrown from the function
and I think that's a good
time to go for a short
break or
yes yeah thank you [name]
that sounds good
so
So we will then have a 10 minute break and reconvene at 10 past the full hour.
Bye.
you
hi so we are back and we are back with test design and I'll hand over to [name]
for that thank you [name] so what we will do now will be also be a bit
hands-on we will now be back to we we we saw here before the break uh automated
testing and and too much was showing how this can be done with github actions
um we could perhaps there was one a few good questions here that we could
highlight here so
So first of all, you're very welcome to work through these automated testing exercises
on your own.
And if you have any questions, you can then certainly, as usual, put them here in the
collaborative document.
How often do you use automated testing?
It depends a lot on the code that I'm working on.
The more likely it is to go into some kind of production, the more likely it is to have
tests.
So one thing which has become very popular and is very useful is this that you set up
up when you host a git repository on github or be it on github then you can then if you are
the maintainer of that repo you can enforce so that i mean first and foremost you cannot just
commit stuff directly to me to the main bronze then secondly when you contribute stuff to fit
your brand then that's a very good location a natural location to to say require that to do
testing so probably if you're developing code and you do it locally on your local computer then you
can run the tests with pipe test or another framework and you do it locally and then when
you commit this new code to your feature branch and you make a merge request back to GitHub, then
that's a good occasion then to request that, okay,
before being able to merge the code, we would like to see all of these tests being passed.
that's definitely something that i've seen being done for larger projects um
where you have multiple different contributors and you just want to make sure that you have a
high quality code base and yeah testing helps in maintaining that high quality code base
especially
and I think this is
very important
indeed it's very important
for larger
projects where you
simply need to have this a little bit
you need to have a bit of bookkeeping
of some kind
because
it's not so that you might
have like in smaller settings
perhaps you have the colleague in the same room
or in the same corridor
you can just go and ask them and so forth but if you're 20 person you sit at five different
locations then you need to have some procedures for this and and what is then provided by these
services companies github gitlab bitbucket and so forth that that's it's a good platform
so what we are going to talk now about is test design so this will be a little bit also provide
examples of how you can for a few different types of functions or different or different code how
you can write tests and you can see here in in the lesson material and perhaps [name]
can you check if we have the direct link to this episode in the notes yes it is okay great
so we will take it here from the top um and uh work few some other examples and yeah this will
be a demo but i will do it rather slow so yeah certainly if you want you can do it a little bit
type along like it but also perfectly fine to get back to it later so
as you can see here we have language specific instructions and that means that
the template codes are available in one-on-one language and also here we have some instructions
on various frameworks for other codes so we'll get back to that a little bit later but for
the beginning here we will work a bit continue to work with Python.
So we have here a function it's called well simply factorial and what it's done what it's
doing is is rather clear it takes one input argument and that is an integer number and
for this input argument it calculates the factorial.
So [name], is this code that can be tested or is there some, let's say, pitfall that
makes it difficult to test?
This is relatively straightforward because you have a clear function that gets inputs
and outputs.
You can test for the value error with PyTester erasers.
can test multiple different values
for it. There is
nothing that
kind of happens on the side
that you have to take care of because
it's all
internal. There's not
even any... There's one
somewhat function called
the range, but
let's assume that
what...
that the Python basic language is
correct.
Yes.
So I will now shift over to the terminal and then we'll have a look on how this code can be tested.
So first I copy the code.
So it's like a definition and.
Yeah, OK, I already had it here.
And also, yeah, actually, I also already had here what is then, let's say, the way how to get started to set up the tests.
So we will here use PyTest.
So, yeah, first is the function.
and adding to this we have the import statement import pytest and we'll then add some assertions
and this case here it is it's rather clear upfront what this could be so yeah the
factorial of zero by definition is one then factorial of one is also one
and factorial of two is two and so we have now here in this case here three
assertions in the code and in the test factorial function so let's see if we
to the terminal what happens if you execute it and as usual we then invoke it with the
pi test so pi test factorial dot pi
and yeah it collected this test item and it came out correctly and it was very fast
i would i would want to add one thing i dislike one thing about this test
and that is that it doesn't test for the um for the value arrow that is raised for n and smaller
than zero yes very good point very good point um because that is an essential part of this
function and it should not return something when a value of smaller than zero gets put in.
There's even things where are factorials of non-integer numbers even defined? I don't
think so. So this function should make a couple more tests actually. Yes.
That could be called in a test.
Just having a couple more assertions, and yeah.
Yes, so that's a good suggestion.
So here, so the assertion statements as we have them here
are for the output, I mean, this is...
For the outputs, yes.
Yeah, I mean, this forces a valid input and you have the valid outputs.
So how could we then do that?
So actually, like here, as you can see up here, already in the definition of this code,
we do have, I mean, we have this check for the argument built into the method,
to the function itself.
So in this case here, we already have a bit of functionality to test for it.
So I would say that this is, I mean, what we have here, raise value error, that is something
with this, there's a specific, that's error handling, namely is that a program, I mean,
we didn't talk about that earlier, but that is something which is rather important for
usability for a program because when you have an intended use case and and if you
are making the code I mean if you're working the code with the inputs which
are nonsensical then it's always good to guide the use of the program to in
right direction so in this case here it will point out that it's not a meaningful thing to
try to calculate factorial for a negative number to me it's uh it's something that i think is
relatively important if you have these kind of functions because it's um very very often uh if
you have a function that can just accept any anything and gives you something you end up with
well, you end up with wrong results
instead of having an error thrown at you.
And wrong results is something that
if you notice that they are wrong,
then, okay, you can start debugging,
but you might even miss that they are wrong.
So if a function is by definition
only allowed to do certain things,
and you expect this function to be used in larger code,
it might make sense to make sure
that it doesn't get wrong inputs
and assert that certain things are not happening
because otherwise you essentially make yourself open to,
well, someone has put a wrong number in there
and you now get complete bollocks
and your results suddenly are
looking nonsensical.
I have had that
in the past that I had a function that
I
expected something to happen
and it didn't because
it
had the wrong input
parameters.
And then it was
a lot of work or a lot of
time spent finding what exactly
went wrong because I got results
but they were just complete bullocks they were complete nonsense and that's something that's
really difficult to debug sometimes yeah yeah you're right about that um i'll say that
i think it goes i mean in in many different fields of science
it is so that i mean the complexity is there which means that if you would like to cover
for all of these scenarios to i mean to provide let's say input which is nonsensical i mean
that the more you can try to catch the better i mean the example i've had here for the factorial
is i mean as simple as as it can be um i mean i know some programs where you have let's say
in the input file you can have two or even 300 different keywords and perhaps the range
with keyword if it is about let's say numerical values or sometimes it can be about switches so
that you have let's say the program will work in three four or five different modes using different
algorithms under hood sometimes i mean the i mean the common the the total number of combinations
it is i mean it's a very very large number so this is nothing that you can exhaust
which brings us to this that for that kind of advanced programs I mean the user has to
be critical to how they are using the program and well often is a little bit forgiving here
if you're doing modeling as part of research projects because after all it's not something
which is let's say it's not air traffic control or something which is let's say mission critical
that's entirely true i would i would just argue it also um helps it also helps you
uh finding bucks easier like like this uh like this factorial if you if you put uh if you have
this in a larger code and the input value for the factorial is something that's being calculated
you could well if you if you end up with a non-integer number
this probably will throw an error because range doesn't allow non-integer values but if you
if you get something that's smaller than zero in your computation that you didn't expect but
um your values given then what you will get as a result from the factorial is zero i think
or something that is definitely not what you expected it to be
mm-hmm
yeah yeah oh you get one actually if you get something negative
so so far in in the examples that we touch upon here we were working with
with numbers be they integer or be they real so i think it would be nice to have a look on
something which is working with other types of variables namely with strings so we have here
an example design a test for a function that receives two strings and returns a number
so this is here in Python we already have functionality for this implemented
so the memory function is count word occurrence in string and we have here
two input arguments the first is a string which contains a text and the second argument is the
word and this is the word for which you would like to count the currents within the text
and you can see here in the comment of the code that there's an example of
let's say example input and then this string here one two one two three four
if you query for the count of one then i mean the expected output is two
so here in python
this this function is i mean this functionality is available up front so we have here the
text.split function which will split the text into the individual words.
And we have then a count function so we can count the occurrence of
the word I mean word here in singular in the words with the object which
contains all of them all of the items in the string so we could type this through
so I start a new source code file here word currents I call it and I paste in
here the definition of this function so as we did earlier I mean we have this
function defined here in the Python code and we can I mean this being a smallish
thing we could add the test code within the same text source code file so what
What we'll then do is we start defining a test and use the keyword test underscore and
we then have the same name for the function as defined, it's only that we have the prefix
of test underscore.
Yeah, so [name], please correct me here if I do some typo.
That looks fine.
Okay, that's just the header of the test function and now the keyword is assert.
and we then call the function count word occurrence in string so we then we need
two arguments here so first you have a mini text AAA we can take BBB and we
query for one of them okay um this example input of the very simplest form
and this is an assert we need them to provide the expected answer and here yeah clearly
for this text aaa bbb we clear for aaa the expected count is one okay that
that's one variant we could then I copy this line and you can make some
variations on width so we could then have we could add here more occurrences
of AAA could have a CCC then I'm clear once again for for AAA yeah expected
count here should be two
Okay, I would say that so far it just looks a little bit, well, this is nothing difficult
in these assert statements so far, but in texts you can have, if it's like normal language,
You could have that your words, which are just a standalone word.
Sorry?
Prefixes.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
You can have prefixes, or you can have composed words.
Composite words, yeah.
Yeah.
So that can make the thing a little bit more complicated.
So let's here have another variant, namely
query for just the five a's the text is five a's and here um this is a bit interesting because
here i'm not taking this from from the lesson material and you know here the suggestion is here
okay the sort meant is that the count should be one and i would actually say no it should be zero
yeah or it should perhaps be three i i think it's not at all clear up front
yeah one well to me zero or three would be acceptable one is actually
the completely unacceptable here um three i i personally if i want to i want to have a word
count um i would assume this is zero because there is no match i'm not looking for prefixes
I'm looking for words
but
one is definitely not what I
would the function
what I would want the function to do
but
let's see what it does
yeah exactly
so
keep that one
open and
So, PyTest, world occurrence, let's see.
Okay, okay, that was then another type of error, that was just a coding error.
So we need to fix that first.
I must have typed wrong here.
no, I don't. No, I don't see it.
What was the error? Just count word occurrence in string is not
find what
okay could you go to the terminal again yeah so it does count word occurrence in
string i don't see it
okay but but i think they should not get stuck here um and so yeah could um
I think we could.
So this was still, I mean, the interesting thing that we identified here is this,
that in this case here, the function functionality here was already available.
I mean, within the Python language, we have this split and we have this count.
So we're making use of that. And then, as we already had identified here, it's not canonical what would be, let's say, the expected or desired output for having this string five A's and then querying for A, A, A.
And as [name] said, I mean, having it designed so that it should be zero.
That's yeah, I mean, that's one choice you can have for it.
Then, I mean, the one that I mentioned where you could possibly count the currents of this
string of three A's, I mean, counting it to three, depending if you're using the first
three letters, or letter two up until four, or letter three up until five.
So yet again, having the base case for what is the actual, let's say,
by construction, the intended output or function is obviously important.
So we will come to an example here which is a bit more delicate situation.
So we have here something which is a function to calculate
it's about calculating the temperature of a reactor and the input argument for this function
is a temperature in celsius and you can see the comment here this function check tractor
temperature is about checking whether the temperature is about a number,
max temperature and then returns the status. And we have here import
statements from reactor, import max temperature and what the function does
it takes the input argument temperature in celsius and it compares it with this max temperatures
so if the temperature is above yeah then the status is one
and else if it's not about the max temperature it's zero so uh okay the functionality here is
perhaps as a such reasonable but but there is a there is a problem here so so how could we test
this so the problem is essentially that we are getting a value from another
class that we don't really have control over and that could change depending on
the depending on whatever other factors there are so we don't know what this max
temperature actually is and we just want to test our functionality and we don't
want to test what the reactor package is doing, we just want to test this check
reactor temperature function. Yes, exactly. So this is a simple
illustration of a code function here which is, I mean you can test it only up
to a point because you have this external dependency and could very well be that external
dependency is something that might be let's say a moving target or something that you do
not have control over i'd say that um sometimes you have let's say some constants like parameters
in a in a program that could be for instance you have some conversion factors for
let's say converting time from hours and minutes to seconds it's clear that the factor of 60 here
is canonical it's not something that will change and depending on what program languages you have
you might have like simply this factor of 60, you might have it stored away in a variable
which is in scope so you can use that value when you are in this function.
Another option that I think might be quite common actually in academia,
you have a sensor that gives you values that has a function that picks a value and your code needs to
pick something from that sensor and use it but for your test you don't want to run this on the
actual sensor you don't want to run this on the actual hardware you want to run this independently
so you have a function that does something and you want to yeah just
fake that this is actually returning a value from something
That's a very similar situation as well.
Mm-hmm, mm-hmm.
Yeah.
Yeah, so I mean, this is all,
I mean, you can have situations where this is
simply what it is. Nevertheless,
if you have, when you, let's say, design a new code or
or augment code, we do building blocks.
With regard to testing, things become more straightforward
if you can use as much as possible pure functions.
Because then in particular unit tests
become much more trackable
because then you can do use assert statements
of the kind that we have been working with here.
but maybe have a quick look at the solution as to how you can try to get these things in
um and one option here is uh to use something that's called monkey patching
uh monkey patch is another library which essentially allows you to set values or
even functions attributes
in Python everything essentially is an
attribute so you can
replace something by
something that is well defined in your
environment so in this
case we are setting the value
the attribute of max temperature to 100
but we could also
if this is
if this is a function that
gets the value from the
from a sensor
we could replace the
i ended it's a function call or originally in your in your check uh reactor reactor or
reactor temperature uh code you we could set an attribute in the reactor that get temperature is
lambda that just returns 10.
or something like this yeah that that's really neat functionality you you
you mentioned it here that this is available as for for for python uh that that's very neat
i'm thinking here about there are similar things in other languages as well but uh yeah in python
it's um with pytest it's very convenient because um what pytest is doing here under the hood is a
so-called fixture monkey patch is a um yeah a fixed fixture that is added to pytest and available
in any test and if you and it's essentially by name so by having this argument monkey patch in
the test function pytest automatically fills in the monkey patch um fixture and then you can use
that and you can you if you have a complex system you can also define your own fixtures
which can help you in replicating things for multiple different tests so you only have to
write the setup once because otherwise you would need to write this yeah this whole
attribution setting and whatnot every time but you could also create your own fixture here
um that just says that's a temperature fixture or a a reactor fixture that essentially replaces
all the relevant values in this reactor package by what you want to have for your tests
that's something that you can do it's not shown here in the example how exactly but if you search
for PyTest and fixtures. That's essentially what this is also doing for monkey patch.
But I think we should also go on a bit because we are starting to get towards the end of the time.
Yes. And then I see in this document here that someone has caught the spelling error that I had
here in the in the code and um yeah the typo here was that there's one r missing in occurrence here
no not here in the asserts
the three lines below that
in the assert statements okay the name of the of the test function doesn't matter but um in here
there is the r's missing yeah i am yeah yeah right you're right yeah yeah certainly yeah this
yes exactly i mean did the the name here of the test function here that doesn't matter
it doesn't matter but here uh this would be here like the canonical name for it because
we just had the prefix test underscore and then the same name okay let's see now if it works
better
oh yeah
now i also save the file
yep we actually see that uh that's also in the comments um we actually see that uh what python
returns here is zero and not one for the aaa in aaa because it's not yes the function splits
it and then it's not present anymore yeah yeah yeah right uh good um so so [name] which which
um example do you think we could highlight now do you have some i i would i would go for the
end-to-end test um i wouldn't go into the randomness test for now i would go to the
end-to-end test uh because it's essentially something that you can also use for um regression
regression testing so um this is conceptually so i think it's design eight
yes so let's
move there
oh yeah it's about the unique
yeah this is also
about word counting
yes but it's for
the concept to have an end-to-end test here
I think makes a
makes a lot of sense in a lot of
yeah scientific
situations where you have
an input, you have an output
to whatever code you have
and you want to keep that
and the concept
is very similar to regression testing
which you very often want
to have for scientific
code
Yes
so this is an example
how our end-to-end test can be made for, and this is here for the unique command, so this
This is another variant of word count that you will see if a word or a string, if it
occurs in the first place, but you would like to filter out the unique occurrences of it.
And if I'm not mistaken here from what the output at least claims, it's reducing repetitions.
It's not actually looking for unique occurrences, which to me is kind of odd, but okay.
Yes, we can see here like a sample input here, which is text which clearly here is with various
lines here because we have the line breaks here and obviously it's here repeated.
we have the first line here occurring five times and then this four times
this intermission only once and so forth
yeah um so since the aim for this tool is to remove repeat remove repetitions what i would
start to write my test in is essentially have a couple of um files being either either files
being present that i can use and then compare the inputs versus outputs so what do i expect
what do i put in and what i would do is create a couple of files that are similar to the example
input here actually um somewhere there's um somewhere there's just one line being rapid
repeated and fair and check that yes this line is actually being generated again um so reading
the output of unique again into a file and then comparing it with something that i had that i have
pre-compiled um since i yeah i i'm still i find it odd that it's not that it's not
really just giving unique lines but just removes repetitions
um and it also it uh i think is supposed to keep the order so um i would also kind of make sure
that yes it will keep the order and and it will not reorder things these are the things that i
would be trying to check here in a test yeah and uh yeah and as i mentioned so so this line here
all together now, occurring there and also occurring there. That's somewhat unexpected
because I mean, I agree. I would have preferred to see it only written up here and not here.
But yet, but again, yeah, from the name, unique, exactly. But like in general, this
This can often be the case that, well it can be the case that when some function is written
then there's some freedom in designing what it should do and how it should do it.
So I mean this is like, this was unexpected and, but it was intentional and then your
text test need to adopt to that um i see here that we have only a few minutes left
and i think here so we did here intentionally hold on to python during this lesson
and as you if i scroll back up here to the well all the way up to the factorial sorry
Factorial example, you probably have seen it already, but if not, we have these different
tabs here.
So Python to the left, but then you can, let's say here you have the function definition
here in in c plus plus and there is a template solution for how to test this in with frameworks
in in in the respective language so for c plus plus you could then for instance use
the catch 2 framework which is available here
well I mean you need to have it on your computer and then you can have them use the include
statement here and then you can get going and you also have correspondingly you have for instance
for Julia R and also for Fortran so here you have some some template Fortran code and here in the
template solution here we are oh sorry for this one the template solution was
actually not there but let's say here for Julia
yeah Julia without touching upon Julia itself it is a rather modern language
where we do have a framework for testing is already there and from the beginning
a little bit in analog with that pytest is sort of available for Python and we
could also highlight here that so if we go here to I mean the very start of the
lesson and now if I open the menu here so you have here under the reference
setting here you have quick reference and here you have a rather extensive
listing of the unit test frameworks and regression test frameworks and so forth
and they have it then broken down to various languages so yeah this is a
place that that you probably would like to have a look at and then if you're
If you're looking for something for C++ or for Julia, you can then find some suggestions on tools that you could make use of.
I want to mention one general thing, which is mainly for non-compiled code or non-compiled languages.
um where what you should well keep in mind when doing testing um if you have anything that
touches global variables or class variables or similar things so um variables that
stay after something is executed make sure that you reset them after the test
because otherwise they might otherwise you might end up depending a bit depending on the
framework you're using you might end up with something that was modified in a previous test
yeah you or yeah just a general comment here
Indeed. And I think it goes also for compiled languages that could be that, I mean, they're executed within a runtime environment that, let's say you have it with some default setting and if you, let's say, work in a terminal on, could be like a, well, in a way it doesn't matter if it's in your local computer or if it is on a shared computer.
because typically also on the shared computer you would like that to have a grip on
your runtime environment so it's like for your session it's your runtime environment
but if you poke around with it set some environment variables and so forth
then if you have first been worked with a and then you go on to work with b then yeah you might
want to have like a reset after working with a before you get going with b
so we can bring up here the notes to see if
yeah there's been some some interaction here um
some questions and some
some answers
say yeah how often do you make end-to-end tests in scientific code um
but not as often as i should is probably for me uh it's
in in the end if you have if if you have an example of your code that is an end-to-end
test or you can easily make it into an end-to-end test you can simply run your example and write a
test that when running my when running the in the code with the input from that example
i would expect the outputs that i just got from this example
yes um
You're right.
So my experience is from courses that I'm working with, either as a user or as a developer,
then end-to-end tests or, yeah, I'm more acquainted with them or have, let's say, direct contact
with them more commonly.
One elegant thing, and there's no time now for us to show like that example, but some
elegant solutions in some codes, we have, let's say, the capacity to do all of this
is that, I mean, you have it all.
You have like the unit tests, you have the integration tests, and you have also the regression
tests.
have it also part of sort of like the build procedure like you configure you make if it's
a compiled language and then after the make or make install you make then also like make check
and it runs then through that could be tens of tests or can even be into the thousands of tests
so now it's
5 past 11 so
it's about time to wrap up
and
it will then be the lunch break and
so what do we have after lunch
[name]
after lunch we are going into
modular
code development so
how do you
get your code into a shape
that it's more easily reusable
how
do you get code
out of this is one large
script that does everything into
pieces that are
testable
that are reusable
by you or by others
and yeah similar
things
yes
that sounds interesting
So we look forward to that lesson and yeah, let's then conclude this part on, on testing
and have a nice lunch break.
All of you.
Let's see you back in roughly an hour.
Bye.
you
and welcome back
Hello. So, yeah, we have some questions in the notes to get started.
So essentially this, the modular coding session is a demonstration and essentially a pair coding demonstration.
And it's also a way of wrapping up and tying everything together.
So it should touch on most things that we have talked about during this entire workshop.
So we have a few different questions in the notes.
It would be great if you could answer at least the first three.
And then we'll get going once we have a few answers to talk through.
Well, we can already start with essentially our answers to the questions.
Yeah, why not?
So I'll start with what does modular code development mean for you?
So for me, it's if you try to structure your code such that you actually have different parts that are responsible for different things
and make clear distinctions as to okay this is something this is a logical logical pack that
belongs together and therefore it's executed in one function um this is a logical group of things
so this is one package and so on that's what module development is about for me yeah so we um
started with version control and we went essentially like we went all the way to
sharing it and putting things online collaborating with sharing code changing someone else's code and
so on um and to me the best although the most um clear definition is when you can actually
take a piece of code maybe maybe an a feature you have create a function you have written
and actually contribute it back to the original software so the original code or even even better
take it and contribute it to some other code base in a way that makes sense so then that
if you can do that then the original that the code base you're contributing to is modular
in the sense that you can put a module in and it works.
And also your starting point is modular
because there is some module that you can pick up
and put somewhere else.
It becomes usable in many different situations.
And this, of course, it happens on different levels.
It could be a function, but it could also be an entire,
well, a Python module, which means a file
or a library in
C
or C++ and so on.
This is also what you
have started writing there
essentially.
The general idea seems to be
pretty similar.
This also
has something to do with unit testing in that
a unit that you can test is
a module
if it doesn't have too many side effects.
A function you can test
is a module that you can
also then plug out
in some way.
Okay, best practices
to arrive at
a well-structured modular code
in your favorite programming
language. I don't actually know what my favorite language
is.
To me, it's
designing well
as in
if I want to have a certain
functionality uh what parts of this functionality are actually reusable what parts of these
functionality are specific to exactly what this is going to do and then separate things that are
more that i think are more generally usable and things that are well more more more specific to
this one task also potentially depending again on the project if it's large enough
thinking about how could someone else provide an alternative approach to some parts of my code
and at which point i automatically have to think okay i might need to have an interface or
something and this inter implementation of this interface that's one piece so i can define the
interface and then put in an implementation someone else could define a different implementation for
the same thing that automatically creates modular code because things can be replaced easily
essentially you surround the module with an interface so yeah if you have a defined interface
what is inside can change and so it is plug and play so one very practical thing um that i at
least when i was like writing mostly c code um in research i saw people use global values global
references so you define some something you define a thing that needs to be accessible essentially
everywhere in the code and you make it globally accessible which means it's not explicitly there
in the arguments of a function for example so like in simulation programs you often do this for
like the world the the 3d world that you are simulating so that kind of thing make means
you cannot take the function
and put it in a different code, right?
Whereas if it's explicit,
if you put the parameter directly
into the function definition,
then you can put it in anywhere
as long as they know to provide that parameter correctly.
So explicit is better than implicit in that sense.
That's, and yeah,
So basically, yeah, writing small functions with a specific task
and then making their interactions explicit.
Have everything that goes into the function be visible in the function definition
and everything that it does should also be visible
either by looking at the return value or looking at the comments.
What I also, that's partly in the answers here as well.
So try not to create a large script that you're running.
Because as soon as there is really computational functionality
in the run script that you have
that could be handled in a function,
it becomes potentially, as it's mentioned here,
difficult later on to refactor this into a function
or to refactor your code such that
this calls a function
and
the sooner you say
this is not about
the individual actions
of my script anymore
this is about
handling what I'm doing
this can normally go into
a function
so if I have something like
a script that I'm
running, this is commonly
create my target
object or whatever
and then run individual functions on that thing.
But I'm not having any,
I would say functional code in there,
in the main script.
All this is just,
essentially I can read through my main script
and know that first it's reading the data.
Second, it's pre-processing.
Third is this, fourth is this.
And just by reading through,
I essentially have one line
for all of these tasks
because it's the function call that does it
that helps me
essentially the same is also true for functions
if the function starts to be longer than
you can actually read and understand
then it's probably too long
it can be split into smaller pieces
that do simpler individual things
and then can be reused
at different places
it's kind of optimally
your code
by just reading through it
explains what it's doing
until you come to so small pieces
that they are relatively obvious
what they are doing
since I said
something about
what the code should be like
so
the reason is to
make it understandable
to make it easier so
it's not just about
style and
like
well it's not just about
telling people
what good code is in some way
this is all
practical advice right
so it makes it easier
to understand and change
and reuse
which is the point
yeah
So what do we have in C? We have, or did we actually go through the answers in B?
Mostly. This is, yeah, minimum things.
Put them in functions.
Smallest task that could be reused.
This is not directly modular code, but in general, having simple and useful comments is very, very useful in general development, regardless of modular or not.
Yeah. So I guess, yeah, maybe I already said this, essentially, the one big thing that kind of defines what modular means here is, or in general, what modular action means is, the code or each part of the code should avoid interacting with other parts of the code as much as possible.
so essentially i would say as much as sensible yeah as much as possible yeah i mean you can
always reduce interactions to zero if you just um uh if you don't care about whether it works
um yeah as much as makes sense of us yeah what you what you very often uh see in things like
style suggestions and so on
is also having not too many input arguments
for functions, which means that
there needs to be a certain balance between
what responsibilities certain functions have
and where they get their data from.
So if your function, because you want to output
it into a function, starts to have 20 input arguments,
it's likely that it's doing
either it's doing more than it should
be doing or it
might be better to have a different
logical unit than a function for this
this might be something that a class should
be doing that you initialize with
a couple of values and then provide
additional data into individual
functions
I've been talking a lot about functions
and
you can also
the data types
and data can also be
modular so you can
combine different values
that are in some way related.
So if you have data about a mesh
that you're running a simulation on,
that mesh can contain multiple different things.
It can contain objects, density, color,
all sorts of things.
And in many cases,
you would want all of those things to be stored under the same name.
So then you could create a data structure or a class or something like that
to put multiple different things in.
And then you can pass that as a single argument.
It also makes it easier to read.
So this is now a single unit of some kind of custom data.
this is the mesh that contains
all the information about
the mesh about all
points in the mesh
something like the world
let's call this a world
or an environment
it has cities, forests
and whatever and you can get those
by either functions or
other properties
yeah
okay
what do you know about programming
that you wish somebody told you earlier, Jaano?
I mean, I should have started using version control from the beginning.
It would have saved a lot of time when I broke something and
essentially had to slowly step by step undo the work until it works again.
So yeah, that's also one of the answers, essentially.
creating a copy before you start
making changes. Version control
does that for you. It's a very good
idea to do.
I would agree with the
use an IDE editor with color coding.
It depends a lot
on the languages that you're using,
but in general,
at least to me,
things like going to definitions of certain imports or something or going to definitions
of functions via an IDE is extremely helpful because this is originally more from typed
languages and pre-compiled languages but nowadays it essentially also works with Python and for
example vs code that you can just right click on a function call go to definition and you get the
function that is being called at this point and you can look into the function what does it actually
do and it helps in understanding what is happening here and um yeah it it just makes it so much more
graspable
what your code is doing
even if it's not that well
or what someone else's code might be doing
if it's not that well documented
yeah
I think actually
modularity
and unit testing
are things that would have been
very useful
to know something about earlier
I remember
at some point I hit upon the
practice of
write a test that
checks
as much of the functionality as possible.
It was essentially
running the code, running
an entire instance of the
code and checking that the values
match some expectations.
But these were all end-to-end tests.
I didn't have any unit tests.
So it would basically
only tell me that something's broken now.
Yeah. So, I think it's time to go to the demonstration. What do you think?
Yep. Let's go to our task.
Yeah.
Okay, so we have some weather data.
And what are we going to do with this data?
What we want to do is essentially, we want to plot the data over time
and make this a bit more modular.
because at the moment we have this kind of script that just plots something
yeah so i guess um
the starting point for me with this would be um i would have this piece of code in a jupiter
notebook that i wrote to do a specific task to um yeah to plot the stuff so here we are
which we essentially have here. We can define the number of measurements here,
but anytime we want to change the number of measurements, we have to modify this and then
hope that we are not forgetting to run something. At the moment, this is what we get.
We can update that, but once we do that, we essentially need to run all the
individual pieces again and we hope to not forget for example to reread the temperatures because
otherwise we get a complete mess in later stages okay so um let me add the bottom of the nodes
I will call it the modular code task,
and I'll also copy in the correct section of the materials.
Okay.
Now, the task is then to make this code better in some way.
What can we do to make it better?
So yeah, please go, if you have ideas,
write into the notes. What do you think we could do here? So one thing, I think, just
looking at the plot, I'm not really sure what is happening there. I mean, you clearly have
a plot of temperatures, but maybe it would be useful, especially if you want to take
the plot and put it in the paper to have
some axis labels.
Yep.
So how would we do that?
So
the
labels, do they
need to be defined before you start
grading the plot?
I think so.
So that's
plt.x
label
and plt.y
label. It makes sense
to put it where you define the number of measurements
this is
x label is a function
it's x label
and then it takes us
yeah yeah okay
so x is days
okay I think so
that
makes sense yeah why not
uh
the temperature
in celsius yeah
I don't find the degree sign
here on that keyboard at the moment
that's not a problem
okay
so now I guess you do need
to rerun the whole thing
okay that just running that
cell did weird things
I guess it has the plot
in memory already and it's outputting
the plot why is that happening
hmm
um because probably this the y label function i guess returns the bot
so it gets displayed yeah okay that works let's do some nope that actually didn't change anything
uh did you try rerunning from the beginning just uh um the restart and run everything
so it's the
two triangles
double run button
looks like a fast forward button
yeah
I've actually never seen
that that's weird
okay well
so this obviously
doesn't work
no I guess we can put
it where
we define the same cell as the plot
might be that this is because
it's in cells
like the original
well okay that works better
that was weird I've never seen that before
that might have been because it's in
well cells now
yeah but I think
well anyway I guess
let's not
but
But it might anyways be an idea to get this
and move it to an actual function
and then reduce what we have here in the plotting
to something that only calls those functions.
Yeah, let me first suggest a complication.
And I guess this is a step towards making it a function.
But the complication is to, instead of just making one plot,
make three different plots with different values
of the number of measurements.
So that means actually now you need to combine
basically all of these cells into a single cell.
because the follow inside the follow up if you change the number of measurements what does that
affect it affects the the part where you read the data because that already sits sets the number of
rows read and then well i guess it doesn't well maybe then you are using that the red data to set
the, yeah, the, the temperature values, okay, temperature values,
so that changes. And then the mean of course changes. And
yeah, everything changes. Okay. And then everything. Yeah. Okay,
So now we have a few different plots being created.
Start this.
So one issue that we had in the original
is not there because we have the days everywhere
because we have them not.
Oh, yeah, we are setting it inside the form.
So if we would redo it like this...
No, you're going to get an extra plot,
and none of the other plots are going to happen.
That's true.
Well, we can.
Yeah, but I mean, it looks like the plot function
is independent of the label setting functions,
but it's actually not.
The plot function, when you say plot.show...
No, actually, no, that's not what's happening here.
what is happening here is that we call plot dot clear um clf yep clear what is the f figure
clear figure okay thanks uh so so we are actually removing the labels oh and we
was forgot something uh well yes going to count that yeah so um you probably want to make it an
string yeah okay yeah so now we are uh changing the file name based on the number of measurements
okay that didn't actually work uh we
it did oh okay it just took a bit to upload update the okay fine so yeah now we actually
have the images that we can include in our um paper about the temperatures in the helsinki
airport um if it loads well well i'm hoping that the png file is actually correct can you
check the one with 25 well png should be it shouldn't depend on the number of i mean it's a
it's a pixel map okay well how seriously do we want to take the um plots being incorrect
rather though the files i don't think it's an issue at the moment
yeah let's go on and we are going to move this into the terminal at some point anyway
Okay. Well, I mean, now we do have this for loop, and we could, this also kind of nicely defines one possible way of splitting it into functions.
I guess that's not really splitting if you take the whole thing and make it a single
function.
Okay, let's, it's going to be a Python file, okay, you're moving into, moving the
whole thing into a script, that makes sense.
Okay, this is not really modular yet, but yeah, before people listening, please do make
suggestions like we are going to actually follow the suggestions that people make in
the notes.
Okay, so now we have, I guess you have to activate the environment.
So now we have a Python function.
Actually check.
Okay, let's check.
What happens?
Yeah, that works.
Okay, and it's creating the file.
It's creating the images.
Oh, it's displaying the images.
Okay, that's fine.
and I need to close them
sometimes that's what you want
sometimes not
but yeah
somehow the files are broken
actually
they are white
okay well let's
take a look at the code then
so it did display them correctly
but the figures being saved
are not
which is a bit strange
that's interesting
well what should we do um well there's definitely one thing that's sort of
functionally separate from everything else which is the plot results part right yeah um so that is
it's doing two things actually it's showing the plot well okay three things it's constructing
the plot, showing the plot,
and saving
it into an image, which for some
reason is not working.
Let's make a function out of this.
Yeah.
So do we want to continue showing the plot
since we are running from the terminal?
I don't
think so, but what we could do
is
we could return the plot.
Yeah.
Yeah, well, I mean, I was going to say, why not, but we are clearing it between each iteration.
Do we?
Because, do we actually need to do that?
I guess we do.
I think we do need to clear it, but what might work is to essentially indicate during the plot data that we want to get a plot, that we want to get some Xs or something.
Maybe that's too much.
okay well uh let's just go on and uh take the whole plotting section move it into a function
function for now yeah and uh that can be fine-tuned later but it's the straightforward
thing to do is to make a new function so now it's taking temperature number of measurements
So the number of measurements affects the file name.
So it is actually...
Does it only affect...
Yeah, it only affects the file name.
Then we might rename that because...
It could be file name.
Yeah, that makes sense.
Okay, and then we construct the file in there.
Okay, so this seems to make sense, although, well, I guess the fact that the function is
defined below, does it matter?
I think it does.
Yeah, there's a difference in how it works in inside classes and in the normal script.
classes you can reorder about the about a script test to have everything defined before it's being
called yeah okay so huh here's a question there we are why do we calculate oh did it actually
create the oh right okay so um one question why do we calculate the mean
oh because it is actually used in the plot right yes in fact somebody said that in the oh yeah
notes and i uh i just didn't understand um okay so um yes you should also include mean as a parameter
Yeah, if you want to have it in the box.
Okay.
And the reason I'm ordering it temperatures mean, because personally to me, temperatures
and mean are what this function actually needs.
And for file name, if I just want to use this once, I could actually give a default value.
Yeah, it could be an option.
That's why I...
kind of ordered in a way um by um by similar things okay
so this is what we now get
which looks yeah okay okay so now it just shows them again and again
it looks like the files are not working correctly they are not um
Okay. Well, we can come back to that at some point. It's a bit weird that we're starting
from a code that doesn't work and trying to make it better by fixing it. Yeah, I just
I don't really know what it could be.
What if we remove the show?
Does that help?
Let's see.
Yes, that helps.
Okay.
What is that?
That's a very good question.
Well, fine.
Now we have some plots.
That's good.
Might it be that show actually clears the plot?
Yeah, could be.
let's test something
okay
what happens if we do this
need to save it
so I'm getting the plots
and
I'm getting the images
so seemingly show cleans
yeah okay but well I mean
that's on one hand interesting
that's good to know
So very much like a Matplotlib-specific thing, a Python-specific thing. So yeah.
Okay, so there are for loops, functions, and so on. You can get this far,
or you can do exactly the same things in any language.
Setting the labels will, of course, be a different function depending on the library.
all of that i think what we can also um move into a function is reading the data
yes so reading the data and this is a suggestion directly from the notes so
another function for reading the data and it could be so read data is very general
and it makes sense it could also be read temperatures or something like that
Well, let's call it readData, if I know.
So the readData reads the temperatures from the CSV file, and it then also picks the column.
So it specifically is the data that we want in this case.
Okay, should we also have a...
I could...
Well, we could make this a bit more general.
well yeah yeah let's uh let's do that since i um since i already mentioned it at this point
might as well do it so you can give it a um file name argument i i would leave it at file name and
um so we are assuming that we have a certain format of the of the data and that this format
it has a column air temperature
degree Celsius.
That's the assumption
that we are putting in. We don't
necessarily know what file name
this is being saved in.
No.
We don't know the output file name.
The read data
needs the input file.
There is one good point
in the notes. There's many
good points in the notes.
One new good point
in the notes, which is that
we could read the data just once
instead of reading it many times
and then taking
the
first n rows.
That's
also an option. Then we remove
this
completely.
We'd need to then put
this
temperature
data is read data this and then we have temperatures blah there's an arrow missing
okay is um actually that is temperature data frame yeah and i'm never sure about
the the exact syntax it's a column so i think you can do a direct number indices
and then it starts with zero yeah i mean you don't have to explicitly write zero but then again why
not let's see if that works um the notes are also suggesting a command line interface is that should
Should we first think about functions a bit more?
Looks correct.
Look at side effects.
So OK, let's have a look.
Personally, I said I would wonder whether we
can return the plot data.
So something like instead of.
and have a
um
so if you are constructing
a new plot you might as well clear it
when you start
right
yeah and then leave it open that's true
Yeah, at which point we could also, in theory, do a this is PLT and then PLT.show to get our visuals back in, for example, a Jupyter Notebook.
Yep.
If you want to put this back into a Jupyter Notebook.
So this function is then usable both as a function in a program
and in a Jupyter Notebook where we want to, in the end, present this.
Yeah, that makes sense.
Okay, did you try running it, though?
Not yet.
But this seems to be correct.
Yeah, it works. Good.
I didn't test it with the PLT.show yet.
Let's see.
Yeah, I'm getting the plots.
I need to now close them again so that it finishes,
but I'm getting the plots.
Yeah.
Okay.
Well, yeah, we don't need the plot.show now.
If you prefer to keep it, then why not?
so in the in this script no we don't need them yeah if we want to put this
way we could we could actually notebook yeah go back to our notebook so what is
it that we currently need to do we essentially have this is what we are
currently doing yeah this is nice to show i mean basically so what we're showing here is um how
you import your own code into the notebook and then when it imports some functions from
no there wasn't weather prediction it was whether what was the name
it was better predictions okay
okay
so yeah importing from the
back from the file
there's an extra
ict
of predictions
predictions
yeah
okay so now we have
data
okay
so that makes sense
and there we are and now our our our script our jupiter script essentially says okay we are
reading data and then we are going over different measurements there is barely any functional code
here anymore so so what do you think about the mean calculation um it is like if you if
we're calculating more complicated statistics, it should become its own function. But it is not a
super complicated thing here, is it? To me, here's a bit of a point. For this mean, I probably
wouldn't create a function. But for the purpose of this, I would probably create something that does
build some statistics
and I would probably
because it's
not that likely that it's just the mean
that you normally need
for statistics.
If you just want
to mean, so there's a very good point
in the notes again.
Writing your own
mean function is also a bit
stupid.
It's like if you want
the standard mean
well I mean yeah the mean the average
there's multiple different averages that we could use so in that sense having a function where you can go
and change which average you want might make sense
but we could also use numpy.mean
or actually it is a pandas column so you can
call just temperatures.mean
would i think it would work i think there's a mean function just directly embedded in the
pandas column class so in in any case i mean whatever language you're using almost certainly
it already has a mean uh function in it or some pretty much like it yes yeah
so so yeah we don't actually have to write our own mean function for this one although
So, again, it would also be a good example.
It's one of the things that you might want to do,
but, well, you already wrote two functions.
So, there's actually a different question
that I would be kind of asking here.
Is the mean actually an input to the plot function or not?
Because the mean here is just used
to create a plot line at the mean level.
so and is something that is a derivative from temperatures so we don't need this as an input
yeah you could move that calculation into yeah and i think this is i don't know what do people
think is this better i think it makes sense this way it also makes sense depending on what you're
doing it might make sense to have um a line argument or x line or is it a y line whichever
it is um in the plot data that allows you to just define where the line goes and it then it doesn't
have to be a mean necessarily it could be whatever line you want um but going a bit into going a bit
um over the top of how this could be designed conceptually temperatures could be a class or
something we could have a temperature object class where you can set what kind of things you want to
have like what kind of average value you want to use and then you would essentially
say temperatures.average and temperatures.values instead of
these two
and then have it dependent on the temperature.
So people want to get to the command line.
One more thing before
we go there.
What do you think of the comments? Oh, actually
two more things. One,
what's the error message
that you get when you run this?
And
how do you figure out where the error is?
Can you run it?
Okay. So how do we figure out what the error message is? This is not the error I was expecting.
I was expecting a different one.
Maybe there is a different one. So I removed the means here. So I need to do that here.
Yeah. So I guess my main point is there's no reason to be scared of errors. They just tell
you the line that you need to change, usually, in almost any language. In some languages,
though you need to fiddle around like compile it differently to get the line numbers but still
um it's always did you mean that error to get errors yes i meant this one
so that's on line uh 11. okay yeah and this is something that a good ide would actually flag
like during the development, that this is not existent, so this can't work.
Yeah.
So two things we want to do, or at least two things, command line interface and tests.
Which do we do first?
So we have command line interface twice in the nodes.
Yeah, then let's go for command line interface.
So let's go with that.
and uh what's your favorite i think um i have started using click more and more because
i've learned it from code refinery and it's um it's convenient i'm generally fine with whatever
um i haven't personally used click that much but um you can in the worst case uh go uh
send me yeah i mean this is again something that i'm like
different languages have their different implementations of how to do command line
arguments so we'll do it again in python the example is in python but yeah you can search
the web for command line interface and the language that you're using and there will
almost certainly be a very good library for doing them in a simple way okay so
So to do this, we want to foreclick.
Yeah, you need a main function.
And then you need to define how you give those arguments in the command line.
Actually, we don't have an out file at the moment.
So our old file is currently fixed. We can change that later, maybe.
So if I see that right, then we have a definition that this is...
So this is kind of an annotation to the main function.
But yeah, this is a command.
Yeah. So now this main function is something you can run from the command line,
and then you add options so options are the command line arguments and they also
must have the same name as oh well i mean the easiest thing to do
is to give them the same name as the parameters of the main function
actually looking at this this is not the same name
this has a minus in fact yes this is well that's a peculiarity of python
yeah maybe a good number of other languages have the same issue so you cannot have a minus sign
inside the name right it would be num minus measurements it would be a math calculation
not a name so uh it has to be an underscore but click will automatically convert the
minus sign into an underscore
here.
Is the
order relevant, or is it really
name matching? The order should be the same
as in the options.
Then it's just the order that it's
using. I think I've tried.
We can try. If you change
the name, I think it will work.
We can also try changing the order.
Well, if we have time.
so these are the two values that we have and then we essentially have our functionality here
and we need to
Oh, no, we have the outfile.
Ah, we have an outfile.
Yeah, of course we have an outfile.
Well, yeah, if we are
plotting one particular number of...
No, we have an outfile.
Yeah, but we can simply replace this
by the outfile.
Yeah, yeah.
So we have an outfile.
Modular.
the modularity helps here already
we have one specific number of measurements
and then a specific name for the output file
that means we don't have the follow-up anymore
yeah, that's true
that's something I just wanted to ask
how do you set defaults in Qlik?
a good question
we don't have it in the example
But probably since this default depends on a different import, let's just have it required.
So, yeah, in this case, it would be nice to show how you add a default value.
It's just default equals something. But for the outfile,
yeah, you should not, you can say default equals none.
Yeah, but then you don't have an outfile number.
but that you mean if it's none then you use the number of measurements
but you also have to remove the required equals true
if you have default equals none i i think at least it makes sense this way
so now we check if a the alt file is not given so the default value is none that's usually easy
to check and usually not what you want so then we can use this default value
okay and otherwise we just use whatever value is in out file so um yeah that should be in file
you could also set this to false and um just have to have another default value for temperatures
of csv or something okay it depends on like how you want to use the interface
a default value for an input file can be surprising
and you generally want to avoid surprises
so now we have the out file now we don't have the for loop anymore right yes we don't have that
anymore yeah oh and yeah now we need the standard python thing if name equals underscore underscore
name if if the name equals main with lots of underscores um then we call the main function
and if you don't know python this doesn't mean anything to you and if you know python
it still doesn't mean anything to you it's just python okay um if i'm calling that correctly it's
due to forks and things, so if you have multiprocessing, only one of the things
will be called main, and therefore execute the main, and everything else will not do that.
Yeah, so essentially if you import it as a module, then main will not execute, and we can still
import it in the Jupyter code, and it will work the same way as before. But if you run it as a script,
then this main section will execute.
So it's something you see often.
If you write something incorrectly or just don't remember what the parameters are
will produce a message that tells you how to run. Okay, it didn't create a 26. Yes,
it did. Okay.
It did. It just takes time to show up.
Okay. So it works. Great. One thing I was thinking a while ago, what do you think
about the comments in this main function?
read the data from a file
this is definitely the wrong place
but readData
the function name readData is
it tells you
exactly the same thing
you don't need the comment
this comment is
more self-explanatory
this could be a
select the
requested
measurements
could
well
I would say for anyone who has
worked with Pandas a bit it's clear what this
does but might still be
useful to have
and then
plot results
so the point is the function
names explain what is happening
if someone is just looking through the
main function
we don't need to actually explain in comments
because now since we made the code modular
and we used helpful function names,
the comments are suddenly a lot less necessary.
The code explains itself, right?
Okay.
Can you also try running this from the Jupyter Notebook?
so we should see that it still works
you mean
where is my
you mean rerunning what we had here
yeah
so this is importing the two functions
and yeah
so the fact that we made this
added this command line interface
doesn't actually change anything
let's restart this
because we have an import here
and
yeah well actually yes
something can change
we no longer give the mean as a parameter
true
you see that's why restarting
was important
true
but yes
general it works
we just had a
small bug
because we changed
our
yeah
so the next thing was to
add tests
no the next thing I think would be to
to have this input
I hope that click
does something with this
yeah it works
So, yeah, this is what Qlik provides you, essentially, all this additional information,
and that you essentially have a command line interface where you can get the standard parameters
like help, some information about, okay, how does this work, and so on.
Okay, yeah, that makes sense.
So yeah, we're just telling what the default value actually is.
If you don't provide a default, I think it's a good idea to help or to give this kind of information.
Oh, and yes, it is in fact time for a break.
We have been going on for an hour.
And yes, since we are not following a schedule, I'm not keeping an eye on it.
It is definitely already, like I should have started the break a while ago, I guess.
but we can take the break now
for 10 minutes and be back
at 14.10
and then do the tests after that
yeah
okay so
yeah let's take a break
walk around a little bit and see you then
bye
see you later
you
and hi again
so we wanted to
get into testing
yeah so
um where would you put the tests i personally would create a tests folder
so it's not a huge project we only have one python file but let's assume it might get become
bigger at some point and even then even if you have just a single python file i would at least
create a separate file for the tests but that's just like i guess we are dealing with relatively
big projects every single time. Well, in any case, it does not hurt. So we can create a test folder,
and then there is a test weather predictions file there. And it's empty.
Yeah, there's nothing there at the moment.
do we test um we have two functions um in our package
was it retail data okay so um
these are both a little bit more complicated than it they're not just returning they're not taking
input values and returning values. Well, read data is, but it is doing something else. It's
reading from disk. And the other one is creating a file to disk. So we can still test this. And
it might actually be quite useful to show that it's not that complicated. So why don't we do
that? Okay, now there's a data folder. Because we want to essentially have our test data as
data for the tests so we create and this could be essentially anything formatted like uh the data we
are reading but in this case we have an example file already so why not use that um so yeah we've
copied the file that contains the temperatures temperatures of csv into this uh data folder
and now we can make a test read data function.
So for PyTest specifically,
the folder name should be tests.
The module that contains the tests
should be test underscore something.
And then the function also needs to be
test underscore something.
But this depends on the framework.
But yeah, so that is why the structure
that we have here exists.
Okay, so test read data.
So what do we do? We call the readData function. I don't think we need really any preample. We can
just call it, give it the file name. And I guess it's in... Is the path relative? It's always
relative to what it's called from. Yeah. And we will call it from the main, so...
Yeah. So it's test slash data slash temperatures dot csv. Okay. And now we can check some values.
Yeah. Where was it?
So it's the green. Yeah.
The values that we had. So let's-
We only take the air temperature column. That's the only column we have. So we can take
number eight. Number eight will actually be-
Number seven.
Python starts indexing from zero. So it's the index seven. Yeah. We do an asset. So one thing
is you can write a test function that doesn't have any asserts, and then the test will fail
only if there's an error. But that can happen. But yeah, so we are checking that the data is
also read correctly 16. so in a lot of cases you won't be able to have exactly the same data in
the in your tests because you don't want to push them to a public repository if you're publishing
your code um but then you can you can create just like randomly type numbers by hand into the file
and that's fine. You can probably use a different text editor than Jupyter labs
to open the CSV file and type some numbers in. And I'm putting the Aprox here also for the minus four
because the problem might be that this line is read as a floating number and we might get
something that is yeah not exactly four most like most likely it is exactly four or minus four but
yeah yeah i mean i guess one of these things where you it might be useful to show that there's an
error but then again it's also that it's specifically pandas that's reading it as
folding point it might happen it might not happen with a different library or different
language and so on so yeah let's just do it like this that this looks good looks correct
Does the read data take any other parameters?
Yes. It takes a column. So we could just...
Oh, you can try a different column name, like time. No, well...
Time might be difficult. The problem is everything else is exactly the same all the
time. So no, wait, the D is not the same. Okay. It's day.
Yeah.
temperatures. Let's see. Yeah, scroll down a good bit to say zero is one and temperatures
62 is three.
These will probably be in the church spot. Oh, you can Yeah, proxy doesn't hurt doesn't
really hurt here okay um so let's try running the test so now we run pi test
it found the test which is nice it also yeah and notice that we do not actually have this module
in the um so yeah i guess this is a bit too python specific
Yeah, this is very specific.
We just have to add a dot in front, right? Or is that relative to the tests?
Let's see. I'm never entirely sure. No, this is... I hate it.
What's the right way around this? This is the annoying thing with it. I mean, the right
way around this would be to turn the whole thing into a package.
Yep, which I'm just doing. This is a bit hacky now, but it's not really. It goes like this.
Yeah, I mean, the thing that makes it a package is that there is an init file.
Do I need an init?
I think you do, in the app folder.
bit set of txt. So there is an extra Yeah, yeah. Okay.
No, no, it didn't know module named app or
Okay.
I think so if you don't get all the package, then you have to either have it in the same
folder as the test or it needs to be a this works on different things
i know that i'm doing exactly this on other projects
anybody is no no comments in the notes so yeah i mean this is one of these things where i'm
I often get confused about what's happening.
Okay, then in this case...
But if we move the test file into the main folder,
and we also move the main file back into the main folder.
No, let's do something that I personally don't really like too much.
But in this case, I think we'll just do this.
well I mean you don't have to do
you don't have to put it in the same file
as long as
they're in the same folder it should work
okay
let's see
actually cut
because we don't want to have this twice
so
one common solution
also is to add
the
path where your
main code is
to add it to the
Python path
where it looks for packages.
Okay, now it actually ran.
PyTest is not defined.
Oh, yes, of course.
No, it's not fun because
We didn't import it here.
Oh, right. It's this PyTest.lab.rocks.
Okay, nice.
Okay, now it passed.
Right.
Good.
This is the test for
our read data.
I guess we still
have our test data
in the tests folder.
We can do read.
Let's assume that the 25 here is correct.
So let's have plot data.
So this shouldn't take too long, but we also don't have too long, so
we can take a couple of minutes to do this and then wrap up.
So this now gets a little bit more complicated because we have the problem that
need a temporary folder here because we need to write to a file for a test that should be a
temporary file but python has a package called temp file which i will use for this purpose
and this is again something that almost any language will have yeah so this gives you
a temporary file name that you can but you can create the file safely and you will not be
overwriting anything. Where that file exactly is will depend on the operating system.
I don't need anything here. And now I need, actually, is it file.name?
So let's look quickly. So you create a temporary file with tempfile.temporaryfile.
Yeah, it's .name. Okay.
And yeah, okay. You found it first. Good.
should work and then file.name and now we need to compare this with the file
that we have so do you have a standard solution there is not really a file
fileCmp. Yeah, fileCmp might make...
I assume that almost any language has a file comparison.
One way or another, worst case, you need to compare these with...
Yeah, so it's fileCmp.CMP, fileName1, fileName2. And I think we can do shallow equals true
Well, it's not going to take that long anyway.
Yes.
Slash 25.png.
Okay.
And then just an assert here.
Yeah.
Oops.
That's one too many.
Let's see if this works.
It will not work because they have a different modified time.
Can I ignore that?
So this is not the contents of the file that is comparing.
Sorry, this is, should we read in the data and read in some bytes from the data and compare
that or just i don't want to feel uh to leave it at this point but um
well but we have very limited time okay then maybe we can do file one
so open both with open file name one as file one
or this is the
as
test
is the file we wrote
not in parentheses
this is a variable name
or test output
and then with
test output okay
with
yeah this file name
as
correct output
test correct
okay
so now it's opened both files
and then you go if
test output dot read
and that's a function
parentheses
no
test underscore output
sorry
and also if doesn't have parentheses
is it has yes i'm working in typescript and javascript too much yeah no well not i mean
it's this is a peculiarity of python again so if it's equal to um isn't it correct output
you can do assert yeah
okay that should work it's actually comparing the entire contents of the files which are
it's a bit over the top but okay yes in object doesn't have an attribute right so
what are we doing so this is in line 18 let's look at line 18 we can figure it out
okay yeah plot data file name oh what is our plot data plot data takes temperatures and
text file name and attribute does what oh it's it's line 12 in plot data
maybe we um oh oh oh no no okay okay okay now um this is no this is incorrect um
I think what we need here is this okay I think this test is always the fun part it happens
very often. Okay.
Because the thing is, um, the file name just gave gave the the
integer the location of the file. Okay, this is a bit
Yeah, I remember seeing stuff like that with a file.
I'm not sure if there is... no. Okay, no.
So it's with tempfile.name temporary file as something, and then it has a something.name.
It's actually a file handler already. You can do temp. Well, I mean, this should work,
I think.
Yeah, I just need to say that. Because I'm not sure.
They need to be, so this line needs to be indented to the same level as the previous one.
Are you sure? Because I'm opening the same file again.
No, otherwise temp file is not...
Yes, that's why I just created an additional variable.
Okay, you don't have to open it. We are running out of time. But you don't have to open it. You
you can use the so this named temporary file gives you a file
handle. So it is already open in the URL. Okay, but then we have
to open it again, you can, if you go to the so you can instead
of using the test output, you can use temp file directly. So
if you remove line 10 to 21 right sorry got a slightly different idea okay um the thing is i
want this to be closed again because i have the impression we are getting a problem that um
we have an open file and we are not closing it properly afterwards uh yeah that was my idea
have to take the name into a different variable yes that's what i just did oh okay
but we do get an issue okay
so this is on line 23 um that's an assert issue uh yeah so uh i wanted to show that this is not
as complicated as it seems. But comparing the files directly seems to be more complicated than...
Might even be.
And I think we need to move on to this.
Yeah. But conceptually, you would take the files and compare them in some way
to see that they are the same.
And look at the contents. We can also just check that the file is there.
I assume it would take us another 10 to 15 minutes
to get this right now.
And I don't think it's actually worth it at the moment.
And it's an image file,
which is generally one of the easier things to check
by looking at it.
So if it was any different kind of a file,
what you would do is open the file,
read the contents,
and then compare to a known example,
which is what we're trying to do here.
So hopefully we didn't get too bogged down and lose the general context.
So the overall idea is to test what the function does.
And in this case, it's writing to the file system.
So to test that, you read the file and you compare it to what you already know it should be.
And the main thing is here, we use known test data.
so we already know what should happen
because we know what this temperatures.csv contains
and then if you were to put this online
this code, publish it
you would publish the known test data as well
and then everybody can run the tests
so
now
we could probably find a clever way
of looking at the contents of the image a little bit
and uh compare the files directly um but it's probably not worth doing today so oh well not
i think the concept hopefully got clear um and this is mainly about the concept here yeah so
one other thing to mention is that we still have everything although both the functions define the
script and everything it works well enough one thing we could have done um especially if it was a
bigger package is to
take the script and put it in a
separate file and then have things
that are imported in a different file
that would also be nice
and it would be a module you can very easily
move around but okay
let's leave it at that
there is the
feedback for day
six available and we still
have a workshop outro
in the schedule so
[name] and [name]
welcome sorry for taking your time um with the debugging the test no worries this is good to show
like this is also showing like this is sometimes what you have to do this is sometimes what you
have to think about and i think it's nice to like watch you to figure it out because that may also
like stick better like next time maybe some of the participants are in the same situation and
then maybe they remember oh yeah there was this one thing that [name] did or this one thing that
[name] suggested maybe so oh CATS is also with us great stuff not working is the most useful part
of the lesson no but it's a good a good thing I think to have it also part of the lesson if
everything would work that's not really that's not real no I mean by most useful I mean actually
most useful to see how stuff goes wrong now that was feedback from other stuff before
oh it's part of the process so don't worry
okay so the feedback is here you can give feedback not just for today but down below on
every day the whole workshop um i guess we should also save what we show now for uh what's it
we could just send this video to people who have attended and they can see the
outdoor even if they're not here right now so we're going on the schedule to the concluding
remarks here yes and it's also linked from the notes because there will be a lot of links that
we are showing here as well now so that you can just go and click them as well and by the way
hello everyone in case we haven't met yet i'm [name] i work at csc and starting may i will
be the project manager for Code Refinery. I've been here day four and day one already and will
now together with [name] go through our concluding remarks. There was a few things we promised already
in the intro that we will tell you about. So let's see that we get to that. But as the very first
thing, thank you very much to everyone. Thank you to all your participants for all your amazing
questions i've been following along a little bit on the side and there have been really good
questions and i hope they have helped you also in the in the learning process we had some team
leaders and hosts this time with us so if you joined in a team also say thank you to your team
leader and to our hosts for doing that and we hope that maybe some of you who are now participating
as a participant and are interested in helping us with this to join us next time maybe as a team
leader maybe as a host to learn with others the same is for instructors thank you all that you
are here still and thanks to also all the instructors of the rest of the week so we had
many different instructors and hopefully that was also valuable to like all the participants that we
had many different voices, many different ways of teaching so
that it did not get boring. Then we had some people working in
the behind the scenes answering the questions in the
collaborative notes. We don't know necessarily who they all
are. We know that [name] answered a lot of them. But then
we also had some people from the participants or from the helpers
answering questions, I believe. And then we have our local partners where they are already covered
with the hosts that provided a classroom for week one to learn together. And yeah, you really make
these workshops possible and enjoyable. So thank you, everyone. [name] mentioned already the
feedback so we are really really happy to read all your feedback for today as well as for the
workshop as a whole if you joined the whole workshop and there was for example a lesson
that you found completely useless let us know like that's how we that's how we get to know
if there was a lesson that you really really enjoyed also let us know because that then we
will probably keep it if we get a lot of feedback in this way and you can do that in the collaborative
notes you can do that via email to support at codefront.org or you can also join our chat and
this last option is also a very good way to stay in contact with us if you like really enjoyed what
we are doing and want to stay in contact with the instructors stay in contact with other people that
are enjoying um talking and discussing about the topics that we have in this workshop then
our chat is a really good good way of doing that and everyone can join there is no no like
restrictions requirements or anything um then you have seen a lot of different lesson materials
written by many different people and sometimes last minute updates can make things a little bit
more confusing than they have to be um and sometimes also the way we write it is not
necessarily how someone who sees it for the first time can understand it so if you had any exercise
or any materials that you were like what what are they talking about this i have no idea what to do
now uh let us know um you have learned in the first week hopefully how to work with github
all our lessons are on github so you can add an issue you can even if you are if you have a lot
of time on your hands you can send a pull request to update any of our lessons and we'll be happy to
review it and discuss there with you and we are always like using all of these to develop the
workshop materials further so it's very much appreciated and then in the future i don't yet
know when but i would guess not not any earlier than half a year from now we will also send a
well post post post post post workshop survey um to everyone who visited this and other workshops
in the past. It's about how you can, how you could make use of what you learned in the workshop. So
right now there's probably some things that you really enjoyed learning, some things that you
want to apply right away, but in half a year maybe you have a better idea of, oh this was really
useful and I'm using this and that's exactly what we would like to know. And that helps us with like
further funding and in general reporting about the project so then we have if you can scroll a little
bit down thank you please keep studying and ask for support so um you may have noticed that we
have introduced you to a lot of different topics and also in week two we didn't have time to do
exercises as part of this workshop but we would really recommend you if you are if you got
interested in any of these topics to go ahead take another hour or so sit down and do the exercises
most of them have quite detailed solutions also attached to them or step-by-step
instructions on how to go about it but if you get stuck with anything we also have
what we call a bring your own code session this is also a session where you can bring your own
question so if you have any questions or anything that you would like to screen share with an
instructor and ask about like is this correct or is this the right way to go about it then these
bring your own code sessions are the best place to come there we will have at least one probably
more instructors available and to make it most useful for you and also for us to know how many
people are interested in this we have a like a very short registration survey for this it's also
linked from the workshop event page schedule just asking I think even just your name and if you want
to you can provide already some information about the things that you would like to discuss
just so that we could invite the correct instructors for that and so far it has been
really fun to go to these sessions and hear about like how you then actually apply what you have
learned in the workshops here so it's also interesting for us um yes [name] do you want
to say something about the videos and where they are available yeah so so far i've been able to get
the videos out the same day and probably will today they're on a youtube playlist and well
there you use them for whatever you'd like i guess the main reason we make them is for
the people in the course to review what we said and the examples while you're trying to follow
along but maybe they're useful to other people yeah and share them with your friends if you want
and the same with our lesson materials so they are available where you found them so far they
will stay available before the next workshop in autumn they might change slightly but only to the
better we hope yeah um we are also working on the notes so okay we are also working on um putting
them on xenodo and we might actually make that happen now during summer for this workshop's
lesson so there you will also then have a pdf version and a like a static thing on the things
you actually learned now in this workshop but yeah the lesson materials on our web pages will
live uh will continue to live on there and you can share them you can reuse them if you
want to teach some of your colleagues about the topics you learned here please reuse the
materials they are all under cc by license so you can do that and you can even cite the lessons if
you want to so there is a citation cff file in all of the lesson repositories
with all the information you need for for citing them nowadays and then if you go a bit further
down yes so i mentioned already you can please do the exercises if you're interested in the topics
and if you cannot come for example to the bring your own code session
there is also a lot of local support available for different places here we now have only from
our partner organizations for some of our partner organizations the information about trainings
about sessions where you can come to ask for more help like at alto the garage session at cse the
weekly user support session and the training calendars but likely your own organization also
has something like this or if not your own organization then maybe your your national
high performance computing center or something like this might have help available for for these
kind of questions so please make use of them and if you really don't have anyone you can always
like reach out to us by coming to the chat or sending us an email and we can try to help you
figure these things out.
Okay, if you go a bit further down.
If you want a certificate for this workshop, if you want to get credit,
ECTS credit for this workshop, then please go on the course web page. There is on the top
middle towards right a tab for certificates there is the instructions on what you need to do and
until until when uh yeah deadline is also here 16th of april um then you can get a certificate
but you need to need to do a little bit something for that and that's described there is that
basically the learning diaries of each day and output of the exercises is it including the week
two exercises or do none of us know because someone else has written that okay i guess
someone else is taking care of that i don't know but i assume it's doing the exercises from the
second week also yeah i would assume so as well yeah you can read about it in detail actually
now that i'm seeing it here um what you need to do there open it
yeah it's a lot of text so let's not read through that now
but yeah it's a it's a learning diary and then some exercises that you all need to do and alto
has
agreed to go through that
and
provide the certificates.
Our colleague [name]
that you also know
already from day
four, I believe.
Okay.
That was certificates.
Then, yes,
code refinery.
We are a project
and we need your support please tell everyone about it as if you liked the workshop and I
already mentioned you can like come and help us for the workshops you can also teach with us in
the future if you want to if you're interested in that the best way also there is to come to
our chat and let us know about your interest and then we can figure out how we can do that in the
future. We are now in May starting our fourth phase, so we will not cease to exist at least
the next three years. But yeah, everyone who is interested in joining us is very welcome to do
that. We have social media accounts on Mastodon, Blue Sky and LinkedIn. All three of them have
usually the same content linkedin sometimes a bit longer something but in general everything the
same we try to post about workshops and other things that we are doing because besides this
workshop we are also collaborating on other workshops like for example python for scientific
computing last year we did a nice course on tools and techniques for high performance computing so
there's a lot going on and yes the rest i already mentioned you can get involved there's also a
newsletter um that we send i think twice a year the biggest the big newsletter that's usually
about like the the big workshops coming up and other possibilities and now i remember that i
forgot to put here also we also have an ambassador program so if you are interested in what we're
doing and would like to kind of get the latest news more often than half a year then we have
the ambassador program which means like people who are interested in what we're doing who want
to re-share about our events and so on but who don't necessarily themselves have the time to
get more involved to become an instructor or to host a breakout room or to host a classroom or
to help us in any other way but this like sharing the information wider and also providing us
feedback is very very valuable to us and that's why we started this ambassador program and you
can find the link on how to join that also on this newsletter page is it though let's let's check
oh it's actually linking from there okay so it's under join
and i can let's put then the link also on the notes it's under join and for individuals
and there you can find further down code refinery ambassadors that you can find the information
about that if you can put that link on the notes that would be really great okay one of the others
who are still here well someone not sharing the screen right now yes exactly okay but now to the
yeah maybe most interesting point of this outro so if you got interested in
this research software development or then there's also an association nowadays called the nordic
research software engineers or short nordic rse and [name] do you want to say something about
who is in RSE? And what do we do there? Well, we often talk, what is the meaning of a research
software engineer? But basically, it's someone that does research, but cares about the software
more than most people, and perhaps wants to be evaluated based on the quality of the code they
write and not just the publications they get. And that's basically all of us here. So we've all
studied different types of science things and then we've liked being part of research but we wanted
something a bit more long term and i found good job supporting the software and data and computing
side of things and now we're here teaching you so yes and you don't have it you don't need like the
title of research software engineer it's still something fairly new also in the nordics
so there's a lot of people who are have titles like postdoc or research assistant or
i don't know what else but many other titles like exist for that and the research software
engineering community is open for everyone who is like interested in the topic who is excited
about it learning about it maybe wants to help make it a bit more of a thing also in the nordics
so we have a community once in a while we also arrange seminars and other events we are hanging
out in the same chat as code refinery so there is a really tight connection and with our own
channel called nordic rse we have our own linkedin mastodon and blue sky same as code refinery we
post on all of those whenever there is something happening and something happening is actually
quite soon we have our second in-person conference on may 20th and 21st in Gothenburg in Sweden and
the general submission deadline is unfortunately already over but we still accept posters and you
can still also join without your own contribution so just to listen on what's going on in the nordics
with regard to research software engineering meet some people discuss your situation here
where there are maybe open positions for research software engineers or research software
engineering interested people and so on and just meet the community and see what's going on
yeah
anything else that we would like to say
at this point
I would want to just
mention
there is now a solution for the plot data
testing
in the collaborative document
awesome, yay
so it's not an unsolvable problem
no, it was
just, yeah
small details
right
okay
but then I think
we are four minutes
before
official closing time
but I guess
that's just good
yeah
thank you very much
for
for joining
for listening
for being so active
thanks to instructors
well we did this already
but thank you very much
and see you again
yeah
thanks a lot
thanks
bye
bye bye
See you.
Bye.
you
Thank you.