Hello, hello.
Hello, everyone.
Welcome to Introduction to
Scientific Computing and HPC,
meaning High Performance Computing.
So let's see who's with me today.
Right now, I see [name] and [name].
Hello, [name].
Which camera am I looking for?
So [name] is the movie
director behind the TV show.
He's taking care of the
cameras and screen sharing and so on.
And [name] is here with
me for some chit-chatting.
We start at 12 o'clock.
Do you want to briefly
tell something about yourself,
[name] and [name]?
i can start um i'm
research software engineer with
auto scientific computing um been
here now for a bit more than four years
and yeah i'm working on a
lot of different things mainly
web service kind of things nowadays
So you're a web developer.
It's fine.
Don't worry.
Yeah, I know.
You're not blaming me.
Everything is either a web
service or it's AI.
Yeah.
I'm [name].
I'm also a research software
engineer in Aldo.
And if [name] has been here
for four years and I guess
I've been here for five, that
has to be roughly correct.
And well, yeah, we have a
good bunch of projects, but we
still find time to help everybody
who comes to Garage and ask questions.
And we get a lot
of interesting computing related
problems to solve.
Yes.
It's fun.
And you will hear later towards the end,
we actually clarify for those of you
who are not yet familiar
with the Garage and how to ask
for help and so on.
But I'm already sharing my screen.
So if you want to switch the,
how do you call that, the
screen view to what I'm sharing
right now, I've basically sent to
all of your reminder about two links.
One link is the stream that
you see right now.
And the second link... Ah, sorry.
So...
supposed to be the director
and not actually sharing the right screen.
It's fine.
Triton user status.
I was assuming that that's
actually what you wanted to show.
Not yet, at least.
But here I'm showing the other
link that I sent you.
So this is a very useful system.
If you never used it, it's called HedgeDoc.
And by clicking the pencil
that right now it's under our
faces, but you see it in your screen.
Sometimes the pencil is also
on the left hand side.
I never really figured out
why sometimes it goes on the
right or on the left.
But anyway, if you click the pencil.
There have been throwing
some so-called icebreakers.
So it's a really a text
editor, like a, you know, like a
VS code or, or VI.
Shortcuts.
So sorry about that.
If you were already planning to use them,
but, um, you can already,
for example, answer to these questions.
How familiar are you with the command line?
Have you used version control before?
What types of computers have
you used for work?
So don't worry.
I don't think we will
write any scientific article about this data.
It's more for us to understand
what type of audience we have today.
And maybe even more interesting is
hearing what type of
programming languages do you use
and what type of work do you do.
It's often, you know, one might think
that everything is Python, but
I would say no, there's
much more beyond Python.
And then of course, we are
very curious to hear about
the actual research that you do.
One good thing, I think
that today the majority of you
are from Aalto University.
And within Aalto, there's so
many fields and so many subfields
and so many different types
of computing and data science.
I don't personally like the
term data science, but I guess
this is what most of us do.
And so you can already write
what you do and so on so that we get an idea.
And when you don't need to edit anymore,
there's another button where
the pencil used to be.
and it looks like an eye so
that you can go to view mode.
And right now there's 50
people editing, which is okay.
But sometimes, for example, in
the Code Refinery workshop, which
will happen in a couple of
months, in the Code Refinery
workshop sometimes we have 150
or 200 people editing.
And so they're switching back to view mode.
This is good for our server
that it doesn't collapse.
All right, there's one minute to go.
Anything to mention, [name] or [name]?
Not from my side.
Are you excited?
No.
Normal excitement for the
general introduction, but I'm
quite happy that we have this because it's,
I think, something that's very useful
for everyone who is actually
just starting with these
kind of high-performance computing
systems and getting into it.
Yes, today the focus, as
the title itself says, this is
more of an introduction.
But of course, those of you
who are already familiar with HPC
and Slurm and things like
that, the good thing is that
the majority of us Triton
experts, RSC experts, they are
around this document that we
are, that I'm sharing right now.
So you can ask during
the course, during these three
hours, you can ask all
sorts of questions related to
Triton or to Slurm or to data.
And we can get an answer.
And this is what it's nice
of this live document that
it really becomes like a,
you know, documentation, written
documentation of what happened
during the workshop and all
the questions that you had.
So it's a great opportunity
to basically ask us anything.
But the clock is 12.00.
So we can officially start.
If you see the link that
I'm clicking right now, that's kind
of our main reference.
for the timeline of the day.
And so welcome everyone.
So as I already mentioned,
this is a somewhat introductory course,
and we start from the very basic
because we don't want to assume
that everyone already knows
the difference between a CPU and
a GPU, but we will not spend
too much time on the two basic stuff.
And then the goal is to actually show
how people use Triton, or
more in general, an
high-performance computing cluster.
Because what we show here is about Triton,
but it's basically the same
whether you go to the CSC
Lumi, or Mahti, or whether you
go to the Lumi supercomputer.
or any other cluster that
you will encounter in your life.
At least the majority of
them are using Slurm.
So if I then, what you
see in the schedule here is
that there's many links.
And so these are the
actual training materials.
So if you never need to go back to,
or if you're lost and you don't know
what the speaker is showing
in the screen, it's one of these links.
So we start with this basics
on the course, which I already started.
The majority of you are
from Aalto University and most
likely you are a doctoral
researcher or a postdoc.
So this is useful for you
if you never used Triton before
or maybe to refresh your memory
on how to use Triton if you
haven't used it for a while.
You understood kind of
this practicalities that this is
a live stream so we are not
in the same Zoom room.
there are advantages of this
way of doing it because we
don't need to worry that you
know somebody is unmuted or some
camera is on and it shouldn't be on
so that we can you
know immediately release the recording
of the workshop and the recording
will be as soon as we
stop the streaming the recordings
are there so it's quite amazing
And the second thing that
you've already experienced this way
to chat with the instructors
through the notes document.
So literally feel free to
ask anything there.
Then if the instructor wants
to share some links, they will
paste the links there and so on.
All the rest, you don't need to worry.
For those who have a
single screen, you might want
to arrange your workspace so that
you can have the Twitch TV
stream on the, for example,
left-hand side of your laptop screen.
And this is exactly why
we have this vertical streaming
so that, you know, it doesn't
take the full screen.
And then in the rest of
the screen, you might want to take some notes.
You want to ask some
questions through the notes document.
Here today is more like
a demo-based teaching.
So you don't really need
to type the comments, but if you want those,
you know, whoever wants to
try, you can open a terminal window.
Try to run some of the
commands that the instructors are
running and so on.
But basically, we can now go
back to our reference document
and to the notes.
Let's see if there's any
question already in the notes.
We can check a little bit of your answers.
So majority of you are
familiar with the shell, the
Linux terminal, and it's okay
if you're not familiar.
Git version control, even if
you're not an expert, I
recommend Code Refinery, but we
talk about that later.
All right, I don't see any questions,
so we can actually continue
with the next topic.
And here is where I'm gonna summon
[name], so a short
introduction to scientific computing.
I can open the dictionary.
Well, first I open this link.
I can open the dictionary and computing is,
you know, whatever it's the
definition of the dictionary.
There's maybe some of you
already seen this funny cartoon
from XKCD that, you know, is
this your machine learning system?
And it's basically a pile of algebra.
Something comes in and something goes out.
So what is in your experience
or opinion of scientific computing, [name]?
In my opinion, scientific
computing is essentially any type
of computing that aims at furthering science.
And most of the time
when people speak about it, it's
somewhat connected to high
performance large system computing,
but even smaller, just small programs
that are run on an
individual researcher's computer, they
are scientific computing.
So there's not really a restriction.
I wouldn't call everything
scientific computing, but anything
where you give instructions to
a computer by means of code, in my opinion.
Yeah.
It...
Of course, it's also
scientific computing if there is a
large UI or something that is
then running your stuff.
You are doing scientific computing,
but it gets more removed
in my feeling because you're
getting removed from what the
things actually do.
You're at that point merely using
a tool to do something,
which is perfectly fine, but it
blurs the lines kind of.
It's true.
And it's nice that you
mentioned tools because if we pick
one of the definitions I wrote one year,
scientific computing is a
collection of tools and techniques
and theories to solve on
a computer some mathematical models
or problems and so on.
This is why maybe data
science is more familiar
than scientific computing.
And often this type of
data science, whatever it means,
workflows are the same workflow
that people do when doing
research, when doing computational research.
And actually talking about
workflow, yeah, you see it might
not apply to everything,
Typical kind of study would have some data,
experimental data, simulated data,
or maybe something from
the literature, from open data
sets, something that is already existing.
There's some processing, some
numbers are made, some amazing
figures are created.
And then you have your posters
and papers, and then you repeat
until forever, until you become
an emeritus professor or whatever
you will become in your life.
But then I still believe
it's important to talk about
the kind of hardware side of things.
I don't know how much
you've experienced, [name], but maybe
we were chatting one day
that someone was trying to back
up some photos from some smartphone.
And it was extremely slow.
And sometimes this type
of technology, smartphones, but today
even modern laptops, even
operating systems like Windows,
that for example, is the most
used at Aalto University.
They hide behind the scenes
where the data is actually stored
and where the computing
sometimes actually happens.
So this is really computer science 101,
or I don't know where
they teach these things this day.
But familiarizing yourself in
what is the hardware behind the scene
so that in your laptop that
most likely you have right now
in front of you, there's a
CPU that does the math.
There's the RAM that is the
piece of paper where you
scribble the numbers that you need
to do the math.
And then you have a little
bit more storage in the disk.
some laptops well maybe today
even almost most laptops to
have some form of gpu yeah
yeah which is like the g in
pu is this graphical processing unit
because graphics like the screen
that you see right now it's
a matrix of whatever amount
of pixel times whatever amount of pixel
And then you can kind of
treat every pixel in parallel
so that, you know, you don't
need to wait many seconds that
the picture, you know, refreshes.
And of course, the good thing is
that instead of using this fast,
how can I call the processing units
for doing the graphics part,
you can also use them
for doing basically linear algebra.
And then, of course, there's the network,
and the network brings us
to all these mysterious cloud parts
that I think in my
Alto laptop, Windows laptop, I'm
still not super sure what is
local and what is in the whatever.
What is the name?
SharePoint?
Is it that OneDrive?
I don't know.
And I should know because I
should be one of those who knows, but
But even on a desktop machine,
I think it out of the most desktop machines,
your user profile is on
a essentially cloud, internal cloud,
but it's not on the machine itself.
It's being loaded from a network drive.
Yeah.
And this is exactly the issue
that I have with this
distributed computing and distributed
storage that sometimes, like the
case of the pictures in
the smartphone, you just want to
open a picture and see it.
You don't want to wait one minute
that the storage where, wherever
in the planet the picture is, you know.
Transfers the data.
Exactly.
So on top of the hardware,
we have all these things
that everyone uses every
day, operating systems, and then
we have the softwares.
I'm not going to talk about containers,
but anyway, hopefully what we
mean with the different components,
it should be clear.
And we are not just wasting
your time here because actually
in high performance computing, we
don't give you a computer.
You decide what you need.
And you like go to the store and say,
I need five CPUs, 16 gig
of RAM, and I don't know, whatever.
Two GPUs.
Exactly.
We don't give you the option
to select what network or hard drive you get.
That is fixed, luckily.
Maybe then we can go to this section
that is maybe the most
interesting one before we move
to the practical things.
these are kind of we're
trying to summarize here with
these questions kind of the
killing the misconceptions that
by just running your thing by
just moving your your software
from your laptop to the
high performance computing cluster
magically everything is faster
I would actually say it's the opposite.
Exactly.
So on average, I would
say that most desktop CPUs that
are around on a one to one basis are faster
than the high performance
computing CPUs because the
high performance computing CPUs
are intended for efficiency.
And for the fact that you
have many of them.
So you can make use of
multiple CPUs at the same time.
And that's the huge advantage
of the high performance computing
systems, not the individual processor speed.
So, yeah.
And this is something where
I think one huge misconception often is
that by just adding a couple
of CPUs to the script or
the program that I'm running,
it's getting faster.
And that's just in 90% of
cases is not true because
most programs still nowadays
are inherently single core.
So they run on one CPU
and they will use one CPU.
And if you give it 40
CPUs, it still will only use one CPU.
Yeah.
And only if you have something
that actually someone has made
the effort to distribute that
onto multiple CPU or
distribute individual things on
multiple CPUs, you get higher performance.
There are several libraries that
do this nowadays, underlying libraries
in your code.
And this is again something
where you really need to
understand what you are doing.
Because depending on what you do,
if you run something on multiple CPUs
and the underlying software
already does some kind of
distribution, you can end up
with slowing things down again a lot
because the different processes
that you've spawned now start
to compete over the CPUs
that you have allocated.
So when going to a
high-performance system or a large
number of CPUs, always think about
what can I actually do.
And I think the most simple approach
for a lot of situations is
that you have one thing that
needs to be done 20,000
times with different parameter sets.
And that's something that you
can really do efficiently on
a high-performance computing system
where you can just run it for all individual
parameter sets and get the
20,000 results essentially processed
in parallel.
And this is exactly what you
will see later today.
And you can experience yourself
with the code examples that we give you,
where then you can really
test, you know, was it faster
with two CPUs, eight CPUs?
You know, you will experience this.
And then even this, can I
just run stuff on top of GPUs?
Most likely, no.
Exactly.
Most likely, just...
Moving your code to a computing node
that has a GPU doesn't make
your code GPU runnable.
But let's not spoil all
the fun because these things we
will talk about later.
One thing that I wanted
to mention, this page, sorry
for the scrolling up and down,
we have this large amount of videos.
Well, not large, we have
a good playlist and also slides
on the kitchen metaphor.
There's a typo there, I just noticed.
So for those of you who
want to understand all the
different parts of CPU, GPU,
using the kitchen metaphor, there
are really great videos here.
So I highly recommend those.
But now to wrap up
this very one-on-one intro on the basics,
it's good to understand if
earlier I was talking about
the geography of what's inside your,
or kind of the physical part of your laptop.
Now let's scale it up to right now
what you see is the whole Alto network
and all the kind of
computing system that are available
for you in the Alto network.
So you might have a
department workstation or your
laptop maybe somewhere.
on the internet connected to
the Aalto network, most likely
through this VPN, which is like a door
where you can authenticate and
reach the machines of the Aalto network.
We have other ways of
accessing the Aalto network.
I like this VDI virtual desktop interface,
which is an easy way if
you don't have your own computer
to grab a file, look at
the content of something that you
have stored in your
workstation, for example, but these
are not very good for computing.
If you really need
more resources, basically there's
a sub network inside the
Aalto network, which is the Triton cluster.
And here, all these nodes, you
can think of many, many,
many laptops or desktop, you
know, they're not actually laptops.
In the Aalto day one, we
actually took one of these nodes
out and showed them in
the Alvaro Lompuisto here.
And they're basically connected
with each other with a super fast connection.
They also have access to
so-called scratch storage, also through
a very fast connection.
And here is where you request,
where you shop for whatever
amount of CPUs and GPUs that
you need and for how long you
need to run your computations.
One little thing that is very important,
you see the sign there, the
login node is how you access the cluster
but you shouldn't stay in the
login node to do computations.
And if you accidentally
do, you're actually, your
computation are going to be
penalized and slow down.
So login node is just a login.
But basically this is what
a cluster is about.
I'm pretty sure from now on,
I should leave the, I will
ask [name] to appear and magically [name] appears.
Hello.
Do you want to say
something about yourself before?
Hello.
My name is [name].
I'm a research software engineer
in the Aalto scientific computing team
and previously worked a lot
with the Triton cluster in
a different position.
So I guess you can take it from here.
Do you want to switch to your screen now?
Should we check first if
we have some questions in the
notes, by the way?
I don't see any questions but
one answer I can give that
probably I didn't hear mentioned is
that if the stream looks blocky
to you at any point do remember
to check in the gear icon
you can switch the stream quality
to the source quality so that
way it will look well the best
so you won't get this kind of buffering kind of
bandwidth saving from Twitch side
that makes text and other
things not as legible as they are.
All right, but I leave the floor to you.
I think who is going to share?
[name].
[name] is sharing.
Yep.
So yes, thank you [name]
and hello everyone.
So in this session, we'll
be looking at this kind of
like an example case that
will go through multiple different kinds of
problems or multiple different
types of interactions that you can
do with the cluster and we
try to demonstrate like what you
can do with the cluster and
how you can interact with the
user interface of the cluster
which is the queue like how
can you actually get your things
running in the queue
And you can run these
examples after the session yourself.
So you're not supposed to type along
while we are doing the
demos because there's lots of
stuff coming your way.
So it's better if you just
focus on what you're seeing
and what you're hearing.
But later on, you can
view this Ngrams example so that
we can check the...
check the example.
And what is this n-grams
example that we're going to be showing?
So this is a code created
by [name] from our team, my boss,
who made this example to
demonstrate how you can do
all sorts of calculations in the cluster.
And in this example, it
calculates these n-grams.
So basically,
bits of word or words and
how they relate to each other.
So n-gram can be like a
piece of a... It can be a
single word or it can be a letter.
So let's say we want
to calculate which words follow the other word.
We can then...
calculate these n-grams on word
basis to determine like... So
it's quite often used in kind
of like language analysis kind of a thing.
Nowadays, if you think about
large language models and
this tokenization that they do,
it's a similar kind of like a
thing as well, if you're familiar with that.
So basically...
like if you want to see
what is the frequency of letters
in a language or book or
something you would calculate like n grams
how different letters follow each
other and you can like create
like two grams which are like
let's say, is a letter A
followed by letter I, or you
can follow, create three grams,
which is like letter A followed by letter I,
followed by letter T. And you
can do all sorts of like analysis of this.
So in this example, we'll
be analyzing some free books
from the Project Gutenberg, which
is this repository of free books
that are in like, they have...
They're no longer under any license.
And we are going to be checking
what sort of like word
frequencies we see in these books.
But this is just a toy example,
but it demonstrates this kind
of like a problem where we have a lot of data.
A lot of data that can be split up.
So we can, let's say,
analyze 100 books with one computer
and 100 books with another
computer, and we can speed things up that way.
So that's what we are going to be doing.
And the first things we want
to do is that we want to get the data.
[name], you have probably
already downloaded the data.
I have already downloaded the
data, but it's also already on the cluster.
So if you want to do this
later on, you can just find it in this folder.
And I think it's also shown
in the example somewhere, the
part where you can also download it.
But let's say...
Well, as I said, I have downloaded it.
I think the most important bit
is for most people how to
get the data to Triton.
Yes.
So if you think that, okay,
you have a problem, you want to solve it,
you want to solve it in
Triton, so you need to get data into Triton.
so [name] what are you now viewing
what is this page so this
is the on-demand interface on
demand is essentially a access
point to the cluster or one
of the access points to the
cluster it offers a couple
of different possibilities or things
that you can do
like individual apps that can be
run on the cluster.
It offers shell access and
it also allows you to do
things like looking into your
files on the cluster.
In this case, we want to have this, yep.
didn't do something for too long.
So in the server, we
have this file browser, right?
File browser app.
And that essentially has, for
most people, it has two.
If you have some project folders,
it has a couple more direct links.
And the important ones are
your home and your work directory.
And for almost all things that
you want to do on the
cluster, you should use the work directory.
The home directory is
mostly for configuration things that
need to be available for multiple projects.
So in this case, I would
like to create a new folder.
Let's say this is kickstart.
And I'm going, nope, that was file.
I should do the right thing.
And then I can upload the file
that I had downloaded, which
is this Gutenberg fiction.
And I'll just upload this
file, which takes a little bit of time.
But depending on where you are,
this can be a lot faster.
I'm currently at home, so
the connection is not as fast
as if you would be on the Altacompass.
And then I have this file
in my work folder and in the kickstart folder.
Okay, nice.
So this is the kind of
like, like a simple copying thing that is
if you're uploading one file,
or you want to download
one file or something, this is
a very useful tool.
Of course, there's like more
advanced tools available.
And you can ask us about that later.
But but
But for this kind of like,
if you want to just get stuff there
and get stuff out of there,
this is a very useful thing to have.
I would personally say this
is something that you can use
for files up to maybe a
few hundred megabytes at most.
anything that's larger i would
transfer in a different way
either via secure via rsync or
some other um concept um if
you want to know more you can
we can tell it in garage but
this is just to get you
started on normal file normal
sized files let's phrase like that and and
Transferring data files and
transferring code files is usually
like we recommend different approaches.
Like with code files,
we definitely recommend using version control.
So let's transfer our code here.
So if you click the open
terminal button in this page, we
can get a terminal that opens
straight up in this folder, which is very nice.
Like we are straight up over here.
Maybe you can zoom in a
bit to make the font a
bit bigger in the terminal.
No, can't actually.
If you press Ctrl plus, I
think in the browser, I think it makes it.
Yeah, true.
Okay.
So yes, so we can see that
we are now in the kickstart folder.
We basically got a connection
to Triton straight from here.
In the main on-demand page,
there's also like a get
a terminal connection to Triton.
There's also like you can do
SSH, like the secure shell
connection that most or many users use.
But for getting like access...
Like simply, this is like a
really good way of doing that.
And for this sort of a
demo, it's like a invaluable asset.
So now that we are in
the folder, we would want to get our code here.
And like I mentioned
previously, we recommend for code transfer,
we recommend that you put your
code into a version control.
So in the code refinery course
that is coming in March, we're
going to be talking a lot
more about good coding practices
and stuff like that.
And there's going to be
like a workshop where you can
train this sort of things.
But we recommend that like if
you have a program that you're working on,
you put it in under version
control and use Git to transfer it around.
So the examples that we are
going to be running are in
our own repository that [name],
you can probably clone the
Yeah, I just show, so
this is essentially the repository
that I'm going to be cloning here.
And this has all the files
and things that we need for
this core, for this kickstart.
And to clone it, I'm essentially taking
I approach that git clone HTTPS
and github.com slash r2sicomp
slash hpcexamples.git.
And that will create a
hpcexamples folder, which
contains all the stuff that
we have also seen online.
And I can also look at this here.
So if I refresh this, it
now has the HPC examples folder in here.
And you notice that [name]
used few like this Linux
command line commands like LS to list files
and CED to change directory
to the directory, the HBC examples directory.
And the reason I'm doing that
minus L here is because if I
just LS, I get this kind of clumped view.
And with LS minus L, I
get a bit more information
about the individual files, which I
find a lot more convenient.
That's a matter of preference.
Yeah.
And like you saw with
the LSL, like sometimes you can, like
once you get accustomed to these tools,
you do some things with
automation, you just type it without thinking.
And that's how it often goes.
Like once you get accustomed
to these command line tools,
you start using them.
like regularly and they go
into your muscle memory to
use those to transfer files
and move to different directories
and edit files and that sort of stuff.
But of course, if you're just starting
and you don't have that
much experience with command line,
I just recommend like just using
it more and that it will come over time.
But there's courses we have
also like course on command line,
But in this session, we don't
have time to go through all
of the different things in the command line.
But there's causes on this.
And over time, you get
accustomed to these things.
And why we often use
command line is because the cluster...
And when we want to speak
to the computer, these commands
are more direct commands.
We don't have to tell the
computer to click this folder open
and go to this folder and click this button.
We can just say to it what
we want it to do.
And that's why we use the
command line so much.
It can be a daunting thing
at the start, but after constant
use, it's like a language.
You start learning the language,
and then you can start
using it more effectively.
And what I want to stress again here,
so on all of these shells
that you will see, you will
have a user at location information.
And this is my user ID,
and I'm currently on login four,
so on the login node.
And that's important because
we don't really want to run
anything on the login node.
And we actually want to
test whether some code is even working.
We don't want to do this on the login node.
We want to do this on
one of the compute nodes.
So [name], what would be a
good example of how can we test this out?
How can we test this out on a compute node?
Like if we want to test
out the examples that we have over there?
um there are a couple
of different possibilities um i think
for kind of the most
flexible uh thing because uh
you can essentially get a um
yeah instance of a kind
of desktop virtual desktop um on
triton is the triton desktop app so if
you are on-demand and start
the Triton desktop app, you
can essentially ask for some
resources on the cluster.
We, for intellectual session, we commonly,
if it's not anything huge,
we commonly recommend this eight
gigabytes of memory.
You can use one or two cores.
That doesn't really make a huge difference.
There are a couple of more options
and you can also request
GPUs for an interactive session.
But if you don't know that you need them,
I would ask you not to
do it because they are relatively limited.
And it's also that if
everything is currently blocked
or everything is in use, your
job will have to wait.
So if you ask for a GPU
and there is no GPU available,
then your job will wait for
it to actually be launched.
That's something that's, I
think, very unintuitive to a lot
of HPC users that the cluster
itself is not something that you
can grab, but you can ask it
to, okay, I would like to get something.
I would like to get a
reservation like in a restaurant.
And at some point the
cluster will tell you, okay, now
that table is free.
Please go there.
And yeah, if I'm now
launching this, it's queued.
It will hopefully not take
too long to start.
Yeah, so like [name] said,
it's a shared system.
So like, it's also like...
of like um like you don't
want to waste other people's time
and if it's a said system
and you use your time ineffectively
it's not to discourage using
the system like the best use
is to use the system it's
very important to use it but but but
If you know what you're
doing, then it's better for everybody.
If you try to use
the resources responsibly and what you need
for your job, then it's,
of course, best for everybody.
For example, the GPU requirements.
This now tells me that it
is on one node, has two cores assigned to it.
It doesn't tell me anything
about the memory, but this
is essentially a very simple
interface for this.
You have some applications.
You can again go to a terminal.
You could even launch a browser,
but commonly what you want to do
and what we want to do here,
we want to go to our
working directory that we had earlier.
And in here, we have the kickstart folder.
And in here, we have this HPC example.
Can you make the font a bit bigger again?
I wonder.
Nope, wait.
I think it might be
under the tree hamburger menu.
Yeah.
And now I need to make
the terminal a bit smaller
because otherwise I don't have
any room for anything here.
So actually I can make it
a bit wider as well.
So you notice that [name]
wrote this CD, this dollar work directory.
So this will always direct
you to your working directory,
like the work directory meant for your user.
So it's a good thing to use
to go always to your
own personal work directory, which
is this path.
So I'm also now using
another command, which is echo.
Echo essentially just writes
out whatever you give it.
And this dollar means it's
an environment variable.
So it will print what's
in this environment variable work tier.
And that is this scratch work 41.
And essentially, whenever I'm
calling a command and I
write $workdir, it replaces this
by this string.
So doing cd $workdir is the
same as doing cd slash scratch
slash work slash 41.
Okay, but we are here in the HPC examples,
and I think we wanted to
run the engrams, or at least
check whether this stuff is even working.
So, there's one huge problem
with the Detroit desktop.
The copy-paste functionality is
not very good.
You can use the left bar
to do the copy-pasting, but
it's quite cumbersome.
You can do something like this.
And then paste it here.
But yeah, it is somewhat inconvenient.
But okay, so our ngrams help works.
And this is actually something
that we also see very, very
often on a lot of programs.
A lot of these programs,
they have some kind of
helper function, often with a dash
dash help or just help or minus H or whatever.
similar commands, or if you
just run them without any
inputs, because most of those
commands do want some inputs.
And if you run them
without anything, they don't know what to do.
So they will just print out the help.
Do note that there can
also be programs that don't
have the help functionality and
they will immediately start
doing something expecting that
that's just help to be like some input.
But those are minority that
don't follow the standards kind of.
Yep.
So essentially, this tells me how
I can use this.
So if I count, I can
indicate an output file, I need
to specify an input parameter and
I can specify some more start things.
There's information on what each
of these things does.
So start selecting a starting
file and so on.
um more details on that can
also uh is also being talked
about in the code refinery
course on scripting and um for us
what we we have our file so yeah
if you remember we had our
file in the kickstart folder and
we are now in the hpc
examples folder so location wise this
is in a folder below and there the good um
Actually, I'm not going to do that,
but I just want to have the auto-completion.
So this is the location of this file.
So if you want to run
this function, this ngrams count.py
now on the good perk, this is
how we can do that.
And I'll quickly mention that
in most programs that you're
going to be running in the
cluster, they most likely... Of
course, there's some graphical programs
that you might want to run
in this desktop environment,
but many scientific codes, they
are written to be used
with this command line interface.
So you have this, you can
use them straight up from
like just telling, tell them what to do.
And they have like certain arguments
that you can give them and
they have this command line
interface that you use.
And most often there's
like reserved characters like
dash dash something or dash
something that can be like an
shorthand for an argument or
you have like positional arguments
like over here we had the
Gutenberg the input file the
Gutenberg fiction was a
positional argument and in these
cases like we use this
this command line interface to
call up the program and run the program.
So many programs work like this.
So usually it depends very
heavily on the program.
What are the input arguments?
What are the outputs and how
do you call up the program?
How do you use it?
And different programs have it,
but there's this certain standard that like
dashes usually mean that it's
like a special argument that
change the mode or something and
that sort of stuff and usually
the input files are like given
in an order or something
but it depends completely from
program to program
It's also important to mention
that in this case, we can
supply the zip file directly
because the program assumes that it
gets a zip file and opens the
zip file and then goes through the zip file.
A lot of programs need
their individual input files that
are not zipped.
And this is, again, something
where it depends a lot
on the program, what's the
actual input in there.
And now we can check the output a bit.
Like what does it actually do
when we just call it like this?
Well, it was counting
the individual elements of
these different books that are in there.
So how often is which
letter, essentially which letter
or which n-gram in this case present.
So spaces are there 8 million
times, ease 5 millions and so on.
And it interestingly also gives
us a output on
How long it took.
What of this is the kind
of user time and system time.
That's kind of allocation of
which parts were done by whom.
And also what's the maximum
memory amount that was being used.
So in this case, it was
just using 49 megabytes of memory
for the whole thing.
Yeah, and now that we have checked that,
okay, this program works, we have gone to,
like, if you look at
the terminal again here in
the Triton desktop session that
[name] has opened, you notice
that in the command line, the
host name, we can see that we
are running now on a different place.
We are not running on the login nodes,
which is good because we don't
want to run on the login node.
And now we are running somewhere else.
But again, like,
In the case of this
program, which accepts stuff from
the command line, we don't
need the graphical interface, right?
Like we don't need it.
Like it's just like something
extra that we can use.
But in this case, we don't really need it.
So we might as well just
use the queue directly and
submit this program directly from
the login node, right?
Yeah, so we can, for example, in here,
we are in the HPC example,
we can run this directly from the command line.
We can, for example, say,
use a command that's called srun.
srun is a submission script
that also adds a job to
the queue with the arguments that
you then give it.
And in our case, we...
probably just need to specify
we actually don't need to
specify anything because the
default values are sufficient let's let's
but like few of the examples
that we had in this yeah
but you can specify let's say
um how much you want it you
want in here so minus c
is minus zero minus minus
Minus minus CPUs per task
is essentially how many CPUs you
want for this job.
Minus minus mem is how much
memory you want for the job.
Let's specify a few others.
Let's also specify the time that
we want it to run.
So we can give it time
and let's say like, yeah,
five minutes or something.
So with this time, we can
specify like how much time we need.
And we can also, when
we're running this interactive mode,
like now we are asking the
queue to run this program
in some computer somewhere, but
we want the queue to handle it.
Let's add also this...
that's just pty there so that like
what this pty does is that
it creates this pseudo terminal whatever
so so what it actually means is
that if the program
does something interactive that it
needs like arguments from you
or something when while it's
running it will like forward
them backs back and so
it's basically like works as
an interactive program
So if we would be running some program
that would have like a
question or something, it would work.
So let's add that as well.
So when you're running, let's say,
a program interactively like this
from the login node, you're
submitting it into queue.
The queue will run it somewhere else,
but it will still look like
it runs here, basically.
what we see over here
that the srun responds that hey
it sets these partitions it will
submit it to multiple different
places like because look where it
gets a gets room first yes and
then it it sets it up into the queue
and it waits for resources and
this is very helpful like if
you have a command line you know
that you have a command line
interface for your program you
can just like basically ask add
srun and add whatever kind
of resource parameters you want
and then run it and test
it out on a compute node.
So now we see that it
has been allocated the resources
and now it's running the same thing again.
So basically... And since this
command has now exited, so
this Python call has exited, we
are back on the login node.
So actually in this case,
PTY didn't really have a huge impact.
No, but in a case where
you would run an interactive
program, you want that to be there.
The one where I know where
this is most likely to be
used is something like this,
where you just want a new
shell on some machine and
now start calling commands.
So that's kind of a very short-term...
approach to, yeah, I want to
shell on a node.
That could essentially be the
same as starting the Triton desktop session.
If you already know the commands
and you don't need to
do anything else, this is essentially the same.
Yeah.
So now that we got
the program running there, [name]
had this dash O for the
Python program so that it
produced output somewhere.
So we can use this command
less to check out the
check out the output so less
is this pager so less is
less than more there's this
other tool called more which is
also a pager and these are like so
so you can view files from
a command line and this is
very helpful because in most
cases like you will want to
view the output of the program
Especially if it's running, like
we'll be later talking
about submission scripts.
If it's running somewhere
in the background, you would want
to view the output without
having to download the files
and stuff like that.
I give one short thing that
I find quite useful in Less
has a search function.
By typing slash and whatever
you want to search for...
you can search for the relevant element.
So you can search for zeros.
And if you would put slash
again, you go to the next.
It's just something that
is very convenient.
And if you want to get out of less again,
because at the moment I'm a
bit stuck, it's just Q. You
just type Q. Then you quit less.
Yeah.
Many of these programs, they
have specific magical things you
need to remember to get out of them.
But, okay, so we now manage
to run the program in
the queue, like, interactively.
But this is not the reason
why we're using these compute clusters.
The compute clusters are basically usually,
like, what I usually think of them is that,
like, think of whatever your program
that you want it to do,
then you write the instructions
for the computer to do what you
want it to do, and then
you just let the computer do
it, and then you come back, and then you
like look at the results.
So basically you tell the computer
what you want it to do, you
let it do it, and then once
it's done, you look at the results.
And for this to be able
to be like possible, what we
usually want to do is we want
to like write a script
that instructs the program, like
instruct you and instruct the,
like basically the whole workflow
of what we are going to be doing.
And for the cluster, we
will be using something
called submission scripts.
So [name], if you create a
new one with nano, nano is
this like small editor that you
can run on the command line.
You can, of course, edit
this in various other ways, but
nano is a great way to do
like small edits like this.
And let's write a small submission script.
So all of these submission
scripts, they start with this hashtag
this, this line called shebang.
So, so it's, it's basically
like what program will run this script.
And in vast majority of
cases, it's the spin bash, which is the,
like run this on the
command line, basically like, like
it will tell, uh, that command
line should be used to run this.
And after that, we will have, uh,
we will have various parameters that,
like slurm parameters, similar to
what we have with the srun
command, but now we- Exactly
the same, except for the PTY.
But now we are giving them with the,
with this sbatch comment so
that the queue manager will read
all of those comments and
then it will determine what
are the resources needed by
this script and then it
will get those resources.
By the way, can you add
equal sign after mem and time?
I think they need it.
Yeah, true.
And also there was a
comment previously that our faces
might be hiding some of the top bars.
So maybe move it a bit downwards.
Okay, yeah, it looks pretty nice.
Yeah, now it looks pretty okay.
But yeah, basically we write
over here what we want the
computer to do for us.
So we write the instructions
for the computer.
So basically the command line
commands that we want it to run.
So in this case, we will run, tell it,
okay, the first line is
the shebang, which is like,
okay, use this command to run this.
And then...
Then we tell it that, hey,
we want one processor.
We want 200 megabytes of memory.
We want five minutes of time.
And then we have the Python command.
Can you also add an argument
called dash n so that we
calculate the two grams?
So instead of one grams,
let's calculate two grams.
so which which will um which
will make sort of like we
get letter pairs it can be wherever
but yeah i tend to like it
when i have this stuff
in a relatively reasonable order
But basically, this is how
you often write these submission scripts.
We write instructions for the
computer on what we want to do.
And basically, the reason why we
do it this way is that once we give the queue,
like, hey, this submission script,
we give it instructions that, hey,
I want you to do this.
it will handle it and we
can just do something else.
It's basically like we can
just fire it away and it will
be finished at a certain point,
but we can start doing something
else in the meantime.
And of course, we will later look at
how we can run multiple of
these and a lot of these,
but basically we can run...
Well, a lot of commands this way.
So I'm now quitting this
by pressing Control X and I
want to save the buffers with yes.
And then it asks me which
file to write to, which is
this submit to this age.
And if I want to submit
that, then I use this S
batch command, which is a batch submission.
So this is telling it, okay,
take the script, look through
the initial comments if there
are any sbatch things and
take those as arguments and
then run this script.
And that is being submitted.
Yeah, now we see that we
have the batch job submitted.
We can now monitor, like we
continue in the terminal where we left off,
like we still have the
same terminal open, but we
can now monitor what's happening there.
And we can do it in two different ways.
The one way is to use
the slurm command that we have, that
if we run slurm queue, we
can see that it's currently running over there.
And we also have the
interactive desktop running.
Which I could turn off now
because that is just blocking
resources at the moment.
Yeah, that's true.
And this is a good example
of why the interactive usage is
not the most effective one.
It looks like constantly using resource,
even when it's like... Yeah,
it was essentially 15 minutes
blocking the CPU, which, yeah.
Now it's over.
But then other way we can use it is
that there's this monitoring
tool called that, well, slow
monitoring tool or what was the name?
It was like that.
It's available from the
main on-demand page.
where you can you can then
view your jobs uh and view your programs
so if you want to if you
go here the slow monitor is
here yes essentially shows you
what has been going on and this is the
This is our last job that we were running.
That's actually quite efficient
because it did the CPU stuff well.
This is probably, that was
the short one that just
started Bash, which didn't have
any CPU usage in the end.
It was just exiting again,
which was quite inefficient.
There is something funny going
on with the memory usage
there, but that's something we
can check later on.
I think that memory usage is actually fine.
That thing takes about 50 megabytes or so.
That's roughly 30% of the
200 megabytes that we are...
The number is not... That's wrong.
That's kilobytes.
Yeah.
You need to fix that.
And then we see this...
desktop session that was, yeah,
using the CPU for a bit, but
in the end, quite inefficiently.
But yes, you can use these
tools to monitor that, hey, what's happening.
And like the basic thing or the main focus,
I would say, the main thing
to gather from all of this is that
it's not usually hard to
write your stuff into an SBAT
script if you know what you want to do.
And so basically, if you figure out,
okay, these are the commands
I'm going to be running, and
if you run them from the command line
or something, you just basically
put them in a script, and
you put some resource requirements there,
and then you just fire it away,
and then you look at the
monitor and, okay, what my
worker ants are doing on
the background, like you just...
see what the workers are
doing and refresh that page occasionally.
And once they're finished, you
go and check what is the output.
And what is the output?
It's usually like all of these scripts,
whatever they print out, they
print out into these files.
So you can later on see what...
they run and of course
the program itself can have some
its own output as well but
it depends on the program but
usually it's kind of like you put it there
and then you can monitor
this output file and then the
queue monitor to check is it
running and what's happening and
And if you don't specify anything else,
which you can in theory, it
will name it slurm job ID and then .out.
And also if there's error
output, it would be slurm job ID .err.error.
And this is essentially the
same that we had earlier.
So these are just the outputs.
That's the initial, yeah, it
found a hundred files.
It found three and a half thousand
or three, a bit over 3,002
grams and ran the stuff here.
That's the summary that was
printed in the end.
And, and for the monitoring,
like, like this program itself
had this kind of like resource monitoring,
but also like the resource
monitoring now in the, in this,
like the job monitor that
[name] showed here, like you can see the,
the resource users over there.
But then there's a command
called sf that you can use
also to monitor these resources.
So if you run sf and you
give it the job ID, so all
of these jobs get their unique
ID that you can then figure
out stuff later on about.
So you can get this
efficiency information this way as well.
There are a few caveats that
I would add to all of
these monitoring tools, especially for memory.
Memory is checked every couple of seconds.
That means that if there is a very short,
large spike, this might not
be covered by the memory utilization.
and that can cause some problems.
It's also possible that
two different systems show
you slightly different values because
how the values are
determined sometimes depends a little
bit on the program itself and
what kind of logging data it was using.
And admittedly for GPUs, we
are still sometimes having a
bit of trouble because the
monitoring tools are not that great.
We are working on it
and hopefully this will be
solved sometime soon, but it's not yet 100%.
The estimation is quite good,
but there are sometimes problems with these.
And I think, like, with this, like,
there's a lot of stuff
coming your way currently.
And there's a good discussion
going on in the notes.
And we'll check some of those notes.
We're going to have a bit of a break.
So you have time to, like, readjust, right?
So... I would say five minutes.
Because we are a bit behind time.
Yeah.
Well...
I would say, okay, let's
say five minute break at this point
and then we have another
break later after the second
part of the session.
So yeah, let's have a five minute break
so you can have a bit of a walk
and get some water and get
some coffee and let's see you
back in five past one or
whatever time zone you're in.
Bye.
And welcome back where we left off.
Hello.
Yeah, it was quite a short break,
but hopefully you got
something refreshing in front of
you or just managed to stand up
for a second or something.
But yeah, during the break,
we checked some of the notes.
There were lots of
good discussion happening there.
So one thing that we thought
that it would be good to clarify is that
like when you're requesting
these resources, like how do
you determine like what are
the resource limits?
And basically like what it's
easiest to think about is
that there's this kind of like
a ceiling set by the memory.
So how much memory can you use?
And then there's like a ceiling set by the
or another wall set by the
time limit or how long can
you use those resources.
And then you can ask for number of CPUs
and the number of
graphical processing units, number of
GPUs you want to use.
And usually what you want to do is
that if your program can
utilize number of CPUs or number
of GPUs, you should usually
tell your program what...
to use them.
And if it can use them,
you should first figure out, can it use them?
And then if it can, you can
give it to them and then tell
the program to use them.
But we'll talk about this more
in the next session about
looking at things from
the program's perspective.
But the main thing is that if your code
or if your job runs out of
time or runs out of memory, so
if it uses more memory than it
has been allocated, it's going
to be killed by this out
of memory, like controller, and
same with the time.
So if it runs out of time,
it's going to be killed by
the out of time thing.
So what you usually want to do is
that you run your job, you
put some bigger memory requirements,
you put some bit of a
longer time period requirements, and
then you see how long it
actually took and how much
memory it actually used, and then you
put those ceilings closer
to the requirements that you want to do.
There's a whole article on how
big is your job that you can
can check afterwards if you
want more information how to
specify these resource limits yeah
it's also just as a comment
it makes sense to try something
a bit smaller and give it a bit of memory
and then see okay how much
did it actually use and then
try to estimate the large the larger job so
to get a bit of an idea
how much you need to
don't overshoot completely because
if you request um a
couple of hundred gigabytes memory
and then use two that's uh
maybe not the optimal and yeah
yeah okay but let's go on
so we have this engrams now
Yeah, and this was the kind
of like a program that we could run on.
We could run with like bigger
data sets as well.
Like we could run it with
a million books or something.
But if we ran it with a million books,
we would run probably in
the situation where it takes a
long time to run the whole thing.
But what we can do, like,
in these sort of situations where it's easy to,
like, split the thing up,
like, in this case, we
could, like, calculate the n-grams
for a piece of the puzzle and then
for, let's say, 1,000 books at
a time or something.
And then we can check what
is the combined result afterwards.
So we can do this kind of map reduce,
it's often called, where we
do something for a piece of
the data at a time.
When there's this sort of
a problem, it's often
called embarrassingly parallel or
like trivially parallel.
We just do the same thing, but
for a lot of different data points, basically.
Like if you have something
that requires you to do the same analysis
for different data sets or
something, it's this sort of a problem.
And for these sort of problems,
there is a very nifty tool
in the queue system itself called
an array job that allows you to run
run the same thing basically over
and over again, but just
using different number each time.
So what the array jobs does is that,
like [name] has written over there,
if you add this dash dash
array argument to the requirements
that you give to the submission script,
What it does is that for each,
when you submit this job,
it will actually submit multiple
jobs that do the exact same thing.
But the only thing that they
do is like differently from each other is
that they set this
environment variable that you can
then use in your code
to determine like, okay, who's
doing what kind of a situation.
So in this n-grams example, if
you want to show [name] from
the start, what is what.
Yeah.
So in this n-grams example,
what we are going to be doing
is we are going to be setting this step feature.
So basically we are taking every 10th book.
So we're saying we have a
hundred books and we're saying that, hey,
take every 10th book from this dataset.
And then we have the
start function that says that,
hey, start from this book.
So if we have now an
array job of 10 numbers, so
we have numbers from zero to nine.
So the first job that it
will be running, it gets this array index.
So it will get this task ID.
that, hey, I'm the first, I
have the number zero, what am
I supposed to be doing with that?
And now we say that, hey,
you take the first book and
take every tenth book of the
data set and do data analysis.
Then the next array task
will start with the first book and so forth.
We basically create this group of jobs now,
like 10 jobs that are
each individual of each other.
They all do their own part of the
calculation, and the rest
of the requirements like CPUs,
memory time, they are identical
across the jobs.
So you don't have to
do any multiplications or
additions or whatever.
So it's like, how long does
it take to run one of these?
one of these like runs, and
then we just do 10 of these.
So basically, so like [name] wrote there,
the array sets this slurm array task ID
for each job, and then you
can do whatever you want with that.
And there's multiple examples
in our documentation on you can
use it to choose configuration parameters.
You can choose it to choose data sets.
Like in this case, we
choose the starting point of
each like analysis code.
So you can do different things with that.
But the main point is that
there is this sort of a feature.
And let's submit it and
let's see what happens if you
check the queue now.
So now we see that after
a job, there's this underscore
and then there's this brackets kind of a thing.
And that means that it's an array job.
And then if we look at
the queue again, okay, it already finished.
They all finished.
Yeah, they all finished.
But if we look at the
history, can we see it from the history?
So, yeah, we can probably also
see it from the history here.
Yeah, we see that.
There are now a lot of
jobs that have been finished.
Essentially, it's all the same job.
And you see the array ID here.
And they all have finished.
And this is much more
effective from the queue point of view than,
let's say, doing a for
loop and submitting multiple jobs individually.
Because in this case, the
queue itself knows that these are
going to be identical.
I will just have to do it
multiple times in a row,
and it's much easier for the queue system.
So if you're going to
be doing something like, let's
say, running the same analysis
like 100 times or something, you
can do it with these array jobs.
This is the jobs that come
up with Slurm history.
Slurm history is another command
that we can use.
And we see all these submit
array jobs with their array job ID,
which note they were on how
much memory was allocated and so on.
So there's additional information on those.
And there's also sometimes
information on individual steps
within this process.
which most often is not
that relevant, but it's present.
That's all the stuff that I've
done in the recent past.
And this is like a
really, really powerful tool.
So there's also like in
the n-grams example, there's this combining
script that we can run.
We can check that the
result is actually the same as
if we would run the same thing,
like if we would run it without the array job.
So I think the Python is wrongly written.
So basically what we can check
is that if we would run this with
with one computer, like do we
get the same result if we
run it, like separate it with
10 computers and then we
combine the stuff together?
And this is quite often what,
if you have a lot of data
you might want to do, like if
you split it into multiple sub things
and then you run these
individually and then you combine
the results together to check what happens.
Again, we don't want to do
this actually on the login
node because it's something that
I don't know how much resources it takes.
If I know that this is
taking a very small amount, I
might run this on the login node.
But if I don't know how much it takes,
I will definitely run this on
the queue and not have it on the login node.
Because there's one more
thing, every single user has
a limited amount of resources that
they can use on the login node.
And if one program that
I'm running there is taking all
of the memory and all of the,
and all of the, okay.
need to check what's going
on there, but let me just finish.
If I'm running something on
the login node and that takes all the CPU
and memory resources, I might
actually not be able to log
in anymore because also even
this shell, even this login
shell needs some resources.
And if everything that I can
use is taken up, then yep, I'm stuck.
And that's something that
I would personally like to not happen to me.
So what's going on now?
It's the compile script.
Combined counts.
Oh, yeah.
Did I?
Yeah.
Okay.
We know that this is taking.
Yeah.
That this is very small, so...
We have ngrams2 and the ngrams... This one.
It's actually the ngrams that's
out and the other command.
Yeah.
So that was the one from before.
If you run a command called
head, you can show a few of the first lines.
Like, let's see if they match.
Yeah.
That comes from typos.
Yeah, so we can see that
the results are basically the same.
So in this sort of case
where we can split the job
into multiple sub jobs, it can
be useful to do this this way.
This was kind of like
this embarrassingly parallel kind of like
we utilize multiple computers, right?
Like in this case, we told
the queue system that, hey, I
want to have like access to, I
want to run the same job 10
times and the queue system can
decide where it wants to run the job.
So it can run them
on separate computers altogether because
all of them are independent kind
of like tasks that do
their own processing independently.
But in some cases, we want
to use more computers
CPUs from the same computer
or even from multiple computers.
And there we come into
this multi-processing kind of like situation.
And nowadays, like a lot
of programs utilize this kind
of like within computer multi-processing.
So basically there's multiple CPUs
in one computer and we try to utilize those
And that's like, or
shared memory multiprocessing,
this alternative name that it's called.
And this program, these n-grams
that we have, it supports
this kind of approach.
So what we can do is that
we can give the slurm
argument that we want to
use multiple CPUs per task
to request multiple CPUs.
And we will now do n-grams
for words and not for individual digits.
The reason for that is this
is a bit more computationally
expensive because it needs to
calculate more things.
It needs to see more
different things, check out
more different things.
So let's try first running it with one CPU.
So over here.
Yep.
And then we can try with multiple CPUs.
I didn't miss anything.
I think I'm fine.
Yes, so currently we are
not requesting multiple CPUs, so
we will get only one CPU and
it will use that one.
But what we can also do
is that we can request multiple CPUs,
but then we also need to
tell the program to utilize
those multiple CPUs.
There's also like many programs nowadays,
they might just decide to
try to use multiple CPUs
even because they don't know
that they only have access to one CPU.
And we'll talk about this
in the next session a bit more.
But yeah, like in this case, we ask
for one and we use only
one, but let's try using multiple.
So if we ask, modify
the requirements and put there
like CPS per task.
And then put, let's say four.
Yeah.
And then in the Python for
the count.py, we give it this threads.
argument equals four as well yeah
and this is actually something
that's very important because a
lot of programs will not use multiple cpus
if they are not told that they are
that they should and even if
they do use multiple cpus
check whether they actually have
indicators on how many cpus they can use
Because the program might try to
look up on the computer how
many CPUs are there to specify
how many threads it will spawn,
so how many processes it will spawn.
And if you don't tell it
how many CPUs you have, it
might end up trying to allocate as many
as there are CPUs on the
machine, but it only can
access whatever you have requested.
which can cause a lot of problems.
So this is something that if
you want to do multiprocessing, always check
if there is something like this threats
or num workers or similar
things available in the tool
that you're using.
Okay, let's see what we get.
Yeah, multiple, there's like
multiple names, like you can
have like number of workers, threads, CPUs,
like there's a lot of
different naming conventions and
there's technical, like...
technical differences with all
of these usually but but like
people also use them like in wrong context
as well uh so so in yeah
you don't need the equal sign
for the threads for python threads
uh you need to give it
without the equals the python argument
The argument for countPy.
Are you sure?
Yes.
But yeah, that sort of stuff can happen.
Nope.
Oh, it's the countMulti.
Yeah, sorry.
It's the countMulti.py.
Yeah, this is, like, this is, again,
like, there's usually, like, if
it is a multiprocessing
implementation, either your program
is written using multiprocessing or not.
Oh, it probably will fail
again now because I now have
the equal sign in again.
Might be, but it might see.
Yeah, let's see.
Nope.
Oh, no, now it works.
Yeah.
A lot of tools actually
are fine with equals or not equals
and just will pass an equal
sign as, yeah, this is the same as a space.
Okay, so this was, well, okay.
Now we have a wall time,
so a total time that it
worked of 15 seconds instead of
the 20 seconds that we had before.
The user time, so the
time that it actually, the compute
time that it took actually went up.
because it now needed
to communicate between the different threats.
So the overall runtime was
lower, but yeah, the efficient
runtime was worse.
And this is also something that is very,
very, very, very common
for multiprocessing situations, that the
The absolute limit would be
it's two times, well, in this
case, it's four times faster.
It's likely at most something
like two times faster, and
that's already quite good.
Yeah, and this can happen with
many sort of like, if we
try to speed up things, like
there are like unseen things
happening in the background that
might like sometimes adding
more processes doesn't make stuff easier.
that much faster because
there's additional startup time needed
to set up the communication and
all sorts of things.
And especially if you're running
GPU jobs or something like
that, there's additional overhead
usually from the CPU side of things.
So it might not make your
code faster to run it with
multiple GPUs, even if it supports it.
There's lots of things that can...
affect the like how good is
the speed up but basically like
in in the best case scenario
world it would be like if you
had if you had one cpu
and now you're running with two
cpus it would be twice as fast right
but but in reality it's
never that never that so like
you always need the good idea
is to usually like
measure and come and discuss
with us what is the sweet
spot, where do you want to run it.
And usually array jobs are
more effective at parallelizing
than using complete multiprocessing.
Yeah, but this is essentially
the things that you can quickly
do on the cluster.
There are a few things that
I would like to just mention
when working with the cluster,
because there are some non-intuitive things.
And one of them is the file system
and the file storage that we
are using on the cluster,
because the large file system that
we have is running with spinning disks.
As maybe some people know, or
maybe a lot of you know,
spinning disks are a lot
slower than solid-state disks that
are nowadays kind of the
standard in most computers, but they
are a lot cheaper.
And for huge storage systems,
it's very often that these
spinning disks are still used for exactly
that reason, because they
are more efficient, more cost efficient.
And with an intelligent file system,
and the cluster has an
intelligent file system, the speed
problem is not that huge, at
least for larger files.
because the files are
essentially distributed over multiple disks.
They are read at the
same time from multiple disks.
So you have the read
speed from multiple disks added
together to get you the files
as fast as possible.
However, that comes with
problems with really small files.
And on really small files,
yeah, the computer or the
IO times significantly drop because
they are only on one spinning
disk and yeah, it just takes time to get there.
So if you have data,
like for example, image data
where you have small images,
bunch it together and read
it from one file.
It's way more efficient.
Or bunch it together, have it
stored on the Scratch file system
as one large file.
copy it over to the compute node
that you have, unpack it there,
and then use the local file systems
because at least on the
GPU nodes, there are solid-state
disks, SSDs, fast SSDs on the
machines so that this disadvantage
can be avoided.
Yeah, I think this goes
quite into the nitty-gritty details.
But to me, it's something
that you just kind of should know
because it's very much a
limitation of the system that we have.
Yeah, what other things you
should probably know is that like
we have to like, due to
this, this winter kickstart is
quite shorter than the summer one that we do.
We had to gloss over a few subjects
that are major subjects, but I recommend
if you have questions about
these, join us in the garage, we will
talk about it at the end
of the day where you can ask help from us.
But the major things we had
to gloss over is MPI parallelization,
which is like this kind
of like traditional classical
parallelization using lots of
different computers and lots of CPUs.
And it's used very heavily
in physics code and stuff like that.
And that we have to
unfortunately gloss over in
this course because it's used
very heavily by those programs that
use it, but not that many
programs nowadays use it.
So it's something that is
a bit more special case
kind of a parallelization for
this like large supercomputers.
And the other thing which
is nowadays getting more and
more popular or has been more
and more popular is GPU computing.
And the main things with
GPU computing is like if
your program uses GPUs,
Or if your program says it
can use GPUs, you can probably use GPUs.
And GPUs you request similarly
to any other resource.
You just tell that you want a GPU.
There's this GPUs flag that you can use it.
But for GPUs, I highly
recommend coming and asking us about
it in a bit more detail.
Because the kind of technical
details that [name] mentioned are
very much more...
like involved with gpus like
there are a lot of this
kind of like unseen bottlenecks
throughout the way that it's good
that somebody uh like explains
in detail because like they
can be pretty technical but
but usually like when it comes
to gpu computing you can get
it get the resources
easily but it's effectively
using those resources can be
a completely different story so
it's better to just like go
case by case basis and ask
what sort of things you can how
can we help you with that
Yeah, in general, I would
say come to Garage if you have any questions.
We are happy to help
there and it's probably the
most efficient way to get
additional details or help with
the code that you are trying to run there.
And we are a bit behind schedule,
but I think we still like
should have like a 10 minute
at least break over here.
So what was the schedule?
Let's check.
Yeah, let's meet back at 45.
Yes.
Should be fine.
Yes, 45 is nice.
So, yeah, so there's a lot
of stuff coming your way, but I would say
that the main things to focus
on is that, hey, you can go
to the cluster and submit your jobs.
And if you don't, if this
was like too much information at
too short of a time, just like
come and ask us and we can help you
do it at your pace and
like the main focus is that how
can you tell the computer that you
want it to do something for
you and then let's let's get
you running in the cluster but
yeah in let's have a 10 minute break
and then we'll talk about how
can you get your software to
the cluster and what should you
keep in mind when you move
your software and your programs to the cluster
So see you in 10 minutes.
And we are back.
Hopefully you had some time
to stretch your legs.
There's good questions in the notes.
We try to answer them.
You can keep them coming.
So now we are kind of in
the part two of this afternoon together.
And you kind of got the idea of
what it means, running programs
to the clusters, but of course
you want to move your own
program to the cluster.
And I really like the metaphor
that is here on this page, leaving home.
So [name], do you want to,
you are the, I always appreciate your metaphor.
So do you want to explain this metaphor?
Yeah.
So yes, so in this
session, unfortunately, we had
some technical difficulties.
So [name] couldn't join us.
Maybe she can join us
later if the technical difficulties are solved.
But yes, so in this session,
we wanted to take a bit of
a different kind of a view.
So if the previous session was
a lot of like,
technical details and lots of
stuff coming your way.
Hopefully this is more like
getting into the mindset kind of a session.
And what we wanted to
like switch the mindset is that like,
often when we talk about like, okay,
we have a program and we
want to do something from in an HPC cluster,
we often think of it is
like, like, okay, the program is,
is the reason why everything is bad.
And the program is the
reason why stuff doesn't work.
And like, why doesn't this work?
But we rarely look at
from the program's point of view.
And we actually should do
that much more often.
So think about how the
program sees the thing that it's
moving from a completely different
place from where it has spent
most of its life in.
So most of the programs that
we're going to be using
in our scientific computing, they are not...
written in scientific clusters.
They're not written in HPC clusters.
They're written in people's
laptops, they're written in
people's desktops, and they're
comfortable in those sorts of environments.
And that's the environment where
they have been created in.
And when we are moving a program,
so here are a cute little
hero over here, when we are moving
Uh, then, okay, nice, [name]
is managed to join us.
Uh, that's a microphone.
Hi.
Great.
Now it's working.
Yeah.
So great.
Now we can continue with the lesson.
So, so yeah, so, so the idea was
that like, we have our program
and we want to move
into a completely different environment.
So it's akin to like moving
from home to a university dorm
or a place like that.
And that's like a similar
kind of an experience where like
you first live alone or with your parents
or something, you live in a
certain kind of environment and
then you move into a
shared environment, like place
where other people live as well,
like in a dorm or something.
And many probably here have
experience of doing that.
They move into a
completely different environment that
might be a shared environment.
Would you agree, [name]?
Yeah, definitely.
Yeah, like there's always like
these kinds of changes that
happen when you move into a different place.
So let's say from the
program's point of view, like
the program might be accustomed to
being in a Linux or like a Mac environment.
And now we are working
in a Linux environment because
the HBC cluster is a Linux system.
And we might be previously
working like we have access
to everything available in our
desktop or in our laptop, but now
we are in a shared system.
So suddenly we need to
play by different rules.
So it might be a
completely different kind of like situation.
And usually similar to moving
to a different apartment, there's
good things that you can keep in mind
when you're moving that make
the whole process a lot easier for yourself.
So the first thing is
when you're planning the move,
you should ask for moving help.
Like if you have friends, family
or something like that, that
can help you move around, or
you have like a tutor or
something like from the university
side that can like introduce you to the place.
That's the first thing you want to do.
Like whenever you're moving
apartments, you want to first
ask, hey, can you help me move on that date?
Like that's what I've done
with my friends often.
I've helped them move.
They've helped me move apartments
and it's very important.
And that doesn't always mean
that you need to ask us about things.
You can also ask your
colleagues, like other people,
have they previously done this sort
of a move before?
Like have they used this
program in a shared system?
Secondly, you can always check, well,
what are the things, like
have other people done this successfully?
So a good place to check is like,
for example, our issue tracker,
where you can see that,
hey, maybe somebody else has
already done this thing before.
And maybe somebody has a good hint on
where is the cheapest moving
company or where do you get
moving boxes or that sort of stuff.
Which city market has the
best banana boxes that you can
ask so that you can get your stuff organized?
And the third one you of
course want to do is to
check the instructions that the programs
creators have done, like, they probably,
or maybe have done something
similar in the past.
So basically, like, in this
case, maybe you have moved before, like,
maybe you know that, okay,
these sort of things might be important
for this program, maybe you
need to like now, like do
similar kinds of things with
this other program.
Yeah, and maybe if I may
add, like don't really discard
this advice so quickly.
Like it seems very intuitive,
but at least from my experience, like
when it's not so trivial
to install something, it maybe
can take days of your time
and a lot of frustration.
Then, you know, if you had asked
for help from the beginning or maybe
even later, you know, like
your first try and then,
okay, someone else maybe has
already suffered through it.
So...
Yeah and often when there's
this kind of like when you have
to work with a certain program
we can often think that the
program is like this kind of
like a magic black box that we
have to like cast these spells to make it work.
Like we just have to like
do these kind of like rituals
and black magic to get it working.
But in reality there's usually
like a reason behind it in the program.
And maybe we don't
understand the reasoning.
Like we think that thunder
is God's wrath and like shouting at the clouds,
but maybe some other person
has like figured out what
thunder actually is that it's like...
ice crystals moving around in
in the clouds and then they
can like explain to us what
is the science behind it and
similar kind of thing happens
with the programs like maybe
somebody else has figured out
hey actually why you need to
run these magic commands and then
one they can explain to us like
hey this is the reason actually
The second thing that you
might want to check is that,
is it already furnished?
Like you don't want to move a sofa
and then just realize that,
hey, there's a sofa already
where I was planning to put my own.
So good idea is to check,
is it already available?
In the clusters, we often provide,
or like the administrators
usually provide commonly used software
as the software modules.
So there are these kind
of like environments that you
can load using these different
kinds of commands.
and these module commands that
you can like pick and choose
like I want this program to be activated
and usually like if it's
a commonly used program there's
lots of people who want to use it
and or if it's a program
that is very hard to install
like usually the administrators are
like okay let's just do this
once so that we don't have to do it again
And then they install it
like globally available for everybody.
So you can think of it like
a sofa in a common room in a dorm or something.
Like somebody brought the sofa there.
It might be even like
somebody who doesn't live in
the apartment anymore.
Like it has passed around,
like multiple people have
changed apartments, but there's still
the sofa left there.
And that's a similar kind
of a situation where like somebody
has made it possible for there
to be like a commonly used
furniture that is available.
available there and you should
probably use that if that is
there of course as as
with commonly used furniture like
if it has been there for a long time
and nobody knows who owns it
that can also happen to software so
so stuff can get moldy like
so you should always like
ask the administrators like hey
is this any more supported or
it's like a really old installation and
and ask can they hey can
you provide with a newer version
like this this doesn't look so good anymore
but if it's a commonly
used installation usually like
somebody can provide the
second newer installation quite
quickly because they know how to
do it yeah once you set
one module like it's easy to
set up a new version usually
it's easy maybe that's famous
words but yeah yeah but usually
the new one yeah
And it doesn't mean that
the administrators will remove
the previous ones.
So it's really nice to have
all of them there.
Yeah, why these clusters use
these module systems, like every cluster,
it's not only Triton, but Lumi
and Puhti and Mahti and other, is
because you can provide
different versions of the
software without breaking somebody
else's workflow.
There's always, if there is
software like this, somebody's
workflow depends on it, and
their research depends on it.
If you have a paper,
from beginning to end, it
might take years to get like
a really annoying paper published.
And during the time you need
to have this exact same software available.
So usually like with the software modules,
it's possible to like
create newer installations without
breaking out the older ones.
So that's also very important.
And talking about breaking things,
It's usually a good idea
to mark fragile things when you're moving.
If you have your glassware and
And all of the fragile things
like your TV and stuff like
that, you want to make
certain that everybody who's moving
them knows that they are fragile.
And this XKCD comic shows
well that software is always very fragile.
We live in this kind of
support zone where stuff works.
But once time goes by, we
reach into this situation where
where stuff doesn't work anymore.
So it's always very, like, especially
for research software, where we
are also interested about reproducibility.
Like, if we want to reproduce results,
we want to know what was
used to generate the results.
And if we're doing computational science,
we want to know what versions
were used to create these things.
Like, is it
Is the result wrong or correct?
Does it have like a bug fix implemented
or does it have like what
sort of user interface it uses?
Like programs update and
every program updates over time.
And sometimes, well, somebody
just stops updating like the
black line over here.
Like once the program is static in time,
eventually it will like become
this kind of like...
Hopefully it works.
And this is important
because whenever you're
writing a program or you
are doing some sort of
project, you usually want to record down
what were the program versions
and the versions that were
used to create this.
You want to record down that, hey,
I was using these versions,
I was using these programs to do my job.
That's important when you're
going to publish the code eventually.
If somebody else needs to
reproduce the code and
the time has moved on,
like stuff doesn't necessarily work.
There was this one case where
I helped the researchers trying
to replicate this AI paper that
they wanted to use this code.
And from the day of the
publication, it was four months
and the framework didn't work anymore
because the versions have updated
and it was like an experimental framework.
So it can be a very
short time when the installation
instructions or the
the previous thing doesn't work anymore.
So it's very important to lock
down or know which versions were
used for your code.
Yeah, and sometimes it's not even
that you like your own
code version, like if you
are developing something, like, of course,
you will keep releasing more
like having these more versions of your code.
And if you don't track
them, of course, this will happen.
But it also can happen
like your code depends on let's
say NumPy or any other
type of dependencies and if
you don't keep checking of course
at some point something will break
and it's no one's fault but
this can happen so that's why
it's also good to like sometimes it's not
even something that you
can control yourself like it's oh
i did this modification but it
still can happen that you break things
Yeah, and like [name] said,
it's not anybody's fault that stuff breaks.
It's the law of entropy
that organized things get
disorganized over time.
So that happens with software as well.
And it's good to keep in mind
when you're starting a project,
this will get moldy over time.
Nothing will stop the passage of time.
And this brings up the next point,
which is very important, that
when you're moving, you want
to usually organize the boxes
that, hey, here's my books.
These are going to the bookshelf.
These are my utensils.
These are going to kitchen.
So you want to organize so
that it's easy to unpack them.
If you're moving, the first
thing you want to usually pack
is that, okay, what am I
needing to assemble my bed once I...
once I get to the new
apartment like you don't want to realize
that okay I have no idea
where my tools are and I have no idea
how I can assemble a sleeping place
for myself once you are
finished with the move so
similarly you usually want to
like record all of the steps
that you're doing while you're installing
and this is very important
also for other people so that
they can help you or if
other people want to reproduce
what you're doing like
Like if they know that, hey,
I have gone this route and
I didn't manage to get it
done, they don't have to go
the same route to figure out
that, okay, this didn't work.
They can try some other approaches.
And if they know that,
okay, this should work, they
can follow those steps that, okay,
they can get to the same
end result that you have.
And if they don't, then
there's like some interesting stuff happening.
Definitely.
Yeah, I'm guilty about this.
I used to never record anything.
And then, you know, the
troubleshooting, it takes even more
time, you know, than to explain people, so...
Yeah, and then it becomes this sort of,
like, treasure hut from your memory that,
hey, like, hey, can I,
like, figure out what did I do previously?
Like, I remember running this command,
I remember running this command,
but I, oh, yeah, I forgot
this one command that actually
makes it actually work.
So it's, like, then it
becomes much harder for you to...
like like do any anything again
and then it also like creates
a lot more kind of like
stress for keeping your software up to date
or this kind of like like
you don't dare to touch it
if it works and that's a bad
thing like if you if you ever
feel this kind of a feeling that hey like
like I don't want to like
even like breathe next to
my like software installation or
otherwise it will break down and
now I can't get my paper done
or I can't get my results done
I can't touch it or otherwise
it will break then you know
that okay like maybe I
should have previously kept a
better record of the steps
to reproduce the results or
reproduce the environment I was
using because otherwise
Well, now you're in a pickle
where you need to like do
the detective work backwards.
Like, okay, how did I get
this working in order to be
able to do any modifications
to your installation?
Yeah, I mean, this comes back
to the black box thingy.
Like, of course, if you don't know
what you're doing or if you kind of just,
okay, this works, don't touch it,
it will crumble otherwise, then
you kind of keep yourself in this loop.
So that's why it's also nice
to kind of try to understand your software.
Yeah, and also, once you, like...
Once you've figured out, okay, this is
what I'm going to be doing
and these are the steps I'm
going to be doing, it's a
good idea to also check where
should I be doing this.
We also already mentioned
the storage places.
in the previous session, but
usually in case of a
cluster, there's usually a work
directory that is meant to house
your code and meant to house your data.
And similarly, if you're moving,
it's good to move your stuff
into your own room.
instead of like leaving them
on the hallways or something
like you probably want your stuff
to be in the correct place
similarly you don't want to
put your private stuff into a shared folder
but maybe something you want to
be in the shared folder so
you should check the places where
do you want to put them and
also it's of course like good
to be organized so if you
have a different projects you
want to probably put the
different projects into its own folders.
You want to organize different papers
and different software into its
own folders so that they don't
get mixed up and not influence each other.
And this brings us to
this good demonstration about if
you ever lived in a dorm, it
can be a super great situation
where you have a...
You have a greatest friend living with you,
or it can be a
situation where your neighbors are
driving you insane.
And this is also important for software.
A lot of software doesn't
play nice with other software.
Uh, like having roommates can
make your life like nice or
they can make it not so nice.
So, so it's usually a good idea to,
uh, like get the software that
works in the same project or same things
and then put them into
its own installation folder
and own environment, and then put
the rest of the stuff into its own one.
Yeah, the way you can
always find everything, which it's
also kind of obvious, but I
think the messier the projects get
and the more things you need to
do, we kind of forget this.
Yeah.
So a few examples are like, for example,
with many of the FRMI
pipelines, if you need to
deal with like MRI images or
that sort of stuff.
They can be like multiple
tools that are like individual tools.
Well first you need to do
this one tool to do some segmentation
and then you need to do
with another tool you need to
do some other like figuring out
and maybe you need to combine the results
and you can have this kind
of like whole pipeline of
different tools taking stuff
from different places.
And in these sort of cases,
you might run into a situation
where you want to install
every tool individually, like
every tool individually into its own place,
but activate only one tool
at a time, depending on what
you need for this specific step.
Because if you try to do
it all in one environment or
one situation, it's going to
go completely ballistic and it
just doesn't work.
And usually, especially nowadays,
we use Python in many cases,
like Python is used in lots of computations.
And the reason why Python is used is that,
well, it has this big
ecosystem of different tools tied to it.
tied to it but of
course the different tools might
need different things so what
you usually want to do is
use something like conda or similar
tools to to make certain that
you can create like individual environments
for these different tools that
you're using and try to
avoid installing things globally so
yeah quite often like when we
help a user but then we
like figure out later that
hey there's some package that
has been installed globally and
now like python for example decides
that hey i will want to
use this one like because
that's that's the global one
and that's higher in the priorities
i will use that one and now like
it becomes this black magic territory.
It's like things just happen
randomly, like weird things happen
and like you hear weird noises
and weird bangs around the room
and you don't figure out
where are the ghosts coming from
and you don't want to get into
this sort of a situation.
So usually having like
separate environments and one software
at a time makes your life a lot easier.
But then to demonstrate this
whole thing, we have this
demo, this Quipy demo.
So [name], maybe you can
run us through what do we have in this demo?
Yeah, so basically this demo
is inspired by one of the
Triton users that reached us out last week.
So he wants to run this
workflow related to atomistic modeling.
I don't know his specific use case,
but if you want to
study chemical reactions or you
want to study some kind of material.
So this type of research he's doing.
And then, well, of course, the workflow is
way more complicated, but one
of the things that it
requires is the installation of
this package called Quipy.
And well, I have a long
history with Quipy for my own research too.
And we will try now, let's
say, to approach this first step to help him.
And we will try to set
up an environment where we
actually only install Quipy.
So we are only focusing on Quipy.
Yeah.
And well, maybe I can tell
a bit more about what Quipy exactly does.
So Quipy is a Python
interface actually to a Fortran
code called Quip.
And this code is used to,
well, to generate the models that
people use for, well, atomistic
modeling in general, but specifically
for molecular dynamic simulations,
they are called.
So we create these
computer experiments, let's say,
where you can just see what
happens to the atoms in
some material, some chemical, as I was saying.
Yeah.
So you can already hear
from the explanation that it's
like Python interface for a program
fortran and then it's like okay
like we are already like quite
deep in this sort of
like there's dependencies uh all
along the way like different
things depending on the other yeah
and in this demo we will
only touch the python part so
they kind of let's say
trivial part of it still we will see
if it is so easy or so straightforward
but um but yeah and i
think one interesting thing about
this package i mean there are many others
but this one in particular so
this one was developed by scientists
so they were doing their
own research they decided these
tools were very useful so they
wanted to share it and it
is still maintained by scientists
so you know it's not
like software developers or like
I mean, of course, they
are experts in coding, but it's not like,
I don't know, an obscure
group of people working exclusively
on this, but it could be you.
Scientists' job is usually
to create science, not like
updating software packages.
So, of course, that creates
like a situation where like,
Like that's not their
main focus necessarily, but
they want everybody else to be
able to do the science.
So it's like a great
thing that they provide.
But it's also like all of
these kinds of like open
software, it depends on so much like unpaid
or like extra labor by
many, many people who do stuff on the side.
Yeah, exactly.
So it can happen that things break
or like, sometimes, you know,
it's normal, like, we don't have
all the time in the world.
So okay, but maybe we can
start trying to go through the demo.
Yeah, so if we look at
the, like the demo with with
the command, should we look at
a quick, what sort of things are
we going to be doing?
So we're going to be
installing a conda environment, right?
Yes, exactly.
So, I mean, of course, first
check would be to check
the installation instructions and also,
well, specific documentation about
conda environments.
We did this already, but you
can of course do it and
everything is linked there.
Just know that all these
commands are specific for doing
this on Triton cluster.
So you will need to check
if you are going to run
this in another HPC cluster.
Yeah, so first we build the environment.
And then in here in Triton,
we use Mamba, but we recommend using Mamba.
Yeah, so Sim already loaded.
And well, if it is your first installation,
like your first setup of
Mamba, you need then also to
tell Mamba, hey, don't install
things in my home directory.
Usually it's much better to
have everything in your work
directory since you have a bigger quota.
I'm taking a better terminal where I can,
like the on-demand terminal, the copy
and paste doesn't work that
well, so I'm taking different terminals.
So yes, so we will tell the tool that,
hey, we are going to install
stuff in the work directory.
And yeah, so that's this bunch of comments.
That's what they do.
And next, we just need
to describe the environment so
Mamba knows what to install and what not to.
And for that, as we said
before, it's good to figure out
where to put your environment first.
And ideally, I think, well,
I don't know what's your opinion, Sima,
but at least I prefer
to have my environments per project.
So if this project
is going to use these
environments, I will have a
specific place inside my project folder.
That's one way of doing it, yes.
Yeah, but of course, yeah,
it depends, I suppose, on the situation.
And then, well, you can
see here, very simple environment.
We are just loading Python,
and we are setting up this
specific version of Python because
if you check the
installation instructions for this
Quipy package, they mention this,
so it's good to add it.
Yes.
And then the Quipy package,
which actually the name for
installing it is Quipy Ace,
which is also important.
Some packages have like a given name
and then the actual name of
the package is different.
So always check these two.
Yeah.
So we just now need
to create the environment.
Yeah.
And while it is creating it, I can add.
So of course here, I
mean, usually probably you would
like more things in your
environment, like, I don't know,
maybe NumPy or any, whatever dependency.
So you could add later on
top of this and update this current environment.
So...
Let's see what happens.
Oh, okay, it failed.
Okay, that's good.
That's what we were looking for today.
But okay, but why did it fail?
So, but maybe... Yeah, so it's like this,
reading this error message can
be quite difficult, like if
you don't know what it means,
but so it looks like we just don't have it.
Like, what's the reason?
Why can't we have a version that...
uh that would have this like even
though that version should
be available what could be the reason
for this yeah like like how is this
even possible we check
the documentation already so the
thing is yeah this the
installation with conda can fail if you
for example uh give like a
wrong version or if there
is some dependency missing it
will give you this
error message even though you
know it's not that it doesn't exist
so you need to be careful with this
but in this case in particular
what we should do is to
check up the github issue issues
because like i think one two
days before we tried to
run this installation another user
had similar issues
And the problem is that
the developers forgot to add
some wheels to build the
Quipy package for certain Python versions.
So the Python version that we
have in our new build environment
is too high, basically.
So if it is higher than
3.14, I think, it will fail
because there is no wheel for it.
Yeah, so if we look
at the previous picture, so
we run somewhere like
something updated somewhere and we
run out of the support zone.
So now we need to get
back into the support zone
by reducing our Python version.
So these kinds of things
can happen quite often that we
need to like do a smaller
modification to our environment to
make certain that we are staying
in the safe zone where stuff works.
Yeah, exactly.
So now we are just
limiting our Python version.
And then we should remove
this environment we built and
rebuild it again.
And then we can see if
this actually solves everything or not.
But yeah, I think it's
very interesting to see that
the errors that you get don't
tell you the whole picture.
And they are actually quite
misleading in this case.
So they are telling you,
hey, this package doesn't even exist.
And I mean, you know, it's not true.
So don't get discouraged if
you bump into these kind of errors.
And usually this kind of like
what we're describing throughout
this session is kind of like approach
that we often like internalize
because we have dealt with
such problems in multiple cases.
Like when we're helping our users,
when we're doing software
installations, we do this sort
of like approach all the time.
So whenever we hear somebody, like
when a user comes to
Garage and explains their problems, our
minds go through this kind
of like a checklist that okay
what are the commands that were
being run is this in a
separate environment are there stuff
in the global packages like could it be
that it's installing into a place
where there's no space left or
like we we do this sort
of like heuristics all the time
when we have to help other
people because we know that
these are the things that
usually trip up situations and
only when we reach this sort
of like situation here where we get an error
that we didn't expect now
we're like okay now is something
new now it's like specific to this case
so for example like maybe
the python version is too new
and then we realized that okay
like this is the reason why why the
what a problem uh what a
thing failed yeah even though
they already tried to uh you
know solve this issue like a
few days ago so this was
very very recent but still
you know everything moves so fast
and uh people can be on top of everything so
Yeah, it's kind of, it's
common, like it's no one's fault.
And of course, everything can get
even more complicated, as we
were saying before.
So this comes from a Fortran code.
So if you needed to, let's
say, tweak some feature, you would
need to have access to
actually the underlying code.
Then you would need to
do the manual installation, which
I think now it's easier.
But in the past, I wouldn't recommend it.
It was kind of a bit
messy, especially in the HPC clusters.
Yeah.
And you can add parallelization
on top of this, then you
would need to change your
content environment and so on.
Yeah, like the Quipy and tools like that,
they utilize, like you can use
MPI to run many of the
simulations and stuff like that.
So it can get quite complicated.
But if we go back to
what we previously talked about,
like what sort of steps you can take,
If we look at what
happened during the whole process,
let's say with this creepy
thing, the first point, ask your colleagues
or local support people, our
user ask us help with this
because they want to know about this.
So we started investigating this.
We checked our documentation,
our conda documentation on how
to create environments, on how to
do that sort of stuff.
We checked the installation
instructions provided by the
Quipi developers.
We checked that it's not installed already.
important we we create the
environment yaml we have the
commands to create the environment
now written out in this document like
so of course we will give
it them to the user who asked
this uh from us and and to
check these things uh he'll
probably need more complex
installation with all of
the different modifications but
Basically, then we'll have
more instructions to give.
We checked the conda docs to specify
where we want to put the
storage, like the environments, where
we want the environments to go.
And then we used this Mamba
tool to install the program
into its own environment.
We didn't need to do
any global installations.
And at the end, we used
the source activate to activate the
the environment so basically
we went through all of these
steps during this one installation process
but often we don't think about
it like we don't think about okay like
what does my software need
what does it need and how
should where should i put this
so that it's it runs uh the
best so it's good idea to
usually start from this point
of view yeah definitely i yeah
i was thinking but i think
yeah you cover everything
Yeah.
And now, like, after you
have done this kind of a move,
so now we moved, basically, we
moved from a home into a new dorm.
Like, our program now lives
in this shared environment.
Like, is this the end of the story?
Like, usually not, because now
we need to live in that
environment and things can get different.
when you live in this sort of environment.
So for that, we have a
few extra hints that you can do.
So first off, what is near your apartment?
Where should you go to dinner?
Where's the laundry room?
Where should you put stuff?
If you don't have any directions
where you need to go or
where should you go, what are
the best places around here?
you can like go in loops,
like you can go all around
and you don't know where to
go and what you should do.
So usually the program needs directions.
The program doesn't know things
that if it's not told that,
hey, like here are the things.
So there's common things that
you can tell your programs.
So we already, in the
previous session, we talked about
command line arguments.
So there's usually like
common line arguments that you
can tell your program that,
hey, use these folders for storage
or use this input file or
use these things to control my behavior.
And that's one common way of doing it.
Some programs utilize configuration files.
So you should check
your program's documentation, what
sort of configuration file it
accepts and what it uses.
And also many programs
utilize environment variables.
So we also mentioned
environment variables previously that,
hey, like there are
some environment variables that are needed.
Okay, like this doesn't look right.
The parsing went wrong apparently.
But anyways, these common
environment variables, they...
Yeah, now it's better.
They include stuff like path,
which sets like this colon
separate list of where the
command line search for executables.
So some, like the module system itself,
it modifies these parameters
to make software available.
So if, and source activate as well,
like when you activate
the Python environment, it
modifies these environment variables
in the background to make it
so that like, hey, like now
the software is visible to you.
And these matter a lot because then
if there is more stuff in the path
or something, it might find
the wrong program or it might
not find the right program.
So you might need to verify that, okay,
what environment variables are set
and what are set correctly.
Another variables, other things
that many programs do is that
they use the home directory or this...
xdg cache home which is
underneath your home directory in
this folder dot cache to put
every all sorts of stuff in
so a lot of programs just
like they don't care about
your personal space they will
put stuff into your cupboards
like whatever like they will
just like put stuff there so um
If you have a program,
it might start filling up
your home directory with all sorts of things.
It might put its downloaded
data sets there.
It might put its
temporary compilation stuff there.
It might put its configuration file there.
There's also .config underneath
home directory, which is a common place.
So there's many of these
that you can change with
these environment variables.
But you should know what
your program is trying to accomplish.
Ask your program, okay, where
are you going?
Are you going to the laundry room?
I can show you where it
is so that you don't go to the wrong place.
And these sort of like, often the programs,
if they don't know what to
do, they assume that they are
in control of the whole system
and they can do whatever they want.
So they will...
wash their feet at the kitchen sink
and you can you have to tell them
that hey no that's not how you
do it in our apartment like you
need to go to the right place
so yeah it's like these
friends that conspire unannounced
like just drop by and then
you know like kind of fills
your own space and you need
to hey okay let's set some boundaries so kind of
similar way with this um [name]
where would you say that
like people should uh like this
uh i mean this home environment
that by default some programs choose like
for instance in triton what would
be a good place to kind
of redirect your software yeah
like it's temporary files yeah
Yes, that's a good point.
So I think in many
cases, like, especially if it's
something that requires a lot of data.
So a good example that is
like, let's say you download
machine learning models from
HagenFace or something like that.
Like it wants to put
everything into your home folder
by default, and that fills up,
it fills up immediately.
And you might want to tell it that,
hey, actually, I have created
you a proper place in the
work directory, put your stuff there.
Another thing is that pip, for example,
if you install Python
environments using pip, it will
put everything to your home
folder as well, which is like...
super annoying like it can
get filled very rapidly and
and usually like what i usually
do is i create custom folders
in my work directory that are like
and then i tell the program
that hey use this they are
often these programs accept some
sort of like global configuration
file so for example with
the conda instructions that's what
we did we told it that hey
set this global configuration that,
hey, everything puts into my
work folder because then it messes up.
These new files that we set up
and then we kind of told
Conda, hey, go here instead of...
And even though we just said
that don't do global things,
sometimes the global things are
the best things to do.
So it's like there are rules
and there are rules.
You can always modify them on a use basis.
But I think it's very
important to know what your
program is trying to do.
So the program just tries to do its job.
And if you don't tell what
its job is, it will try to like...
just do whatever and you don't know.
So it's better to look
at the documentation of the program
and figure out what does
it, and these magic words
of like environment variables,
command line arguments, comma
configuration files.
Like usually we go to
the program's documentation and look
for these words where they
end up and figure out, okay,
how do we control this program?
And once you have figured out, okay,
these are the best places to
go to, it's a good idea
to usually form good habits on...
on like how do you specify these things.
And this is like same kind of stuff
that we talked about
documenting the installation procedure
is good to document the
runtime procedure as well.
So if you're running a
program, we talked about the serial jobs
or running these jobs with
the batch scripts in the previous session.
So what you can do is
that you can recall to those batch scripts
what sort of like things
your program should be doing.
So for example, you can
record, you can record like, Hey,
I want to, I want you to put your stuff.
I want to load these environments.
I want to set up
these environment variables.
I want to run these scripts.
I want to set these.
like variables, and then
they're all recorded into
your submission script.
So later on, if you need
to replicate your simulation, you have
that also recorded there
because otherwise that might be lost
and then you don't know
what parameters you use to
run the simulation with or something like that.
Yeah, and also if you want
to share them with someone else,
like you have someone new coming
up in your group or, I
mean, you are collaborating with
someone else, like it's good to have them.
And for this, we have like
a short demo that we can show.
This, I first deactivate
the currently activated environment and
I will do this module purge to
purge all of the modules
that might have loaded while doing that.
So let's start from a clear spot.
And in this demo, I will
show like, we want to use large language models.
Like nowadays, they're all
everywhere, like large language models.
But sometimes, let's say we want
to do some processing, like
on the different models,
on a lot of different
prompts or something in a cluster environment.
Let's say we have sensitive data.
We want the code to analyze that.
We don't want to give it
to OpenAI or other players.
We want to keep it internally.
So in this case, we want
to run a large language model ourselves.
And for that, we will use this...
framework called Transformers by
Hugging Face, which is this
big framework to do that.
And we have here like a
small Python code that basically
it initializes this large
language model pipeline, and then
it runs like a command through the
asks the command from the
last language model and then
asks for the response.
So let me create like a demo over here.
So this would be like, let's say my code.
I immediately opened it with
Veeam, like this is like how
I get, like I get,
Like you get accustomed to
the tools you're using.
So, but yes, so here's our example
and we will use this like Mistral model,
this open source model that
is available for everybody.
But let's write the submission
script for this, for running this model.
So here we have the submission script.
I will copy it over here and
we can look at it in more detail.
So in this submission script,
I have few additions to the
previous ones that we had.
So over here, we specify that
we want to use a GPU
because this runs much faster on a GPU.
So we use this as the GPUs to ask for GPU.
And then we load some modules.
So we load this model hugging face.
So we have some pre-downloaded
open source models available because
like so many people are using these.
We have this kind of
like our own repository where we have
these loaded or available.
And then we have also
like existing environments that have
been like handcrafted by us to
have a lot of the commonly used packages.
So you don't always have
to start from scratch.
So, so in this case, we
can just use that as a
starting point for running our code.
So let's, let's use this
and let's just submit it and, and let's see.
So now we see that it, we get.
It's automatically setting the
partition and we see a job there.
Let's see if it's in the queue.
Okay.
It might be that there's others like.
I'm wondering, is there like
a... Okay, now it's running.
Yeah.
Some of the nodes are
being rebooted apparently or something,
but we see that now it's
running on one of the GPU nodes
and we can see the output being generated here.
So let's use like less to see the output.
So now here we see the
output that the model provides.
So it says that the sequence is known as...
Fibonacci sequence, the next
number, maybe I'll actually, is
it like, no, is it?
No, I can't remember what
is the character for, maybe
I'll just catenate it, yeah.
Yeah, maybe, yeah.
Yeah, so now it says that
the next number is found by
adding the previous numbers.
And so basically we did
like this quick prompting and it says that
it's probably a Fibonacci sequence
and this is how it works.
So we managed to ask
the large language model some things.
But what is really important
here is that in the example script,
We have written here out what
is needed to run this.
We don't have to load anything to run this.
It will load the correct environments.
It will load the correct things.
And if we look at this...
If we load, for example,
this model HuggingFace, if we
load this module that is provided,
we can see that it sets
this HuggingFace hub cache
environment variable.
So it tells the program that, hey,
Like here is the model place.
Like get your model here, like from here.
Don't try to like download it again.
And this is like what happens many,
like often in the module
system on the background, it is
just like these magic variables.
They see magic until
they're explained, like why does it work?
But in reality, many of
these are available in the documentation.
It's just the question of like...
looking at, knowing that they
exist and checking this up.
So in many cases, like this
is just one program that
uses certain environment variable,
but all programs have their
own like quirks and things that
they want you to know.
And it's good idea to check those.
What is specific for your program?
Yeah, I think it's always nice
to have all these module
load already inside your, because
if you run something and
you already have some module loaded there,
it might be that it's
affecting your calculations, even if
you don't know.
Like it really depends on,
yeah, on everything that Sima said, basically.
Also these global variables too.
So be careful with this.
And now I can quickly show, like, if,
let's say, if you check your,
if you use this echo command
that we used in the previous
session to view what is your path variable,
it shows that, okay, these
are the places where the
program is checking for executables
and things to run on.
And if you, let's say,
load this sci-comp llm env and
you run this echo path again,
you notice that now it adds this, like,
path that is generated by
our installation tools to install
it over here.
And here's where the actual like meat
and potatoes is like, here's
the stuff coming from.
And it seems black magic
that this happens on the background,
but that's why this kind of
like tools are generated to make
it easier to do.
But it's important to know
that, okay, like, hey, my program just...
it needs to, to know, it's
good to think from the program's point of view,
what, what do I need in
order to make what I need, uh, happen?
Like what, what information I need.
And, and we have collected like
as a, as a total list, this kind of like,
like you can think about the
quote by, uh, John F. Kennedy
from his, like, uh, he, he's, uh,
Like inauguration speech, he
mentioned this famous line of ask not
what your country can do for you, ask
what you can do for your
country, but you can formulate it in that.
Ask not what your program can
do for you, ask what you
can do for your program.
So think from the program's
point of view, like what does it know?
What does it need to know?
And here's like a good list
of things you can keep in mind.
So the more you do this kind of like stuff,
the more familiar you get with
this sort of like...
You start to see the patterns.
You can see the patterns around,
but this is how we often
think of things when we help
users and when we try to
figure out what's wrong with the program.
It's not that the program is faulty.
It's not necessarily that
it's badly written or anything like that.
It's all about like, hey,
it just doesn't understand that
it's running in an HPC system.
It's scared and it's running
in a completely new environment
that it doesn't understand what's happening.
And now it's like behaving
badly because of them.
Yeah, not badly, but you need
to give the new instructions to it.
But yeah, I think, well,
most of the questions, I think, are answered.
And maybe [name] now would
like to continue.
Yes, and maybe [name] is.
And [name], yeah.
here with me.
Yeah, thank you so much.
But yes, you are.
Thank you.
So I will ask the
director, the movie director to go
back to my screen share.
Yeah.
I know I have a button for doing that.
No, actually, I don't have
a button for doing that.
Because it's one of those zoom things.
So
yeah i'm sharing only the vertical
but basically we are wrapping
up thank you everyone for
these three hours together hopefully
this was motivating enough to
get started with the cluster
because the goal here is you
know to actually get started some
of you might want to have a credit
and so soon we will talk
about courses and this type of
needs that of course
doctoral candidates doctoral researchers have
But the most important thing
that will be useful for
everyone beyond doctoral researchers
is of course how to ask for help.
So the link here goes to the help page.
It's a long page.
It's not to scare you.
The reason is that
there's different channels, many,
many channels and many ways to
ask for help from us.
And on top of that, the map.
of people who can help you
at Aalto is really big.
So maybe before going to what
is the best way and what are the best channels,
it's good to understand, since
the majority of you are at Aalto University,
it's good to understand the
structure of different services
at Aalto University.
It took me many years
to understand this structure.
Now I'm confident enough that
I can explain it to others.
So Science IT, which is
the official name of other
scientific computing actually lives
inside the School of Science, but
we are not limited to
support the researchers of the
School of Science.
We support in practice everyone
else who needs computational resources.
And so the Triton cluster
is inside the Science IT team,
but of course we don't work independently.
At Aalto, your Aalto account, emails,
and many other IT systems
are governed by the centralized
Aalto IT services.
And of course we work closely with them
so that for example, you
know, the same username and
password can be used for logging
into Triton or using on demand.
There are of course other
services at Aalto and the
second biggest partner for us and
for you is research services.
Research services covers both
the doctoral education services,
but all sorts of other services
that are related to research,
whether you need ethical review or,
I don't know, help with
personal data and today is data protection day.
So it's a good moment to
talk about this, at least mention it.
And then of course, there's
all the other part of the
joint services, the finance, HR, and
so on and so on.
Now, within our team,
Aalto Scientific Computing, there
is a sub-team, which is
called Research Software Engineers.
And here I would like to ask [name],
since you are one of
the research software engineers, so
what is so special about Aalto
RSCs and in general, what
are research software engineers?
Well, it's...
I think the term itself
hasn't got a dictionary definition,
and it's an emerging kind
of field, so definitions have been a bit fuzzy.
But generally, we are people who
are from a science background, who know
how research works, but who also know
how computing works and can
help anyone with how to compute things.
So if you...
The research software engineers
help on different levels.
If you've got a problem with
how your own research code works on Triton
or that it does not
work on Triton, research software
engineers can help.
Also the Triton admins might
be the right people to ask,
but we know each other.
Then also, if you have a problem
where you have a code, but
you want it to run faster,
that's something we can help
with optimizing code.
Or even if you have a
very large project and you know
how you want to do your research, you know
how you want to answer
your question, but you don't
know what software to use, we
can help with that.
We can do custom implementations
if that is what is actually needed
or give you advice on
what solutions there might already be.
I like these examples here.
Do it for you.
Do it with you.
And what about make it reusable?
Is this connected to kind of open science?
Yes, of course.
So if you have a code,
well, if you have code already
and it's only running in your
group and you want to get
it published or want to get it
even to just be usable
by your collaborators in
a different environment, we can
help with how to set that up.
We can help you put
things under version control and
take a general look at your code base
and say, help you find what
code goes where and what does
need to go under version control.
And that kind of thing.
Excellent.
So one thing of the
research software engineer and one
thing about asking help from us is
that many of them, if not
the majority of them, plus
other Triton helpers, Triton
administrator, we all sit together
every day at 1 p.m.
in the Triton Garage.
So one of the links that
you get here on the top is basically our daily,
it's kind of an office hour,
but with full of different
experts from different fields
who are researchers or have
been researchers, so they kind of
know what it feels.
And just, you know, that's the lowest part.
You can even join Garage even
if you don't know what to ask.
You know, we can figure
out the question together.
But of course, there are
more resources to ask for help.
The web pages that I'm
showing right now that we've
been using all day, they're
actually also the documentation of the cluster.
They of course feels gigantic,
but the good thing is that
you can always search for
what you're looking for, whether
it's a code snippet or
some information about storage
and computing and so on.
And then we have also more
kind of usual ways of asking
for help, like the, you
know, email ticketing system.
One thing that I also
want to mention before we talk
about courses is the SciComp
Chat, which is based on Zulip.
So Zulip is like Slack, but
it's an open source version.
And this version that we run
here is fully run on-prem at Aalto University.
And so it's a big chat with, I don't know,
maybe are we now at 600
or 700 people in that chat?
But, you know, it's an easy
way to ask, for example, is the cluster down?
If you see that you're not
able to connect, is it just
me or is it everybody else?
And of course, you know,
it's yet another chat to
follow, blah, blah, blah.
But yes, I guess we are almost done.
Maybe final words about upcoming courses.
So specifically for, and I
can see already appearing in
the notes, this feedback session.
The feedback is there for you
so that you can let us
know if this was useful, if this
was too fast or too slow
and anything that we can improve it.
Soon the feedback will, there
it is, you see this typo.
But now to talk about the courses.
So from this year, we actually
have our own MyCourses or SISU course code.
So for those of you who need the credit,
you can visit this page and
see all the various courses that we have.
You need to open this left
hand side here to see what's going on.
And a good thing that
we have integrated these modules
also with the trainings offered by CSC.
So if I go back to the
notes, I have added this CSC training calendar.
I can already tell you
that something, well let me
first accept the cookies.
Something interesting that is coming up,
I think in April we are
organizing with CSC this
practical deep learning.
You see there's many specific courses
that maybe are, you know,
not interest all of you.
We have the practical deep
learning in April coming.
In May, we will have data science with R,
but the big one for us
is code refinery workshop, which is
in a little bit less than two months from now.
And in the notes, there's also
the link to the next edition
of the code refinery workshop.
The registrations are open.
I'm one of the main
organizers with Diana Jussan from Uppsala.
It's a big effort of
distributed partners around Finland,
Sweden, Norway.
CSC is kind of the
umbrella organization on top of us.
And the main content of
the Code Refinery Workshop is
Git version control.
And that workshop really, you know,
you actually need to do
exercises during the workshop on
how to publish your code to
GitHub, how to suggest changes
to someone else's code.
And this is all the content of week one.
The week two, day four, five,
and six, they focus
on reproducibility, reproducible research,
how to document software.
And this year we have a new session on
how to basically use generative
AI for getting help in writing
some of your code.
Right.
Then you can check other
trainings like Lumia AI
Factory trainings, which we
also contribute to, and our old catalogs.
So I think that's all for
today and for this time.
We still have five minutes.
If you want to ask a
question, I still see [name] here
with me and others hiding with the camera off.
Anything else to mention?
Anything else to tell to our viewers?
Yeah, I would just add that like,
if there's a lot of stuff
coming your way in this session, and
if you join our summer
kickstart, there's like a three-day kickstart,
so you can have like a lot,
we have a lot more exercises
there, so if you feel like
you're missing some exercise and
stuff like that you can look
at the previous videos or join
us during the summer to do
those and I would say that
like don't get discouraged because
there's lots of things to
learn like that's what we are
what education is about really
like learning things right so
it's not a bad thing to learn things
and it's not bad to ask things
and it's a good idea to
just like utilize the resources
that are available to you.
So basically like if you have
let's say you have holidays
mandated by law or something.
And if you don't use
them, that's just weird.
And like, that's not a good idea.
It's the same kind of
thing with support kind of
like services that we provide.
Like it's, it's, it's, it's valid to go,
go at it alone, but
sometimes it's, it's also valid to
ask, ask for help.
Like it's, it's not a
question of like, like,
in this sort of like
science in general it's not a question
that like hey did you manage
to do it completely without
help from anybody like do you
get a medal out of that
not necessarily like you get
more collaborators you get more
faster done stuff done by
by asking your colleagues
asking us, asking the community.
If you join the Zulip, there's
a lot of people answering
each other's questions, which is
really nice and really helpful.
So just like join and join
us either in Garaz or Zulip or whatever.
Like it's not like
It can be daunting at
first, but it's better if it's not.
Let's not make it too
difficult, the whole field,
because the technical things
are difficult enough.
Let's not make the social
things difficult as well.
I added this link to the
picture I wanted to show that sometimes
when we want to tell the people
that you're not alone, we
use this idea behind the imposter syndrome,
which I'm sure everyone has
experienced and we will all
continue to experience forever.
We can't escape from that.
But the imposter syndrome is
that you think that you know very little
and everybody else actually knows
more than you, but the reality
is that you know
all of us they know something
we have some overlap with each
other we also know something unique
and only through this type of
you know this is like
a distributed computing system of
brains we can actually help
you and sometimes learn from
you i've learned so much doing
this type of work so yes
What I would add is that
if you find anything in the system that's odd,
that's strange, that doesn't work
as you would expect it or
where there are bugs or stuff, it can happen.
And please let us know
because we are relying on
feedback from users about things
that don't work as you were
hoping for it to work
because otherwise, yeah, we can't fix it.
if you don't know about it.
Right.
So as you see, the notes
are there for you, this notes document.
So if you could now spend
the remaining one minute to
write something good about today.
Thank you for whoever wrote
that the examples were good.
And also something to improve
because we actually change this
every time we run it.
So there's always room for improvements.
Somebody was asking about the
videos and yes, the videos will be there.
Well, if you're on the same
Twitch TV URL that you're using,
the video will be there immediately
as soon as we stop the streaming.
But then we long-term archive
it into YouTube because I
think Twitch keeps it only for
a week these days, something like that.
And I think that's all for
today and it's 3 PM sharp.
So thank you all the instructors
for the big work and thank
you for all of you participants
to make this possible.
So keep in touch and
thank you again, everyone.
Bye bye.